<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="57810" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2015-06-24</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="201" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>201</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="701" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>701</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Wirtschaft, Bildung und Forschung</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'économie, de la formation et de la recherche</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'economia, della formazione e della ricerca</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Economic Affairs, Education and Research</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="1070" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>1070</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Der Bundesrat</name>
      <name lang="fr">Conseil fédéral</name>
      <name lang="it">Il Consiglio federale</name>
      <name lang="en">The Federal Council</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.admin.ch/gov/de/start.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.admin.ch/gov/fr/accueil.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.admin.ch/gov/it/pagina-iniziale.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.admin.ch/gov/en/start.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="201">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <department id="701">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Wirtschaft, Bildung und Forschung</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'économie, de la formation et de la recherche</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'economia, della formazione e della ricerca</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Economic Affairs, Education and Research</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <department id="1070">
      <name lang="de">Der Bundesrat</name>
      <name lang="fr">Conseil fédéral</name>
      <name lang="it">Il Consiglio federale</name>
      <name lang="en">The Federal Council</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.admin.ch/gov/de/start.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.admin.ch/gov/fr/accueil.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.admin.ch/gov/it/pagina-iniziale.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.admin.ch/gov/en/start.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Bundesrat nimmt von den Ergebnissen der Vernehmlassung zur Weiterführung des Bundesgesetzes über die Zusammenarbeit mit den Staaten Osteuropas Kenntnis</title>
      <lead>Der Bundesrat hat vom Ergebnis des Vernehmlassungsverfahrens zur Weiterführung des Bundesgesetzes über die Zusammenarbeit mit den Staaten Osteuropas (BG Ost) Kenntnis genommen. Das aktuelle Gesetz ist noch bis Ende Mai 2017 gültig. Die Erneuerung des BG Ost würde die Weiterführung der Zusammenarbeit mit den Staaten Osteuropas und der ehemaligen Sowjetunion, welche nicht Mitglieder der Europäischen Union sind, ermöglichen. Die entsprechende Botschaft soll dem Parlament spätestens bis Ende Februar 2016 überwiesen werden. </lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Die Schweiz unterstützt den politischen, wirtschaftlichen und sozialen Übergang (Transition) in Osteuropa und in Ländern der ehemaligen Sowjetunion (Transitionszusammenarbeit) seit Beginn der 1990er Jahre. Die rechtliche Grundlage dafür stellt das Bundesgesetz über die Zusammenarbeit mit den Staaten Osteuropas (BG Ost) von 2006 dar. Gleichzeitig bildet dieses Bundesgesetz die Rechtsgrundlage für den Schweizer Beitrag zur Verringerung der wirtschaftlichen und sozialen Ungleichheiten in der erweiterten Europäischen Union (EU). Das BG Ost ist bis 31. Mai 2017 gültig. Um die Zusammenarbeit mit den Staaten Osteuropas fortsetzen zu können, hat der Bundesrat in der Vernehmlassung vorgeschlagen, das Gesetz bis Ende 2024 zu verlängern. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Die Transition zu demokratischen und pluralistischen Staaten und der Übergang zu freien und sozialen Marktwirtschaften gehören zu den übergeordneten Zielen und Interessen der Schweiz in der Zusammenarbeit mit den Staaten Osteuropas und den Ländern der ehemaligen Sowjetunion. Die Transitionszusammenarbeit soll dazu beitragen, die Stabilität und den Frieden zu festigen, positive Entwicklungsperspektiven in diesen Ländern zu schaffen, soziale Ungleichheiten abzubauen und das Umfeld für Handel und Investitionen zu stärken. Wie die Vernehmlassung gezeigt hat, wird die Weiterführung der Rechtsgrundlage für die Transitionszusammenarbeit grossmehrheitlich unterstützt. Vor diesem Hintergrund hat der Bundesrat das EDA und das WBF mit der Erneuerung des BG Ost beauftragt.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Überweisung der Botschaft spätestens Ende Februar 2016&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Das neue BG Ost soll dem Bundesrat bis spätestens Ende Februar 2016 zusammen mit der Botschaft über die internationale Zusammenarbeit der Schweiz 2017-2020 und dem Rahmenkredit für die Finanzierung der Transitionszusammenarbeit vorgelegt werden. Damit kann das Parlament 2016 gleichzeitig über den finanziellen Beitrag zur Weiterführung der Transitionszusammenarbeit und über dessen künftige Rechtsgrundlage befinden. Gestützt auf die Vernehmlassungsergebnisse beabsichtigt der Bundesrat weiterhin, die Transitionszusammenarbeit ab 2025 dem Bundesgesetz über die internationale Entwicklungszusammenarbeit und humanitäre Hilfe zu unterstellen.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;In der Vernehmlassung wurde verschiedentlich gefordert, eine separate Rechtsgrundlage für eine allfällige Erneuerung des Beitrags der Schweiz zur Verringerung der wirtschaftlichen und sozialen Ungleichheiten in der erweiterten EU (Erweiterungsbeitrag) zu schaffen. Der Bundesrat wird einen Entscheid dazu spätestens anlässlich der Überweisung der Botschaft zum BG Ost Ende Februar 2016 fällen. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Eine allfällige Erneuerung der Rechtsgrundlage nimmt die Frage weiterer finanzieller Beiträge an die neuen EU-Mitgliedstaaten nicht vorweg. Für den Bundesrat steht fest, dass über eine mögliche Erneuerung des Erweiterungsbeitrags im Lichte der weiteren Entwicklung der Gesamtbeziehungen zwischen der Schweiz und der EU entschieden werden soll. Dabei kommt dem Verlauf der aktuellen Verhandlungen im Rahmen der vom Bundesrat angestrebten Konsolidierung und Erneuerung des bilateralen Wegs sowie der Frage einer Lösung für die Personenfreizügigkeit eine entscheidende Rolle zu. &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>EDA Information Tel. +41 58 462 31 53 info@eda.admin.ch SECO-Information Tel: +41 58 464 09 10 info@seco-cooperation.admin.ch</contact>
      <attachment id="137882">
        <title>Bericht</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>57</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/40018.pdf</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </attachment>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Prolongation de la durée de validité de la loi fédérale sur la coopération avec les Etats d’Europe de l’Est: le Conseil fédéral prend connaissance des résultats de la consultation</title>
      <lead>Le Conseil fédéral a pris connaissance des résultats de la procédure de consultation concernant la prolongation de la durée de validité de la loi fédérale sur la coopération avec les Etats d’Europe de l’Est (LF Est). La loi actuelle arrive à échéance fin mai 2017. La mise à jour de la LF Est permettrait de poursuivre la coopération avec les Etats de l'Europe de l'Est et de l'ancienne Union soviétique qui ne sont pas membres de l'Union européenne. Le message du Conseil fédéral doit être transmis au Parlement avant la fin février 2016 au plus tard. </lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;La Suisse soutient la transition politique, économique et sociale en Europe de l’Est et dans les pays de l’ancienne Union soviétique (aide à la transition) depuis le début des années 1990. La loi fédérale de 2006 sur la coopération avec les Etats d’Europe de l’Est offre une base légale aux efforts déployés dans ce contexte. Cette loi constitue également la base légale de la contribution suisse à l’atténuation des disparités économiques et sociales dans l’Union européenne élargie (UE). Or, la durée de validité de ce texte arrivera à expiration le 31 mai 2017. Le Conseil fédéral a donc proposé, dans le cadre de la procédure de consultation, de la prolonger jusqu’à fin 2024 pour pouvoir poursuivre la coopération avec les Etats d’Europe de l’Est. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;La transition vers des démocraties pluralistes et le passage à des économies de marché libres et sociales figurent parmi les objectifs et intérêts primordiaux que poursuit la Suisse à travers sa coopération avec les pays d’Europe de l’Est et de l’ancienne Union soviétique. L'aide à la transition doit contribuer à consolider la stabilité et la paix, à ouvrir de nouvelles perspectives de développement, à réduire les inégalités sociales et à créer des conditions propices au commerce et à l’investissement. Il ressort de la procédure de consultation qu'une grande majorité des sondés souhaite prolonger la validité de la base légale sur laquelle repose l'aide à la transition. Le Conseil fédéral a donc chargé le DFAE et le DEFR de mettre à jour la LF Est.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Transmission du message d'ici fin février 2016 au plus tard&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;La nouvelle LF Est doit être présentée au Conseil fédéral d'ici fin février 2016 au plus tard, en même temps que le message concernant la coopération internationale de la Suisse 2017-2020 et le crédit-cadre destiné à l'aide à la transition. En 2016, le Parlement pourra ainsi se prononcer simultanément sur la contribution financière en faveur de la poursuite de l'aide à la transition et sur sa future base légale. Sur la base des résultats de la procédure de consultation, le Conseil fédéral entend en outre soumettre l'aide à la transition à la loi fédérale sur la coopération au développement et l’aide humanitaire à partir de 2025.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;Durant la procédure de consultation, plusieurs voix ont demandé la création d'une base légale distincte en cas de renouvellement de la contribution suisse à l’atténuation des disparités économiques et sociales dans l’Union européenne élargie (contribution à l'élargissement). Le Conseil fédéral prendra une décision en la matière au plus tard lors de la transmission du message sur la LF Est, fin février 2016. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Les décisions portant sur les contributions financières en faveur des nouveaux Etats membres de l'UE sont indépendantes de l'éventuelle mise à jour de la base légale. Pour le Conseil fédéral, il est en effet clair qu'il faudra encore, à la lumière de l'évolution générale des relations entre la Suisse et l'UE, se prononcer sur un possible renouvellement de la contribution à l'élargissement. Les négociations en cours dans le cadre de la consolidation et du renouvellement de la voie bilatérale visés par le Conseil fédéral ainsi que la recherche d'une solution pour la libre circulation des personnes constituent des facteurs clés à cet égard. &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Information DFAE Tél. +41 58 462 31 53 info@eda.admin.ch Information SECO Tel: +41 58 464 09 10 info@seco-cooperation.admin.ch</contact>
      <attachment id="137883">
        <title>Rapport</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>57</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/40019.pdf</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </attachment>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Il Consiglio federale prende atto dei risultati della procedura di consultazione sul estensione della validità della legge federale sulla cooperazione con gli Stati dell’Europa dell’Est</title>
      <lead>Il Consiglio federale ha preso atto dei risultati della procedura di consultazione sul estensione della validità della legge federale sulla cooperazione con gli Stati dell’Europa dell’Est. La legge attuale è valida ancora fino alla fine di maggio 2017. Il rinnovo della legge federale sulla cooperazione con gli Stati dell’Europa dell’Est consentirebbe di proseguire la cooperazione con gli Stati dell’Europa dell’Est e i Paesi dell’ex Unione sovietica che non sono membri dell’Unione europea. Il relativo messaggio sarà trasmesso al Parlamento al più tardi entro la fine di febbraio 2016. </lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;La Svizzera sostiene la transizione politica, economica e sociale nell’Europa dell’Est e nei Paesi dell’ex Unione sovietica (cooperazione di transizione) dall’inizio degli anni 1990. La legge federale del 24 marzo 2006 sulla cooperazione con gli Stati dell’Europa dell’Est ne costituisce la base legale. Allo stesso tempo, questa legge disciplina anche il contributo svizzero volto a diminuire le disparità economiche e sociali nell’Unione europea allargata (UE). La legge federale sulla cooperazione con gli Stati dell’Europa dell’Est è valida fino al 31 maggio 2017. Per poter continuare la cooperazione con gli Stati dell’Europa dell’Est, nella procedura di consultazione il Consiglio federale ha proposto di prolungare la validità della legge fino alla fine del 2024. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Tra gli obiettivi principali e gli interessi della Svizzera nell’ambito della cooperazione con gli Stati dell’Europa dell’Est e i Paesi dell’ex Unione sovietica vi è la transizione verso Stati democratici e pluralistici e verso economie di mercato libere e sociali. La cooperazione di transizione vuole contribuire a consolidare la stabilità e la pace, a creare prospettive di sviluppo positive in questi Paesi, a rimuovere le disuguaglianze sociali e a rafforzare il contesto per il commercio e gli investimenti. Come dimostrato dalla procedura di consultazione, la maggioranza è favorevole al mantenimento della base legale per la cooperazione di transizione. Per questo motivo il Consiglio federale ha incaricato il DFAE e il DEFR di procedere al rinnovo della legge federale sulla cooperazione con gli Stati dell’Europa dell’Est.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Trasmissione del messaggio prevista entro la fine di febbraio 2016&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;La nuova legge sulla cooperazione con gli Stati dell’Europa dell’Est sarà presentata al Consiglio federale entro la fine di febbraio 2016, insieme al messaggio concernente la cooperazione internazionale della Svizzera 2017-2020 e il credito quadro per il finanziamento della cooperazione di transizione. Nel 2016, il Parlamento potrà così pronunciarsi anche sul contributo finanziario per il proseguimento della cooperazione di transizione e sulla rispettiva futura base legale. Visti i risultati della procedura di consultazione, il Consiglio federale auspica inoltre che, dal 2025, la cooperazione di transizione sia sottoposta alla legge federale sulla cooperazione allo sviluppo e l’aiuto umanitario internazionali.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;Vari partecipanti alla procedura di consultazione hanno espresso la richiesta di creare una base legale separata per un eventuale rinnovo del contributo svizzero per la riduzione delle disparità economiche e sociali nell’UE allargata (contributo all’allargamento). Su questo punto, il Consiglio federale prenderà una decisione al più tardi a fine febbraio 2016, in occasione della trasmissione del messaggio concernente la legge federale sulla cooperazione con gli Stati dell’Europa dell’Est. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Un eventuale mantenimento della base legale non anticipa la questione di altri contributi ai nuovi Stati membri dell’UE. Il Consiglio federale ritiene che un possibile rinnovo del contributo all’allargamento debba essere deciso alla luce dell’evoluzione delle relazioni complessive tra la Svizzera e l’UE. In questo senso, l’esito dei negoziati in corso per rafforzare e rinnovare la via bilaterale, come richiesto dal Consiglio federale, compresa una soluzione alla questione della libera circolazione delle persone, è un fattore cruciale. &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Informazione DFAE Tel. +41 58 462 31 53 info@eda.admin.ch Informazione SECO Tel: +41 58 464 09 10 info@seco-cooperation.admin.ch</contact>
      <attachment id="137884">
        <title>Rapporto</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>55</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/40020.pdf</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </attachment>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>The Federal Council notes the results of the consultation on continuation of the Federal Act on Cooperation with the States of Eastern Europe</title>
      <lead>The Federal Council has taken note of the results of the consultation on continuation of the Federal Act on Cooperation with the States of Eastern Europe, which remains in force until the end of May 2017. Its renewal would enable the continuation of cooperation with those states of Eastern Europe and the former Soviet Union that are not members of the European Union. The corresponding dispatch to Parliament is expected to be submitted by the end of February 2016 at the latest. </lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Switzerland has supported the political, economic and social transition in Eastern Europe and in countries of the former Soviet Union (transition cooperation) since the start of the 1990s. The 2006 Federal Act on Cooperation with the States of Eastern Europe provides the legal framework for this. It also serves as the legal basis for Switzerland's contribution to reducing economic and social disparities in the enlarged European Union (EU). The current act remains in force until 31 May 2017. In order to continue cooperation with the states of Eastern Europe, the Federal Council proposed in the consultation to extend the act until 2024. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The transition to democratic, pluralistic states and to free and social market economies are among Switzerland's overriding objectives and interests in its cooperation with the countries of Eastern Europe and the former Soviet Union. This transition cooperation is intended to help strengthen stability and peace in these countries while reducing social disparities, creating positive development prospects and improving the environment for trade and investments. As the consultation has made clear, continuing the legal basis for transition cooperation has the support of a very large majority. Against this background the Federal Council has mandated the FDFA together with the Federal Department of Economic Affairs, Education and Research (EAER) to renew the Eastern Europe Cooperation Act.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dispatch to be submitted by the end of February 2016 at the latest&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The new Eastern Europe Cooperation Act should be submitted to the Federal Council by the end of February 2016 together with the Dispatch on International Cooperation 2017-2020 and the framework credit for the financing of transition cooperation. This will make it possible for parliament to debate on the financial contribution and the future legal basis for transition cooperation at the same time in 2016. On the basis of the result of the consultation it is still the intention of the Federal Council to make transition cooperation subject to the Federal Act on International Development Cooperation and Humanitarian Aid as of 2025.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;In the consultation there were several calls to create a separate legal basis for eventual renewal of Switzerland's contribution to reducing economic and social disparities in the enlarged European Union (enlargement contribution). The Federal Council will decide on this at the latest at the end of February 2016, at the time of the submission of the Dispatch on the Eastern Europe Cooperation Act. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Eventual renewal of the legal basis does not prejudge the question of further financial contributions to the new EU member states. As far as the Federal Council is concerned a decision on the possible renewal of the enlargement contribution should be made in the light of the future development of overall relations between Switzerland and the EU. The course of current negotiations on the consolidation and renewal of the bilateral approach desired by the Federal Council as well as the question of a solution to the issue of the free movement of persons are of crucial importance in this context. &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>FDFA Information Tel. +41 58 462 31 53 info@eda.admin.ch SECO Information Tel: +41 58 464 09 10 info@seco-cooperation.admin.ch</contact>
      <attachment id="137885">
        <title>Report (DE)</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>57</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/40021.pdf</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </attachment>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="34">
        <name lang="de">Europa</name>
        <name lang="fr">Europe</name>
        <name lang="it">Europa</name>
        <name lang="en">Europe</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
