<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="99433" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2023-12-14</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="1063" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>701</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Paul Scherrer Institut</name>
      <name lang="fr">Institut Paul Scherrer</name>
      <name lang="it">Istituto Paul Scherrer</name>
      <name lang="en">Paul Scherrer Institut</name>
      <www lang="de"/>
      <www lang="fr"/>
      <www lang="it"/>
      <www lang="en"/>
      <email lang="de">info@psi.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@psi.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@psi.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@psi.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="701">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Wirtschaft, Bildung und Forschung</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'économie, de la formation et de la recherche</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'economia, della formazione e della ricerca</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Economic Affairs, Education and Research</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Villigen</city>
      <title>Früherkennung von Krebs möglich machen</title>
      <lead>Blutzellen verraten Tumore im Körper. Forschende des Paul Scherrer Instituts PSI erzielen Fortschritte bei der Entwicklung eines Tests für die frühzeitige Diagnose von Krebs.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Einen entstehenden Tumor in einem sehr frühen Stadium zu erkennen sowie den Erfolg oder Misserfolg einer Krebstherapie engmaschig zu überwachen, ist für das Überleben von Patientinnen und Patienten entscheidend. In beiden Punkten haben Forschende des Paul Scherrer Instituts PSI nun einen Durchbruch erzielt. Eine Gruppe um G.V. Shivashankar, Leiter der Mechano-Genomik am PSI und Professor an der ETH Zürich, konnte belegen, dass Veränderungen in der Organisation des Zellkerns mancher Blutzellen einen sicheren Hinweis auf einen Tumor im Körper liefern können. Mit ihrer Technik – unter Einsatz von künstlicher Intelligenz – konnten die Wissenschaftler Gesunde und Erkrankte mit einer Treffsicherheit von rund 85 Prozent unterscheiden. Ausserdem gelang es ihnen, die Art der Tumor-Erkrankung – Melanom, Gliom oder Kopf-Hals-Tumor – korrekt zu bestimmen. «Das ist das erste Mal weltweit, dass dies jemand geschafft hat», freut sich Shivashankar. Ihre Ergebnisse haben die Forschenden in der Fachzeitschrift &lt;i&gt;npj Precision Oncology&lt;/i&gt; veröffentlicht.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Tumorzellen verraten sich selbst&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Eine Krebserkrankung im Körper zu erkennen oder deren Therapieverlauf zu überwachen, ist normalerweise sehr aufwendig und erfolgt oft erst in einer späten Phase, wenn die Anzeichen unübersehbar werden. Grundlagenforschende sind deswegen auf der Suche nach Verfahren, die sowohl im klinischen Alltag einfach einzusetzen als auch verlässlich und empfindlich sind. Die Forschungsgruppe um Shivashankar nahm dabei Lymphozyten und Monozyten ins Visier, die in Fachkreisen unter der Bezeichnung mononukleäre Zellen des peripheren Blutes geführt werden. Diese sind über eine einfache Blutprobe leicht zu gewinnen und haben einen im Mikroskop gut sichtbaren, runden Kern. Das dort befindliche Erbmaterial, so die Vermutung der Forschenden, reagiert auf Stoffe in der Blutbahn, die der Tumor abgibt, das sogenannte Sekretom. Dieses aktiviert das sogenannte Chromatin in den Kernen der Blutzellen, verändert also die Organisation der Erbsubstanz darin. Das kann dann wiederum als Indikator oder Biomarker dienen. «Unsere Hypothese war, dass die Blutzellen Tumor-Detektoren darstellen – das hat uns weit gebracht», erklärt Shivashankar.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Künstliche Intelligenz hilft bei der Diagnose&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Die Forschenden untersuchten das Chromatin der Blutzellen – so nennt sich die zu einer Art Knäuel verpackte Erbsubstanz DNA – mithilfe der Fluoreszenz-Mikroskopie. Dabei erfassten sie etwa die äussere Textur, die Packungsdichte oder den Kontrast des Chromatins in den Lymphozyten oder Monozyten, zusammen genommen etwa zweihundert Merkmale. Die Mikroskop-Bilder von jeweils gesunden und erkrankten Versuchsteilnehmenden speisten sie in eine künstliche Intelligenz (KI) ein. Dabei nutzen sie die Bedingungen des «supervised learning», die dazu dienen, der Software bekannte Unterschiede beizubringen. Beim folgenden Ansatz des «deep learnings» identifizierte der Algorithmus dann selbst Unterschiede zwischen «gesunden» und «kranken» Zellen, die für den menschlichen Betrachter nicht erkennbar sind.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Die Forschungsgruppe verfolgte drei verschiedene Ansätze. In einer ersten Versuchsreihe untersuchte sie, ob das Verfahren gesunde Kontrollpersonen und Erkrankte voneinander unterscheiden kann. Dazu verglich sie die Blutzellen von zehn Patientinnen und Patienten mit jenen von zehn Gesunden. Die KI konnte gesunde und krebskranke Patienten mit einer Genauigkeit von 85 Prozent unterscheiden. «Selbst die Analyse nur einer einzigen beliebigen Zelle erfolgte noch mit einer sehr hohen Genauigkeit», so Shivashankar. In einem zweiten Ansatz ging es darum, zu ermitteln, ob die KI sogar unterschiedliche Tumorarten unterscheiden kann. Dazu fütterten die Forschenden den Algorithmus mit den Chromatin-Daten der Blutzellen von je zehn Erkrankten mit einem Gliom (Tumor des Stützgewebes der Nervenzellen), einem Meningiom (Tumor der Hirnhaut) und einem Hals-Nasen-Ohrentumor. Auch dieser Versuch erwies sich als erfolgreich. Die Zuordnungen wiesen eine Genauigkeit von mehr als 85 Prozent auf. In einer dritten Fragestellung schliesslich ging es um Patienten, die sich am Zentrum für Protonentherapie ZPT des PSI einer Bestrahlung unterzogen oder unterzogen hatten.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Damien Weber, Leiter und Chefarzt des ZPT, sieht in dem diagnostischen Ansatz grosses Potenzial und bat 150 seiner Patienten um Zustimmung, ihre Blutproben für die Studie auswerten zu dürfen: «Wir erhoffen uns von der neuen Methode, dass sie sowohl Diagnose als auch die Kontrolle des Therapieerfolges verbessern können.»&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt; Um den Erfolg der Intervention zu erfassen, wurden die Blutproben vor, während und nach der Strahlentherapie entnommen. Auch hier arbeitete die Software erfolgreich und ordnete die Muster mit einer sehr hohen Genauigkeit richtig zu. Die Behandlung, so die Erwartung, sollte die Konzentration und Zusammensetzung der Tumorsignale im Blut verringern – und so trat es auch ein und das Aussehen der Erbsubstanz der Blutzellen normalisierte sich. «Es war erstaunlich zu beobachten, wie sich die Struktur des Chromatins im Verlauf der Behandlung wieder mehr dem gesunden Muster näherte», zeigte sich Shivashankar zufrieden.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Viele Anwendungen in der Tumordiagnose und -therapie denkbar&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Aus Sicht des Biologen und seiner Mitarbeiter ist das neue Verfahren auf Basis des Blutzellen-Chromatins nicht nur auf die untersuchten Tumore anwendbar, sondern auf zahlreiche Krebsarten. Und es könnte nicht nur auf die Verlaufskontrolle der Protonentherapie beschränkt sein, sondern auch auf viele weitere Therapieformen, so etwa bei der Strahlentherapie generell, der Chemotherapie und bei Operationen. Ob das so ist, müssen nun weitere Forschungen belegen. In einer entsprechenden Publikation in der Fachzeitschrift &lt;i&gt;Scientific Reports&lt;/i&gt; hat die Gruppe um Shivashankar in Zusammenarbeit mit dem Zentrum für Radiopharmazeutische Wissenschaften (CRS) am PSI bereits getestet, ob die Chromatin-Biomarker zum Aufspüren von strahlen- und chemoresistenten Zellen verwendet werden können. Bis eine Zulassung des Verfahrens durch die Behörden in der klinischen Praxis möglich ist, bleibt noch viel Arbeit zu tun – vor allem Studien mit einer grösseren Zahl an Teilnehmenden, um abzuklären, wie hoch unter klinischen Bedingungen die Zahl der falschen positiven Alarme sowie die falschen negativen Aussagen sind. Dass der Weg in die klinische Anwendung vorgezeichnet ist und Patienten von dem Verfahren profitieren werden, steht für Shivashankar ausser Zweifel. «Die Methode steht!», sagt er. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Text: Werner Siefer&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Über das PSI&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; Das Paul Scherrer Institut PSI entwickelt, baut und betreibt grosse und komplexe Forschungsanlagen und stellt sie der nationalen und internationalen Forschungsgemeinde zur Verfügung. Eigene Forschungsschwerpunkte sind Zukunftstechnologien, Energie und Klima, Health Innovation und Grundlagen der Natur. Die Ausbildung von jungen Menschen ist ein zentrales Anliegen des PSI. Deshalb sind etwa ein Viertel unserer Mitarbeitenden Postdoktorierende, Doktorierende oder Lernende. Insgesamt beschäftigt das PSI 2200 Mitarbeitende, das damit das grösste Forschungsinstitut der Schweiz ist. Das Jahresbudget beträgt rund CHF 420 Mio. Das PSI ist Teil des ETH-Bereichs, dem auch die ETH Zürich und die ETH Lausanne angehören sowie die Forschungsinstitute Eawag, Empa und WSL.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Originalveröffentlichung&lt;/h3&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Imaging and AI based chromatin biomarkers for cancer diagnosis and therapy evaluation from liquid biopsies &lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Kiran Challa, Daniel Paysan, Dominic Leiser, Nadia Sauder, Damien Weber and Shivashankar, G.V. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;i&gt;npj Precision Oncology,&lt;/i&gt; 14.12.2023&lt;br /&gt;DOI: 10.1038/s41698-023-00484-8 &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Prof. Dr. G.V. Shivashankar Leiter des Labors für Biologie im Nanobereich Paul Scherrer Institut, Forschungsstrasse 111, 5232 Villigen PSI, Schweiz Telefon: +41 56 310 42 50, E-Mail: gv.shivashankar@psi.ch [Englisch]</contact>
      <link id="268426">
        <title>Bilder und weitere Informationen</title>
        <uri>https://psi.ch/de/node/60742</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Villigen</city>
      <title>Permettre une détection précoce du cancer</title>
      <lead>Les cellules sanguines révèlent la présence de tumeurs dans l’organisme. Des scientifiques de l’Institut Paul Scherrer PSI progressent dans le développement d’un test pour le diagnostic précoce du cancer.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Dépister précocement un cancer en train d’apparaître à un stade très précoce, et surveiller de manière serrée le succès ou l’échec d’un traitement anticancéreux est décisif pour la survie des patients. Des scientifiques du PSI viennent d’accomplir une percée sur les deux fronts. Un groupe emmené par G.V. Shivashankar, responsable de la mécanogénomique au PSI et professeur à l’ETH Zurich, a réussi à démontrer que des modifications au niveau de l’organisations du noyau cellulaire de certaine cellules sanguines pouvaient fournir un indice sûr de la présence d’une tumeur dans l’organisme. Avec leur technique – qui utilise l’intelligence artificielle – les scientifiques ont pu démontrer qu’ils étaient en mesure de distinguer les personnes saines des personnes malades avec précision d’environ 85%. Par ailleurs, ils ont réussi à déterminer correctement le type de cancer dont souffrait les patients: mélanome, gliome ou cancer de la tête et du cou. «C’est la première fois au monde que quelqu’un y parvient», se réjouit G.V. Shivashankar. Les scientifiques ont publié leurs résultats dans la revue spécialisée &lt;i&gt;npj Precision Oncology&lt;/i&gt;.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Les cellules tumorales se trahissent toutes seules &lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;En principe, identifier la présence d’une maladie cancéreuse dans l’organisme ou surveiller le déroulement de son traitement sont des tâches très fastidieuses, qui interviennent souvent à une phase avancée, lorsque les signes deviennent évidents. Les spécialistes de la recherche fondamentale sont donc à la recherche d’une méthode qui serait à la fois facile à utiliser dans le quotidien clinique, mais aussi fiable et sensible. Le groupe de recherche emmené par G.V. Shivashankar s’est intéressée aux lymphocytes et aux monocytes, appelés cellules mononucléaires du sang périphérique par les spécialistes. Ils peuvent être facilement obtenus par un simple prélèvement sanguin et leur noyau rond est bien visible au microscope. L’hypothèse des scientifiques était la suivante: le matériel génétique que contient leur noyau réagit aux substances que la tumeur émet dans la circulation sanguine, que l’on appelle le sécrétome. Ce sécrétome active la chromatine dans les noyaux des cellules sanguines. Autrement dit, il modifie l’organisation du matériel génétique qui s’y trouve. Cela peut servir d’indicateur ou de biomarqueur. «Notre hypothèse était que les cellules sanguines étaient des détecteurs de tumeurs, résume G.V. Shivashankar. Et cela nous a menés loin.» &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;L’aide de l’intelligence artificielle lors du diagnostic &lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Les scientifiques ont étudié la chromatine des cellules sanguines – c’est ainsi que l’on appelle la structure au sein de laquelle l’ADN ou le génome est emballé en une espèce de pelote – à l’aide de la microscopie par fluorescence. Celle-ci a capté par exemple la texture externe, la densité de l’emballage ou encore le contraste de la chromatine dans les lymphocytes et les monocytes, soit quelque 200 caractéristiques en tout. Ils ont alimenté une intelligence artificielle (IA) avec les images de sujets sains et de sujets malades obtenues au microscope. Ce faisant, ils ont exploité les conditions du «supervised learning», dont le but est d’inculquer au logiciel les différences connues. Lors de l’étape suivante du «deep learning», l’algorithme a ensuite identifié lui-même des différences entre les cellules «saines» et les cellules «malades», qui n’étaient pas visibles pour l’observateur humain.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Le groupe de recherche a poursuivi trois démarches différentes. Lors d’une première série d’essais, il a étudié si la méthode était capable de distinguer les personnes contrôles des personnes malades. Pour ce faire, il a comparé les cellules sanguines de dix patients avec celles de dix personnes saines. L’IA a pu distinguer les patients sains des patients cancéreux avec une précision de 85 pour cent. «Même l’analyse d’une seule cellule quelconque a été effectuée avec une grande précision», souligne G.V. Shivashankar. Dans le cadre d’une deuxième démarche, il s’est agi de déterminer si l’IA pouvait distinguer différents types de cancers. Pour ce faire, les scientifiques ont alimenté l’algorithme avec les données de la chromatines des cellules sanguines de dix malades atteints d’un gliome (cancer du tissu de soutien des cellules nerveuses), d’un méningiome (cancer des méninges) et d'une tumeurs en oto-rhino-laryngologie. Cet essai a été couronné de succès, lui aussi. Les cancers ont été attribués avec une exactitude de plus de 85 pour cent. Enfin, une troisième question portait sur les patients qui ont été ou sont toujours en traitement au Centre de protonthérapie (CPT) du PSI. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Damien Weber, directeur et médecin-chef du ZPT voit un grand potentiel dans cette approche diagnostique et a demandé à 150 de ses patients de donner leur accord pour que leurs échantillons de sang soient analysés dans le cadre de l'étude: «Nous espérons que cette nouvelle méthode peut améliorer à la fois le diagnostic et le contrôle du succès du traitement.»&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Pour évaluer le succès de l’intervention, les scientifiques ont prélevé des échantillons de sang avant, pendant et après la radiothérapie. Là encore, le logiciel a fonctionné avec succès et a correctement classé les échantillons avec une très grande précision. On s’attendait à ce que le traitement réduise la concentration et la composition des signaux tumoraux dans le sang, et c’est ce qui s’est produit: l’apparence du matériel génétique des cellules sanguines s’est normalisée. «Observer la manière dont la structure de la chromatine se rapprochait à nouveau du modèle sain au fil du traitement s’est avéré étonnant», relève G.V. Shivashankar, satisfait.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;De nombreuses applications envisageables dans le domaine du diagnostic et du traitement des cancers &lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Du point de vue du biologiste et de ses collaborateurs, la nouvelle méthode basée sur la chromatine des cellules sanguines n’est pas uniquement applicable aux cancers étudiés, mais aussi à un grand nombre d’autres. Et elle pourrait bien ne pas se limiter au contrôle du déroulement de la protonthérapie, mais être utilisée pour surveiller d’autres types de traitements, comme la radiothérapie en général, la chimiothérapie et la chirurgie. D’autres travaux de recherche doivent désormais démontrer si c’est bel et bien le cas. Dans une publication parue dans la revue spécialisée &lt;i&gt;Scientific Reports&lt;/i&gt;, le groupe de G.V. Shivashankar a déjà testé, en collaboration avec le Centre des sciences radiopharmaceutiques (CRS) du PSI, si les biomarqueurs de la chromatine pouvaient être utilisés pour détecter des cellules résistantes aux radiations et à la chimiothérapie. D’ici à ce que les autorités délivrent une autorisation de la méthode dans la pratique clinique, il reste beaucoup de travail à faire. Notamment des études incluant un plus grand nombre de participants, afin de déterminer le nombre de faux positifs et de faux négatifs dans des conditions cliniques. Mais pour G.V. Shivashankar, il est hors de doute que la voie qui mène à l’application clinique est tracée et que les patients profiteront du procédé. «La méthode est prête!», affirme-t-il. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Texte: Werner Siefer&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;À propos du PSI&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; L'Institut Paul Scherrer PSI développe, construit et exploite des grandes installations de recherche complexes et les met à la disposition de la communauté scientifique nationale et internationale. Les domaines de recherche de l'institut sont centrés sur des technologies d'avenir, énergie et climat, innovation santé ainsi que fondements de la nature. La formation des générations futures est un souci central du PSI. Pour cette raison, environ un quart de nos collaborateurs sont des postdocs, des doctorants ou des apprentis. Au total, le PSI emploie 2200 personnes, étant ainsi le plus grand institut de recherche de Suisse. Le budget annuel est d'environ CHF 420 millions. Le PSI fait partie du domaine des EPF, les autres membres étant l'ETH Zurich, l'EPF Lausanne, l'Eawag (Institut de Recherche de l'Eau), l'Empa (Laboratoire fédéral d'essai des matériaux et de recherche) et le WSL (Institut fédéral de recherches sur la forêt, la neige et le paysage).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3&gt;&lt;b&gt;Publication originale&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/h3&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Implanting mechanically reprogrammed fibroblasts for aged tissue regeneration and wound healing&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Kiran Challa, Daniel Paysan, Dominic Leiser, Nadia Sauder, Damien Weber and Shivashankar, G.V.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;i&gt;npj Precision Oncology, &lt;/i&gt;14.12.2023&lt;br /&gt;DOI: 10.1038/s41698-023-00484-8&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Prof. G.V. Shivashankar Directeur du Laboratoire de biologie à l’échelle nanométrique Institut Paul Scherrer, Forschungsstrasse 111, 5232 Villigen PSI, Suisse Téléphone: +41 56 310 42 50, e-mail: gv.shivashankar@psi.ch [anglais]</contact>
      <link id="268427">
        <title>Images et informations supplémentaires</title>
        <uri>https://psi.ch/fr/node/60742</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Villigen</city>
      <title>Enabling early detection of cancer</title>
      <lead>Blood cells reveal tumours in the body. Researchers at the Paul Scherrer Institute achieve an advance with the development of a test for early diagnosis of cancer.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;The ability to detect a developing tumour at a very early stage and to closely monitor the success or failure of cancer therapy is crucial for a patient’s survival. A breakthrough on both counts has now been achieved by researchers at the Paul Scherrer Institute PSI. Researchers led by G.V. Shivashankar, head of PSI‘s Laboratory for Nanoscale Biology and professor of Mechano-Genomics at ETH Zurich, were able to prove that changes in the organisation of the cell nucleus of some blood cells can provide a reliable indication of a tumour in the body. With their technique – using artificial intelligence – the scientists were able to distinguish between healthy and sick people with an accuracy of around 85 percent. Besides that, they managed to correctly determine the type of tumour disease – melanoma, glioma, or head and neck tumour. “This is the first time anyone, worldwide, has achieved this,” Shivashankar says happily. The researchers have published their results in the journal &lt;i&gt;npj Precision Oncology.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Tumour cells give themselves away&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;It is normally very time-consuming to detect cancer in the body or to monitor it during the course of therapy, and these procedures are often carried out only in a late phase, when the signs become obvious. For this reason, scientists engaged in fundamental research are looking for techniques that will be easy to use in everyday clinical practice as well as reliable and sensitive. Shivashankar’s research group set its sights on lymphocytes and monocytes, which people in the field refer to as mononuclear cells of peripheral blood. These are easy to obtain using a simple blood sample and have a round nucleus that is easy to see under the microscope. The researchers‘ hunch was that the genetic material there reacts to substances released by the tumour into the bloodstream, the so-called secretome. This activates the so-called chromatin in the nuclei of the blood cells and thus alters the organisation of the genetic material it contains. This can then serve as either an indicator or a biomarker. “Our hypothesis was that the blood cells act as tumour detectors – and that took us a long way,” Shivashankar explains.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Artificial intelligence helps with diagnosis&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The researchers used fluorescence microscopy to examine the chromatin of the blood cells – this is the term for the genetic material DNA packaged in a tangled ball. They recorded around 200 different characteristics in all, including the external texture, the packing density, and the contrast of the chromatin in the lymphocytes or monocytes. They fed microscope images of samples from healthy and sick test participants into an artificial intelligence (AI) system. In doing so, they employed “supervised learning,” which is used to teach known differences to the software. In the subsequent “deep learning” approach, the algorithm itself identified differences between “healthy” and “sick” cells that would not be discernible to a human observer.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The research group took three different approaches. In an initial series of experiments, the researchers investigated whether the technique could distinguish healthy control subjects from those suffering from the disease. To do this, they compared the blood cells of ten cancer patients with those of ten healthy people. The artificial intelligence system was able to distinguish healthy and cancer patients with 85 percent accuracy. “Even the analysis of just one arbitrary individual cell was carried out with a very high level of accuracy,» Shivashankar says. A second approach was to determine whether the AI system could distinguish between different types of tumours. To do this, the researchers fed the algorithm with the chromatin data from the blood cells of ten patients with a glioma (a tumour of the supporting tissue of nerve cells), a meningioma (a tumour of membranes that protect the brain and spinal cord), and a head and neck tumour. This experiment too proved successful. The assignments had an accuracy of more than 85 percent. Finally, a third question concerned patients who were undergoing or had received treatment at the Centre for Proton Therapy CPT at PSI.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Damien Weber, director and Chief Physician of the ZPT, sees great potential in the diagnostic approach and asked 150 of his patients for permission to analyse their blood samples for the study: “We hope that the new method could improve both diagnosis and the monitoring of treatment success.”&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;To determine the success of the intervention, the scientists took blood samples before, during, and after the radiation therapy. Here too the software worked successfully and correctly assigned the patterns with a very high level of accuracy. The treatment was expected to reduce the concentration and build-up of tumour signals in the blood – this is what happened, and the appearance of the genetic material of the blood cells normalised. “It was amazing to observe how the structure of the chromatin moved closer to the healthy pattern during the course of treatment,” says Shivashankar with satisfaction.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Many applications in tumour diagnosis and therapy are conceivable&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;From the point of view of the biologist and his colleagues, the new technique based on blood cell chromatin is applicable not only to the tumours they studied, but also to many different types of cancer. And it may not be limited to the follow-up of proton therapy, but rather applicable as well to many other forms of therapy, including radiation therapy in general, chemotherapy, and surgical operations. Ascertaining whether this is true or not will require further research. As described in a paper in the journal Scientific Reports, Shivashankar’s group and collaborators at PSI’s Centre for Radiopharmaceutical Sciences (CRS) have already tested whether the chromatin biomarkers can be used to detect radiation- and chemo-resistant cells. A lot of work remains to be done before regulatory authorities can approve the use of the new technique in clinical practice – particularly studies with a larger number of participants to ascertain how high the numbers of false positive alarms and false negatives are under clinical conditions. Shivashankar has no doubts about the path to clinical application or the prospect that patients will benefit from the technique: “The method stands,” he says.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Text: Werner Siefer&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;About PSI&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; The Paul Scherrer Institute PSI develops, builds and operates large, complex research facilities and makes them available to the national and international research community. The institute's own key research priorities are in the fields of future technologies, energy and climate, health innovation and fundamentals of nature. PSI is committed to the training of future generations. Therefore about one quarter of our staff are post-docs, post-graduates or apprentices. Altogether PSI employs 2200 people, thus being the largest research institute in Switzerland. The annual budget amounts to approximately CHF 420 million. PSI is part of the ETH Domain, with the other members being the two Swiss Federal Institutes of Technology, ETH Zurich and EPFL Lausanne, as well as Eawag (Swiss Federal Institute of Aquatic Science and Technology), Empa (Swiss Federal Laboratories for Materials Science and Technology) and WSL (Swiss Federal Institute for Forest, Snow and Landscape Research).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3&gt;&lt;b&gt;Original publication&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/h3&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Imaging and AI based chromatin biomarkers for cancer diagnosis and therapy evaluation from liquid biopsies&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt; Kiran Challa, Daniel Paysan, Dominic Leiser, Nadia Sauder, Damien Weber and Shivashankar, G.V. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;i&gt;npj Precision Oncology, &lt;/i&gt;14.12.2023&lt;br /&gt;DOI : 10.1038/s41698-023-00484-8&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Prof. Dr. G.V. Shivashankar Head of the Laboratory for Nanoscale Biology Paul Scherrer Institute, Forschungsstrasse 111, 5232 Villigen PSI, Switzerland Telephone: +41 56 310 42 50, e-mail: gv.shivashankar@psi.ch [English]</contact>
      <link id="268428">
        <title>Images and additional information</title>
        <uri>https://psi.ch/en/node/60742</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="15">
        <name lang="de">Gesundheit</name>
        <name lang="fr">Santé</name>
        <name lang="it">sanità</name>
        <name lang="en">Health</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="19">
        <name lang="de">Medien</name>
        <name lang="fr">Médias</name>
        <name lang="it">Media</name>
        <name lang="en">Media</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
