<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="99517" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2023-12-20</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="506" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>501</department-id>
      <name lang="de">armasuisse</name>
      <name lang="fr">Armasuisse</name>
      <name lang="it">Armasuisse</name>
      <name lang="en">Armasuisse</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.ar.admin.ch/</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.ar.admin.ch/</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.ar.admin.ch/</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.ar.admin.ch/</www>
      <email lang="de">info@armasuisse.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@armasuisse.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@armasuisse.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@armasuisse.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="502" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>501</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Generalsekretariat VBS</name>
      <name lang="fr">Secrétariat général du DDPS</name>
      <name lang="it">Segreteria generale del DDPS</name>
      <name lang="en">General Secretariat DDPS</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.vbs.admin.ch/</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.vbs.admin.ch/</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.vbs.admin.ch/</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.vbs.admin.ch/</www>
      <email lang="de">postmaster.vbs@gs-vbs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">postmaster.vbs@gs-vbs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">postmaster.vbs@gs-vbs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">postmaster.vbs@gs-vbs.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="505" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>501</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Gruppe Verteidigung</name>
      <name lang="fr">Groupement de la Défense</name>
      <name lang="it">Aggruppamento Difesa</name>
      <name lang="en">Defence</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.vtg.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.vtg.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.vtg.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.vtg.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@vtg.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@vtg.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@vtg.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@vtg.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="501">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Verteidigung, Bevölkerungsschutz und Sport</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de la défense, de la protection de la population et des sports</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale della difesa, della protezione della popolazione e dello sport</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Defence, Civil Protection and Sports DDPS</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.vbs.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.vbs.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.vbs.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.vbs.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@gs-vbs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@gs-vbs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@gs-vbs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@gs-vbs.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Projektdauer für das Aufklärungsdrohnensystem (ADS 15) verlängert sich</title>
      <lead>Vor dem Hintergrund der technischen Probleme im Frühjahr 2023 und insbesondere der unsicheren Lage im Nahen Osten hat sich das Bundesamt für Rüstung armasuisse mit der Lieferantin des ADS 15 (Elbit Systems Ltd) auf eine Projektverlängerung um zwei Jahre bis Ende 2026 geeinigt. Als Kompensation muss Elbit der Schweiz ein zusätzliches Supportpaket liefern und die Garantiefrist für die Schweizer Drohnen um zwei Jahre verlängern. Weiter hat Elbit verbindliche Leistungsgarantien abgegeben, die durch umfangreiche Strafzahlungen bei Nichterfüllung abgesichert sind. </lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Aufgrund eines technischen Zwischenfalls im März 2023 musste der Flugbetrieb des ADS 15 in der Schweiz für mehrere Wochen unterbrochen werden. In der Folge hat armasuisse mit der israelischen Lieferantin Elbit Verhandlungen über Kompensationsleistungen für die entstandenen Kosten aufgenommen. Zusätzlich musste Elbit für die Verzögerungen, die durch die technischen Probleme verursacht wurden, Konventionalstrafen bezahlen. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Mit der unsicheren Lage im Nahen Osten hat sich die Ausgangslage ab Oktober 2023 verschlechtert. Seither arbeitet Elbit unter erheblich erschwerten Bedingungen. Zudem ist es derzeit für Schweizer Spezialistinnen und Spezialisten nicht möglich, beispielsweise für Abnahmearbeiten nach Israel zu reisen. Vor diesem Hintergrund wie auch aufgrund der im Frühjahr 2023 entstandenen Verzögerungen hielt es armasuisse für nötig, der Lieferantin mehr Zeit für die Vertragserfüllung einzuräumen. Die Projektverlängerung und entsprechende Gegenleistungen haben armasuisse und Elbit Mitte Dezember 2023 in einem Vertragsnachtrag verbindlich festgehalten.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Umfangreiche Kompensationsleistungen&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Das Projektende ist neu für Ende 2026 anstatt wie bisher für Ende 2024 vorgesehen. Elbit muss der Schweiz die längere Vertragsdauer sowie die im Frühjahr 2023 entstandenen Kosten kompensieren. Die Firma hat sich verpflichtet, armasuisse ein zusätzliches Supportpaket im Wert eines niedrigen zweistelligen Millionenbetrags zu liefern. Dieses umfasst insbesondere zusätzliche Ersatzteile sowie weiteres Material für den Betrieb der Drohnen in der Schweiz. Weiter hat Elbit die Garantiefrist für alle Schweizer Drohnen um zwei Jahre verlängert. Die Frist beginnt ab dem Zeitpunkt der erfolgreichen Vertragserfüllung. Schliesslich muss Elbit umfangreiche Strafzahlungen leisten, falls sie die vereinbarten Leistungen nicht rechtzeitig erbringen kann. Diese Strafzahlungen übersteigen die im bisherigen Projektverlauf veranschlagten und geltend gemachten Konventionalstrafen um ein Vielfaches. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Projektplan wird überarbeitet &lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Aufgrund der unsicheren Lage im Nahen Osten konnte die Lieferung von drei ausstehenden Schweizer Drohnen und dazugehörigen Bodenkontrollstationen nicht wie ursprünglich vorgesehen noch im laufenden Jahr erfolgen. Generell ist es nach wie vor nicht möglich, abschliessende Aussagen über die weiteren Folgen des Konfliktes auf die Beschaffung des ADS 15 zu machen. In dieser Ausgangslage erarbeiten armasuisse und Elbit zurzeit einen detaillierten Projektplan für das nächste Jahr. armasuisse und Elbit haben zudem vereinbart, ab sofort wöchentlich gemeinsame Projektsitzungen abzuhalten. Sollten es die weiteren Entwicklungen notwendig machen, können so allfällige Anpassungen und Massnahmen möglichst frühzeitig eingeleitet werden. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Projekt ADS 15&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;ADS 15 ist ein unbemanntes und unbewaffnetes Aufklärungssystem. Die Drohnen dienen der Lage- und Zielaufklärung, können aber bei Bedarf auch mit anderen Sensoren ausgerüstet werden. Die Drohnen erlauben unter anderem die Überwachung von grossen Räumen und tragen zum Schutz kritischer Infrastrukturen sowie der eigenen Kräfte bei. Die Drohnen sind bei Tag und Nacht einsetzbar. Die Nutzer der Drohnen werden sowohl militärische als auch zivile Stellen wie beispielsweise kantonale Führungsstäbe, Polizei- und Rettungsorgane oder das Bundesamt für Zoll und Grenzschutz (BAZG) sein. Die Schweizer Beschaffung umfasst sechs Drohnen inklusive Bodenkomponenten, Simulator und Logistik.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Jacqueline Stampfli-Bieri Stv. Leiterin Kommunikation armasuisse +41 58 464 60 42</contact>
      <link id="268922">
        <title>Medienmitteilung 4. April 2023: Flugbetrieb des Aufklärungsdrohnensystems (ADS 15) vorsorglich nicht weitergeführt</title>
        <uri>https://www.vbs.admin.ch/de/nsb?id=94106</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="268923">
        <title>Medienmitteilung 23. Mai 2023: Flugbetrieb für das Aufklärungsdrohnensystem (ADS 15) wieder aufgenommen</title>
        <uri>https://www.vbs.admin.ch/de/nsb?id=95326</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Prolongation de la durée du projet pour le système de drones de reconnaissance (ADS 15)</title>
      <lead>Dans le contexte des problèmes techniques survenus au printemps 2023 et en particulier de la situation volatile au Proche-Orient, l’Office fédéral de l’armement armasuisse a convenu avec le fournisseur de l’ADS 15 (Elbit Systems Ltd) de prolonger le projet de deux ans, jusqu’à fin 2026. En compensation, Elbit doit fournir à la Suisse un paquet de support supplémentaire et prolonger de deux ans le délai de garantie pour les drones suisses. En outre, Elbit a fourni des garanties de performance contraignantes, couvertes par d’importantes pénalités en cas de non-respect. </lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;En raison d’un incident technique survenu en mars 2023, l’exploitation de l’ADS 15 en Suisse a dû être interrompue pendant plusieurs semaines. Par la suite, armasuisse a entamé des négociations avec le fournisseur israélien Elbit afin d’obtenir des compensations pour les coûts occasionnés. De plus, Elbit a dû payer des peines conventionnelles pour les retards causés par ces problèmes techniques. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Avec la situation volatile au Proche-Orient, le contexte s’est dégradé à partir d’octobre 2023. Depuis lors, Elbit travaille dans des conditions nettement plus difficiles. De plus, les spécialistes suisses sont actuellement dans l’impossibilité de se rendre en Israël, par exemple pour des travaux de réception. Dans ce contexte, ainsi qu’en raison des retards survenus au printemps 2023, armasuisse a jugé nécessaire d’accorder plus de temps au fournisseur pour l’exécution du contrat. La prolongation du projet et les contreparties correspondantes ont été fixées de manière contraignante entre armasuisse et Elbit à la mi-décembre 2023 dans un avenant au contrat.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Vastes prestations de compensation&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Le projet devrait désormais s’achever fin 2026 au lieu de fin 2024 comme jusqu’à présent. Elbit doit fournir une compensation à la Suisse au titre de la prolongation de la durée du contrat ainsi que pour les coûts occasionnés au printemps 2023. L’entreprise s’est engagée à fournir à armasuisse un paquet de support supplémentaire d’une valeur de plusieurs dizaines de millions de francs. Celui-ci comprend notamment des pièces de rechange ainsi que du matériel supplémentaire pour l’exploitation des drones en Suisse. En outre, Elbit a prolongé de deux ans le délai de garantie pour tous les drones suisses. Ce délai commence à courir à partir de la date de la bonne exécution du contrat. Enfin, Elbit doit s’acquitter d’importantes pénalités si elle n’est pas en mesure de fournir à temps les prestations convenues. Ces pénalités dépassent de plusieurs fois les peines conventionnelles estimées et réclamées jusqu’à présent dans le cadre du projet. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Plan de projet en cours de révision &lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;En raison de la situation volatile au Proche-Orient, la livraison de trois drones suisses en attente et des stations de contrôle au sol correspondantes n’a pas pu être effectuée cette année comme prévu initialement. De manière générale, il n’est toujours pas possible de faire des déclarations définitives sur les conséquences futures du conflit sur l’acquisition de l’ADS 15. Vu cette situation, armasuisse et Elbit élaborent actuellement un plan de projet détaillé pour l’année prochaine. armasuisse et Elbit ont en outre convenu de tenir dès à présent des séances de projet communes hebdomadaires. Si les développements ultérieurs le rendent nécessaire, il sera ainsi possible d’introduire le plus tôt possible des adaptations et mesures éventuelles. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Projet ADS 15&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;L’ADS 15 est un système de reconnaissance non armé et sans équipage. L’ADS 15 assure la capacité d’exploration permettant d’appréhender l’image de la situation et de reconnaître les objectifs, mais il peut aussi, si nécessaire, être équipé d’autres capteurs. Les drones permettent notamment de surveiller de grands espaces et contribuent à la protection des infrastructures critiques ainsi que des propres forces. Les drones peuvent être utilisés de jour comme de nuit. Les utilisateurs des drones seront aussi bien des militaires que des civils, comme les états-majors de conduite cantonaux, les organes de police et de sauvetage ou l’Office fédéral de la douane et de la sécurité des frontières (OFDF). L’acquisition suisse comprend six drones, y compris les composants au sol, le simulateur et la logistique.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Jacqueline Stampfli-Bieri Suppl. chef de la communication d’armasuisse +41 58 464 60 42</contact>
      <link id="268924">
        <title>Communiqué de presse 4 avril 2023 : L’exploitation du système de drones de reconnaissance (ADS 15) est suspendue par mesure de précaution</title>
        <uri>https://www.vbs.admin.ch/fr/nsb?id=94106</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="268925">
        <title>Communiqué de presse 23 mai 2023 : Reprise de l’exploitation du système de drones de reconnaissance (ADS 15)</title>
        <uri>https://www.vbs.admin.ch/fr/nsb?id=95326</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Prorogata la durata del progetto sul sistema di ricognitori telecomandati (ADS 15)</title>
      <lead>In considerazione dei problemi tecnici occorsi nella primavera 2023 e in particolare dell’incertezza della situazione in Medio Oriente, l’Ufficio federale dell’armamento armasuisse si è accordato con il fornitore dell’ADS 15 (Elbit Systems Ltd) in merito a un prolungamento del progetto di due anni fino al termine del 2026. A titolo di compensazione, Elbit dovrà fornire alla Svizzera un pacchetto di supporto supplementare e prorogare di due anni il termine di garanzia relativo ai droni svizzeri. Elbit ha fornito inoltre garanzie vincolanti sulle prestazioni su cui gravano ingenti penali in caso di inadempimento. </lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;A causa di un contrattempo tecnico a marzo 2023, è stato necessario interrompere per diverse settimane le operazioni di volo dell’ADS 15 in Svizzera. In seguito armasuisse ha avviato trattative con il fornitore israeliano Elbit in merito alle prestazioni di compensazione per i costi sostenuti. Elbit ha inoltre dovuto pagare penali per i ritardi causati dai problemi tecnici. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;L’incertezza in Medio Oriente ha prodotto da ottobre 2023 un peggioramento della situazione di partenza. Da allora Elbit lavora in condizioni nettamente più difficoltose. Tra le altre cose, alle specialiste e agli specialisti svizzeri non è per esempio consentito recarsi in Israele per operazioni di collaudo. In questo contesto, anche in considerazione dei ritardi originatisi nella primavera del 2023, armasuisse ha ritenuto necessario concedere al fornitore più tempo per l’esecuzione del contratto. A metà dicembre, armasuisse ed Elbit hanno definito in maniera vincolante la proroga del progetto e le corrispondenti controprestazioni mediante un’aggiunta al contratto.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Ingenti prestazioni di compensazione&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;La conclusione del progetto è ora prevista per la fine del 2026 anziché del 2024 come inizialmente stabilito. Elbit dovrà compensare la Svizzera per la maggiore durata del contratto, così come per i costi sostenuti nella primavera del 2023. La ditta si è impegnata a fornire ad armasuisse un pacchetto di supporto supplementare con un valore nell’ordine di qualche decina di milioni. Quest’ultimo comprenderà in particolare ulteriori pezzi di ricambio, nonché altro materiale d’esercizio per i droni in Svizzera. Elbit ha inoltre prorogato di due anni il termine di garanzia per tutti i droni svizzeri, che inizierà a decorrere dal momento del corretto adempimento del contratto. Infine, Elbit dovrà pagare ingenti penali nel caso in cui non riesca a fornire le prestazioni concordate nei tempi previsti. Tali penali superano notevolmente le penali convenzionali finora preventivate e rivendicate nel corso del progetto. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Revisione del piano di progetto &lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;In considerazione della situazione incerta in Medio Oriente, la fornitura di tre droni svizzeri e delle corrispondenti stazioni di controllo a terra ancora in sospeso non è potuta avvenire già quest’anno come originariamente previsto. In generale, non è ancora possibile pronunciarsi in maniera definitiva sulle ulteriori conseguenze del conflitto per quanto riguarda l’acquisto dell’ADS 15. In questa situazione, armasuisse ed Elbit stanno attualmente elaborando un dettagliato piano di progetto per il prossimo anno e hanno inoltre concordato di svolgere fin d’ora riunioni di progetto a cadenza settimanale. In questo modo, nel caso in cui gli ulteriori sviluppi dovessero renderlo necessario, sarà possibile attuare nel più breve tempo possibile eventuali modifiche e provvedimenti. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Progetto ADS 15&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;L’ADS 15 è un sistema di ricognizione senza equipaggio e non armato. I droni servono alla sorveglianza ottica e alla ricognizione aerea, ma se necessario può essere impiegato anche equipaggiandolo di altri sensori. Tra le altre prestazioni, consentono la sorveglianza di ampie aree e contribuiscono alla protezione delle infrastrutture critiche, così come delle proprie forze. Il sistema può essere utilizzato sia di giorno sia di notte. Gli utenti dei droni saranno gli organi di condotta militari e civili, come gli Stati maggiori cantonali di condotta, gli organi di polizia e di salvataggio o l’Ufficio federale della dogana e della sicurezza dei confini (UDSC). L’acquisto da parte svizzera comprende sei droni, compresi i componenti al suolo, il simulatore e la logistica.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Jacqueline Stampfli-Bieri Sost. Capo Comunicazione armasuisse +41 58 464 60 42</contact>
      <link id="268926">
        <title>Comunicato stampa 4 aprile 2023: Operazioni di volo del sistema di ricognitori telecomandati (ADS 15) preventivamente interrotte</title>
        <uri>https://www.vbs.admin.ch/it/nsb?id=94106</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="268927">
        <title>Comunicato stampa 23 maggio 2023: Riprese le operazioni di volo del sistema di ricognitori telecomandati (ADS 15)</title>
        <uri>https://www.vbs.admin.ch/it/nsb?id=95326</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Project duration for the reconnaissance drone system (ADS 15) to be extended</title>
      <lead>In view of the technical problems in early 2023 and in particular the volatile situation in the Middle East, the Federal Office for Defence Procurement armasuisse has agreed with the supplier of the ADS 15 (Elbit Systems Ltd) on an extension of the project by two years up to the end of 2026. As compensation, Elbit has to deliver an additional support package to Switzerland and extend the warranty period for the Swiss drones by two years. Moreover, Elbit has provided binding performance guarantees which are secured by extensive financial penalties in the event of non-fulfilment. </lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Due to a technical incident in March 2023, the flight operation of the ADS 15 in Switzerland had to be interrupted for several weeks. As a result, armasuisse commenced negotiations with the Israeli supplier Elbit about the compensation payments for the costs which had been incurred. In addition, Elbit had to pay contractual penalties for the delays which were caused by the technical problems. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;With the volatile situation in the Middle East, the status quo worsened from October 2023. Since then, Elbit has been working under considerably more difficult conditions. In addition, it is currently not possible for Swiss specialists to travel to Israel, for example, for acceptance work. In view of this as well as due to the delays which arose in early 2023, armasuisse considered it necessary to grant the supplier more time for the contractual performance. armasuisse and Elbit set out the project extension and corresponding compensatory measures bindingly in a contract addendum in mid-December 2023.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Extensive compensation payments&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;The end of the project is now scheduled for the end of 2026 instead of for the end of 2024, as previously. Elbit has to compensate Switzerland for the longer duration of the contract as well as for the costs which were incurred in early 2023. The company has committed to deliver armasuisse an additional support package valued in the low double-digit millions. In particular, this will cover additional spare parts as well as other material for operating the drones in Switzerland. Elbit has also extended the warranty period for all Swiss drones by two years. The term will commence from the time of successful fulfilment of the contract. Finally, Elbit will have to pay extensive penalties if it cannot provide the agreed services in time. These penalties will exceed the contractual penalties estimated and asserted during the course of the project to date many times over. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Project plan will be revised &lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Due to the volatile situation in the Middle East, delivery of the three outstanding Swiss drones and the accompanying ground control stations could not take place in the current year as originally scheduled. In general, it is still not possible to make any conclusive statements regarding the further consequences of the conflict on the procurement of the ADS 15. From this initial situation, armasuisse and Elbit are currently developing a detailed project plan for the following year. armasuisse and Elbit have also agreed to hold joint weekly project meetings with immediate effect. Should further developments make it necessary, any adjustments and measures can be initiated as early as possible. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Project ADS 15&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;ADS 15 is an unmanned and unarmed reconnaissance system. The drones are used for situation and target intelligence, but can also be equipped with different sensors if necessary. Among other things, the drones enable large areas to be monitored and contribute to protecting critical infrastructures as well as own forces. The drones can be deployed during the daytime or at night. The users of the system are military and civilian authorities such as Cantonal Management Staff, police and rescue agencies and the Federal Office for Customs and Border Security (FOCBS). The Swiss procurement comprises six drones including ground components, simulator and logistics.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Jacqueline Stampfli-Bieri Deputy Head of Communications armasuisse +41 58 464 60 42</contact>
      <link id="268928">
        <title>Press release 4 April 2023: Flight operation of reconnaissance drone system (ADS 15) not resumed as a precautionary measure (in German)</title>
        <uri>https://www.vbs.admin.ch/de/nsb?id=94106</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="268929">
        <title>Press release 23 May 2023: Flight operation for the reconnaissance drone system (ADS 15) resumed</title>
        <uri>https://www.vbs.admin.ch/en/nsb?id=95326</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <keywords>
      <keyword id="5180" org-id="505">
        <name lang="de">Armee</name>
        <name lang="fr">Armée</name>
        <name lang="it">Esercito</name>
        <name lang="en">armed forces</name>
      </keyword>
    </keywords>
    <topics>
      <topic id="3">
        <name lang="de">Armee</name>
        <name lang="fr">Armée</name>
        <name lang="it">Esercito</name>
        <name lang="en">Armed Forces</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="40">
        <name lang="de">Sicherheit</name>
        <name lang="fr">Sécurité</name>
        <name lang="it">Sicurezza</name>
        <name lang="en">Security</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
