<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="16314" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2007-12-18</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="322" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>301</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Staatssekretariat für Bildung und Forschung (SBF) - ab 1.1.2013 SBFI</name>
      <name lang="fr">Secrétariat d'Etat à l'éducation et à la recherche (SER) - dès le 1.1.2013 SEFRI</name>
      <name lang="it">Segreteria di Stato per l'educazione e la ricerca (SER) - a partire dal 1.1.2013 SEFRI</name>
      <name lang="en">State Secretariat for Education and Research (SER) - as of 1.1.2013 SERI</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.sbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.sbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.sbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.sbf.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@sbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@sbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@sbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@sbf.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="301">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement des Innern</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'intérieur</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'interno</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Home Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Besuch von Staatssekretär Charles Kleiber in Russland</title>
      <lead>Eine hochrangige Schweizer Delegation unter der Leitung des Staatssekretärs für Bildung und Forschung, Charles Kleiber, weilt vom 20. bis 21. Dezember 2007 in Moskau. Zweck der Reise sind Diskussionen über die Implementierung der Strategie zur bilateralen Zusammenarbeit zwischen der Schweiz und Russland in den Bereichen Wissenschaft und Technologie. Im Rahmen der Bundespolitik zur Förderung von Bildung, Forschung und Innovation in den Jahren 2008 – 2011 zählt Russland neben China, Indien, Japan, Südafrika, Südkorea, Brasilien und Chile zu den ausgewählten Schwerpunktländern.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Staatssekretär Charles Kleiber wird bei seinem Russlandbesuch namentlich begleitet von Ursula Renold, Direktorin des Bundesamtes für Berufsbildung und Technologie BBT, Prof. Patrick Aebischer, Präsident der ETH Lausanne, Prof. Jean Dominique Vassalli, Rektor der Universität Genf, Pius Knüsel, Direktor der Schweizer Kulturstiftung Pro Helvetia, sowie von Vertretern des Schweizerischen Nationalfonds zur Förderung der wissenschaftlichen Forschung und der Kommission für Technologie und Innovation.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Der Besuch markiert eine wichtige Etappe auf dem Weg zu offiziellen Beziehungen zwischen Russland und der Schweiz in den Bereichen Wissenschaft und Technologie. Anlässlich des Treffens von Staatssekretär Kleiber mit dem russischen Minister für Bildung und Wissenschaft, Andrey Fursenko, in Moskau sollen die nächsten Schritte zur Implementierung der Strategie der bilateralen Zusammenarbeit erörtert werden. Auf der Schweizer Seite sollen dabei die Universität Genf und die ETH Lausanne eine wichtige Rolle spielen. Sie werden die künftigen Bestrebungen von Schweizer Universitäten, Fachhochschulen und Forschungsinstitutionen zur Zusammenarbeit mit russischen Partnern koordinieren. Dabei sind die interessierten Kreise eingeladen, die konkreten Forschungsschwerpunkte gemeinsam mit ihren russischen Partnern selber zu definieren&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Ein weiteres Thema der Gespräche wird das schweizerische Berufsbildungssystem sein, für das die russische Seite grosses Interesse bekundet hat und zu dem ein Workshop unter der Leitung der BBT-Direktorin Ursula Renold stattfinden wird. Der Schweizerische Nationalfonds schliesslich wird die Reise zu vertieften Gesprächen mit seinem russischen Pendant, der Russischen Stiftung für Grundlagenforschung RFBR nutzen.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Die Schweizer Delegation wird ausserdem Gelegenheit haben, wertvolle Kontakte mit Verantwortlichen von verschiedenen Forschungseinrichtungen in Moskau zu knüpfen.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Staatssekretariat für Bildung und Forschung Pierre Berlincourt Ressort Bilaterale Forschungszusammenarbeit Tel. 031 322 86 17</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Visite du secrétaire d’Etat Charles Kleiber en Russie</title>
      <lead>Une délégation suisse de haut niveau dirigée par le secrétaire d’Etat à l’éducation et à la recherche Charles Kleiber se rendra les 20 et 21 décembre 2007 à Moscou pour des entretiens sur la mise en œuvre de la stratégie de coopération scientifique et technologique bilatérale entre les deux pays. La Russie fait partie – avec la Chine, l’Inde, le Japon, l’Afrique du Sud, la Corée du Sud, le Brésil et le Chili – des pays prioritaires retenus par la Suisse pour renforcer les partenariats bilatéraux dans le contexte de la politique fédérale d’encouragement de la formation, de la recherche et de l’innovation pour les années 2008 à 2011.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Dans son déplacement en Russie, le secrétaire d'Etat Charles Kleiber sera notamment accompagné par Ursula Renold, directrice de l'Office fédéral de la formation professionnelle et de la technologie (OFFT), Patrick Aebischer, président de l'EPFL, Jean Dominique Vassalli, recteur de l'Université de Genève, Pius Knüsel, directeur de la Fondation suisse pour la culture Pro Helvetia, et des représentants du Fonds national suisse (FNS) et de la Commission pour la technologie et l'innovation (CTI).&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Cette visite marque une étape importante dans le développement des relations officielles entre la Suisse et la Russie dans le domaine de la science et de la technologie. Les entretiens du secrétaire d'Etat Charles Kleiber avec le ministre russe de l'éducation et de la science Andreï Fursenko serviront à déterminer les prochains pas dans la mise en œuvre de la stratégie de coopération bilatérale. L'Université de Genève et l'EPFL joueront le rôle de chefs de file du côté suisse. Elles sont appelées à coordonner les activités de coopération que les hautes écoles et institutions de recherche suisses entendent mener avec les partenaires russes. Les acteurs de la coopération définiront eux-mêmes les priorités thématiques.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;La formation professionnelle sera également à l'ordre du jour. Les interlocuteurs russes ont signalé leur grand intérêt pour le système suisse de la formation professionnelle, et un atelier sera dirigé sur ce sujet par la directrice de l'OFFT Ursula Renold. Pour sa part, le Fonds national suisse profitera de ce voyage pour mener des entretiens approfondis avec son pendant russe, la Fondation russe pour la recherche fondamentale RFBR. Enfin, la délégation suisse rencontrera les responsables de diverses institutions de recherche à Moscou.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Secrétariat d’Etat à l’éducation et à la recherche Pierre Berlincourt, Conseiller scientifique Coopération bilatérale de recherche tél. 031 322 86 17</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Visita del segretario di Stato Charles Kleiber in Russia</title>
      <lead>Una delegazione svizzera d’alto rango diretta dal segretario di Stato Charles Kleiber si recherà in visita a Mosca dal 20 al 21 dicembre 2007. Al centro delle discussioni vi sarà l’attuazione della strategia per la cooperazione bilaterale tra Svizzera e Russia in campo scientifico e tecnologico. Nell’ambito della politica federale per il promovimento dell’educazione, dell’innovazione e della ricerca negli anni 2008-2011 la Russia figura con Cina, India, Giappone, Africa del Sud, Corea del Sud, Brasile e Cile tra i Paesi prioritari.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Il segretario di Stato Charles Kleiber sarà accompagnato da Ursula Renold, direttrice dell'Ufficio federale della formazione professionale e della tecnologia (UFFT), da Patrick Aebischer, presidente del Politecnico di Losanna, da Jean Dominique Vassalli, rettore dell'Università di Ginevra, da Pius Knüsel, direttore della Fondazione svizzera per la cultura Pro Helvetia e da rappresentanti del Fondo nazionale svizzero (FNS) e della Commissione della tecnologia e dell'innovazione (CTI).&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;La visita segna un passo importante nello sviluppo delle relazioni ufficiali tra la Svizzera e la Russia in campo scientifico e tecnologico. Gli incontri del segretario di Stato Charles Kleiber con il ministro russo dell'educazione e della scienza Andrey Fursenko serviranno a fissare le prossime tappe per l'attuazione della strategia di cooperazione bilaterale. Da parte svizzera un ruolo di primo piano sarà svolto dall'Università di Ginevra e dal Politecnico federale di Losanna. Questi due istituti sono chiamati a coordinare le attività di cooperazione che le università e le istituzioni di ricerca svizzere intendono condurre con i partner russi. Spetta agli attori coinvolti definire concretamente con i loro partner russi le priorità tematiche.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Altro tema all'ordine del giorno sarà la formazione professionale. Le autorità russe si sono dette molto interessate a conoscere il funzionamento del sistema svizzero di formazione professionale. A tal proposito è previsto un workshop tenuto dalla direttrice dell'UFFT Ursula Renold. Infine, i responsabili del FNS coglieranno l'occasione per condurre un'approfondita discussione con i loro omologhi russi della Fondazione per la ricerca fondamentale (RFBR).&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;La delegazione svizzera avrà inoltre modo di incontrare a Mosca i responsabili di diverse istituzioni di ricerca.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Segreteria di Stato per l’educazione e la ricerca Pierre Berlincourt, consigliere scientifico Cooperazione bilaterale nella ricerca tel. 031 322 86 17</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>State Secretary Charles Kleiber to visit Russia</title>
      <lead>A high-level Swiss delegation headed by the State Secretary for Education and Research, Charles Kleiber, is visiting Moscow from 20 to 21 December 2007. The purpose of the visit is to hold discussions on the implementation of the strategy on bilateral cooperation between Switzerland and Russia in the areas of science and technology. Along with China, India, Japan, South Africa, South Korea, Brazil and Chile, Russia is one of the priority countries selected by Switzerland as part of its federal policy on the promotion of education, research and innovation for the period from 2008 – 2011.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;During his Russian visit, State Secretary Charles Kleiber will be accompanied by Ursula Renold, director of the Federal Office for Professional Education and Technology OPET, Prof. Patrick Aebischer, president of the EPF Lausanne, Prof. Jean Dominique Vassalli, rector of the University of Geneva, Pius Knüsel, director of the Swiss arts foundation Pro Helvetia, and representatives of the Swiss National Science Foundation and the Innovation Promotion Agency CTI.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The visit marks an important step on the path to official relations between Russia and Switzerland in the areas of science and technology. The meeting in Moscow between State Secretary Kleiber and the Russian minister for education and science, Andrey Fursenko, will help to determine the next steps for the implementation of the strategy of bilateral cooperation. On the Swiss side, the University of Geneva and the EPF Lausanne will play a defining role, coordinating the future efforts of Swiss universities and research institutes to cooperate with Russian partners. They will be called on to define specific research activities together with their Russian partners.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;A further topic for discussion will be vocational education and training. As the Russian side has expressed great interest in the Swiss system of vocational education and training, a workshop on this subject will be held by OPET director Ursula Renold. Finally, the Swiss National Science Foundation will use the visit to conduct more in-depth talks with its Russian counterpart, the Russian Foundation for Basic Research RFBR.At the same time the Swiss delegation will have the opportunity to do some valuable networking with the heads of the various research institutes in Moscow.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>State Secretariat for Education and Research SER Pierre Berlincourt Scientific adviser, Bilateral Research Cooperation Unit Tel. 031 322 86 17 Hallwylstrasse 4 3003 Berne</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <keywords>
      <keyword id="325.1" org-id="322">
        <name lang="de">Universitäten</name>
        <name lang="fr">Universités</name>
        <name lang="it">Università</name>
        <name lang="en">Universities</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="325.8" org-id="322">
        <name lang="de">Technologie</name>
        <name lang="fr">Technologie</name>
        <name lang="it">Tecnologia</name>
        <name lang="en">Technology</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="325.10" org-id="322">
        <name lang="de">Wissenschaft</name>
        <name lang="fr">Science</name>
        <name lang="it">Scienza</name>
        <name lang="en">Science</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="325.11" org-id="322">
        <name lang="de">Eidgenössische Technische Hochschule ETH</name>
        <name lang="fr">Ecole polytechnique fédérale EPF</name>
        <name lang="it">Politecnico federale</name>
        <name lang="en">Federal Institutes of Technology</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="325.15" org-id="322">
        <name lang="de">Schweizerischer Nationalfonds</name>
        <name lang="fr">Fonds national suisse</name>
        <name lang="it">Fondo nazionale Svizzero</name>
        <name lang="en">Swiss National Science Foundation</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="325.20" org-id="322">
        <name lang="de">Forschungsförderung</name>
        <name lang="fr">Encouragement de la recherche</name>
        <name lang="it">Promozione della ricerca</name>
        <name lang="en">Research promotion</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="325.21" org-id="322">
        <name lang="de">Wissenschaftsaussenpolitik</name>
        <name lang="fr">Politique scientifique extérieure</name>
        <name lang="it">Politica scientifica dell'esterno</name>
        <name lang="en">Foreign scientific policy</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="325.27" org-id="322">
        <name lang="de">Institution</name>
        <name lang="fr">Institution</name>
        <name lang="it">Istituzione</name>
        <name lang="en">Institution</name>
      </keyword>
    </keywords>
    <topics>
      <topic id="8">
        <name lang="de">Bildung und Forschung</name>
        <name lang="fr">Formation et recherche</name>
        <name lang="it">Formazione e ricerca</name>
        <name lang="en">Education and Research</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="45">
        <name lang="de">Technologie</name>
        <name lang="fr">Technologie</name>
        <name lang="it">Tecnologia</name>
        <name lang="en">Technology</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
