<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="77223" revoked="no">
    <version>7</version>
    <pubdate>2019-11-26</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="201" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>201</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="810" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>801</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Bundesamt für Kommunikation</name>
      <name lang="fr">Office fédéral de la communication</name>
      <name lang="it">Ufficio federale delle comunicazioni</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Office of Communications</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.bakom.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.ofcom.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.ufcom.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.ofcom.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">media@bakom.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">media@bakom.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">media@bakom.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">media@bakom.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="201">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <department id="801">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Umwelt, Verkehr, Energie und Kommunikation</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'environnement, des transports, de l'énergie et de la communication</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'ambiente, dei trasporti, dell'energia e delle comunicazioni</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of the Environment, Transport, Energy and Communications</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.uvek.admin.ch/uvek/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.uvek.admin.ch/uvek/fr/home.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.uvek.admin.ch/uvek/it/home.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.uvek.admin.ch/uvek/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-uvek.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-uvek.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-uvek.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-uvek.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Internet Governance Forum: Bundesrat Cassis plädiert für Einbezug aller Akteure in Diskussion über den Umgang mit digitalen Technologien</title>
      <lead>Am diesjährigen Internet Governance Forum (IGF) in Berlin setzt sich die Schweiz für sinnvolle Regeln der digitalen Gouvernanz ein. Das betrifft wirtschaftliche Fragen sowie Fragen der Sicherheit und Menschenrechte. Bundesrat Ignazio Cassis plädierte dabei für einen «Schweizer Ansatz», bei dem alle Akteure und Interessengruppen gemeinsam die Fragen angehen, die sich durch digitale Technologien ergeben. Genf biete bereits heute beste Voraussetzungen für einen solchen Multistakeholder-Ansatz, der Brücken zwischen allen Entscheidungsträgern bildet.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Die Digitalisierung durchdringt alle Aspekte des Lebens und bietet grosse Vorteile und Möglichkeiten. Gleichzeitig bringt sie neue Herausforderungen mit sich. Die Privatsphäre schwindet, Menschen werden im Arbeitsleben abgehängt und künstliche Intelligenz droht die menschliche zu dominieren. Digitale Technologien sind zum Spielball der Geopolitik geworden, und Befürchtungen über Beeinflussung, Wahlmanipulation und Spionage machen sich breit. Einige Staaten setzen dem Internet zudem immer engere Grenzen und nutzen digitale Technologien für die Überwachung der Bevölkerung. Dies und die Tatsache, dass der Einfluss einzelner Unternehmen immer grösser wird, bedroht die Vision eines offenen, freien und sicheren digitalen Raums (Cyberspace), für den sich die Schweiz einsetzt.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;«Wir müssen die digitalen Technologien Menschen-zentriert gestalten und Vertrauen aufbauen», sagte Bundesrat Cassis am IGF. Dazu müsse die internationale Zusammenarbeit und das politische Engagement intensiviert werden. Um einen offenen, freien und sicheren Cyberraum zu erhalten, müsse die internationale Gouvernanz, also Regeln, die durch das koordinierte Vorgehen der internationalen Gemeinschaft festgelegt werden, in diesem Bereich verstärkt werden. «Der aktuelle institutionelle Rahmen genügt nicht mehr», sagte Bundesrat Cassis.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Der Vorsteher des EDA lobte das IGF als Plattform, an der neue Themen identifiziert und Lösungsansätzen diskutiert werden. Allerdings müssten weitere Akteure in den Austausch einbezogen werden, die interdisziplinär zusammenarbeiten. «Alle Betroffenen und Interessengruppen müssen gemeinsam an Lösungen arbeiten, denn wir müssen es auch schaffen, unsere Diskussionen in politische Entscheide und konkrete wirtschaftliche und soziale Resultate zu transformieren», sagte er, der dieses Vorgehen als «typischen Schweizer Ansatz» bezeichnete.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Als Beispiel für einen solchen Multistakeholder-Ansatz nannte Bundesrat Cassis den «Geneva Dialogue on Responsible Behaviour in Cyberspace». Im Rahmen dieses Dialogs, den das EDA im letzten November lanciert hat, sollen Unternehmen aus allen Weltregionen miteinander ins Gespräch kommen, um Verhaltensnormen zu entwickeln. Genf spiele heute schon eine wichtige Rolle in der globalen Digitalpolitik, sagte Bundesrat Cassis weiter. Der Bundesrat wolle diese Rolle weiter ausbauen und Genf zu einem führenden Standort der globalen Digitalisierungs- und Technologiedebatten machen.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Der Vorsteher des EDA unterstrich, dass die digitale Diplomatie einen wichtigen Stellenwert in der neuen aussenpolitischen Strategie der Schweiz habe und auch ein zentraler Aspekt der «Aussenpolitischen Vision 2028» sei. Die Schweiz baue hier auf die anerkannte Expertise in der Friedensförderung. «Wir möchten unsere Guten Dienste vermehrt auch in der «online» Welt einbringen», sagte er. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Digitale Strategie Schweiz&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Die Schweiz hat die Entwicklung des IGF als Dialogforum für alle Aspekte der Digitalisierung seit dessen Gründung im Jahr 2006 massgeblich mitgestaltet. Auch im Inland werden die Entwicklungen der Digitalisierung eng verfolgt. Strategische Leitlinien für den Umgang mit der Digitalisierung gibt es seit 1998. Seit 2016 gibt die Strategie «Digitale Schweiz» die Leitlinien für das staatliche Handeln im Bereich Digitalisierung vor mit dem Ziel, die chancengleiche Teilhabe aller zu ermöglichen und Solidarität zu stärken, Sicherheit, Vertrauen und Transparenz zu gewährleisten, die digitale Befähigung der Menschen weiter zu stärken und die Wertschöpfung, das Wachstum und den Wohlstand sicherstellen.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Die Strategie wird dezentral umgesetzt, und von einer Interdepartementalen Koordinationsgruppe unter Vorsitz des Bundesamts für Kommunikation (BAKOM) gesteuert. Dessen Direktor Philipp Metzger hat gestern die Schweiz im Rahmen des IGF an einem Digitalministertreffen vertreten.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Kommunikation EDA Bundeshaus West CH-3003 Bern Tel. Kommunikationsservice: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Medienstelle: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <link id="195829">
        <title>Digitale Schweiz</title>
        <uri>https://www.bakom.admin.ch/bakom/de/home/digital-und-internet/strategie-digitale-schweiz.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions>
        <revision date="2019-11-28 12:59" type="R"/>
        <revision date="2019-11-28 10:32" type="R"/>
        <revision date="2019-11-26 19:05" type="R"/>
        <revision date="2019-11-28 13:42" type="R"/>
      </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Forum sur la gouvernance de l’Internet: le conseiller fédéral Ignazio Cassis plaide pour l’implication de tous les acteurs dans le débat sur l’utilisation des technologies numériques</title>
      <lead>À l’occasion de l’édition 2019 du Forum sur la gouvernance de l’Internet (FGI) organisé à Berlin, la Suisse se mobilise en faveur de l’adoption de règles pertinentes en matière de gouvernance numérique, notamment sur des thèmes économiques, mais également sur des questions liées à la sécurité et aux droits de l’homme. Le conseiller fédéral Ignazio Cassis prône une «approche suisse» réunissant tous les acteurs et groupes d’intérêt pour traiter ensemble les questions liées aux technologies numériques. Cette approche multipartite, qui vise à jeter des ponts entre tous les décideurs, est déjà profondément ancrée à Genève.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Le numérique s’immisce dans toutes les sphères de la vie et présente des avantages et des opportunités considérables. Mais il est également synonyme de nouveaux défis. La sphère privée est de moins en moins privée, au travail les gens sont incapables de suivre le rythme des changements technologiques et l’intelligence artificielle menace de dépasser l’intelligence humaine. Les technologies numériques sont devenues le jouet de la géopolitique et les craintes face aux tentatives d’influence, de manipulation électorale et d’espionnage se généralisent. Certains pays restreignent de plus en plus l’accès à Internet et utilisent les technologies numériques pour surveiller leur population. Une influence croissante est en outre exercée par certaines entreprises. Tout cela menace la vision d’un cyberespace ouvert, libre et sûr, pour lequel la Suisse s’engage.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;«Nous devons façonner les technologies numériques dans l’intérêt des populations et restaurer la confiance», a déclaré le conseiller fédéral Ignazio Cassis lors du FGI. Pour ce faire, il est impératif de renforcer la coopération internationale et l’engagement politique. Pour favoriser un cyberespace ouvert, libre et sûr, il faut, dans ce domaine, améliorer la gouvernance mondiale, c’est-à-dire les règles produites par l'action coordonnée de la communauté internationale. «Le cadre institutionnel actuel ne suffit plus», a indiqué M. Cassis.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Le chef du DFAE a fait l’éloge du FGI, une plateforme permettant d’identifier de nouveaux thèmes et de discuter de solutions possibles. Il estime toutefois que d’autres acteurs doivent être impliqués dans le débat et que ces derniers doivent s’engager dans une collaboration interdisciplinaire. «Tous les acteurs et groupes d’intérêt concernés doivent se concerter pour trouver ensemble des solutions, car nous devons aussi parvenir à transformer nos discussions en décisions politiques et en résultats économiques et sociaux concrets», a expliqué le conseiller fédéral Ignazio Cassis pour défendre ce qu’il appelle une approche typiquement suisse.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Cette approche multipartite se traduit, à titre d’exemple, par le dialogue de Genève sur le comportement responsable dans le cyberespace (Geneva Dialogue on Responsible Behaviour in Cyberspace). Lancé par le DFAE en novembre dernier, ce dialogue vise à réunir des entreprises de toutes les régions du monde pour qu’ensemble, elles élaborent des normes de comportement. «Genève joue déjà actuellement un rôle important dans la politique numérique mondiale», a déclaré M. Cassis. Le Conseil fédéral entend consolider ce rôle et faire de Genève l’épicentre des discussions mondiales sur le numérique et les technologies.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Le chef du DFAE a affirmé que la diplomatie numérique occupait une place importante dans la nouvelle stratégie de politique étrangère de la Suisse et constituait un aspect essentiel de la «Vision de la politique étrangère de la Suisse à l’horizon 2028». La Suisse s’appuie à cet égard sur une expertise reconnue dans le domaine de la promotion de la paix. «Nous souhaitons également proposer nos bons offices dans le monde «en ligne», a indiqué M. Cassis. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Stratégie «Suisse numérique»&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;La Suisse a grandement contribué à ce que le FGI, créé en 2006, devienne au fil du temps un forum de dialogue consacré à tous les aspects du numérique. Sur le plan national également, les évolutions du numérique font également l’objet d’une attention particulière. La Suisse a fixé des orientations stratégiques en la matière dès 1998. Adoptée en 2016, la stratégie «Suisse numérique» définit les lignes directrices régissant l’action de l’État dans le domaine du numérique. Ses objectifs sont d’établir l’égalité des chances et de renforcer la solidarité, de garantir la sécurité, la confiance et la transparence, de renforcer les compétences numériques, et d’assurer la création de valeur, la croissance et la prospérité.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Appliquée de manière décentralisée, cette stratégie est pilotée par un groupe de coordination interdépartemental placé sous la direction de l’Office fédéral de la communication (OFCOM). Le directeur de l’OFCOM Philipp Metzger a représenté la Suisse lors d’une réunion des ministres du numérique organisée en marge du FGI.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Communication DFAE Palais fédéral ouest CH-3003 Berne Tél. Service de communication: +41 58 462 31 53 Tél. Service de presse: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <link id="195830">
        <title>Suisse numérique</title>
        <uri>https://www.bakom.admin.ch/bakom/fr/page-daccueil/suisse-numerique-et-internet/strategie-suisse-numerique.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions>
        <revision date="2019-11-28 12:59" type="R"/>
        <revision date="2019-11-27 12:29" type="R"/>
        <revision date="2019-11-26 19:05" type="R"/>
      </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Internet Governance Forum: il consigliere federale Cassis chiede il coinvolgimento di tutti gli attori nel dibattito sull’uso delle tecnologie digitali</title>
      <lead>Nel quadro dell’Internet Governance Forum (IGF) di quest’anno, a Berlino, la Svizzera si batte a favore di regole ragionevoli in materia di governance digitale su questioni economiche, di sicurezza e inerenti ai diritti umani. Il capo del Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri (DFAE) ha auspicato un «approccio svizzero» attraverso il quale tutti gli attori e i gruppi di interesse affrontino insieme le questioni legate alle tecnologie digitali. Ginevra offre già oggi i presupposti migliori per attuare un simile approccio multistakeholder –pluripartitico- in grado di creare ponti tra tutti i responsabili delle decisioni.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;La digitalizzazione concerne tutti gli aspetti della vita e offre grandi vantaggi e opportunità. Allo stesso tempo, però, porta con sé nuove sfide. La sfera privata viene meno, ci sono persone che perdono piede nella vita lavorativa e l’intelligenza artificiale minaccia di dominare quella umana. Le tecnologie digitali sono diventate uno strumento di geopolitica, non senza timore che possano essere utilizzate per influenzare l’opinione pubblica, manipolare le elezioni e spiare i cittadini e le cittadine. Alcuni Paesi fissano inoltre limiti sempre più rigorosi in Internet e utilizzano le tecnologie digitali per monitorare la popolazione. Questo, e il fatto che l’influenza di singole aziende sta aumentando, minaccia la visione di uno spazio digitale (cyberspazio) aperto, libero e sicuro, che la Svizzera si è impegnata a realizzare.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;«Dobbiamo far sì che le tecnologie digitali siano incentrate sulle persone e dobbiamo costruire la fiducia», ha detto il consigliere federale Cassis all’IGF. A tal fine, occorre intensificare la cooperazione internazionale e l’impegno politico. Per favorire un cyberspazio aperto, libero e sicuro, si deve rafforzare la governance internazionale, ossia le regole prodotte dall’azione coordinata della comunità internazionale. «L’attuale quadro istituzionale non è più sufficiente», ha dichiarato Ignazio Cassis.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Il capo del DFAE ha elogiato l’IGF come piattaforma per individuare nuovi temi e discutere di possibili soluzioni. Sarebbe tuttavia necessario coinvolgere nello scambio altri attori che collaborano in modo interdisciplinare. «Tutti gli attori coinvolti e i gruppi d’interesse devono lavorare insieme per trovare soluzioni: dobbiamo riuscire a trasformare i nostri dibattiti in decisioni politiche e risultati economici e sociali concreti», ha puntualizzato, definendo questo modus operandi «un tipico approccio svizzero».&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Come esempio di tale approccio multistakeholder, il consigliere federale ha citato il «Geneva Dialogue on Responsible Behaviour in Cyberspace». Nel quadro di questo dialogo, lanciato dal DFAE lo scorso novembre, le imprese di tutte le regioni del mondo dovranno interagire per sviluppare codici di condotta. Ginevra svolge già oggi un ruolo importante nella politica digitale globale, ha continuato il consigliere federale Cassis. Il Governo svizzero intende ampliare ulteriormente questo ruolo e fare di Ginevra un polo dei dibattiti globali sulla digitalizzazione e la tecnologia.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Il capo del DFAE ha sottolineato che la diplomazia digitale è una componente importante della nuova strategia di politica estera della Svizzera e un aspetto centrale della Visione per la politica estera della Svizzera nel 2028. La Svizzera si affida alla sua solida esperienza nei processi di promozione della pace. «Vogliamo portare sempre più i nostri buoni uffici anche online» ha affermato il consigliere federale. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Strategia «Svizzera digitale»&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;La Svizzera ha dato un contributo determinante allo sviluppo dell’IGF come forum di dialogo per tutti gli aspetti della digitalizzazione sin dalla sua fondazione nel 2006. Anche in Svizzera si seguono da vicino gli sviluppi della digitalizzazione. Dal 1998, sono in vigore direttive strategiche su come gestire la digitalizzazione e nel 2016 è stata adottata la strategia «Svizzera digitale», che definisce le linee guida dell’azione governativa nel settore della digitalizzazione, con l’obiettivo di garantire pari opportunità per tutti e rafforzare la solidarietà, garantire sicurezza, fiducia e trasparenza, potenziare l’alfabetizzazione digitale e assicurare il valore aggiunto della digitalizzazione, la crescita e il benessere.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;La Strategia sarà attuata in maniera decentrata e gestita da un gruppo di coordinamento interdipartimentale presieduto dall’Ufficio federale delle comunicazioni (UFCOM), il cui direttore Philipp Metzger ha rappresentato ieri la Svizzera in un incontro dei ministri del digitale nell’ambito dell’IGF.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Comunicazione DFAE Palazzo federale ovest CH-3003 Berna Tel. Servizio di comunicazione: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Servizio stampa: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <link id="195831">
        <title>Svizzera digitale</title>
        <uri>https://www.bakom.admin.ch/bakom/it/pagina-iniziale/digitale-e-internet/strategia-svizzera-digitale.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions>
        <revision date="2019-11-28 12:59" type="R"/>
        <revision date="2019-11-27 10:39" type="R"/>
        <revision date="2019-11-26 19:05" type="R"/>
      </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Internet Governance Forum: Federal Councillor Ignazio Cassis calls for all stakeholders to be included in debate on use of digital technologies</title>
      <lead>At this year's Internet Governance Forum (IGF) in Berlin, Switzerland is advocating judicious rules on digital governance, covering economic issues as well as security and human rights. Federal Councillor and Head of the Federal Department of Foreign Affairs (FDFA) Ignazio Cassis has called for a "Swiss approach" in which all actors and stakeholders join forces to address the issues raised by digital technologies. He said that Geneva already provided the perfect conditions for such a multi-stakeholder approach, which would bring together all relevant decision-makers.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Digitalisation is permeating all aspects of life, bringing with it great benefits and opportunities but also new challenges. Privacy is dwindling, people face being left behind at work, and artificial intelligence threatens to outstrip human intelligence. Digital technologies have become a geopolitical football, while fears of interference, electoral manipulation and espionage are spreading. Meanwhile, some governments are placing ever-tighter restrictions on the internet and using digital technologies to monitor their populations. These factors, combined with the growing influence of individual corporations, threaten the vision of an open, free and secure cyberspace to which Switzerland is committed.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"We have to make digital technologies people-centred and build trust," Mr Cassis told the IGF, adding that this required greater international cooperation and political commitment. To maintain an open, free and secure cyberspace, stronger international governance – i.e. common rules produced by the coordinated action of the international community – was needed in this area. "The current institutional framework is no longer adequate," he said.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mr Cassis praised the IGF for providing a platform to identify new issues and discuss potential solutions. However, other actors needed to be involved in the debate and to work together in an interdisciplinary way, he said. "All stakeholders and interested parties must work on solutions jointly, because we also need to be able to transform our discussions into political decisions and tangible economic and social outcomes," he explained, describing this as a "typically Swiss approach".&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As an example of such a multi-stakeholder approach, Mr Cassis cited the Geneva Dialogue on Responsible Behaviour in Cyberspace. Launched by the FDFA last November, the dialogue brings together companies from around the world to discuss the development of behavioural standards. Mr Cassis noted that Geneva was already playing an important role in global digital politics, a role which he wanted to further expand, making Geneva a leading centre for global digitalisation and technology debates.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;He emphasised that digital diplomacy held an important place in Switzerland's new foreign policy strategy, as well as being a central component of its 2028 Foreign Policy Vision. In this area, Switzerland was building on its recognised expertise in peacebuilding. "We increasingly want to bring our good offices to bear in the online world as well," he said. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Switzerland's digital strategy&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Switzerland has been instrumental in shaping the IGF's development as a forum for dialogue on all aspects of digitalisation since its inception in 2006. Within Switzerland too, developments in the field of digitalisation are closely monitored. Strategic guidance on digitalisation has been in place since 1998, while since 2016 the Digital Switzerland strategy has set out guidelines for government action in this area. Its goals are to enable equal participation for all, strengthen solidarity, guarantee security, trust and transparency, further improve people's digital empowerment, and ensure value creation, growth and prosperity.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The strategy is implemented in a decentralised way and overseen by an Interdepartmental Coordination Group chaired by the Federal Office of Communications (OFCOM). OFCOM's Director General Philipp Metzger represented Switzerland at a meeting of digital ministers yesterday, as part of the IGF.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>FDFA Communication Federal Palace West Wing CH-3003 Bern, Switzerland Tel. Communication service: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Press service: +41 58 460 55 55 E-mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @SwissMFA</contact>
      <link id="195832">
        <title>Digital Switzerland</title>
        <uri>https://www.bakom.admin.ch/bakom/en/homepage/digital-switzerland-and-internet/strategie-digitale-schweiz.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions>
        <revision date="2019-11-28 12:59" type="R"/>
        <revision date="2019-11-26 19:05" type="R"/>
      </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="19">
        <name lang="de">Medien</name>
        <name lang="fr">Médias</name>
        <name lang="it">Media</name>
        <name lang="en">Media</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="28">
        <name lang="de">Telekommunikation</name>
        <name lang="fr">Télécommunications</name>
        <name lang="it">Telecomunicazione</name>
        <name lang="en">Telecommunications</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="36">
        <name lang="de">Informatik und E-Government</name>
        <name lang="fr">Informatique et cyberadministration</name>
        <name lang="it">Informatica ed e-government</name>
        <name lang="en">IT and E-Government</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
