<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="77193" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2019-11-25</pubdate>
    <blocking-period>2019-11-25</blocking-period>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="318" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>301</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Bundesamt für Statistik</name>
      <name lang="fr">Office fédéral de la statistique</name>
      <name lang="it">Ufficio federale di statistica</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Statistical Office</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.statistik.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.statistique.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.statistica.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.statistics.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@bfs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@bfs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@bfs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@bfs.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="301">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement des Innern</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'intérieur</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'interno</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Home Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Neuchâtel</city>
      <title>In den letzten 25 Jahren ist der tägliche Alkoholkonsum in der Schweiz stark zurückgegangen</title>
      <lead>2017 tranken mehr als 80% der Bevölkerung Alkohol. Dieser Anteil hat sich seit 25 Jahren kaum verändert, während sich der Anteil Personen, die täglich Alkohol konsumieren, von 20% im Jahr 1992 auf 11% im Jahr 2017 halbiert hat. Demgegenüber ist bei den Personen, die sich mindestens einmal pro Monat betrinken, seit zehn Jahren eine Zunahme zu verzeichnen. 2017 belief sich ihr Anteil auf 16%. Männer trinken häufiger und weitaus mehr Alkohol als Frauen. Gemäss der vom Bundesamt für Statistik (BFS) durchgeführten Schweizerischen Gesundheitsbefragung (SGB) nehmen die Geschlechterunterschiede jedoch tendenziell ab.</lead>
      <text link="no">Diese Medienmitteilung und weitere Informationen zum Thema finden Sie auf der Website des BFS (siehe Link unten).</text>
      <contact>Marco Storni, BFS, Sektion Gesundheit der Bevölkerung, Tel.: +41 58 463 65 63, E-Mail: Marco.Storni@bfs.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="195470">
        <title>Kompletter Text und Mediendossier</title>
        <uri>https://www.bfs.admin.ch/news/de/2019-0209</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Neuchâtel</city>
      <title>Forte diminution de la consommation quotidienne d’alcool en Suisse ces 25 dernières années</title>
      <lead>En 2017, plus de 80% de la population buvait de l’alcool. Cette proportion est restée stable depuis 25 ans, alors que celle des personnes en consommant tous les jours a diminué de moitié, passant de 20% en 1992 à 11% en 2017. À l’inverse, la part de la population s’enivrant au moins une fois par mois est en hausse depuis dix ans et elle a atteint 16%. Les hommes consomment plus souvent de l’alcool que les femmes et en plus grande quantité, mais la différence tend à se réduire, selon l’Enquête suisse sur la santé (ESS) de l’Office fédéral de la statistique (OFS).</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Vous trouverez ce communiqué de presse et d'autres informations sur ce thème sur le site web de l'OFS (cf. lien ci-dessous).&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Renaud Lieberherr, OFS, Section Santé de la population, tél.: +41 58 463 65 61, e-mail: Renaud.Lieberherr@bfs.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="195471">
        <title>Texte intégral et dossier de presse</title>
        <uri>https://www.bfs.admin.ch/news/fr/2019-0209</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Neuchâtel</city>
      <title>Forte calo del consumo quotidiano di alcol in Svizzera negli ultimi 25 anni</title>
      <lead>Nel 2017, oltre l’80% della popolazione consumava alcol. Questa quota è stabile da 25 anni, mentre quella delle persone che consumano alcol quotidianamente si è dimezzata, passando dal 20% nel 1992 all’11% nel 2017. Negli ultimi dieci anni invece, è aumentata la percentuale della popolazione che si ritrova in stato di ebbrezza almeno una volta al mese. Tale quota ha raggiunto il 16%. Gli uomini consumano alcol più spesso e in quantità maggiori rispetto alle donne ma, stando all’indagine sulla salute in Svizzera (ISS) realizzata dall’Ufficio federale di statistica (UST), la differenza tende a diminuire.</lead>
      <text link="no">Il presente comunicato stampa e ulteriori informazioni sul tema sono reperibili sulla pagina Internet dell'UST (link sotto).</text>
      <contact>Renaud Lieberherr, UST, Sezione Salute della popolazione, tel.: +41 58 463 65 61, e-mail: Renaud.Lieberherr@bfs.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="195472">
        <title>Testo integrale e dossier per i media</title>
        <uri>https://www.bfs.admin.ch/news/it/2019-0209</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Neuchâtel</city>
      <title>Strong decrease in the daily consumption of alcohol in Switzerland over the past 25 years</title>
      <lead>In 2017, over 80% of the population drank alcohol. This share has remained stable for 25 years, while that of persons consuming alcohol every day has declined by half, decreasing from 20% in 1992 to 11% in 2017. By contrast, the share of the population that got drunk at least once per month has increased over the past ten years, reaching 16%. Men consume alcohol more often than women and in larger quantities but the gap between the genders is narrowing, according to the Swiss Health Survey (SHS) from the Federal Statistical Office (FSO).</lead>
      <text link="no">This press release and further information on this topic can be found on the FSO website (see link below).</text>
      <contact>Renaud Lieberherr, FSO, Population Health section, tel.: +41 58 463 65 61, e-mail: Renaud.Lieberherr@bfs.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="195473">
        <title>Complete text and press kit - Please note that the English version only includes the release's lead</title>
        <uri>https://www.bfs.admin.ch/news/it/2019-0209</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <keywords>
      <keyword id="317.15" org-id="318">
        <name lang="de">Gesundheit</name>
        <name lang="fr">Santé</name>
        <name lang="it">Salute</name>
        <name lang="en">Health</name>
      </keyword>
    </keywords>
    <topics>
      <topic id="15">
        <name lang="de">Gesundheit</name>
        <name lang="fr">Santé</name>
        <name lang="it">sanità</name>
        <name lang="en">Health</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="37">
        <name lang="de">Konsum</name>
        <name lang="fr">Consommation</name>
        <name lang="it">Consumo</name>
        <name lang="en">Consumer Affairs</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="43">
        <name lang="de">Statistik</name>
        <name lang="fr">Statistiques</name>
        <name lang="it">Statistica</name>
        <name lang="en">Statistics</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
