<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="76955" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2019-11-06</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="1070" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>1070</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Der Bundesrat</name>
      <name lang="fr">Conseil fédéral</name>
      <name lang="it">Il Consiglio federale</name>
      <name lang="en">The Federal Council</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.admin.ch/gov/de/start.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.admin.ch/gov/fr/accueil.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.admin.ch/gov/it/pagina-iniziale.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.admin.ch/gov/en/start.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="yes" id="703" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>701</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Staatssekretariat für Wirtschaft</name>
      <name lang="fr">Secrétariat d'Etat à l'économie</name>
      <name lang="it">Segreteria di Stato dell'economia</name>
      <name lang="en">State Secretariat for Economic Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.seco.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.seco.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.seco.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.seco.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@seco.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@seco.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@seco.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@seco.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="1070">
      <name lang="de">Der Bundesrat</name>
      <name lang="fr">Conseil fédéral</name>
      <name lang="it">Il Consiglio federale</name>
      <name lang="en">The Federal Council</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.admin.ch/gov/de/start.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.admin.ch/gov/fr/accueil.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.admin.ch/gov/it/pagina-iniziale.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.admin.ch/gov/en/start.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <department id="701">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Wirtschaft, Bildung und Forschung</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'économie, de la formation et de la recherche</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'economia, della formazione e della ricerca</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Economic Affairs, Education and Research</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Bundesrat ermöglicht Umsetzung von Ausnahmen zu Nordkorea-Sanktionen</title>
      <lead>Der Bundesrat hat am 6. November 2019 die Sanktionen gegenüber der Demokratischen Volksrepublik Korea punktuell angepasst. Damit ermöglicht er die Umsetzung von Ausnahmen zum Exportverbot, welche zuvor durch das zuständige Sanktionskomitee des Sicherheitsrates der Vereinten Nationen beschlossen wurden. Die Änderung tritt am 1. Dezember 2019 in Kraft. </lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Die Verordnung über Massnahmen gegenüber der Demokratischen Volksrepublik Korea verbietet den Verkauf, die Lieferung, die Ausfuhr, die Durchfuhr und den Transport sämtlicher Güter der Zolltarifnummern 72 bis 89, darunter teilweise auch medizinisches und orthopädisches Material. In Übereinstimmung mit den relevanten Resolutionen des Sicherheitsrates sah die Verordnung bisher in diesem Zusammenhang aber lediglich für Schiffe eine Ausnahmemöglichkeit vor.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Mit der beschlossenen Verordnungsänderung kann die Lieferung von humanitären und anderen Gütern, für welche eine Ausnahmebewilligung des zuständigen Sanktionskomitees des UNO-Sicherheitsrates vorliegt, in Zukunft auch gestützt auf das Schweizer Recht bewilligt werden. Dies erhöht die Rechtssicherheit der beteiligten Akteure.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Für die Exporteure solcher Güter ändert sich nichts. Auch in Zukunft muss dem SECO jede Ausfuhr im Voraus angemeldet werden. Zudem werden wie bisher sämtliche Sendungen nach Nordkorea physisch überprüft. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Der Bundesrat hatte erstmals am 25. Oktober 2006 Massnahmen gegenüber der Demokratischen Volksrepublik Korea beschlossen. Diese erfolgten gestützt auf die Resolutionen des UNO-Sicherheitsrates, welche aufgrund des nordkoreanischen Nuklearprogramms erlassen wurden. &lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Antje Baertschi, Leiterin Kommunikation, SECO, Tel. 058 463 52 75 Fabian Maienfisch, Stv. Leiter Kommunikation, SECO, Tel. 058 462 40 20</contact>
      <attachment id="194685">
        <title>Verordnung</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>109</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/58944.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Le Conseil fédéral reconnaît des exceptions aux sanctions à l’encontre de la Corée du Nord</title>
      <lead>Le 6 novembre 2019, le Conseil fédéral a modifié sur certains points les sanctions prononcées à l’encontre de la République populaire démocratique de Corée (Corée du Nord). Il permet ainsi l’application des exceptions à l’interdiction d’exportation décidées par le comité des sanctions compétent du Conseil de sécurité des Nations Unies. Cette modification entrera en vigueur le 1er décembre 2019. </lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;L’ordonnance instituant des mesures à l’encontre de la République populaire démocratique de Corée interdit la vente, la fourniture, l’exportation, le transit et le transport de tous les biens des positions tarifaires 72 à 89, qui comprennent notamment du matériel médical et orthopédique. Conformément aux résolutions du Conseil de sécurité à ce sujet, la version actuelle de l’ordonnance n’autorise des exceptions dans ce domaine que pour les bateaux.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Grâce à la révision de l’ordonnance adoptée par le Conseil fédéral, le droit suisse permettra la livraison de biens humanitaires et d’autres biens faisant l’objet d’une autorisation exceptionnelle du comité des sanctions compétent du Conseil de sécurité de l’ONU. Cela améliorera la sécurité juridique pour les acteurs concernés.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Rien ne changera pour les exportateurs de ce type de biens, qui devront continuer de déclarer préalablement chaque exportation au Secrétariat d’État à l’économie (SECO). Tous les envois à destination de la Corée du Nord continueront d’être vérifiés physiquement. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Le Conseil fédéral a arrêté ses premières sanctions à l’encontre de la Corée du Nord le 25 octobre 2006. Elles étaient fondées sur les résolutions décrétées par le Conseil de sécurité de l’ONU en réponse au programme nucléaire nord-coréen. &lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Antje Baertschi, cheffe de la Communication, SECO, 058 463 52 75 Fabian Maienfisch, suppléant de la cheffe de la Communication, SECO, 058 462 40 20</contact>
      <attachment id="194686">
        <title>Ordonnance</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>102</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/58945.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Il Consiglio federale ammette deroghe alle sanzioni contro la Corea del Nord</title>
      <lead>Il 6 novembre 2019 il Consiglio federale ha adeguato in alcuni punti le sanzioni nei confronti della Repubblica popolare democratica di Corea. Sarà così possibile derogare al divieto d’esportazione che era stato deciso dal Comitato per le sanzioni del Consiglio di sicurezza dell’ONU. La modifica entrerà in vigore il 1° dicembre 2019. </lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;L’ordinanza che istituisce provvedimenti nei confronti della Repubblica popolare democratica di Corea vieta la vendita, la fornitura, l’esportazione, il transito e il trasporto di tutti i beni elencati alle voci di tariffa doganale da 72 a 89, tra cui in parte anche il materiale medico e ortopedico. In linea con le risoluzioni corrispondenti del Consiglio di sicurezza dell’ONU, l’unica possibilità di deroga riguardava finora le navi.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;A seguito dell’adeguamento dell’ordinanza, le forniture di beni umanitari e di altri prodotti per i quali esiste un permesso eccezionale rilasciato dal Comitato per le sanzioni competente potranno essere effettuate anche in base al diritto svizzero. Per gli operatori interessati aumenta così la sicurezza giuridica.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Per gli esportatori di questi beni non cambia nulla: anche in futuro dovranno notificare anticipatamente alla SECO tutte le esportazioni che intendono effettuare e – come finora – tutte le forniture alla Corea del Nord saranno sottoposte a controlli fisici. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Il 25 ottobre 2006 il Consiglio federale aveva deciso per la prima volta di infliggere sanzioni alla Repubblica popolare democratica di Corea a seguito delle risoluzioni adottate dal Consiglio di sicurezza dell’ONU in segno di protesta per il programma nucleare nordcoreano. &lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Antje Baertschi, capo Comunicazione, SECO, tel. +41 58 463 52 75; medien@seco.admin.ch Fabian Maienfisch, vicecapo Comunicazione, SECO, tel. +41 58 462 40 20; medien@seco.admin.ch</contact>
      <attachment id="194687">
        <title>Ordinanza</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>103</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/58946.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Federal Council gives green light to exceptions to North Korea sanctions</title>
      <lead>On 6 November, the Federal Council made selective adjustments to sanctions against the Democratic People’s Republic of Korea. This means that the exceptions to the export ban agreed by the United Nations Security Council Sanctions Committee can now be implemented. The amendment will come into force on 1 December 2019. </lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;The Ordinance on Measures against the Democratic People’s Republic of Korea prohibits the sale, delivery, export, transit and transport of all goods under customs tariff numbers 72 to 89, including some medical and orthopaedic equipment. In accordance with the corresponding Security Council resolutions, the Ordinance has until now only provided for a possible exemption for ships.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The amendment to the Ordinance means that the delivery of humanitarian aid and other goods for which an exception has been granted by the UN Security Council sanctions committee can in future also be authorised under Swiss law. This will increase legal certainty for those involved.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Nothing will change for exporters of such goods. SECO will still have to be notified in advance of all exports. In addition, all shipments to North Korea will continue to be physically inspected.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The Federal Council first adopted measures against the Democratic People’s Republic of Korea on 25 October 2006. These measures were based on the resolutions of the UN Security Council, issued as a result of the North Korean nuclear programme.&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Antje Baertschi, Head of Communications, SECO, Tel. 058 463 52 75 Fabian Maienfisch, Deputy Head of Communications, SECO, Tel. 058 462 40 20</contact>
      <attachment id="194685">
        <title>Verordnung</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>109</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/58944.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="194686">
        <title>Ordonnance</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>102</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/58945.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="194687">
        <title>Ordinanza</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>103</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/58946.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <offers>
      <offer id="255" org-id="703">
        <name lang="de">Sanktionen / Embargos und Exportkontrollen</name>
        <name lang="fr">sanctions / embargos et contrôles à l‘exportation</name>
        <name lang="it">Sanzioni / embarghi e controlli delle esportazioni</name>
        <name lang="en">sanctions / embargoes and export controls</name>
      </offer>
    </offers>
    <topics>
      <topic id="47">
        <name lang="de">Wirtschaft</name>
        <name lang="fr">Économie</name>
        <name lang="it">Economia</name>
        <name lang="en">Economic Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
