<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="77224" revoked="no">
    <version>3</version>
    <pubdate>2019-11-26</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="201" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>201</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="201">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Erdbeben Albanien: Die Schweiz entsendet ein humanitäres Expertenteam</title>
      <lead>Die Humanitäre Hilfe der DEZA entsendet ein Team des Schweizerischen Korps für Humanitäre Hilfe (SKH) in das vom Erdbeben betroffene Gebiet nach Albanien. Sie reagiert damit auf das offizielle Hilfsgesuch der albanischen Regierung.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Heute Dienstag, 26. November 2019, 03.45 Uhr (Lokalzeit und Schweizer Zeit) wurde Albanien von einem schweren Erdbeben mit der Stärke von 6,4 Magnitude erschüttert. Das Epizentrum des Bebens lag rund 10km nördlich von Durres, der zweitwichtigsten Stadt Albaniens. Die Hafenstadt liegt rund 30km westlich der Hauptstadt Tirana.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Diese Region war schon im September von mehreren Erdbeben betroffen. Es ist damit zu rechnen, dass durch das starke Beben die Not der Bevölkerung noch vergrössert wird. Zudem ist mit steigenden Opferzahlen, Verletzten und Vermissten sowie mit zusätzlich beträchtlichen Schäden an Infrastruktur zu rechnen.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Die Humanitäre Hilfe der Direktion für Entwicklung und Zusammenarbeit (DEZA) entsendet noch heute Abend ein Expertenteam. Die rund 15 Spezialistinnen und Spezialisten des Schweizerischen Korps für humanitäre Hilfe (SKH) unterstützen die albanischen Einsatzkräfte in den Bereichen Suche und Rettung von Verschütteten, Überprüfen der betroffenen Gebäude auf ihre Baustatik sowie humanitäre Bedürfnisabklärungen. Das Team wird zudem weitere Hilfsunterstützungen vorbereiten und konkrete Nothilfemassnahmen einleiten.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Die Schweiz ist schon durch die DEZA und ihre Partner im Land aktiv.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Kommunikation EDA Bundeshaus West CH-3003 Bern Tel. Kommunikationsservice: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Medienstelle: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <link id="195749">
        <title>Engagement der DEZA in Albanien</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/deza/de/home/laender/albanien.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Séisme en Albanie: la Suisse envoie une équipe d’experts humanitaires</title>
      <lead>En réponse à une demande d’aide officielle du gouvernement albanais, l’Aide humanitaire de la DDC s’apprête à détacher une équipe du Corps suisse d’aide humanitaire (CSA) dans la région frappée par un séisme. </lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Mardi 26 novembre 2019, à 3h45 (heure locale et heure suisse), l’Albanie a été touchée par un violent séisme d’une magnitude de 6,4. L’épicentre de la secousse était situé à environ 10 km au nord de Durres, la deuxième plus grande ville d’Albanie. Cette ville portuaire se trouve à une trentaine de kilomètres à l’ouest de la capitale Tirana.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;La région avait déjà été touchée par plusieurs tremblements de terre en septembre dernier. Ce nouveau séisme violent vient encore accroître la détresse des habitants. Le nombre de victimes, de blessés et de personnes disparues ne cesse de croître et les dégâts sur les infrastructures sont considérables.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;L’Aide humanitaire de la Direction du développement et de la coopération (DDC) va envoyer dès ce soir une équipe d’experts dans la région concernée. La quinzaine de membres du Corps suisse d’aide humanitaire (CSA) détachée sur place va aider les équipes de secours albanaises à rechercher et sauver des personnes ensevelies, à vérifier la stabilité des bâtiments et à évaluer les besoins humanitaires. L’équipe d’experts va également organiser d’autres opérations de secours et mettre en œuvre des mesures d’aide d’urgence concrètes.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;La Suisse est déjà active en Albanie à travers l’engagement de la DDC et de ses partenaires.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Communication DFAE Palais fédéral ouest CH-3003 Berne Tél. Service de communication: +41 58 462 31 53 Tél. Service de presse: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <link id="195750">
        <title>Engagement de la DDC en Albanie</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/deza/fr/home/pays/albanie.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions>
        <revision date="2019-11-27 12:26" type="R"/>
      </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Terremoto in Albania: la Svizzera invia un team di esperti umanitari</title>
      <lead>L’Aiuto umanitario della DSC invia una squadra del Corpo svizzero di aiuto umanitario (CSA) nella zona dell’Albania colpita dal sisma, accogliendo così la richiesta ufficiale di aiuto da parte del Governo albanese.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Martedì 26 novembre 2019, alle ore 3.45 (ora locale e ora svizzera), l’Albania è stata colpita da un grave terremoto di magnitudo 6,4. L’epicentro del sisma è stato localizzato a circa 10 km a nord di Durazzo, la seconda città più importante dell’Albania, città portuale che si trova a circa 30 km a ovest della capitale Tirana.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Questa regione era già stata colpita da diverse scosse nel mese di settembre e ora si teme che il forte sisma aggravi ulteriormente la situazione della popolazione. Sono da mettere in conto un aumento delle vittime, dei feriti e dei dispersi nonché ingenti danni supplementari alle infrastrutture.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Martedì in serata, l’Aiuto umanitario della Direzione dello sviluppo e della cooperazione (DSC) ha inviato un team di esperti. I circa 15 specialisti e specialiste del Corpo svizzero di aiuto umanitario (CSA) danno supporto alle forze di intervento albanesi nell’ambito della ricerca e del salvataggio delle persone intrappolate sotto le macerie, della verifica della sicurezza statica degli edifici colpiti e dell’accertamento delle esigenze umanitarie. La squadra predisporrà inoltre ulteriori aiuti e misure di emergenza concrete.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;La Svizzera è già attiva attraverso la DSC e i suoi partner nel Paese.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Comunicazione DFAE Palazzo federale ovest CH-3003 Berna Tel. Servizio di comunicazione: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Servizio stampa: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <link id="195751">
        <title>Impegno della DSC in Albania</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/deza/it/home/paesi/albania.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions>
        <revision date="2019-11-27 16:38" type="R"/>
      </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Earthquake in Albania: Switzerland sends team of humanitarian experts</title>
      <lead>In response to an official request from the Albanian government, Swiss Humanitarian Aid is dispatching a team of experts from its Swiss Humanitarian Aid Unit (SHA) to the affected area of Albania.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;On 26 November 2019 at 3.45am a 6.4 magnitude earthquake struck Albania. The epicentre was approximately 10km north of the coastal city of Durres. Durres lies 30km to the west of the capital Tirana and is Albania's second largest city. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This region already suffered several earthquakes in September, and this latest quake will exacerbate the situation for an already struggling population. The number of people reported injured, missing or dead is likely to rise, and further damage to infrastructure is expected. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Swiss Humanitarian Aid, part of the Swiss Agency for Development and Cooperation (SDC), is sending an expert team to the area this evening. Around 15 Swiss Humanitarian Aid Unit (SHA) specialists will assist the Albanian emergency forces in search and rescue operations to extract victims, in ascertaining humanitarian needs and assessing the structural safety of affected buildings. The team will also make preparations for further support missions and initiate specific relief measures. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Switzerland is already active in Albania through the SDC and its partners.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>FDFA Communication Federal Palace West Wing CH-3003 Bern, Switzerland Tel. Communication service: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Press service: +41 58 460 55 55 E-mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @SwissMFA</contact>
      <link id="195752">
        <title>SDC's commitment in Albania</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/deza/en/home/countries/albania.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions>
        <revision date="2019-11-27 12:26" type="R"/>
      </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
