<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="61315" revoked="no">
    <version>6</version>
    <pubdate>2016-04-12</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="408" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>408</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Bundesanwaltschaft</name>
      <name lang="fr">Ministère public de la Confédération</name>
      <name lang="it">Ministero pubblico della Confederazione</name>
      <name lang="en">Office of the Attorney General of Switzerland</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.ba.admin.ch/ba/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.ba.admin.ch/ba/fr/home.html</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.ba.admin.ch/ba/it/home.html</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.ba.admin.ch/</www>
      <email lang="de">info@ba.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@ba.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@ba.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@ba.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="408">
      <name lang="de">Bundesanwaltschaft</name>
      <name lang="fr">Ministère public de la Confédération</name>
      <name lang="it">Ministero pubblico della Confederazione</name>
      <name lang="en">Office of the Attorney General of Switzerland</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.ba.admin.ch/ba/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.ba.admin.ch/ba/fr/home.html</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.ba.admin.ch/ba/it/home.html</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.ba.admin.ch/</www>
      <email lang="de">info@ba.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@ba.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@ba.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@ba.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Fall 1MDB: Ausdehnung des schweizerischen Strafverfahrens</title>
      <lead>Im Rahmen des Strafverfahrens wegen des Verdachts der Veruntreuung zum Nachteil des malaysischen Staatsfonds 1MDB (1Malaysia Development Berhad) hat die Bundesanwaltschaft (BA) ihr Verfahren auf zwei ehemalige Beamte der Vereinigten Arabischen Emirate ausgedehnt, die sich um Staatsfonds von Abu Dhabi kümmerten. Die BA hat weiter Luxemburg und Singapur um Rechtshilfe ersucht.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Die beiden ehemaligen Beamten der Vereinigten Arabischen Emirate werden des Betruges (Art. 146 Strafgesetzbuch / StGB), der ungetreuen Geschäftsbesorgung (Art. 158 StGB), der ungetreuen Amtsführung (Art. 314 StGB), der Urkundenfälschung (Art. 251 StGB), der Bestechung fremder Amtsträger (Art. 322septies StGB) und der Geldwäscherei (Art. 305bis StGB) beschuldigt. Die Ausdehnung erfolgte im Teil Genting-Tanjong, einem der vier strafrechtlich relevanten Sachverhalte des am 14. August 2015 durch die BA eröffneten schweizerischen Strafverfahrens (vgl. Medienmitteilung der BA vom 29.01.2016). Die Filialen von 1MDB haben zwei Serien von Obligationen emittiert zur Finanzierung von Investitionen in Kraftwerke. Die Umstände, unter welchen erreicht wurde, dass ein Staatsfonds von Abu Dhabi deren Rückzahlung garantiert, ist Gegenstand dieses Teils des Strafverfahrens. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Die Schweizerischen Behörden verfügen über Anhaltspunkte, wonach die Beträge, die im Zusammenhang mit dieser Garantie geflossen sind, nicht dem Staatsfonds von Abu Dhabi zugutegekommen sind, der die wirtschaftlichen Risiken trug. Die Beträge gingen vielmehr an Dritte, insbesondere an die betreffenden Beamten sowie an eine Gesellschaft mit Verbindungen zur Filmindustrie. Auch ein ehemaliges Organ von 1MDB, das im schweizerischen Verfahren bereits beschuldigt ist, soll von diesen Beträgen profitiert haben. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Im Zusammenhang mit dem schweizerischen Strafverfahren und insbesondere mit dessen Ausdehnung richtete die BA je ein neues Rechtshilfeersuchen an Luxemburg und an Singapur. In internationaler Zusammenarbeit wird an der Feststellung des Sachverhalts gearbeitet. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Wie für alle Beschuldigten gilt für beide Beamten der Vereinigten Arabischen Emirate sowie für die anderen Beschuldigten die Unschuldsvermutung. &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>André Marty, Informationschef Bundesanwaltschaft; +41 58 464 32 40; info@ba.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions>
        <revision date="2016-04-12 13:59" type="I"/>
      </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Affaire 1MDB: extension de la procédure pénale suisse</title>
      <lead>Dans le cadre de la procédure pénale menée sur les soupçons de détournements commis au détriment du fonds souverain malaisien 1MDB (1Malaysia Development Berhad), le Ministère public de la Confédération (MPC) a étendu sa procédure à deux anciens agents publics émiratis, en charge de fonds souverains d’Abu Dhabi. Le MPC a également adressé deux demandes d’entraide au Luxembourg et à Singapour.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Cette mise en prévention pour escroquerie (art. 146 Code pénal / CP), gestion déloyale (art. 158 CP), gestion déloyale des intérêts publics (art. 314 CP), faux dans les titres (art. 251 CP), corruption d’agents publics étrangers (art. 322septies CP) et blanchiment d'argent (art. 305bis CP) intervient dans le cadre du volet Genting/Tanjong, un des quatre volets importants de l’enquête suisse ouverte le 14 août 2015 (cf. communiqué de presse du MPC du 29.01.2016). Des filiales de 1MDB ont émis deux séries d’obligations afin de financer des investissements dans des centrales électriques. Les circonstances dans lesquelles ces filiales ont obtenu qu’un fonds souverain d’Abu Dhabi garantisse le remboursement de ces obligations font l’objet de ce volet de la procédure. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Les éléments en mains des autorités suisses permettent de suspecter que les montants versés en relation avec cette garantie ne sont pas revenus au fonds souverain d’Abu Dhabi, qui supportait le risque commercial. Au contraire, ces montants auraient profité à des tiers, notamment aux agents publics concernés ainsi qu’à une société liée au monde du cinéma. Un ancien organe de 1MDB, déjà prévenu dans la procédure suisse, aurait également bénéficié de ces montants. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;En relation avec la procédure pénale suisse et en particulier avec son extension, le MPC a adressé deux nouvelles demandes d’entraide, au Luxembourg et à Singapour. Grâce à la coopération internationale, il oeuvre ainsi à l’établissement des faits. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Comme pour tout prévenu, les deux agents publics émiratis ainsi que les autres prévenus sont présumés innocents. &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>André Marty, chef de l'information du Ministère public de la Confédération; +41 58 464 32 40; info@ba.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Caso 1MDB: estensione del procedimento penale svizzero</title>
      <lead>Nell’ambito del procedimento penale condotto per distrazioni a scapito del fondo sovrano malese 1Malaysia Development Berhad (1MDB), il Ministero pubblico della Confederazione (MPC) ha esteso il suo procedimento a due ex pubblici ufficiali emirati, incaricati dei fondi sovrani di Abu Dhabi. Il MPC ha inoltre presentato due domande di assistenza giudiziaria, al Lussemburgo e a Singapore.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;L’estensione del procedimento penale condotto per truffa (art. 146 Codice penale / CP), amministrazione infedele (art. 158 CP), infedeltà nella gestione pubblica (art. 314 CP), falsità in documenti (art. 251 CP), corruzione di pubblici ufficiali stranieri (art. 322septies CP) e riciclaggio di denaro (art. 305bis CP) avviene nell’ambito della parte Genting/Tanjong, una delle quattro fattispecie rilevanti dell’inchiesta svizzera aperta il 14 agosto 2015 (v. comunicato di stampa del MPC del 29.01.2016). Questa parte verte sulle circostanze che hanno permesso a filiali di 1MDB di ottenere che un fondo sovrano di Abu Dhabi garantisca il rimborso di due serie di obbligazioni emesse dalle filiali allo scopo di finanziare investimenti in centrali elettriche. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Gli elementi in possesso delle autorità svizzere indicano che gli importi versati in relazione alla garanzia non avrebbero beneficiato al fondo sovrano di Abu Dhabi, che copriva il rischio commerciale, bensì a terzi, segnatamente ai pubblici ufficiali menzionati e a una società legata al mondo del cinema. Anche un ex organo di 1MDB, già imputato nel procedimento penale svizzero, avrebbe beneficiato degli importi. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;In relazione con la procedura penale svizzero e anche in seguito all’estensione del suo procedimento, il MPC ha presentato due nuove domande di assistenza giudiziaria, una al Lussemburgo e una a Singapore, per fare luce sui fatti in cooperazione con le autorità di questi Paesi. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Come ogni imputato, entrambi i due ex pubblici ufficiali emirati nonché gli altri imputati sono presunti innocenti. &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>André Marty, capo Informazione del Ministero pubblico della Confederazione; +41 58 464 32 40; info@ba.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>1MDB case: Swiss investigation extended</title>
      <lead>As part of the criminal proceedings into allegations of embezzlement involving the Malaysian sovereign fund 1MDB (1Malaysia Development Berhad), the Office of the Attorney General of Switzerland (OAG) has extended its proceedings to include two former officials from the United Arab Emirates, who were in charge of Abu Dhabi sovereign funds. The OAG has also sent two requests for mutual legal assistance to Luxembourg and Singapore.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;The two former Emirati officials are under investigation for fraud (Art. 146 Swiss Criminal Code (SCC)), criminal mismanagement (Art. 158 SCC), misconduct in public office (Art. 314 SCC), forgery of a document (Art. 251 SCC), bribery of foreign public officials (Art. 322septies SCC) and money laundering (Art. 305bis SCC). The extension of the criminal proceedings took place as part of the Genting / Tanjong chapter, one of the four main chapters in the Swiss investigation opened on 14 August 2015 (see OAG's press release of 29 January 2016). 1MDB subsidiaries issued two series of bonds to finance investments in electricity power plants. This chapter of the proceedings covers the circumstances in which these subsidiaries obtained the guarantee to repay these bonds from an Abu Dhabi sovereign fund. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Swiss authorities have evidence that the amounts paid in connection with this guarantee were not returned to the Abu Dhabi sovereign fund that was bearing the commercial risk. Instead these sums were apparently paid to third parties, in particular the two public officials concerned and a company connected with to the film industry. A former 1MDB official, already a suspect in the Swiss proceedings, also received a share of the money. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; As part of the Swiss criminal proceedings, and in particular this new avenue of enquiry, the OAG has filed two new requests for mutual legal assistance, to Luxembourg and Singapore. The OAG is thus working with its international partners to establish the facts. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; As is always the case, the presumption of innocence applies to the two Emirati public officials and to other suspects in this case. &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>André Marty, Head of Communication &amp; Public Affairs of the Office of the Attorney General of Switzerland, +41 58 464 32 40; info@ba.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions>
        <revision date="2018-05-16 17:11" type="R"/>
        <revision date="2016-04-12 13:41" type="I"/>
        <revision date="2016-04-12 11:16" type="I"/>
      </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="17">
        <name lang="de">Kriminalität</name>
        <name lang="fr">Criminalité</name>
        <name lang="it">Criminalità</name>
        <name lang="en">Criminality</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="35">
        <name lang="de">Finanzplatz</name>
        <name lang="fr">Place financière</name>
        <name lang="it">Piazza finanziaria</name>
        <name lang="en">Financial Centre</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
