<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="13614" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2007-07-10</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="302" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>301</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Generalsekretariat EDI</name>
      <name lang="fr">Secrétariat général DFI</name>
      <name lang="it">Segreteria generale DFI</name>
      <name lang="en">General Secretariat FDHA</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="322" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>301</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Staatssekretariat für Bildung und Forschung (SBF) - ab 1.1.2013 SBFI</name>
      <name lang="fr">Secrétariat d'Etat à l'éducation et à la recherche (SER) - dès le 1.1.2013 SEFRI</name>
      <name lang="it">Segreteria di Stato per l'educazione e la ricerca (SER) - a partire dal 1.1.2013 SEFRI</name>
      <name lang="en">State Secretariat for Education and Research (SER) - as of 1.1.2013 SERI</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.sbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.sbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.sbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.sbf.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@sbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@sbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@sbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@sbf.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="301">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement des Innern</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'intérieur</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'interno</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Home Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Bundesrat Pascal Couchepin hat das Abkommen über die wissenschaftliche und technologische Zusammenarbeit zwischen der Schweiz und Japan unterzeichnet</title>
      <lead>Bundesrat Pascal Couchepin und der japanische Aussenminister Taro Aso haben heute in Tokio ein bilaterales Abkommen über die künftige wissenschaftliche und technologische Zusammenarbeit zwischen der Schweiz und Japan unterzeichnet. Das Abkommen liegt auf der Linie der vom Bundesrat in der Botschaft zur Förderung von Bildung, Forschung und Innovation in den Jahren 2008-2011 formulierten Strategie, wonach der Kreis der Schweizer Beziehungen in Bildung und Forschung vermehrt auch in Richtung geeigneter und ihrerseits an bilateraler Zusammenarbeit interessierter aussereuropäischer Partnerländer erweitert werden soll.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Nachdem die Schweiz und Japan in den vergangenen Jahren verschiedene Round Table-Gespräche über Wissenschaft und Technologie (W&amp;amp;T) geführt hatten, haben sie nun ein bilaterales Abkommen für die Zusammenarbeit in diesem Bereich unterzeichnet. Das Abkommen regelt die Formen der künftigen Zusammenarbeit, setzt aber nicht die zu bearbeitenden Forschungsschwerpunkte und –themen fest. Diese sollen von den interessierten Kreisen sowohl des öffentlichen als auch des privaten Bereichs beider Länder nun selbst konkretisiert und definiert werden. Dabei zeigt die bislang punktuell stattgefundene Zusammenarbeit zwischen schweizerischen und japanischen Institutionen, dass ein reges gegenseitiges Kooperationsinteresse auf zahlreichen Wissenschaftszweigen besteht, von den Life sciences, der Nanotechnologie und den Informations- und Kommunikationstechnologien über die Umweltwissenschaften bis hin zu den Geistes- und Sozialwissenschaften.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Für jedes Land noch zu bezeichnende Institutionen werden als Leading Houses die bilaterale Zusammenarbeit mit dem Partnerland koordinieren und dabei auf nationaler Ebene den Einbezug aller Hochschulen und Forschungsinstitutionen gewährleisten.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Die Finanzierung der bilateralen W&amp;amp;T-Aktivitäten wird schwergewichtig über die in beiden Ländern bestehenden Institutionen der Forschungsförderung (in der Schweiz der Nationalfonds zur Förderung der wissenschaftlichen Forschung und die Förderagentur für Innovation KTI) und die einzelnen involvierten Hochschulen laufen. Eine wichtige Rolle in der Zusammenarbeit mit Japan werden auch die Institutionen des ETH-Bereichs spielen, dessen Engagement für die bilaterale internationale Zusammenarbeit insgesamt im Leistungsauftrag des Bundesrates 2008-2011 explizit festgehalten ist.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ausbau der bilateralen Schweizer Wissenschafts- und Forschungspolitik&lt;br /&gt; &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt; Das W&amp;amp;T-Abkommen mit Japan liegt auf der Linie der in der Botschaft zur Förderung von Bildung, Forschung und Innovation in den Jahren 2008-2011 (BFI) formulierten bilateralen Strategie. Danach soll die Schweiz engere Beziehungen im BFI-Bereich vermehrt auch mit geeigneten, wissenschaftlich und technologisch herausragenden Partnerländern ausserhalb Europas knüpfen. Im Rahmen der Botschaft wird ein Kredit von CHF 43 Millionen beantragt zur teilweisen Mitfinanzierung konkreter Kooperationsaktivitäten von Schweizer Hochschulen.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Zu den Schwerpunktländern zählen für den Bundesrat neben Japan auch China, Indien, Russland, Südkorea, Südafrika sowie Brasilien und Chile. Die Umsetzung dieser Strategie ist je Schwerpunktland unterschiedlich weit fortgeschritten.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Mit Indien (Leading House ETH Lausanne) und China (ETH Zürich) wurden bereits im Jahr 2003 bilaterale Abkommen über die W&amp;amp;T-Zusammenarbeit abgeschlossen, auf deren Basis Pilotprogramme im den Bereichen Lebenswissenschaften sowie Informations- und Kommunikationstechnologien entwickelt und finanziert wurden. Die Bilanz dieser Pilotprogramme, die ein grosses Zusammenarbeitspotenzial und starkes Interesse an einer Zusammenarbeit mit Schweizer Wissenschafterinnen und Wissenschaftern deutlich gemacht haben, ist sehr positiv. Entsprechend wird diese Zusammenarbeit in den kommenden Jahren verstärkt weitergeführt.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Bezüglich der wissenschaftliche Zusammenarbeit mit Russland, Südkorea und Südafrika (Leading House Universität Basel) ist die Unterzeichnung jeweiliger bilateraler Abkommen noch in diesem Jahr vorgesehen. Und was die Ausrichtung der bilateralen Wissenschaftszusammenarbeit mit Brasilien und Chile betrifft, so befindet sich das Staatssekretariat für Bildung und Forschung im Eidgenössischen Departement des Innern noch in der Erkundungsphase.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Jean-Marc Crevoisier, Kommunikationschef EDI, Tel. 079 763 84 10 Claudio Fischer, Staatssekretariat für Bildung und Forschung, Ressortleiter Bilaterale Forschungszusammenarbeit, Tel. 031 322 96 53</contact>
      <link id="29409">
        <title>Abkommen zwischen dem Schweizerischen Bundesrat und der Regierung von Japan über die wissenschaftliche und technologische Zusammenarbeit:</title>
        <uri>http://www.sbf.admin.ch/japan2007.htm</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Le conseiller fédéral Pascal Couchepin signe un accord de coopération scientifique et technologique entre la Suisse et le Japon</title>
      <lead>Le conseiller fédéral Pascal Couchepin et le ministre japonais des affaires étrangères Taro Aso ont signé, aujourd’hui à Tokyo, un accord de coopération scientifique et technologique entre la Suisse et le Japon. L’accord s’inscrit dans la stratégie formulée par le Conseil fédéral dans le message relatif à l’encouragement de la formation, de la recherche et de l’innovation pendant les années 2008 à 2011 qui prévoit de développer les relations scientifiques extérieures de la Suisse avec un certain nombre de pays partenaires extra-européens, intéressés par un resserrement de la coopération bilatérale.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Les différentes Tables-Rondes qui ont eu lieu ces dernières années sur la coopération scientifique et technologique entre la Suisse et le Japon aboutissent maintenant à la signature d’un accord qui règle les termes de la future coopération, sans pour autant en fixer les priorités thématiques. Celles-ci seront identifiées par les milieux de la recherche publique et privée des deux pays. Les coopérations éparses qui ont déjà vu le jour entre institutions suisses et japonaises dénotent un vif intérêt mutuel dans divers secteurs, en particulier les sciences de la vie, les nanotechnologies, les technologies de l’information et de la communication, les sciences environnementales et les sciences humaines et sociales.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Dans chacun des deux pays, les actions de coopération seront coordonnées par une institution («Leading House») qui veillera à y associer toutes les universités, hautes écoles et institutions de recherche. Les activités conjointes seront soutenues essentiellement par les agences de financement des deux pays (en Suisse: le Fonds national suisse de la recherche scientifique et l’Agence de promotion de l’innovation CTI) et les universités participantes.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Un rôle important est dévolu aux institutions du domaine des EPF. Leur mission en faveur de la coopération scientifique bilatérale fait l’objet du mandat de prestations du Conseil fédéral au domaine des EPF pour les années 2008-2011.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Développement des relations scientifiques bilatérales&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; L’accord de coopération scientifique avec le Japon s’insère dans la stratégie de coopération bilatérale formulée dans le message relatif à l’encouragement de la formation, de la recherche et de l’innovation pendant les années 2008 à 2011. Cette stratégie prévoit le resserrement des relations avec des pays partenaires extra-européens choisis en fonction de leur potentiel scientifique et technologique. Un crédit de 43 millions de francs est demandé au Parlement pour cofinancer les actions de coopération des hautes écoles suisses.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; En dehors du Japon, les pays prioritaires retenus par le Conseil fédéral dans cette stratégie sont la Chine, l’Inde, la Russie, la Corée du Sud ainsi que le Brésil et le Chili. L’état d’avancement de la mise en œuvre de la stratégie varie selon les pays.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Des accords de coopération scientifique et technologique ont été signés en 2003 avec l’Inde (Leading House: EPFL) et la Chine (EPFZ), qui ont donné lieu à des programmes pilotes en sciences de la vie et en technologies de l’information et de la communication. Les programmes pilotes ont mis en évidence le grand potentiel de coopération et l’intérêt marqué des scientifiques suisses pour ce type de coopération bilatérale. Les programmes seront donc étoffés au cours des années à venir.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; La signature d’accords de coopération scientifique avec la Russie, la Corée et l’Afrique du Sud (Leading House: Université de Bâle) est prévue avant la fin de l’année en cours. Dans le cas du Brésil et du Chili, le développement de la coopération bilatérale est encore en phase exploratoire.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Jean-Marc Crevoisier, chef de la communication du DFI, tél. 079 763 84 10 Claudio Fischer, chef de l’unité Coopération bilatérale de recherche, Secrétariat d’Etat à l’éducation et à la recherche, tél. 031 322 96 53</contact>
      <link id="29410">
        <title>Accord entre le Conseil fédéral suisse et le Gouvernement du Japon relatif à la coopération scientifique et technologique:</title>
        <uri>http://www.sbf.admin.ch/japan2007.htm</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Il consigliere federale Pascal Couchepin firma l'accordo sulla cooperazione scientifica e tecnologica tra la Svizzera e il Giappone</title>
      <lead>Il consigliere federale Pascal Couchepin e il ministro degli affari esteri giapponese Taro Aso hanno firmato oggi a Tokyo un accordo sulla futura cooperazione scientifica e tecnologica tra la Svizzera e il Giappone. L'accordo rientra nella strategia formulata dal Consiglio federale nel messaggio concernente il promovimento dell'educazione, della ricerca e dell'innovazione negli anni 2008-2011 che prevede di estendere le relazioni nel campo dell'educazione e della ricerca a Paesi extraeuropei che rispondono a determinati criteri e che sono interessati a una cooperazione.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Dopo diverse discussioni preparatorie condotte negli ultimi anni, Svizzera e Giappone hanno firmato un accordo bilaterale sulla cooperazione scientifica e tecnologica. L'accordo regolamenta le modalità della futura collaborazione senza tuttavia fissare né i temi né le priorità della ricerca comune. Questi dovranno essere definiti in modo autonomo dalle cerchie interessate del settore pubblico e privato di entrambi i Paesi. Le cooperazioni occasionali tra istituzioni svizzere e giapponesi hanno messo in evidenza un forte interesse a cooperare in diversi rami quali le scienze della vita, la nanotecnologia, le tecnologie dell'informazione e della comunicazione, le scienze ambientali e le scienze umane e sociali.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Ogni Paese dovrà designare le istituzioni che fungeranno da «leading house» e che dovranno coordinare la cooperazione bilaterale e assicurare la partecipazione di tutte le scuole universitarie e istituzioni di ricerca sul piano nazionale.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Le attività scientifiche e tecnologiche saranno finanziate principalmente dalle istituzioni preposte alla promozione della ricerca nei due Paesi (in Svizzera sono il Fondo nazionale svizzero e l'Agenzia per la promozione dell'innovazione) e dalle singole scuole universitarie interessate. Un ruolo attivo sarà inoltre svolto dalle istituzioni del settore dei PF, esplicitamente incaricate dal Consiglio federale nel mandato di prestazioni per il quadriennio 2008-2011 di impegnarsi in favore delle cooperazioni bilaterali internazionali.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Estensione della politica svizzera in materia di scienza e ricerca&lt;br /&gt; &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt; L'accordo con il Giappone rientra nella strategia formulata nel messaggio concernente il promovimento dell'educazione, della ricerca e dell'innovazione negli anni 2008-2011 che prevede di estendere le relazioni della Svizzera nel campo dell'educazione, della ricerca e dell'innovazione anche a Paesi extraeuropei con un elevato sviluppo scientifico e tecnologico. Nel messaggio è stato chiesto un credito di 43 milioni di franchi per finanziare in parte le attività di cooperazione concrete svolte dalle scuole universitarie svizzere.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Oltre al Giappone, il Consiglio federale annovera tra i Paesi prioritari la Cina, l'India, la Russia, la Corea del Sud, il Sudafrica, il Brasile e il Cile. Lo stato di attuazione di questa strategia varia a seconda del Paese prioritario.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Già nel 2003 sono stati conclusi accordi sulla cooperazione scientifica e tecnologica con l'India («leading house»: PF di Losanna) e la Cina («leading house»: PF di Zurigo) sulla base dei quali sono stati avviati e finanziati programmi pilota nelle scienze della vita e nelle tecnologie dell'informazione e della comunicazione. Il bilancio di queste iniziative, che hanno messo in evidenza grandi potenzialità di cooperazione e notevole interesse a collaborazioni con ricercatori svizzeri, è molto positivo. Pertanto nei prossimi anni saranno portate avanti e potenziate.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Ancora quest'anno è prevista la stipulazione di accordi di cooperazione scientifica con la Russia, la Corea del Sud e il Sudafrica («leading house»: Università di Basilea). Inoltre la Segreteria di Stato per l'educazione e la ricerca, subordinata amministrativamente al Dipartimento federale dell'interno, ha avviato primi contatti per definire l'impostazione della futura cooperazione scientifica con il Brasile e il Cile.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Jean-Marc Crevoisier, responsabile della comunicazione del DFI, tel. 079 763 84 10 Claudio Fischer, Segreteria di Stato per l'educazione e la ricerca, capo unità Cooperazione bilaterale nella ricerca, tel. 031 322 96 53</contact>
      <link id="29411">
        <title>Accordo tra il Consiglio federale svizzero e il Governo del Giappone concernente la cooperazione scientifica e tecnologica:</title>
        <uri>http://www.sbf.admin.ch/japan2007.htm</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Federal Councillor Pascal Couchepin signs agreement on scientific and technological cooperation between Switzerland and Japan</title>
      <lead>Federal Councillor Pascal Couchepin and Japanese Foreign Minister Taro Aso signed a bilateral agreement in Tokyo today on future scientific and technological cooperation between Switzerland and Japan. The agreement falls in line with the strategy laid out in the Federal Council’s Message on the Promotion of Education, Research and Innovation for the years 2008-2011 whereby Switzerland’s ties in the field of education and research are to be expanded to include suitable non-European partner countries that are interested in bilateral cooperation.</lead>
      <text link="no">Following recent years of round table discussions on science and technology (S&amp;amp;T), Switzerland and Japan have now entered into a bilateral agreement in this area. While the agreement establishes the terms of future cooperation it does not indicate the priorities or themes that will guide the two countries’ joint research endeavours. These matters will be ironed out in separate discussions within and between the public and private sector in both countries. Along this line, Swiss and Japanese institutions will play an important role. Having worked together on several occasions in the past, these institutions share a strong interest in many different scientific fields, ranging from life sciences, nanotechnologies and information and communication technologies&amp;nbsp; to environmental sciences, humanities and social sciences.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; In each country, various institutions will be chosen to act as Leading Houses, which means that they will be called upon to coordinate bilateral cooperation between the two countries and ensure that all universities and research institutes are involved at the national level. &lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Funding for bilateral S&amp;amp;T activities will come mainly from each country’s existing institutions that are responsible for promoting research. In Switzerland, these include the Swiss National Science Foundation (SNSF), the Innovation Promotion Agency (CTI) and individual participating universities. Switzerland’s two federal institutes of technology (ETH in Zurich and EPFL in Lausanne) as well as their respective research institutes will also play a major role in cooperation with Japan. Their commitment to international bilateral cooperation is explicitly stated in the Federal Council’s performance mandate for 2008-2011.&lt;br /&gt; &amp;nbsp;&lt;br /&gt; &lt;strong&gt;Development of Swiss bilateral scientific and research policies&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; The S&amp;amp;T agreement with Japan falls in line with the bilateral strategy described in the Message on the Promotion of Education, Research and Innovation for the years 2008-2011. Switzerland intends to sign similar agreements on education, research and innovation with suitable non-European partner countries that have made outstanding achievements in scientific and technological fields. Within the framework of the Message, a credit of CHF 43 million has been set aside to help fund specific cooperation activities pursued by Swiss universities.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Alongside Japan, the Federal Council’s list of priority countries also includes China, India, Russia, South Korea, South Africa, Brazil and Chile. Implementation of the strategy is at various stages in each priority country.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Bilateral agreements in the area of S&amp;amp;T were already signed with India (EPF Lausanne as Leading House) and China (ETH Zurich as Leading House) back in 2003. It was on the basis of these agreements that pilot programmes in the fields of life sciences and ICTs could be developed and funded. The outcome of these pilot programmes was very positive: considerable potential for cooperation was observed and there was strong interest expressed to work with Swiss scientists. Cooperation will therefore be developed in the coming years.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; In terms of scientific cooperation with Russia, South Korea and South Africa (University of Basel as Leading House) bilateral agreements should be signed within the year. The FDHA’s State Secretariat for Education and Research is still in the information-gathering phase as far as bilateral scientific cooperation with Brazil and Chile is concerned.</text>
      <contact>Jean-Marc Crevoisier, Head of Communications FDHA, Tel. 079 763 84 10 Claudio Fischer, State Secretariat for Education and Research, Head of Bilateral Research Cooperation Unit, Tel. 031 322 96 53</contact>
      <link id="29412">
        <title>Agreement between the Government of Japan and the Swiss Federal Council on Cooperation in Science and Technology:</title>
        <uri>http://www.sbf.admin.ch/japan2007.htm</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="8">
        <name lang="de">Bildung und Forschung</name>
        <name lang="fr">Formation et recherche</name>
        <name lang="it">Formazione e ricerca</name>
        <name lang="en">Education and Research</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
