<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="69104" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2017-12-06</pubdate>
    <blocking-period>2017-12-06</blocking-period>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="318" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>301</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Bundesamt für Statistik</name>
      <name lang="fr">Office fédéral de la statistique</name>
      <name lang="it">Ufficio federale di statistica</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Statistical Office</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.statistik.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.statistique.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.statistica.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.statistics.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@bfs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@bfs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@bfs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@bfs.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="301">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement des Innern</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'intérieur</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'interno</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Home Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Neuchâtel</city>
      <title>Bundesgesetz über die Unternehmens-Identifikationsnummer (UIDG) - Zulassung des BFS als Schweizer Vergabestelle der LEI</title>
      <lead>(BFS) – Das Bundesamt für Statistik (BFS) ist seit heute berechtigt, den Legal Entity Identifier (LEI), eine eindeutige Identifikationsnummer der Finanzmarktakteure, an Schweizer Unternehmen und Fonds zu vergeben. Die LEI trägt dazu bei, Risiken im Finanzsektor früher zu erkennen und die Finanzstabilität zu fördern, indem sie den Behörden und anderen Akteuren die zuverlässige Identifikation von Vertragspartnern ermöglicht.</lead>
      <text link="no">Diese Medienmitteilung und weitere Informationen zum Thema finden Sie auf der Website des BFS (siehe Link unten)</text>
      <contact>Bertrand Loison, Vizedirektor BFS, +41 58 463 67 70, Bertrand.Loison@bfs.admin.ch Fabio Tomasini, Sektionschef Betriebs- und Unternehmensregister BFS, +41 58 463 64 38, Fabio.Tomasini@bfs.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="173364">
        <title>Kompletter Text und Mediendossier</title>
        <uri>http://www.lei-schweiz.ch/</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Neuchâtel</city>
      <title>Loi fédérale sur le numéro d'identification des entreprises (LIDE) - L'OFS accrédité pour délivrer des identifiants internationaux d’entreprise (LEI) en Suisse</title>
      <lead>(OFS) – L’OFS est dès aujourd’hui habilité à attribuer des identifiants internationaux d'entité juridique (Legal Entity Identifier, LEI) aux entreprises et fonds suisses qui en font la demande. Le LEI contribue à prévenir les risques dans le secteur financier et à promouvoir la stabilité en permettant aux autorités et aux acteurs d'identifier de manière fiable les partenaires contractuels.</lead>
      <text link="no">Vous trouverez ce communiqué de presse et d'autres informations sur ce thème sur le site web de l'OFS (voir le lien ci-dessous)</text>
      <contact>Bertrand Loison, Vice-directeur OFS, +41 58 463 67 70, Bertrand.Loison@bfs.admin.ch Fabio Tomasini, Chef de la section Registre des entreprises et établissements, OFS, +41 58 463 64 38, Fabio.Tomasini@bfs.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="173365">
        <title>Texte intégral et dossier de presse</title>
        <uri>http://www.lei-suisse.ch/</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Neuchâtel</city>
      <title>Legge federale sul numero d’identificazione delle imprese (LIDI) - L’UST accreditata ufficialmente a rilasciare gli identificativi internazionali per le imprese (LEI) in Svizzera</title>
      <lead>(UST) – Da oggi l’UST è abilitata a rilasciare identificativi internazionali di soggetti giuridici (Legal Entity Identifier, LEI) per le imprese e i fondi svizzeri che ne fanno richiesta. Il codice LEI contribuisce a prevenire i rischi nel settore finanziario e a promuovere la stabilità permettendo alle autorità e agli attori di identificare in modo attendibile le parti contraenti.</lead>
      <text link="no">Il presente comunicato stampa e ulteriori informazioni sul tema sono reperibili sulla pagina Internet dell'UST (link sotto)</text>
      <contact>Bertrand Loison, Vicedirettore UST, +41 58 463 67 70, Bertrand.Loison@bfs.admin.ch Fabio Tomasini, capo della Sezione Registro delle imprese e degli stabilimenti, UST, +41 58 463 64 38, Fabio.Tomasini@bfs.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="173366">
        <title>Testo integrale e dossier per i media</title>
        <uri>http://www.lei-svizzera.ch/</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Neuchâtel</city>
      <title>Federal Act on the Business Identification Number (BINA) - The FSO accredited to issue legal entity identifiers (LEI) in Switzerland</title>
      <lead>(FSO) – As of today the FSO has official accreditation to allocate legal entity identifiers (LEI) to Swiss businesses and funds that request one. The LEI contributes to risk prevention in the financial sector and encourages stability by enabling the authorities and interested parties to reliably identify contractual partners.</lead>
      <text link="no">This press release and further information on this topic can be found on the FSO website (see link below)</text>
      <contact>Bertrand Loison, Vice-director, FSO, +41 58 463 67 70, bertrand.Loison@bfs.admin.ch Fabio Tomasini, Head of Business Register section, FSO, 058 463 64 38, fabio.tomasini@bfs.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="173367">
        <title>Complete text and press kit</title>
        <uri>https://www.bfs.admin.ch/bfs/en/home/registers/enterprise-register/lei-legal-entity-identifier.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <keywords>
      <keyword id="317" org-id="318">
        <name lang="de">Statistische Grundlagen und Übersichten (Statistische Grundlagen)</name>
        <name lang="fr">Bases statistiques et produits généraux (Bases statistiques)</name>
        <name lang="it">Basi statistiche e presentazioni generali (Basi statistiche)</name>
        <name lang="en">Statistical basis and overviews (Statistical basis)</name>
      </keyword>
    </keywords>
    <topics>
      <topic id="43">
        <name lang="de">Statistik</name>
        <name lang="fr">Statistiques</name>
        <name lang="it">Statistica</name>
        <name lang="en">Statistics</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
