<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="69354" revoked="no">
    <version>2</version>
    <pubdate>2017-12-21</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="1070" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>1070</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Der Bundesrat</name>
      <name lang="fr">Conseil fédéral</name>
      <name lang="it">Il Consiglio federale</name>
      <name lang="en">The Federal Council</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.admin.ch/gov/de/start.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.admin.ch/gov/fr/accueil.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.admin.ch/gov/it/pagina-iniziale.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.admin.ch/gov/en/start.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="101" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>101</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Bundeskanzlei</name>
      <name lang="fr">Chancellerie fédérale</name>
      <name lang="it">Cancelleria federale</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Chancellery</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.bk.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.bk.admin.ch/index.html?lang=fr</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.bk.admin.ch/index.html?lang=it</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.bk.admin.ch/index.html?lang=en</www>
      <email lang="de">infokomm@admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">infokomm@admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">infokomm@admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">infokomm@admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="1070">
      <name lang="de">Der Bundesrat</name>
      <name lang="fr">Conseil fédéral</name>
      <name lang="it">Il Consiglio federale</name>
      <name lang="en">The Federal Council</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.admin.ch/gov/de/start.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.admin.ch/gov/fr/accueil.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.admin.ch/gov/it/pagina-iniziale.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.admin.ch/gov/en/start.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <department id="101">
      <name lang="de">Bundeskanzlei</name>
      <name lang="fr">Chancellerie fédérale</name>
      <name lang="it">Cancelleria federale</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Chancellery</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.bk.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.bk.admin.ch/index.html?lang=fr</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.bk.admin.ch/index.html?lang=it</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.bk.admin.ch/index.html?lang=en</www>
      <email lang="de">infokomm@admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">infokomm@admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">infokomm@admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">infokomm@admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Erklärung von Bundespräsidentin Doris Leuthard zum Entscheid der EU zur Börsenäquivalenz</title>
      <lead>-</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Der Bundesrat hat sich mehrfach mit der Frage der Börsenäquivalenz befasst. In den letzten Tagen und Wochen hat die Schweiz auf verschiedenen Ebenen interveniert. Sie hat ihre Position insbesondere bei den Mitgliedstaaten, der Kommission und dem Kommissionspräsidenten, deutlich gemacht. Und diese Position ist klar: die Schweiz erfüllt die Bedingungen für die Anerkennung der Börsenäquivalenz, genauso wie die anderen Drittstaaten, die eine unbefristete Anerkennung bekommen haben. Daher betrachten wir die befristete Anerkennung als klare Diskriminierung der Schweiz. Auch die Verbindung dieses technischen Dossiers mit den institutionellen Fragen ist sachfremd und inakzeptabel.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Heute Morgen hat der Bundesrat an einer ausserordentlichen Sitzung seine Haltung zum absehbaren formellen Entscheid festgelegt. Aus Sicht des Bundesrates gibt es Zweifel an der Rechtmässigkeit dieses Entscheides. Der Bundesrat hat auch den Eindruck, dass dieser Entscheid der Europäischen Union zum Ziel hat, den Finanzplatz Schweiz zu schwächen. Er will den diskriminierenden Beschlüssen der EU Massnahmen entgegensetzen, die die Wettbewerbsfähigkeit der Schweiz erhöhen. Er hat deshalb heute beschlossen, den Schweizer Börsen- und Finanzplatz zu stärken und entsprechende Arbeiten sofort aufzunehmen. Das Eidgenössische Finanzdepartement (EFD) wurde beauftragt, dem Bundesrat bis Ende Januar Vorschläge zu unterbreiten. Dabei steht die Abschaffung der Stempelabgabe im Vordergrund. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Der heutige Entscheid der europäischen Union belastet zudem die bilateralen Beziehungen in wichtigen Dossiers. Die zweite Tranche eines Erweiterungsbeitrags an die EU-Oststaaten wurde verschiedentlich genannt. Der Bundesrat behält sich vor, die Arbeiten an der entsprechenden Vernehmlassungsvorlage angesichts dieser Entwicklungen neu zu beurteilen. Der Bundesrat stand immer für die Weiterentwicklung der bilateralen Beziehungen ein. Und er hat das Weiterführen der Verhandlungen für ein institutionelles Abkommen als Ziel für 2018 festgelegt. Er stellt aber auch fest, dass weiterhin grosse Differenzen bestehen. Die Überwindung dieser Differenzen setzt die gegenseitige Bereitschaft voraus, eine sachliche Diskussion in einem vertrauensvollen Klima zu führen. &lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Kontakt: André Simonazzi Bundesratssprecher 058 462 37 03 andre.simonazzi@bk.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Déclaration de la présidente de la Confédération Doris Leuthard sur la décision de l’UE concernant l’équivalence boursière</title>
      <lead>-</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Le Conseil fédéral s’est plusieurs fois penché sur la question de l’équivalence boursière. Ces dernières semaines, la Suisse est intervenue à différents niveaux et a annoncé clairement sa position, notamment aux Etats membres, à la Commission et au président de la Commission : la Suisse remplit les conditions pour la reconnaissance de l’équivalence boursière, au même titre que les autres Etats tiers qui ont obtenu une reconnaissance illimitée. Nous considérons dès lors que la reconnaissance limitée est une discrimination à l’égard de la Suisse. Du reste, il est infondé et inacceptable de lier ce dossier technique à la question institutionnelle.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Ce matin, lors d’une séance extraordinaire, le Conseil fédéral a pris position sur la probable décision formelle. Il doute de la régularité de cette décision et suppose que l’UE procède de la sorte pour affaiblir la place financière suisse. Il veut répondre à cette manœuvre discriminante par des mesures qui renforceront la compétitivité de la Suisse. C’est pourquoi il a décidé aujourd’hui d’entreprendre aussitôt des travaux pour renforcer la place boursière et financière suisse. Le Département fédéral des finances a été chargé de soumettre des propositions au Conseil fédéral d’ici fin janvier. On songe notamment à la suppression du droit de timbre.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;La décision que l’UE a prise aujourd’hui grève en outre les relations bilatérales sur des dossiers importants. La deuxième tranche de la contribution à l’élargissement en faveur des Etats de l’Est a déjà été citée plusieurs fois et le Conseil fédéral n’exclut pas de revoir le projet à mettre en consultation. Le Conseil fédéral a toujours souhaité le renforcement des bilatérales et a fait de la poursuite des négociations en vue d’un accord institutionnel un objectif pour 2018. Il constate toutefois que de nombreuses divergences subsistent. Or, pour éliminer celles-ci, il est nécessaire d’instaurer un climat de confiance dans les discussions.&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Contact: André Simonazzi porte-parole du Conseil fédéral 058 462 37 03 andre.simonazzi@bk.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Dichiarazione della presidente della Confederazione Doris Leuthard in merito alla decisione dell’UE sull’equivalenza delle borse</title>
      <lead>-</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Il Consiglio federale si è occupato a più riprese della questione dell’equivalenza delle borse. Negli ultimi giorni e settimane la Svizzera è intervenuta a più livelli, ribadendo la propria posizione in particolare nei confronti degli Stati membri, della Commissione e del presidente della Commissione. E la sua posizione è chiara: la Svizzera adempie le condizioni per il riconoscimento dell’equivalenza delle borse, esattamente come gli altri Paesi terzi che hanno ricevuto un riconoscimento senza limiti temporali. Pertanto riteniamo che il riconoscimento limitato nel tempo costituisca una chiara discriminazione della Svizzera. Anche il fatto di vincolare questo dossier tecnico alle questioni istituzionali risulta inopportuno e inaccettabile.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;In occasione dell’odierna seduta straordinaria, il Consiglio federale ha definito la sua posizione in merito all’imminente decisione formale dell’Unione europea. Esso ritiene che la legalità di tale decisione sia dubbia e ha pure l’impressione che essa abbia lo scopo di indebolire la piazza finanziaria della Svizzera. Esso intende opporsi alle decisioni discriminatorie relative ai provvedimenti UE, che pregiudicano la competitività della Svizzera. Ha pertanto deciso oggi di rafforzare la piazza finanziaria e borsistica svizzera avviando immediatamente i lavori in tal senso. Il Dipartimento federale delle finanze (DFF) è stato incaricato di sottoporre proposte al Consiglio federale entro la fine di gennaio. In questo contesto sarà prioritaria l’abolizione della tassa di bollo.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;La decisione odierna dell’Unione europea peggiora inoltre le relazioni bilaterali in dossier importanti. La seconda tranche di un contributo all’allargamento a beneficio dei Paesi dell’Europa dell’Est è stata menzionata da più parti. Alla luce di questi sviluppi il Consiglio federale si riserva il diritto di una nuova rivalutazione dei lavori relativi al progetto in merito che sarà sottoposto a consultazione. Il Governo si è sempre fatto garante dello sviluppo delle relazioni bilaterali e si è posto come obiettivo di proseguire nel 2018 i negoziati per un accordo istituzionale. Constata però anche le profonde divergenze che continuano a permanere e per superare le quali occorre la disponibilità reciproca a condurre una discussione oggettiva in un clima di completa fiducia. &lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Contatto: André Simonazzi portavoce del Consiglio federale 058 462 37 03 andre.simonazzi@bk.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Statement by President Doris Leuthard on the EU’s decision regarding stock market equivalence</title>
      <lead>-</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;The Federal Council has addressed the issue of stock market equivalence on a number of occasions. In recent days and weeks, Switzerland has made approaches at various levels. It has made its position clear, in particular to member states, the Commission and the Commission president. That position is that Switzerland fulfils the conditions for recognition of stock market equivalence every bit as much as the other third countries that have been granted indefinite recognition. Switzerland therefore considers this limited recognition to be a clear case of discrimination. The linking of this technical dossier with institutional issues is extraneous and unacceptable.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The Federal Council held an extraordinary meeting this morning in which it defined its position regarding the EU’s expected formal decision. In the Federal Council’s view there is doubt as to the legality of this decision. The Federal Council also has the impression that this decision by the European Union is intended to weaken Switzerland’s financial sector. It will take measures to counter the discriminatory decisions of the EU, which will improve Switzerland’s competitiveness. It has therefore decided to bolster Switzerland’s stock exchange and financial sector, and to that end intends to begin work immediately. The Federal Department of Finance (FDF) has been given the task of submitting proposals to the Federal Council by the end of January. The abolition of stamp duty is one of the key measures being considered.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Today’s decision by the European Union also risks harming bilateral relations on other important dossiers. The second instalment of the enlargement contribution to the EU’s eastern states has been cited as an example. In light of these developments, the Federal Council reserves the right to reconsider work on the relevant consultation paper. The Federal Council has always defended the further development of bilateral relations and has set the continuation of negotiations on an institutional agreement as an objective for 2018. It also recognises that significant differences still exist. A prerequisite for overcoming these differences is the willingness of both parties to hold objective discussions in an atmosphere of trust.&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Contact: André Simonazzi Federal Council spokesperson 058 462 37 03 andre.simonazzi@bk.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="10">
        <name lang="de">Bundesrat</name>
        <name lang="fr">Conseil fédéral</name>
        <name lang="it">Consiglio federale</name>
        <name lang="en">Federal Council</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="33">
        <name lang="de">Bundespräsident/-in</name>
        <name lang="fr">Président/e de la Confédération</name>
        <name lang="it">Presidente della Confederazione</name>
        <name lang="en">President of the Swiss Confederation</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
