<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="102630" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2024-09-30</pubdate>
    <blocking-period>2024-09-30</blocking-period>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="318" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>301</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Bundesamt für Statistik</name>
      <name lang="fr">Office fédéral de la statistique</name>
      <name lang="it">Ufficio federale di statistica</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Statistical Office</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.statistik.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.statistique.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.statistica.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.statistics.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@bfs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@bfs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@bfs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@bfs.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="301">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement des Innern</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'intérieur</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'interno</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Home Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Neuchâtel</city>
      <title>Grosse Lohnunterschiede bei den Kulturschaffenden</title>
      <lead>Die Hälfte der Kulturschaffenden arbeitet Teilzeit, 14% sind mehrfachbeschäftigt und gut ein Viertel sind Selbständige, deutlich mehr als in der Gesamtwirtschaft. In der Schweiz verdienten die Kulturschaffenden im Jahr 2023 im Median 69 600 Franken, bei Teilzeit waren es 45 700 Franken. Der Unterschied zwischen den Geschlechtern ist gross: Eine weibliche Kulturschaffende verdiente bei Vollzeit 78 000 Franken, ihr männlicher Kollege 98 000 Franken. Dies sind einige der neuen Ergebnisse der Statistik der Kulturwirtschaft des Bundesamtes für Statistik (BFS), erstmals mit detaillierten Daten zu den Löhnen.</lead>
      <text link="no">Diese Medienmitteilung und weitere Informationen zum Thema finden Sie auf der Website des BFS (siehe Link unten)</text>
      <contact>Olivier Moeschler, BFS, Sektion Politik, Kultur und Medien, Tel.: +41 58 463 69 67, E-Mail: poku@bfs.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="280100">
        <title>Kompletter Text und Mediendossier</title>
        <uri>https://www.bfs.admin.ch/news/de/2024-0389</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Neuchâtel</city>
      <title>Fortes disparités salariales chez les travailleurs culturels</title>
      <lead>La moitié des travailleurs culturels occupent un emploi à temps partiel, 14% cumulent plusieurs emplois et un bon quart exercent une activité indépendante. C’est nettement plus que dans l’ensemble de l’économie. En Suisse, les travailleurs culturels à temps plein gagnaient un salaire médian de 69 600 francs en 2023 alors que leurs collègues à temps partiel touchaient 45 700 francs. Dans ce domaine, une forte disparité est à noter entre les sexes: pour un temps plein, une femme gagnait 78 000 francs alors qu’un homme 98 000 francs. Ce sont là quelques-uns des récents résultats de la statistique de l’économie culturelle de l’Office fédéral de la statistique (OFS) qui contiennent, pour la première fois, des données détaillées sur les salaires.</lead>
      <text link="no">Vous trouverez ce communiqué de presse et d'autres informations sur ce thème sur le site web de l'OFS (voir le lien ci-dessous)</text>
      <contact>Olivier Moeschler, OFS, section Politique, culture et médias, tél.: +41 58 463 69 67, e-mail: poku@bfs.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="280101">
        <title>Texte intégral et dossier de presse</title>
        <uri>https://www.bfs.admin.ch/news/fr/2024-0389</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Neuchâtel</city>
      <title>Grandi differenze salariali tra gli operatori culturali</title>
      <lead>La metà degli operatori culturali lavora a tempo parziale, il 14% ha più impieghi e oltre un quarto lavora come indipendente, quote significativamente maggiori rispetto all’economia nel suo complesso. In Svizzera, il reddito mediano degli operatori culturali nel 2023 era di 69 600 franchi, mentre per quelli che lavoravano a tempo parziale la mediana era di 45 700 franchi. Si registra una grande differenza tra i sessi: le operatrici culturali a tempo pieno guadagnavano 78 000 franchi, mentre i loro colleghi di sesso maschile 98 000 franchi. Questi sono alcuni dei nuovi risultati della statistica dell’economia culturale elaborata dall’Ufficio federale di statistica (UST), che include per la prima volta dati dettagliati sui salari.</lead>
      <text link="no">Il presente comunicato stampa e ulteriori informazioni sul tema sono reperibili sulla pagina Internet dell'UST (link sotto)</text>
      <contact>Olivier Moeschler, UST, sezione Politica, cultura e media, tel.: +41 58 463 69 67, e-mail: poku@bfs.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="280102">
        <title>Testo integrale e dossier per i media</title>
        <uri>https://www.bfs.admin.ch/news/it/2024-0389</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Neuchâtel</city>
      <title>Wide differences in pay among cultural workers</title>
      <lead>Half of cultural workers work part-time, 14% have more than one job and just over a quarter are self-employed, considerably more than in the overall economy. In Switzerland, cultural workers earned a median wage of CHF 69 600, and for part-time work CHF 45 700 in 2023. There was a large gender pay gap: a female cultural worker earned CHF 78 000 for a full-time job, while her male colleague earned CHF 98 000. These are some of the new results from the Federal Statistical Office's cultural economy statistics, updated today for the first time with detailed information on wages.</lead>
      <text link="no">This press release and further information on this topic can be found on the FSO website (see link below)</text>
      <contact>Olivier Moeschler, FSO, Politics, Culture and Media Section, tel.: +41 58 463 69 67, email: poku@bfs.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="280103">
        <title>Please note that the English version only includes the release's lead</title>
        <uri>https://www.bfs.admin.ch/news/en/2024-0389</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="18">
        <name lang="de">Kultur</name>
        <name lang="fr">Culture</name>
        <name lang="it">Cultura</name>
        <name lang="en">Culture</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="43">
        <name lang="de">Statistik</name>
        <name lang="fr">Statistiques</name>
        <name lang="it">Statistica</name>
        <name lang="en">Statistics</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
