<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="102282" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2024-09-03</pubdate>
    <blocking-period>2024-09-03</blocking-period>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="318" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>301</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Bundesamt für Statistik</name>
      <name lang="fr">Office fédéral de la statistique</name>
      <name lang="it">Ufficio federale di statistica</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Statistical Office</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.statistik.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.statistique.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.statistica.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.statistics.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@bfs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@bfs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@bfs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@bfs.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="301">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement des Innern</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'intérieur</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'interno</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Home Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Neuchâtel</city>
      <title>Immer weniger Personen trinken täglich Alkohol</title>
      <lead>2022 konsumierten 83% der Schweizer Bevölkerung ab 15 Jahren Alkohol. Dieser Anteil ist seit 1992 stabil. Demgegenüber ist der Anteil der Personen, die täglich Alkohol konsumieren, in den vergangenen 30 Jahren von 20% auf 9% zurückgegangen. Während das Rauschtrinken mindestens einmal pro Monat bei jungen Männern zwischen 15 und 24 Jahren am meisten verbreitet ist (31%), ist der tägliche Alkoholkonsum bei Männern ab 65 Jahren am häufigsten anzutreffen (31%). Dies sind einige Ergebnisse aus der neusten Publikation des Bundesamtes für Statistik (BFS) zum Alkoholkonsum.</lead>
      <text link="no">Diese Medienmitteilung und weitere Informationen zum Thema finden Sie auf der Website des BFS (siehe Link unten)</text>
      <contact>Marco Storni, BFS, Sektion Gesundheit der Bevölkerung, Tel.: +41 58 463 65 63, E-Mail: marco.storni@bfs.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="278730">
        <title>Kompletter Text und Mediendossier</title>
        <uri>https://www.bfs.admin.ch/news/de/2024-0167</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Neuchâtel</city>
      <title>Moins de consommateurs quotidiens d’alcool</title>
      <lead>En 2022, 83% de la population suisse de 15 ans et plus buvaient de l’alcool. Cette proportion est restée stable depuis 1992. Par contre, la part des consommateurs quotidiens d’alcool a baissé de 20% à 9% ces 30 dernières années. Les ivresses ponctuelles au moins une fois par mois concernent davantage les jeunes hommes de 15 à 24 ans (31%) et la consommation quotidienne d’alcool plutôt les hommes de 65 ans et plus (31%). Ce sont là quelques résultats de la nouvelle publication de l’Office fédéral de la statistique (OFS) consacrée à la consommation d’alcool.</lead>
      <text link="no">Vous trouverez ce communiqué de presse et d'autres informations sur ce thème sur le site web de l'OFS (voir le lien ci-dessous)</text>
      <contact>Renaud Lieberherr, OFS, Section Santé de la population, tél.: +41 58 463 65 61, e-mail: renaud.lieberherr@bfs.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="278731">
        <title>Texte intégral et dossier de presse</title>
        <uri>https://www.bfs.admin.ch/news/fr/2024-0167</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Neuchâtel</city>
      <title>Diminuisce il numero di persone che consuma giornalmente bevande alcoliche</title>
      <lead>Nel 2022, l’83% della popolazione svizzera dai 15 anni in su consumava alcol. Questa percentuale è rimasta stabile dal 1992, mentre quella di consumatori giornalieri è scesa dal 20 al 9% negli ultimi 30 anni. Il binge drinking almeno una volta al mese è più comune tra i giovani dai 15 ai 24 anni (31%), mentre il consumo giornaliero di alcol è più comune tra gli uomini di età pari o superiore a 65 anni (31%). Questi sono alcuni dei risultati della nuova pubblicazione dell’Ufficio federale di statistica (UST) dedicata al tema del consumo di alcol.</lead>
      <text link="no">Il presente comunicato stampa e ulteriori informazioni sul tema sono reperibili sulla pagina Internet dell'UST (link sotto)</text>
      <contact>Renaud Lieberherr, UST, Sezione Salute della popolazione, tel.: +41 58 463 65 61, e-mail: renaud.lieberherr@bfs.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="278732">
        <title>Testo integrale e dossier per i media</title>
        <uri>https://www.bfs.admin.ch/news/it/2024-0167</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Neuchâtel</city>
      <title>Fewer daily drinkers</title>
      <lead>In 2022, 83% of the Swiss population aged 15 and over drank alcohol. This proportion has remained stable since 1992. However, the share of people using alcohol on a daily basis has fallen from 20% to 9% over the past 30 years. Binge drinking at least once a month concerns mainly young men aged 15 to 24 (31% of this age group) and daily alcohol consumption mostly men aged 65 and over (31%). These are some of the results from the Federal Statistical Office’s (FSO) new publication dedicated to alcohol consumption. </lead>
      <text link="no">This press release and further information on this topic can be found on the FSO website (see link below)</text>
      <contact>Renaud Lieberherr, FSO, Population Health section, tel.: +41 58 463 65 61, email: renaud.lieberherr@bfs.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="278733">
        <title>Please note that the English version only includes the release's lead</title>
        <uri>https://www.bfs.admin.ch/news/en/2024-0167</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <keywords>
      <keyword id="317.15" org-id="318">
        <name lang="de">Gesundheit</name>
        <name lang="fr">Santé</name>
        <name lang="it">Salute</name>
        <name lang="en">Health</name>
      </keyword>
    </keywords>
    <topics>
      <topic id="15">
        <name lang="de">Gesundheit</name>
        <name lang="fr">Santé</name>
        <name lang="it">sanità</name>
        <name lang="en">Health</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="43">
        <name lang="de">Statistik</name>
        <name lang="fr">Statistiques</name>
        <name lang="it">Statistica</name>
        <name lang="en">Statistics</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
