<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="5962" revoked="no">
    <version>4</version>
    <pubdate>2006-07-04</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="815" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>801</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössische Kommunikationskommission ComCom</name>
      <name lang="fr">Commission fédérale de la communication ComCom</name>
      <name lang="it">Commissione federale delle comunicazioni ComCom</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Communications Commission ComCom</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.comcom.admin.ch/</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.comcom.admin.ch/</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.comcom.admin.ch/</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.comcom.admin.ch/</www>
      <email lang="de">comcom@comcom.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">comcom@comcom.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">comcom@comcom.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">comcom@comcom.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="801">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Umwelt, Verkehr, Energie und Kommunikation</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'environnement, des transports, de l'énergie et de la communication</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'ambiente, dei trasporti, dell'energia e delle comunicazioni</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of the Environment, Transport, Energy and Communications</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.uvek.admin.ch/uvek/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.uvek.admin.ch/uvek/fr/home.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.uvek.admin.ch/uvek/it/home.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.uvek.admin.ch/uvek/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-uvek.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-uvek.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-uvek.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-uvek.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>ComCom senkt die Preise für die Portierung von Einzelnummern</title>
      <teaser>Die Eidgenössische Kommunikationskommission (ComCom) senkt im Rahmen eines Interkonnektionsverfahrens für die Jahre 2004 bis 2006 die Preise von Swisscom für die Portierung von Einzelnummern im Festnetz. Die Gesuchstellerin Cablecom kommt für diese Jahre in den Genuss von Preisreduktionen von rund 40% - 60%.</teaser>
      <lead>Die Eidgenössische Kommunikationskommission (ComCom) senkt im Rahmen eines Interkonnektionsverfahrens für die Jahre 2004 bis 2006 die Preise von Swisscom für die Portierung von Einzelnummern im Festnetz. Die Gesuchstellerin Cablecom kommt für diese Jahre in den Genuss von Preisreduktionen von rund 40% - 60%.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Die Cablecom hat im Herbst 2004 bei der ComCom ein Gesuch zur Überprüfung der Gebühren der Swisscom für die Portierung von Telefonnummern zu einem anderen Anbieter eingereicht. Die ComCom hat darauf im Rahmen eines Interkonnektionsverfahrens, die für die Preisbestimmung aus gesetzlicher Sicht relevanten Kosten bestimmt. Basierend auf durch das Bundesamt für Kommunikation (BAKOM) durchgeführten Kostenanalysen kommt die ComCom zum Schluss, dass Swisscom die Preise für die Portierung von Einzelnummern im Festnetz von Fr. 31.--&amp;nbsp; auf&amp;nbsp; Fr. 17.65 für 2004, Fr. 15.15 für 2005 und Fr. 11.90 für 2006 senken muss.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Begründet liegt die Senkung insbesondere darin, dass Swisscom in ihre Preisberechnung Kosten miteinbezogen hatte, welche gemäss den gesetzlichen Vorgaben jede Anbieterin bei der Realisierung des Nummernportierungssystems selber tragen muss. Weiter hat die ComCom die anrechenbaren Lohnkosten auf ein branchenübliches Niveau reduziert.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Das Fernmeldegesetz (FMG) verpflichtet grundsätzlich alle Anbieterinnen von Fernmeldediensten die Nummernportabilität (vgl. Art. 28 Abs. 4 FMG) sicherzustellen. Damit soll gewährleistet werden, dass eine Kundin oder ein Kunde seine Telefonnummer behalten kann, wenn er die Anbieterin wechselt. Strittig waren vorliegend die einmaligen Kosten, welche die den Kunden übernehmende Anbieterin der ihn abgebenden Anbieterin für die Übertragung der Nummer bezahlen muss. Bei der Kostenberechnung kamen die Regeln der Interkonnektion sinngemäss zur Anwendung.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Die Verfügung der ComCom kann von den Parteien beim Bundesgericht angefochten werden.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Christian Bovet, Vizepräsident der ComCom, Sekretariat der ComCom, 031 323 52 90</contact>
      <attachment id="14329">
        <title>Interkonnektion: Verfügung der Bedingungen der Nummernportabilität</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>132</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/3151.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <link id="14334">
        <title>Entscheide der ComCom</title>
        <uri>http://www.comcom.admin.ch/themen/00500/index.html?lang=de</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions>
        <revision date="2006-07-04 11:04" type="R"/>
      </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>La ComCom baisse les prix facturés pour la portabilité des numéros individuels</title>
      <teaser>Dans le cadre d'une procédure d'interconnexion ouverte pour les années 2004 à 2006, la Commission fédérale de la communication (ComCom) baisse les prix facturés par Swisscom pour la portabilité, dans le réseau fixe, des numéros attribués individuellement. Cablecom, le requérant, bénéficie ainsi de réductions de prix de 40 à 60% pour ces années-là.</teaser>
      <lead>Dans le cadre d'une procédure d'interconnexion ouverte pour les années 2004 à 2006, la Commission fédérale de la communication (ComCom) baisse les prix facturés par Swisscom pour la portabilité, dans le réseau fixe, des numéros attribués individuellement. Cablecom, le requérant, bénéficie ainsi de réductions de prix de 40 à 60% pour ces années-là.</lead>
      <text link="no">En automne 2004, Cablecom a déposé auprès de la ComCom une demande d'examen des taxes prélevées par Swisscom pour la portabilité des numéros de téléphone vers un autre fournisseur. Dans le cadre d'une procédure d'interconnexion, la ComCom a déterminé du point de vue légal les coûts relevant de la fixation des prix. Se fondant sur l'analyse des coûts réalisée par l'Office fédéral de la communication (OFCOM), elle a conclu que Swisscom devait réduire les prix facturés pour la portabilité, dans le réseau fixe, des numéros attribués individuellement de 31 fr. à 17 fr. 65 pour 2004, à 15 fr.15 pour 2005 et à 11 fr. 90 pour 2006. &lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; La baisse se justifie notamment par le fait que Swisscom avait intégré dans ses calculs de prix des frais que chaque fournisseur doit, selon les dispositions légales, assumer lui-même pour l'application du système de portabilité des numéros. La ComCom a également diminué les charges salariales imputables, qui sont ramenées dorénavant à un niveau usuel dans la branche. &lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; La loi sur les télécommunications (LTC) contraint tous les fournisseurs de services de télécommunication à assurer la portabilité des numéros (voir art. 28, al. 4, LTC). Lorsqu'il change d'opérateur, le client a la garantie de pouvoir conserver son numéro de téléphone. En l'occurrence, le litige portait sur les frais uniques que le nouvel opérateur doit payer à l'ancien opérateur pour le transfert du numéro. Les règles de l'interconnexion s'appliquent par analogie dans un tel cas.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Les parties peuvent contester la décision de la ComCom devant le Tribunal fédéral.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;</text>
      <contact>Christian Bovet, vice-président de la ComCom, Secrétariat de la ComCom, 031 323 52 90</contact>
      <attachment id="14329">
        <title>Interkonnektion: Verfügung der Bedingungen der Nummernportabilität</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>132</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/3151.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <link id="14335">
        <title>Décisions de la ComCom</title>
        <uri>http://www.comcom.admin.ch/themen/00500/index.html?lang=fr</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions>
        <revision date="2006-07-04 11:04" type="R"/>
      </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>La ComCom abbassa i prezzi per la portabilità dei numeri individuali</title>
      <teaser>Nell'ambito di una procedura d'interconnessione, la Commissione federale delle comunicazioni (ComCom) ha abbassato i prezzi praticati da Swisscom negli anni 2004-2006 per la portabilità dei numeri individuali nella rete fissa. La richiedente Cablecom godrà per questi anni di una riduzione di prezzo del 40-60% circa.</teaser>
      <lead>Nell'ambito di una procedura d'interconnessione, la Commissione federale delle comunicazioni (ComCom) ha abbassato i prezzi praticati da Swisscom negli anni 2004-2006 per la portabilità dei numeri individuali nella rete fissa. La richiedente Cablecom godrà per questi anni di una riduzione di prezzo del 40-60% circa.</lead>
      <text link="no">Nell'autunno del 2004 Cablecom aveva richiesto alla ComCom di verificare le tariffe praticate da Swisscom per la portabilità dei numeri telefonici verso un'altro operatore. Nell'ambito di una procedura d’interconnessione, la ComCom ha in seguito determinato i costi rilevanti dal punto di vista legale per la determinazione dei prezzi. In base all'analisi dei costi svolta dall'Ufficio federale delle comunicazioni (UFCOM), la ComCom è giunta alla conclusione che Swisscom deve abbassare i prezzi per la portabilità dei numeri individuali nella rete fissa da 31.- franchi a 17.65 franchi per il 2004, a 15.15 franchi per il 2005 e a 11.90 franchi per il 2006. &lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; La riduzione è motivata in particolare dal fatto che Swisscom ha incluso nel suo calcolo dei prezzi costi che, conformemente alle disposizioni legali, ogni fornitore deve invece assumere nell'applicazione del sistema di portabilità dei numeri. La ComCom ha inoltre abbassato i costi salariali calcolabili, portandoli al livello usuale del settore. La legge sulle telecomunicazioni (LTC) obbliga fondamentalmente tutti i fornitori di servizi di telecomunicazione a garantire la portabilità dei numeri (cfr. art. 28 cpv. 4 LTC). In questo modo si assicura che il cliente possa conservare il suo numero telefonico anche se cambia operatore. In questo caso la controversia portava sui costi unici, che i nuovi operatori devono pagare al vecchio operatore per il trasferimento del numero del cliente. Sono state inoltre applicate per analogia le regole dell'interconnessione.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; La decisione della ComCom può essere impugnata dalle parti dinanzi al Tribunale federale.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;</text>
      <contact>Prof. Christian Bovet, vicepresidente della ComCom, Segretariato della ComCom, 031 323 52 90</contact>
      <attachment id="14329">
        <title>Interkonnektion: Verfügung der Bedingungen der Nummernportabilität</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>132</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/3151.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <link id="14336">
        <title>Decisioni della ComCom</title>
        <uri>http://www.comcom.admin.ch/themen/00500/index.html?lang=it</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions>
        <revision date="2006-07-04 11:09" type="R"/>
        <revision date="2006-07-04 11:04" type="R"/>
      </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>ComCom drops prices for porting of individual numbers</title>
      <teaser>As part of an interconnection procedure for the years 2004 to 2006, the Federal Communications Commission (ComCom) is reducing Swisscom's prices for porting individual numbers within the fixed network. For these years, the applicant, Cablecom, will benefit from price reductions of about 40-60%.</teaser>
      <lead>As part of an interconnection procedure for the years 2004 to 2006, the Federal Communications Commission (ComCom) is reducing Swisscom's prices for porting individual numbers within the fixed network. For these years, the applicant, Cablecom, will benefit from price reductions of about 40-60%.</lead>
      <text link="no">In autumn 2004, Cablecom submitted an application to ComCom for an examination of Swisscom's charges for porting telephone numbers to a different provider. Within the framework of an interconnection procedure, ComCom then determined the costs which are relevant from the legal point of view for establishing the prices. On the basis of the cost analyses carried out by the Federal Office of Communications (OFCOM), ComCom concludes that Swisscom must reduce the prices for porting individual numbers in the fixed network from CHF 31.00 to CHF 17.65 for 2004, CHF 15.15 for 2005 and CHF 11.90 for 2006. &lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; The reduction is based in particular on the fact that Swisscom included in their price calculation costs which, according to the legal stipulations, must be borne by each provider itself when it implements the number porting system. Furthermore, ComCom has reduced the chargeable wage costs to a level which is customary within the sector. &lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; The Law on Telecommunications (LTC) requires all providers of telecommunications services to ensure number portability (cf. art. 28 para. 4 LTC). This is intended to guarantee that a customer is able to keep his or her telephone number when switching to a different provider. In this case there was a dispute over the one-off costs which the provider acquiring the customer must pay the provider losing the customer for transferring the number. The rules governing interconnection were in this case applied in analogy. &lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; The parties of this interconnection procedure may appeal against ComCom's decision in the Federal Court.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;</text>
      <contact>Prof. Christian Bovet, ComCom Deputy President, ComCom Secretariat, 031 323 52 90</contact>
      <attachment id="14329">
        <title>Interkonnektion: Verfügung der Bedingungen der Nummernportabilität</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>132</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/3151.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <link id="14337">
        <title>ComCom decisions</title>
        <uri>http://www.comcom.admin.ch/themen/00500/index.html?lang=en</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions>
        <revision date="2006-07-04 11:04" type="R"/>
      </revisions>
    </content>
    <offers>
      <offer id="120" org-id="815">
        <name lang="de">Medienmitteilungen</name>
        <name lang="fr">Communiqués de presse</name>
        <name lang="it">Comunicati stampa</name>
        <name lang="en">Press releases</name>
      </offer>
    </offers>
    <keywords>
      <keyword id="630" org-id="815">
        <name lang="de">Kommunikationskommission, Eidg. ComCom</name>
        <name lang="fr">Commission fédérale de la communication ComCom</name>
        <name lang="it">Commissione federale delle comunicazioni ComCom</name>
        <name lang="en">Federal Communications Commission ComCom</name>
      </keyword>
    </keywords>
    <topics>
      <topic id="28">
        <name lang="de">Telekommunikation</name>
        <name lang="fr">Télécommunications</name>
        <name lang="it">Telecomunicazione</name>
        <name lang="en">Telecommunications</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
