<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="8547" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2006-11-27</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="201" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>201</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="201">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Offizielle Arbeitsbesuche von Bundesrätin Micheline Calmy-Rey am 30. November, in Brüssel und Helsinki</title>
      <lead>Bundesrätin Micheline Calmy-Rey, Vorsteherin des Eidgenössischen Departements für auswärtige Angelegenheiten, begibt sich am 30. November 2006, für einen offiziellen Arbeitsbesuch bei Benita Ferrero-Waldner, Kommissarin für Aussenbeziehungen der Europäischen Union, nach Brüssel. Am selben Tag wird sie in Helsinki ihren finnischen Amtskollegen Erkki Tuomioja und damit einen Vertreter der EU-Präsidentschaft treffen, die zur Zeit von Finnland wahrgenommen wird.</lead>
      <text link="no">Dank der Annahme des Bundesgesetzes über die Zusammenarbeit mit den Staaten Osteuropas durch das Schweizer Volk am Sonntag, 26. November 2006, können an den Treffen vom Donnerstag die Umsetzung der Bilateralen sowie europapolitische Themen von gemeinsamem Interesse besprochen werden. Bei den Gesprächen wird es unter anderem um die Frage der Liberalisierung des Strommarkts, ein mögliches Freihandels­abkommen für Landwirtschaftsprodukte mit der Europäischen Union, das Satelliten­navigations­system Galileo sowie ein mögliches Rahmenabkommen für alle bilateralen Abkommen gehen. &amp;nbsp;Bei den aktuellen internationalen Themen werden unter anderem der Menschenrechtsrat und die Situation in Südosteuropa zur Sprache kommen. &amp;nbsp;Das letzte Treffen zwischen Bundesrätin Micheline Calmy-Rey und Frau Benita Ferrero-Waldner fand im September 2005 in Brüssel statt. Ein bilaterales Treffen mit ihrem finnischen Amtskollegen fand 2004 in Bern statt.</text>
      <contact>Presse- und Informationsdienst Bundeshaus West CH-3003 Bern Tel.: (+41) 031 322 31 53 Fax: (+41) 031 324 90 47 / 48</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Visites officielles de travail de la Conseillère fédérale Micheline Calmy-Rey jeudi 30 novembre à Bruxelles et Helsinki</title>
      <lead>La Conseillère fédérale Micheline Calmy-Rey, Cheffe du Département fédéral des affaires étrangères, se rendra jeudi 30 novembre 2006 à Bruxelles pour une visite officielle de travail avec Mme Benita Ferrero-Waldner, Commissaire européenne aux affaires extérieures. Elle rencontrera le même jour la présidence de l'UE assurée par son homologue finlandais, M. Erkki Tuomioja, à Helsinki.</lead>
      <text link="no">Après l'acceptation par le peuple suisse de la loi sur la coopération avec les Etats d'Europe de l'Est dimanche 26 novembre 2006 les deux rencontres de jeudi permettront d'aborder la mise en œuvre des accords bilatéraux ainsi que des sujets d'intérêt commun en matière de politique européenne. Les entretiens porteront notamment sur la question de la libéralisation du marché de l'électricité, sur un éventuel accord de libre-échange sur les produits agricoles avec l'Union européenne, sur le système de navigation par satellite Galileo ainsi que sur un éventuel accord-cadre chapeautant l'ensemble des accords bilatéraux.&amp;nbsp;Parmi les sujets d'actualité internationale figureront le nouveau Conseil des droits de l'homme ainsi que la situation dans les Balkans. &amp;nbsp;La dernière rencontre de la Conseillère fédérale Micheline Calmy-Rey avec Mme Benita Ferrero-Waldner remonte au mois de septembre 2005 à Bruxelles. Une rencontre bilatérale avec son homologue finlandais avait eu lieu à Berne en 2004. &amp;nbsp;</text>
      <contact>Service de presse et d'information Palais fédéral ouest CH-3003 Berne Tél.: (+41) 031 322 31 53 Fax: (+41) 031 324 90 47 / 48</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Visite ufficiali di lavoro della Consigliera federale Micheline Calmy-Rey giovedì 30 novembre a Bruxelles e Helsinki</title>
      <lead>La Consigliera federale Micheline Calmy-Rey, capo del Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri, si recherà giovedì 30 novembre 2006 a Bruxelles per un incontro ufficiale di lavoro con Benita Ferrero-Waldner, Commissaria europea per gli affari esteri. Nello stesso giorno incontrerà a Helsinki il suo omologo finlandese Erkki Tuomioja. La Finlandia assume la direzione della presidenza dell'UE.</lead>
      <text link="no">Dopo l’accettazione da parte del popolo svizzero della legge sulla cooperazione con gli Stati dell’Europa dell’Est domenica 26 novembre 2006, i due incontri di giovedì consentiranno di affrontare l’attuazione degli accordi bilaterali e temi di interesse comune in materia di politica europea. I colloqui verteranno in particolare sulla questione della liberalizzazione del mercato dell’elettricità, sull’eventuale accordo di libero scambio sui prodotti agricoli con l’Unione Europea, sul sistema di navigazione satellitare Galileo e su un eventuale accordo quadro che riunisca tutti gli accordi bilaterali.&amp;nbsp;Tra i temi d’attualità internazionale figureranno il nuovo Consiglio dei diritti dell’uomo e la situazione nei Balcani. &amp;nbsp;L’ultimo incontro della Consigliera federale Micheline Calmy-Rey con Benita Ferrero-Waldner risale al settembre 2005 a Bruxelles. Un incontro bilaterale con il suo omologo finlandese ha avuto luogo a Berna nel 2004.</text>
      <contact>Servizio stampa e informazione Palazzo federale ovest CH-3003 Berna Tel.: (+41) 031 322 31 53 Fax: (+41) 031 324 90 47 / 48</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Official working visits by Federal Councillor Micheline Calmy-Rey to Brussels and Helsinki on Thursday 30 November 2006</title>
      <lead>Federal Councillor Micheline Calmy-Rey, head of the Swiss Federal Department of Foreign Affairs (DFA), will travel to Brussels on Thursday 30 November 2006 for official talks with the European Commissioner in charge of External Relations and European Neighbourhood Policy, Mrs Benita Ferrero-Waldner. Later on in the day, Mrs Calmy-Rey will travel on to Helsinki to meet Mr. Erkki Tuomioja, the Finnish foreign minister of Finland who currently holds the presidency of the European Union.</lead>
      <text link="no">Following the acceptance by the people of Switzerland of the Federal Act on Cooperation with the States of Eastern Europe in the popular vote on Sunday 26 November 2006, the two meetings on Thursday will permit to discuss the implementation of Switzerland’s bilateral agreements with the EU as well as matters of common interest concerning EU policy. The meetings will deal in particular with the question of the liberalisation of the electricity market, with a possible agreement with free trade in agricultural products with the EU, with the satellite navigation system, Galileo, and with a possible framework agreement concering all the bilateral agreements.&amp;nbsp;Current international issues to be discussed will include the new Human Rights Council of the United Nations and the situation in the Balkans. &amp;nbsp;The last meeting between Federal Councillor Calmy-Rey and Mrs Ferrero-Waldner was in September 2005 in Brussels. The last meeting between the Head of the DFA and her Finnish counterpart was in 2004 in Bern.</text>
      <contact>Press and Information Service Bundeshaus West CH-3003 Berne Tel.: (+41) 031 322 31 53 Fax: (+41) 031 324 90 47 / 48</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
