<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="8571" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2006-11-28</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="201" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>201</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="201">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Offizieller Arbeitsbesuch des slowakischen Aussenministers Jan Kubis bei Bundesrätin Micheline Calmy-Rey in Bern am 1. Dezember 2006</title>
      <lead>Bundesrätin Micheline Calmy-Rey, Vorsteherin des Eidgenössischen Departements für auswärtige Angelegenheiten, wird am 1. Dezember 2006 den slowakischen Aussenminister Jan Kubis zu einem offiziellen Arbeitsbesuch in Bern empfangen.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Im Mittelpunkt der Gespräche stehen die bilateralen Beziehungen und die Europäische Integration. Bundesrätin Calmy-Rey wird mit ihren Amtskollegen auch über die Verwendung des Schweizer Beitrags zur Verringerung der wirtschaftlichen und sozialen Ungleichheiten in der erweiterten EU diskutieren, insbesondere über die zukünftige Zusammenarbeit mit der Slowakei nach der Abstimmung über das Osthilfegesetz von vergangenem Sonntag. Schliesslich werden internationale Themen wie die Lage im Westbalkan, die Situation im Nahen und Mittleren Osten und die UNO besprochen. Die Slowakei hält zurzeit einen nicht-ständigen Sitz im UN-Sicherheitsrat.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Die bilateralen Beziehungen zwischen der Schweiz und der Slowakei sind sehr gut und problemfrei. Die Bilateralen Abkommen I und II zwischen der Schweiz und der EU, sowie die EU-Mitgliedschaft der Slowakei bilden ausgezeichnete Voraussetzung für eine weitere Vertiefung der Kooperation zwischen den beiden Ländern. &amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Es ist dies das erste Treffen zwischen Aussenminister Kubis und Bundesrätin Calmy-Rey. Das letzte offizielle Treffen auf Ebene Aussenminister zwischen der Schweiz und der Slowakei fand am 28. November 2005 in Bratislava statt.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Presse- und Informationsdienst Bundeshaus West CH-3003 Bern Tel.: (+41) 031 322 31 53 Fax: (+41) 031 324 90 47 / 48</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Visite officielle de travail de M. Jan Kubis, Ministre slovaque des Affaires étrangères auprès de la Conseillère fédérale Micheline Calmy-Rey à Berne le 1er décembre 2006</title>
      <lead>La Conseillère fédérale Micheline Calmy-Rey, Cheffe du Département fédéral des Affaires étrangères, recevra le 1er décembre 2006 M. Jan Kubis, Ministre slovaque des Affaires étrangères, en visite officielle de travail à Berne.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Leurs discussions seront centrées sur les relations bilatérales et l'intégration européenne. La Conseillère fédérale Micheline Calmy-Rey abordera également avec son homologue l'utilisation de la contribution de la Suisse à la réduction des disparités économiques et sociales dans l'Union européenne élargie, et notamment la coopération future avec la Slovaquie après la votation de dimanche dernier sur la loi sur la coopération avec les pays d’Europe de l'Est. Seront évoqués en outre des sujets internationaux, comme la situation dans les Balkans occidentaux, au Proche-Orient et au Moyen-Orient ainsi que l'ONU. La Slovaquie occupe actuellement un siège non permanent au Conseil de sécurité des Nations unies.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Les relations bilatérales entre la Suisse et la Slovaquie sont très bonnes et sans problème. Les accords bilatéraux I et II entre la Suisse et l'UE, de même que l'adhésion de la Slovaquie à l'Union, réunissent des conditions tout à fait propices à l'approfondissement de la coopération entre les deux pays.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Ce sera la première rencontre entre la Conseillère fédérale Micheline Calmy-Rey et le Ministre des Affaires étrangères Jan Kubis. La dernière rencontre officielle entre ministres des Affaires étrangères suisse et slovaque a eu lieu le 28&amp;nbsp;novembre&amp;nbsp;2005 à Bratislava.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Service de presse et d'information Palais fédéral ouest CH-3003 Berne Tél.: (+41) 031 322 31 53 Fax: (+41) 031 324 90 47 / 48</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Visita di lavoro ufficiale il 1° dicembre 2006 a Berna del Ministro degli affari esteri slovacco Jan Kubis alla Consigliera federale Micheline Calmy-Rey, Capo del Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</title>
      <lead>Il 1° dicembre 2006 la Consigliera federale Micheline Calmy-Rey, Capo del Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri, riceverà a Berna, in visita di lavoro ufficiale, il Ministro degli affari esteri slovacco Jan Kubis.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;I colloqui verteranno sulle relazioni bilaterali e sull’integrazione&amp;nbsp; europea. La Consigliera federale Micheline Calmy-Rey discuterà con il suo omologo anche dell’utilizzo del contributo svizzero all’attenuazione delle disparità economiche e sociali nell’UE allargata, in particolare della futura collaborazione con la Slovacchia dopo la votazione sulla legge sulla cooperazione con l’Europa dell’Est di domenica scorsa. Per finire verranno discussi temi internazionali quali la situazione nei Balcani occidentali, quella nel Vicino e Medio Oriente e l’ONU. Attualmente la Slovacchia occupa un seggio non permanente nel Consiglio di sicurezza dell’ONU.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Le relazioni bilaterali tra la Svizzera e la Slovacchia sono molto buone e senza problemi. Gli Accordi Bilaterali I e II tra la Svizzera e l’UE e l’adesione all’UE della Slovacchia costituiscono premesse eccellenti per un ulteriore approfondimento della cooperazione tra i due Paesi. &amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;È il primo incontro tra il Ministro degli affari esteri Jan Kubis e la Consigliera federale Micheline Calmy-Rey. L’ultimo incontro ufficiale a livello di ministri degli affari esteri tra la Svizzera e la Slovacchia si è svolto a Bratislava il 28 novembre 2005.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Servizio stampa e informazione Palazzo federale ovest CH-3003 Berna Tel.: (+41) 031 322 31 53 Fax: (+41) 031 324 90 47 / 48</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Official working visit by the Slovakian Foreign Minister Jan Kubis with Federal Councillor Micheline Calmy-Rey in Bern on 1 December 2006</title>
      <lead>Federal Councillor Micheline Calmy-Rey, head of the Swiss Federal Department of Foreign Affairs, will receive the Slovakian Foreign Minister, Jan Kubis, for an official working visit in Bern on 1 December 2006.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;The talks will primarily deal with bilateral relations and European integration. Federal Councillor Calmy-Rey will also discuss with her Slovakian counterpart ways to use Switzerland’s contribution to the reduction of economic and social disparities within the enlarged European Union, and in particular future cooperation between the two countries following the acceptance of the Federal Act on Cooperation with the States of Eastern Europe in a popular vote in Switzerland last Sunday. In addition, they will discuss international issues such as the situation in the Western Balkans, the Near and Middle East, and the UN. Slovakia currently occupies a non-permanent seat on the United Nations Security Council.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Relations between Switzerland and Slovakia are very good and without problems. Bilateral agreements I and II between Switzerland and the EU and Slovakia’s membership of the EU form an excellent basis to further deepen the cooperation between the two countries. &amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;This is the first meeting between the Slovakian Foreign Minister, Jan Kubis, and Federal Councillor Calmy-Rey. The last official meeting at ministerial level between Switzerland and Slovakia took place in Bratislava on 28 November 2005.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Press and Information Service Bundeshaus West CH-3003 Berne Tel.: (+41) 031 322 31 53 Fax: (+41) 031 324 90 47 / 48</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="34">
        <name lang="de">Europa</name>
        <name lang="fr">Europe</name>
        <name lang="it">Europa</name>
        <name lang="en">Europe</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
