<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="21263" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2008-09-09</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="324" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>301</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Swissmedic, Schweizerisches Heilmittelinstitut</name>
      <name lang="fr">Swissmedic, Institut suisse des produits thérapeutiques</name>
      <name lang="it">Swissmedic, Istituto svizzero per gli agenti terapeutici</name>
      <name lang="en">Swiss Agency for Therapeutic Products</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.swissmedic.ch/</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.swissmedic.ch/?lang=3</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.swissmedic.ch/?lang=4</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.swissmedic.ch/?lang=2</www>
      <email lang="de"/>
      <email lang="fr"/>
      <email lang="it"/>
      <email lang="en"/>
    </originator>
    <department id="301">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement des Innern</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'intérieur</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'interno</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Home Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Weltweite Tagung von Experten der Arzneimittelbehörden und der WHO in Bern</title>
      <lead>Die Zusammenarbeit und die Rolle von Arzneimittelbehörden beim weltweiten Zugang zu Medikamenten, die Harmonisierung der technischen Anforderungen an die Medikamentenzulassung, die Herausforderungen bei der Entwicklung von neuen Arzneimitteln und Massnahmen gegen Fälschungen sind Hauptthemen der 13. International Conference of Drug Regulatory Authorities (ICDRA) vom 16. bis 19. September in Bern.</lead>
      <text link="no">Zu den Workshops und Diskussionsforen werden in Bern Experten der Arzneimittelbehörden aller WHO-Mitgliedsländer erwartet. Die internationale Tagung, die von der Weltgesundheitsorganisation WHO in diesem Jahr in Zusammenarbeit mit Swissmedic, dem Schweizerischen Heilmittelinstitut, durchgeführt wird, findet alle zwei Jahre in einem anderen WHO-Mitgliedsstaat statt. &amp;nbsp;An der Konferenz selbst nehmen ausschliesslich Behördenvertreter teil. Auf einer &lt;b&gt;Pressekonferenz am Freitag, 19. September, 12.30h&lt;/b&gt; werden verantwortliche Vertreter der WHO und der Zulassungsbehörden aus Singapur, Südafrika und der Schweiz zu den Ergebnissen der Konferenz Stellung nehmen.&amp;nbsp;&lt;b&gt;“Better Medicines for Children – the Way Forward”&lt;/b&gt; ist das Thema einer zweitägigen Pre-Conference vom 14. bis 15. September in Bern. Hierfür kommen Vertreter von Organisationen der UN, von Regierungsbehörden, der Pharmaindustrie und von Nichtregierungsorganisationen aus Industriestaaten und so genannten Entwicklungsländern zusammen, um „neue Wege“ bei der Bekämpfung von Krankheiten und Kindersterblichkeit in aller Welt zu identifizieren. Hauptthemen sind ethische Herausforderungen bei klinischen Versuchen mit Kindern, Sicherheit von Arzneimitteln für Kinder, Medikamente für Neugeborene, spezielle Arzneiformen und Zugang zu klinischer Forschung. Diese Konferenz ist Teil der Arbeit der WHO im Zusammenhang mit der im Dezember 2007 gestarteten Initiative &lt;b&gt;„Make medicines child size“&lt;/b&gt; für bessere und sicherere Arzneimittel für Kinder.&amp;nbsp;Über die Ergebnisse der Tagung werden Pädiatrieexperten der Europäischen Arzneimittelzulassungsbehörde (EMEA), der US-amerikanischen Food und Drug Administration (FDA), der International Alliance for Better Medicines for Children, der International Federation of Pharmaceutical Manufacturers and Associations (IFPMA), des South Asian Chapter of American College of Clinical Pharmacy, der Swissmedic und der WHO auf einer &lt;b&gt;Pressekonferenz am Montag, 15. September, 12.30h&lt;/b&gt; die Medien informieren.</text>
      <contact>Ort der Pressekonferenz: Kursaal Allegro, Bern Weitere Informationen: www.icdra.ch Anmeldung zu den Pressekonferenzen: Joachim Gross. Leiter Medienstelle Swissmedic, joachim.gross@swissmedic.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Conférence internationale d’experts des autorités de réglementation des médicaments et de l’OMS à Berne</title>
      <lead>La collaboration et le rôle des autorités de réglementation des médicaments en matière d’accès aux médicaments dans le monde entier, l’harmonisation des exigences techniques posées à l’autorisation de mise sur le marché de médicaments, les défis à relever dans le développement de nouveaux médicaments et les mesures à prendre contre les contrefaçons sont les principaux thèmes de la 13ème Conférence internationale des organismes de réglementation pharmaceutique (ICDRA), qui se tiendra du 16 au 19 septembre 2008 à Berne.</lead>
      <text link="no">Des experts représentant les autorités qui assurent le contrôle des médicaments dans tous les Etats membres de l’Organisation mondiale de la santé (OMS) participeront aux ateliers de travail et aux forums de discussion. Cette manifestation internationale, organisée cette année par l’OMS en collaboration avec Swissmedic, Institut suisse des produits thérapeutiques, a lieu tous les deux ans dans un autre Etat membre de l’OMS. &amp;nbsp;La conférence proprement dite est destinée uniquement aux représentants d’autorités. &lt;b&gt;Une conférence de presse sera organisée le vendredi 19 septembre, à 12h30&lt;/b&gt;, lors de laquelle des responsables de l’OMS et des autorités de contrôle des médicaments d’Afrique du Sud, de Singapour et de Suisse dresseront le bilan de la conférence.&lt;b&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;b&gt;«&amp;nbsp;Better Medicines for Children – the Way Forward&amp;nbsp;»&lt;/b&gt;, tel est le thème de la pré-conférence qui se déroulera les 14 et 15 septembre à Berne. Elle réunira des représentants d’organismes des Nations unies, d’autorités gouvernementales, de l’industrie pharmaceutique et d’organisations non gouvernementales de pays industrialisés comme de pays dits en développement dans le but d’identifier de nouveaux moyens de lutte contre les maladies et la mortalité infantile dans le monde. Les débats porteront principalement sur les problèmes éthiques soulevés par les essais cliniques sur les enfants, la sécurité des médicaments pédiatriques, les médicaments pour nouveau-nés, les formes pharmaceutiques spéciales et l’accès à la recherche clinique. Cette pré-conférence s’inscrit dans les tâches de l’OMS liées à l’initiative &lt;b&gt;«&amp;nbsp;Make medicines child size&amp;nbsp;»&lt;/b&gt; lancée en décembre 2007 et qui vise à améliorer la qualité et la sécurité des médicaments pédiatriques.&amp;nbsp;Les résultats de la pré-conférence seront communiqués aux médias lors de la &lt;b&gt;conférence de presse du lundi 15 septembre à 12h30&lt;/b&gt; par des experts en pédiatrie de l’Agence européenne des médicaments (EMEA), de la Food und Drug Administration (FDA) américaine, de l’International Federation of Pharmaceutical Manufacturers and Associations (IFPMA), du South Asian Chapter of American College of Clinical Pharmacy, de Swissmedic et de l’OMS.</text>
      <contact>Lieu de la conférence de presse: Kursaal Allegro, Berne Pour de plus amples informations : www.icdra.ch Inscription aux conférences de presse : Joachim Gross, responsable Relations médias Swissmedic, joachim.gross@swissmedic.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Regulatory experts on medicinal products from around the world meet with the World Health Organization (WHO) in Berne</title>
      <lead>Regulators' cooperation and role in worldwide access to medicine, harmonization of technical requirements for their approval, combating counterfeit drugs, and addressing the challenges involved in developing new medicinal products are among main topics at the 13th International Conference of Drug Regulatory Authorities (ICDRA), to be held from 16-19 September in Berne.</lead>
      <text link="no">Experts from drug regulatory authorities in all Member States of the World Health Organization (WHO) are expected to attend the workshops and discussion forums in Berne. The international conference, organised by WHO in collaboration with host Swissmedic, the Swiss Agency for Therapeutic Products, is held every two years in a different WHO Member State. &amp;nbsp;While the conference is open only to regulatory authorities, senior representatives of WHO and drug regulatory authorities from Singapore, South Africa and Switzerland will speak on the results of the meeting at a &lt;b&gt;press conference&lt;/b&gt; on &lt;b&gt;Friday, 19 September&lt;/b&gt; at &lt;b&gt;12.30 p.m.&lt;/b&gt;.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;b&gt;“Better Medicines for Children – the Way Forward”&lt;/b&gt; is the subject of a two-day Pre-Conference, from 14-15 September in Berne. The Pre-Conference brings together UN partners, governments, industry, civil society and academics from developed and developing countries to identify "The way forward" in ensuring that the medicines needed to reduce child mortality and suffering be developed and made available to children all over the world. Topics being discussed include: ethical challenges of clinical trials in children, safety of paediatric medicines, off-label use of medicines in neonates, dosage forms, and access to research.&amp;nbsp; This meeting is part of the work of WHO in relation to the initiative &lt;b&gt;make medicines child size&lt;/b&gt; launched in December 2007, to increase children's access to safe and effective medicines. &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;Experts in paediatrics from the European Medicines Agency (EMEA), US Food and Drug Administration (FDA), International Alliance for Better Medicines for Children, International Federation of Pharmaceutical Manufacturers &amp;amp; Associations (IFPMA), South Asian Chapter of American College of Clinical Pharmacy, Swissmedic and WHO will provide information on the outcomes of the event to the media at a &lt;b&gt;press conference&lt;/b&gt; on &lt;b&gt;Monday, 15 September&lt;/b&gt; at &lt;b&gt;12.30 p.m.&lt;/b&gt;.</text>
      <contact>Where: Kursaal Allegro Berne, Switzerland For further information: www.icdra.ch Registration for the press conferences: Joachim Gross, Head of Media Relations, Swissmedic: joachim.gross@swissmedic.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
  </message>
</messages>
