<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="60381" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2016-01-20</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="323" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>701</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidg. Materialprüfungs- und Forschungsanstalt</name>
      <name lang="fr">Laboratoire fédéral d'essai des matériaux et de recherche</name>
      <name lang="it">Laboratorio federale di prova dei materiali e di ricerca</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Laboratory for Materials Testing and Research</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.empa.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.empa.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.empa.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.empa.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">contact@empa.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">contact@empa.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">contact@empa.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">contact@empa.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="701">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Wirtschaft, Bildung und Forschung</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'économie, de la formation et de la recherche</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'economia, della formazione e della ricerca</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Economic Affairs, Education and Research</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Dübendorf, St. Gallen und Thun</city>
      <title>Additive Manufacturing – ein Beitrag der Empa zur «Industrie 4.0»</title>
      <lead>Eines der Hauptthemen am derzeitigen World Economic Forum (WEF) in Davos ist die «Umwandlung der Industrie durch Digitalisierung». Die nächste industrielle Revolution steht also vor der Tür: Sie nennt sich «Industrie 4.0» und soll die Produktionsmethoden in den Industrieländern tiefgreifend verändern. «Industrie 4.0» wird nach Einschätzung von Experten die Verschmelzung von virtuellen Daten mit realen Produktionsmaschinen sein. In einer so entstehenden «intelligenten Fabrik» rücken Kunde und Lieferant näher zusammen: Produktionsaufträge werden vom Kunden direkt an die Maschine geschickt, die Produktionsdaten in Echtzeit an den Vertriebspartner übermittelt. Die Produktion wird schlanker und schneller.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Additive Manufacturing – 3-D-Druck in Metall&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Ein wesentlicher Baustein zur Verwirklichung von «Industrie 4.0» sind Maschinen, die Bauteile schneller, flexibler und präziser fertigen können als bisher. Weniger Prototypenbau, weniger Gusswerkzeuge, weniger Nachbearbeitung. Aus Daten müssen in Zukunft schneller Bauteile und Produkte werden. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Eine Vorstellung von dieser Art Produktion liefern 3-D-Drucker. Die ersten dieser Apparate wurden in den 1980er-Jahren erfunden; heute gibt es bereits Hobbygeräte für unter 700 Franken zu kaufen. Doch bislang produzierten 3-D-Drucker meist Objekte aus Kunststoff. Entsprechend begrenzt sind die mechanischen Eigenschaften und die Temperaturstabilität dieser Objekte, weshalb sie überwiegend zu Anschauungszwecken, also als Modelle verwendet werden. Deshalb wird der 3-D-Druck oft mit dem Synonym «Rapid Prototyping» umschrieben.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Für die nächste industrielle Revolution muss die Technik des 3-D-Drucks einen Schritt weiter gehen: vom Rapid Prototyping zum «Advanced Manufacturing», dem Herstellen von dauerhaften, funktionellen Bauteilen mit definierten mechanischen und thermischen Eigenschaften: Produkte aus Metallen oder Keramiken. &lt;/p&gt;Die Empa arbeitet mit drei Forschungsgruppen an diesem Thema. Eine Gruppe untersucht die optimierte Anwendung von Lasern; eine erforscht neuartige Legierungen, die mit dieser Technologie erstmals greifbar werden. Eine weitere Abteilung nutzt Additive Manufacturing zum Bau neuer geometrischer Formen, die mit herkömmlichen Herstellungsmethoden bisher nicht möglich waren. </text>
      <contact>Dr. Pierangelo Gröning, Dept. Advanced Materials and Surfaces / Direktionsmitglied, Tel. +41 58 765 40 04, pierangelo.groening@empa.ch Dr. Christian Leinenbach, Advanced Materials Processing, Tel. +41 58 765 45 18, christian.leinenbach@empa.ch Prof. Dr. Patrik Hoffmann, Advanced Materials Processing, Tel. +41 58 765 62 62, patrik.hoffmann@empa.ch</contact>
      <attachment id="146873">
        <title>Laser-gedruckte Probekörper aus Titanaluminid</title>
        <format>jpg</format>
        <size-kb>9946</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/42643.jpg</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="146874">
        <title>Infografik Additive Manufacturing (c) Empa</title>
        <format>jpg</format>
        <size-kb>7086</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/42644.jpg</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <link id="146876">
        <title>Homepage Empa</title>
        <uri>http://www.empa.ch/web/s604/wef-industry-4.0</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Dübendorf, St. Gallen und Thun</city>
      <title>Additive Manufacturing – Empa’s part of Industry 4.0</title>
      <lead>At the World Economic Forum (WEF) in Davos a key topic is focusing on “The Digital Transformation of Industries”. The fourth industrial revolution is imminent. It goes by the name “Industry 4.0” and is expected to fundamentally change, among other things, the production methods and business models currently used in industrialized countries. Experts estimate that Industry 4.0 will result in virtual data merging with real production equipment. The resulting “smart factory” will bring customers and suppliers closer together, as production orders will be sent by the customer directly to the machine, and the production data will be transferred to the distribution partner in real time. Manufacturing will become leaner and faster and respond to customers’ needs.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Additive Manufacturing – 3D printing in metal&lt;/b&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;A key component in making Industry 4.0 a reality are machines that can produce the desired components faster, more flexibly and more precisely than ever before. Less prototype construction, fewer dies, less post-processing. In future it will have to be possible to turn data into components and products at an incredible speed.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;3D printers give a sneak preview of what this type of production might look like. The first of these devices were created in the 1980s, and nowadays you can buy entry-level devices for less than 700 Swiss francs. But so far, 3D printers have generally been used to make objects from plastic. The mechanical properties and the temperature stability of these objects are pretty limited as a result, which is why they are mainly used for illustrative purposes, i.e. as visual models. This is why 3D printing is often described as “rapid prototyping”.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;For the fourth industrial revolution, the technique used for 3D printing will have to go one step further: from rapid prototyping to Advanced Manufacturing, the production of lasting and functional components with defined mechanical and thermal properties: products made from metals or ceramics.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Empa, the Swiss Federal Laboratories for Materials Science and Technology, is working on this topic with various research groups. One group is examining the optimized use of lasers, while another is researching new types of alloys that this technology makes feasible for the first time. A further lab is using Additive Manufacturing to build new, geometric forms that were not possible up to now with the traditional production methods available.&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Dr. Pierangelo Gröning, Dept. Advanced Materials and Surfaces / Direktionsmitglied, Tel. +41 58 765 40 04, pierangelo.groening@empa.ch Dr. Christian Leinenbach, Advanced Materials Processing, Tel. +41 58 765 45 18, christian.leinenbach@empa.ch Prof. Dr. Patrik Hoffmann, Advanced Materials Processing, Tel. +41 58 765 62 62, patrik.hoffmann@empa.ch</contact>
      <attachment id="146875">
        <title>Info graphics Additive Manufacturing (c) Empa</title>
        <format>jpg</format>
        <size-kb>2923</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/42645.jpg</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <link id="146877">
        <title>http://www.empa.ch/web/s604/wef-industry-4.0</title>
        <uri>http://www.empa.ch/web/s604/wef-industry-4.0</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="8">
        <name lang="de">Bildung und Forschung</name>
        <name lang="fr">Formation et recherche</name>
        <name lang="it">Formazione e ricerca</name>
        <name lang="en">Education and Research</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
