<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="70568" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2018-04-25</pubdate>
    <blocking-period>2018-04-25</blocking-period>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="1070" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>1070</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Der Bundesrat</name>
      <name lang="fr">Conseil fédéral</name>
      <name lang="it">Il Consiglio federale</name>
      <name lang="en">The Federal Council</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.admin.ch/gov/de/start.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.admin.ch/gov/fr/accueil.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.admin.ch/gov/it/pagina-iniziale.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.admin.ch/gov/en/start.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="201" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>201</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="601" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>601</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Finanzdepartement</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des finances</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale delle finanze</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Finance</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.efd.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.dff.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.efd.admin.ch/efd/it/home.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.efd.admin.ch/efd/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="401" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>401</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Justiz- und Polizeidepartement</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de justice et police</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale di giustizia e polizia</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Justice and Police</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.ejpd.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.ejpd.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.ejpd.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.ejpd.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-ejpd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">Info@gs-ejpd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-ejpd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-ejpd.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="701" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>701</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Wirtschaft, Bildung und Forschung</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'économie, de la formation et de la recherche</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'economia, della formazione e della ricerca</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Economic Affairs, Education and Research</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="1070">
      <name lang="de">Der Bundesrat</name>
      <name lang="fr">Conseil fédéral</name>
      <name lang="it">Il Consiglio federale</name>
      <name lang="en">The Federal Council</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.admin.ch/gov/de/start.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.admin.ch/gov/fr/accueil.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.admin.ch/gov/it/pagina-iniziale.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.admin.ch/gov/en/start.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <department id="201">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <department id="601">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Finanzdepartement</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des finances</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale delle finanze</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Finance</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.efd.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.dff.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.efd.admin.ch/efd/it/home.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.efd.admin.ch/efd/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <department id="401">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Justiz- und Polizeidepartement</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de justice et police</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale di giustizia e polizia</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Justice and Police</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.ejpd.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.ejpd.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.ejpd.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.ejpd.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-ejpd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">Info@gs-ejpd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-ejpd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-ejpd.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <department id="701">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Wirtschaft, Bildung und Forschung</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'économie, de la formation et de la recherche</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'economia, della formazione e della ricerca</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Economic Affairs, Education and Research</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Bundesrat empfängt den deutschen Bundespräsidenten Frank-Walter Steinmeier</title>
      <lead>Der Bundesrat unter Leitung von Bundespräsident Alain Berset hat den deutschen Bundespräsidenten Frank-Walter Steinmeier und dessen Gattin Elke Büdenbender am Mittwoch, 25. April 2018, zum Staatsbesuch in der Schweiz empfangen. Im Zentrum der offiziellen Gespräche standen die bilateralen Beziehungen, die Europapolitik sowie die Zusammenarbeit der beiden Länder im internationalen Kontext. Beide Seiten betonten die Vorteile, die aus der intensiven Zusammenarbeit erwachsen.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;In seiner Rede zum Empfang in Bern sagte Bundespräsident Berset, dass die Schweiz und Deutschland eine Wertegemeinschaft bildeten. Er betonte zudem, die enge kulturelle, gesellschaftliche und wirtschaftliche Verflechtung mit ihren Nachbarn sei eine unverzichtbare Bedingung für eine erfolgreiche Schweiz. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Neben dem Bundespräsidenten nahmen seitens der Schweiz der Vize-Präsident des Bundesrates Ueli Maurer, Bundesrätin Simonetta Sommaruga, Bundesrat Johann N. Schneider-Ammann und Bundesrat Ignazio Cassis an den Gesprächen im Bernerhof teil.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Beide Seiten würdigten die ausgezeichneten bilateralen Beziehungen, die enge Zusammenarbeit bei Bildung, Forschung und Innovation sowie den Umstand, dass der erfolgreiche wirtschaftliche Austausch 2017 ein Handelsvolumen von rund 100 Milliarden Franken erreichte.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Im Verkehrsbereich funktioniert die Zusammenarbeit ebenfalls gut. Deutschland hat die Investitionen in die Verkehrsinfrastruktur in den vergangenen Jahren stark erhöht. Wichtig seien auch verlässliche, gute Rahmenbedingungen für den Flughafen Zürich, erklärte die Schweizer Delegation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mit Blick auf die Beziehungen der Schweiz zur Europäischen Union (EU) kam das derzeit günstige Zeitfenster für Fortschritte in den institutionellen Verhandlungen zur Sprache. Die Delegation des Bundesrates informierte über die Entwicklungen in diesem Dossier und unterstrich zugleich die Bedeutung des bilateralen Wegs für die Schweiz.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Beim Themenkreis Migration erklärten sich die Schweiz und Deutschland einig, dass eine europaweit koordinierte Antwort auf die Migrationsbewegungen erforderlich sei. Die Delegationen tauschten sich des Weiteren aus über internationale Themen wie die Lage auf der koreanischen Halbinsel und im Iran. Beide Seiten unterstrichen die Bedeutung des 2015 erzielten Atom-Abkommens mit Iran.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Zweiter Tag in Freiburg und Zürich&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Am Abend des ersten Tages findet das Gala-Dinner in Bern statt. Das Besuchsprogramm des zweiten Tages, 26. April, ist Fragen der Demokratie und der Nachhaltigkeit gewidmet. In Freiburg werden Bundespräsident Berset und Bundespräsident Steinmeier an einer Podiumsdiskussion zu den Perspektiven der Demokratie im 21. Jahrhundert teilnehmen.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Anschliessend besichtigen sie gemeinsam mit Bundesrätin Doris Leuthard, Vorsteherin des Eidgenössischen Departements für Umwelt, Verkehr, Energie und Kommunikation (UVEK), das an Schweizer Hochschulen entwickelte Solarhaus „NeighborHub". Am Nachmittag wird Bundespräsident Berset den Staatsgast nach Zürich begleiten und ihn dort verabschieden.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>André Simonazzi Bundesratssprecher +41 (0)79 597 64 49 Information EDI +41 (0)58 462 85 79 media@gs-edi.admin.ch Information EFD +41 (0)58 462 60 33 info@gs-efd.admin.ch Information EJPD +41 (0)58 462 18 18 info@gs-ejpd.admin.ch Information WBF +41 (0)58 462 20 07 info@wbf.admin.ch Information EDA +41 (0)58 462 31 53 info@eda.admin.ch Logistik und Organisation: Information EDA +41 (0)58 462 31 53 info@eda.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="177240">
        <title>Staatsbesuch des deutschen Bundespräsidenten Frank-Walter Steinmeier</title>
        <uri>https://www.edi.admin.ch/edi/de/home/dokumentation/anlaesse/Staatsbesuch-Deutschland.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="177244">
        <title>Bilaterale Beziehungen Schweiz–Deutschland</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/countries/germany/de/home/bilaterale-beziehungen/in-kuerze.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Le Conseil fédéral reçoit le président de la République fédérale d’Allemagne Frank-Walter Steinmeier</title>
      <lead>Emmené par le président de la Confédération Alain Berset, le Conseil fédéral a reçu, pour une visite d’État en Suisse, le président de la République fédérale d’Allemagne Frank-Walter Steinmeier et son épouse Elke Büdenbender le mercredi 25 avril 2018. Les discussions officielles ont essentiellement porté sur les relations bilatérales, la politique européenne et la coopération des deux pays dans le contexte international. Les deux parties ont salué les avantages qu’apporte cette intense coopération.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Dans son allocution de bienvenue à Berne, le président de la Confédération Alain Berset a déclaré que la Suisse et l'Allemagne formaient une communauté de valeurs. Il a en outre souligné que, sans les liens étroits qui l'unissent à ses voisins sur les plans culturel, sociétal et économique, la Suisse ne serait pas ce qu'elle est.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Côté suisse, outre M. Berset, ont participé aux discussions au Bernerhof le vice-président du Conseil fédéral Ueli Maurer, la conseillère fédérale Simonetta Sommaruga ainsi que les conseillers fédéraux Johann N. Schneider-Ammann et Ignazio Cassis.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Les deux parties ont salué les excellentes relations bilatérales, l'étroite coopération en matière de formation, de recherche et d'innovation ainsi que le volume des échanges germano-suisse, qui a atteint quelque 100 milliards de francs en 2017.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Dans le domaine des transports également, la coopération fonctionne bien. L'Allemagne a fortement accru ces dernières années les investissements dans l'infrastructure de transport. La délégation suisse a relevé l'importance, pour l'aéroport de Zurich, de pouvoir évoluer dans un contexte prévisible et favorable.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Au chapitre des relations de la Suisse avec l'Union européenne (UE), il a été question du calendrier actuellement propice à une avancée dans les négociations institutionnelles. La délégation du Conseil fédéral a informé ses invités des développements intervenus dans ce dossier tout en soulignant l'importance de la voie bilatérale pour la Suisse.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;S'agissant de la migration, la Suisse et l'Allemagne ont estimé toutes deux que les mouvements migratoires actuels appelaient une réponse coordonnée à l'échelle européenne. Les délégations ont par ailleurs évoqué des thèmes internationaux tels que la situation prévalant sur la péninsule coréenne et en Iran. Les uns comme les autres ont souligné l'importance de l'accord sur le nucléaire iranien conclu en 2015.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Deuxième jour à Fribourg et Zurich&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Le soir du premier jour aura lieu le dîner de gala à Berne. Le programme du deuxième jour, soit le 26 avril, est consacré à des questions touchant à la démocratie et au développement durable. À Fribourg, les deux présidents participeront à une table ronde sur les perspectives de la démocratie au XXIe siècle.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ensuite, ils visiteront, en compagnie de la conseillère fédérale Doris Leuthard, responsable du Département fédéral de l'environnement, des transports, de l'énergie et de la communication (DETEC), le pavillon solaire « NeighborHub » développé par de hautes écoles suisses. L'après-midi, le président de la Confédération accompagnera son hôte à Zurich, où il prendra congé de lui.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>André Simonazzi porte-parole du Conseil fédéral +41 (0)79 597 64 49 Information DFI +41 (0)58 462 85 79 media@gs-edi.admin.ch Information DFF +41 (0)58 462 60 33 info@gs-efd.admin.ch Information DFJP +41 (0)58 462 18 18 info@gs-ejpd.admin.ch Information DEFR +41 (0)58 462 20 07 info@wbf.admin.ch Information DFAE +41 (0)58 462 31 53 info@eda.admin.ch Logistique et organisation : Information DFAE +41 (0)58 462 31 53 info@eda.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="177241">
        <title>Visite d’État du président de la République fédérale d’Allemagne Frank-Walter Steinmeier</title>
        <uri>https://www.edi.admin.ch/edi/fr/home/documentation/manifestations/Staatsbesuch-Deutschland.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="177245">
        <title>Relations bilatérales Suisse-Allemagne</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/countries/germany/fr/home/relations-bilaterales/bilaterale.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Il Consiglio federale riceve il presidente della Repubblica federale tedesca Frank-Walter Steinmeier</title>
      <lead>Diretta dal presidente della Confederazione Alain Berset, mercoledì 25 aprile 2018 il Consiglio federale ha accolto per una visita di Stato in Svizzera il presidente della Repubblica federale di Germania, Frank-Walter Steinmeier, e la sua consorte, Elke Büdenbender. Al centro dei colloqui ufficiali vi sono state le relazioni bilaterali, la politica europea e la cooperazione tra i due Paesi nel contesto internazionale. Entrambe le parti hanno sottolineato i vantaggi risultanti dall’intensa cooperazione.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Nel suo discorso in occasione del ricevimento a Berna il presidente Berset ha affermato che la Svizzera e la Germania condividono valori comuni. Egli ha inoltre evidenziato come la stretta interdipendenza culturale, sociale ed economica con i propri vicini sia una condizione irrinunciabile affinché il nostro Paese abbia successo.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Oltre al presidente della Confederazione, per la Svizzera hanno partecipato ai colloqui al Bernerhof il vicepresidente del Consiglio federale Ueli Maurer, la consigliera federale Simonetta Sommaruga e i consiglieri federali Johann N. Schneider-Ammann e Ignazio Cassis.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Entrambe le parti hanno espresso apprezzamento per le eccellenti relazioni bilaterali, la stretta cooperazione nei settori della formazione, della ricerca e dell'innovazione nonché per il fatto che nel 2017 il proficuo scambio economico ha raggiunto un volume commerciale di circa 100 miliardi di franchi.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Anche nel settore dei trasporti la cooperazione è ottimale. Negli ultimi anni, la Germania ha fortemente incrementato gli investimenti nelle infrastrutture di trasporto. La delegazione svizzera ha sosttolineato l'importanza, per l'aeroporto di Zurigo, di disporre di condizioni quadro favorevoli e attendibilie ha sottolineato l'importanza, per l'aeroporto di Zurigo, di disporre di condizioni quadro favorevoli e attendibili.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Riguardo alle relazioni tra la Svizzera e l'Unione europea (UE), si è discusso della finestra temporale attualmente favorevole per compiere progressi nei negoziati istituzionali. La delegazione del Consiglio federale ha informato in merito agli sviluppi in questo dossier e ha sottolineato nel contempo l'importanza della via bilaterale per il nostro Paese.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Per quanto riguarda il tema della migrazione, la Svizzera e la Germania si sono dichiarate concordi sul fatto che è necessario dare una risposta coordinata a livello europeo ai movimenti migratori. Le delegazioni hanno poi discusso di temi internazionali quali la situazione sulla penisola coreana e in Iran. Entrambe le parti hanno sottolineato l'importanza dichiarato di volere preservare gli effetti positivi dell'accordo sul nucleare con l'Iran delconcluso nel 2015. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Seconda giornata a Friburgo e Zurigo&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;La sera della prima giornata si terrà la cena di gala a Berna. Il programma della seconda giornata, il 26 aprile, è dedicato a questioni riguardanti la democrazia e la sostenibilità. A Friburgo il presidente Berset e il suo omologo Steinmeier parteciperanno a una tavola rotonda sulle prospettive della democrazia nel 21° secolo.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In seguito, assieme alla consigliera federale Doris Leuthard, responsabile del Dipartimento federale dell'ambiente, dei trasporti, dell'energia e delle comunicazioni (DATEC), visiteranno la casa a energia solare &lt;i&gt;«&lt;/i&gt;&lt;i&gt;NeighborHub&lt;/i&gt;&lt;i&gt;»&lt;/i&gt;, sviluppata da alcune università svizzere. Nel pomeriggio il presidente della Confederazione Berset accompagnerà a Zurigo il suo ospite e si congederà da lui.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>André Simonazzi portavoce del Consiglio federale +41 (0)79 597 64 49 Informazione DFI +41 (0)58 462 85 79 media@gs-edi.admin.ch Informazione DFF +41 (0)58 462 60 33 info@gs-efd.admin.ch Informazione DFGP +41 (0)58 462 18 18 info@gs-ejpd.admin.ch Informazione SEFR +41 (0)58 462 20 07 info@wbf.admin.ch Informazione DFAE +41 (0)58 462 31 53 info@eda.admin.ch Logistica e organizzazione: Informazione DFAE +41 (0)58 462 31 53 info@eda.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="177242">
        <title>Visita di Stato del presidente della Repubblica federale tedesca Frank-Walter Steinmeier</title>
        <uri>https://www.edi.admin.ch/edi/it/home/dokumentation/manifestazioni/Staatsbesuch-Deutschland.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="177246">
        <title>Relazioni bilaterali</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/countries/germany/it/home/la-svizzera-e/relazioni-bilaterali.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Federal Council receives German President Frank-Walter Steinmeier</title>
      <lead>On Wednesday, 25 April, the German president, Frank-Walter Steinmeier, arrived in Switzerland for a state visit, accompanied by his wife, Elke Büdenbender, and was greeted by the Federal Council, led by President Alain Berset. Official talks focused on bilateral relations, European policy, and cooperation between the two countries in an international context. Both sides stressed the advantages arising from their intensive cooperation.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;In his address during the reception in Bern, President Berset stated that Switzerland and Germany formed a community of shared values, and stressed that Switzerland would not be what it is today without the close cultural, social and economic ties with its neighbour.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the Swiss side, the talks in the Bernerhof were attended by President Berset, the vice president of the Federal Council, Ueli Maurer, and federal councillors Simonetta Sommaruga, Johann N. Schneider-Ammann and Ignazio Cassis.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Both sides praised the excellent state of bilateral relations, the close cooperation in education, research and innovation, and the success of economic exchanges, which last year reached a volume of roughly CHF 100 billion.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Cooperation is also good in the field of transport, where Germany has significantly increased investment in transport infrastructure in recent years. The Swiss delegation also stressed the importance of stable and favourable conditions for Zurich airport.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;With regard to Switzerland's relations with the European Union (EU), reference was made to the favourable window of opportunity for progress in institutional negotiations. The Federal Council delegation briefed the German delegation on developments in that dossier and emphasised the &lt;br /&gt;importance of the bilateral path for Switzerland.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the subject of migration, Switzerland and Germany agreed that a coordinated Europe-wide response was needed to address migratory movements. The delegations also discussed a number of international issues, such as the situation on the Korean peninsula and in Iran. Both sides underlined the importance of the nuclear agreement with Iran concluded in 2015.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Second day in in Fribourg and Zurich&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A traditional gala dinner will be held in Bern on the first evening. The programme for the second day of the visit, 6 April, is dedicated to the themes of democracy and sustainability. In Fribourg President Berset and President Steinmeier will take part in a podium discussion on prospects fro democracy in the 21st century. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Afterwards, together with Federal Councillor Doris Leuthard, head of the Federal Department of the Environment, Transport, Energy and Communisations (DETEC), the two presidents will visit the ‘NeighborHub' solar-powered house project developed by a group of Swiss universities. In the afternoon, Mr Berset will accompany Mr Steinmeier to Zurich where he will take leave of his guest.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>André Simonazzi Federal Council spokesperson +41 (0)79 597 64 49 Information FDHA +41 (0)58 462 85 79 media@gs-edi.admin.ch Information FDF +41 (0)58 462 60 33 info@gs-efd.admin.ch Information FDJP +41 (0)58 462 18 18 info@gs-ejpd.admin.ch Information EAER +41 (0)58 462 20 07 info@wbf.admin.ch Information FDFA +41 (0)58 462 31 53 info@eda.admin.ch Logistics and organisation: Information EDA +41 (0)58 462 31 53 info@eda.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="177243">
        <title>State visit by German President Frank-Walter Steinmeier</title>
        <uri>https://www.edi.admin.ch/edi/en/home/dokumentation/anlaesse/Staatsbesuch-Deutschland.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="177247">
        <title>Bilateral relations Switzerland–Germany</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/countries/germany/en/home/switzerland-and/bilateral-relations.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <keywords>
      <keyword id="203" org-id="601">
        <name lang="de">Personalia</name>
        <name lang="fr">Nommément</name>
        <name lang="it">Dati personali</name>
        <name lang="en">Personnel matters</name>
      </keyword>
    </keywords>
    <topics>
      <topic id="47">
        <name lang="de">Wirtschaft</name>
        <name lang="fr">Économie</name>
        <name lang="it">Economia</name>
        <name lang="en">Economic Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
