<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="98063" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2023-10-05</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="323" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>701</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidg. Materialprüfungs- und Forschungsanstalt</name>
      <name lang="fr">Laboratoire fédéral d'essai des matériaux et de recherche</name>
      <name lang="it">Laboratorio federale di prova dei materiali e di ricerca</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Laboratory for Materials Testing and Research</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.empa.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.empa.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.empa.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.empa.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">contact@empa.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">contact@empa.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">contact@empa.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">contact@empa.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="701">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Wirtschaft, Bildung und Forschung</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'économie, de la formation et de la recherche</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'economia, della formazione e della ricerca</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Economic Affairs, Education and Research</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Dübendorf, St. Gallen und Thun</city>
      <title>Bauen mit Lehm: Saubere Schlammschlacht</title>
      <lead>Umweltschonend, überall verfügbar und wiederverwertbar: Lehm lockt als saubere Alternative unter den Baustoffen. Wie sich die begehrte Erde tatsächlich nachhaltig und stabil verbauen lässt, findet Empa-Forscherin Ellina Bernard jetzt heraus. Ihr Projekt wird vom Schweizerischen Nationalfonds (SNF) mit einem «Ambizione»-Grant gefördert.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Die gebaute Umwelt ist zugleich das bauliche Fundament einer Gesellschaft sowie einer ihrer grössten Klimasünder. Allein bei der Zementherstellung entstehen rund sieben Prozent aller Treibhausgasemissionen weltweit. Empa-Forschende arbeiten daher an verschiedenen Wegen, diese Emissionen mit innovativen Baumaterialien und -technologien zu senken. Einer dieser Wege zum sauberen Bauen ist ein schlammiger: Ellina Bernard vom «Beton &amp; Asphalt»-Labor der Empa in Dübendorf und der Professur für Nachhaltiges Bauen an der ETH Zürich untersucht derzeit das Potenzial von Lehm als nachhaltiger Baustoff. Denn im Vergleich zu Beton sollte Lehm deutlich weniger CO2 freisetzen. Zudem ist er nahezu unbegrenzt verfügbar, wiederverwertbar und lässt sich gut verarbeiten - durchaus auch gemeinsam mit weiteren «Hipstern» der modernen Baukultur wie organischen Abfallstoffen aus der Hanfverarbeitung.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;b&gt;Erdige Paste für Wohnhäuser&lt;/b&gt;&lt;p&gt;Das Potenzial dieser Beton-Alternative wäre gewaltig. Zwar könnte Beton nicht bei allen Bauzwecken durch Lehm ersetzt werden. Möglich sind aber - neben einer Vielzahl von nicht-tragenden Konstruktionen - tragende Wände von Wohnhäusern. Und immerhin werden mehr als die Hälfte aller Baubewilligungen beispielsweise in der Schweiz gerade für Wohnbauten vergeben. Dabei kann sogenannte gegossene Erde in einer Verschalung verwendet werden oder gepresster Lehm in Form von vorgefertigten Bausteinen. Und diese luftgetrockneten Lehmziegel haben eine entsprechend günstigere Energiebilanz als ihre gebrannten Artgenossen, die Backsteine.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Ein wahres Wundermittel? «Noch nicht», sagt Empa-Forscherin Bernard. Denn obwohl Lehm bereits seit rund 10'000 Jahren genutzt wird und damit zu den ursprünglicheren Baumaterialien der menschlichen Geschichte gehört, lässt sich die erdige Paste bis heute nicht so richtig in den Griff bekommen. Zum einen ist das Naturmaterial in seiner geologischen Zusammensetzung überall auf der Welt unterschiedlich, was die standardisierte Herstellung und Verwendung erschwert. Zum anderen wird dem Lehm derzeit herkömmlicher Zement zugefügt, damit ein stabiles und haltbares Baumaterial entsteht. Durch diese Zugabe rutscht der ökologische Fussabdruck des Lehms jedoch wieder in den roten Bereich. Ellina Bernard will darum gemeinsam mit ihrem Team das erdige Material ergründen, Standards für die Zusammensetzung und die mechanische Belastbarkeit definieren und damit gleichzeitig ein sauberes alternatives Baumaterial für die industrielle Anwendung entwickeln. Für dieses ehrgeizige Vorhaben wird die Empa-Forscherin mit einem der begehrten «Ambizione»-Grants des SNF gefördert.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Die sanfte Kraft von Magnesium&lt;/b&gt;&lt;p&gt;Der Verwandlung einer schlammigen Paste aus Wasser und Erde in ein felsenfestes Produkt haftet etwas Geheimnisvolles an. Um dies zu enträtseln und letztlich zu kontrollieren, taucht Ellina Bernard in das Innerste der Materie ein. Im Gegensatz zu Zement, den chemische Bindungen zusammenhalten, gehen die feinen Tonmineralien im Lehm bei der Lufttrocknung physikalische Bindungen ein. Eine Stabilität wie die von Beton ist auf diese Weise nicht zu erreichen. Darum sucht die Forscherin nach einem geeigneten stabilisierenden Bindemittel.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Unterstützung erhält sie hierbei vom Geologen Raphael Kuhn, der derzeit seine Dissertation über Lehm-Zusatzstoffe anfertigt. Ein vielversprechender Kandidat ist Magnesiumoxid. Bei entsprechend nachhaltiger Gewinnung hat es eine hervorragende Klimabilanz im Vergleich zu Calcium-haltigem Zement, dessen chemische Reaktion grosse Mengen an CO2 freisetzt. Zudem verkürzt Magnesiumoxid die Trocknungszeit, wirkt durch die Bildung von Nanokristallen der gefürchteten Klumpenbildung im Lehm entgegen und greift dennoch nur sanft in die vorteilhafte Mikro- und Nanostruktur der lehmigen Elementarteilchen ein.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;In ersten Laborexperimenten erreicht das Team mit verschiedenen Lehm-Rezepturen bereits eine Druckfestigkeit von bis zu 15 Megapascal - ein Vielfaches von unbehandeltem Lehm. Zum Vergleich: Lehm mit Zementzusatz erreicht bis 20 Megapascal.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;«Das ist aber erst der Anfang», sagt Ellina Bernard. Da sie die Nachhaltigkeit von Baumaterialien ganzheitlich beurteilen möchte, müssen die Laborexperimente auch von Lebenszyklusanalysen begleitet werden, die Haltbarkeit, Rückbau und Wiederverwertung der Materialien erfassen.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class="nsbtextkasten"&gt;&lt;b&gt;«Ambizione»-Grant des SNF&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/b&gt;Ellina Bernards Projekt «Deciphering the role of magnesium in earth materials for sustainable construction» wird vom Schweizer Nationalfonds (SNF) mit einem «Ambizione»-Grant gefördert. Der Grant wird an herausragende junge Forschende mit einem eigenständigen Projekt vergeben, die ihr Doktorat bereits abgeschlossen haben. &lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Dr. Ellina Bernard Beton &amp; Asphalt Tel. +41 58 765 48 88 ellina.bernard@empa.ch</contact>
      <attachment id="263605">
        <title>Alternativer Baustoff Lehm: Ellina Bernhard mit einer Laborprobe. Bild: Empa</title>
        <format>jpg</format>
        <size-kb>2101</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/83221.jpg</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="263606">
        <title>Erdige Rohstoffe: Lehm besteht aus Tonmineralen, Sand und feinkörnigen Silt-Sedimenten. Für stabiles Bauen müssen weitere Zusatzstoffe beigemengt werden. Bild: Empa</title>
        <format>jpg</format>
        <size-kb>2147</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/83222.jpg</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="263607">
        <title>Empa-Forscher Raphael Kuhn will Lehm nachhaltig stabilisieren. Bild: Empa</title>
        <format>jpg</format>
        <size-kb>2824</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/83223.jpg</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="263608">
        <title>Die geologische Zusammensetzung von Lehm ist überall auf der Welt unterschiedlich. Ellina Bernard möchte Standards für die Anwendung in der Bauindustrie entwickeln. Bild: Empa</title>
        <format>jpg</format>
        <size-kb>3410</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/83224.jpg</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <link id="263609">
        <title>Bauen mit Lehm: Saubere Schlammschlacht</title>
        <uri>https://www.empa.ch/web/s604/baumaterial-lehm</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="263610">
        <title>Video</title>
        <uri>https://youtu.be/e_zu4tWOs7s?si=idbIYcxaIi5BWWBS</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Dübendorf, St. Gallen und Thun</city>
      <title>Construire avec de l'argile : Une bataille de boue propre</title>
      <lead>Écologique, disponible partout et recyclable : l’argile séduit comme alternative propre parmi les matériaux de construction. Ellina Bernard, chercheuse de l’Empa, découvre aujourd’hui comment cette terre très convoitée peut effectivement être utilisée de manière durable et stable dans la construction. Son projet est soutenu par le Fonds national suisse (FNS) avec une « Ambizione-Grant ».</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;L'environnement construit est à la fois le fondement architectural d'une société et l'un de ses plus grands pollueurs. La production de ciment à elle seule génère environ 7 % des émissions de gaz à effet de serre dans le monde. Les chercheurs de l'Empa travaillent donc sur différents moyens de réduire ces émissions grâce à des matériaux et des technologies de construction innovants. L'une de ces voies vers une construction propre est boueuse : Ellina Bernard du laboratoire « Béton &amp; Asphalte » de l'Empa à Dübendorf et de la chaire de construction durable de l'ETH Zurich étudie actuellement le potentiel de l'argile en tant que matériau de construction durable. En effet, par rapport à la terre cuite, l'argile devrait dégager nettement moins de CO2. De plus, il est disponible presque indéfiniment, recyclable et facile à travailler - tout à fait en association avec d'autres « hipsters » de la culture moderne de la construction, comme les déchets organiques issus du traitement du chanvre.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Pâte terreuse pour habitations&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Le potentiel de cette alternative au béton serait énorme. Certes, le béton ne pourrait pas être remplacé par l'argile pour tous les types de construction. Mais, en plus d'une multitude de constructions non porteuses, des murs porteurs de maisons d'habitation sont possibles. Et après tout, plus de la moitié de tous les permis de construire, par exemple en Suisse, sont justement attribués à des bâtiments d'habitation. Il est possible d'utiliser de la terre coulée dans un moule ou de l'argile comprimée sous forme de blocs de construction préfabriqués. Et ces briques d'argile séchées à l'air ont un bilan énergétique plus favorable que leurs congénères cuites, les briques de terre cuite.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Un véritable remède miracle ? « Pas encore », répond la chercheuse de l'Empa Ellina Bernard. En effet, bien que l'argile soit utilisée depuis environ 10 000 ans et fasse donc partie des matériaux de construction les plus primitifs de l'histoire de l'humanité, cette pâte terreuse n'est pas encore vraiment maîtrisée à ce jour. D'une part, la composition géologique de ce matériau naturel varie d'un pays à l'autre, ce qui rend difficile une production et une utilisation standardisées. D'autre part, du ciment traditionnel est actuellement ajouté à l'argile afin d'obtenir un matériau de construction stable et durable. Or, cet ajout fait à nouveau passer l'empreinte écologique de l'argile dans la zone rouge. Ellina Bernard et son équipe veulent donc étudier le matériau terreux, définir des normes pour la composition et la résistance mécanique et développer ainsi un matériau de construction alternatif propre pour l'utilisation industrielle. Pour ce projet ambitieux, la chercheuse de l'Empa est soutenue par l'un des « Ambizione Grants » très convoités du FNS.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;b&gt; La force douce du magnésium&lt;/b&gt;&lt;p&gt;La transformation d'une pâte boueuse d'eau et de terre en un produit solide comme le roc a quelque chose de mystérieux. Pour l'élucider et finalement la contrôler, Ellina Bernard plonge au cœur de la matière. Contrairement au ciment, dont la cohésion est assurée par des liaisons chimiques, les fins minéraux composants l'argile forment des liaisons physiques lors du séchage à l'air. Une stabilité comme celle du béton ne peut pas être obtenue de cette manière. C'est pourquoi la chercheuse est à la recherche d'un liant stabilisant approprié.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Elle est aidée dans sa tâche par le géologue Raphael Kuhn, qui prépare actuellement sa thèse sur les additifs pour argile. L'oxyde de magnésium est un candidat prometteur. S'il est extrait de manière durable, il présente un excellent bilan climatique par rapport au ciment contenant du calcium, dont la réaction chimique libère de grandes quantités de CO2. De plus, l'oxyde de magnésium réduit le temps de séchage, agit contre la formation redoutée de grumeaux dans l'argile grâce à la formation de nanocristaux et n'intervient pourtant que peu dans la microstructure et la nanostructure avantageuses des particules élémentaires d'argile.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Lors des premières expériences en laboratoire, l'équipe a déjà atteint une résistance à la compression allant jusqu'à 15 mégapascals avec différentes formules d'argile - un multiple de l'argile non traitée. À titre de comparaison, l'argile additionnée de ciment atteint jusqu'à 20 mégapascals.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;« Mais ce n'est que le début », explique Ellina Bernard. Comme elle souhaite évaluer la durabilité des matériaux de construction de manière globale, les expériences en laboratoire doivent également être accompagnées d'analyses de cycle de vie qui englobent la durabilité, la déconstruction et le recyclage des matériaux.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class="nsbtextkasten"&gt;&lt;b&gt;Subvention « Ambizione »&lt;/b&gt; &lt;b&gt; du FNS&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/b&gt;Le projet d'Ellina Bernards intitulé « Décrypter le rôle du magnésium dans les matériaux terrestres pour une construction durable » a été soutenu par le Fonds national suisse (FNS) au moyen d'une subvention « Ambizione ». Cette subvention est destinée aux jeunes chercheuses qui ont un projet personnel et qui ont déjà obtenu leur doctorat. &lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Dr. Ellina Bernard Concrete &amp; Asphalt Tél. +41 58 765 48 88 ellina.bernard@empa.ch</contact>
      <attachment id="263611">
        <title>L'argile, un matériau de construction alternatif : Ellina Bernhard avec un échantillon de laboratoire. Image: Empa</title>
        <format>jpg</format>
        <size-kb>2101</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/83225.jpg</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="263612">
        <title>Matières premières terreuses : l'argile est composée de minéraux argileux, de sable et de sédiments de silt à grains fins. Pour une construction stable, d'autres additifs doivent être ajoutés. Image: Empa</title>
        <format>jpg</format>
        <size-kb>2147</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/83226.jpg</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="263613">
        <title>Le chercheur de l'Empa Raphael Kuhn veut stabiliser durablement l'argile. Image : Empa</title>
        <format>jpg</format>
        <size-kb>2824</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/83227.jpg</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="263614">
        <title>La composition géologique de l'argile est différente partout dans le monde. Ellina Bernard souhaite développer des normes pour son utilisation dans l'industrie du bâtiment. Image: Empa</title>
        <format>jpg</format>
        <size-kb>3410</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/83228.jpg</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <link id="263615">
        <title>Construire avec de l'argile : Une bataille de boue propre</title>
        <uri>https://www.empa.ch/web/s604/baumaterial-lehm</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="263616">
        <title>Vidéo (en allemand)</title>
        <uri>https://youtu.be/e_zu4tWOs7s?si=Wq0ZmMqHbc6g43DS</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Dübendorf, St. Gallen und Thun</city>
      <title>Sustainable construction: Clean dirt</title>
      <lead>Environmentally friendly, ubiquitously available and recyclable: Clay is a clean alternative among building materials. Empa researcher Ellina Bernard is trying to find out how the coveted material can actually be used to build in a sustainable and stable way. Her research project is being funded by the Swiss National Science Foundation (SNSF) with an Ambizione grant.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;The built environment is both the structural foundation of a society and one of its biggest climate polluters. Cement production alone accounts for around seven percent of all greenhouse gas emissions worldwide. Empa researchers are therefore working on various ways to reduce these emissions with innovative building materials and technologies. One of these paths to clean buildings is a muddy one: Ellina Bernard from Empa's Concrete &amp; Asphalt laboratory in Dübendorf and the Chair of Sustainable Building at ETH Zurich is currently investigating the potential of clay as a sustainable building material. This is because clay should release significantly less CO2 than concrete. In addition, it is available in almost unlimited quantities, is recyclable and can be easily processed - even together with other "hipsters" of modern building culture such as organic waste materials from hemp processing.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;b&gt;Earthen paste for housing&lt;/b&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The potential of this concrete alternative would be enormous. Admittedly, clay could not replace concrete for all construction purposes. However, in addition to a large number of non-load-bearing constructions, load-bearing walls of residential buildings are possible. And after all, more than half of all building permits in Switzerland, for example, are issued for residential buildings. So-called poured earth can be used in a casing, pressed clay in the form of prefabricated building blocks. And these air-dried clay bricks have a more favorable energy balance than their baked counterparts, bricks.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;A true miracle product? "Not yet," says Empa researcher Bernard. Although clay has been used for around 10,000 years, making it one of the more primitive building materials in human history, the earthy paste still hasn't really taken off - yet. On the one hand, the geological composition of the natural material varies all over the world, which makes standardized production and use difficult. Secondly, conventional cement is currently added to the clay to create a stable and durable building material. This addition, however, pushes the ecological footprint of clay back into the red zone. Ellina Bernard and her team thus want to explore the earthy material, define standards for its composition and mechanical strength, and at the same time develop a clean alternative building material for industrial use. For this ambitious project, the Empa researcher has been awarded one of the SNSF's Ambizione grants.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;b&gt;The gentle power of magnesium&lt;/b&gt;&lt;p&gt;There is something mysterious about the transformation of a muddy paste of water and earth into a rock-solid product. To unravel and ultimately control this process, Ellina Bernard delves into the very heart of the matter. Unlike cement, which is held together by chemical bonds, the fine minerals in clay form physical bonds as they air-dry. Stability like that of concrete cannot be achieved in this way. That is why the researcher is looking for a suitable stabilizing binder.She is supported by geologist Raphael Kuhn, who is currently writing his dissertation on clay additives. One promising candidate is magnesium oxide.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;If it is produced in a sustainable manner, it has an excellent carbon footprint compared to calcium-containing cement, whose chemical reaction releases large amounts of CO2. In addition, magnesium oxide shortens the drying time, counteracts the dreaded formation of lumps in clay by forming nanocrystals, and yet only gently interferes with clay's advantageous micro- and nanostructure.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;In initial laboratory experiments, the team has already achieved a ­compressive strength of up to 15 megapascals with the magnesium oxide clay - many times that of untreated clay. By comparison, clay with added cement reaches up to 20 megapascals, and a wall subject to rather limited load, such as inside an apartment, must be able to withstand up to 10 megapascals.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;"But that's just the beginning," says Ellina Bernard. Since she wants to assess the sustainability of building materials holistically, the laboratory experiments must also be accompanied by life cycle analyses that record the durability, deconstruction and recycling of the materials.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class="nsbtextkasten"&gt;&lt;b&gt;Ambizione grant from the SNSF&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/b&gt;Ellina Bernard's project "Deciphering the role of magnesium in earth materials for sustainable construction" is being supported by the Swiss National Science Foundation (SNSF) with an Ambizione grant. The grant is awarded to outstanding young researchers with an independent project who have already completed their doctorate.&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Dr. Ellina Bernard Concrete &amp; Asphalt Phone +41 58 765 48 88 ellina.bernard@empa.ch</contact>
      <attachment id="263617">
        <title>Alternative building material clay: Ellina Bernhard with a lab sample. Image: Empa</title>
        <format>jpg</format>
        <size-kb>2101</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/83229.jpg</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="263618">
        <title>Earthen raw materials: Clay consists of clay minerals, sand and fine-grained silt sediments. For stable construction, other additives must be added. Image: Empa</title>
        <format>jpg</format>
        <size-kb>2147</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/83230.jpg</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="263619">
        <title>Empa researcher Raphael Kuhn wants to stabilize clay in a sustainable way. Image: Empa</title>
        <format>jpg</format>
        <size-kb>2824</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/83231.jpg</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="263620">
        <title>The geological composition of clay varies around the world. Ellina Bernard wants to develop standards for use in the construction industry. Image: Empa</title>
        <format>jpg</format>
        <size-kb>3410</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/83232.jpg</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <link id="263621">
        <title>Sustainable construction: Clean dirt</title>
        <uri>https://www.empa.ch/web/s604/baumaterial-lehm</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="263622">
        <title>Video</title>
        <uri>https://youtu.be/rccC5aplA10?si=lvjVVsoLMrvGgdxQ</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="29">
        <name lang="de">Umwelt und Natur</name>
        <name lang="fr">Environnement et nature</name>
        <name lang="it">Ambiente e natura</name>
        <name lang="en">Environment and Nature</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="45">
        <name lang="de">Technologie</name>
        <name lang="fr">Technologie</name>
        <name lang="it">Tecnologia</name>
        <name lang="en">Technology</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
