<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="98337" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2023-10-26</pubdate>
    <blocking-period>2023-10-26</blocking-period>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="318" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>301</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Bundesamt für Statistik</name>
      <name lang="fr">Office fédéral de la statistique</name>
      <name lang="it">Ufficio federale di statistica</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Statistical Office</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.statistik.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.statistique.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.statistica.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.statistics.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@bfs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@bfs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@bfs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@bfs.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="301">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement des Innern</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'intérieur</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'interno</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Home Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Neuchâtel</city>
      <title>Struktur der kleinen und mittleren Unternehmen (KMU) in der Schweiz im Jahr 2021 - KMU haben sich 2021 erholt</title>
      <lead>Kleine und mittlere Unternehmen (KMU) erhalten die Schweizer Wirtschaft am Leben. Im Jahr 2021 beschäftigten die KMU rund 3,1 Millionen Menschen. Gegenüber 2020 sind dies 64 000 Stellen mehr. Zwischen 2011 und 2021 hat der Anteil der Unternehmen mit weniger als 10 Beschäftigten auf Kosten jener mit 10 bis 49 Beschäftigten zugenommen. Zudem sind seit 2011 insbesondere die KMU im Gesundheitswesen zahlreicher geworden. Was den Warenexport und -import angeht, schneiden die KMU in multinationalen Gruppen am besten ab. Dies sind einige Ergebnisse der Publikation «Porträt der Schweizer KMU» des Bundesamtes für Statistik (BFS). </lead>
      <text link="no">Diese Medienmitteilung und weitere Informationen zum Thema finden Sie auf der Website des BFS (siehe Link unten).</text>
      <contact>Nicolas Vallon, BFS, Sektion Wirtschaftsstruktur und -analysen, Tel.: +41 58 465 03 95, E-Mail: nicolas.vallon@bfs.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="264502">
        <title>Kompletter Text und Mediendossier</title>
        <uri>https://www.bfs.admin.ch/news/de/2023-0277</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Neuchâtel</city>
      <title>Structure des petites et moyennes entreprises (PME) suisses en 2021 - Les PME ont retrouvé des couleurs en 2021</title>
      <lead>Les petites et moyennes entreprises (PME) font battre le pouls de l’économie suisse. En 2021, elles ont employé près de 3,1 millions de personnes. Par rapport à 2020, l’emploi a augmenté de 64 000 unités. Entre 2011 et 2021, la part des entreprises de moins de 10 emplois s’accroît aux dépens des entreprises comptant 10 à 49 emplois. Les PME se sont particulièrement développées dans le domaine de la santé depuis 2011. Sur le plan des exportations et importations de biens, elles sont d’autant plus performantes qu’elles appartiennent à un groupe multinational. Ce sont là quelques résultats de la publication «Portrait des PME suisses» de l’Office fédéral de la statistique (OFS).</lead>
      <text link="no">Vous trouverez ce communiqué de presse et d'autres informations sur ce thème sur le site web de l'OFS (cf. lien ci-dessous).</text>
      <contact>Nicolas Vallon, OFS, Section Structure et analyses économiques, tél.: +41 465 03 95, e-mail: nicolas.vallon@bfs.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="264503">
        <title>Texte intégral et dossier de presse</title>
        <uri>https://www.bfs.admin.ch/news/fr/2023-0277</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Neuchâtel</city>
      <title>Struttura delle piccole e medie imprese (PMI) svizzere nel 2021 - PMI in ripresa nel 2021</title>
      <lead>Le piccole e medie imprese (PMI) sono il cuore pulsante dell’economia svizzera. Nel 2021, occupavano quasi 3,1 milioni di persone. Rispetto al 2020, gli impieghi sono aumentati di 64 000 unità. Tra il 2011 e il 2021, la quota di imprese con meno di 10 impieghi è cresciuta a scapito delle imprese che contavano dai 10 ai 49 impieghi. Dal 2011 le PMI sono particolarmente floride nel settore sanitario e, in termini di esportazioni e importazioni di beni, sono più redditizie se appartengono a un gruppo multinazionale. Questi sono alcuni dei risultati della pubblicazione sul profilo delle PMI svizzere edita dall’Ufficio federale di statistica (UST).</lead>
      <text link="no">Il presente comunicato stampa e ulteriori informazioni sul tema sono reperibili sulla pagina Internet dell'UST (link sotto).</text>
      <contact>Nicolas Vallon, UST, sezione Struttura e analisi economiche, tel.: +41 58 465 03 95, e-mail: nicolas.vallon@bfs.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="264504">
        <title>Testo integrale e dossier per i media</title>
        <uri>https://www.bfs.admin.ch/news/it/2023-0277</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Neuchâtel</city>
      <title>Structure of Swiss small and medium enterprises (SME) in 2021 - SMEs bounce back in 2021</title>
      <lead>Small and medium-sized enterprises (SMEs) are the beating heart of the Swiss economy. In 2021, they employed almost 3.1 million people. Compared with 2020, employment rose by 64,000 jobs. Between 2011 and 2021, the proportion of enterprises with fewer than 10 jobs increased at the expense of those with 10 to 49 jobs. SMEs have grown particularly in the healthcare sector since 2011. In terms of the export and import of goods, they perform even better when they are part of a multinational group. These are some of the findings from the publication "Portrait of Swiss SMEs" by the Federal Statistical Office (FSO).</lead>
      <text link="no">This press release and further information on the topic can be found on the FSO website (see link below).</text>
      <contact>Nicolas Vallon, FSO, Economic Structure and Analyses, tel.: +41 58 465 03 95, e-mail: nicolas.vallon@bfs.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="264505">
        <title>Complete text and press kit - Please note that the English version only includes the release's lead</title>
        <uri>https://www.bfs.admin.ch/news/en/2023-0277</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <keywords>
      <keyword id="317" org-id="318">
        <name lang="de">Statistische Grundlagen und Übersichten (Statistische Grundlagen)</name>
        <name lang="fr">Bases statistiques et produits généraux (Bases statistiques)</name>
        <name lang="it">Basi statistiche e presentazioni generali (Basi statistiche)</name>
        <name lang="en">Statistical basis and overviews (Statistical basis)</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="317.7" org-id="318">
        <name lang="de">Industrie und Dienstleistungen</name>
        <name lang="fr">Industrie et services</name>
        <name lang="it">Industria e servizi</name>
        <name lang="en">Industry and services</name>
      </keyword>
    </keywords>
    <topics>
      <topic id="2">
        <name lang="de">Arbeit</name>
        <name lang="fr">Travail</name>
        <name lang="it">Lavoro</name>
        <name lang="en">Labour</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="43">
        <name lang="de">Statistik</name>
        <name lang="fr">Statistiques</name>
        <name lang="it">Statistica</name>
        <name lang="en">Statistics</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
