<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="98160" revoked="no">
    <version>2</version>
    <pubdate>2023-10-12</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="yes" id="502" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>501</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Generalsekretariat VBS</name>
      <name lang="fr">Secrétariat général du DDPS</name>
      <name lang="it">Segreteria generale del DDPS</name>
      <name lang="en">General Secretariat DDPS</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.vbs.admin.ch/</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.vbs.admin.ch/</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.vbs.admin.ch/</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.vbs.admin.ch/</www>
      <email lang="de">postmaster.vbs@gs-vbs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">postmaster.vbs@gs-vbs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">postmaster.vbs@gs-vbs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">postmaster.vbs@gs-vbs.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="505" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>501</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Gruppe Verteidigung</name>
      <name lang="fr">Groupement de la Défense</name>
      <name lang="it">Aggruppamento Difesa</name>
      <name lang="en">Defence</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.vtg.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.vtg.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.vtg.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.vtg.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@vtg.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@vtg.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@vtg.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@vtg.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="501">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Verteidigung, Bevölkerungsschutz und Sport</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de la défense, de la protection de la population et des sports</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale della difesa, della protezione della popolazione e dello sport</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Defence, Civil Protection and Sports DDPS</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.vbs.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.vbs.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.vbs.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.vbs.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@gs-vbs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@gs-vbs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@gs-vbs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@gs-vbs.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Bundesrätin Amherd trifft europäische Verteidigungsministerinnen und -minister in Brüssel</title>
      <lead>Das multinationale Format für die gemeinsame Fähigkeitsentwicklung von Streitkräften Framework Nations Concept (FNC) feiert sein 10-jähriges Bestehen. Deutschland als Rahmennation hat zu einem Treffen in Brüssel eingeladen, um diese Kooperation zu würdigen. Bundesrätin Viola Amherd nimmt am Treffen mit weiteren europäischen Amtskolleginnen und Amtskollegen teil und wird sich über die aktuelle sicherheitspolitische Lage, insbesondere den Krieg in der Ukraine und die Angriffe der Hamas in Israel, austauschen. </lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Das Framework Nations Concept (FNC) ist ein multinationales, von Deutschland im Jahr 2013 initiiertes Kooperationsformat, das dazu dient, die militärische Kooperation unter europäischen Staaten zu fördern. Auf freiwilliger Basis arbeiten bei FNC verschiedene Staatengruppen in ausgewählten Themenbereichen zusammen, um bei bestimmten militärischen Fähigkeiten, die im Interesse der betroffenen Staaten sind, Synergien zu nutzen und Plattformen für den Informationsaustausch zu schaffen. Insgesamt gibt es drei FNC-Plattformen, die jeweils von Deutschland, Italien und dem Vereinigten Königreich (UK) geführt und finanziert werden. Die Schweiz beteiligt sich zusammen mit Österreich und 18 Nato-Staaten in der deutschen FNC-Gruppe, weil sich diese auf koordinierte Fähigkeitsentwicklungen in verschiedenen Bereichen ausrichtet. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Die Schweiz nimmt seit 2017 als Partnerstaat an dieser europäischen Kooperationsinitiative teil. Sie beteiligt sich an bestimmten FNC-Projekten, wie zum Beispiel Mission Networks, das dazu dient, Erfahrungen im Einsatz und Verbund von Führungssystemen und ihren Sensoren auszutauschen. Ein weiteres Beispiel ist das Enhanced Host Nation Support – ein Projekt mit Fokus auf die logistische Unterstützung von Verschiebungen im Ausland, das die Schweizer Armee im Kontext der militärischen Friedensförderungsaktivitäten, insbesondere der SWISSCOY, interessiert.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Stärkung der Expertise und Fähigkeiten der Schweizer Armee&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mit der Teilnahme an diesen Kooperationsprojekten werden dank des Erfahrungsaustausches mit anderen Staaten die Expertise und Fähigkeiten der Schweizer Armee sowie die Interoperabilität in der internationalen militärischen Zusammenarbeit gestärkt.&lt;br /&gt;Anlässlich des ministeriellen Treffens wird der 7. Progress Report verabschiedet; im Report wird der Stand der Entwicklungen der jeweiligen FNC-Aktivitäten zusammengefasst. Das Treffen bietet Bundesrätin Amherd die Möglichkeit, sich mit ihren Amtskolleginnen und Amtskollegen bilateral auszutauschen. Der inhaltliche Fokus liegt dabei auf dem Krieg in der Ukraine und der aktuellen Lage im Nahen Osten. &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Kommunikation VBS +41 58 464 50 58 kommunikation@gs-vbs.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>La conseillère fédérale Viola Amherd rencontre les ministres européens de la défense à Bruxelles</title>
      <lead>Le format multinational pour le développement commun des capacités des forces armées – appelé Framework Nations Concept (FNC) – fête ses dix ans. L’Allemagne, en qualité de nation-cadre, a organisé une rencontre à Bruxelles pour célébrer cette coopération. La conseillère fédérale Viola Amherd y sera présente, parmi d’autres de ses homologues européens avec qui elle parlera de la situation actuelle qui prévaut dans le domaine de la politique de sécurité, notamment la guerre en Ukraine et l’attaque menée par le Hamas contre Israël. </lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Le FNC est un format multinational de coopération lancé par l’Allemagne en 2013 et destiné à promouvoir la coopération militaire entre les États européens. Plusieurs groupes d’États collaborent volontairement au FNC dans des domaines choisis. L’objectif est de tirer profit de synergies et de créer des plates-formes pour échanger des informations dans le cadre de certaines capacités militaires intéressant de prêt les États concernés. Il existe actuellement trois plates-formes FNC, dirigées et financées respectivement par l’Allemagne, l’Italie et le Royaume-Uni. La Suisse ainsi que l’Autriche et 18 États de l’OTAN prennent part aux travaux du groupe FNC de l’Allemagne, car celui-ci se consacre principalement au développement coordonné des capacités dans divers domaines. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;La Suisse participe depuis 2017, en qualité de partenaire, à cette initiative européenne de coopération. Elle est aussi présente dans certains projets FNC, comme les Mission Networks, lesquels servent à échanger des expériences dans l’engagement et la mise en réseau de systèmes de conduite et de leurs capteurs. Autre exemple : le Enhanced Host Nation Support – un projet axé sur le soutien logistique des déplacements à l’étranger –, qui intéresse l’Armée suisse, et en particulier la SWISSCOY, dans le contexte des activités militaires de promotion de la paix.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Renforcement de l’expertise et des capacités de l’Armée suisse&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;La participation à ces projets de coopération permet, grâce aux échanges avec d’autres États, de renforcer l’expertise et les capacités de l’Armée suisse ainsi que l’interopérabilité dans la collaboration militaire internationale.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Le 7e Progress Report va être adopté lors de la rencontre ministérielle. Il fait notamment le point sur le développement des diverses activités FNC. La rencontre donne à Mme Amherd la possibilité d’avoir des échanges bilatéraux avec ses homologues, essentiellement à propos de la guerre en Ukraine et de la situation actuelle au Proche-Orient. &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Communication DDPS +41 58 464 50 58 kommunikation@gs-vbs.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions>
        <revision date="2023-10-12 15:24" type="R"/>
      </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>La consigliera federale Amherd incontra a Bruxelles i ministri della difesa europei</title>
      <lead>Il formato multinazionale per lo sviluppo comune di capacità delle forze armate Framework Nations Concept (FNC) celebra il suo 10° anniversario. Nella sua veste di nazione quadro la Germania ha invitato a partecipare a un incontro a Bruxelles per rendere merito a questa cooperazione. La consigliera federale Viola Amherd parteciperà all’incontro insieme ad altri omologhi europei e si confronterà sulla situazione attuale in materia di politica di sicurezza, in particolare sulla guerra in Ucraina e sugli attacchi perpetrati da Hamas in Israele. </lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Il Framework Nations Concept (FNC) è un formato di cooperazione multinazionale avviato dalla Germania nel 2013 che ha lo scopo di promuovere la cooperazione in ambito militare tra gli Stati europei. In seno al FNC vari gruppi di Stati collaborano su base volontaria in aree tematiche selezionate al fine di sfruttare sinergie per quanto riguarda determinate capacità militari che sono in linea con gli interessi degli Stati coinvolti e di creare piattaforme per lo scambio di informazioni. Complessivamente esistono tre piattaforme FNC che vengono dirette e finanziate rispettivamente da Germania, Italia e Regno Unito. Insieme all’Austria e a 18 Stati della NATO la Svizzera partecipa al gruppo FNC diretto dalla Germania, dato che questo si concentra sugli sviluppi coordinati di capacità in diversi ambiti. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;La Svizzera aderisce a questa iniziativa di cooperazione europea dal 2017 in veste di Stato partner. Partecipa a diversi progetti FNC, come ad esempio Mission Networks, il quale serve a scambiare esperienze nell’impiego e nell’utilizzo integrato di sistemi di condotta e dei loro sensori. Un altro esempio è costituito dal progetto Enhanced Host Nation Support che si concentra sul supporto logistico a spostamenti all’estero che interessa all’Esercito svizzero nel contesto delle attività di promovimento militare della pace, in particolare della SWISSCOY.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Rafforzare le competenze e le capacità dell’Esercito svizzero&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Partecipare a questi progetti di cooperazione e scambiare esperienze con altri Stati permette di rafforzare le competenze e le capacità dell’Esercito svizzero nonché l’interoperabilità nell’ambito della cooperazione militare internazionale.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In occasione dell’incontro ministeriale verrà approvato il 7° Progress Report; il rapporto sintetizza lo stato di avanzamento delle rispettive attività del FNC. Per la consigliera federale Amherd l’incontro rappresenterà un’opportunità per confrontarsi a livello bilaterale con i suoi omologhi. L’attenzione si concentrerà sulla guerra in Ucraina e sulla situazione attuale in Medio Oriente. &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Comunicazione DDPS +41 58 464 50 58 kommunikation@gs-vbs.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Federal Councillor Amherd to meet with European defence ministers in Brussels</title>
      <lead>The Framework Nations Concept (FNC), a multinational initiative for the joint development of defence capabilities, is celebrating its tenth anniversary. As initiator of the FNC, Germany has invited ministers to a meeting in Brussels to honour the cooperation programme. Federal Councillor Viola Amherd will attend the meeting with her European counterparts and exchange views on the current security situation, in particular the war in Ukraine and the attacks by Hamas in Israel.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;The FNC is a multinational cooperation programme that was launched by Germany in 2013 to promote military cooperation between European states. Within the FNC, groups of states work together on a voluntary basis in thematic areas of their choice in order to exploit synergies in their military capabilities where it is in their interest to do so, and to create platforms for information exchange. There are currently three FNC platforms, led and funded by Germany, Italy and the UK respectively. Switzerland participates in the German FNC group with Austria and 18 NATO states, because it aims to coordinate the development of capabilities in various fields.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Switzerland has been a partner state in this European cooperation initiative since 2017. It participates in FNC projects such as Mission Networks, in which countries can exchange experiences in the deployment and interconnection of C2 systems and their sensors. Another example is Enhanced Host Nation Support, which is a project focusing on providing logistical support for missions abroad, which is of interest to the Swiss Armed Forces in the context of military peace support operations, in particular SWISSCOY.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Strengthening the Swiss Armed Forces’ skills and capabilities&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Swiss Armed Forces are able to strengthen their skills and capabilities by participating in these cooperation projects. Exchanging experiences with other states also helps improve interoperability in international military cooperation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the occasion of the ministerial meeting, the 7th Progress Report will be adopted; the report summarises the state of development of the FNC’s various activities. The meeting is an opportunity for Ms Amherd to engage in bilateral exchanges with her counterparts. The war in Ukraine and the current situation in the Middle East are at the centre of these exchanges.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>DDPS Communications +41 58 464 50 58 kommunikation@gs-vbs.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <keywords>
      <keyword id="505" org-id="505">
        <name lang="de">Sicherheitspolitik</name>
        <name lang="fr">Politique de sécurité</name>
        <name lang="it">Politica di sicurezza</name>
        <name lang="en">Security Policy</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="5180" org-id="505">
        <name lang="de">Armee</name>
        <name lang="fr">Armée</name>
        <name lang="it">Esercito</name>
        <name lang="en">armed forces</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="5330" org-id="505">
        <name lang="de">Friedensförderung</name>
        <name lang="fr">Promotion de la paix</name>
        <name lang="it">Promovimento della pace</name>
        <name lang="en">peace support</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="5530" org-id="505">
        <name lang="de">Bundespolitik / Bundesrat</name>
        <name lang="fr">Politique fédérale</name>
        <name lang="it">Politica federale / Consiglio federale</name>
        <name lang="en">federal policy, Federal Council(lor)</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="5930" org-id="505">
        <name lang="de">Internationale Beziehungen</name>
        <name lang="fr">Relations internationales</name>
        <name lang="it">Relazioni internazionali</name>
        <name lang="en">international relations</name>
      </keyword>
    </keywords>
    <topics>
      <topic id="3">
        <name lang="de">Armee</name>
        <name lang="fr">Armée</name>
        <name lang="it">Esercito</name>
        <name lang="en">Armed Forces</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="10">
        <name lang="de">Bundesrat</name>
        <name lang="fr">Conseil fédéral</name>
        <name lang="it">Consiglio federale</name>
        <name lang="en">Federal Council</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="40">
        <name lang="de">Sicherheit</name>
        <name lang="fr">Sécurité</name>
        <name lang="it">Sicurezza</name>
        <name lang="en">Security</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
