<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="98048" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2023-10-09</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="324" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>301</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Swissmedic, Schweizerisches Heilmittelinstitut</name>
      <name lang="fr">Swissmedic, Institut suisse des produits thérapeutiques</name>
      <name lang="it">Swissmedic, Istituto svizzero per gli agenti terapeutici</name>
      <name lang="en">Swiss Agency for Therapeutic Products</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.swissmedic.ch/</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.swissmedic.ch/?lang=3</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.swissmedic.ch/?lang=4</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.swissmedic.ch/?lang=2</www>
      <email lang="de"/>
      <email lang="fr"/>
      <email lang="it"/>
      <email lang="en"/>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="302" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>301</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Generalsekretariat EDI</name>
      <name lang="fr">Secrétariat général DFI</name>
      <name lang="it">Segreteria generale DFI</name>
      <name lang="en">General Secretariat FDHA</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="301">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement des Innern</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'intérieur</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'interno</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Home Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Gesundheitsrisiken durch Designerdrogen: Weitere psychoaktive Substanzen verboten</title>
      <lead>Wer Designerdrogen nimmt, kennt deren Gesundheitsrisiken nicht. Das Eidgenössische Departement des Innern (EDI) verbietet ab 9. Oktober 2023 weitere 10 Einzelsubstanzen und eine Substanzgruppe, um den Missbrauch neuer synthetischer Stoffe als Betäubungsmittel zu bekämpfen. Mit der Anpassung der entsprechenden Verordnung werden diese psychoaktiven Substanzen den Betäubungsmitteln gleichgestellt: Herstellung, Handel und Anwendung sind illegal und unterliegen der Strafandrohung des Betäubungsmittelgesetzes.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Neue psychoaktive Substanzen sind betäubungsmittelähnlich wirkende, synthetische Stoffe. Sie werden als Rauschmittel vermarktet und auch als Designerdrogen bezeichnet. Der Konsum solcher Designerdrogen ist ein Gesundheitsrisiko: Es ist nicht bekannt, wie sie zusammen mit anderen Substanzen wirken, ob und wie stark sie abhängig machen und wie giftig sie sind, wenn sie wiederholt eingenommen werden. Wegen der ähnlichen Struktur zu Substanzen, die bereits unter Kontrolle stehen, ist von einer betäubungsmittelähnlichen Wirkung mit beträchtlichem Abhängigkeits- und Missbrauchspotential auszugehen.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Mit der Aufnahme in die Verzeichnisse der kontrollierten Substanzen wird die Verbreitung neuer Designerdrogen auf dem Schwarzmarkt und damit der Konsum dieser potentiell gesundheitsgefährdenden Stoffe wirkungsvoll bekämpft. Die Aktualisierung der Betäubungsmittelverzeichnisverordnung erfolgt auf Antrag des Schweizerischen Heilmittelinstituts Swissmedic und ist international abgestimmt. Damit soll verhindert werden, dass die Schweiz zu einem Umschlagplatz für den Handel mit Designerdrogen wird. Seit Dezember 2011 sind 287 Einzelsubstanzen und 15 Gruppen (Derivate) in das das Verzeichnis e (Anhang 6) der Betäubungsmittelverzeichnisverordnung aufgenommen worden.&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Swissmedic Medienstelle +41 58 462 02 76 media@swissmedic.ch</contact>
      <link id="263563">
        <title>Betäubungsmittelverzeichnisverordnung (BetmVV-EDI, SR 812.121.11)</title>
        <uri>https://www.fedlex.admin.ch/eli/cc/2011/363/de</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="263564">
        <title>Kampf gegen Designerdrogen: Betäubungsmittelverzeichnis um 11 Einzelsubstanzen ergänzt</title>
        <uri>https://www.swissmedic.ch/swissmedic/de/home/news/mitteilungen/kampf-gegen-designerdrogen.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Risques sanitaires des drogues de synthèse : interdiction de nouvelles substances psychotropes</title>
      <lead>Les consommateurs de drogues de synthèse ignorent les risques sanitaires que comportent ces substances. Aussi le Département fédéral de l’intérieur (DFI) a-t-il décidé d’interdire dix nouvelles substances individuelles et un nouveau groupe de substances à compter du 9 octobre 2023, afin de lutter contre l’usage abusif de nouvelles substances synthétiques en tant que stupéfiants. La modification de l’ordonnance à ce propos permettra d’assimiler ces substances psychotropes à des stupéfiants, et de faire en sorte que leur fabrication, leur commerce et leur utilisation soient illicites et passibles des sanctions pénales prévues dans la loi sur les stupéfiants. </lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Les nouvelles substances psychotropes (new psychoactive substances, NPS) sont des substances de synthèse dont l'effet est semblable à celui des stupéfiants. Ces substances, qui sont commercialisées comme des stupéfiants, sont également appelées drogues de synthèse. Or leur consommation présente un risque pour la santé car on ne sait ni comment elles interagissent avec d'autres substances, ni si - et le cas échéant dans quelle mesure - elles entraînent une dépendance, et on ne connaît pas non plus leur degré de toxicité en cas de consommation répétée. De plus, au vu de leur structure analogue à celle de substances qui sont déjà soumises à contrôle, il y a lieu de supposer que leurs effets s'apparentent à ceux des stupéfiants et qu'elles peuvent être à la source de dépendances et d'abus. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Leur ajout dans les tableaux des substances soumises à contrôle permettra de lutter efficacement contre la multiplication des nouvelles drogues de synthèse sur le marché noir, et, de ce fait, contre la consommation de ces substances potentiellement dangereuses pour la santé. Cette mise à jour de l'ordonnance sur les tableaux des stupéfiants fait suite à une demande de Swissmedic, l'Institut suisse des produits thérapeutiques, et reflète un consensus à l'échelon international, l'objectif étant également d'éviter que la Suisse devienne une plaque tournante du commerce des drogues de synthèse. Depuis le mois de décembre 2011, 287 substances individuelles et quinze groupes de substances (dérivées) ont ainsi été ajoutés au tableau e (annexe 6) de l'ordonnance sur les tableaux des stupéfiants. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Service de presse de Swissmedic +41 58 462 02 76 media@swissmedic.ch</contact>
      <link id="263557">
        <title>Ordonnance sur les tableaux des stupéfiants (OTStup-DFI, RS 812.121.11</title>
        <uri>https://www.fedlex.admin.ch/eli/cc/2011/363/fr</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="263558">
        <title>Lutte contre les drogues de synthèse : ajout d’onze substances individuelles dans les tableaux des stupéfiants</title>
        <uri>https://www.swissmedic.ch/swissmedic/fr/home/news/mitteilungen/kampf-gegen-designerdrogen.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Rischi per la salute dovuti alle nuove droghe sintetiche: altre sostanze psicoattive vietate</title>
      <lead>Chi assume nuove droghe sintetiche non ne conosce i rischi per la salute. A partire dal 9 ottobre 2023 il Dipartimento federale dell’interno (DFI) vieta altre 10 sostanze singole e un gruppo di sostanze, al fine di combattere l’abuso di nuove sostanze sintetiche utilizzate come stupefacenti. Con l’adeguamento della relativa ordinanza queste sostanze psicoattive sono equiparate agli stupefacenti. Questo significa che fabbricarle, commercializzarle e consumarle è illegale e passibile di pena ai sensi della legge sugli stupefacenti.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Le nuove sostanze psicoattive (New Psychoactive Substances, NPS) sono sostanze sintetiche dagli effetti simili a quelli degli stupefacenti. Vengono commercializzate come sostanze stupefacenti e sono denominate anche «droghe di design». Il consumo di tali nuove droghe sintetiche è un rischio per la salute: non si sa come possano interagire con altre sostanze, quanto siano tossiche se assunte ripetutamente e se provochino assuefazione e in che misura. Data la somiglianza strutturale con sostanze già poste sotto controllo, si può presumere un effetto analogo a quello degli stupefacenti, con un notevole potenziale di dipendenza e abuso.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Mediante inclusione negli elenchi delle sostanze controllate si combatte efficacemente la diffusione di nuove droghe sintetiche sul mercato nero e quindi il consumo di queste sostanze potenzialmente pericolose per la salute. L'aggiornamento dell'ordinanza del DFI sugli elenchi degli stupefacenti viene effettuato su richiesta dell'Istituto svizzero per gli agenti terapeutici Swissmedic ed è armonizzato a livello internazionale. In tal modo si intende impedire che la Svizzera diventi una piattaforma per il commercio delle nuove droghe sintetiche. Dal dicembre 2011 l'elenco «e» (allegato 6) dell'ordinanza del DFI sugli elenchi degli stupefacenti ha incluso 287 sostanze singole e 15 gruppi di sostanze (derivati).&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Ufficio stampa Swissmedic +41 58 462 02 76 media@swissmedic.ch</contact>
      <link id="263561">
        <title>Ordinanza del DFI sugli elenchi degli stupefacenti (OEStup-DFI, RS 812.121.11)</title>
        <uri>https://www.fedlex.admin.ch/eli/cc/2011/363/it</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="263562">
        <title>Lotta contro le nuove droghe sintetiche: elenchi degli stupefacenti integrati con 11 sostanze singole</title>
        <uri>https://www.swissmedic.ch/swissmedic/it/home/news/mitteilungen/kampf-gegen-designerdrogen.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Health risks of designer drugs: further psychoactive substances prohibited</title>
      <lead>Anyone who takes designer drugs doesn’t know their health risks. From 9 October 2023, the Federal Department of Home Affairs (FDHA) is prohibiting a further ten individual substances and one substance group to tackle the misuse of new synthetic substances as narcotics. The amendment of the relevant ordinance will make these psychoactive substances equivalent to narcotics. Their manufacture, trade and use will be illegal and subject to penalties under the Narcotics Act.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;New psychoactive substances are synthetic substances with narcotic-like effects. They are marketed as intoxicants and also called designer drugs. Consumption of such designer drugs is a health risk. It is not known how they act in conjunction with other substances, whether they are addictive - and if so, how addictive they are - or how toxic they are when taken repeatedly. Due to their structural similarity to substances that are already controlled, an effect similar to narcotics with significant potential for addiction or abuse can be assumed.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Their inclusion in the lists of controlled substances is an effective means of tackling the spread of new designer drugs on the black market and, as a result, the consumption of these products which are potentially damaging to health. The Narcotics Lists Ordinance has been updated at the request of Swissmedic, the Swiss Agency for Therapeutic Products, and has been agreed at international level. This should prevent Switzerland becoming a transshipment centre for the trade in designer drugs. Since December 2011, 287 individual substances and 15 groups (derivatives) have been incorporated into List E (Annex 6) of the Narcotics Lists Ordinance.&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Swissmedic Media Unit +41 58 462 02 76 media@swissmedic.ch</contact>
      <link id="263559">
        <title>Narcotics Lists Ordinance (NarcLO-FDHA, SR 812.121.11) (German)</title>
        <uri>https://www.fedlex.admin.ch/eli/cc/2011/363/de</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="263560">
        <title>Combating designer drugs: 11 individual substances added to the Narcotics List</title>
        <uri>https://www.swissmedic.ch/swissmedic/en/home/news/mitteilungen/kampf-gegen-designerdrogen.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="5">
        <name lang="de">Behörden</name>
        <name lang="fr">Autorités</name>
        <name lang="it">Autorità</name>
        <name lang="en">Authorities</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="10">
        <name lang="de">Bundesrat</name>
        <name lang="fr">Conseil fédéral</name>
        <name lang="it">Consiglio federale</name>
        <name lang="en">Federal Council</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
