<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="71914" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2018-08-24</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="201" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>201</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="201">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Informeller Austausch zwischen Bundesrat Ignazio Cassis und EU-Kommissar Johannes Hahn</title>
      <lead>Bundesrat Ignazio Cassis hat am Donnerstag, 23. August 2018, am Rand der Salzburger Festspiele EU-Kommissar Johannes Hahn getroffen, der innerhalb der Europäischen Kommission namentlich für die Beziehungen mit der Schweiz zuständig ist.</lead>
      <text link="no">Gesprächsthema waren die bilateralen Beziehungen zwischen der Schweiz und der EU und insbesondere die Verhandlungen über ein institutionelles Abkommen.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;Bundesrat Cassis hat Kommissar Hahn bereits mehrmals getroffen, unter anderem im Januar 2018 am Rand des Weltwirtschaftsforums (WEF) in Davos und Anfang Sommer im Tessin. Bei beiden Treffen wurden bilaterale und internationale Themen besprochen.</text>
      <contact>Kommunikation EDA Bundeshaus West CH-3003 Bern Tel. Kommunikationsservice: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Medienstelle: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Echange informel entre le conseiller fédéral Ignazio Cassis et le commissaire européen Johannes Hahn</title>
      <lead>Le conseiller fédéral Ignazio Cassis a rencontré, jeudi 23 août 2018 en marge du festival de Salzbourg, le commissaire européen Johannes Hahn, qui est notamment chargé, au sein de la Commission européenne, des relations avec la Suisse.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Les deux hommes ont fait le point sur les relations bilatérales entre la Suisse et l’UE, en particulier sur les négociations sur un accord institutionnel. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;M. Cassis a déjà rencontré M. Hahn à diverses reprises par le passé, notamment en janvier 2018 en marge du Forum économique mondial (WEF) à Davos et au début de l’été au Tessin. Lors de ces contacts, ils ont à chaque fois évoqué des sujets bilatéraux et internationaux.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Communication DFAE Palais fédéral ouest CH-3003 Berne Tél. Service de communication: +41 58 462 31 53 Tél. Service de presse: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Incontro informale tra il consigliere federale Ignazio Cassis e il commissario europeo Johannes Hahn</title>
      <lead>Giovedì 23 agosto 2018 il consigliere federale Ignazio Cassis ha incontrato, a margine del Festival di Salisburgo, il commissario europeo Johannes Hahn, incaricato delle relazioni con la Svizzera presso la Commissione europea.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Cassis e Hahn hanno fatto il punto sulle relazioni bilaterali tra la Svizzera e l’UE, in particolare sui negoziati per un accordo istituzionale. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ignazio Cassis aveva già incontrato Johannes Hahn in diverse occasioni, ad esempio a margine del Forum economico mondiale (WEF) di Davos a gennaio 2018 e in Ticino all’inizio dell’estate. Durante questi incontri si è parlato di temi bilaterali e internazionali.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Comunicazione DFAE Palazzo federale ovest CH-3003 Berna Tel. Servizio di comunicazione: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Servizio stampa: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Informal talks between Federal Councillor Ignazio Cassis and European Commissioner Johannes Hahn</title>
      <lead>On Thursday 23 August 2018, Federal Councillor Ignazio Cassis met European Commissioner Johannes Hahn, who is responsible for relations with Switzerland at the European Commission, on the margins of the Salzburg Festival.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;The two men reviewed bilateral relations between Switzerland and the EU, in particular the negotiations on an institutional agreement. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mr Cassis has already met Mr Hahn on several occasions in the past, including in January 2018 on the margins of the World Economic Forum in Davos and in the early summer in the canton of Ticino. On each of those occasions they discussed bilateral and international matters.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>FDFA Communication Federal Palace West Wing CH-3003 Bern, Switzerland Tel. Communication service: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Press service: +41 58 460 55 55 E-mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @SwissMFA</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
