<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="68958" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2017-11-27</pubdate>
    <blocking-period>2017-11-27</blocking-period>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="318" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>301</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Bundesamt für Statistik</name>
      <name lang="fr">Office fédéral de la statistique</name>
      <name lang="it">Ufficio federale di statistica</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Statistical Office</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.statistik.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.statistique.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.statistica.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.statistics.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@bfs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@bfs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@bfs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@bfs.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="301">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement des Innern</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'intérieur</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'interno</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Home Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Neuchâtel</city>
      <title>Statistiken der Gesundheitsversorgung in den Spitälern 2016 - Der ambulante Spitalbereich in der Schweiz legt zu</title>
      <lead>(BFS) – Im Jahr 2016 kam es in den Schweizer Spitälern zu 18,3 Millionen ambulanten Konsultationen und beinahe 1,5 Millionen stationären Spitalaufenthalten. Dabei sind die Kosten im ambulanten Bereich während der letzten fünf Jahre doppelt so schnell gewachsen wie im stationären. Zudem nimmt der Einsatz von bildgebenden Geräten in den Spitälern stetig zu. Dies sind einige Ergebnisse der neuen Spitalstatistiken des Bundesamtes für Statistik (BFS).</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Diese Medienmitteilung und weitere Informationen zum Thema finden Sie auf der Website des BFS (siehe Link unten)&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Edith Salgado Valdivia, BFS, Sektion Gesundheitsversorgung, Tel.: +41 58 463 66 21, E-Mail: edith.salgado-thalmann@bfs.admin.ch Patrick Schwab, BFS, Sektion Gesundheitsversorgung, Tel.: +41 58 463 64 28, E-Mail: patrick.schwab@bfs.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="172952">
        <title>Kompletter Text und Mediendossier</title>
        <uri>https://www.bfs.admin.ch/news/de/2017-0103</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Neuchâtel</city>
      <title>Statistiques des hôpitaux 2016 - Le secteur ambulatoire est en progression en Suisse</title>
      <lead>(OFS) – En 2016, on a dénombré dans les hôpitaux suisses 18,3 millions de consultations ambulatoires et près de 1,5 million d’hospitalisations. Au cours des cinq dernières années, les coûts ont augmenté deux fois plus vite dans le secteur ambulatoire que dans le secteur stationnaire. Par ailleurs, l’utilisation des outils d’imagerie médicale est en hausse constante dans les hôpitaux. Ce sont là quelques-uns des résultats des nouvelles statistiques des hôpitaux de l’Office fédéral de la statistique (OFS).</lead>
      <text link="no">Vous trouverez ce communiqué de presse et d'autres informations sur ce thème sur le site web de l'OFS (cf. lien ci-dessous)</text>
      <contact>Edith Salgado Valdivia, OFS, Section Services de santé, tél.: +41 58 463 66 21, e-mail: edith.salgado-thalmann@bfs.admin.ch Patrick Schwab, OFS, Section Services de santé, tél.: +41 58 463 64 28, e-mail: patrick.schwab@bfs.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="172953">
        <title>Texte intégral et dossier de presse</title>
        <uri>https://www.bfs.admin.ch/news/fr/2017-0103</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Neuchâtel</city>
      <title>Statistiche sulla copertura sanitaria negli ospedali 2016 - Il settore ambulatoriale ospedaliero guadagna terreno</title>
      <lead>(UST) – Nel 2016 negli ospedali svizzeri sono stati recensiti 18,3 milioni di consulti ambulatoriali e quasi 1,5 milioni di ricoveri ospedalieri stazionari. Negli ultimi cinque anni, le spese del settore ambulatoriale sono aumentate due volte più in fretta che nel settore stazionario. Inoltre aumenta l’uso di apparecchiature di diagnostica per immagini negli ospedali. Sono questi alcuni dei risultati delle nuove statistiche ospedaliere realizzate dall'Ufficio federale di statistica (UST).</lead>
      <text link="no">Il presente comunicato stampa e ulteriori informazioni sul tema sono reperibili sulla pagina Internet dell'UST (link sotto)</text>
      <contact>Edith Salgado Valdivia, UST, Sezione Sistema sanitario, tel.: +41 58 463 66 21, e-mail: edith.salgado-thalmann@bfs.admin.ch Patrick Schwab, UST, Sezione Sistema sanitario, tel.: +41 58 463 64 28, e-mail: patrick.schwab@bfs.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="172954">
        <title>Testo integrale e dossier per i media</title>
        <uri>https://www.bfs.admin.ch/news/it/2017-0103</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Neuchâtel</city>
      <title>Statistics on health care provision in hospitals 2016 - Growth in Switzerland’s outpatient hospital care</title>
      <lead>(FSO) – In 2016 there were 18.3 million outpatient consultations and nearly 1.5 million inpatient stays in Swiss hospitals. Over the past five years, outpatient costs have risen twice as fast as those for inpatient care. In addition, the use of imaging equipment in hospitals is steadily increasing. These are some of the findings from the Hospital Statistics from the Federal Statistical Office (FSO).</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;This press release and further information on this topic can be found on the FSO website (see link below)&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Edith Salgado Valdivia, FSO, Health Services, tel.: +41 58 463 66 21, e-mail: edith.salgado-thalmann@bfs.admin.ch Patrick Schwab, FSO, Health Services, tel.: +41 58 463 64 28, e-mail: patrick.schwab@bfs.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="172955">
        <title>Complete text and press kit - Please note that the English version only includes the release's lead</title>
        <uri>https://www.bfs.admin.ch/news/en/2017-0103</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="15">
        <name lang="de">Gesundheit</name>
        <name lang="fr">Santé</name>
        <name lang="it">sanità</name>
        <name lang="en">Health</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
