<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="68689" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2017-11-08</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="1070" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>1070</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Der Bundesrat</name>
      <name lang="fr">Conseil fédéral</name>
      <name lang="it">Il Consiglio federale</name>
      <name lang="en">The Federal Council</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.admin.ch/gov/de/start.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.admin.ch/gov/fr/accueil.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.admin.ch/gov/it/pagina-iniziale.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.admin.ch/gov/en/start.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="804" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>801</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Generalsekretariat UVEK</name>
      <name lang="fr">Secrétariat général DETEC</name>
      <name lang="it">Segreteria generale DATEC</name>
      <name lang="en">General Secretariat of the Federal Department of Environment, Transport, Energy and Communications; General Secretariat DETEC</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.uvek.admin.ch/uvek/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.uvek.admin.ch/uvek/fr/home.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.uvek.admin.ch/uvek/it/home.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.uvek.admin.ch/uvek/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-uvek.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-uvek.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-uvek.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-uvek.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="810" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>801</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Bundesamt für Kommunikation</name>
      <name lang="fr">Office fédéral de la communication</name>
      <name lang="it">Ufficio federale delle comunicazioni</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Office of Communications</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.bakom.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.ofcom.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.ufcom.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.ofcom.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">media@bakom.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">media@bakom.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">media@bakom.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">media@bakom.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="1070">
      <name lang="de">Der Bundesrat</name>
      <name lang="fr">Conseil fédéral</name>
      <name lang="it">Il Consiglio federale</name>
      <name lang="en">The Federal Council</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.admin.ch/gov/de/start.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.admin.ch/gov/fr/accueil.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.admin.ch/gov/it/pagina-iniziale.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.admin.ch/gov/en/start.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <department id="801">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Umwelt, Verkehr, Energie und Kommunikation</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'environnement, des transports, de l'énergie et de la communication</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'ambiente, dei trasporti, dell'energia e delle comunicazioni</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of the Environment, Transport, Energy and Communications</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.uvek.admin.ch/uvek/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.uvek.admin.ch/uvek/fr/home.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.uvek.admin.ch/uvek/it/home.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.uvek.admin.ch/uvek/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-uvek.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-uvek.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-uvek.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-uvek.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Neue Frequenzbänder für die 5G-Einführung in der Schweiz</title>
      <lead>Der mobilen Kommunikation werden neue Frequenzbänder zugeteilt, um die Einführung der 5G-Technologie in der Schweiz zu ermöglichen. Das hat der Bundesrat an seiner Sitzung vom 8. November 2017 beschlossen, an der er die Änderungen des Nationalen Frequenzzuweisungsplanes (NaFZ) angenommen hat.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Um dem steigenden Frequenzbedarf im Bereich der mobilen Kommunikationstechnologien gerecht zu werden, setzt der Bundesrat einen Entscheid der Weltfunkkonferenz 2015 um: Der ursprünglich dem Rundfunk vorbehaltene Frequenzbereich 694–790 MHz wird umgenutzt und ist neu für breitbandige Mobilfunkanwendungen vorgesehen. Zudem werden strategische Weichen gestellt, um künftig auch in zusätzlichen Frequenzbändern eine Mobilfunknutzung zu ermöglichen. Mit diesen Massnahmen schafft der Bundesrat die Voraussetzungen für den Ausbau bestehender Mobilfunkinfrastrukturen und ebnet den Weg zur Einführung der neuen 5G-Technologie in der Schweiz. Diese neue Mobilfunktechnologie wird ein zentrales Element der Telekommunikationsinfrastruktur der digitalen Gesellschaft von morgen bilden. Sie erlaubt unter anderem eine viel höhere Geschwindigkeit bei der Übertragung der Daten und viel kürzere Antwortzeiten als bei der 4G-Technologie. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Die neuen Frequenzen sollen im kommenden Jahr von der Eidgenössischen Kommunikationskommission (ComCom) vergeben werden. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Im Rahmen der Revision des NaFZ hat der Bundesrat auch Massnahmen getroffen, um den steigenden Bedarf der schweizerischen Behörden und Organisationen für Rettung und Sicherheit (BORS) nach mobiler Breitbandkommunikation sicherzustellen. Dies erfolgt in Zusammenarbeit mit öffentlichen Mobilfunkbetreibern. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Im Alpenraum nehmen aufgrund der Klimaerwärmung die Gefahren von Lawinen und Hangrutschen zu. Deshalb werden im NaFZ zur Früherkennung und Überwachung gefährdeter Gebiete zusätzliche Frequenzressourcen für Radarsysteme ausgewiesen. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; Der NaFZ definiert, welche Frequenzen für welche Dienste verwendet werden. Für seine Aktualisierung ist das Bundesamt für Kommunikation (BAKOM) zuständig.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Bundesamt für Kommunikation BAKOM Medienstelle, +41 58 460 55 50, media@bakom.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="172146">
        <title>BAKOM: Nationaler Frequenzzuweisungsplan</title>
        <uri>https://www.bakom.admin.ch/bakom/de/home/frequenzen-antennen/nationaler-frequenzzuweisungsplan.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>De nouvelles bandes de fréquences pour lancer la 5G en Suisse</title>
      <lead>De nouvelles bandes de fréquences vont être attribuées à la communication mobile afin de permettre le lancement de la technologie "5G" en Suisse. Ainsi en a décidé le Conseil fédéral dans sa séance du 8 novembre 2017, en approuvant les modifications du Plan national d'attribution des fréquences (PNAF).</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Afin de continuer à répondre à la demande croissante en fréquences dans le secteur des technologies de la communication mobile, le Conseil fédéral applique une décision de la Conférence mondiale des radiocommunications 2015: initialement réservée à la radiodiffusion, la bande de fréquences des 694-790 MHz est dorénavant dévolue aux applications de téléphonie mobile à large bande. Des jalons stratégiques sont en outre posés, pour permettre à l'avenir une utilisation mobile également dans des bandes de fréquences supplémentaires. Avec ces mesures, le Conseil fédéral crée les conditions nécessaires au développement des infrastructures existantes et ouvre la voie à l'introduction de la nouvelle technologie 5G en Suisse. Celle-ci constituera un élément clé de l'infrastructure des télécommunications de la société numérique de demain. Elle permettra entre autres d'obtenir des débits beaucoup plus élevés lors de la transmission de données et des temps de réponse beaucoup plus courts qu'avec la technologie 4G.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Les nouvelles fréquences seront attribuées l'année prochaine par la Commission fédérale de la communication (ComCom).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Dans le cadre de la révision du PNAF, le Conseil fédéral a également pris des mesures pour répondre aux besoins des autorités et organisations chargées du sauvetage et de la sécurité (AOSS) en matière de communications mobiles à haut débit. Le processus s'est déroulé en concertation avec les opérateurs publics de téléphonie mobile. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Dans les régions alpines, les risques d'avalanches et de glissements de terrain augmentent en raison du réchauffement climatique. Par conséquent, le PNAF prévoit des ressources supplémentaires en fréquences pour les systèmes de radar, aux fins de détection précoce et de surveillance des zones menacées. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Le PNAF définit quelles fréquences sont utilisées pour quels services. Sa mise à jour relève de la compétence de l'Office fédéral de la communication (OFCOM).&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Office fédéral de la communication OFCOM Service de presse +41 58 460 55 50, media@bakom.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="172147">
        <title>OFCOM: Plan national d'attribution des fréquences</title>
        <uri>https://www.bakom.admin.ch/bakom/fr/page-daccueil/frequences-et-antennes/plan-national-d-attribution-des-frequences.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>5G in Svizzera: frequenze pronte al lancio</title>
      <lead>Nuove bande di frequenze saranno attribuite alla comunicazione mobile per consentire l'introduzione della tecnologia "5G" in Svizzera. Ecco quanto deciso dal Consiglio federale nella sua seduta dell'8 novembre 2017, che ha segnato l'approvazione delle modifiche al Piano nazionale di attribuzione delle frequenze (PNAF).</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Per soddisfare la crescente domanda di frequenze nel settore delle tecnologie di comunicazione mobile, il Consiglio federale mette in atto quanto stabilito in occasione della Conferenza mondiale delle radiocomunicazioni del 2015: cambia infatti la destinazione d'uso della gamma di frequenze dei 694-790 MHz, originariamente riservata alla radiocomunicazione e d'ora in poi attribuita alle applicazioni di comunicazione mobile a banda larga. Si gettano inoltre le basi strategiche affinché in futuro bande di frequenze supplementari possano essere impiegate per la radiocomunicazione mobile. Tramite queste misure il Consiglio federale crea le condizioni per potenziare le infrastrutture di comunicazione mobile esistenti e spiana la strada all'introduzione in Svizzera della nuova tecnologia di comunicazione 5G, che diventerà un elemento cardine dell'infrastruttura di telecomunicazione nella società digitale di domani. La tecnologia 5G garantisce velocità di trasmissione dei dati nettamente superiori e tempi di risposta molto più brevi rispetto alla tecnologia 4G. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;La Commissione federale delle comunicazioni (ComCom) prevede di attribuire le nuove frequenze nel corso del prossimo anno. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Nel quadro della revisione del PNAF, il Consiglio federale ha inoltre adottato una serie di provvedimenti volti a soddisfare il crescente fabbisogno di comunicazione mobile a banda larga da parte delle Autorità e delle organizzazioni svizzere attive nel campo del salvataggio e della sicurezza (AOSS). Queste modifiche sono realizzate in cooperazione con i fornitori pubblici di servizi di comunicazione mobile.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Nello spazio alpino il riscaldamento climatico accresce il rischio di valanghe e di frane. Per riconoscere tempestivamente le zone a rischio e sorvegliarle, nel PNAF sono state attribuite maggiori risorse di frequenze ai sistemi radar. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Il PNAF definisce quali frequenze sono utilizzate per quali servizi. Il suo aggiornamento compete all'Ufficio federale delle comunicazioni (UFCOM).&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Ufficio federale delle comunicazioni UFCOM Servizio stampa +41 58 460 55 50, media@bakom.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="172148">
        <title>UFCOM: Piano nazionale di attribuzione delle frequenze</title>
        <uri>https://www.bakom.admin.ch/bakom/it/pagina-iniziale/frequenze-antenne/piano-nazionale-di-attribuzione-delle-frequenze.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Frequencies for launching 5G in Switzerland</title>
      <lead>New frequency bands are to be allocated to the mobile communications sector to enable the launch of "5G" technology in Switzerland. This was decided by the Federal Council at its session on 8 November 2017 when the changes to the National Frequency Allocation Plan (NFAP) were approved.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;In order to meet the growing demand for frequencies in the communication technologies sector, the Federal Council is implementing a decision of the 2015 World Radio Conference: use of the 694-790 MHz range of frequencies, originally reserved for broadcasting, will be changed and will henceforth be designated for broadband mobile radio applications. Furthermore, strategic measures are being taken to enable future use of mobile radio frequencies in additional frequency bands. With these measures the Federal Council is creating the conditions for the expansion of existing mobile radio infrastructures and is paving the way for the introduction of the new 5G technology in Switzerland. This new mobile radio technology will constitute a key element of the telecommunications infrastructure of tomorrow's digital society. Among other things it permits much higher data transfer rates and much shorter response times than 4G technology. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The new frequencies will be allocated in the coming year by ComCom, the Swiss Federal Communications Commission. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Within the framework of the revision of the NFAP (National Frequency Allocation Plan), the Federal Council has also taken measures to meet the growing demand for mobile broadband communications from the Swiss rescue and security authorities and organisations (BORS). This is taking place in cooperation with public mobile radio operators. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In the Alpine region, the risks of avalanches and landslides are increasing because of climate change. Consequently, additional frequency resources are being allocated in the NFAP to radar systems for early detection and monitoring of the areas at risk. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The National Frequency Allocation Plan defines which frequencies are used for which services. The Federal Office of Communications (OFCOM) is responsible for updating it.&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Federal Office of Communications OFCOM Press Service +41 58 460 55 50, media@bakom.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="172149">
        <title>OFCOM: National Frequency Allocation Plan</title>
        <uri>https://www.bakom.admin.ch/bakom/en/homepage/frequencies-and-antennas/national-frequency-allocation-plan.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <offers>
      <offer id="67" org-id="810">
        <name lang="de">Medienmitteilungen Telecom</name>
        <name lang="fr">Communiqués de presse télécommunications</name>
        <name lang="it">Comunicati stampa telecomunicazioni</name>
        <name lang="en">Press releases Telecom</name>
      </offer>
    </offers>
    <keywords>
      <keyword id="210" org-id="810">
        <name lang="de">Bundesrat</name>
        <name lang="fr">Conseil fédéral</name>
        <name lang="it">Consiglio federale</name>
        <name lang="en">Federal Council</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="1260" org-id="810">
        <name lang="de">Telekommunikation</name>
        <name lang="fr">Télécommunications</name>
        <name lang="it">Telecomunicazioni</name>
        <name lang="en">Telecommunications</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="550" org-id="810">
        <name lang="de">Infrastruktur</name>
        <name lang="fr">Infrastruktur</name>
        <name lang="it">Infrastruktur</name>
        <name lang="en">Infrastruktur</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="1220" org-id="810">
        <name lang="de">Fernmeldedienstanbieter</name>
        <name lang="fr">Fournisseurs de service de télécommunication</name>
        <name lang="it">Fornitori di servizi di telecomunicazione</name>
        <name lang="en">Telecom service providers</name>
      </keyword>
    </keywords>
    <topics>
      <topic id="19">
        <name lang="de">Medien</name>
        <name lang="fr">Médias</name>
        <name lang="it">Media</name>
        <name lang="en">Media</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="28">
        <name lang="de">Telekommunikation</name>
        <name lang="fr">Télécommunications</name>
        <name lang="it">Telecomunicazione</name>
        <name lang="en">Telecommunications</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="36">
        <name lang="de">Informatik und E-Government</name>
        <name lang="fr">Informatique et cyberadministration</name>
        <name lang="it">Informatica ed e-government</name>
        <name lang="en">IT and E-Government</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
