<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="90029" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2022-08-25</pubdate>
    <blocking-period>2022-08-25</blocking-period>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="318" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>301</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Bundesamt für Statistik</name>
      <name lang="fr">Office fédéral de la statistique</name>
      <name lang="it">Ufficio federale di statistica</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Statistical Office</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.statistik.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.statistique.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.statistica.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.statistics.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@bfs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@bfs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@bfs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@bfs.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="301">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement des Innern</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'intérieur</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'interno</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Home Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Neuchâtel</city>
      <title>Die Zahl der Unternehmen und der Beschäftigten ist erstmals seit 2011 zurückgegangen</title>
      <lead>Die Schweiz zählte 2020 rund 617 000 Unternehmen und knapp 5,3 Millionen Beschäftigte. Nachdem diese Zahlen seit Beginn der statistischen Reihe im Jahr 2011 stetig gestiegen waren, verzeichnen sie nun erstmals einen Rückgang. Es wurden rund 900 Unternehmen und 33 000 Arbeitsplätze weniger gezählt als 2019, was einem Minus von 0,1% bzw. 0,6% entspricht. Besonders stark betroffen waren die Wirtschaftszweige Gastronomie und Beherbergung. Dort gingen knapp 15 600 bzw. 9900 Arbeitsplätze verloren. Soweit die jüngsten Ergebnisse der Statistik der Unternehmensstruktur (STATENT) des Bundesamtes für Statistik (BFS).</lead>
      <text link="no">Diese Medienmitteilung und weitere Informationen zum Thema finden Sie auf der Website des BFS (siehe Link unten)</text>
      <contact>Andrea Grossi, BFS, Sektion Wirtschaftsstruktur und -analysen, Tel.: +41 58 463 66 40, E-Mail: andrea.grossi@bfs.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="234429">
        <title>Kompletter Text und Mediendossier</title>
        <uri>https://www.bfs.admin.ch/news/de/2022-0427</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Neuchâtel</city>
      <title>Baisse du nombre d’entreprises et d’emplois en 2020: une première depuis 2011</title>
      <lead>En 2020, l’économie suisse comptait près de 617 000 entreprises et un peu moins de 5,3 millions d’emplois. Après une croissance ininterrompue depuis le début de la série statistique en 2011, on observe pour la première fois un fléchissement du nombre d’entreprises et d’emplois. Par rapport à 2019, on enregistre quelque 900 unités et 33 000 places de travail en moins, soit un recul de respectivement 0,1% et 0,6%. Les branches de la restauration et de l’hébergement ont été particulièrement touchées, avec un recul de près de 15 600 respectivement 9900 emplois. Ce sont là les derniers résultats de la statistique structurelle des entreprises (STATENT) de l’Office fédéral de la statistique (OFS).</lead>
      <text link="no">Vous trouverez ce communiqué de presse et d'autres informations sur ce thème sur le site web de l'OFS (voir le lien ci-dessous)</text>
      <contact>Andrea Grossi, OFS, Section Structure et analyses économiques, tél.: +41 58 463 66 40, e-mail: andrea.grossi@bfs.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="234430">
        <title>Texte intégral et dossier de presse</title>
        <uri>https://www.bfs.admin.ch/news/fr/2022-0427</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Neuchâtel</city>
      <title>Calo del numero di imprese e di impieghi nel 2020: una prima dal 2011</title>
      <lead>Nel 2020, l’economia svizzera contava circa 617 000 imprese e poco meno di 5,3 milioni di impieghi. Dopo una crescita ininterrotta dall’inizio della serie statistica nel 2011, per la prima volta si osserva una flessione del numero di imprese e di impieghi. Rispetto al 2019, si registrano circa 900 unità e 33 000 posti di lavoro in meno: si tratta di un calo rispettivamente dello 0,1 e dello 0,6%. Particolarmente toccati sono stati i rami dell’alloggio e della ristorazione, con un calo rispettivo di circa 15 600 e 9900 impieghi. Questi sono gli ultimi risultati della statistica strutturale delle imprese (STATENT) realizzata dall’Ufficio federale di statistica (UST).</lead>
      <text link="no">Il presente comunicato stampa e ulteriori informazioni sul tema sono reperibili sulla pagina Internet dell'UST (link sotto)</text>
      <contact>Andrea Grossi, UST, sezione Struttura e analisi economiche, tel.: +41 58 463 66 40, e-mail: andrea.grossi@bfs.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="234431">
        <title>Testo integrale e dossier per i media</title>
        <uri>https://www.bfs.admin.ch/news/it/2022-0427</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Neuchâtel</city>
      <title>Number of businesses and jobs fell in 2020 for the first time since 2011</title>
      <lead>In 2020, the Swiss economy had almost 617 000 businesses and just under 5.3 million jobs. After uninterrupted growth since the start of the statistical series in 2011, the number of businesses and jobs has declined for the first time. Compared with 2019, around 900 fewer units and 33 000 fewer workplaces were recorded, a decline of 0.1% and 0.6% respectively. Food and beverage service activities and the accommodation sector were particularly affected, with a drop of nearly 15 600 and 9900 jobs respectively. These are the latest results of the Federal Statistical Office’s (FSO) structural business statistics (STATENT).</lead>
      <text link="no">This press release and further information on this topic can be found on the FSO website (see link below)</text>
      <contact>Andrea Grossi, FSO, Economic Structure and Analyses section, tel.: +41 58 463 66 40, email: andrea.grossi@bfs.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="234432">
        <title>Please note that the English version only includes the release's lead</title>
        <uri>https://www.bfs.admin.ch/news/en/2022-0427</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <keywords>
      <keyword id="317.7" org-id="318">
        <name lang="de">Industrie und Dienstleistungen</name>
        <name lang="fr">Industrie et services</name>
        <name lang="it">Industria e servizi</name>
        <name lang="en">Industry and services</name>
      </keyword>
    </keywords>
    <topics>
      <topic id="43">
        <name lang="de">Statistik</name>
        <name lang="fr">Statistiques</name>
        <name lang="it">Statistica</name>
        <name lang="en">Statistics</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="47">
        <name lang="de">Wirtschaft</name>
        <name lang="fr">Économie</name>
        <name lang="it">Economia</name>
        <name lang="en">Economic Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
