<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="84364" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2021-07-06</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="201" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>201</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="201">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Doppeljubiläum und Digitalisierung im Zentrum der Treffen von Bundesrat Cassis in Estland</title>
      <lead>Nach seinem ersten Halt in Lettland traf Bundesrat Ignazio Cassis heute in Estland die Aussenministerin Eva-Maria Liimets und Parlamentspräsident Jüri Ratas. Die Gespräche drehten sich um die Digitalisierung, die Europapolitik und die Schweizer Kandidatur für den UNO-Sicherheitsrat 2023–2024. Bundesrat Cassis besuchte ausserdem das NATO Cyber Defence Centre of Excellence in Tallinn.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Anlässlich des Doppeljubiläums 100 Jahre Anerkennung der Unabhängigkeit Estlands durch die Schweiz sowie 30 Jahre Wiederaufnahme der diplomatischen Beziehungen nach dem Zerfall der Sowjetunion, würdigten Bundesrat Cassis und Aussenministerin Liimets die sehr guten bilateralen Beziehungen zwischen der Schweiz und Estland. Beide Seiten bekundeten die Absicht, die Beziehungen weiter auszubauen und zu vertiefen. Mit Blick auf die Europapolitik tauschte sich Bundesrat Cassis mit seiner Gesprächspartnerin über die jüngsten Entwicklungen aus, insbesondere über den Entscheid des Bundesrates, das Institutionelle Abkommen mit der Europäischen Union (EU) nicht abzuschliessen. Er hielt fest, dass die Schweiz die enge, vielfältige Partnerschaft mit der EU und ihren Mitgliedstaaten weiterhin pflegen und stärken möchte.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Bundesrat Cassis tauschte sich zudem mit seiner Amtskollegin über die Erfahrungen Estlands als nichtständiges Mitglied des UNO-Sicherheitsrats 2020–2021 aus und bedankte sich für die gute Zusammenarbeit mit Estland und den offenen Austausch. Er stellte die Kandidatur der Schweiz für einen Sitz als nichtständiges Mitglied im UNO-Sicherheitsrat 2023–2024 vor. «Die Schweiz will dabei auf ihrem bekannten und etablierten multilateralen Profil aufbauen und sich dort einbringen, wo sie über wertvolle Expertise verfügt» so Bundesrat Cassis. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Digitalaussenpolitik&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Der Vorsteher des EDA wir auf seiner Baltikumsreise von zwei Parlamentarierinnen begleitet, Nationalrätin Corina Gredig und Nationalrätin Lilian Studer. In Zentrum des Besuchs in Tallinn stand die Umsetzung der Strategie Digitalaussenpolitik 2021–2024 der Schweiz, die ein Schwerpunkt der aussenpolitischen Strategie des Bundesrats ist. So auch in den Gesprächen mit Parlamentspräsident Jüri Ratas und dem Vorsitzenden des Komitees für auswärtige Angelegenheiten des estnischen Parlaments, Marko Mihkelson. Bundesrat Cassis erläuterte die Absicht des Bundesrats das internationale Genf als führenden Standort der Digitalisierungs- und Technologiedebatten zu positionieren. «Estland trägt mit seiner Erfahrung im Bereich Digitalisierung einiges bei zu diesen Debatten», so der Vorsteher des EDA. Ausserdem besuchte Bundesrat Cassis das NATO Cyber Defence Centre of Excellence. Cybersicherheit ist eines von vier Aktionsfeldern der Schweizer Digitalaussenpolitik. «Digitale Technologien bieten neue Möglichkeiten für die Diplomatie, die Armutsbekämpfung und die Förderung einer nachhaltigen Entwicklung», so Bundesrat Cassis. Er besuchte ebenfalls das e-Estonia Briefing Centre, wo er sich über die Erfahrungen Estlands im Bereich E-Gouvernanz – einem weiteren wichtigen Aktionsfeld der Strategie Digitalaussenpolitik – sowie über E-Health informierte. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Doppeljubiläum mit Estland&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Es ist der erste Besuch eines EDA-Vorstehers in Estland seit sieben Jahren. Dieses Jahr jährt sich die Anerkennung Estlands als unabhängiges Land zum 100. Mal. Vor 30 Jahren nahmen die Schweiz und Estland zudem ihre diplomatischen Beziehungen wieder auf. Der Besuch von Bundesrat Cassis zeichnet anlässlich des Doppeljubiläums von Wertschätzung und Anerkennung der sehr guten Beziehungen mit Estland. Bundesrat Cassis reist zum Abschluss seiner Baltikumsreise weiter nach Vilnius, wo er an der Ukraine Reformkonferenz teilnehmen wird und sich mit dem litauischen Aussenminister Gabrielius Landsbergis und weiteren anwesenden Amtskollegen zu bilateralen Gesprächen trifft.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Kommunikation EDA Bundeshaus West CH-3003 Bern Tel. Kommunikationsservice: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Medienstelle: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <link id="218706">
        <title>Bilaterale Beziehungen Schweiz–Estland</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home/vertretungen-und-reisehinweise/estland/bilatereale-beziehungenschweizestland.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="218712">
        <title>Strategie Digitalaussenpolitik 2021-2024</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/dam/eda/de/documents/publications/SchweizerischeAussenpolitik/20201104-strategie-digitalaussenpolitik_DE.pdf</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Double anniversaire et transition numérique au cœur des séances de travail du conseiller fédéral Ignazio Cassis en Estonie</title>
      <lead>Après une première étape en Lettonie, le conseiller fédéral Ignazio Cassis a rencontré aujourd’hui, en Estonie, la ministre des affaires étrangères Eva-Maria Liimets et le président du Parlement Jüri Ratas. Leurs entretiens ont notamment porté sur la transition numérique, la politique européenne et la candidature suisse au Conseil de sécurité de l’ONU pour le biennium 2023-2024. Le conseiller fédéral Ignazio Cassis a en outre visité le Centre d’excellence pour la cyberdéfense en coopération de l’OTAN à Tallinn.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Il y a 100 ans, la Suisse reconnaissait l’indépendance de l’Estonie et il y a 30 ans, après l’effondrement de l’Union soviétique, les deux pays rétablissaient leurs relations bilatérales. À l’occasion de ce double anniversaire, le conseiller fédéral Cassis et la ministre des affaires étrangères Eva-Maria Liimets se sont félicités des très bonnes relations qu’entretiennent leurs deux pays et ont exprimé leur volonté de continuer à développer et à approfondir ces liens. Le conseiller fédéral Ignazio Cassis a par ailleurs discuté avec son interlocutrice des derniers développements survenus en matière de politique européenne, et en particulier de la décision du Conseil fédéral de ne pas conclure d’accord institutionnel avec l’Union européenne (UE). Il a relevé que la Suisse souhaite continuer à cultiver et à renforcer le partenariat étroit et diversifié qu’elle entretient avec l’UE et ses États membres.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Le chef du Département fédéral des affaires étrangères (DFAE) Ignazio Cassis a également évoqué avec son homologue les expériences réalisées par l’Estonie en tant que membre non permanent du Conseil de sécurité de l’ONU pendant la période 2020-2021 et l’a remerciée de la bonne coopération entre les deux pays et de ces échanges francs et ouverts. Il lui a en outre présenté la candidature de la Suisse à un siège de membre non permanent au Conseil de sécurité de l’ONU pour le biennium 2023-2024. «La Suisse veut s’appuyer sur son profil multilatéral établi et reconnu pour apporter sa contribution dans les domaines où elle dispose d’une expertise avérée», a déclaré le conseiller fédéral Ignazio Cassis. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Politique extérieure numérique&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Le chef du DFAE est accompagné dans son voyage dans les pays baltes par deux conseillères nationales, Corina Gredig et Lilian Studer. La mise en œuvre de la stratégie de politique extérieure numérique 2021-2024 de la Suisse, qui constitue une priorité de la stratégie de politique extérieure du Conseil fédéral, était au cœur de la visite à Tallinn. Ce fut également le cas lors des entretiens avec le président du Parlement, Jüri Ratas, et le président de la commission des affaires étrangères du Parlement estonien, Marko Mihkelson. Le conseiller fédéral Ignazio Cassis a expliqué l’intention du Conseil fédéral de promouvoir la Genève internationale en tant que haut-lieu du débat mondial sur la numérisation et les nouvelles technologies. «L’Estonie, forte d’une solide expérience en matière de transition numérique, apporte beaucoup à ces débats», a déclaré le chef de la diplomatie suisse. Le conseiller fédéral Ignazio Cassis a également visité le Centre d’excellence pour la cyberdéfense en coopération de l’OTAN. La cybersécurité est l’un des quatre champs d’action de la politique extérieure numérique de la Suisse. Comme l’a relevé le conseiller fédéral Ignazio Cassis, «les technologies numériques ouvrent de nouvelles perspectives en matière de diplomatie, de réduction de la pauvreté et de promotion du développement durable». Le chef du DFAE a également visité la salle d’exposition d’e-Estonia, où il a pu se faire une idée du chemin parcouru par l’Estonie en matière de gouvernance numérique – un autre champ d’action important de la stratégie de politique extérieure numérique – et des expériences que celle-ci a réalisées avec son système de santé numérique. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Double anniversaire avec l’Estonie&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;La dernière visite d’un chef du DFAE en Estonie remonte à sept ans. Cette année marque le 100e anniversaire de la reconnaissance de l’Estonie en tant que pays indépendant. La Suisse et l’Estonie ont également rétabli leurs relations diplomatiques il y a 30 ans. La visite du conseiller fédéral Ignazio Cassis effectuée à l’occasion de ce double anniversaire témoigne de l’estime que la Suisse porte à l’Estonie et de la reconnaissance des très bonnes relations bilatérales cultivées par les deux pays. La dernière étape de son voyage dans les pays baltes conduira le conseiller fédéral Ignazio Cassis à Vilnius, où il participera à la Conférence sur les réformes en Ukraine et mènera des entretiens bilatéraux avec le ministre lituanien des affaires étrangères Gabrielius Landsbergis et d’autres homologues présents dans la capitale lituanienne.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Communication DFAE Palais fédéral ouest CH-3003 Berne Tél. Service de communication: +41 58 462 31 53 Tél. Service de presse: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <link id="218707">
        <title>Relations bilatérales Suisse–Estonie</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae/representations-et-conseils-aux-voyageurs/estonie/suisse-estonie.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="218711">
        <title>Stratégie de politique extérieure numérique 2021-2024</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/dam/eda/fr/documents/publications/SchweizerischeAussenpolitik/20201104-strategie-digitalaussenpolitik_FR.pdf</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Doppio anniversario e digitalizzazione al centro degli incontri del consigliere federale Cassis in Estonia</title>
      <lead>Dopo la prima tappa in Lettonia, il consigliere federale Ignazio Cassis ha incontrato oggi in Estonia la ministra degli esteri Eva-Maria Liimets e il presidente del Parlamento Jüri Ratas. I colloqui hanno riguardato la digitalizzazione, la politica europea e la candidatura della Svizzera al Consiglio di sicurezza dell’ONU per il biennio 2023-2024. Il consigliere federale Cassis ha inoltre visitato il Centro di eccellenza della NATO per la cyberdifesa cooperativa a Tallinn.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;In occasione del doppio anniversario che ricorre quest’anno, ovvero 100 anni dal riconoscimento dell’indipendenza dell’Estonia da parte della Svizzera e 30 anni dalla ripresa delle relazioni diplomatiche dopo il crollo dell’Unione Sovietica, il consigliere federale Cassis e la ministra degli esteri Liimets hanno reso omaggio alle ottime relazioni bilaterali tra la Svizzera e l’Estonia. Entrambe le parti hanno inoltre espresso l’intenzione di ampliare e approfondire ulteriormente le relazioni. Per quanto riguarda la politica europea, il consigliere federale Cassis ha avuto con la sua interlocutrice uno scambio di opinioni sui recenti sviluppi in quest’ambito, in particolare sulla decisione del Consiglio federale di non concludere l’accordo istituzionale con l’Unione europea (UE). In tale occasione ha sottolineato il desiderio della Svizzera di mantenere e continuare a rafforzare la stretta e multiforme collaborazione con l’UE e i suoi Stati membri. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Con la sua omologa il consigliere federale Cassis ha anche parlato dell’esperienza dell’Estonia come membro non permanente del Consiglio di sicurezza dell’ONU 2020-2021 e ha ringraziato per la buona collaborazione e per il dialogo aperto con questo Paese baltico. Ha inoltre presentato la candidatura della Svizzera a un seggio non permanente nel Consiglio di sicurezza dell’ONU per il biennio 2023-2024. «La Svizzera vuole rafforzare il suo ben noto e consolidato profilo multilaterale e impegnarsi negli ambiti in cui possiede un prezioso know-how», ha affermato Cassis. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Politica estera digitale&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Nel suo viaggio nei Paesi baltici il capo del DFAE è accompagnato da due parlamentari, le consigliere nazionali Corina Gredig e Lilian Studer. La visita a Tallinn è stata incentrata sull’attuazione della Strategia di politica estera digitale 2021–2024 della Svizzera, che è una priorità della strategia di politica estera del Consiglio federale. Questo tema è stato anche al centro degli incontri con il presidente del Parlamento, Jüri Ratas, e il presidente della commissione per gli affari esteri del Parlamento estone, Marko Mihkelson. Il consigliere federale Cassis ha spiegato l’intenzione del Consiglio federale di posizionare la Ginevra internazionale come centro nevralgico del dibattito in materia di digitalizzazione e di tecnologia. «L’Estonia, con la sua esperienza nel campo della digitalizzazione, contribuisce notevolmente a questo dibattito», ha sottolineato il capo del DFAE. Cassis ha inoltre visitato il Centro di eccellenza della NATO per la cyberdifesa cooperativa (NATO Cooperative Cyber Defence Centre of Excellence, CCD COE). La cybersicurezza è uno dei quattro campi d’azione della politica estera digitale della Svizzera. «Le tecnologie digitali offrono nuove opportunità per la diplomazia, la lotta alla povertà e la promozione dello sviluppo sostenibile», ha spiegato il consigliere federale Cassis. Il capo del DFAE ha visitato anche l’e-Estonia Briefing Centre, dove ha raccolto informazioni sulle esperienze fatte dall’Estonia nel campo della governance digitale, altro importante campo d’azione della strategia di politica estera digitale, e sull’e-health (o salute digitale). &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Doppio anniversario con l’Estonia&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Questa è la prima visita di un capo del DFAE in Estonia da sette anni. Quest’anno ricorrono anche il centesimo anniversario del riconoscimento dell’Estonia come Stato indipendente da parte della Svizzera e i 30 anni dalla ripresa delle relazioni diplomatiche tra la Svizzera e l’Estonia: una doppia ricorrenza che il consigliere federale Cassis ha celebrato all’insegna dell’apprezzamento e del riconoscimento delle ottime relazioni con questo Paese. Come ultima tappa del suo viaggio nei Paesi baltici, il consigliere federale Cassis si recherà a Vilnius, dove parteciperà alla conferenza sulla riforma ucraina e terrà colloqui bilaterali con il ministro degli esteri lituano Gabrielius Landsbergis e altri ministri degli esteri presenti.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Comunicazione DFAE Palazzo federale ovest CH-3003 Berna Tel. Servizio di comunicazione: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Servizio stampa: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <link id="218708">
        <title>Relazioni bilaterali Svizzera–Estonia</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae/rappresentanze-e-consigli-di-viaggio/estonia/svizzera-estonia.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="218713">
        <title>Strategia di politica estera digitale 2021-2024</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/dam/eda/it/documents/publications/SchweizerischeAussenpolitik/20201104-strategie-digitalaussenpolitik_IT.pdf</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Federal Councillor Ignazio Cassis visits Estonia to mark double anniversary and discuss digitalisation</title>
      <lead>Following the first leg of his visit to the Baltic States in Latvia, today Federal Councillor Ignazio Cassis, head of the Federal Department of Foreign Affairs, travelled to Estonia where he met with Minister of Foreign Affairs Eva-Maria Liimets and Parliamentary Speaker Jüri Ratas. Their talks focused on digitalisation, European policy and Switzerland's candidacy for a seat on the UN Security Council in the period 2023–24. Mr Cassis also visited the NATO Cooperative Cyber Defence Centre of Excellence in Tallinn.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Mr Cassis' visit to Estonia marks two anniversaries: a hundred years since Switzerland recognised Estonia's independence and 30 years since the two countries resumed diplomatic relations following the collapse of the Soviet Union. Mr Cassis and Ms Liimets paid tribute to the excellent bilateral relations between Switzerland and Estonia and affirmed their intention to further develop and deepen relations between their two countries. Mr Cassis and Ms Liimets also discussed the latest developments in European policy, in particular the Federal Council's decision not to conclude the institutional agreement with the EU. Mr Cassis stressed Switzerland's determination to continue to nurture and strengthen its close, multifaceted partnership with the EU and its member states.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;He also discussed with Ms Liimets Estonia's experience as a non-permanent member of the UN Security Council in 2020–21 and expressed his appreciation for Switzerland's good cooperation and open dialogue with Estonia. He also briefed Ms Liimets on Switzerland's candidacy for a non-permanent seat on the UN Security Council for the period 2023–24. "Switzerland aims to build on its recognised and well-established multilateral profile and contribute in areas where it has valuable expertise", said Cassis. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Digital foreign policy&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Two members of the National Council, Corina Gredig and Lilian Studer, are accompanying Mr Cassis on his trip to the Baltic States. Mr Cassis' visit to Tallinn was primarily focused on the implementation of Switzerland's Digital Foreign Policy Strategy 2021–24, which is a priority of the Federal Council's foreign policy strategy. This was also the case in the talks with the President of the Parliament, Jüri Ratas, and the Chairman of the Foreign Affairs Committee of the Estonian Parliament, Marko Mihkelson. Mr Cassis explained the Federal Council's intention to position International Geneva as a leading centre for global digitalisation and technology debates. "Thanks to its experience in the field of digitalisation, Estonia has a great deal to contribute to these debates," said Cassis. Mr Cassis also visited the NATO Cooperative Cyber Defence Centre of Excellence. Cybersecurity is one of four fields of action of Switzerland's digital foreign policy. "Digital technologies offer new opportunities for diplomacy, poverty reduction and the promotion of sustainable development", added Cassis. Mr Cassis also visited the e-Estonia Briefing Centre, where he was briefed on Estonia's experience in e-governance – another important field of action of the digital foreign policy strategy – and e-health. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Double anniversary with Estonia&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;This is the first visit by a Swiss foreign minister to Estonia in seven years. This year marks the 100th anniversary of Switzerland's recognition of Estonia as an independent state. It is also the 30th anniversary of the resumption of diplomatic relations between Switzerland and Estonia. Mr Cassis' visit on the occasion of the double anniversary signals Switzerland's appreciation and recognition of its excellent relations with Estonia. Mr Cassis will conclude his trip to the Baltic States with a visit to Vilnius, where he will participate in the Ukraine Reform Conference and hold bilateral talks with Lithuanian Minister of Foreign Affairs Gabrielius Landsbergis and other foreign ministers.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>FDFA Communication Federal Palace West Wing CH-3003 Bern, Switzerland Tel. Communication service: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Press service: +41 58 460 55 55 E-mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @SwissMFA</contact>
      <link id="218709">
        <title>Bilateral relations Switzerland–Estonia</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/fdfa/representations-and-travel-advice/estonia/switzerland-estonia.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="218710">
        <title>Digital Foreign Policy Strategy 2021-24</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/dam/eda/en/documents/publications/SchweizerischeAussenpolitik/20201104-strategie-digitalaussenpolitik_EN.pdf</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
