<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="84383" revoked="no">
    <version>3</version>
    <pubdate>2021-07-09</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="317" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>301</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Bundesamt für Gesundheit</name>
      <name lang="fr">Office fédéral de la santé publique</name>
      <name lang="it">Ufficio federale della sanità pubblica</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Office of Public Health</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.bag.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.bag.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.bag.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.bag.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">media@bag.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">media@bag.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">media@bag.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">media@bag.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="301">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement des Innern</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'intérieur</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'interno</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Home Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>EU anerkennt Schweizer Covid-Zertifikat</title>
      <lead>Die EU hat das Schweizer Covid-Zertifikat offiziell als gleichwertig anerkannt. Die Schweiz anerkennt ihrerseits die Zertifikate, die durch die EU- und EFTA-Mitgliedstaaten ausgestellt werden. </lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Die EU hat das Schweizer Zertifikat offiziell anerkannt. Zugleich hat die Schweiz ihrerseits die Anerkennung der in den EU- und EFTA-Mitgliedsstaaten ausgestellten Zertifikate sichergestellt. Das Schweizer Covid-Zertifikat wurde mit der digitalen Schnittstelle der EU verbunden und ist seit letzter Nacht, vom 8. auf den 9. Juli, im gesamten EU-/EFTA-Raum anwendbar. Der internationalen Kompatibilität wurde bei der Erstellung des Schweizer Covid-Zertifikats seit Beginn der Entwicklung eine hohe Priorität beigemessen.». &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ziel des «EU Digital COVID Certificate» ist es, das sichere Reisen während der Covid-19-Pandemie zu erleichtern. Wie das Zertifikat eingesetzt werden kann, entscheiden die einzelnen Staaten. Jedes Land bestimmt seine eigenen Einreiseregelungen und hat die Hoheit, sie je nach Entwicklung der epidemiologischen Lage anzupassen. Für Reisende mit dem Zertifikat ist es daher wichtig, sich stets über die aktuellen Einreisebestimmungen des Ziellandes zu informieren. &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Bundesamt für Gesundheit Infoline Coronavirus +41 58 463 00 00 Infoline Covid-19-Impfung +41 58 377 88 92</contact>
      <attachment id="218877">
        <title>FAQ – EU-Anerkennung und Anwendung</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>96</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/67576.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <link id="218871">
        <title>Coronavirus: Covid-Zertifikat</title>
        <uri>https://www.bag.admin.ch/bag/de/home/krankheiten/ausbrueche-epidemien-pandemien/aktuelle-ausbrueche-epidemien/novel-cov/covid-zertifikat.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="218872">
        <title>Coronavirus: Auslandsreisen und weltweite Zahlen</title>
        <uri>https://www.bag.admin.ch/bag/de/home/krankheiten/ausbrueche-epidemien-pandemien/aktuelle-ausbrueche-epidemien/novel-cov/empfehlungen-fuer-reisende/auslandsreisen.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="218873">
        <title>Re-open EU</title>
        <uri>https://reopen.europa.eu/de/</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>L’UE reconnaît le certificat COVID de la Suisse</title>
      <lead>L’UE a reconnu officiellement l’équivalence du certificat COVID suisse. De son côté, la Suisse reconnaît les certificats délivrés par les États membres de l’UE et de l’AELE. </lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;L’UE a reconnu officiellement le certificat suisse. Dans le même temps, la Suisse a garanti la reconnaissance des certificats délivrés par les États membres de l’UE et de l’AELE. Le certificat suisse est relié à l’interface numérique de l’UE et peut être utilisé depuis la nuit dernière, du 8 au 9 juillet, dans l’ensemble de l’espace UE/AELE. Dès le début du développement du certificat suisse, une haute priorité a été accordée à la compatibilité internationale. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;L’objectif du « certificat COVID numérique de l’UE » est de faciliter les voyages pendant la pandémie de COVID-19. Il appartient à chaque État de définir les modalités précises d’utilisation du certificat. Chaque État définit ses propres dispositions d’entrée et est libre de les adapter à l’évolution de la situation épidémiologique. Il est important pour les voyageurs munis du certificat de s’informer en continu sur les dispositions en vigueur pour entrer dans le pays de destination. &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Office fédéral de la santé publique Infoline coronavirus +41 58 463 00 00 Infoline vaccination COVID-19 +41 58 377 88 92</contact>
      <attachment id="218884">
        <title>Questions fréquentes : reconnaissance du</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>111</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/67572.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <link id="218874">
        <title>Coronavirus: certificat COVID</title>
        <uri>https://www.bag.admin.ch/bag/fr/home/krankheiten/ausbrueche-epidemien-pandemien/aktuelle-ausbrueche-epidemien/novel-cov/covid-zertifikat.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="218875">
        <title>Coronavirus : voyages à l’étranger et chiffres dans le monde</title>
        <uri>https://www.bag.admin.ch/bag/fr/home/krankheiten/ausbrueche-epidemien-pandemien/aktuelle-ausbrueche-epidemien/novel-cov/empfehlungen-fuer-reisende/auslandsreisen.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="218876">
        <title>Re-open EU</title>
        <uri>https://reopen.europa.eu/fr/</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions>
        <revision date="2021-07-09 09:40" type="R"/>
      </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>L’UE riconosce il certificato COVID svizzero</title>
      <lead>L’UE ha ufficialmente riconosciuto l’equivalenza del certificato COVID svizzero. Dal canto suo, la Svizzera riconosce i certificati emessi dagli Stati membri dell’UE e dell’AELS.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;L’UE ha ufficialmente riconosciuto il certificato svizzero e, allo stesso tempo, la Svizzera ha garantito dal canto suo il riconoscimento dei certificati emessi negli Stati membri dell’UE e dell’AELS. Il certificato COVID svizzero è stato collegato all’interfaccia digitale dell’UE e potrà essere impiegato in tutto lo spazio UE e può essere impiegato in tutto lo spazio UE/AELS da ieri notte, 8-9 luglio. Nella creazione del certificato COVID svizzero, fin dall’inizio del suo sviluppo era stata accordata un’elevata priorità alla compatibilità internazionale.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;L’obiettivo del «Certificato COVID digitale UE» è facilitare viaggi sicuri durante la pandemia di COVID-19. Spetta ai singoli Stati decidere come può essere impiegato il certificato. Ogni Paese definisce le proprie disposizioni di entrata e ha la competenza di adeguarle in funzione dell’evoluzione epidemiologica. È quindi importante che i viaggiatori in possesso del certificato si tengano costantemente aggiornati sulle attuali disposizioni di entrata del Paese di destinazione.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Ufficio federale della sanità pubblica UFSP Infoline Coronavirus +41 58 463 00 00 Infoline vaccinazione anti-COVID-19 +41 58 377 88 92</contact>
      <attachment id="218885">
        <title>FAQ – Riconoscimento da parte dell’UE e utilizzo del certificato COVID nello spazio UE</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>94</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/67573.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <link id="218878">
        <title>Coronavirus: certificato COVID</title>
        <uri>https://www.bag.admin.ch/bag/it/home/krankheiten/ausbrueche-epidemien-pandemien/aktuelle-ausbrueche-epidemien/novel-cov/covid-zertifikat.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="218879">
        <title>Coronavirus: viaggi all’estero e cifre nel mondo</title>
        <uri>https://www.bag.admin.ch/bag/it/home/krankheiten/ausbrueche-epidemien-pandemien/aktuelle-ausbrueche-epidemien/novel-cov/empfehlungen-fuer-reisende/auslandsreisen.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="218880">
        <title>Re-open EU</title>
        <uri>https://reopen.europa.eu/it/</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>EU recognises Swiss COVID certificate</title>
      <lead>The EU has officially recognised the Swiss COVID certificate as equivalent. For its part, Switzerland recognises the certificates issued by EU and EFTA states. </lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;The EU has officially recognised the Swiss COVID certificate. At the same time, Switzerland for its part has assured recognition of the certificates issued by EU and EFTA states. The Swiss COVID certificate has been connected with the EU’s digital interface and will be usable throughout the entire EU/EFTA area starting last night, 8 to 9 July. International interoperability has been a high priority in the creation of the Swiss COVID certificate since the beginning of its development. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The EU Digital COVID Certificate is designed to facilitate safe travel during the COVID-19 pandemic. Individual states decide how the certificate can be used. Each country decides its own entry requirements and has the authority to adjust them on an ongoing basis according to how the epidemiological situation develops. It is therefore important for people travelling with the certificate to always find out about the current entry requirements for the country they are travelling to. &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Federal Office of Public Health Coronavirus Infoline: +41 58 463 00 00 COVID-19 vaccination infoline: +41 58 377 88 92</contact>
      <attachment id="218886">
        <title>FAQ: EU recognition and use of the COVID certificate in the EU area</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>94</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/67574.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <link id="218881">
        <title>Coronavirus: COVID certificate</title>
        <uri>https://www.bag.admin.ch/bag/en/home/krankheiten/ausbrueche-epidemien-pandemien/aktuelle-ausbrueche-epidemien/novel-cov/covid-zertifikat.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="218882">
        <title>Coronavirus: travel abroad and global statistics</title>
        <uri>https://www.bag.admin.ch/bag/en/home/krankheiten/ausbrueche-epidemien-pandemien/aktuelle-ausbrueche-epidemien/novel-cov/empfehlungen-fuer-reisende/auslandsreisen.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="218883">
        <title>Re-open EU</title>
        <uri>https://reopen.europa.eu/en/</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <keywords>
      <keyword id="109" org-id="317">
        <name lang="de">2019-nCoV-DE</name>
        <name lang="fr">2019-nCoV-FR</name>
        <name lang="it">2019-nCoV-IT</name>
        <name lang="en">2019-nCoV-EN</name>
      </keyword>
    </keywords>
    <topics>
      <topic id="15">
        <name lang="de">Gesundheit</name>
        <name lang="fr">Santé</name>
        <name lang="it">sanità</name>
        <name lang="en">Health</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="41">
        <name lang="de">Soziales</name>
        <name lang="fr">Social</name>
        <name lang="it">Opere sociali</name>
        <name lang="en">Social Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
