<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="27692" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2009-06-25</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="yes" id="602" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>601</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Generalsekretariat EFD</name>
      <name lang="fr">Secrétariat général DFF</name>
      <name lang="it">Segreteria generale DFF</name>
      <name lang="en">Secretariat-General FDF</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.efd.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.efd.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.efd.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.efd.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="601">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Finanzdepartement</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des finances</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale delle finanze</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Finance</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.efd.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.dff.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.efd.admin.ch/efd/it/home.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.efd.admin.ch/efd/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Fall des Eisernen Vorhangs vor 20 Jahren: Bundespräsident Merz nimmt an der Jubiläumsfeier in Budapest teil</title>
      <teaser>Auf Einladung der ungarischen Regierung nimmt Bundespräsident Hans-Rudolf Merz am kommenden Samstag, den 27. Juni 2009, an der Feier zum 20jährigen Jubiläum des Falls des Eisernen Vorhangs teil. Er wird am offiziellen Festakt im Parlaments-gebäude in Budapest eine Ansprache halten. An der Feier nehmen Entscheidträger der damaligen Zeit sowie amtierende Staatschefs und Politiker teil.</teaser>
      <lead/>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Auf Einladung der ungarischen Regierung nimmt Bundespräsident Hans-Rudolf Merz am kommenden Samstag, den 27. Juni 2009, an der Feier zum 20jährigen Jubiläum des Falls des Eisernen Vorhangs teil. Er wird am offiziellen Festakt im Parlaments-gebäude in Budapest eine Ansprache halten. An der Feier nehmen Entscheidträger der damaligen Zeit sowie amtierende Staatschefs und Politiker teil.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Am 27. Juni sind es genau 20 Jahre her, seit Ungarn im Einverständnis mit Österreich seine Grenzen öffnete und so vor allem Menschen aus der damaligen DDR die Flucht in den Westen ermöglichte. Der Fall der Berliner Mauer am 9. November 1989 bedeutete das definitive Ende des Eisernen Vorhangs.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Roland Meier, Mediensprecher EFD, Tel.031 322 60 86</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>20e anniversaire de la chute du rideau de fer: le président de la Confédération participe aux festivités</title>
      <teaser>Le samedi 27 juin 2009, le président de la Confédération Hans-Rudolf Merz participera aux festivités organisées à l'occasion du 20e anniversaire de la chute du rideau de fer, auxquelles il a été invité par le gouvernement hongrois. Il prononcera une allocution lors de la cérémonie officielle qui se tiendra au palais du Parlement, à Budapest. Certains dirigeants de l'époque ainsi que des chefs d'Etat et des personnalités politiques en exercice prendront part à l'événement.</teaser>
      <lead/>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Le samedi 27 juin 2009, le président de la Confédération Hans-Rudolf Merz participera aux festivités organisées à l'occasion du 20e&amp;nbsp;anniversaire de la chute du rideau de fer, auxquelles il a été invité par le gouvernement hongrois. Il prononcera une allocution lors de la cérémonie officielle qui se tiendra au palais du Parlement, à Budapest. Certains dirigeants de l'époque ainsi que des chefs d'Etat et des personnalités politiques en exercice prendront part à l'événement.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Le 27 juin, il y aura exactement 20&amp;nbsp;ans que la Hongrie a ouvert ses frontières, en accord avec l'Autriche, permettant ainsi surtout à des ressortissants de l'ex-Allemagne de l'Est de fuir vers l'Ouest. La chute du mur de Berlin, le 9 novembre 1989, marqua la fin définitive du rideau de fer.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Roland Meier, porte-parole du DFF, tél.: 031 322 60 86</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>20° anniversario della caduta della cortina di ferro: il presidente della Confederazione Merz partecipa alla commemorazione</title>
      <teaser>Il prossimo 27 giugno il presidente della Confederazione Hans-Rudolf Merz parteciperà su invito del governo ungherese ai festeggiamenti per il 20° anniversario della caduta della cortina di ferro e pronuncerà un discorso durante la commemorazione ufficiale che si terrà a Budapest nel palazzo del Parlamento. Saranno presenti alcuni protagonisti del passato che detenevano il potere decisionale, nonché capi di governo e politici in carica.</teaser>
      <lead/>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Il prossimo 27&amp;nbsp;giugno il presidente della Confederazione Hans-Rudolf Merz parteciperà su invito del governo ungherese ai festeggiamenti per il 20° anniversario della caduta della cortina di ferro e pronuncerà un discorso durante la commemorazione ufficiale che si terrà a Budapest nel palazzo del Parlamento. Saranno presenti alcuni protagonisti del passato che detenevano il potere decisionale, nonché capi di governo e politici in carica.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Il 27&amp;nbsp;giugno di 20 anni fa l'Ungheria aprì le sue frontiere d'intesa con l'Austria permettendo soprattutto a cittadini dell'ex DDR di fuggire a ovest. Il 9&amp;nbsp;novembre 1989 la caduta del muro di Berlino segnò la fine della cortina di ferro.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Roland Meier, portavoce DFF, tel. 031 322 60 86</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>20 years since fall of the Iron Curtain: President Merz to attend anniversary celebrations in Budapest</title>
      <teaser>At the invitation of the Hungarian government, President Hans-Rudolf Merz will attend the celebration to mark the 20th anniversary of the fall of the Iron Curtain on 27 June. He will deliver an address at the official ceremony in Parliament in Budapest. The celebrations will be attended by decision-makers from that period as well as by current heads of State and politicians.</teaser>
      <lead/>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;At the invitation of the Hungarian government, President Hans-Rudolf Merz will attend the celebration to mark the 20th anniversary of the fall of the Iron Curtain on 27 June. He will deliver an address at the official ceremony in Parliament in Budapest. The celebrations will be attended by decision-makers from that period as well as by current heads of State and politicians.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;On 27 June it will be twenty years to the day since Hungary, with the agreement of Austria, opened its borders thereby enabling people mainly from the former GDR to flee to the West. The fall of the Berlin Wall on 9 November 1989 marked the definitive end of the Iron Curtain.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Roland Meier, FDF Press Officer, Tel.031 322 60 86</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <keywords>
      <keyword id="234" org-id="602">
        <name lang="de">Eveline Widmer-Schlumpf, Bundespräsidentin 2012</name>
        <name lang="fr">Eveline Widmer-Schlumpf, présidente de la Confédération en 2012</name>
        <name lang="it">Eveline Widmer-Schlumpf, presidente della Confederazione 2012</name>
        <name lang="en">Eveline Widmer-Schlumpf, President of the Swiss Confederation 2012</name>
      </keyword>
    </keywords>
    <topics>
      <topic id="10">
        <name lang="de">Bundesrat</name>
        <name lang="fr">Conseil fédéral</name>
        <name lang="it">Consiglio federale</name>
        <name lang="en">Federal Council</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="33">
        <name lang="de">Bundespräsident/-in</name>
        <name lang="fr">Président/e de la Confédération</name>
        <name lang="it">Presidente della Confederazione</name>
        <name lang="en">President of the Swiss Confederation</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
