<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="24171" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2005-12-09</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="401" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>401</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Justiz- und Polizeidepartement</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de justice et police</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale di giustizia e polizia</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Justice and Police</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.ejpd.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.ejpd.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.ejpd.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.ejpd.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-ejpd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">Info@gs-ejpd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-ejpd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-ejpd.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="401">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Justiz- und Polizeidepartement</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de justice et police</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale di giustizia e polizia</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Justice and Police</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.ejpd.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.ejpd.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.ejpd.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.ejpd.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-ejpd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">Info@gs-ejpd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-ejpd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-ejpd.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Einen modernen und sicheren Finanzplatz schaffen - Bundesrat will das Haager Wertpapierübereinkommen unterzeichnen</title>
      <lead>Der Bundesrat hat am Freitag beschlossen, das Haager Wertpapierübereinkommen zu unterzeichnen. Damit will er einen Beitrag zur Schaffung eines modernen und sicheren Finanzplatzes leisten. Eine Botschaft zur Ratifikation des Übereinkommens ist in Bearbeitung.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Aktien und andere Wertpapiere werden heute in der Regel nicht mehr durch die Anleger selbst, sondern durch Finanzintermediäre verwahrt. Der Besitz des Wertpapiers hat bei dieser mediatisierten Wertpapierverwahrung keine Bedeutung mehr. Der Anspruch eines Anlegers auf eine bestimmte Anzahl Wertpapiere ist durch eine Gutschrift in einem Konto ausgewiesen, das der Finanzintermediär auf den Namen des Anlegers führt. Die Wertpapierbestände der Finanzintermediäre sind ihrerseits durch Gutschriften in Wertpapierkonten bei einer zentralen Wertpapierverwahrungsstelle ausgewiesen. Die rechtlichen Grundlagen der mediatisierten Wertpapierverwahrung sind heute veraltet und müssen modernisiert werden.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; &lt;b&gt;Einheitliche Rechtsanwendung&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt; Das Haager Wertpapierübereinkommen ist das bedeutendste Projekt zur Vereinheitlichung des internationalen Privatrechts im Bereich der mediatisiert verwahrten Wertpapiere. Dieses unter Mitwirkung der Schweiz erarbeitete Übereinkommen enthält Regeln, um das bei grenzüberschreitenden Wertpapiergeschäften anzuwendende Recht bestimmen zu können. Diesem sog. Kollisionsrecht kommt entscheidende Bedeutung zu, weil der Anteil der grenzüberschreitenden Wertpapiergeschäfte besonders hoch ist und zugleich die Rechtsunsicherheit gross ist. Die mediatisierte und elektronische Wertpapierverwahrung hat nämlich dazu geführt, dass sich nur noch mit äusserst grossem Aufwand feststellen lässt, wo ein Wertpapier verwahrt wird und welches Recht demzufolge anwendbar ist. Das Haager Wertpapierübereinkommen schafft hier Klarheit. Es lässt eine begrenzte Rechtswahl durch die Parteien zu und gewährleistet eine einheitliche Rechtsanwendung&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; &lt;b&gt;Übernahme ins schweizerische Recht&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt; Zurzeit steht noch nicht fest, wann das Haager Wertpapierübereinkommen in Kraft treten wird. Der Bundesrat beabsichtigt deshalb, die Regeln dieses Übereinkommens in das Bundesgesetz über das Internationale Privatrecht (IPRG) zu übernehmen. Damit wird dieses moderne Regelungswerk bis zum völkerrechtlichen Inkrafttreten als autonomes Recht gelten und die Rechtssicherheit des schweizerischen Finanzplatzes erhöhen. Das Eidg. Justiz- und Polizeidepartement (EJPD) und das Eidg. Finanzdepartement (EFD) werden die Botschaft zur Ergänzung des IPRG und zur Ratifikation des Haager Wertpapierübereinkommens sowie zum Bucheffektengesetz, welches das Wertpapierrecht inhaltlich modernisiert, ausarbeiten.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Thomas Mayer, Bundesamt für Justiz, T +41 31 323 06 68</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Faire de la Suisse une place financière moderne et sûre - Le Conseil fédéral entend signer la Convention de La Haye sur la loi applicable à certains droits sur des titres détenus auprès d’un intermédiaire</title>
      <lead>Vendredi, le Conseil fédéral a décidé de signer la convention de La Haye sur les titres. Ce faisant, il veut contribuer à faire de la Suisse une place financière moderne et sûre. Un message relatif à la ratification de ladite convention est en cours d’élaboration.</lead>
      <text link="no">Aujourd’hui les actions et autres titres ne sont, en règle générale, plus détenus auprès des investisseurs eux-mêmes, mais auprès d’intermédiaires financiers. Dans ces conditions, la conservation des papiers-valeurs par les investisseurs a perdu toute son importance. Les droits de propriété sur un nombre déterminé de titres sont attestés par un crédit porté sur un compte que l’intermédiaire financier gère au nom de l’investisseur. Quant aux stocks de papiers-valeurs détenus par les intermédiaires financiers, leur existence est attestée par des crédits portés à des comptes de titres auprès d’un dépositaire central. Les normes qui régissent actuellement la détention de titres auprès d’un intermédiaire sont surannées et, partant, doivent être actualisées. &lt;b&gt;&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Garantir une application uniforme du droit&lt;br /&gt; &lt;/b&gt;La convention de La Haye sur les titres est le projet le plus important d’unification du droit international privé concernant les titres détenus auprès d’intermédiaires. Cette convention à l’élaboration de laquelle la Suisse a participé, contient des normes permettant de déterminer la loi applicable lors de transactions internationales portant sur des titres (papiers-valeurs et droits-valeurs). Ces règles dites de conflit de lois revêtent une importance éminente parce que les transactions internationales portant sur les titres représentent une part considérable de l’ensemble des transactions dans ce domaine et souffrent d’une insécurité juridique caractérisée. L’essor pris par le dépôt de titres auprès d’un intermédiaire et la gestion de ceux-ci au moyen de l’informatique ont précisément eu pour effet qu’il est aujourd’hui extrêmement difficile de localiser le titre et partant de déterminer la loi applicable en la matière. La convention de La Haye sur les titres apporte plus de clarté. Elle autorise les parties à faire, dans certaines limites une élection de droit et assure une application uniforme du droit.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; &lt;b&gt;Intégration des règles de la convention dans le droit suisse&lt;br /&gt; &lt;/b&gt;A l’heure actuelle, on ne connaît pas encore la date à laquelle la convention de La Haye sur les titres entrera en vigueur. Aussi, le Conseil fédéral a l’intention de reprendre les règles de cet instrument international dans la loi fédérale sur le droit international privé (LDIP). Cet ensemble de normes modernes sera appliqué à titre de droit autonome jusqu’à l’entrée en vigueur de la convention, ce qui ne pourra qu’accroître la sécurité juridique pour la place financière suisse. Le Département fédéral de justice et police (DFJP) et le Département fédéral des finances (DFF) élaboreront le message relatif au complément à apporter à la LDIP, à la ratification de la convention de La Haye sur les titres ainsi qu’au projet de loi sur lesdits titres intermédiés qui permettra d’actualiser le droit régissant les papiers-valeurs.</text>
      <contact>Thomas Mayer, Office fédéral de la justice, T +41 31 323 06 68</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Per una piazza finanziaria moderna e sicura - Il Consiglio federale si appresta a firmare la Convenzione dell'Aia sugli strumenti finanziari</title>
      <lead>Venerdì il Consiglio federale ha deciso di firmare la Convenzione dell'Aia sulla legge applicabile ad alcuni diritti su strumenti finanziari detenuti presso un intermediario, contribuendo in tal modo a rendere moderna e sicura la piazza finanziaria svizzera. Il messaggio concernente la ratifica della Convenzione è in elaborazione.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Di norma, oggi le azioni e gli altri titoli non sono più custoditi dall'investitore stesso, ma da intermediari finanziari. Poiché la custodia è mediata, il possesso del titolo non riveste più alcuna importanza. I diritti di un investitore su un determinato pacchetto di titoli sono accreditati su un conto gestito dall'intermediario a nome dell'investitore. A loro volta, i titoli gestiti dall'intermediario sono accreditati su appositi conti presso un servizio centrale di custodia dei titoli. Le basi legali della custodia mediata di titoli sono ormai obsolete e vanno pertanto modernizzate.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Unificazione delle norme applicabili&lt;br /&gt; &lt;/b&gt;La Convenzione dell'Aia sugli strumenti finanziari è il principale progetto mirante a unificare le norme di diritto internazionale privato concernenti la custodia mediata dei titoli. Elaborata con il concorso della Svizzera, la Convenzione prevede regole che determinano il diritto applicabile alle operazioni transfrontaliere riguardanti titoli. Queste cosiddette norme di conflitto rivestono grande importanza poiché tali operazioni sono particolarmente frequenti e al riguardo regna una grande incertezza giuridica. La custodia mediata e in forma elettronica dei titoli ha reso estremamente difficile stabilire il luogo in cui un titolo è custodito, rendendo quindi arduo determinare il diritto applicabile. La Convenzione dell'Aia sugli strumenti finanziari fa chiarezza in merito, limitando la scelta alle parti del diritto applicabile e garantendo l'applicazione uniforme delle norme.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Trasposizione nel diritto interno&lt;br /&gt; &lt;/b&gt;Poiché non è dato sapere quando entrerà in vigore la Convenzione dell'Aia sugli strumenti finanziari, il Consiglio federale intende integrare le norme della Convenzione nella legge federale sul diritto internazionale privato (LDIP). Queste moderne disposizioni saranno quindi applicabili fino all'entrata in vigore della Convenzione, contribuendo ad accrescere la certezza giuridica della piazza finanziaria svizzera. Il messaggio concernente la modifica della LDIP, la ratifica della Convenzione dell'Aia e la legge sui titoli contabili (la quale modernizza la legislazione sui titoli) sarà elaborato dal Dipartimento federale di giustizia e polizia (DFGP) e dal Dipartimento federale delle finanze (DFF).&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Thomas Mayer, Ufficio federale di giustizia, T +41 31 323 06 68</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Creating a secure financial centre for today's world - Swiss Federal Council to sign Hague Securities Convention</title>
      <lead>The Swiss Federal Council decided on Friday to sign the Hague Convention on the Law Applicable to Certain Rights in Respect of Securities Held With an Intermediary. In doing so, it aims to help create a secure financial centre for today's world. An Opinion on the ratification of the Convention is currently in preparation.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Nowadays, shares and other securities are generally held in safekeeping by a financial intermediary rather than by the investors themselves. Where securities are held with an intermediary, the issue of who actually is in the possession of security certificates becomes irrelevant. The investor's claim to a certain number of securities is recorded in the form of a credit to an account that the financial intermediary operates in the name of the investor. The financial intermediary's securities holdings are, in turn, evidenced by credits to securities accounts which it holds with a central securities depository. The legal foundations for securities held by intermediaries no longer reflect current circumstances and must be modernized.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Uniform application of law&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt; The Hague Securities Convention is the most important project aimed at standardizing private international law as it applies to securities held with intermediaries. The Convention, in the drafting of which Switzerland was involved, contains rules which will help determine applicable law in cross-border securities transactions. These rules on what is known as conflict of laws are of decisive importance, because the proportion of cross-border securities transactions is high, as is the degree of legal uncertainty. Specifically, the holding of securities with intermediaries and electronically has led to a situation which requires an enormous amount of effort and resources to establish where exactly physical securities are being held and, as a result, which law applies. The Hague Securities Convention creates clarity in this respect. It allows the parties to choose – to a certain extent – the applicable law to their relationship and also guarantees a uniform application of the law.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Adoption into Swiss law&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt; It is not yet clear when the Hague Securities Convention will enter into force. The Federal Council is therefore intending to incorporate the Convention's rules in Swiss federal legislation on private international law (the &lt;em&gt;Bundesgesetz über das Internationale Privatrecht&lt;/em&gt;, or IPRG). The progressive regulations of the Convention will therefore apply as autonomous law until the Convention itself becomes international law, thereby improving legal certainty in Switzerland's financial sector. The Federal Department of Justice and Police (FDJP) and the Federal Department of Finance (FDF) will now draw up the Federal Council Opinion on the addition to the IPRG and the ratification of the Hague Securities Convention, as well as on the Securities Held With an Intermediary Act (&lt;em&gt;Bucheffektengesetz / Loi fédérale sur les titres intermédiés&lt;/em&gt;), which will bring the content of the Swiss securities legislation up to date.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Thomas Mayer, Federal Office of Justice, T +41 31 323 06 68</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="10">
        <name lang="de">Bundesrat</name>
        <name lang="fr">Conseil fédéral</name>
        <name lang="it">Consiglio federale</name>
        <name lang="en">Federal Council</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
