<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="30" revoked="no">
    <version>2</version>
    <pubdate>2005-05-20</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="yes" id="603" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>601</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidg. Finanzverwaltung</name>
      <name lang="fr">Administration fédérale des finances</name>
      <name lang="it">Amministrazione federale delle finanze</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Finance Administration</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.efv.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.efv.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.efv.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.efv.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@efv.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@efv.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@efv.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@efv.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="601">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Finanzdepartement</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des finances</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale delle finanze</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Finance</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.efd.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.dff.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.efd.admin.ch/efd/it/home.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.efd.admin.ch/efd/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>EFD publiziert Kennzahlen zum Finanzstandort Schweiz auf dem Internet</title>
      <lead>Das Eidg. Finanzdepartement EFD publiziert ab heute auf www.efd.admin.ch/finanzplatz eine Auswahl von Kennzahlen zum Finanzstandort Schweiz. Die Angaben werden periodisch aktualisiert. Um diesen Service in den Fachkriesen bekannt zu machen, veröffentlicht das EFD die Zahlen ausnahmsweise auch in einer kleinen Broschüre.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Die Wirtschaftsaktivität des Finanzdienstleistungssektors in der Schweiz wird statistisch von mehreren öffentlichen und privaten Stellen erfasst. Trotz der zahlreichen Angaben ist es nicht einfach, die aus volkswirtschaftlicher Sicht wichtigsten Kennzahlen zum Finanzplatz Schweiz in geraffter Form zu finden.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Die Kennzahlen des EFD auf www.efd.admin.ch/finanzplatz stützen sich auf zehn ausgewählte Indikatoren zur volkswirtschaftlichen Bedeutung des Finanzplatzes Schweiz, die sich ausschliesslich auf offizielle Quellen beziehen. Dargestellt werden die aussagekräftigsten Strukturdaten zum schweizerischen Finanzsektor und deren Entwicklung über die letzten Jahre.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Die nur ein einziges Mal produzierte Broschüre: "Kennzahlen zum Finanzstandort Schweiz" wird durch das EFD, die Schweizerische Bankiervereinigung und die SWX Swiss Exchange den Fachkreisen zugestellt.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Rudolf Zurkinden, Eidg. Finanzverwaltung Tel. 031 325 09 20</contact>
      <link id="235">
        <title>Kennzahlen zum Finanzstandort Schweiz</title>
        <uri>http://www.efd.admin.ch/finanzplatz</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Publication par le DFF de chiffres-clés relatifs à la place financière suisse</title>
      <lead>Le Département fédéral des finances (DFF) publie dès aujour-d'hui sur le site www.dff.admin.ch/placefinanciere une sélection de chiffres-clés relatifs à la place financière suisse. Ces informa-tions, qui seront régulièrement mises à jour, sont également pu-bliées à titre exceptionnel sous forme de brochure, afin de faire connaître ce service dans les milieux spécialisés.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Différents organismes, publics ou privés, publient en Suisse des statisti-ques concernant le secteur des services financiers. Malgré l’abondance d’informations disponibles, il n’est pas simple d’obtenir un aperçu des principales données macro-économiques concernant la place financière suisse.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Les chiffres-clés du DFF, accessibles sur le site www.dff.admin.ch/placefinanciere, se basent sur dix indicateurs, tous tirés de sources officielles, qui reflètent l’importance macro-économique de la place financière suisse. La priorité a été accordée aux données structurelles qui caractérisent le mieux le secteur financier suisse ainsi que son évolution au cours des dernières années.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;La brochure intitulée "Chiffres-clés relatifs à la place financière suisse", publiée une seule fois sous forme imprimée, est distribuée aux milieux spécialisés par l’intermédiaire du DFF, de l’Association suisse des ban-quiers et de Swiss Exchange (SWX).&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Rudolf Zurkinden, Administration fédérale des finances tél. 031.32509 20</contact>
      <link id="236">
        <title>Chiffres-clés relatifs à la place financière suisse</title>
        <uri>http://www.dff.admin.ch/placefinanciere</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>FDF publishes key data relating to the Swiss financial centre on the Internet</title>
      <lead>The Federal Department of Finance FDF is today publishing a selection of key data relating to the Swiss financial centre which can be viewed at www.finance.admin.ch/financialcentre. The information will be updated at regular intervals. In order to generate awareness about this service among experts in the field, the FDF will on this occasion also be publishing the data in the form of a small brochure.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Statistics on the economic activity of the financial services sector in Switzerland are gathered by a number of institutions both private and public. Despite the wealth of available information it is not altogether easy to find the most important economic data on the Swiss financial centre in concise form.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The key data presented by the FDF at www.finance.admin.ch/financialcentre are based on ten selected indicators of economic relevance relating to the Swiss financial centre and are drawn exclusively from official sources. The information presented is the most significant structural data on the Swiss financial sector and developments over recent years.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The one-off brochure: "Key data on the Swiss financial centre" will be sent out to experts in the field by the FDF, the Swiss Bankers’ Association and SWX Swiss Exchange.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Rudolf Zurkinden, Fed. Finance Administration, tel. 031 325 09 20</contact>
      <link id="237">
        <title>Key data relating to the Swiss financial centre</title>
        <uri>http://www.finance.admin.ch/financialcentre</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <offers>
      <offer id="3" org-id="603">
        <name lang="de">Wirtschaft, Währung</name>
        <name lang="fr">Economie, monnaie</name>
        <name lang="it">Economia, Moneta</name>
        <name lang="en">Economic, Monetary affairs</name>
      </offer>
    </offers>
    <keywords>
      <keyword id="126" org-id="603">
        <name lang="de">Finanzplatz Schweiz</name>
        <name lang="fr">Place financière suisse</name>
        <name lang="it">Piazza finanziaria svizzera</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland as a financial centre</name>
      </keyword>
    </keywords>
    <topics>
      <topic id="35">
        <name lang="de">Finanzplatz</name>
        <name lang="fr">Place financière</name>
        <name lang="it">Piazza finanziaria</name>
        <name lang="en">Financial Centre</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="47">
        <name lang="de">Wirtschaft</name>
        <name lang="fr">Économie</name>
        <name lang="it">Economia</name>
        <name lang="en">Economic Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
