<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="51712" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2014-01-20</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="201" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>201</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="201">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Besuch des italienischen Wirtschafts- und Finanzministers Fabrizio Saccomanni am 30. Januar</title>
      <lead>Der italienische Wirtschafts- und Finanzminister Fabrizio Saccomanni kommt am 30. Januar 2014 in die Schweiz. Gemeinsam mit Bundespräsident Didier Burkhalter wird er das 2. Forum für den Dialog zwischen Italien und der Schweiz eröffnen. Er wird auch die Vorsteherin des Eidgenössischen Finanzdepartements (EFD), Bundesrätin Eveline Widmer Schlumpf, treffen.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Der Besuch soll dazu dienen, die Gespräche zwischen der Schweiz und Italien über Steuer- und Finanzfragen fortzusetzen. Der Präsident des Ministerrates Italiens, Enrico Letta, musste seinerseits einen Arbeitsbesuch in der Schweiz auf einen späteren Zeitpunkt verschieben. Ein Staatsbesuch von Giorgio Napolitano, Präsident der Italienischen Republik, ist für den Monat Mai dieses Jahres geplant.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Auskünfte:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Information EDA&lt;br /&gt;Jean-Marc Crevoisier, Chef Information&lt;br /&gt;079 / 763 84 10&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Staatssekretariat für internationale Finanzfragen – SIF&lt;br /&gt;Mario Tuor, Leiter Kommunikation&lt;br /&gt;031 / 322 46 16&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Kommunikation EDA Bundeshaus West CH-3003 Bern Tel. Kommunikationsservice: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Medienstelle: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <link id="118521">
        <title>Bilaterale Beziehungen Schweiz-Italien</title>
        <uri>http://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home/reps/eur/vita/bilita.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Visite du ministre italien de l’économie et des finances Fabrizio Saccomanni le 30 janvier</title>
      <lead>Le ministre italien de l’économie et des finances Fabrizio Saccomanni se rendra en Suisse le 30 janvier. Il ouvrira le 2ème Forum pour le dialogue entre la Suisse et l’Italie en compagnie du président de la Confédération Didier Burkhalter. Il rencontrera également la conseillère fédérale Eveline Widmer Schlumpf, cheffe du Département fédéral des finances (DFF). </lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Ce déplacement permettra de continuer à faire avancer les discussions entre l’Italie et la Suisse sur les questions fiscales et financières. Le président du Conseil des ministres italien M. Enrico Letta a quant à lui dû reporter sa visite de travail en Suisse qui interviendra ainsi plus tard cette année. Une visite d’Etat du président de la République italienne, M. Giorgio Napolitano, est quant à elle prévue au mois de mai prochain.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Renseignements:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Information DFAE&lt;br /&gt;Jean-Marc Crevoisier, Chef Information&lt;br /&gt;079 / 763 84 10&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Secrétariat d'Etat aux questions financières internationales – SFI&lt;br /&gt;Mario Tuor, Chef information&lt;br /&gt;031 / 322 46 16&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Communication DFAE Palais fédéral ouest CH-3003 Berne Tél. Service de communication: +41 58 462 31 53 Tél. Service de presse: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <link id="118522">
        <title>Relations bilatérales Suisse – Italie</title>
        <uri>http://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/home/reps/eur/vita/bilita.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Visita del ministro italiano dell'economia e delle finanze Fabrizio Saccomanni il 30 gennaio</title>
      <lead>Il 30 gennaio il ministro italiano dell'economia e delle finanze Fabrizio Saccomanni sarà in Svizzera, dove inaugurerà il secondo Forum per il dialogo tra l'Italia e la Svizzera insieme al presidente della Confederazione Didier Burkhalter. Saccomanni incontrerà inoltre la consigliera federale Eveline Widmer Schlumpf, capo del Dipartimento federale delle finanze (DFF).</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Questo viaggio del ministro italiano consentirà di portare avanti le discussioni tra l'Italia e la Svizzera sulle questioni fiscali e finanziarie. Il presidente del Consiglio dei ministri italiano Enrico Letta ha dovuto rinviare la sua visita di lavoro in Svizzera, che si terrà comunque entro l'anno. Una visita di Stato del presidente della Repubblica Italiana Giorgio Napolitano è invece prevista nel prossimo mese di maggio.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Contatti:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Informazione DFAE&lt;br /&gt;Jean-Marc Crevoisier, Capo dell’Informazione &lt;br /&gt;079 / 763 84 10&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Segreteria di Stato per le questioni finanziarie internazionali – SIF&lt;br /&gt;Mario Tuor, Capo dell’Informazione&lt;br /&gt;031 / 322 46 16&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Comunicazione DFAE Palazzo federale ovest CH-3003 Berna Tel. Servizio di comunicazione: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Servizio stampa: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <link id="118523">
        <title>Relazioni bilaterali Svizzera – Italia</title>
        <uri>http://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/home/reps/eur/vita/bilita.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Visit by the Italian minister of economy and finance, Fabrizio Saccomanni, on 30 January 2014</title>
      <lead>The Italian minister of economy and finance, Fabrizio Saccomanni, will travel to Switzerland on 30 January 2014. He will open the second forum for dialogue between Switzerland and Italy in the company of the president of the Confederation, Didier Burkhalter. He will also meet Federal Councillor Eveline Widmer Schlumpf, head of the Federal Department of Finance (FDF).</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;This visit will contribute to advancing the discussions between Switzerland and Italy on fiscal and financial issues. The prime minister of Italy, Enrico Letta, has had to postpone his working visit to Switzerland to later this year. A state visit by the president of the Italian Republic, Giorgio Napolitano, is scheduled for the month of May this year.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Contacts&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Information FDFA&lt;br /&gt;Jean-Marc Crevoisier, Head of Information &lt;br /&gt;079 / 763 84 10&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;State Secretariat for International Financial Matters - SIF&lt;br /&gt;Mario Tuor, Head of Information&lt;br /&gt;031 / 322 46 16&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>FDFA Communication Federal Palace West Wing CH-3003 Bern, Switzerland Tel. Communication service: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Press service: +41 58 460 55 55 E-mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @SwissMFA</contact>
      <link id="118524">
        <title>Bilateral relations between Switzerland and Italy</title>
        <uri>http://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home/reps/eur/vita/bilita.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
