<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="52190" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2014-03-03</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="yes" id="1060" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>601</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Staatssekretariat für internationale Finanzfragen</name>
      <name lang="fr">Secrétariat d'Etat aux questions financières internationales</name>
      <name lang="it">Segreteria di Stato per le questioni finanziarie internazionali</name>
      <name lang="en">State Secretariat for International Financial Matters</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.sif.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.sif.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.sif.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.sif.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@sif.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@sif.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@sif.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@sif.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="601">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Finanzdepartement</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des finances</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale delle finanze</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Finance</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.efd.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.dff.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.efd.admin.ch/efd/it/home.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.efd.admin.ch/efd/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Arbeitstreffen von Staatssekretär Jacques de Watteville und OECD-Steuerdirektor Pascal Saint-Amans in Bern</title>
      <lead>In Bern haben sich heute Staatssekretär Jacques de Watteville und der OECD-Direktor für Steuerpolitik, Pascal Saint-Amans, zu einer Arbeitssitzung getroffen. Sie erörterten den Stand des OECD-Projekts zur Unternehmensbesteuerung (BEPS, Base Erosion and Profit Shifting) sowie der Arbeiten zur Entwicklung des globalen Standards für den automatischen Informationsaustausch. Zur Schweizer Delegation gehörte auch der Direktor der Eidgenössischen Steuerverwaltung, Adrian Hug.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Mit dem BEPS-Projekt soll insbesondere erreicht werden, dass Gewinne am Ort der tatsächlichen wirtschaftlichen Tätigkeit besteuert, aggressive Steuerplanung unterbunden und die internationale Nichtbesteuerung vermieden werden. Damit sollen gleich lange Spiesse zwischen den Wirtschaftsstandorten entstehen. Die ersten Ergebnisse des BEPS-Projekt werden für September 2014 erwartet; auf OECD-Ebene dürften die Gesamtarbeiten bis im Dezember 2015 abgeschlossen werden. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Der Kampf gegen Steuerhinterziehung gehört zu den Prioritäten der Organisation für wirtschaftliche Zusammenarbeit und Entwicklung (OECD). Als OECD-Mitglied bekennt sich auch die Schweiz zu diesem Ziel. Der globale Standard zum Automatischen Informationsaustausch wird in den nächsten Monaten in der OECD finalisiert. Die Gesprächspartner betonten, dass der Standard auf Reziprozität basiere, den Datenschutz berücksichtige und dass wirtschaftlich Berechtigte von Finanzkonstrukten identifiziert werden müssten. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Weitere Gesprächsthemen waren das Global Forum für Steuertransparenz und internationale Aspekte der Mehrwertsteuer. &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Mario Tuor, Kommunikation Staatssekretariat für internationale Finanzfragen SIF Tel. +41 31 322 46 16, mario.tuor@sif.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Rencontre à Berne entre le Secrétaire d’Etat aux questions financières internationales, Jacques de Watteville, et le directeur du CTP de l’OCDE, Pascal Saint-Amans</title>
      <lead>Le Secrétaire d’Etat aux questions financières internationales, Jacques de Watteville, et le directeur du Centre de politique et d’administration fiscales (CTP) de l’Organisation de coopération et de développement économiques (OCDE), Pascal Saint-Amans, se sont rencontrés aujourd’hui à Berne pour une séance de travail. Ils ont fait le point sur l’état d’avancement du projet de l’OCDE sur l’imposition des entreprises (BEPS, Base Erosion and Profit Shifting [Erosion de la base d’imposition et transfert de bénéfices]) et sur les travaux visant à développer une norme internationale en matière d’échange automatique de renseignements. Le directeur de l’Administration fédérale des contributions, Adrian Hug, faisait également partie de la délégation suisse.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Le projet BEPS doit notamment permettre d'imposer les bénéfices à l'endroit où l'activité économique se déroule, d'empêcher la planification fiscale agressive et d'éviter la non-imposition internationale. Ainsi, les places économiques sont mises sur un pied d'égalité. Les premiers résultats du projet BEPS sont attendus pour septembre 2014, alors qu'au niveau de l'OCDE, les travaux devraient être achevés en décembre 2015. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;La lutte contre la soustraction d'impôt constitue une priorité pour l'OCDE. La Suisse, en tant que membre de l'organisation, s'engage pour la réalisation de cet objectif. Au cours des prochains mois, l'OCDE finalisera la norme mondiale régissant l'échange automatique de renseignements. Les interlocuteurs ont souligné que la norme doit se fonder sur la réciprocité et prendre en considération la protection des données. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;La discussion a également porté sur le Forum mondial sur la transparence et l'échange de renseignements à des fins fiscales et des aspects liés à la TVA. &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Mario Tuor, Communication du Secrétariat d’Etat aux questions financières internationales (SFI) Tél. +41 31 322 46 16, mario.tuor@sif.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Incontro di lavoro a Berna tra il segretario di Stato Jacques de Watteville e il direttore del Centro per la politica e l’amministrazione fiscale dell’OCSE Pascal Saint-Amans</title>
      <lead>In data odierna il segretario di Stato Jacques de Watteville ha incontrato a Berna il direttore del Centro per la politica e l’amministrazione fiscale dell’Organizzazione per la cooperazione e lo sviluppo economici (OCSE) Pascal Saint-Amans per una riunione di lavoro. In tale occasione hanno discusso dello stato attuale del progetto BEPS (Base Erosion and Profit Shifting) relativo all’imposizione delle imprese e dei lavori riguardanti lo sviluppo dello standard globale per lo scambio automatico di informazioni. Della delegazione svizzera faceva parte anche il direttore dell’Amministrazione federale delle contribuzioni Adrian Hug.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Con il progetto BEPS si intende in particolare fare in modo che gli utili siano tassati sul luogo dell'attività economica effettiva e che siano impedite pianificazioni fiscali aggressive e la non imposizione internazionale. In tal modo si vuole creare condizioni eque tra le piazze economiche. I primi risultati del progetto BEPS sono attesi per settembre 2014. I lavori complessivi dell'OCSE dovrebbero essere conclusi entro dicembre 2015. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;La lotta alla sottrazione d'imposta rientra tra le priorità dell'OCSE. Nella sua veste di membro dell'OCSE anche la Svizzera si impegna per raggiungere questo obiettivo. Nei prossimi mesi verrà finalizzato nell'OCSE lo standard globale per lo scambio automatico di informazioni. Gli interlocutori hanno sottolineato che lo standard deve basarsi sul principio della reciprocità e tenere conto della protezione dei dati e che gli aventi economicamente diritto di strutture finanziarie devono essere identificati.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Altri temi oggetto di discussione sono stati il Forum globale sulla trasparenza a fini fiscali ed aspetti internazionali in materia di imposta sul valore aggiunto.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Mario Tuor, Comunicazione Segreteria di Stato per le questioni finanziarie internazionali (SFI), tel. +41 31 322 46 16, mario.tuor@sif.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>State Secretary Jacques de Watteville's working visit in Bern with Pascal Saint-Amans, Director of the OECD Centre for Tax Policy and Administration</title>
      <lead>Today in Bern, State Secretary Jacques de Watteville and the Director of the OECD Centre for Tax Policy and Administration, Pascal Saint-Amans, met for a working visit. They discussed the status of the OECD project on corporate taxation (BEPS, base erosion and profit shifting) and the work on developing the global standard for the automatic exchange of information. The Swiss delegation also included the Director of the Federal Tax Administration, Adrian Hug.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;The primary aims of the BEPS project are to ensure that profits are taxed in the location where the actual economic activity takes place, to prevent aggressive tax planning and to avoid international non-taxation. A level playing field should thereby be established between the business locations. The first results of the BEPS project are expected in September 2014, and the work as a whole is likely to end at the OECD level by December 2015. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Efforts to combat tax evasion are one of the priorities of the Organisation for Economic Co-operation and Development (OECD). As an OECD member, Switzerland is also committed to this objective. The global standard for the automatic exchange of information will be finalised in the OECD in the next few months. The parties emphasised that the standard has to be based on reciprocity, that data protection must be taken into account and that the beneficial owners of financial constructs must be identified. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Other topics of discussion were the Global Forum on Transparency and Exchange of Information for Tax Purposes and international aspects of value added tax.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Mario Tuor, Communications, State Secretariat for International Financial Matters (SIF) Tel.: 41 31 322 46 16, mario.tuor@sif.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <offers>
      <offer id="291" org-id="1060">
        <name lang="de">Wirtschaft, Währung, Finanzplatz</name>
        <name lang="fr">Economie, monnaie, place financière</name>
        <name lang="it">Economia, Moneta, Piazza finanziaria</name>
        <name lang="en">Economic, Monetary and Financial Affairs</name>
      </offer>
    </offers>
    <keywords>
      <keyword id="235" org-id="1060">
        <name lang="de">Internationale Steuerpolitik</name>
        <name lang="fr">Politique fiscale internationale</name>
        <name lang="it">Politica fiscale internazionale</name>
        <name lang="en">International tax policy</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="116" org-id="1060">
        <name lang="de">Finanzmarktkriminalität</name>
        <name lang="fr">Criminalité financière</name>
        <name lang="it">Criminalità nei mercati finanziari</name>
        <name lang="en">Financial-market crime</name>
      </keyword>
    </keywords>
    <topics>
      <topic id="35">
        <name lang="de">Finanzplatz</name>
        <name lang="fr">Place financière</name>
        <name lang="it">Piazza finanziaria</name>
        <name lang="en">Financial Centre</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="44">
        <name lang="de">Steuern</name>
        <name lang="fr">Impôts</name>
        <name lang="it">Imposte</name>
        <name lang="en">Taxation</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="47">
        <name lang="de">Wirtschaft</name>
        <name lang="fr">Économie</name>
        <name lang="it">Economia</name>
        <name lang="en">Economic Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
