<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="53464" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2014-06-23</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="1070" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>1070</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Der Bundesrat</name>
      <name lang="fr">Conseil fédéral</name>
      <name lang="it">Il Consiglio federale</name>
      <name lang="en">The Federal Council</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.admin.ch/gov/de/start.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.admin.ch/gov/fr/accueil.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.admin.ch/gov/it/pagina-iniziale.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.admin.ch/gov/en/start.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="yes" id="1060" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>601</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Staatssekretariat für internationale Finanzfragen</name>
      <name lang="fr">Secrétariat d'Etat aux questions financières internationales</name>
      <name lang="it">Segreteria di Stato per le questioni finanziarie internazionali</name>
      <name lang="en">State Secretariat for International Financial Matters</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.sif.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.sif.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.sif.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.sif.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@sif.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@sif.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@sif.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@sif.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="1070">
      <name lang="de">Der Bundesrat</name>
      <name lang="fr">Conseil fédéral</name>
      <name lang="it">Il Consiglio federale</name>
      <name lang="en">The Federal Council</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.admin.ch/gov/de/start.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.admin.ch/gov/fr/accueil.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.admin.ch/gov/it/pagina-iniziale.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.admin.ch/gov/en/start.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <department id="601">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Finanzdepartement</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des finances</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale delle finanze</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Finance</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.efd.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.dff.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.efd.admin.ch/efd/it/home.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.efd.admin.ch/efd/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Bundesrat setzt revidiertes Steueramtshilfegesetz in Kraft</title>
      <lead>Der Bundesrat hat beschlossen, das revidierte Steueramtshilfegesetz auf den 1. August 2014 in Kraft zu setzen. Das Referendum gegen die Vorlage wurde nicht ergriffen.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Die Referendumsfrist läuft am 10. Juli 2014 ab. Das Referendum wurde bisher nicht ergriffen. Falls dies so bleibt, wird das geänderte Gesetz auf den 1. August 2014 in Kraft gesetzt werden. Das Eidgenössische Parlament hat die Revision des Steueramtshilfegesetzes am 21. März 2014 gutgeheissen. Die Änderung umfasst eine neue Bestimmung, die in Ausnahmefällen ein Verfahren über die nachträgliche Information der beschwerdeberechtigten Personen vorsieht, sowie Präzisierungen in Bezug auf Gruppenersuchen. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Damit erfüllt die Schweiz den geltenden internationalen Amtshilfestandard in Steuersachen und eine zusätzliche Empfehlung des Global Forum on Tax Transparency.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Mario Tuor, Kommunikation Staatssekretariat für internationale Finanzfragen SIF Tel. +41 58 462 46 16, mario.tuor@sif.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="124177">
        <title>Bundesgesetz</title>
        <uri>http://www.admin.ch/opc/de/federal-gazette/2014/2887.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Le Conseil fédéral met en vigueur la loi sur l’assistance administrative fiscale</title>
      <lead>Le Conseil fédéral a décidé de mettre en vigueur au 1er août 2014 la loi révisée sur l’assistance administrative fiscale. Aucun référendum n’a été lancé contre le projet de loi.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Le délai référendaire court jusqu'au 10 juillet 2014. Aucun référendum n'a été demandé pour le moment. Si aucun référendum n'aboutit d'ici là, la loi révisée entrera en vigueur le 1er août 2014. Le Parlement a approuvé la révision de la loi sur l'assistance administrative fiscale le 21 mars 2014. Les modifications comportent, d'une part, une nouvelle disposition qui prévoit, dans des cas exceptionnels, une procédure sur l'information ultérieure des personnes habilitées à recourir et, d'autre part, des précisions concernant les demandes groupées. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;La Suisse respecte ainsi la norme en vigueur sur l'assistance administrative internationale en matière fiscale et une recommandation supplémentaire du Forum mondial sur la transparence et l'échange de renseignements à des fins fiscales. &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Mario Tuor, Communication du Secrétariat d’Etat aux questions financières internationales SFI Tél. +41 58 462 46 16, mario.tuor@sif.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="124178">
        <title>Loi fédérale</title>
        <uri>http://www.admin.ch/opc/fr/federal-gazette/2014/2797.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Il Consiglio federale pone in vigore la riveduta legge sull’assistenza amministrativa fiscale</title>
      <lead>Il Consiglio federale ha deciso di porre in vigore con effetto al 1° agosto 2014 la riveduta legge sull’assistenza amministrativa fiscale. Contro il progetto non è stato finora lanciato nessun referendum.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Il termine per il referendum scade il 10 luglio 2014. Finora il referendum non è ancora stato lanciato. In questo caso la riveduta legge sarà posta in vigore con effetto al 1° agosto 2014. Il Parlamento svizzero ha approvato la revisione della legge sull'assistenza amministrativa fiscale il 21 marzo 2014. La modifica comprende una nuova disposizione che in casi eccezionali prevede una procedura di informazione a posteriori delle persone legittimate a ricorrere, nonché precisazioni in merito a domande raggruppate. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;La Svizzera soddisfa quindi il vigente standard internazionale sull'assistenza amministrativa in materia fiscale come pure una raccomandazione supplementare del Global Forum on Tax Transparency. &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Mario Tuor, Comunicazione Segreteria di Stato per le questioni finanziarie internazionali SFI tel. +41 58 462 46 16, mario.tuor@sif.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="124179">
        <title>Legge federale</title>
        <uri>http://www.admin.ch/opc/it/federal-gazette/2014/2623.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Federal Council brings revised Tax Administrative Assistance Act into force</title>
      <lead>The Federal Council resolved to bring the revised Tax Administrative Assistance Act into force on 1 August 2014. No referendum has been called against the bill.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;The referendum deadline will expire on 10 July 2014, and no referendum has been called to date. If that remains the case, the amended act will enter into force on 1 August 2014. Parliament approved the revision of the Tax Administrative Assistance Act on 21 March 2014. The amendment includes a new provision that envisages a procedure with, in exceptional cases, deferred notification of persons entitled to appeal, as well as more precise specifications regarding group requests. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Switzerland will thereby comply with the applicable international standard for administrative assistance in tax matters as well as an additional recommendation of the Global Forum on Tax Transparency. &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Mario Tuor, Communications, State Secretariat for International Financial Matters SIF Tel. +41 58 462 46 16, mario.tuor@sif.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="124177">
        <title>Bundesgesetz</title>
        <uri>http://www.admin.ch/opc/de/federal-gazette/2014/2887.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <offers>
      <offer id="291" org-id="1060">
        <name lang="de">Wirtschaft, Währung, Finanzplatz</name>
        <name lang="fr">Economie, monnaie, place financière</name>
        <name lang="it">Economia, Moneta, Piazza finanziaria</name>
        <name lang="en">Economic, Monetary and Financial Affairs</name>
      </offer>
    </offers>
    <keywords>
      <keyword id="235" org-id="1060">
        <name lang="de">Internationale Steuerpolitik</name>
        <name lang="fr">Politique fiscale internationale</name>
        <name lang="it">Politica fiscale internazionale</name>
        <name lang="en">International tax policy</name>
      </keyword>
    </keywords>
    <topics>
      <topic id="35">
        <name lang="de">Finanzplatz</name>
        <name lang="fr">Place financière</name>
        <name lang="it">Piazza finanziaria</name>
        <name lang="en">Financial Centre</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="44">
        <name lang="de">Steuern</name>
        <name lang="fr">Impôts</name>
        <name lang="it">Imposte</name>
        <name lang="en">Taxation</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="47">
        <name lang="de">Wirtschaft</name>
        <name lang="fr">Économie</name>
        <name lang="it">Economia</name>
        <name lang="en">Economic Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
