<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="53617" revoked="no">
    <version>3</version>
    <pubdate>2014-07-01</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="yes" id="703" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>701</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Staatssekretariat für Wirtschaft</name>
      <name lang="fr">Secrétariat d'Etat à l'économie</name>
      <name lang="it">Segreteria di Stato dell'economia</name>
      <name lang="en">State Secretariat for Economic Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.seco.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.seco.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.seco.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.seco.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@seco.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@seco.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@seco.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@seco.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="701">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Wirtschaft, Bildung und Forschung</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'économie, de la formation et de la recherche</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'economia, della formazione e della ricerca</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Economic Affairs, Education and Research</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Die Schweiz und China feiern das Inkrafttreten des Freihandelsabkommens</title>
      <lead>Bundesrat Johann N. Schneider-Ammann hat am Dienstagnachmittag im Basler Rheinhafen die Feierlichkeiten zum Inkrafttreten des Freihandelsabkommens zwischen der Schweiz und China eröffnet. Für den Schweizer Aussenhandel ist dieses Freihandelsabkommen das bedeutendste seit jenem mit der Europäischen Union von 1972.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Fast genau ein Jahr nachdem Bundesrat Johann N. Schneider-Ammann und sein chinesischer Amtskollege, Handelsminister Gao Hucheng, am 6. Juli 2013 in Beijing das umfassende Freihandelsabkommen zwischen der Schweiz und China unterzeichnet hatten, tritt es am 1. Juli 2014 in Kraft. Die Wirtschaft und insbesondere die Exportwirtschaft hat auf diesen Moment gewartet, weil sich ihr Marktzugang in China gegenüber jenem der europäischen Konkurrenten verbessert.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Bundesrat Schneider-Ammann hat Wirtschafts- und Behördenvertreter zur Feier im Rheinhafen Basel eingeladen, weil der Ort wie kaum ein anderer in der Schweiz das Tor zur Welt darstellt. Als Vertreter des chinesischen Handelsministers nimmt der Botschafter Chinas bei der Welthandelsorganisation (WTO), Yu Jianhua, am Festakt teil. Gleichzeitig mit diesem Anlass in der Schweiz feiert auch die Volksrepublik China das neue Freihandelsabkommen. Die Direktorin des SECO, Staatssekretärin Marie-Gabrielle Ineichen-Fleisch, nimmt für die Schweiz an den Feierlichkeiten in Peking teil.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Die Volksrepublik China ist der wichtigste Handelspartner der Schweiz in Asien. Mit einem Handelsvolumen von über 20 Milliarden Franken im vergangenen Jahr ist China hinter der EU und den USA der drittwichtigste Handelspartner weltweit.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Das Freihandelsabkommen verbessert den gegenseitigen Marktzugang für Waren und Dienstleistungen. Mit dem Abkommen werden die Zölle - zum Teil mit Übergangsfristen - auf dem grössten Teil des bilateralen Handels vollständig oder teilweise abgebaut sowie die Rechtssicherheit für den bilateralen wirtschaftlichen Austausch und den Schutz des geistigen Eigentums erhöht. Das Freihandelsabkommen wird zusammen mit dem gleichzeitig abgeschlossenen bilateralen Abkommen zu Arbeits- und Beschäftigungsfragen, welches am 9. Juni 2014 in Kraft getreten ist, zur nachhaltigen Entwicklung beitragen.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Staatssekretariat für Wirtschaft SECO Holzikofenweg 36 CH-3003 Bern Tel. +41 58 462 56 56 Fax +41 58 462 56 00</contact>
      <attachment id="154927">
        <title>Swiss-China Free Trade Agreement</title>
        <format>jpg</format>
        <size-kb>90</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/35494.jpg</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>La Suisse et la Chine célèbrent l’entrée en vigueur de l’accord de libre-échange</title>
      <lead>Mardi après-midi, au port rhénan de Bâle, le conseiller fédéral Johann N. Schneider-Ammann a donné le coup d’envoi aux célébrations de l’entrée en vigueur de l’accord de libre-échange entre la Suisse et la Chine. Pour le commerce extérieur suisse, il s’agit de l’accord de libre-échange le plus important depuis celui conclu avec l’Union européenne en 1972.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;L'accord de libre-échange de large portée entre la Suisse et la Chine entre en vigueur le 1er juillet 2014, presque un an après sa signature, le 6 juillet 2013 à Pékin, par le conseiller fédéral Johann N. Schneider-Ammann et son homologue chinois, le ministre du Commerce Gao Hucheng. Ce moment était très attendu par l'économie suisse, en particulier par l'économie d'exportation, étant donné que cet accord améliore l'accès au marché chinois par rapport aux concurrents européens.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Le conseiller fédéral Johann N. Schneider-Ammann a invité des représentants de l'économie et des autorités à prendre part aux célébrations au port rhénan de Bâle, lieu qui symbolise mieux que tout autre en Suisse l'ouverture vers le monde. Yu Jianhua, ambassadeur de la Chine auprès de l'Organisation mondiale du commerce (OMC), représente le ministre chinois du Commerce lors des festivités. Parallèlement, l'entrée en vigueur de l'accord de libre-échange est également célébrée en République populaire de Chine. A cette occasion, la Suisse est représentée à Pékin par Marie-Gabrielle Ineichen-Fleisch, secrétaire d'Etat et directrice du SECO.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;La République populaire de Chine est le principal partenaire commercial de la Suisse en Asie. Avec un volume commercial supérieur à 20 milliards de francs l'an passé, la Chine est le troisième partenaire commercial de la Suisse à l'échelle mondiale, après l'UE et les Etats-Unis.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;L'accord de libre-échange facilite l'accès réciproque aux marchés pour les produits et services. Il permet de supprimer, intégralement ou en partie, les droits de douane (pour certains, avec des délais transitoires) sur la majeure partie des échanges bilatéraux, ainsi que d'accroître la sécurité juridique de ces échanges et de la protection de la propriété intellectuelle. Conjugué à l'accord bilatéral sur la coopération en matière de travail et d'emploi, conclu en parallèle et entré en vigueur le 9 juin 2014, cet accord contribuera également au développement durable.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Secrétariat d'Etat à l'économie SECO Holzikofenweg 36 CH-3003 Berne tél. +41 58 462 56 56 fax +41 58 462 56 00</contact>
      <attachment id="154927">
        <title>Swiss-China Free Trade Agreement</title>
        <format>jpg</format>
        <size-kb>90</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/35494.jpg</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Svizzera e Cina celebrano l’entrata in vigore dell’accordo di libero scambio</title>
      <lead>Martedì pomeriggio al porto sul Reno di Basilea il consigliere federale Johann N. Schneider-Ammann ha aperto le celebrazioni per l’entrata in vigore dell’accordo di libero scambio tra Svizzera e Cina. Si tratta dell’accordo di libero scambio più importante per il commercio estero svizzero dopo quello stipulato con l’Unione europea nel 1972.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Dopo quasi un anno dalla firma da parte del consigliere federale Johann N. Schneider-Ammann e del ministro del commercio cinese Gao Hucheng, avvenuta a Pechino il 6 luglio 2013, il 1° luglio 2014 l'accordo di libero scambio tra Svizzera e Cina entra in vigore. L'economia e il settore delle esportazioni hanno atteso a lungo questo momento. D'ora in poi, infatti, il nostro Paese avrà un accesso agevolato al mercato cinese rispetto ai concorrenti europei. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Il consigliere federale Schneider-Ammann ha invitato i rappresentanti dell'economia e delle autorità alle celebrazioni presso il porto sul Reno di Basilea, un luogo altamente simbolico per la Svizzera. &lt;br /&gt;In rappresentanza del ministro del commercio cinese era presente Yu Jianhua, ambasciatore della Cina presso l'Organizzazione mondiale del commercio (OMC). L'entrata in vigore dell'accordo viene festeggiata anche a Pechino, dove la direttrice della SECO e segretaria di Stato Marie-Gabrielle Ineichen-Fleisch partecipa alle celebrazioni per conto della Svizzera.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;La Repubblica popolare cinese è il principale partner commerciale della Svizzera in Asia. Con un volume d'affari di oltre 20 miliardi di franchi nel 2013 è stato anche il terzo partner più importante al mondo dopo Unione europea e Stati Uniti. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;L'accordo di libero scambio migliora l'accesso reciproco al mercato dei beni e dei servizi. Inoltre, prevede l'eliminazione totale o parziale dei dazi doganali su gran parte del commercio bilaterale, contemplando in parte periodi transitori, e aumenta la certezza del diritto sugli scambi economici bilaterali e la tutela della proprietà intellettuale. Insieme all'accordo bilaterale in materia di lavoro e occupazione, stipulato contemporaneamente ed entrato in vigore il 9 giugno 2014, l'accordo di libero scambio contribuirà allo sviluppo sostenibile.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Segreteria di Stato dell'economia SECO Holzikofenweg 36 CH-3003 Berna tel. +41 58 462 56 56 fax +41 58 462 56 00</contact>
      <attachment id="154927">
        <title>Swiss-China Free Trade Agreement</title>
        <format>jpg</format>
        <size-kb>90</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/35494.jpg</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Switzerland and China celebrate the entry into force of their free trade agreement</title>
      <lead>Federal Councillor Johann N. Schneider-Ammann opened the ceremony to mark the entry into force of the free trade agreement between Switzerland and China at the Rhine port in Basel on Tuesday afternoon. This is the most important free trade agreement for Swiss foreign trade since the agreement with the European Union in 1972.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;The comprehensive free trade agreement between Switzerland and China enters into force on 1 July 2014, almost a year to the day since Federal Councillor Johann N. Schneider-Ammann and his Chinese counterpart, Minister of Commerce Gao Hucheng, signed the agreement in Beijing on 6 July 2013. Swiss business, especially the export industry, has been keenly awaiting this day because its access to the Chinese market improves compared to that of its European competitors. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Federal Councillor Schneider-Ammann invited representatives from business and government to the ceremony at the Rhine port in Basel, a place that best represents Switzerland's gateway to the world. The Chinese minister of commerce will be represented at the ceremony by China's ambassador to the World Trade Organisation (WTO), Yu Jianhua. A ceremony to celebrate the free trade agreement will also be held simultaneously in the People's Republic of China. The director of SECO, State Secretary Marie-Gabrielle Ineichen-Fleisch, will be representing Switzerland at the celebrations in Beijing.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The People's Republic of China is Switzerland's most important trade partner in Asia. With a trade volume of over CHF 20 billion last year, China is the third most important trade partner worldwide after the EU and the USA.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The free trade agreement improves mutual market access for goods and services. With the agreement's entry into force, customs duties on the vast majority of bilateral trade will be abolished in full or in part (transitional periods apply in some areas), and legal certainty in bilateral economic relations and in the protection of intellectual property will be improved. Taken together, the free trade agreement and the bilateral agreement on labour and employment issues, which was concluded at the same time and which entered into force on 9 June, contribute to long-term economic development.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>State Secretariat for Economic Affairs SECO Holzikofenweg 36 CH-3003 Bern Tel. +41 58 462 56 56 Fax +41 58 462 56 00</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="10">
        <name lang="de">Bundesrat</name>
        <name lang="fr">Conseil fédéral</name>
        <name lang="it">Consiglio federale</name>
        <name lang="en">Federal Council</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="47">
        <name lang="de">Wirtschaft</name>
        <name lang="fr">Économie</name>
        <name lang="it">Economia</name>
        <name lang="en">Economic Affairs</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="48">
        <name lang="de">Zoll</name>
        <name lang="fr">Douanes</name>
        <name lang="it">Dogane</name>
        <name lang="en">Customs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
