<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="54791" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2014-10-10</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="1070" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>1070</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Der Bundesrat</name>
      <name lang="fr">Conseil fédéral</name>
      <name lang="it">Il Consiglio federale</name>
      <name lang="en">The Federal Council</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.admin.ch/gov/de/start.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.admin.ch/gov/fr/accueil.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.admin.ch/gov/it/pagina-iniziale.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.admin.ch/gov/en/start.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="201" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>201</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="yes" id="606" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>601</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössische Zollverwaltung</name>
      <name lang="fr">Administration fédérale des douanes</name>
      <name lang="it">Amministrazione federale delle dogane</name>
      <name lang="en">The Federal Customs Administration</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.ezv.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.ezv.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.ezv.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.ezv.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">ozd.zentrale@ezv.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">ozd.zentrale@ezv.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">ozd.zentrale@ezv.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">ozd.zentrale@ezv.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="1070">
      <name lang="de">Der Bundesrat</name>
      <name lang="fr">Conseil fédéral</name>
      <name lang="it">Il Consiglio federale</name>
      <name lang="en">The Federal Council</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.admin.ch/gov/de/start.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.admin.ch/gov/fr/accueil.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.admin.ch/gov/it/pagina-iniziale.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.admin.ch/gov/en/start.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <department id="201">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <department id="601">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Finanzdepartement</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des finances</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale delle finanze</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Finance</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.efd.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.dff.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.efd.admin.ch/efd/it/home.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.efd.admin.ch/efd/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Aktualisierung des Abkommens über Zollerleichterungen und Zollsicherheit mit der EU</title>
      <lead>Der Beschluss Nr. 1/2014 zur Anpassung des Anhangs I des Abkommens zwischen der Schweiz und der EU über Zollerleichterungen und Zollsicherheit wurde heute von der Präsidentin des Gemischten Ausschusses unterzeichnet. Dieser Beschluss ist am 8. Oktober 2014 vom Bundesrat genehmigt worden und tritt am Tag nach seiner Unterzeichnung in Kraft.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Das Abkommen vom 25. Juni 2009 zwischen der Schweiz und der EU über die Erleichterung der Kontrollen und Formalitäten im Güterverkehr und über zollrechtliche Sicherheitsmassnahmen enthält Anhänge zu so genannten summarischen Eingangs- und Ausgangsanmeldungen sowie zu den zugelassenen Wirtschaftsbeteiligten. Das Abkommen strebt ein gleichwertiges Sicherheitsniveau zwischen der Schweiz und der EU im Zollbereich an. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Anhang I des Abkommens sieht vor, dass die Zollverwaltung des Ausfuhrstaates die sicherheitsrelevanten Daten an die Zollverwaltung des Ausgangsstaates (via den der Ausfuhrstaat seine Waren aus dem gemeinsamen Sicherheitsraum bringt) übermittelt, wenn die Waren das Zollgebiet der anderen Vertragspartei überqueren. Werden diese Daten nicht übermittelt, so sind diese Daten spätestens beim Verlassen des Ausgangsstaates abzugeben, es sei denn, die Überquerung erfolgt im direkten Luftverkehr.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Der Beschluss Nr. 1/2014 sieht eine zusätzliche Ausnahme der Datenübermittlung für Waren vor, die von einem Luftfahrtunternehmen übernommen worden sind, wenn der erste Teil des Transports auf der Strasse stattfindet (sog. Luftfrachtersatzverkehr).&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Serge Gumy, Chef Abteilung Zollveranlagung, Oberzolldirektion, Eidgenössische Zollverwaltung EZV Tel. 058 462 67 98, serge.gumy@ezv.admin.ch Information EDA Tel. 058 462 31 53, info@eda.admin.ch</contact>
      <attachment id="128756">
        <title>Beschluss</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>19</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/36843.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Actualisation de l'accord avec l'UE sur la facilitation et la sécurité douanières</title>
      <lead>La décision no 1/2014 portant modification de l'annexe I de l'accord entre la Suisse et l'UE sur la facilitation et la sécurité douanières a été signée aujourd'hui par la présidente du comité mixte. Cette décision a été approuvée par le Conseil fédéral le 8 octobre 2014 et est entrée en vigueur le jour suivant sa signature.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;L'accord conclu le 25 juin 2009 entre la Suisse et l'UE sur la facilitation des contrôles et des formalités lors du transport des marchandises et les mesures douanières de sécurité comporte des annexes relatives aux déclarations sommaires d'entrée et de sortie et aux opérateurs économiques agréés. Cet accord vise à assurer un niveau de sécurité équivalent entre la Suisse et l'UE dans le domaine douanier. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;L'annexe I de l'accord prévoit que l'administration des douanes de l'Etat d'exportation transmet les données importantes en matière de sécurité à l'administration des douanes de l'Etat de sortie (par lequel l'Etat d'exportation achemine ses marchandises hors de l'espace de sécurité commun) lorsque les marchandises traversent le territoire douanier de l'autre partie contractante. Si ces données ne sont pas transmises, leur remise doit intervenir au plus tard au moment où les marchandises quittent l'Etat de sortie, à moins que le transit n'ait lieu dans le trafic aérien direct.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;La décision no 1/2014 prévoit une nouvelle exception à la transmission des données pour les marchandises qui, après avoir été prises en charge par une compagnie aérienne, sont tout d'abord transportées par camion (trafic dit de substitution du fret aérien) avant d'être expédiées par avion.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Serge Gumy, chef de la division Régimes douaniers, Direction générale des douanes, Administration fédérale des douanes AFD Tél. 058 462 67 98, serge.gumy@ezv.admin.ch Information DFAE tél. 058 462 31 53, info@eda.admin.ch</contact>
      <attachment id="128757">
        <title>Accord</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>23</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/36844.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Adeguamento dell’accordo sulla facilitazione e la sicurezza doganali con l’UE</title>
      <lead>In data odierna, la presidente del comitato misto ha firmato la decisione numero 1/2014 che comporta l’adeguamento dell’allegato I dell’accordo tra la Svizzera e l’UE sulla facilitazione e la sicurezza doganali. La decisione, approvata dal Consiglio federale l’8 ottobre 2014, entra in vigore il giorno successivo alla firma.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;L'accordo del 25 giugno 2009 tra la Confederazione Svizzera e la Comunità europea riguardante l'agevolazione dei controlli e delle formalità nei trasporti di merci e le misure doganali di sicurezza contiene allegati sulle cosiddette dichiarazioni sommarie di entrata e di uscita nonché sugli operatori economici autorizzati. Scopo dell'accordo è mantenere un livello di sicurezza equivalente nel settore doganale sia in Svizzera sia nell'UE.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;L'allegato I dell'accordo prevede che l'amministrazione delle dogane del Paese di esportazione trasmetta i dati rilevanti in materia di sicurezza all'amministrazione delle dogane del Paese di uscita (attraverso il quale il Paese di esportazione indirizza le sue merci fuori dallo spazio di sicurezza comune) quando le merci attraversano il territorio doganale dell'altra parte contraente. Se tali dati non vengono trasmessi, occorre consegnarli al più tardi quando le merci lasciano il Paese di uscita, a meno che l'attraversamento avvenga nel traffico aereo diretto.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;La decisione numero 1/2014 prevede una nuova eccezione riguardante la trasmissione dei dati per le merci prese in consegna da un'impresa di navigazione aerea, qualora la prima parte del trasporto abbia luogo su strada (cosiddetto traffico sostitutivo del trasporto aereo).&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Serge Gumy, capo della divisione Regimi doganali, Direzione generale delle dogane, Amministrazione generale delle dogane AFD Tel. 058 462 67 98, serge.gumy@ezv.admin.ch Informazione DFAE tel. 058 462 31 53, info@eda.admin.ch</contact>
      <attachment id="128758">
        <title>Accordo</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>17</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/36845.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Update of the agreement with the EU on the simplification of customs formalities and on customs security measures</title>
      <lead>Today, the chairperson of the joint committee signed decree no. 1/2014 on the amendment of Annex I to the agreement between Switzerland and the EU on the simplification of customs formalities and on customs security measures. The decree was approved by the Federal Council on 8 October 2014 and entered into force the day after it was signed.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;The agreement of 25 June 2009 between Switzerland and the EU on the simplification of inspections and formalities in respect of the carriage of goods and on customs security measures contains annexes on what are known as entry and exit summary declarations and on authorised economic operators. The agreement aims to ensure an equivalent level of security between Switzerland and the EU in the area of customs.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Annex I to the agreement provides that the customs administration of the country of export shall transmit the security-related information to the customs administration of the country of exit (through which the country of export carries its goods out of the joint security area) if the goods leave from the customs territory of the other Contracting Party. If this information is not transmitted, it must be submitted at the latest upon leaving the country of exit, except if the goods are carried via direct air traffic.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Decree no. 1/2014 provides for an additional exception for the transmission of data relating to goods that are carried by an airline if the first part of the transport was undertaken by road (known as air freight replacement transport)&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Serge Gumy, Head of the Customs Clearance Division, Directorate General of Customs, Federal Customs Administration FCA Tel. 058 462 67 98, serge.gumy@ezv.admin.ch Information FDFA Tel. 058 462 31 53, info@eda.admin.ch</contact>
      <attachment id="128759">
        <title>Degree (available in German)</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>19</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/36846.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <keywords>
      <keyword id="207" org-id="606">
        <name lang="de">Zoll Diverses</name>
        <name lang="fr">Douanes: divers</name>
        <name lang="it">Dogane: diversi</name>
        <name lang="en">Customs Misc.</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="184" org-id="606">
        <name lang="de">Zollverfahren</name>
        <name lang="fr">Procédure douanière</name>
        <name lang="it">Operazioni doganali</name>
        <name lang="en">Customs procedure</name>
      </keyword>
    </keywords>
    <topics>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
