<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="55439" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2014-11-28</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="1070" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>1070</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Der Bundesrat</name>
      <name lang="fr">Conseil fédéral</name>
      <name lang="it">Il Consiglio federale</name>
      <name lang="en">The Federal Council</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.admin.ch/gov/de/start.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.admin.ch/gov/fr/accueil.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.admin.ch/gov/it/pagina-iniziale.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.admin.ch/gov/en/start.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="yes" id="605" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>601</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössische Steuerverwaltung</name>
      <name lang="fr">Administration fédérale des contributions</name>
      <name lang="it">Amministrazione federale delle contribuzioni</name>
      <name lang="en">The Federal Tax Administration</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.estv.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.estv.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.estv.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.estv.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de"/>
      <email lang="fr"/>
      <email lang="it"/>
      <email lang="en"/>
    </originator>
    <department id="1070">
      <name lang="de">Der Bundesrat</name>
      <name lang="fr">Conseil fédéral</name>
      <name lang="it">Il Consiglio federale</name>
      <name lang="en">The Federal Council</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.admin.ch/gov/de/start.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.admin.ch/gov/fr/accueil.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.admin.ch/gov/it/pagina-iniziale.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.admin.ch/gov/en/start.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <department id="601">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Finanzdepartement</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des finances</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale delle finanze</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Finance</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.efd.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.dff.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.efd.admin.ch/efd/it/home.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.efd.admin.ch/efd/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Botschaft des Bundesrates zur Revision der Quellenbesteuerung des Erwerbseinkommens</title>
      <lead>Wer für sein Erwerbseinkommen an der Quelle besteuert wird und in der Schweiz ansässig ist, soll künftig nachträglich ordentlich veranlagt werden können. Diese Möglichkeit soll auch Quellenbesteuerten offen stehen, die nicht in der Schweiz ansässig sind, aber einen Grossteil ihrer weltweiten Einkünfte in der Schweiz erzielen. Dadurch können Ungleichbehandlungen zwischen quellenbesteuerten und ordentlich besteuerten Personen beseitigt werden. Der Bundesrat hat heute vom Ergebnisbericht zur Vernehmlassung Kenntnis genommen und die Botschaft zu einer entsprechenden Gesetzesänderung verabschiedet.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Unmittelbarer gesetzgeberischer Anpassungsbedarf an der geltenden Quellensteuerordnung ergibt sich aus einem Entscheid des Bundesgerichts. Dieses stellte am 26. Januar 2010 erstmals fest, dass die Quellenbesteuerung in gewissen Fällen gegen das mit der Europäischen Union abgeschlossene Personenfreizügigkeitsabkommen verstösst. Gemäss Bundesgericht haben Quellensteuerpflichtige ohne Wohnsitz in der Schweiz, die hier mehr als 90 Prozent ihrer weltweiten Einkünfte erzielen (so genannte Quasi-Ansässige), Anspruch auf die gleichen Abzüge wie in der Schweiz ordentlich besteuerte Personen. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mit der Revision bleibt für die heute betroffenen Personenkategorien die Erhebung einer Quellensteuer bestehen. Künftig soll jedoch allen ansässigen Quellensteuerpflichtigen nachträglich eine ordentliche Veranlagung offen stehen. Ab einem noch festzulegenden Erwerbseinkommen sind sie wie im geltenden Recht von Amtes wegen nachträglich im ordentlichen Verfahren zu veranlagen. Alle andern können eine nachträgliche ordentliche Veranlagung beantragen. Die ergänzende ordentliche Veranlagung, mit welcher nicht quellensteuerpflichtige Einkünfte und Vermögen erfasst werden, soll ebenfalls durch die nachträgliche ordentliche Veranlagung ersetzt werden. Dies führt zu einer Vereinheitlichung der Verfahren bei den ansässigen Quellensteuerpflichtigen. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Die nachträgliche ordentliche Veranlagung steht auch Nicht-Ansässigen offen, sofern sie einen Grossteil ihrer Einkünfte in der Schweiz erzielen und damit die Voraussetzungen zur Quasi-Ansässigkeit erfüllen. Für alle übrigen Nicht-Ansässigen ist die Quellensteuer definitiv. Sie tritt an die Stelle der im ordentlichen Verfahren zu veranlagenden Steuern auf dem unselbstständigen Erwerbseinkommen. Mit der Neugestaltung des Quellensteuerregimes erübrigt sich künftig das Instrument der Tarifkorrekturen zur nachträglichen Geltendmachung zusätzlicher Abzüge. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Eine Schätzung über die finanziellen Auswirkungen lässt sich mangels zuverlässiger Daten nicht treffen. Die Beseitigung von Ungleichbehandlungen zwischen quellenbesteuerten und ordentlich besteuerten Personen hat für die kantonalen Steuerbehörden veranlagungsbedingt Mehraufwand zur Folge. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class="nsbtextkasten"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Quellenbesteuerung und Quellenbesteuerte in der Schweiz&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Ausländische Arbeitnehmende in der Schweiz, die nicht im Besitz der Niederlassungsbewilligung sind, werden für ihr Erwerbseinkommen an der Quelle besteuert. Heute werden in der Schweiz rund 760‘000 unselbstständig Erwerbstätige ohne Niederlassungsbewilligung an der Quelle besteuert. Davon haben rund 490‘000 Personen einen steuerrechtlichen Wohnsitz oder Aufenthalt in der Schweiz und gelten als Ansässige. Rund 270‘000 Personen sind ohne steuerrechtlichen Wohnsitz oder Aufenthalt in der Schweiz und gelten als Nicht-Ansässige. Quasi-ansässig sind Arbeitnehmende ohne steuerrechtlichen Wohnsitz oder Aufenthalt in der Schweiz, die hier aber einen Grossteil ihrer weltweiten Einkünfte erzielen. Laut Bundesgerichtsurteil stehen ihnen dieselben Abzugsmöglichkeiten wie ordentlich Besteuerten zu. Bei der Quellenbesteuerung des Erwerbseinkommens zieht der Arbeitgeber die geschuldete Steuer direkt vom Lohn ab. &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Lukas Schneider, wissenschaftlicher Mitarbeiter, Eidgenössische Steuerverwaltung ESTV Tel. 058 462 72 51, Lukas.Schneider@estv.admin.ch</contact>
      <attachment id="130741">
        <title>Gesetzesentwurf</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>56</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/37492.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="130743">
        <title>Botschaft</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>278</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/37494.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="130745">
        <title>Ergebnisbericht Vernehmlassung</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>135</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/37496.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Message du Conseil fédéral concernant la révision de l’imposition à la source du revenu de l’activité lucrative</title>
      <lead>Dorénavant, tous les contribuables imposés à la source qui sont domiciliés en Suisse pourront recourir à la taxation ordinaire ultérieure. Cette possibilité sera également offerte aux contribuables soumis à lʼimposition à la source qui ne sont pas domiciliés en Suisse mais qui y réalisent une grande partie de leur revenu mondial. La révision doit permettre dʼéliminer les inégalités de traitement entre les personnes imposées à la source et les personnes soumises à la taxation ordinaire. Aujourd’hui, le Conseil fédéral a pris connaissance du rapport sur les résultats de la consultation et adopté le message relatif à la modification de la loi.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Un arrêt du Tribunal fédéral rend nécessaire l'adaptation immédiate des dispositions régissant l'imposition à la source en vigueur. Dans cet arrêt du 26 janvier 2010, le Tribunal fédéral a constaté pour la première fois que, dans certains cas, lʼimposition à la source allait à lʼencontre de lʼaccord sur la libre circulation des personnes conclu avec lʼUE. Le Tribunal fédéral considère que les contribuables soumis à lʼimposition à la source qui ne sont pas domiciliés en Suisse mais qui y réalisent plus de 90 % de leur revenu mondial (contribuables dits quasi-résidents) ont droit aux mêmes déductions que les personnes soumises à la taxation ordinaire en Suisse.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Les catégories de personnes concernées demeurent imposées à la source après la révision. Cependant, tous les contribuables imposés à la source qui sont domiciliés en Suisse pourront désormais recourir à la taxation ordinaire ultérieure. Les personnes qui ont un revenu brut supérieur à un certain seuil, qui reste à définir, feront obligatoirement lʼobjet dʼune taxation ordinaire ultérieure, comme c'est déjà le cas aujourd'hui. Les personnes qui ont un revenu brut inférieur à ce seuil auront le droit de demander une taxation ordinaire ultérieure. La taxation ordinaire complémentaire, qui permet aujourdʼhui de déclarer les revenus et la fortune qui n'ont pas été imposés à la source, sera également remplacée par la taxation ordinaire ultérieure. Cela permet d'unifier les procédures qui s'appliquent aux résidents imposés à la source. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Les personnes qui ne sont pas domiciliées en Suisse mais qui y réalisent plus de 90 % de leur revenu mondial et remplissent ainsi les conditions pour être qualifiées de quasi-résidents pourront également recourir à la taxation ordinaire ultérieure. L'impôt à la source a un effet libératoire pour tous les autres non-résidents. Il se substitue aux impôts perçus selon la procédure de taxation ordinaire sur le revenu de l'activité lucrative dépendante. La nouvelle conception du régime de l'imposition à la source rend superflues les corrections ultérieures de l'impôt à la source, après que les personnes imposées à la source ont fait valoir leur droit à des déductions supplémentaires.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Il n'est pas possible d'estimer les conséquences financières de la révision faute de données fiables. L'élimination des inégalités de traitement entre les personnes soumises à lʼimposition à la source et celles soumises à l'imposition ordinaire entraîne un coût supplémentaire lié à la taxation pour les autorités fiscales cantonales.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class="nsbtextkasten"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Imposition à la source et personnes imposées à la source en Suisse&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Le revenu de l'activité lucrative de tous les employés étrangers qui ne disposent pas d'un permis d'établissement en Suisse est imposé à la source. Aujourd'hui, environ 760 000 employés ne disposant pas dʼun permis dʼétablissement en Suisse sont imposés à la source. Environ 490 000 employés sont domiciliés ou en séjour en Suisse au regard du droit fiscal et ont le statut de résident et environ 270 000 ne sont ni domiciliés ni en séjour en Suisse et ont le statut de non-résident. Les quasi-résidents sont des personnes qui ne sont ni domiciliées ni en séjour en Suisse au regard du droit fiscal mais qui y réalisent une grande partie de leur revenu mondial. D'après l'arrêt du Tribunal fédéral, ils ont droit aux mêmes déductions que les contribuables soumis à la procédure ordinaire. Dans le cadre de l'imposition à la source du revenu de l'activité lucrative, l'employeur prélève directement l'impôt dû sur le salaire.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Lukas Schneider, collaborateur scientifique, Administration fédérale des contributions AFC Tél. 058 462 72 51, lukas.schneider@estv.admin.ch</contact>
      <attachment id="130742">
        <title>Projet de loi</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>58</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/37493.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="130744">
        <title>Message</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>279</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/37495.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="130746">
        <title>Rapport sur les résultats de la consultation</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>138</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/37497.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Messaggio del Consiglio federale concernente la revisione dell’imposizione alla fonte del reddito da attività lucrativa</title>
      <lead>Chi è assoggettato all’imposizione alla fonte per il proprio reddito da attività lucrativa ed è residente in Svizzera dovrebbe poter essere sottoposto a tassazione ordinaria ulteriore. Questa possibilità dovrebbe essere offerta anche a tutte le persone che sono assoggettate alla fonte e non sono residenti in Svizzera, ma conseguono gran parte dei loro proventi mondiali nel nostro Paese. In questo modo si potranno eliminare le disparità di trattamento tra le persone assoggettate all’imposta alla fonte e quelle che sottostanno alla procedura d’imposizione ordinaria. In data odierna il Consiglio federale ha preso atto del rapporto dei risultati della consultazione e ha licenziato il messaggio concernente la relativa modifica di legge.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;La necessità di un'immediata modifica a livello legislativo dell'ordinamento vigente sull'imposizione alla fonte emerge da una sentenza del Tribunale federale. Il 26 gennaio 2010 il Tribunale federale ha constatato per la prima volta che in determinati casi l'imposizione alla fonte viola l'Accordo sulla libera circolazione delle persone (ALC) che la Svizzera ha concluso con l'Unione europea. Esso ritiene che gli assoggettati all'imposta alla fonte, che non sono residenti in Svizzera e vi conseguono oltre il 90 per cento dei loro proventi mondiali (i cosiddetti «quasi residenti»), abbiano diritto alle stesse deduzioni delle persone tassate in Svizzera in via ordinaria.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Con la revisione la ritenuta dell'imposta alla fonte rimane per le categorie di persone attualmente interessate. Tuttavia, in futuro tutte le persone residenti assoggettate all'imposta alla fonte potranno chiedere la tassazione ordinaria ulteriore. Da un importo del reddito da attività lucrativa, che deve essere ancora stabilito, esse saranno obbligatoriamente assoggettate d'ufficio alla procedura della tassazione ordinaria ulteriore come nel diritto vigente. Tutti gli altri possono chiedere la tassazione ordinaria ulteriore. La tassazione ordinaria complementare, con la quale vengono rilevati proventi e sostanza non sottoposti a tassazione alla fonte, dovrebbe parimenti essere sostituita dalla tassazione ordinaria ulteriore. Questo determina un'uniformazione delle procedure per le persone residenti assoggettate all'imposizione alla fonte. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Anche i non residenti hanno la possibilità di chiedere la tassazione ordinaria ulteriore, purché conseguano gran parte dei loro proventi in Svizzera e soddisfino in questo modo i requisiti per la «quasi residenza». Per tutti gli altri non residenti l'imposizione alla fonte è definitiva. Essa sostituisce le imposte da applicare sul reddito da attività lucrativa dipendente nella procedura di tassazione ordinaria. Con la rielaborazione del regime di imposizione alla fonte diventerà superfluo lo strumento delle correzioni della tariffa per la pretesa a posteriori di deduzioni ulteriori.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A causa della mancanza di dati affidabili, le ripercussioni finanziarie della revisione non sono quantificabili. Per le autorità cantonali di tassazione, l'eliminazione delle disparità tra le persone assoggettate all'imposta alla fonte e quelle che sottostanno alla procedura d'imposizione ordinaria provoca un maggiore onere amministrativo legato alla tassazione.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class="nsbtextkasten"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Imposizione alla fonte e persone assoggettate all'imposta alla fonte in Svizzera&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;I redditi da attività lucrativa dei lavoratori stranieri in Svizzera che non sono in possesso di un permesso di domicilio sono tassati alla fonte. Attualmente in Svizzera sono tassati alla fonte circa 760 000 persone che esercitano un'attività lucrativa dipendente senza permesso di domicilio, di cui circa 490 000 hanno domicilio fiscale o dimora nel nostro Paese e sono considerati residenti. Circa 270 000 persone non hanno domicilio fiscale né dimora in Svizzera e sono considerati non residenti. I «quasi residenti» sono lavoratori senza domicilio fiscale o dimora in Svizzera, dove però conseguono gran parte dei loro proventi mondiali. Secondo la sentenza del Tribunale federale, essi devono poter operare le stesse deduzioni delle persone tassate in via ordinaria. Nel caso dell'imposizione alla fonte del reddito da attività lucrativa il datore di lavoro deduce l'imposta dovuta direttamente dallo stipendio.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Lukas Schneider, collaboratore scientifico, Amministrazione federale delle contribuzioni AFC tel. 058 462 72 51, Lukas.Schneider@estv.admin.ch</contact>
      <attachment id="130742">
        <title>Projet de loi</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>58</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/37493.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="130744">
        <title>Message</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>279</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/37495.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="130747">
        <title>Rapporto sui risultati della consultazione</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>138</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/37498.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Federal Council dispatch on revision of withholding tax on earned income</title>
      <lead>In the future, anyone resident in Switzerland whose earned income is taxed at source should have the option of a subsequent ordinary tax assessment. This option should also be available to people taxed at source who are not resident in Switzerland but earn a major part of their global income in Switzerland. Differences between the tax treatment of individuals taxed at source and those subject to ordinary taxation can be eliminated in this way. Today, the Federal Council took note of the report on the results of the consultation procedure and adopted the dispatch for a corresponding legislative amendment.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;There is an immediate need to amend the current withholding tax system at the legislative level because of a Federal Supreme Court ruling. On 26 January 2010, the FSC stated for the first time that, in certain cases, withholding tax contravenes the Agreement on the Free Movement of Persons concluded with the European Union. According to the FSC, people taxed at source who are not domiciled in Switzerland and who earn more than 90% of their global income in Switzerland (so-called "quasi-residents") are entitled to the same deductions as those subject to ordinary taxation in Switzerland. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Following the revision, withholding tax will continue to be levied for the groups of people currently affected. In the future, however, all residents taxed at source should have the option of a subsequent ordinary tax assessment. Above an income threshold still to be determined, they will officially be subject to a subsequent ordinary tax assessment as is the case under currently applicable law. All others can request a subsequent ordinary tax assessment. The supplementary ordinary tax assessment, which includes income and assets not subject to withholding tax, should also be replaced by the subsequent ordinary tax assessment. This will harmonise the procedure for residents subject to withholding tax.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A subsequent ordinary tax assessment is also available to non-residents, provided they earn a major part of their income in Switzerland and thus meet the quasi-residency requirements. Withholding tax is definitive for all other non-residents. It replaces the taxes to be assessed on income from employment in the ordinary procedure. Following the restructuring of the withholding tax regime, the rate-correction tool for subsequently claiming additional deductions will be superfluous. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;It is not possible to estimate the financial impact due to a lack of reliable data. The elimination of differences between the tax treatment of individuals taxed at source and those subject to ordinary taxation will result in additional assessment-related work for the cantonal tax authorities. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class="nsbtextkasten"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Withholding tax and people taxed at source in Switzerland&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Withholding tax is levied at source on the income of foreign employees in Switzerland who do not have a permanent residence permit (C permit). At present, there are approximately 760,000 employees without a permanent residence permit taxed at source in Switzerland. Some 490,000 of these have their tax domicile or place of residence in Switzerland and are therefore considered residents. Approximately 270,000 do not have their tax domicile or place of residence in Switzerland and are considered non-residents. Quasi-residents are employees who do not have their tax domicile or place of residence in Switzerland but generate a major part of their global income here. According to the Federal Supreme Court judgment, these people are entitled to the same deductions as those subject to ordinary taxation. In the case of withholding tax applied to earned income, the employer deducts the tax payable directly from the salary. &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Lukas Schneider, Researcher, Federal Tax Administration FTA Tel. 058 462 72 51, Lukas.Schneider@estv.admin.ch</contact>
      <attachment id="130741">
        <title>Gesetzesentwurf</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>56</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/37492.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="130743">
        <title>Botschaft</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>278</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/37494.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="130745">
        <title>Ergebnisbericht Vernehmlassung</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>135</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/37496.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <offers>
      <offer id="9" org-id="605">
        <name lang="de">Steuern allgemein</name>
        <name lang="fr">Impôts en général</name>
        <name lang="it">Imposte in generale</name>
        <name lang="en">Taxes in general</name>
      </offer>
    </offers>
    <keywords>
      <keyword id="130" org-id="605">
        <name lang="de">Direkte Bundessteuer</name>
        <name lang="fr">Impôt fédéral direct</name>
        <name lang="it">Imposta federale diretta</name>
        <name lang="en">Direct federal tax</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="153" org-id="605">
        <name lang="de">Einkommenssteuer</name>
        <name lang="fr">Impôt sur le revenu</name>
        <name lang="it">Imposta sul reddito</name>
        <name lang="en">Income tax</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="149" org-id="605">
        <name lang="de">Quellensteuer</name>
        <name lang="fr">Impôt à la source</name>
        <name lang="it">Imposta alla fonte</name>
        <name lang="en">Withholding tax</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="159" org-id="605">
        <name lang="de">Steuern Diverses</name>
        <name lang="fr">Impôts: divers</name>
        <name lang="it">Imposte: diversi</name>
        <name lang="en">Taxes Misc.</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="235" org-id="605">
        <name lang="de">Internationale Steuerpolitik</name>
        <name lang="fr">Politique fiscale internationale</name>
        <name lang="it">Politica fiscale internazionale</name>
        <name lang="en">International tax policy</name>
      </keyword>
    </keywords>
    <topics>
      <topic id="10">
        <name lang="de">Bundesrat</name>
        <name lang="fr">Conseil fédéral</name>
        <name lang="it">Consiglio federale</name>
        <name lang="en">Federal Council</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="44">
        <name lang="de">Steuern</name>
        <name lang="fr">Impôts</name>
        <name lang="it">Imposte</name>
        <name lang="en">Taxation</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
