<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="101385" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2024-06-12</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="201" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>201</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="201">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Bundesrat Ignazio Cassis bespricht mit IAEA-Generaldirektor Rafael Mariano Grossi die Lage der ukrainischen Nuklearanlagen</title>
      <lead>Bundesrat Ignazio Cassis hat am 12. Juni 2024 in Bern den Generaldirektor der Internationalen Atomenergie-Agentur (IAEA), Dr. Rafael Mariano Grossi, empfangen. Im Zentrum des Treffens standen die Sicherheit der ukrainischen Nuklearanlagen sowie die Unterstützung der Schweiz für die Arbeit der IAEA in der Ukraine. Das Treffen reiht sich ein in eine Serie von Austauschen mit der IAEA auf hohem Level und unterstreicht die Bedeutung, welche die Schweiz der nuklearen Sicherheit und Sicherung sowie der Organisation als Ganzes beimisst, insbesondere im Kontext des Kriegs gegen die Ukraine.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Bundesrat Ignazio Cassis dankte IAEA-Generaldirektor Grossi für dessen Einsatz für die Aufrechterhaltung der nuklearen Sicherheit in der Ukraine in einer herausfordernden Lage. Die IAEA-Missionen sind auf allen ukrainischen Kernkraftwerken und Tschernobyl präsent und stellen der Öffentlichkeit wichtige Informationen zum Zustand der Anlagen zur Verfügung. Die Schweiz unterstützt diese Missionen sowie die die durch die IAEA ausgearbeiteten Sieben Pfeiler der nuklearen Sicherung und Sicherheit und Fünf Prinzipien zum Schutz des Kernkraftwerks Saporischschja umfassend und konsequent. Die Schweiz fazilitierte bereits die Präsentation der Fünf Prinzipien durch den IAEA-Generaldirektor im UN-Sicherheitsrat unter Vorsitz von Bundesrat Ignazio Cassis im Mai 2023. Die Schweiz stellte der Ukraine auch bereits materielle Unterstützung zur Verfügung.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Neben der Ukraine wurden auch die Entwicklungen im Nahen und Mittleren Osten sowie die hochrangige Konferenz über den Frieden in der Ukraine besprochen, bei der unter anderem die nukleare Sicherheit thematisiert werden soll. Der Besuch des IAEA-Generaldirektors ist auch eine Anerkennung für das Schweizer Engagement innerhalb der IAEA. Die Schweiz ist Gründungsmitglied der IAEA und bemisst deren Arbeit eine grosse Bedeutung zu. Entlang der Strategie Rüstungskontrolle und Abrüstung 2022-2025 des Bundesrates setzt sich die Schweiz für die Stärkung der IAEA ein.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Kommunikation EDA Bundeshaus West CH-3003 Bern Tel. Medienstelle: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Entretien entre le conseiller fédéral Ignazio Cassis et le directeur général de l’AIEA Rafael Mariano Grossi au sujet des installations nucléaires en Ukraine</title>
      <lead>Le conseiller fédéral Ignazio Cassis a reçu le directeur général de l’AIEA Rafael Mariano Grossi à Berne le 12 juin 2024. L’entretien portait principalement sur la sécurité des installations nucléaires en Ukraine et le soutien de la Suisse aux activités de l’AIEA dans ce pays. Cette rencontre s’inscrit dans une série d’échanges de haut niveau avec l’AIEA et souligne l’importance que la Suisse accorde à la sécurité et à la sûreté nucléaires ainsi qu’à l’agence onusienne dans son ensemble, en particulier dans le contexte de la guerre contre l’Ukraine. </lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Le conseiller fédéral Ignazio Cassis a remercié le directeur général de l’AIEA Rafael Mariano Grossi de son engagement pour le maintien de la sécurité nucléaire en Ukraine dans un contexte délicat. Les missions de l’AIEA couvrent toutes les centrales nucléaires ukrainiennes ainsi que Tchernobyl et délivrent au public des informations importantes sur l’état des installations. La Suisse soutient de manière globale et systématique ces missions ainsi que les sept piliers élaborés par l’AIEA pour adapter l’évaluation de la situation en matière de sûreté et de sécurité nucléaires en Ukraine au contexte du conflit armé en cours et les cinq principes mis au point pour protéger la centrale de Zaporijia. Lorsque le directeur général de l’AIEA avait exposé sa proposition en cinq points au Conseil de sécurité de l’ONU en mai 2023, la Suisse, qui assurait alors la présidence du Conseil, avait notamment joué un rôle de facilitateur. Elle a également offert un soutien matériel à l’Ukraine. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Les discussions ont en outre porté sur l’évolution de la situation au Proche et au Moyen-Orient ainsi que sur la conférence de haut niveau sur la paix en Ukraine, au cours de laquelle le thème de la sécurité nucléaire sera abordé. La visite du directeur général de l’AIEA est également un gage de la reconnaissance de l’engagement de la Suisse au sein de l’agence de l’ONU. La Suisse est un membre fondateur de l’AIEA et accorde une grande importance au travail qu’elle effectue. En adéquation avec la stratégie de maîtrise des armements et de désarmement 2022-2025 du Conseil fédéral, elle œuvre au renforcement de l’AIEA.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Communication DFAE Palais fédéral ouest CH-3003 Berne Tél. Service de presse: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Il consigliere federale Ignazio Cassis discute della situazione degli impianti nucleari ucraini con il direttore generale dell’AIEA Rafael Mariano Grossi</title>
      <lead>Il 12 giugno 2024 il consigliere federale Ignazio Cassis ha ricevuto a Berna il direttore generale dell’Agenzia internazionale per l’energia atomica (AIEA) Rafael Mariano Grossi. Il colloquio si è incentrato sulla sicurezza degli impianti nucleari ucraini e sul sostegno della Svizzera al lavoro dell’AIEA in Ucraina. L’incontro fa parte di una serie di dialoghi ad alto livello con l’AIEA e sottolinea l’importanza che la Svizzera attribuisce alla sicurezza nucleare e all’Agenzia nel suo complesso, in particolare nel contesto della guerra contro l’Ucraina.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Il consigliere federale Ignazio Cassis ha ringraziato il direttore generale dell’AIEA Grossi per il suo impegno a tutela della sicurezza nucleare in Ucraina in una situazione molto difficile. Le missioni dell’AIEA sono presenti in tutte le centrali nucleari ucraine e a Chernobyl e rendono pubbliche informazioni fondamentali sulle condizioni degli impianti. La Svizzera sostiene pienamente e coerentemente queste missioni nonché i sette pilastri della sicurezza e della protezione nucleare e i cinque principi per la protezione della centrale nucleare di Zaporizhzhya elaborati dall’AIEA. Nel maggio del 2023 ha già facilitato la presentazione dei cinque principi da parte del direttore generale dell’AIEA al Consiglio di sicurezza dell’ONU sotto la presidenza del consigliere federale Cassis. Ha inoltre già fornito all’Ucraina sostegno materiale.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Il colloquio ha riguardato non solo la situazione in Ucraina ma anche gli sviluppi in Medio Oriente e la conferenza di alto livello sulla pace in Ucraina che affronterà il tema della sicurezza nucleare. La visita del direttore generale dell’AIEA è anche un riconoscimento dell’impegno della Svizzera all’interno di questa Agenzia. Il nostro Paese è uno dei suoi membri fondatori e attribuisce grande importanza al suo lavoro. In linea con la Strategia di controllo degli armamenti e di disarmo 2022–2025 del Consiglio federale, la Svizzera si adopera per rafforzare l’AIEA. &lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Comunicazione DFAE Palazzo federale ovest CH-3003 Berna Tel. Servizio stampa: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Ignazio Cassis discusses Ukraine's nuclear facilities with IAEA Director General Rafael Mariano Grossi</title>
      <lead>Federal Councillor Ignazio Cassis received Director General of the International Atomic Energy Agency (IAEA) Rafael Mariano Grossi in Bern on 12 June 2024. The discussions focused on the safety of Ukraine's nuclear facilities and Switzerland's support for the IAEA's work in Ukraine. The meeting is part of a series of high-level exchanges with the IAEA, and underscores the importance that Switzerland attaches to nuclear safety and security and to the IAEA as a whole, particularly in the context of the war in Ukraine. </lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Mr Cassis thanked Mr Grossi for his commitment to maintaining nuclear safety in Ukraine in challenging circumstances. IAEA missions are present at all Ukrainian nuclear power plants and Chernobyl, and provide the public with important information on the condition of the plants. Switzerland fully and consistently supports these missions, as well as the IAEA's Seven Indispensable Pillars for ensuring nuclear safety and security and its Five Concrete Principles for the protection of the Zaporizhzhya nuclear power plant. Switzerland facilitated the presentation of the Five Principles by the IAEA director general to the UN Security Council under the chairmanship of Mr Cassis in May 2023. Switzerland has also provided Ukraine with material support. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;In addition to Ukraine, developments in the Middle East and the upcoming Summit on Peace in Ukraine were also discussed, at which nuclear safety will be one of the key topics on the agenda. The visit by Mr Grossi is also recognition of Switzerland's commitment within the IAEA. Switzerland is a founding member of the IAEA and attaches great importance to its work. In keeping with the Federal Council's Arms Control and Disarmament Strategy 2022–25, Switzerland is committed to strengthening the IAEA. &lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>FDFA Communication Federal Palace West Wing CH-3003 Bern, Switzerland Tel. Press service: +41 58 460 55 55 E-mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @SwissMFA</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
