<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="101428" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2024-06-14</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="1070" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>1070</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Der Bundesrat</name>
      <name lang="fr">Conseil fédéral</name>
      <name lang="it">Il Consiglio federale</name>
      <name lang="en">The Federal Council</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.admin.ch/gov/de/start.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.admin.ch/gov/fr/accueil.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.admin.ch/gov/it/pagina-iniziale.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.admin.ch/gov/en/start.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="yes" id="1040" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>701</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössische Forschungsanstalt für Wald, Schnee und Landschaft</name>
      <name lang="fr">Institut fédéral de recherches sur la forêt, la neige et le paysage</name>
      <name lang="it">Istituto federale di ricerca per la foresta, la neve e il paesaggio</name>
      <name lang="en">Swiss Federal Institute for Forest, Snow and Landscape Research</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.wsl.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.wsl.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.wsl.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.wsl.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">wslinfo@wsl.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">wslinfo@wsl.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">wslinfo@wsl.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">wslinfo@wsl.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="1070">
      <name lang="de">Der Bundesrat</name>
      <name lang="fr">Conseil fédéral</name>
      <name lang="it">Il Consiglio federale</name>
      <name lang="en">The Federal Council</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.admin.ch/gov/de/start.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.admin.ch/gov/fr/accueil.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.admin.ch/gov/it/pagina-iniziale.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.admin.ch/gov/en/start.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <department id="701">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Wirtschaft, Bildung und Forschung</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'économie, de la formation et de la recherche</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'economia, della formazione e della ricerca</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Economic Affairs, Education and Research</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Rolf Holderegger wird neuer WSL-Direktor</title>
      <lead>Der Bundesrat hat am 14. Juni 2024 Rolf Holderegger zum neuen Direktor der Eidgenössischen Forschungsanstalt für Wald, Schnee und Landschaft (WSL) gewählt. Er ist derzeit Leiter der Forschungseinheit Biodiversität und Naturschutzbiologie der WSL sowie Titular professor an der ETH Zürich. Der 59-Jährige wird sein neues Amt am 1. Oktober 2024 antreten.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Rolf Holderegger übernimmt die Leitung der WSL vom stellvertretenden Direktor Christoph Hegg, der die Institution seit Juli 2023 ad interim führt. Rolf Holderegger studierte Biologie an der Universität Zürich, wo er 1997 promovierte. Danach arbeitete er zwei Jahre als Postdoktorand an der University of St Andrews in Schottland. Er arbeitete auch Teilzeit als Gymnasiallehrer sowie als Berater im Bereich Naturschutz. 2001 nahm er eine Stelle als stellvertretender Leiter der Sektion Ökologische Genetik an der WSL an. 2006 wurde Rolf Holderegger zum Leiter der Forschungseinheit ökologische Genetik und Evolution an der WSL befördert und 2009 zum Titularprofessor am Departement für Umweltsystemwissenschaften der ETH Zürich ernannt. Seit 2011 leitet er die Forschungseinheit Biodiversität und Naturschutzbiologie der WSL. Rolf Holderegger war von 2011 bis 2023 Mitglied der Direktion der WSL.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Die von Rolf Holderegger aufgebaute und geführte Forschungseinheit ist eine der grössten Forschungseinheiten der WSL mit über 60 Mitarbeitenden, die überdurchschnittliche Aktivitäten in Forschungsanwendung und Outreach aufweist. Die Forschungseinheit untersucht die Vielfalt des Lebens in seinen verschiedenen Formen, von der genetischen Diversität zur Vielfalt der Arten und Lebensräume sowie ihre Wechselwirkungen. In Zusammenarbeit mit Partnern wie Bund, Kantone und Gemeinden erarbeitet Rolf Holderegger mit seiner Forschungseinheit wissenschaftliche Grundlagen für Managementstrategien zum Schutz der biologischen Vielfalt und der natürlichen Ressourcen in der Schweiz und international. Seine Forschungsprojekte wurden von der Europäischen Union, vom SNF, von der Innosuisse, vom BAFU, von Kantonen und Gemeinden, durch Mittel des ETH-Bereichs sowie von diversen Stiftungen unterstützt.&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Kommunikation GS-WBF info@gs-wbf.admin.ch +41 58 462 20 07</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Rolf Holderegger, nouveau directeur du WSL</title>
      <lead>Le 14 juin 2024, le Conseil fédéral a nommé Rolf Holderegger au poste de directeur de l’Institut fédéral de recherches sur la forêt, la neige et le paysage (WSL). Rolf Holderegger, âgé de 59 ans, est actuellement chef de l’unité de recherche Biodiversité et écologie de la conservation du WSL et professeur titulaire à l’EPFZ. Il prendra ses nouvelles fonctions le 1er octobre 2024.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Rolf Holderegger va reprendre les rênes du WSL. Il succèdera au directeur suppléant Christoph Hegg, qui dirigeait l'institut par intérim depuis juillet 2023. M. Holderegger a étudié la biologie à l'université de Zurich, où il a obtenu son doctorat en 1997, puis a travaillé deux ans comme post-doctorant à l'université de St Andrews en Écosse. Il a également travaillé à temps partiel comme enseignant du secondaire &lt;i&gt;II&lt;/i&gt; et comme consultant dans le domaine de la protection de la nature. En 2001, il est devenu chef adjoint de l'unité de recherche Génétique écologique du WSL. En 2006, Rolf Holderegger a été promu chef de l'unité de recherche Génétique écologique et Évolution au WSL, avant d'être nommé professeur titulaire au Département des sciences des systèmes environnementaux de l'EPFZ en 2009. Depuis 2011, il dirige l'unité de recherche Biodiversité et écologie de la conservation du WSL. Il a également a été membre de la direction de l'institut de 2011 à 2023.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;L'unité de recherche mise en place et dirigée par Rolf Holderegger est l'une des plus grandes unités de recherche du WSL : elle compte plus de 60 collaborateurs et mène des activités d'excellence en matière de recherche appliquée et de sensibilisation. Elle étudie la diversité de la vie sous ses diverses formes, en passant de la diversité génétique à la diversité des espèces et des milieux naturels, ainsi que les interactions entre ces derniers. En collaboration avec la Confédération, les cantons, les communes et d'autres partenaires, Rolf Holderegger et son unité de recherche définissent les bases scientifiques pour des stratégies de gestion destinées à protéger la biodiversité et les ressources naturelles de la Suisse et de l'étranger. Ses projets de recherche ont été soutenus par l'Union européenne, le Fonds national suisse (FNS), Innosuisse, l'Office fédéral de l'environnement (OFEV), des cantons et des communes, des fonds du domaine des écoles polytechniques fédérales ainsi que par diverses fondations.&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Communication DEFR info@gs-wbf.admin.ch +41 58 462 20 07</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Rolf Holderegger nominato nuovo direttore del WSL</title>
      <lead>Il 14 giugno 2024 il Consiglio federale ha nominato Rolf Holderegger nuovo direttore dell’Istituto federale di ricerca per la foresta, la neve e il paesaggio (WSL). Al momento è a capo dell’unità di ricerca dedicata alla biodiversità e alla biologia della conservazione («Biodiversität und Naturschutzbiologieۚ») del WSL e professore titolare al Politecnico di Zurigo. Il 59enne entrerà in funzione il 1° ottobre 2024.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Rolf Holderegger subentrerà a Christoph Hegg, direttore a. i. del WSL da luglio 2023. Ha studiato biologia all'Università di Zurigo, dove ha conseguito un dottorato nel 1997. In seguito ha svolto un post-dottorato di due anni all'Università di St Andrews, in Scozia, e ha lavorato a tempo parziale come docente di liceo e consulente nell'ambito della protezione della natura. Nel 2001 è diventato viceresponsabile della sezione di genetica ecologica («Ökologische Genetik») del WSL, per poi assumere la direzione dell'unità di ricerca che si occupa di genetica ecologica ed evoluzione («Ökologische Genetik und Evolution») nel 2006. Nel 2009 è stato nominato professore titolare presso il dipartimento di scienze dei sistemi ambientali («Departement für Umweltsystemwissenschaften») del Politecnico di Zurigo. Dal 2011 è a capo dell'unità di ricerca dedicata alla biodiversità e alla biologia della conservazione del WSL e tra il 2011 e il 2023 è stato membro della Direzione dell'istituto. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Questa unità di ricerca, fondata da Holderegger e in cui collaborano più di 60 persone, svolge numerose attività di ricerca applicata ed è una delle unità più grandi e con maggiore visibilità. Si occupa di biodiversità in tutte le sue forme, dalla diversità genetica alla diversità delle specie e degli ambienti, così come delle varie interazioni. In collaborazione con alcuni enti, tra cui Confederazione, Cantoni e Comuni, Holderegger e il suo team elaborano basi scientifiche per strategie a tutela della biodiversità e delle risorse naturali in Svizzera e all'estero. I progetti di ricerca svolti sono stati sostenuti dall'Unione europea, dal Fondo nazionale svizzero, da Innosuisse, dall'Ufficio federale dell'ambiente, da Cantoni e Comuni, con mezzi del settore dei Politecnici federali e da varie fondazioni. &lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Comunicazione SG-DEFR info@gs-wbf.admin.ch +41 58 462 20 07</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Rolf Holderegger becomes new WSL Director</title>
      <lead>On 14 June, the Federal Council appointed Rolf Holderegger as the new director of the Swiss Federal Institute for Forest, Snow and Landscape Research (WSL). He is currently head of the Biodiversity and Conservation Biology Research Unit at WSL and titular professor at ETH Zurich. The 59-year-old will take up his new post on 1 October.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Rolf Holderegger is taking over the management of WSL from deputy director Christoph Hegg, who has led the institution ad interim since July 2023. Rolf Holderegger studied biology at the University of Zurich, completing his doctorate in 1997. He then worked for two years as a postdoctoral researcher at the University of St Andrews in Scotland. He also worked part-time as a secondary school teacher and as a nature conservation consultant. In 2001 he took up a position as deputy head of the Ecological Genetics section at the WSL, going on to head the Ecological Genetics and Evolution research unit from 2006. In 2009 he was appointed titular professor at the Department of Environmental Systems Sciences at ETH Zurich. Since 2011 he has headed the Biodiversity and Conservation Biology research unit at WSL. Rolf was a member of the WSL senior management from 2011 to 2023.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The research unit set up and headed by Rolf Holderegger is one of the largest research units at the WSL, with over 60 employees and above-average activities in research application and outreach. The unit investigates the diversity of life in its various forms, from genetic diversity to the diversity of species and habitats and their interactions. In collaboration with partners such as the federal government, cantons and communes, Rolf and his research unit develop scientific foundations for management strategies to protect biodiversity and natural resources in Switzerland and internationally. His research projects have been funded by the European Union, the SNSF, Innosuisse, the FOEN, the cantons and communes, the ETH Domain and several foundations.&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Communication GS-EAER info@gs-wbf.admin.ch +41 58 462 20 07</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="8">
        <name lang="de">Bildung und Forschung</name>
        <name lang="fr">Formation et recherche</name>
        <name lang="it">Formazione e ricerca</name>
        <name lang="en">Education and Research</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="10">
        <name lang="de">Bundesrat</name>
        <name lang="fr">Conseil fédéral</name>
        <name lang="it">Consiglio federale</name>
        <name lang="en">Federal Council</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="29">
        <name lang="de">Umwelt und Natur</name>
        <name lang="fr">Environnement et nature</name>
        <name lang="it">Ambiente e natura</name>
        <name lang="en">Environment and Nature</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="47">
        <name lang="de">Wirtschaft</name>
        <name lang="fr">Économie</name>
        <name lang="it">Economia</name>
        <name lang="en">Economic Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
