<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="101239" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2024-06-02</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="317" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>301</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Bundesamt für Gesundheit</name>
      <name lang="fr">Office fédéral de la santé publique</name>
      <name lang="it">Ufficio federale della sanità pubblica</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Office of Public Health</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.bag.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.bag.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.bag.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.bag.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">media@bag.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">media@bag.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">media@bag.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">media@bag.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="302" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>301</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Generalsekretariat EDI</name>
      <name lang="fr">Secrétariat général DFI</name>
      <name lang="it">Segreteria generale DFI</name>
      <name lang="en">General Secretariat FDHA</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="301">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement des Innern</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'intérieur</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'interno</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Home Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Weltgesundheitsversammlung der WHO: Mehr Zeit für Verhandlungen über Pandemieabkommen</title>
      <lead>Diese Woche haben sich die Mitgliedsstaaten der WHO in Genf zur jährlichen Weltgesundheitsversammlung (WHA) getroffen. Sie wurde gestern Samstag abgeschlossen. Die WHA hat die Internationalen Gesundheitsvorschriften angepasst und sich auf das weitere Vorgehen zu einem möglichen Pandemieabkommen geeinigt.</lead>
      <text link="no">Als vollwertiges Mitglied der WHO engagierte sich die Schweiz während der diesjährigen Weltgesundheitsversammlung zu einer breiten Reihe an Themen. Sie brachte sich aktiv in die Diskussionen zu Antibiotikaresistenzen und zum Einfluss des Klimawandels auf die Gesundheit ein und engagiert sich fortlaufend dafür, dass die WHO ihre Arbeit effizient ausführt. Weiter hat die Weltgesundheitsversammlung die «Global Health and Peace»-Initiative verabschiedet, die die Schweiz als Mitinitiantin lanciert hat. Die Initiative kommt fragilen, konfliktbetroffenen und gefährdeten Regionen zugute.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;Zudem konnten die Verhandlungen zu den Anpassungen an den Internationalen Gesundheitsvorschriften IGV (2005) im Rahmen einer Arbeitsgruppe mit Teilnahme aller Mitgliedstaaten diese Woche abgeschlossen werden. Der angepasste Text wurde durch die Weltgesundheitsversammlung im Konsens angenommen. Die Annahme der Anpassungen an den Internationalen Gesundheitsvorschriften IGV (2005) durch die WHA bindet die Schweiz noch nicht daran. Die Schweiz wird nun nach den geltenden nationalen Verfahren und gemäss den verfassungsrechtlichen und gesetzlichen Grundlagen entscheiden, ob sie diese Anpassungen gutheissen oder ablehnen will. Diese Entscheidung trifft die Schweiz souverän. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;In Bezug auf das WHO-Pandemieabkommen konnte bis zur Versammlung in Genf keine Einigung erzielt werden. Somit lag kein Text vor, welcher der Weltgesundheitsversammlung zur Verabschiedung vorgelegt werden konnte. Die Weltgesundheitsversammlung hat entschieden, dass die Verhandlungen zum Pandemieabkommen maximal um ein Jahr verlängert werden. Das Resultat soll spätestens der 78. Weltgesundheitsversammlung im Mai 2025 vorgelegt werden.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Die Schweiz begrüsst dies, denn es ist wichtig, dass die internationalen Frühwarn- und Meldesysteme effizient funktionieren und dass alle Staaten, insbesondere jene mit niedrigem Einkommen, über die nötigen Kapazitäten verfügen, um übertragbare Krankheiten zu erkennen und zu bekämpfen.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Bundesrätin Elisabeth Baume-Schneider leitete die Delegation der Schweiz an dieser WHA zum ersten Mal. Am Rande der Versammlung wurden verschiedene bilaterale Gespräche mit Gesundheitsministerinnen und Gesundheitsministern anderer Staaten geführt. Gemeinsam mit ministeriellen Delegationen aus Qatar, Estland und Portugal fand auf Initiative der Schweiz ein vertiefter Austausch zum Thema digitale Gesundheit statt. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Die Weltgesundheitsversammlung ist das oberste Entscheidungsgremium der WHO. Jedes Jahr im Mai treffen sich die Delegierten der 194 WHO-Mitgliedstaaten in Genf, um die thematische, finanzielle und organisatorische Ausrichtung und die zukünftigen Programme der Organisation zu prüfen und festzulegen. </text>
      <contact>Bundesamt für Gesundheit, Medien und Kommunikation, +41 58 462 95 05, media@bag.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Assemblée mondiale de la santé de l’OMS : les négociations pour un accord sur les pandémies sont prolongées</title>
      <lead>Les États membres de l’OMS se sont réunis cette semaine à Genève à l’occasion de l’Assemblée mondiale de la santé (AMS), qui s’est achevée hier. L’AMS a adapté le Règlement sanitaire international et s’est mise d’accord sur la marche à suivre pour un éventuel accord sur les pandémies.</lead>
      <text link="no">Membre à part entière de l’OMS, la Suisse s’est investie dans différents domaines lors de l’AMS de cette année, notamment la résistance aux antibiotiques et les répercussions du changement climatique sur la santé. Elle s’engage aussi en permanence pour que l’OMS mène ses activités de manière efficace. En outre, l’AMS a adopté l’initiative « Santé pour la paix », que la Suisse a co-lancée et qui cible les régions fragiles, en proie aux conflits ou menacées. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;En outre, les négociations portant sur les adaptations du Règlement sanitaire international (RSI) de 2005 ont pris fin cette semaine. Elles étaient organisées dans le cadre d’un groupe de travail, avec la participation de tous les États membres. L’AMS a approuvé par consensus la version adaptée du texte. Les modifications apportées ne déploient pas encore d’effet contraignant pour la Suisse, qui doit d’abord examiner si elle accepte ou rejette ces adaptations, conformément à ses procédures et à ses bases constitutionnelles et légales. Elle prend cette décision en toute souveraineté. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;L’accord de l’OMS sur les pandémies n’a pas fait l’objet d’une entente avant l’Assemblée à Genève. Ainsi, aucun texte n’a pu lui être soumis. L’AMS a décidé de prolonger d’une année au maximum les négociations concernant cet accord. Le résultat sera présenté au plus tard lors de la 78e AMS, en mai 2025.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;La Suisse salue cette décision. Elle estime qu’il est important que les systèmes d’alerte précoce et de déclaration fonctionnent efficacement et que tous les États, notamment ceux à faible revenu, disposent des capacités nécessaires pour détecter et combattre les maladies transmissibles.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Pour la première fois, la conseillère fédérale Elisabeth Baume-Schneider dirigeait la délégation suisse à l’AMS. En marge de l’Assemblée, elle a mené des entretiens bilatéraux avec différents ministres de la santé. À l’initiative de la Suisse, un échange approfondi s’est déroulé sur la santé numérique avec les délégations ministérielles du Qatar, de l’Estonie et du Portugal. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;L’AMS est l’organe décisionnel suprême de l’OMS. Chaque année en mai, les délégués de ses 194 États membres se réunissent à Genève pour examiner et définir l’orientation thématique, financière et organisationnelle ainsi que les futurs programmes de l’organisation. </text>
      <contact>Office fédéral de la santé publique, Médias et communication, +41 58 462 95 05, media@bag.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Assemblea mondiale della sanità dell’OMS: più tempo per i negoziati su un accordo pandemico</title>
      <lead>Questa settimana gli Stati membri dell’Organizzazione mondiale della sanità (OMS) si sono riuniti a Ginevra in occasione dell’annuale Assemblea mondiale della sanità, conclusasi ieri sabato. L’Assemblea ha emendato il Regolamento sanitario internazionale e ha convenuto come procedere su un possibile accordo pandemico.</lead>
      <text link="no">In quanto membro a pieno titolo dell’OMS, durante l’Assemblea mondiale della sanità di quest’anno la Svizzera si è impegnata in un ampio spettro di temi. Ha partecipato attivamente alle discussioni riguardanti l’antibiotico-resistenza e l’influsso dei cambiamenti climatici sulla salute e ha continuato ad adoperarsi affinché l’OMS svolga il proprio lavoro in maniera efficiente. L’Assemblea mondiale della sanità ha inoltre adottato l’iniziativa «Global Health and Peace» (Salute globale e pace), di cui la Svizzera è co-promotrice. L’iniziativa è pensata per essere attuata in regioni fragili, a rischio e caratterizzate da conflitti.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;Questa settimana, nell’ambito di un gruppo di lavoro con la partecipazione di tutti gli Stati membri si sono inoltre conclusi i negoziati sugli emendamenti del Regolamento sanitario internazionale RSI (2005). L’Assemblea mondiale della sanità ha adottato il testo emendato per consenso. L’adozione degli emendamenti del RSI (2005) da parte dell’Assemblea non è ancora vincolante per la Svizzera, che ora valuterà se approvarli o respingerli in base alle procedure nazionali vigenti nonché alle basi costituzionali e legali, decidendo in modo sovrano. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Per quanto riguarda l’accordo dell’OMS in materia di pandemie, siccome a Ginevra non si è riusciti a raggiungere un’intesa entro l’Assemblea mondiale della sanità, non era disponibile alcun testo da sottoporre all’Assemblea per approvazione. L’Assemblea mondiale della sanità ha deciso di prorogare i negoziati sull’accordo pandemico di un anno al massimo: il risultato dovrà essere presentato entro la 78a Assemblea mondiale della sanità, che si svolgerà nel maggio 2025.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;La Svizzera si compiace di questa decisione, poiché è importante che i sistemi internazionali di allerta precoce e di segnalazione funzionino in maniera efficiente e che tutti gli Stati, in particolare quelli a basso reddito, dispongano delle capacità necessarie per individuare e combattere le malattie trasmissibili.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;Era la prima volta che la consigliera federale Elisabeth Baume-Schneider guidava la delegazione elvetica all’Assemblea mondiale della sanità. A margine dell’Assemblea, Elisabeth Baume-Schneider ha tenuto vari colloqui bilaterali con i ministri della sanità di altri Stati. Su iniziativa della Svizzera si è inoltre svolto un intenso scambio sulla salute digitale assieme alle delegazioni ministeriali del Qatar, dell’Estonia e del Portogallo. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;L’Assemblea mondiale della sanità è il massimo organo decisionale dell’OMS. Ogni anno, in maggio, i delegati dei 194 Stati membri dell’OMS si riuniscono a Ginevra per esaminare e fissare gli obiettivi tematici, finanziari e organizzativi nonché i futuri programmi dell’organizzazione. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;</text>
      <contact>Ufficio federale della sanità pubblica UFSP, Media e comunicazione, +41 58 462 95 05, media@bag.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>WHO World Health Assembly: more time for negotiations on Pandemic Agreement</title>
      <lead>The WHO member states convened in Geneva this week for the annual World Health Assembly (WHA), which closed yesterday (Saturday 1 June). The WHA amended the International Health Regulations and agreed on the way forward to conclude a proposed Pandemic Agreement.</lead>
      <text link="no">As a full member of WHO, Switzerland championed a broad range of topics at this year’s World Health Assembly. It was actively involved in the discussions on antibiotic resistance and on the impact of climate change on health, and works on an ongoing basis to promote efficiency within WHO. In addition, the World Health Assembly adopted the Global Health and Peace Initiative, which Switzerland co-launched. The initiative will benefit healthcare in fragile, conflict-affected and vulnerable settings.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;The negotiations on the package of amendments to the International Health Regulations IHR (2005) were also concluded this week in a working group involving all member states. The amended text was adopted by the World Health Assembly in a consensus decision. The adoption of the amendments to the International Health Regulations IHR (2005) by the WHA is not yet binding on Switzerland, which will now decide, based on the applicable national procedures and in accordance with constitutional and legal frameworks, whether it wants to approve or reject the amended IHR. Switzerland will take a sovereign decision on this matter. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;With regard to the WHO Pandemic Agreement, it was not possible to reach an agreement ahead of the Assembly in Geneva, so there was no text to present to the World Health Assembly for approval. The World Health Assembly decided that negations on a Pandemic Agreement will be extended by a maximum of one year. The outcome of the negotiations is to be presented to the 78th World Health Assembly in May 2025 at the latest.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Switzerland welcomes this decision because it is important that international early warning and notification systems function effectively and that all countries – particularly low-income ones – have the necessary capacity to detect and control communicable diseases.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Federal Councillor Elisabeth Baume-Schneider led the Swiss delegation at this WHA for the first time. On the sidelines of the Assembly, various bilateral meetings were held with health ministers from other countries. Switzerland also instigated an in-depth dialogue on digital health with ministerial delegations from Qatar, Estonia and Portugal. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The World Health Assembly is the highest decision-making body of WHO. Every year in May, delegates from the 194 WHO member states meet in Geneva to decide the thematic, financial and organisational direction of WHO and to review and determine its future programmes. &lt;br /&gt;</text>
      <contact>Federal Office of Public Health, Media and Communication, +41 58 462 95 05, media@bag.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="5">
        <name lang="de">Behörden</name>
        <name lang="fr">Autorités</name>
        <name lang="it">Autorità</name>
        <name lang="en">Authorities</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="10">
        <name lang="de">Bundesrat</name>
        <name lang="fr">Conseil fédéral</name>
        <name lang="it">Consiglio federale</name>
        <name lang="en">Federal Council</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
