<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="58060" revoked="no">
    <version>3</version>
    <pubdate>2015-07-09</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="201" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>201</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="201">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Frankophonie: Integration der Jugend und Friedensförderung im Zentrum des Gesprächs zwischen Didier Burkhalter und Michaëlle Jean</title>
      <lead>Am Rande der 41. Tagung der Parlamentarischen Versammlung der Frankophonie (APF), die vom 6. bis 10. Juli 2015 in Bern stattfindet, hat sich Bundesrat Didier Burkhalter, Vorsteher des Eidgenössischen Departements für auswärtige Angelegenheiten (EDA), mit Michaëlle Jean, der Generalsekretärin der Internationalen Organisation der Frankophonie (OIF), unterhalten. Sie besprachen insbesondere die Prioritäten, die die Schweiz in ihrer Zusammenarbeit mit der OIF setzen möchte. Danach trafen sie Vertreterinnen und Vertreter des frankophonen Jugendparlaments und nahmen an der offiziellen Eröffnung der Parlamentarischen Versammlung teil.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Die Schweiz gehört der Internationalen Organisation der Frankophonie seit 1996 an und ist die drittgrösste Geberin. Beim Treffen mit OIF-Generalsekretärin Michaëlle Jean unterstrich EDA-Vorsteher Didier Burkhalter die ausgezeichnete Zusammenarbeit zwischen der Schweiz und der Frankophonie. Er sprach die beiden Prioritäten der Schweiz in der Zusammenarbeit mit der OIF an: Die Schweiz will erstens den Frieden und die Menschenrechte fördern, indem sie Mitgliedsländer bei der Überwindung ihrer Krisen und bei der Versöhnung unterstützt. Zweitens will sie den gewaltbereiten Extremismus bekämpfen und die Integration der Jugendlichen fördern, indem sie mithilft, die Zukunftsperspektiven zu verbessern. Die Schweiz ist diesbezüglich sehr aktiv in der Frankophonie und gibt ihr Fachwissen im Bereich Berufsbildung und Online-Studiengänge weiter.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Bundesrat Burkhalter sprach zudem das Thema internationales Genf an. Er erwähnte namentlich die Genfer Kandidatur für den Sitz des Ständigen Sekretariats des Vertrags über den Waffenhandel (ATT), den die UNO-Generalversammlung am 2. April 2013 verabschiedet hat. Genf ist die einzige frankophone Kandidatin. Ein weiteres Gesprächsthema war das Mandat von alt Bundespräsident Pascal Couchepin als Sonderbeauftragter der OIF für die Region der Grossen Seen und seine Mission in Burundi vom 3. bis 7. Juni 2015.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Anschliessend unterhielten sich die beiden Gesprächspartner mit Vertreterinnen und Vertretern des frankophonen Jugendparlaments über den Beitrag der Jugend zum politischen Leben, den Klimawandel, die Berufsbildung und die Geschlechtergleichstellung. Am späten Vormittag nahmen sie gemeinsam an der offiziellen Eröffnung der Parlamentarischen Versammlung der Frankophonie teil, wo sie eine Rede hielten.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;An der 41. Plenarsitzung der Parlamentarischen Versammlung der Frankophonie (APF), die vom 6. bis 10. Juli 2015 in der Schweiz stattfindet, nehmen 300 Parlamentsmitglieder teil, die über 50 Staaten vertreten. Das auf Einladung der Schweizer Sektion der APF in Bern durchgeführte Treffen ist dem Thema «Förderung qualitativ hochwertiger Bildungschancen für alle: eine prioritäre Herausforderung für die Frankophonie» gewidmet. Die APF ist gemäss der Frankophonie-Charta die konsultative Versammlung der Frankophonie. Sie ist seit 1967 das zentrale Gremium zur demokratischen Debatte der frankophonen Länder, trägt zur Stärkung der demokratischen Institutionen bei und engagiert sich in der Bildung und Zusammenarbeit, insbesondere mit den Parlamenten des Südens.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Kommunikation EDA Bundeshaus West CH-3003 Bern Tel. Kommunikationsservice: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Medienstelle: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <link id="138920">
        <title>Parlamentarische Versammlung der Frankophonie – Medienmitteilung der Parlamentsdienste (FR)</title>
        <uri>http://www.parlament.ch/d/mm/2015/Seiten/pp-apf-2015-07-01.aspx</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="138921">
        <title>Internationale Organisation der Frankophonie (OIF) (FR)</title>
        <uri>http://www.francophonie.org/</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions>
        <revision date="2015-07-09 12:32" type="R"/>
      </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Francophonie : l’intégration de la jeunesse et la promotion de la paix au cœur de l’entretien entre Didier Burkhalter et Michaëlle Jean</title>
      <lead>Le conseiller fédéral et chef du Département fédéral des affaires étrangères (DFAE) Didier Burkhalter s’est entretenu avec la Secrétaire générale de l’Organisation internationale de la Francophonie (OIF) Michaëlle Jean en marge de la 41ème session de l’Assemblée parlementaire de la Francophonie (APF), qui se tient à Berne du 6 au 10 juillet. Ils ont notamment discuté des priorités que la Suisse entend privilégier dans sa collaboration avec l’OIF. Leur entretien a été suivi d’une rencontre avec des représentants du Parlement francophone des jeunes et de leur participation à la cérémonie officielle d’ouverture de l’Assemblée.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Membre de l’Organisation internationale de la Francophonie depuis 1996, la Suisse en est le 3e contributeur. Lors de sa rencontre avec la Secrétaire générale de l’organisation Michaëlle Jean, le conseiller fédéral et chef du DFAE Didier Burkhalter a souligné l’excellente coopération entre la Suisse et la Francophonie. Il a abordé les deux priorités que la Confédération met dans sa collaboration avec l’OIF. Pour la Suisse, il s’agit d’une part de promouvoir la paix et les droits de l’homme, en soutenant en particulier les pays membres concernés en matière de sortie de crise et de réconciliation. Il s’agit d’autre part de lutter contre l’extrémisme violent et de favoriser l’intégration des jeunes en augmentant les perspectives d’avenir. A ce niveau, la Suisse est très engagée au sein de la Francophonie pour partager son savoir-faire dans le domaine de la formation professionnelle et des cours académiques en ligne.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;M. Burkhalter a par ailleurs évoqué la Genève internationale avec Mme Jean. Il a notamment attiré son attention sur la candidature de Genève pour accueillir le siège du Secrétariat permanent institué en vertu du Traité sur le commerce des armes (TCA) adopté par l’Assemblée générale de l’ONU le 2 avril 2013. A cet égard, Genève est la seule ville candidate francophone. M. Burkhalter et Mme Jean ont aussi évoqué le mandat attribué par l’OIF à l’ancien président de la Confédération Pascal Couchepin en qualité d’Envoyé spécial pour la région des Grand Lacs africains, et sa mission au Burundi du 3 au 7 juin 2015.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A l’issue de leur entretien, M. Burkhalter et Mme Jean ont conversé avec des représentants du Parlement Francophone des Jeunes, abordant l’apport de la jeunesse à la vie politique, les changements climatiques, la formation professionnelle et l’égalité des genres. En fin de matinée, ils ont participé ensemble à la cérémonie d’ouverture de l’Assemblée parlementaire de la Francophonie, où ils ont prononcé des discours d’ouverture.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Du 6 au 10 juillet 2015, la Suisse accueille l’assemblée plénière de la 41e session de l’Assemblée parlementaire de la Francophonie (APF) en présence de 300 parlementaires représentant plus de 50 pays. Organisée à Berne à l’invitation de la section suisse de l’APF, elle a pour thématique principale : « Encourager l’accès à une formation de qualité pour tous : un défi prioritaire pour la Francophonie ». L’APF est, d’après la Charte de la Francophonie, l’assemblée consultative de la Francophonie. Elle est, depuis 1967, au cœur du débat démocratique francophone, participe au renforcement des institutions démocratiques et conduit des actions de formation et de coopération à destination principalement des parlements du Sud.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Communication DFAE Palais fédéral ouest CH-3003 Berne Tél. Service de communication: +41 58 462 31 53 Tél. Service de presse: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <link id="138918">
        <title>Assemblée parlementaire de la Francophonie – communiqué de presse des Services du Parlement</title>
        <uri>http://www.parlament.ch/f/mm/2015/Pages/pp-apf-2015-07-01.aspx</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="138919">
        <title>Organisation internationale de la Francophonie (OIF)</title>
        <uri>http://www.francophonie.org/</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Francofonia: integrazione della gioventù e promozione della pace al centro del colloquio di Didier Burkhalter con Michaëlle Jean</title>
      <lead>Il consigliere federale e capo del Dipartimento degli affari esteri (DFAE) Didier Burkhalter si è intrattenuto con la segretaria generale dell’Organizzazione internazionale della Francofonia (OIF) Michaëlle Jean a margine della 41a sessione dell’Assemblea parlamentare della Francofonia (APF) che ha luogo a Berna dal 6 al 10 luglio. In particolare hanno discusso delle priorità della Svizzera nel quadro della sua collaborazione con l’OIF. Dopo il colloquio si sono incontrati con i rappresentanti del parlamento francofono dei giovani e hanno partecipato alla cerimonia ufficiale di apertura dell’Assemblea.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;La Svizzera è membro dell’Organizzazione internazionale della Francofonia dal 1996 ed è il 3° maggiore contributore. In occasione dell’incontro con la segretaria generale dell’organizzazione Michaëlle Jean, il consigliere federale e capo del DFAE Didier Burkhalter ha sottolineato l’eccellente cooperazione tra la Svizzera e la Francofonia e ha affrontato i due temi prioritari sui quali punta la Confederazione in collaborazione con l’OIF. La Svizzera mira da un lato a promuove la pace e i diritti umani, aiutando in particolare i Paesi membri interessati a uscire da una crisi o ad avviare un processo di riconciliazione. Intende inoltre lottare contro l’estremismo violento e favorire l’integrazione dei giovani incrementando le prospettive per il futuro. In tale contesto, la Svizzera si impegna molto in seno alla Francofonia per condividere le sue competenze nell’ambito della formazione professionale e dei corsi accademici online.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Il consigliere federale Burkhalter ha inoltre menzionato alla segretaria generale Jean la Ginevra internazionale, evidenziando in particolare la candidatura di Ginevra per accogliere la sede del Segretariato permanente creato nell’ambito del Trattato sul commercio delle armi (TCA) adottato dall’Assemblea generale dell’ONU il 2 aprile 2013. Tra l’altro, Ginevra è l’unica città francofona candidata. Il consigliere federale Burkhalter e la segretaria generale Jean hanno discusso anche del mandato attribuito dall’OIF all’ex presidente della Confederazione Pascal Couchepin in qualità di inviato speciale per la regione dei Grandi Laghi africani e della sua missione in Burundi dal 3 al 7 giugno 2015.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Al termine dell’incontro, il consigliere federale Burkhalter e la segretaria generale Jean si sono intrattenuti con i rappresentati del Parlamento francofono dei giovani, toccando temi come il contributo dei giovani alla vita politica, i cambiamenti climatici, la formazione professionale e l’uguaglianza di genere. Al termine della mattinata hanno partecipato alla cerimonia di apertura dell’Assemblea parlamentare della Francofonia, pronunciando ambedue un discorso di apertura.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Dal 6 al 10 luglio 2015 la Svizzera accoglie l’assemblea plenaria della 41a sessione dell’Assemblea parlamentare della Francofonia (APF) in presenza di 300 parlamentari rappresentanti oltre 50 Paesi. L’Assemblea è stata organizzata a Berna su invito della sezione svizzera dell’APF e verte sul tema: «Promovimento dell’accesso alla formazione di qualità per tutti: una sfida prioritaria per la Francofonia». Conformemente alla Carta della Francofonia, l’APF costituisce l’assemblea consultiva della Francofonia. Dal 1967 è un elemento centrale del dibattito democratico francofono, partecipa al rafforzamento delle istituzioni democratiche e svolge campagne di formazione e di cooperazione destinate principalmente ai parlamenti del Sud.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Comunicazione DFAE Palazzo federale ovest CH-3003 Berna Tel. Servizio di comunicazione: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Servizio stampa: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <link id="138922">
        <title>Assemblea parlamentare della Francofonia - comunicato stampa dei Servizi del Parlamento (FR)</title>
        <uri>http://www.parlament.ch/i/mm/2015/Pagine/pp-apf-2015-07-01.aspx</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="138923">
        <title>Organizzazione internazionale della Francofonia (OIF) (FR)</title>
        <uri>http://www.francophonie.org/</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions>
        <revision date="2015-07-09 14:45" type="R"/>
      </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Francophonie: meeting between Didier Burkhalter and Michaëlle Jean focuses on including young people and peacebuilding</title>
      <lead>Federal Councillor and Head of the Federal Department of Foreign Affairs Didier Burkhalter met with the secretary general of the International Organisation of La Francophonie (IOF), Michaëlle Jean, on the margins of the 41st session of the Parliamentary Assembly of La Francophonie held in Bern from 6 to 10 July. The two discussed topics Switzerland plans to prioritise in its cooperation with the IOF. After their meeting they spoke with representatives from the French-speaking youth parliament and took part in the assembly's official opening ceremony.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Switzerland has been a member of the International Organisation of La Francophonie since 1996 and is the 3rd largest contributor to the organisation. During his meeting with Ms Jean, Mr Burkhalter emphasised the excellent cooperation between Switzerland and the Francophonie organisation. He spoke about the two priorities for the Swiss Confederation in its work with the IOF. One priority for Switzerland is peacebuilding and human rights, in particular supporting the affected member states in crisis resolution and reconciliation. Another is addressing violent extremism and promoting the inclusion of young people by improving their prospects. As a member of the IOF, Switzerland is actively sharing its expertise in vocational and online academic training with other French-speaking countries.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mr Burkhalter also discussed International Geneva with Ms Jean. He drew her attention in particular to Geneva's application to host the headquarters of the Permanent Secretariat established under the Arms Trade Treaty (ATT) adopted by the UN General Assembly on 2 April 2013. Geneva is the only candidate from a French-speaking nation. Mr Burkhalter and Ms Jean also discussed the mandate entrusted by the IOF to the former President of the Swiss Confederation Pascal Couchepin as the special envoy to the Great Lakes region and his mission to Burundi from 3 to 7 June 2015.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Following their meeting, Mr Burkhalter and Ms Jean spoke with French-speaking youth parliament representatives about what young people bring to politics and about climate change, vocational education and training and gender equality. Later that morning they both took part in the opening ceremony of the Parliamentary Assembly of La Francophonie, where they delivered opening speeches.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;From 6 to 10 July 2015, Switzerland is hosting the plenary of the 41st session of the Parliamentary Assembly of La Francophonie, attended by 300 parliamentarians from over 50 countries. Held in Bern at the invitation of the Swiss section of the Parliamentary Assembly, it's main theme is: "Encourager l’accès à une formation de qualité pour tous : un défi prioritaire pour la Francophonie" [encouraging access to good quality education for all, a key challenge for La Francophonie]. According to the IOF's charter, the Parliamentary Assembly is a consultative assembly for French-speaking countries. It has been at the centre of French debate on democracy since 1967, helps strengthen democratic institutions and conducts training and cooperation activities, mainly for parliaments in the global South.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>FDFA Communication Federal Palace West Wing CH-3003 Bern, Switzerland Tel. Communication service: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Press service: +41 58 460 55 55 E-mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @SwissMFA</contact>
      <link id="138924">
        <title>Parliamentary Assembly of La Francophonie - Swiss Parliamentary Services press release (FR)</title>
        <uri>http://www.parlament.ch/e/mm/2015/Pages/pp-apf-2015-07-01.aspx</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="138925">
        <title>The International Organisation of La Francophonie (IOF)</title>
        <uri>http://www.francophonie.org/Welcome-to-the-International.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions>
        <revision date="2015-07-09 12:32" type="R"/>
      </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
