<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="58077" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2015-07-09</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="701" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>701</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Wirtschaft, Bildung und Forschung</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'économie, de la formation et de la recherche</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'economia, della formazione e della ricerca</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Economic Affairs, Education and Research</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="yes" id="1080" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>701</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Staatssekretariat für Bildung, Forschung und Innovation</name>
      <name lang="fr">Secrétariat d'Etat à la formation, à la recherche et à l'innovation</name>
      <name lang="it">Segreteria di Stato per la formazione, la ricerca e l'innovazione</name>
      <name lang="en">State Secretariat for Education, Research and Innovation</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.sbfi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.sbfi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.sbfi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.sbfi.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@sbfi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@sbfi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@sbfi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@sbfi.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="yes" id="703" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>701</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Staatssekretariat für Wirtschaft</name>
      <name lang="fr">Secrétariat d'Etat à l'économie</name>
      <name lang="it">Segreteria di Stato dell'economia</name>
      <name lang="en">State Secretariat for Economic Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.seco.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.seco.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.seco.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.seco.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@seco.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@seco.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@seco.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@seco.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="701">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Wirtschaft, Bildung und Forschung</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'économie, de la formation et de la recherche</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'economia, della formazione e della ricerca</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Economic Affairs, Education and Research</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Bundesrat Schneider-Ammann unterzeichnet zum Abschluss seiner USA-Reise eine Absichtserklärung zur Berufsbildung</title>
      <lead>Bundesrat Johann N. Schneider-Ammann hat heute in Washington zum Abschluss seiner USA-Reise mit Handelsministerin Penny S. Pritzker eine Absichtserklärung zur Berufsbildung unterzeichnet. Sie lanciert eine intensivierte Zusammenarbeit zwischen der Schweiz und den USA. Zuvor hatte der Vorsteher des Eidgenössischen Departements für Wirtschaft, Bildung und Forschung WBF Treffen mit Vertretern der US-Regierung zu wirtschaftlichen Fragen – insbesondere zum transatlantischen Freihandelsabkommen (TTIP) – abgehalten. Im ersten Teil der Mission besuchte die Wirtschafts- und Wissenschaftsdelegation unter Leitung des WBF-Vorstehers die US-Westküste, um für den Bildungs-, Forschungs- und Investitionsstandort Schweiz zu werben und den Austausch insbesondere im Innovationsbereich zu vertiefen. </lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Die Berufsbildung ist ein zentraler Pfeiler des Schweizer Bildungssystems. Sie trägt wesentlich dazu bei, dass die jungen Menschen in der Schweiz eine hervorragende Ausbildung erhalten und in der Arbeitswelt Fuss fassen können. Dieses Erfolgsmodell stösst international auf immer grösseres Interesse. Mit den USA pflegt die Schweiz seit mehreren Jahren einen Dialog zur Berufsbildung. Im Herbst 2014 hatten Bundesrat Schneider-Ammann und der US-Arbeitsminister Thomas Perez die Arbeiten für eine vertiefte Zusammenarbeit angestossen, die nun mit der Unterzeichnung der Absichtserklärung lanciert wird. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ein Arbeitsprogramm mit konkreten Massnahmen wird derzeit ausgearbeitet. So ist beispielsweise ein Pilotprojekt zum Erfahrungsaustausch in einzelnen US-Staaten vorgesehen, das bei Firmen anknüpft, die bereits Erfahrungen mit der Ausbildung von Berufsleuten gesammelt haben. Auch Projekte für Praktika und zur Förderung der Vergleichbarkeit und Akzeptanz von Abschlüssen der Berufsbildner und Lehrpersonen werden geprüft. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Am letzten Tag der fünftägigen USA-Reise fanden zudem verschiedene Treffen mit Regierungsvertretern statt. Der WBF-Vorsteher schlug dem United States Trade Representative Michael B. Froman vor, im Rahmen des existierenden Handelsdialogs zwischen den USA und den EFTA-Staaten konkrete Schritte zum weiteren Ausbau der wirtschaftlichen Beziehungen zu prüfen. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Die USA sind der zweitwichtigste Handelspartner unseres Landes (Handelsvolumen von über 48 Milliarden Franken), das wiederum der sechstgrösste Investor in den Vereinigten Staaten ist. Die Schweiz setzt deshalb alles daran, auch nach dem geplanten Abschluss eines transatlantischen Freihandelsabkommens zwischen der EU und den USA (TTIP) den Schweizer Firmen optimale Wettbewerbsbedingungen auf dem US-Markt und damit Wettbewerbsfähigkeit und Arbeitsplätze zu sichern. Auch die gleichentags unterzeichnete Vereinbarung zur gegenseitigen Anerkennung der Bio-Vorschriften beider Länder dient dem verbesserten Marktzugang für Schweizer Produkte.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Im ersten Teil der Reise an der US-Westküste hatte Bundesrat Schneider-Ammann mit einer Wirtschafts- und Wissenschaftsdelegation für die Schweiz als Bildungs-, Forschungs- und Investitionsstandort geworben. Vor allem im Innovationsbereich wurde mit Gesprächen und Besuchen im Silicon Valley der Austausch vertieft. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Die Schweiz nimmt seit Jahren Spitzenplätze in Innovationsrankings ein. Die Delegation konnte entsprechend eigene Erfahrungen einbringen und ihrerseits unter anderem für den Aufbau des Schweizerischen Innovationsparks von den Kompetenzen der amerikanischen Partner profitieren. Mit Jerry Brown, dem Gouverneur Kaliforniens, sprach der WBF-Vorsteher über wirtschaftliche Fragen und die schweizerische Präsenz in San Francisco, die mit der Vereinigung von Generalkonsulat, swissnex, Swiss Business Hub und Schweiz Tourismus unter einem Dach weiter gestärkt wird.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Noé Blancpain, Leiter Kommunikation WBF, Tel. 058 462 39 60 (falls aufgrund Zeitverschiebung nicht erreichbar: Sekretariat Kommunikation WBF, Tel. 058 462 20 07)</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Le chef du DEFR signe une déclaration d’intention sur la formation professionnelle au terme de son voyage aux Etats-Unis</title>
      <lead>Au terme de son voyage aux Etats-Unis, le conseiller fédéral Johann N. Schneider-Ammann a signé aujourd’hui, à Washington, une déclaration d’intention sur la formation professionnelle avec Penny S. Pritzker, ministre du Commerce, qui pose les jalons d’une coopération renforcée entre la Suisse et les Etats-Unis. Le chef du Département fédéral de l’économie, de la formation et de la recherche (DEFR) a auparavant rencontré des représentants du gouvernement américain pour s’entretenir de questions économiques, en particulier du partenariat transatlantique de commerce et d’investissement (TTIP). Durant la première partie de la mission, la délégation économique et scientifique, emmenée par le chef du DEFR, s’est rendue sur la côte ouest des Etats-Unis afin de promouvoir la place suisse de recherche, de formation et d’innovation, et d’approfondir les échanges, notamment en matière d’innovation.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;La formation professionnelle est l'un des piliers du système de formation suisse. Elle permet aux jeunes de bénéficier d'une excellente formation et de faire leurs premiers pas dans le monde du travail. Le modèle de réussite suscite toujours plus d'intérêt sur le plan international et la Suisse entretient depuis plusieurs années un dialogue avec les Etats-Unis à ce sujet. Le conseiller fédéral Schneider-Ammann et le ministre américain du Travail, Thomas Perez, avaient engagé l'automne dernier des travaux visant une coopération renforcée, qui prend effet avec la signature de la déclaration d'intention. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Un programme de travail contenant des mesures concrètes est en cours de développement. Il prévoit par exemple un projet pilote d'échange d'expériences dans certains Etats américains qui se fonde sur la collaboration avec des entreprises expérimentées dans la formation de professionnels. Des projets relatifs aux stages et à la promotion de la comparabilité et de la reconnaissance des diplômes de formateurs et d'enseignants sont également à l'étude.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Au cours du cinquième et dernier jour du voyage, différentes réunions ont été organisées avec des représentants du gouvernement. Le chef du DEFR a proposé au représentant américain au commerce, Michael B. Froman, d'examiner des mesures concrètes pour développer les relations économiques dans le cadre du dialogue commercial existant entre les Etats-Unis et l'AELE.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Les Etats-Unis étant le deuxième partenaire commercial de la Suisse (volume des échanges supérieur à 48 milliards de francs), et notre pays le sixième investisseur aux Etats-Unis, la Suisse s'attache à maintenir des conditions de concurrence optimales sur le marché américain pour ses entreprises, et ce même si le partenariat transatlantique de commerce et d'investissement (TTIP) entre l'UE et les Etats-Unis est conclu, afin que ces entreprises puissent préserver leur compétitivité et les emplois. L'accord sur la reconnaissance réciproque des dispositions relatives aux produits biologiques, signé le même jour que la déclaration d'intention, vise également à améliorer l'accès au marché pour les produits suisses.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Durant la première partie du séjour, le conseiller fédéral Schneider-Ammann s'était rendu sur la côte ouest avec une délégation économique et scientifique afin de promouvoir la place suisse de formation, de recherche et d'innovation. Les échanges ont été particulièrement intenses dans le domaine de l'innovation, à travers des discussions et des visites dans la Silicon Valley. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Depuis des années, la Suisse occupe les premiers rangs dans les classements internationaux en matière d'innovation. La délégation a ainsi pu partager son expérience et, en retour, profiter des compétences des partenaires américains, notamment pour le développement du Parc suisse d'innovation. Le chef du DEFR s'est entretenu avec le gouverneur de la Californie, Jerry Brown, de questions économiques et de la présence suisse à San Francisco, renforcée par la réunion, sous le même toit, du consulat général, de swissnex, du Swiss Business Hub et de Suisse Tourisme.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Noé Blancpain, chef du service de la Communication du DEFR, tél. 058 462 39 60 (si injoignable en raison du décalage horaire, s’adresser au secrétariat du service de la Communication du DEFR, tél. 058 462 20 07)</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Il consigliere federale Schneider-Ammann conclude il viaggio negli USA e firma una dichiarazione d’intenti sulla formazione professionale</title>
      <lead>Al termine del suo viaggio negli Stati Uniti, oggi a Washington il consigliere federale Johann N. Schneider-Ammann ha firmato una dichiarazione d’intenti sulla formazione professionale insieme alla ministra del commercio Penny S. Pritzker. Il documento inaugura una collaborazione più intensa tra la Svizzera e gli USA. In precedenza il capo del Dipartimento federale dell’economia, della formazione e della ricerca (DEFR) ha discusso di questioni economiche con i rappresentanti del governo americano, in particolare del Partenariato transatlantico sul commercio e gli investimenti (TTIP). Durante la prima parte della missione la delegazione scientifica ed economica che ha accompagnato il capo del DEFR si è recata sulla costa ovest per esporre i pregi della piazza svizzera in materia di educazione, ricerca e innovazione e approfondire gli scambi, specialmente nel campo dell’innovazione. </lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;La formazione professionale è un pilastro del sistema educativo svizzero grazie al quale i giovani nel nostro Paese vantano un'eccezionale livello formativo che permette loro di entrare nel mondo del lavoro. Questo modello di successo sta suscitando un crescente interesse nel mondo intero e da diversi anni ormai la Svizzera coltiva con gli Stati Uniti un dialogo incentrato proprio sulla formazione professionale. Nell'autunno del 2014 il consigliere federale Schneider-Ammann e il ministro del lavoro USA Thomas Perez si erano ripromessi di approfondire la collaborazione che ora è stata lanciata con la firma della dichiarazione d'intenti. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;È attualmente allo studio un programma di lavoro con misure concrete. Per esempio, è previsto un progetto pilota sullo scambio di esperienze in alcuni Stati degli USA: si tratta di imprese che hanno già raccolto esperienze in materia di formazione di professionisti. L'analisi verte anche su progetti per praticantati o per promuovere il riconoscimento dei titoli dei formatori professionali e dei docenti. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Durante l'ultimo dei cinque giorni negli Stati Uniti ci sono stati diversi incontri con rappresentanti del governo americano. Il capo del DEFR ha proposto misure concrete al rappresentante del Commercio degli Stati Uniti Michael B. Froman per potenziare ulteriormente le relazioni economiche nell'ambito del dialogo commerciale che già esiste tra gli USA e gli Stati dell'AELS. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Gli Stati Uniti sono il secondo partner commerciale del nostro Paese (il volume degli scambi commerciali supera i 48 miliardi di franchi), che a sua volta è il sesto investitore in assoluto negli Stati Uniti. La Svizzera pertanto sta facendo il massimo, anche dopo la prevista stipula di un Partenariato transatlantico sul commercio e gli investimenti tra gli Stati Uniti e l'Unione europea (TTIP), per garantire alle imprese svizzere le migliori condizioni concorrenziali sul mercato USA, e dunque competitività e posti di lavoro. Lo stesso giorno è stato firmato anche un accordo sul mutuo riconoscimento delle norme per l'agricoltura biologica di entrambi i Paesi, che faciliterà l'accesso dei prodotti svizzeri al mercato americano.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Durante la prima parte del viaggio lungo la costa occidentale, il consigliere federale Schneider-Ammann accompagnato da una delegazione economica e scientifica ha vantato i pregi della Svizzera quale piattaforma di formazione, ricerca e innovazione. Gli scambi di opinioni hanno toccato in particolar modo il settore dell'innovazione, con colloqui e visite nella Silicon Valley. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Da anni ormai la Svizzera svetta ai vertici delle classifiche dell'innovazione. La delegazione ha dunque potuto condividere le proprie esperienze e approfittare delle competenze dei partner americani, non da ultimo per l'allestimento del parco svizzero dell'innovazione, lo Swiss Innovation Park. Con il governatore della California Jerry Brown il capo del DEFR ha discusso di questioni economiche e della presenza svizzera a San Francisco, che uscirà rinforzata dalla concentrazione in un'unica sede del Consolato generale, swissnex, Swiss Business Hub e Svizzera Turismo.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Noé Blancpain, capo Comunicazione DEFR, tel. 058 462 39 60 (se irreperibile causa fuso orario: segreteria Comunicazione DEFR, tel. 058 462 20 07)</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Federal Councillor Schneider-Ammann Concludes His Trip to the United States by Signing a Declaration of Intent on Vocational Education and Training</title>
      <lead>Federal Councillor Johann N. Schneider-Ammann wrapped up his trip to the U.S. today by signing a declaration of intent on Vocational Education and Training with U.S. Secretary of Commerce Penny S. Pritzker. This declaration will pave the way to more substantive cooperation between Switzerland and the U.S.. Before the declaration was signed, the Head of the Federal Department of Economic Affairs, Education and Research (EAER) held talks with U.S. government representatives on economic issues, namely the Transatlantic Trade and Investment Partnership (TTIP). On the first leg of the trip, the economic and scientific delegation, led by the Head of the EAER, visited the West Coast of the United States to promote Switzerland as a destination for education, research and investment, and to promote new partnerships in innovation.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Vocational education and training are core principles of the Swiss educational system. They play a major role in ensuring adequate education and job preparation for young people in Switzerland. Switzerland has received quite a lot of international interest in its apprenticeship model. Together, Switzerland and the United States have maintained a productive dialogue on Vocational Education and Training (VET). Last fall, Federal Councillor Schneider-Ammann and U.S. Secretary of Labor Thomas Perez helped initiate this bilateral cooperation which has now materialized in the signing of this declaration of intent.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A work program containing various aspects of the cooperation is currently being developed, including pilot projects in a select number of U.S. states where Swiss affiliates already have a presence. Opportunities are also being explored for traineeships and to improve the comparability and appreciation of qualifications not only for apprentices and students but also for VET trainers and teaching staff.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the last day of the five-day visit to the United States, members of the Swiss delegation participated in a number of meetings with U.S. government representatives. The Head of the EAER met with U.S. Trade Representative Michael B. Froman, and the two examined concrete steps to further expansion of economic relations within the framework of the existing trade dialogue between the U.S. and the EFTA states.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The United States is Switzerland's second most important trade partner (trade volume of over CHF 48 billion), and Switzerland is the sixth largest foreign investor in the U.S.. Switzerland will therefore seek to ensure that Swiss companies enjoy an optimal framework in which to conduct business in the U.S. in case a transatlantic free trade agreement between the EU and the U.S. should be found, thus safeguarding competitiveness and jobs. The agreement on the mutual recognition of rules on organic production signed on the same day is also intended to improve market access for Swiss products.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the first leg of the trip, Federal Councillor Schneider-Ammann and an economic and scientific delegation laid out the advantages Switzerland has as a destination for education, research and innovation. Exchanges were solidified through discussions and visits to Silicon Valley in California, a hub for research, development, and innovation in the United States.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Switzerland has enjoyed high marks in global innovation rankings for a number of consecutive years. Members of the delegation shared experiences and expertise in developing Innovation Hubs with their U.S. counterparts, who have established a similar center. During talks with California Governor Jerry Brown, Federal Councillor Schneider-Ammann discussed economic issues and the further strengthening of Switzerland's presence in San Francisco by joining the Consulate General, swissnex, the Swiss Business Hub, and Switzerland Tourism under one roof.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Noé Blancpain, Head of EAER Communications, Tel. 058 462 39 60 (if unavailable due to time difference: EAER Communications Secretariat, Tel. 058 462 20 07)</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="47">
        <name lang="de">Wirtschaft</name>
        <name lang="fr">Économie</name>
        <name lang="it">Economia</name>
        <name lang="en">Economic Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
