<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="20130" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2008-07-11</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="201" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>201</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="201">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Besuch von Staatssekretär Michael Ambühl in Washington</title>
      <lead>Anlässlich seines Besuchs in den USA am 10. und 11. Juli 2008 traf EDA-Staatssekretär Michael Ambühl seinen amerikanischen Amtskollegen, den neuen US-Staatssekretär für Politische Angelegenheiten im amerikanischen Aussenministerium, William J. Burns.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Dieses Treffen fand im Rahmen der regelmässigen Politischen Konsultationen statt, welche seit der Unterzeichnung eines Memorandum of Understanding für eine verstärkte Zusammenarbeit zwischen den USA und der Schweiz seit 2006 bestehen.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Die offiziellen Gespräche in Washington boten Gelegenheit, aktuelle bilaterale Fragen sowie internationale Themen wie Kosovo, Iran und Afghanistan zu erörtern. &amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Während seines Aufenthaltes traf Staatssekretär Michael Ambühl zudem mit Vertretern der Aussenpolitischen Kommission des Repräsentantenhauses zusammen und führte Gespräche mit politischen Beratern der Präsidentschaftskandidaten zu aktuellen aussenpolitischen Fragen der USA.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Presse- und Informationsdienst Bundeshaus West CH-3003 Bern Tel.: +41 (0)31 322 31 53 Fax: +41 (0)31 324 90 47 E-Mail: info@eda.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Visite du Secrétaire d’Etat Michael Ambühl à Washington</title>
      <lead>À l’occasion de sa visite aux Etats-Unis les 10 et 11 juillet 2008, le Secrétaire d’Etat du DFAE M. Michael Ambühl a rencontré son homologue américain, le nouveau Sous-secrétaire d’Etat aux affaires politiques du Ministère des affaires étrangères américain, M. William J. Burns.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Cette rencontre a eu lieu dans le cadre des consultations politiques organisées régulièrement depuis la signature en 2006 d’un protocole d’entente (Memorandum of Understanding) visant au renforcement de la coopération entre la Suisse et les Etats-Unis.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Les entretiens officiels à Washington ont permis d’aborder des sujets bilatéraux actuels et des thèmes internationaux tels que le Kosovo, l’Iran et l’Afghanistan. &amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Lors de son séjour, M.&amp;nbsp;Michael Ambühl a également rencontré des membres de la Commission des affaires étrangères de la Chambre des représentants, et s’est entretenu avec des conseillers politiques des candidats présidentiels sur des questions d’actualité liées à la politique étrangère des Etats-Unis.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Service de presse et d'information Palais fédéral ouest CH-3003 Berne Tél.: (+41) 031 322 31 53 Fax: (+41) 031 324 90 47 E-Mail: info@eda.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Visita del segretario di Stato Michael Ambühl a Washington</title>
      <lead>In occasione della sua visita negli Stati Uniti, il 10 e l'11 luglio 2008, Michael Ambühl, segretario di Stato del Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri (DFAE), ha incontrato il suo omologo americano William J. Burns, nuovo Segretario di Stato per gli affari politici del Ministero degli affari esteri americano.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Questo incontro si è svolto nel quadro delle periodiche consultazioni politiche avviate nel 2006 con la firma di un Memorandum d'intesa per una rafforzata cooperazione fra Stati Uniti e Svizzera. &amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;I colloqui ufficiali a Washington hanno fornito l'occasione per uno scambio di vedute su questioni bilaterali attuali e temi internazionali come il Kosovo, l'Iran e l'Afghanistan. &amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Durante il suo soggiorno, il segretario di Stato Michael Ambühl ha avuto un incontro comune con alcuni rappresentanti delle commissioni di politica estera della Camera dei rappresentanti, nonché colloqui con consulenti politici dei candidati presidenziali su questioni attuali di politica estera statunitense.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Servizio stampa e informazione Palazzo federale ovest CH-3003 Berna Tel.: (+41) 031 322 31 53 Fax: (+41) 031 324 90 47 E-Mail: info@eda.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Visit to Washington by State Secretary Michael Ambühl</title>
      <lead>Michael Ambühl, State Secretary of the Federal Department of Foreign Affairs, paid a visit on 10 and 11 July to his new counterpart, Mr. William J. Burns, Under Secretary of State, who is in charge of political affairs at the U.S. Department of State in Washington.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;This meeting was part of the regular consultations between Switzerland and the United States following the adoption of a Memorandum of Understanding agreed by both countries in May 2006 to establish a framework for intensified cooperation.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The official talks in Washington gave the opportunity to address bilateral questions as well as international themes such as Kosovo, Iran and Afghanistan.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;During his visit in Washington, State Secretary Ambühl also met with Members of the House of Representatives Committee on Foreign Affairs. He moreover met with political advisors of the presidential candidates to discuss current foreign policy issues of the United States.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Press and Information Service Bundeshaus West CH-3003 Bern Tel.: (+41) 031 322 31 53 Fax: (+41) 031 324 90 47 E-Mail: info@eda.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
