<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="25423" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2009-02-19</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="811" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>801</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Bundesamt für Umwelt BAFU</name>
      <name lang="fr">Office fédéral de l'environnement OFEV</name>
      <name lang="it">Ufficio federale dell'ambiente UFAM</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Office for the Environment FOEN</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.bafu.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.bafu.admin.ch/fr</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.bafu.admin.ch/it</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.bafu.admin.ch/en</www>
      <email lang="de">info@bafu.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@bafu.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@bafu.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@bafu.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="801">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Umwelt, Verkehr, Energie und Kommunikation</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'environnement, des transports, de l'énergie et de la communication</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'ambiente, dei trasporti, dell'energia e delle comunicazioni</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of the Environment, Transport, Energy and Communications</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.uvek.admin.ch/uvek/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.uvek.admin.ch/uvek/fr/home.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.uvek.admin.ch/uvek/it/home.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.uvek.admin.ch/uvek/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-uvek.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-uvek.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-uvek.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-uvek.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Informationen über Schadstoffe und Abfälle grösserer Firmen neu im Internet einsehbar</title>
      <lead>Die Schweiz hat sich international verpflichtet, Informationen über Schadstofffreisetzungen und –transfers öffentlich einsehbar zu machen. Ab heute sind auf der Internetseite des Bundesamts für Umwelt BAFU Meldungen von knapp 200 Betrieben aus dem Jahr 2007 abrufbar.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Das Bundesamt für Umwelt stellt ab sofort unter www.umwelt-schweiz.ch/swissprtr der Öffentlichkeit ein neues Umweltinformationssystem zur Verfügung, das so genannte Schadstofffreisetzungs- und -transferregister der Schweiz (Swiss Pollutant Release and Transfer Register, SwissPRTR). Es liefert Informationen zu Freisetzungen und Transfers von Schadstoffen und Abfällen von Betrieben sowie aus diffusen Quellen. SwissPRTR leistet einen Beitrag zur Information der Öffentlichkeit über die Umweltsituation und trägt zur Reduktion der Umweltbelastung in der Schweiz bei.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Mit diesem neuen Instrument soll Transparenz geschaffen und die faktenbasierte Kommunikation gefördert werden. Das Management von meldepflichtigen Betrieben kann die eigenen Daten mit denen anderer Betriebe vergleichen und entscheiden, ob weitere Maßnahmen nötig sind, um seine Verantwortung gegenüber Mitarbeitenden und der Öffentlichkeit wahrzunehmen. Vertiefte Kenntnisse über Zusammenhänge von betrieblichen Prozessen, den Einsatz von Chemikalien und die resultierenden Schadstofffreisetzungen oder Abfälle können zu Innovationen und Kostensenkungen führen.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Behörden können das Register als Führungsinstrument für das nachhaltige Management von Schadstofffreisetzungen sowie von Transfers von Abfällen und Schadstoffen in Abwasser nutzen. Die Übersicht über die örtliche Verteilung und den zeitlichen Verlauf von Schadstofffreisetzungen kann dann zur Planung von langfristig angelegten Massnahmen zur Schadstoffreduktion sowie als Mittel der Überwachung und Steuerung verwendet werden.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Das Register umfasst zurzeit knapp 200 Unternehmen sowie 86 Schadstoffe. Ebenfalls enthält es Informationen über Transfers von Abfällen und Sonderabfällen. Die Daten werden jährlich aktualisiert.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Die rechtliche Grundlage von SwissPRTR ist die Verordnung zum Register über die Freisetzung von Schadstoffen sowie den Transfer von Abfällen und von Schadstoffen in Abwasser vom 15. Dezember 2006.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Auskünfte Georg Karlaganis, Chef Abteilung Stoffe, Boden, Biotechnologie BAFU, 079 415 99 62 Christoph Moor, Sektion Biotechnologie und Stoffflüsse BAFU, 031 322 93 84</contact>
      <link id="51424">
        <title>Schadstoffregister SwissPRTR</title>
        <uri>http://www.bafu.admin.ch/chemikalien/prtr/index.html?lang=de</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Mise en ligne d'un registre sur les rejets et transferts de polluants des entreprises</title>
      <lead>La Suisse s’est engagée au plan international à mettre à disposition du public des informations sur les rejets et transferts de polluants. Dès aujourd’hui, il est possible de consulter, sur le site internet de l’Office fédéral de l’environnement (OFEV), les notifications pour 2007 de près de 200 entreprises.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Un nouveau système d’information environnementale a été mis aujourd’hui à disposition du public par l’Office fédéral de l’environnement (cf. www.environnement-suisse.ch/swissprtr). Il s’agit du Registre suisse des rejets et transferts de polluants (Swiss Pollutant Release and Transfer Register, SwissPRTR), qui fournit des informations sur les polluants et déchets rejetés ou transférés par les entreprises et les sources diffuses. SwissPRTR contribue à informer le public de l’état de l’environnement et à réduire la pollution en Suisse.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Ce nouvel instrument doit créer la transparence et favoriser la communication basée sur des faits. Il permettra aux dirigeants des entreprises soumises à notification de comparer leurs propres données avec celles d’autres entreprises, afin de décider s’ils doivent prendre des mesures supplémentaires pour répondre entièrement de leur responsabilité à l’égard de leurs collaborateurs et de la société. De plus, de meilleures connaissances des liens existants entre les processus internes aux entreprises, l’emploi de produits chimiques et les rejets de polluants ou de déchets qui en résultent peuvent favoriser les innovations et les économies.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Le registre pourra servir d’outil aux autorités pour gérer, dans une optique durable, les rejets de polluants,&amp;nbsp; ainsi que les transferts de déchets et de polluants dans les eaux usées. La vue d’ensemble qu’il offre de la répartition géographique et temporelle des rejets devrait faciliter la planification de mesures de réduction des polluants à long terme et fera de SwissPRTR un instrument précieux de surveillance et de pilotage.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;A l’heure actuelle, le registre contient les données d’environ 200 entreprises et de 86 polluants, de même que des informations sur les transferts de déchets et de déchets spéciaux. Les données seront mises à jour chaque année.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Le registre est fondé sur l’ordonnance du 15 décembre 2006 sur le registre des rejets de polluants et des transferts de déchets et de polluants dans les eaux usées (ORRTP).&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Renseignements M. Georg Karlaganis, chef de la division Substances, sol, biotechnologie, +41 79 415 99 62 M. Christoph Moor, section Biotechnologie et flux de substances de l’OFEV, +41 31 322 93 84</contact>
      <link id="51425">
        <title>Registre des polluants SwissPRTR</title>
        <uri>http://www.bafu.admin.ch/chemikalien/prtr/index.html?lang=fr</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Informazioni su sostanze inquinanti e rifiuti di grandi imprese: ora disponibili in Internet</title>
      <lead>La Svizzera si è impegnata a livello internazionale a rendere pubbliche le informazioni relative alle emissioni e ai trasferimenti di sostanze inquinanti. Sul sito dell’Ufficio federale dell’ambiente (UFAM) è da oggi possibile consultare le notifiche, risalenti al 2007, di quasi 200 imprese.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Nel suo sito www.ambiente-svizzera.ch/swissprtr, l’Ufficio federale dell’ambiente mette da subito a disposizione del pubblico un nuovo sistema di informazione ambientale, il cosiddetto Registro svizzero delle emissioni e dei trasferimenti di sostanze inquinanti (Swiss Pollutant Release and Transfer Register, SwissPRTR). Tale registro fornisce informazioni sulle emissioni e i trasferimenti di sostanze inquinanti e di rifiuti delle imprese come pure di fonti diffuse. SwissPRTR informa il pubblico sulla situazione ambientale e contribuisce alla riduzione dell’inquinamento ambientale in Svizzera.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Con questo nuovo strumento si intende creare trasparenza e favorire una comunicazione basata sui fatti. I dirigenti delle imprese con obbligo di notifica possono confrontare i propri dati con quelli di altre imprese e quindi decidere se sono necessarie misure supplementari al fine di garantire le proprie responsabilità nei confronti dei collaboratori e della collettività. Conoscenze più approfondite sulle relazioni fra i processi aziendali, l’impiego di prodotti chimici e le emissioni di sostanze inquinanti o rifiuti che ne conseguono possono portare a innovazioni o alla riduzione dei costi.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Le autorità possono utilizzare il registro quale strumento direttivo per la gestione sostenibile delle emissioni di sostanze inquinanti e per i trasferimenti di rifiuti e sostanze inquinanti nelle acque di scarico. Il quadro d’insieme sulla ripartizione geografica e l’andamento temporale delle emissioni di sostanze inquinanti può essere impiegato per pianificare misure a lungo termine al fine di ridurre le emissioni di sostanze inquinanti o quale strumento per la sorveglianza e la gestione.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Il registro comprende attualmente poco meno di 200 imprese e 86 sostanze inquinanti. Contiene altresì informazioni sui trasferimenti di rifiuti e rifiuti speciali. I dati sono aggiornati annualmente.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;La base giuridica di SwissPRTR è costituita dall’ordinanza del 15 dicembre 2006 concernente il registro delle emissioni di sostanze inquinanti e dei trasferimenti di rifiuti e di sostanze inquinanti nelle acque di scarico.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Informazioni Georg Karlaganis, capo della divisione Sostanze, suolo, biotecnologia UFAM, 079 415 99 62 Christoph Moor, sezione Biotecnologia e flussi di sostanze UFAM, 031 322 93 84</contact>
      <link id="51426">
        <title>Registro delle emissioni di inquinanti SwissPRTR</title>
        <uri>http://www.bafu.admin.ch/chemikalien/prtr/index.html?lang=it</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Information on pollutants and waste from large companies now visible on the Internet</title>
      <lead>Switzerland has made an international commitment to provide public access to information about pollutant releases and transfers. Starting today, data reported for 2007 by approximately 200 facilities can be viewed on the Internet site of the Federal Office for the Environment (FOEN).</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;The Federal Office for the Environment’s new environmental information system known as the Swiss Pollutant Release and Transfer Register, or the SwissPRTR for short, is now available to the public at www.environment-switzerland.ch/swissprtr. It provides information about releases and transfers of pollutants and waste from facilities and diffuse sources. The SwissPRTR helps inform the public about the state of the environment and reduce environmental pollution in Switzerland.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;This new instrument is intended to create transparency and promote the communication based on accurate information. The management of facilities subject to report requirement can compare their own data with that of other facilities. This may help companies decide whether they must take further measures in order to fulfil their responsibility towards their employees and society in general. Furthermore, better knowledge of the relations between operational processes, the use of certain chemicals and the resulting releases of pollutants or production of waste can favour innovations and help find ways of cutting costs.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Authorities can use the register as an instrument to control the sustainable management of pollutant releases and of transfers of waste and pollutants into waste water. The overview that the SwissPRTR offers on the spatial and temporal distribution of pollutant releases can help to plan long-term pollutant reduction measures and aid surveillance and control efforts.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The register currently contains data for 200 companies and 86 pollutants as well as information about transfers of hazardous and non hazardous waste. It will be updated every year.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The legal basis for the SwissPRTR is the Ordinance of 15 December 2006 on the Register relating to Pollutant Release and the Transfer of Waste and of Pollutants in Waste Water.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Address for enquiries: Georg Karlaganis, Director, FOEN Substances, Soil, Biotechnology Division, +41 79 415 99 62 Christoph Moor, FOEN Biotechnology and Substance Flows Section, +41 31 322 93 84</contact>
      <link id="51427">
        <title>SwissPRTR pollutant register</title>
        <uri>http://www.bafu.admin.ch/chemikalien/prtr/index.html?lang=en</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <offers>
      <offer id="143" org-id="811">
        <name lang="de">Medienmitteilungen des BAFU</name>
        <name lang="fr">Communiqués de l'OFEV</name>
        <name lang="it">Comunicati dell'UFAM</name>
        <name lang="en">Media releases of the FOEN</name>
      </offer>
    </offers>
    <keywords>
      <keyword id="230" org-id="811">
        <name lang="de">Chemikalien</name>
        <name lang="fr">Produits chimiques</name>
        <name lang="it">Prodotti chimici</name>
        <name lang="en">Chemicals</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="1300" org-id="811">
        <name lang="de">Umweltbeobachtung</name>
        <name lang="fr">Observation de l'environnement</name>
        <name lang="it">Monitoraggio ambientale</name>
        <name lang="en">"Environmental monitoring</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="510" org-id="811">
        <name lang="de">Gewässerschutz</name>
        <name lang="fr">Gewässerschutz</name>
        <name lang="it">Gewässerschutz</name>
        <name lang="en">Gewässerschutz</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="1390" org-id="811">
        <name lang="de">Wasser</name>
        <name lang="fr">Eaux</name>
        <name lang="it">Acqua</name>
        <name lang="en">Water</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="700" org-id="811">
        <name lang="de">Luft</name>
        <name lang="fr">Air</name>
        <name lang="it">Aria</name>
        <name lang="en">Air</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="110" org-id="811">
        <name lang="de">Boden</name>
        <name lang="fr">Sol</name>
        <name lang="it">Suolo</name>
        <name lang="en">Soil</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="173" org-id="811">
        <name lang="de">Bundesamt für Umwelt: Startseite</name>
        <name lang="fr">Office fédéral de l'environnement: page d'accueil</name>
        <name lang="it">Ufficio federale dell'ambiente: pagina iniziale</name>
        <name lang="en">Federal Office for the Environment: Homepage</name>
      </keyword>
    </keywords>
    <topics>
      <topic id="29">
        <name lang="de">Umwelt und Natur</name>
        <name lang="fr">Environnement et nature</name>
        <name lang="it">Ambiente e natura</name>
        <name lang="en">Environment and Nature</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
