<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="25544" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2009-02-25</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="201" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>201</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="201">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Letzte Verlängerung der Blockierung der Mobutu-Gelder</title>
      <lead>Mit Bundesratsbeschluss vom 12. Dezember 2008 war die Blockierung der Vermögenswerte des verstorbenen zairischen Präsidenten Mobutu und seines Umfelds (ca. 7,7 Mio. Franken) bis zum 28. Februar 2009 verlängert worden. Diese Verlängerung sollte es einerseits dem Anwalt der Demokratischen Republik Kongo (DRK) erlauben, in der Schweiz ein Verfahren zur gerichtlichen Sperrung der Vermögenswerte einzuleiten, und andererseits der zuständigen Gerichtsbehörde ermöglichen, über die Fortführung des Verfahrens zu entscheiden. Die DRK hat am 23. Januar 2009 bei der Bundesanwaltschaft Strafanzeige eingereicht. Da das Aktenstudium sehr aufwändig ist, hielt es der Bundesrat für notwendig, eine letzte Verlängerung der Blockierung um zwei Monate, bis zum 30. April 2009, anzuordnen.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Die Blockierung der Vermögenswerte Mobutus (ca. 7,7&amp;nbsp;Mio. Franken) geht auf das Jahr 1997 zurück, als die DRK der Schweiz ein Rechtshilfegesuch in Strafsachen unterbreitet hatte. Das Bundesamt für Justiz sah sich im Dezember 2003 aber ge­zwungen, das Rechtshilfegesuch abzulehnen, worauf der Bundesrat eine Blockie­rung der Gelder gemäss Artikel&amp;nbsp;184 Absatz&amp;nbsp;3 BV anordnete. Diese Sperre, die 2006 und Ende 2008 verlängert wurde, wäre am 28.&amp;nbsp;Februar 2009 abgelaufen. In der Zwischenzeit hatte der Bundesrat dem Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten (EDA) den Auftrag erteilt, die Parteien bei der Suche nach einer zufriedenstellenden Lösung zu unterstützen. &amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Die DRK reichte darauf am 23.&amp;nbsp;Januar 2009 Strafanzeige bei der Bundesanwalt­schaft ein. Die Anzeige richtet sich gegen Mitglieder des Regimes des verstorbenen Mobutu sowie Angehörige seiner Familie, denen vorgeworfen wird, an einer kriminel­len Orga­nisation beteiligt gewesen zu sein. Sie fordert zudem die gerichtliche Sperrung der Vermögenswerte, die im Moment vom Bundesrat gemäss Artikel&amp;nbsp;184 Absatz&amp;nbsp;3 BV blockiert werden. &amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Sollte die Bundesanwaltschaft entscheiden, ein Verfahren einzuleiten, könnte dies zu einer Verfügung über die Einziehung der Vermögenswerte führen. Eine weitere Verlängerung der Blockierung der Mobutu-Gelder bis zum 30.&amp;nbsp;April 2009, wurde deshalb als notwendig beurteilt.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Presse- und Informationsdienst Bundeshaus West CH-3003 Bern Tel.: +41 (0)31 322 31 53 Fax: +41 (0)31 324 90 47 E-Mail: info@eda.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Extension de l'ultime prolongation du blocage des avoirs Mobutu</title>
      <lead>Par décision du Conseil fédéral du 12 décembre 2008, le blocage des avoirs de feu Mobutu et de son entourage (env. CHF 7.7 mio) avait été prolongé jusqu'au 28 février 2009. Cette prolongation avait pour but, d'une part, de permettre à l’avocat de la République démocratique du Congo (RDC) d’initier une procédure en Suisse visant à obtenir le blocage judiciaire des avoirs et, d'autre part, de permettre à l’autorité judiciaire compétente de se prononcer sur la suite à donner à cette procédure. Une dénonciation pénale a été déposée auprès du MPC le 23 janvier 2009 par la RDC. Partant du principe que l’étude du dossier implique un travail important, le Conseil fédéral a estimé nécessaire d’ordonner une extension de deux mois de l'ultime prolongation du blocage, soit jusqu'au 30 avril 2009.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Le blocage des avoirs de feu Mobutu (env. CHF 7.7 mio) remonte à 1997, année durant laquelle la République démocratique du Congo (RDC) avait présenté une demande d'entraide judiciaire en matière pénale à la Suisse. L'Office fédéral de la justice n'avait finalement pas eu d'autre possibilité que de rendre en décembre 2003 une décision négative. Le Conseil fédéral a alors ordonné le blocage des avoirs sur la base de l'article 184 alinéa 3 Cst. Ce blocage, renouvelé en 2006 et à la fin 2008, aurait dû arriver à échéance le 28 février 2009. Durant cette période, le Conseil fédéral a confié au DFAE un mandat de facilitateur pour assister les parties, en vue de rechercher une issue aussi satisfaisante que possible.&lt;b&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;La République démocratique du Congo (RDC) a effectivement déposé une plainte pénale, auprès du Ministère public de la Confédération (MPC), le 23 janvier 2009. Cette plainte vise des membres du régime de feu Mobutu, ainsi que des membres de sa famille, auxquels il est reproché d'avoir participé à une organisation criminelle. Cette plainte tend également au blocage sur le plan judicaire des avoirs actuellement bloqués par le Conseil fédéral sur la base de l'article 184 alinéa 3 Cst. &amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Une décision favorable du MPC quant à l’ouverture d’une procédure pourrait permettre d’aboutir à une décision de confiscation des avoirs. Une extension de deux mois, soit jusqu'au 30 avril 2009, de l'ultime prolongation de la mesure de blocage des avoirs Mobutu a donc été jugée nécessaire.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Service de presse et d'information Palais fédéral ouest CH-3003 Berne Tél.: (+41) 031 322 31 53 Fax: (+41) 031 324 90 47 E-Mail: info@eda.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Blocco degli averi Mobutu: estensione dell’ultimo prolungamento</title>
      <lead>Il 12 dicembre 2008 il Consiglio federale aveva deciso di bloccare gli averi del defunto Mobutu e del suo entourage (ca. 7,7 mio. di fr.) fino al 28 febbraio 2009. Con il prolungamento s’intendeva consentire all’avvocato della Repubblica democratica del Congo (RDC) di avviare in Svizzera una procedura volta a ottenere il blocco giudiziario degli averi nonché di permettere all’autorità giudiziaria competente di pronunciarsi sul seguito da dare a detta procedura. Il 23 gennaio 2009 la RDC ha depositato una denuncia penale davanti al MPC. Partendo dal principio che lo studio del dossier comporta una notevole mole di lavoro, il Consiglio federale ha ritenuto necessario ordinare un’estensione di due mesi dell’ultimo prolungamento del blocco, ossia fino al 30 aprile 2009.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Il blocco degli averi del defunto Mobutu (ca. 7.7 mio. di fr.) risale al 1997, anno in cui la Repubblica democratica del Congo (RDC) aveva presentato alla Svizzera una domanda di assistenza giudiziaria in materia penale. L’Ufficio federale di giustizia non aveva potuto far altro che emanare una decisione negativa nel dicembre 2003. Il Consiglio federale ha quindi ordinato il blocco degli averi in base all’articolo 184 capoverso 3 Cost. Il blocco, rinnovato nel 2006 e alla fine del 2008, sarebbe dovuto scadere il 28 febbraio 2009. In questo lasso di tempo il Consiglio federale ha conferito al DFAE un mandato di facilitatore per assistere le parti in attesa di trovare una soluzione soddisfacente.&lt;b&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Il 23 gennaio 2009 la Repubblica democratica del Congo (RDC) ha in effetti sporto querela penale presso il Ministero pubblico della Confederazione (MPC) contro alcuni membri sia del regime sia della famiglia del defunto Mobutu rimproverandoli di aver partecipato a un’organizzazione criminale. La querela intende anche bloccare sul piano giudiziario gli averi attualmente bloccati dal Consiglio federale in base all’articolo 184 capoverso 3 Cost. &amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Una decisione favorevole del MPC in merito all’apertura di una procedura potrebbe consentire di giungere a una decisione di confisca degli averi. Un’estensione di due mesi, ossia fino al 30 aprile 2009, dell’ultimo prolungamento della misura di blocco degli averi Mobutu è stata dunque ritenuta necessaria.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Servizio stampa e informazione Palazzo federale ovest CH-3003 Berna Tel.: (+41) 031 322 31 53 Fax: (+41) 031 324 90 47 E-Mail: info@eda.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Extension of the final prolongation of the freezing of Mobutu's assets</title>
      <lead>On 12 December 2008, the Federal Council decided to prolong the freezing of the assets of the late president Mobutu and of his entourage (approx. CHF 7.7 million) to 28 February 2009. The purpose of this prolongation was to enable the lawyer of the Democratic Republic of Congo (RDC) to initiate proceedings in Switzerland to block the assets and to enable the competent legal authority to decide how to deal with the case. A criminal complaint was filed with the Federal State Prosecutor by the RDC on 23 January 2009. As the examination of the case is a time-consuming task, the Federal Council considered it necessary to order a further extension to the final freezing, i.e. until 30 April 2009.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;The freezing of the assets of the late president Mobutu (approx. CHF 7.7 million) dates back to 1997, when the Democratic Republic of the Congo (RDC) presented a request for legal assistance in a criminal matter to Switzerland. The Federal Office of Justice finally had no other option than to make a negative ruling in December 2003. The Federal Council then ordered the freezing of the assets on the basis of article 184 paragraph 3 Cst. This was renewed in 2006 and at the end of 2008. It should have expired on 28 February 2009. During this period, the Federal Council asked the FDFA to operate as a facilitator to assist the parties in order to find a satisfactory solution.&lt;b&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The Democratic Republic of the Congo (RDC) filed a criminal complaint with the Federal State Prosecutor (FSS) on 23 January 2009. This complaint concerns members of the regime of the late Mr Mobutu as well as members of his family, who are accused of involvement in a criminal organisation. This complaint also seeks to provide a&amp;nbsp; legal footing for the freezing of the assets that are currently frozen by the Federal Council on the basis of article 184 paragraph 3 Cst. &amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;A favourable decision by the FSS on the opening of proceedings could pave the way for a ruling to confiscate the assets. It was therefore considered necessary to extend the freeze by two months, i.e. until 30 April 2009.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Press and Information Service Bundeshaus West CH-3003 Bern Tel.: (+41) 031 322 31 53 Fax: (+41) 031 324 90 47 E-Mail: info@eda.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
