<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="30086" revoked="no">
    <version>3</version>
    <pubdate>2009-11-12</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="yes" id="602" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>601</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Generalsekretariat EFD</name>
      <name lang="fr">Secrétariat général DFF</name>
      <name lang="it">Segreteria generale DFF</name>
      <name lang="en">Secretariat-General FDF</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.efd.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.efd.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.efd.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.efd.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="601">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Finanzdepartement</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des finances</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale delle finanze</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Finance</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.efd.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.dff.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.efd.admin.ch/efd/it/home.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.efd.admin.ch/efd/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Bundespräsident Merz empfängt Vizekanzler Westerwelle zu einem Höflichkeitsbesuch</title>
      <lead>Bundespräsident Hans-Rudolf Merz hat heute Guido Westerwelle zu einem Höflichkeitsbesuch in Bern empfangen. Er gratulierte dem neuen deutschen Vizekanzler und Aussenminister zu seiner Wahl und dankte ihm für den so kurz nach Amtsantritt erfolgten Besuch. Vizekanzler Westerwelle betonte, die gute Nachbarschaft zwischen beiden Ländern pflegen und Meinungsverschieden-heiten konstruktiv lösen zu wollen. Das Gespräch fand in einer herzlichen Atmosphäre statt.</lead>
      <text link="no">An dem kurzen Treffen erörterten die beiden Minister die aktuelle Wirtschaftskrise und die Notwendigkeit von strukturellen Reformen. Bundespräsident Merz legte Vizekanzler Westerwelle die Haltung der Schweiz im EU-Steuerdialog dar und gab seiner Hoffnung Ausdruck, dass dieser bald zu einem guten Abschluss komme. Beide Minister bekräftigten den Willen, das Doppelbesteuerungsabkommen zwischen den beiden Ländern auf der Basis von Art. 26 des OECD-Musterabkommens rasch zu revidieren. Bundespräsident Merz hob hervor, dass parallel dazu die Frage des Marktzutritts für Schweizer Finanzdienstleister zu klären sei.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Bundespräsident Merz wiederholte die Einladung an den deutschen Bundespräsi-denten Horst Köhler zu einem Staatsbesuch in der Schweiz.</text>
      <contact>Delphine Jaccard, Mediensprecherin EFD, Tel. 031 324 14 07</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Le président de la Confédération Hans-Rudolf Merz reçoit à Berne le vice-chancelier allemand Guido Westerwelle</title>
      <lead>Le président de la Confédération Hans-Rudolf Merz a reçu aujourd’hui Guido Westerwelle en visite de courtoisie à Berne. Il a félicité le nouveau ministre des affaires étrangères et vice-chancelier allemand de son élection et l’a remercié pour cette visite effectuée si peu de temps après son entrée en fonction. Le vice-chancelier Westerwelle a souligné qu'il entendait soigner les rapports de bon voisinage liant les deux pays et chercher des solutions constructives aux divergences d'opinion. La rencontre s'est déroulée dans une atmosphère cordiale.</lead>
      <text link="no">Lors de cette brève rencontre, les deux ministres ont parlé de la crise économique actuelle et de la nécessité de procéder à des réformes structurelles. Le président de la Confédération Hans-Rudolf Merz a exposé au vice-chancelier Westerwelle la position de la Suisse dans le dialogue en matière fiscale avec l'UE et a exprimé l'espoir que celui-ci trouverait bientôt une issue positive. Les deux ministres ont réaffirmé leur volonté de réviser rapidement la convention de double imposition liant les deux pays conformément à l'art. 26 du Modèle de convention de l'OCDE. Le président de&amp;nbsp; la Confédération Hans-Rudolf Merz a déclaré qu'il importait parallèlement de clarifier la question de l'accès au marché des prestataires suisses de services financiers.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Le président de la Confédération Hans-Rudolf Merz a réitéré l'invitation faite au président allemand Horst Köhler d'effectuer une visite d'Etat en Suisse.</text>
      <contact>Delphine Jaccard, porte-parole du DFF, tél. 031 324 14 07</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Il presidente della Confederazione Merz riceve il vicecancelliere Westerwelle in visita di cortesia</title>
      <lead>In data odierna il presidente della Confederazione Hans-Rudolf Merz ha ricevuto a Berna Guido Westerwelle in visita di cortesia. Egli si è congratulato con il nuovo vicecancelliere e ministro degli esteri tedesco per la sua nomina e lo ha ringraziato per la visita effettuata già poco tempo dopo l'assunzione della carica. Il vicecancelliere Westerwelle ha sottolineato di voler preservare i buoni rapporti di vicinato tra i due Paesi e di risolvere in modo costruttivo le divergenze d'opinione. I colloqui si sono tenuti in un'atmosfera cordiale.</lead>
      <text link="no">In occasione del breve incontro i due Ministri hanno discusso dell'attuale crisi economica e della necessità di procedere a riforme strutturali. Il presidente della Confederazione Merz ha spiegato al vicecancelliere Westerwelle la posizione della Svizzera nella contesa fiscale con l'UE e ha espresso la speranza che questa possa essere risolta quanto prima. Entrambi i Ministri hanno ribadito la volontà di rivedere in tempi brevi la Convenzione di doppia imposizione tra i due Paesi sulla base dell'articolo 26 del modello di convenzione dell'OCSE. Il presidente della Confederazione Merz ha inoltre evidenziato che parallelamente a questi lavori deve essere chiarita anche la questione dell'accesso ai mercati per gli istituti finanziari svizzeri.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Il presidente della Confederazione Merz ha rinnovato al presidente della Repubblica tedesca Horst Köhler l'invito a effettuare una visita di Stato in Svizzera.</text>
      <contact>Delphine Jaccard, portavoce DFF, tel. 031 324 14 07</contact>
      <revisions>
        <revision date="2009-11-13 10:44" type="R"/>
      </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>President Merz receives Vice Chancellor Westerwelle for a courtesy call</title>
      <lead>Today President Merz received Guido Westerwelle for a courtesy call in Bern. He congratulated the new German Vice Chancellor and Foreign Minister upon his election and thanked him for his visit undertaken so soon after assuming office. Vice Chancellor Westerwelle emphasised wanting to maintain good neighbourly relations between the two countries and settling differences of opinion constructively. The talks took place in a cordial atmosphere.</lead>
      <text link="no">During the short meeting, the two ministers discussed the current economic crisis and the necessity of carrying out structural reforms. President Merz outlined Switzerland's stance to Vice Chancellor Westerwelle on the EU tax dialogue and expressed the hope that this will soon have a positive outcome. Both ministers reiterated their willingness to swiftly revise the double taxation agreement between the two countries on the basis of Art. 26 of the OECD Model Convention. President Merz emphasised that, parallel to this, the question of market access for Swiss financial institutions should be clarified. &lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; President Merz once again extended an invitation to the President of Germany to pay a state visit to Switzerland.</text>
      <contact>Delphine Jaccard, FDF Press spokesperson, tel. 031 324 14 07</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <keywords>
      <keyword id="126" org-id="602">
        <name lang="de">Finanzplatz Schweiz</name>
        <name lang="fr">Place financière suisse</name>
        <name lang="it">Piazza finanziaria svizzera</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland as a financial centre</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="137" org-id="602">
        <name lang="de">Internationale Doppelbesteuerung</name>
        <name lang="fr">Double imposition internationale</name>
        <name lang="it">Doppia imposizione internazionale</name>
        <name lang="en">International double taxation</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="268" org-id="602">
        <name lang="de">Wirtschaftspolitik und Finanzmärkte</name>
        <name lang="fr">Politique économique et marchés financiers</name>
        <name lang="it">Politica economica e mercati finanziari</name>
        <name lang="en">Economic policy and financial markets</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="234" org-id="602">
        <name lang="de">Eveline Widmer-Schlumpf, Bundespräsidentin 2012</name>
        <name lang="fr">Eveline Widmer-Schlumpf, présidente de la Confédération en 2012</name>
        <name lang="it">Eveline Widmer-Schlumpf, presidente della Confederazione 2012</name>
        <name lang="en">Eveline Widmer-Schlumpf, President of the Swiss Confederation 2012</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="235" org-id="602">
        <name lang="de">Internationale Steuerpolitik</name>
        <name lang="fr">Politique fiscale internationale</name>
        <name lang="it">Politica fiscale internazionale</name>
        <name lang="en">International tax policy</name>
      </keyword>
    </keywords>
    <topics>
      <topic id="33">
        <name lang="de">Bundespräsident/-in</name>
        <name lang="fr">Président/e de la Confédération</name>
        <name lang="it">Presidente della Confederazione</name>
        <name lang="en">President of the Swiss Confederation</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="34">
        <name lang="de">Europa</name>
        <name lang="fr">Europe</name>
        <name lang="it">Europa</name>
        <name lang="en">Europe</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="35">
        <name lang="de">Finanzplatz</name>
        <name lang="fr">Place financière</name>
        <name lang="it">Piazza finanziaria</name>
        <name lang="en">Financial Centre</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="44">
        <name lang="de">Steuern</name>
        <name lang="fr">Impôts</name>
        <name lang="it">Imposte</name>
        <name lang="en">Taxation</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
