<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="30190" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2009-11-18</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="201" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>201</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="201">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Die Schweiz fordert die Einstellung der israelischen Siedlungsvorhaben in Gilo, Ostjerusalem</title>
      <lead>Das Eidgenössische Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten (EDA) ist äusserst besorgt über das Vorhaben Israels, die jüdische Siedlung in Gilo, Ost-Jerusalem, um 900 Wohnungen zu erweitern. Es appelliert an die israelische Regierung, diese Aktivitäten unverzüglich einzustellen und sämtliche Siedlungsprojekte im besetzten palästinensischen Gebiet zu stoppen.</lead>
      <text link="no">Das EDA verfolgt die Ereignisse in Ost-Jerusalem mit Besorgnis und bedauert die Vorgehensweise der israelischen Regierung. Es fordert die israelische Regierung auf, keine neuen Wohnungen in Gilo, auf palästinensischem Boden, zu errichten. Ost-Jerusalem ist integraler Bestandteil des besetzten palästinensischen Gebiets. Israel ist aufgrund des humanitären Völkerrechts verpflichtet, für den Schutz der Bevölkerung zu sorgen.&amp;nbsp;Nach Auffassung der Schweiz verstossen die israelischen Siedlungsprojekte und die Zerstörung von Häusern im besetzten palästinensischen Gebiet gegen das humanitäre Völkerrecht. Dieses untersagt es einer Besatzungsmacht, im besetzten Gebiet Güter zu zerstören oder Zivilpersonen umzusiedeln. &amp;nbsp;Die Weiterführung der israelischen Siedlungstätigkeit ist nicht vereinbar mit einem echten Friedensprozess zur Erarbeitung einer umfassenden und dauerhaften Lösung für den israelisch-palästinensischen Konflikt.</text>
      <contact>Information EDA Bundeshaus West CH-3003 Bern Tel.: +41 (0)31 322 31 53 Fax: +41 (0)31 324 90 47 E-Mail: info@eda.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>La Suisse demande l’abandon du projet d’implantation israélienne à Gilo, Jérusalem-Est</title>
      <lead>Le Département fédéral des affaires étrangères (DFAE) est profondément préoccupé par le projet israélien d’élargir de 900 appartements supplémentaires la zone d’habitation juive à Gilo, Jérusalem-Est. Il demande au Gouvernement israélien de renoncer sans délai à ces activités et de mettre terme à tous les projets d’implantation dans le Territoire palestinien occupé.</lead>
      <text link="no">Le DFAE suit les événements qui se déroulent à Jérusalem-Est avec préoccupation et déplore la démarche du Gouvernement israélien. Il invite ce dernier à renoncer à toute construction de nouveaux logements à Gilo, en territoire palestinien. En effet, Jérusalem-Est fait partie intégrante du Territoire palestinien occupé, dont la protection de la population incombe à Israël en vertu du droit international humanitaire.&amp;nbsp;La Suisse est d’avis que les projets israéliens d’implantation et la destruction d’habitations dans le Territoire palestinien occupés constituent une violation du droit international humanitaire. Ce dernier interdit à toute force d’occupation de détruire des biens dans un territoire occupé ou de procéder au déplacement de la population civile. &amp;nbsp;La poursuite de la politique d’implantation pratiquée par Israël est incompatible avec un authentique processus de paix visant à élaborer une solution exhaustive et durable au conflit israélo-palestinien.&amp;nbsp;</text>
      <contact>Information DFAE Palais fédéral ouest CH-3003 Berne Tél.: (+41) 031 322 31 53 Fax: (+41) 031 324 90 47 E-Mail: info@eda.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>La Svizzera esorta a sospendere l’espansione degli insediamenti israeliani a Gilo, Gerusalemme Est</title>
      <lead>Il Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri (DFAE) esprime la sua sincera preoccupazione per l’intenzione di Israele di espandere l’insediamento ebraico nel quartiere di Gilo, a Gerusalemme Est, con la costruzione di 900 nuove case. Il DFAE lancia un appello al Governo israeliano perché sospenda immediatamente i lavori e blocchi tutti i progetti di insediamento nel Territorio palestinese occupato.</lead>
      <text link="no">Il DFAE segue con preoccupazione gli avvenimenti a Gerusalemme Est e deplora il modo di procedere del Governo israeliano. Esorta quest’ultimo a non costruire nuove case a Gilo, su suolo palestinese. Gerusalemme Est è parte integrante del Territorio palestinese occupato. In base al diritto internazionale umanitario Israele è tenuta a provvedere alla protezione della popolazione.&amp;nbsp;Secondo la Svizzera i progetti d’insediamento israeliani e la distruzione di case nel Territorio palestinese occupato violano il diritto internazionale umanitario che proibisce a una forza d’occupazione di distruggere beni nei territori da essa occupati o di trasferire altrove civili.&amp;nbsp;L’attività d’insediamento israeliana non è compatibile con un autentico processo di pace inteso a elaborare una soluzione completa e duratura del conflitto israelo-palestinese.&amp;nbsp;</text>
      <contact>Informazione DFAE Palazzo federale ovest CH-3003 Berna Tel.: (+41) 031 322 31 53 Fax: (+41) 031 324 90 47 E-Mail: info@eda.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Switzerland calls for an end to Israeli settlement plans in Gilo, East Jerusalem</title>
      <lead>The Federal Department of Foreign Affairs (FDFA) is extremely concerned about Israel's plans to extend the Jewish settlement in Gilo, East Jerusalem, by 900 apartments. It appeals to the Israeli government to end these activities immediately and to stop all settlement projects in the occupied Palestinian territory.</lead>
      <text link="no">The FDFA is monitoring events in East Jerusalem with concern, and it regrets the procedures adopted by the Israeli government. It calls on the Israeli government to refrain from building new apartments in Gilo, on Palestinian territory. East Jerusalem is an integral part of the occupied Palestinian territory. Israel is obliged by international humanitarian law to ensure the protection of the civilian population.&amp;nbsp;In Switzerland's view, the Israeli settlement projects and the destruction of houses in the occupied Palestinian territory violate international humanitarian law, which prohibits an occupying power from destroying property or from re-settling civilians in the occupied territory.&amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp;The continuation of Israeli settlement activity is not compatible with a genuine peace process whose goal is to work out a comprehensive and lasting solution to the Israeli-Palestinian conflict.</text>
      <contact>Information FDFA Bundeshaus West CH-3003 Bern Tel.: (+41) 031 322 31 53 Fax: (+41) 031 324 90 47 E-Mail: info@eda.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
