<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="3404" revoked="no">
    <version>2</version>
    <pubdate>1998-04-20</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="815" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>801</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössische Kommunikationskommission ComCom</name>
      <name lang="fr">Commission fédérale de la communication ComCom</name>
      <name lang="it">Commissione federale delle comunicazioni ComCom</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Communications Commission ComCom</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.comcom.admin.ch/</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.comcom.admin.ch/</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.comcom.admin.ch/</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.comcom.admin.ch/</www>
      <email lang="de">comcom@comcom.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">comcom@comcom.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">comcom@comcom.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">comcom@comcom.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="801">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Umwelt, Verkehr, Energie und Kommunikation</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'environnement, des transports, de l'énergie et de la communication</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'ambiente, dei trasporti, dell'energia e delle comunicazioni</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of the Environment, Transport, Energy and Communications</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.uvek.admin.ch/uvek/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.uvek.admin.ch/uvek/fr/home.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.uvek.admin.ch/uvek/it/home.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.uvek.admin.ch/uvek/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-uvek.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-uvek.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-uvek.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-uvek.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Die ComCom erteilt je eine Mobilfunkkonzession an diAx AG und Orange Communications SA</title>
      <teaser>Die Eidg. Kommunikationskommission (ComCom) hat entschieden, diAx AG und Orange Communications SA je eine Konzession für ein neues nationales Mobiltelefonnetz zu erteilen. Damit lanciert sie den Wettbewerb auch im dynamischen Markt der Mobiltelefonie.</teaser>
      <lead>Die Eidg. Kommunikationskommission (ComCom) hat entschieden, diAx AG und Orange Communications SA je eine Konzession für ein neues nationales Mobiltelefonnetz zu erteilen. Damit lanciert sie den Wettbewerb auch im dynamischen Markt der Mobiltelefonie.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Insgesamt werden in nächster Zeit drei landesweite Mobilfunknetze den Konsumentinnen und Konsumenten zur Verfügung stehen. Die Swisscom erhält kraft des Gesetzes eine Konzession für den Betrieb von einem GSM Dualband - Netz (mit Frequenzen im Bereich von 900 MHz und 1800 MHz). Die ComCom erteilt nun einem neuen Betreiber, der diAx AG, ebenfalls das Recht, gleich viel Frequenzen wie die Swisscom zu nutzen. Die andere neue Konzessionärin, Orange Communications SA, wird ihr Netz im Bereich der 1800 MHz Frequenzen betreiben; dabei kann sie eine annähernd gleiche Flächendeckung bei sehr hoher Qualität der Versorgung erreichen. Dies jedoch zu etwas höheren Kosten und zu einem späteren Zeitpunkt.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Für beide neuen Konzessionen haben sich For::tel SA, diAx AG, Orange Communications SA und Sunrise beworben. Unlimitel hat ein Gesuch nur für die erste, CheaperNet nur für die zweite neue Konzession eingereicht. Mit Ausnahme von CheaperNet waren alle Eingaben qualitativ hochstehend. CheaperNet schied bereits während des Evaluationsverfahrens wegen ungenügender Eingabe aus.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Die Eingaben wurden nach einem Kriterienwettbewerb evaluiert. Bei der Beurteilung hat sich die ComCom auf die Kriterien Leistungsfähigkeit, technisches Konzept und Umsetzung, Business- und Serviceplan, Versorgungspflicht und Innovationsgehalt gestützt.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Die zwei Gewinner zeichneten sich durch folgende Stärken aus:&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;DiAx AG wird aufgrund einer bereits weit fortgeschrittenen und gründlichen Planung schnell auf dem Markt sein. Die mit dem Aufbau verbundenen Risiken wurden dank der soliden Vorbereitung als gering eingestuft. Das Unternehmen sieht unter den Bewerbern die grösste Flächendeckung vor. Weiter ist ihr Netz durch eine hohe Qualität gekennzeichnet (gute Funkversorgung auch in Gebäuden und ländlichen Gegenden). Die ComCom verspricht sich mit der Wahl von diAx positive Impulse auch für den Wettbewerb auf Festnetzen.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Orange Communications SA bringt trotz etwas langsamerem Netzaufbau und späterem Markteintritt eine ausgezeichnete nationale Versorgung mit einer sehr guten Dienstleistungsqualität. Sie gilt als sehr erfahren im Betrieb von Netzen und für die Vermarktung von Dienstleistungen speziell im Anwendungsbereich von 1800 MHz-Frequenzen. Ihr Netz stellt eine gute Plattform für neue Dienste mit hohem Innovationsgehalt dar. Mit Orange Communications SA tritt ein weiterer Akteur im schweizerischen Fernmeldemarkt auf und belebt diesen zum Vorteil der Konsumentinnen und Konsumenten.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Die ComCom hatte die Ausschreibung der beiden neuen Konzessionen im November 1997 veröffentlicht. Um eine Ungleichbehandlung der neuen Konzessionären gegenüber der Swisscom zu vermeiden, hat die ComCom eine Vergabe mittels Kriterienwettbewerb und nicht aufgrund einer Auktion beschlossen. Die Swisscom erhält nämlich ihre Konzession kraft Gesetzes ohne einen Auktionspreis bezahlen zu müssen.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Auf den 13. Februar 1998 (Abgabefrist) gingen beim Bundesamt für Kommunikation (BAKOM) für jede ausgeschriebene Konzession 5 Bewerbungen ein. Das BAKOM hat die umfangreichen Unterlagen innert zwei Monaten und mit externer fachlicher Unterstützung ausgewertet. Die ComCom stützte sich in ihren intensiven Beratungen auf diese Auswertung, auf den Antrag des BAKOM sowie auf Hearings mit den Bewerbern.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Die ComCom amtet seit dem 1. Januar 1998 als unabhängige Regulierungsbehörde im liberalisierten Fernmeldemarkt.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact/>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>La ComCom octroie une concession de téléphonie mobile à diAx SA et à Orange Communications SA</title>
      <teaser>La Commission fédérale de la communication (ComCom) a décidé d'octroyer une concession à diAx SA et une autre à Orange Communications SA pour exploiter un réseau national de téléphonie mobile. Elle donne ainsi le coup d'envoi à la concurrence sur le marché dynamique de la téléphonie mobile.</teaser>
      <lead>La Commission fédérale de la communication (ComCom) a décidé d'octroyer une concession à diAx SA et une autre à Orange Communications SA pour exploiter un réseau national de téléphonie mobile. Elle donne ainsi le coup d'envoi à la concurrence sur le marché dynamique de la téléphonie mobile.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Les consommateurs disposeront bientôt de trois réseaux nationaux de téléphonie mobile. En vertu de la loi, l'un d'entre eux est attribué à Swisscom, qui a reçu une concession pour l'exploitation d'un réseau GSM à double bande, dans les fréquences 900 MHz et 1800 MHz. La ComCom vient d'octroyer à un deuxième opérateur, diAx SA, le droit d'utiliser autant de fréquences que Swisscom. Le troisième réseau, dans les fréquences 1800 MHz, sera géré par la société Orange Communications SA qui, grâce à la concession qu'elle vient de recevoir, pourra assurer une desserte d'une qualité très élevée sur un territoire presque aussi étendu que celui de ses concurrents, néanmoins à des coûts légèrement supérieurs et à partir d'une date ultérieure.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Ces deux nouvelles concessions étaient convoitées par quatre sociétés: For::tel SA, diAx SA, Orange Communications SA et Sunrise. Un autre concurrent, Unlimitel, avait déposé une demande pour la première concession seulement, tandis que la société CheaperNet visait la seconde. Tous les dossiers étaient d'excellente qualité, à l'exception de celui de CheaperNet, cette société a finalement été écartée au cours de la procédure d'évaluation en raison des informations lacunaires qu'elle a fournies.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Les candidatures ont été évaluées selon des critères précis: performances, projet et mise en oeuvre techniques, plans de développement et de prestations, obligations en matière de desserte et degré d'innovation. Les deux gagnants se sont distingués grâce aux atouts suivants: diAx SA pourra assurer rapidement une présence sur le marché en raison de sa préparation sérieuse et du degré de maturité très avancé de son projet. Quant aux risques inhérents à la mise en service du réseau, ils ont été jugés faibles, précisément parce que ce dossier bénéficie d'une solide préparation. La société diAx SA est, parmi les concurrents en lice, celle qui prévoit la desserte la plus généreuse. En outre, son réseau se distingue par sa grande qualité grâce à une bonne desserte dans les bâtiments et dans les zones de campagne. En optant pour diAx, la ComCom s'assure que la concurrence sera plus vive sur le marché des réseaux fixes également.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Malgré l'installation plus lente de son réseau et son entrée plus tardive sur le marché, Orange Communications SA est le gage d'une excellente desserte nationale associée à des prestations de très haute qualité. L'évaluation a montré qu'elle possède une grande expérience dans l'exploitation des réseaux et la commercialisation des prestations, en particulier dans le domaine d'application des 1800 MHz. De plus, son réseau constitue une bonne plate-forme pour de nouveaux services présentant un haut degré d'innovation. Avec Orange Communications SA, c'est un nouvel acteur qui s'installe sur le marché suisse des télécommunications et qui saura l'animer au profit des consommateurs.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;La ComCom avait publié la mise au concours de ces deux nouvelles concessions au mois de novembre 1997. Afin d'éviter un traitement différencié par rapport à Swisscom, elle a décidé de les octroyer en fonction de certains critères et non selon le principe de la mise aux enchères. Précisons qu'en vertu de la loi, Swisscom a obtenu sa concession sans avoir à payer le prix d'une enchère. Le 13 février 1998 (délai de remise des dossiers), l'Office fédéral de la communication (OFCOM) avait reçu 5 candidatures pour chaque concession. Avec le concours de spécialistes externes, il a examiné et analysé les volumineux dossiers en deux mois. Dans ses considérations, la ComCom s'est appuyée sur cette analyse, sur la proposition de l'OFCOM et sur les entretiens avec les candidats.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;La ComCom exerce ses fonctions d'autorité indépendante de régulation du marché des télécommunications depuis le 1er janvier 1998.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact/>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>La ComCom rilascia due concessioni di telefonia mobile: una alla diAx SA e una alla Orange Communications SA</title>
      <teaser>La Commissione federale delle comunicazioni (ComCom) ha deciso di rilasciare una concessione ciascuno alla diAx SA e alla Orange Communications SA per l'esercizio di una nuova rete di telefonia mobile nazionale. In questo modo essa apre alla concorrenza anche il dinamico mercato della telefonia mobile.</teaser>
      <lead>La Commissione federale delle comunicazioni (ComCom) ha deciso di rilasciare una concessione ciascuno alla diAx SA e alla Orange Communications SA per l'esercizio di una nuova rete di telefonia mobile nazionale. In questo modo essa apre alla concorrenza anche il dinamico mercato della telefonia mobile.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;In futuro verranno messe a disposizione dei consumatori e delle consumatrici complessivamente tre reti di telefonia mobile nazionali. In virtù della legge una delle reti è attribuita alla Swisscom, che ha ottenuto una concessione per l'esercizio di una rete GSM a doppia banda nelle frequenze 900 MHz e 1800 MHz. La ComCom ha ora accordato a un secondo operatore, la diAx SA, il diritto di utilizzare lo stesso numero di frequenze come la Swisscom. La terza rete, nelle frequenze 1800 MHz, sarà gestita dalla società Orange Communications SA che, grazie alla sua concessione, potrà assicurare una copertura di ottima qualità su un territorio vasto quasi quanto quello degli altri operatori, tuttavia a costi leggermente superiori ed entrando sul mercato soltanto in un secondo momento.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Le due nuove concessioni erano contese da quattro società: For::tel SA, diAx SA, Orange Communications SA e Sunrise. Un'ulteriore concorrente, Unlimitel, era interessata soltanto alla prima concessione e la società CheaperNet si era candidata solo per la seconda. Tutti i dossier inoltrati presentavano un'ottima qualità ad eccezione della candidatura di CheaperNet, società scartata già durante la procedura di valutazione perché il suo dossier era lacunoso.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Le candidature sono state valutate dalla ComCom in base ai seguenti criteri: efficienza, progetto e realizzazione tecnica, piani di sviluppo e di prestazioni, obbligo di approvvigionamento e contenuto innovativo. Le società vincenti si sono profilate per le seguenti qualità: La diAx SA sarà in grado di garantire rapidamente la sua presenza sui mercato grazie a un'accurata pianificazione, in fase già molto avanzata. I rischi legati alla messa in servizio della rete sono giudicati minimi vista la solida e seria preparazione dei dossier. La società diAx SA, tra tutti i candidati in lizza, è quella che copre il territorio più vasto. Inoltre, la sua rete si distingue per l'elevata qualità (buona ricezione anche all'interno degli edifici e nelle zone rurali). Optando per la diAx SA, la ComCom si ripromette impulsi positivi anche per la competitività tra le reti fisse. Nonostante la messa in servizio più lenta della rete e l'entrata sul mercato più tardiva, la società Orange Communications SA può assicurare un eccellente approvvigionamento nazionale e prestazioni di ottima qualità. Essa vanta grande esperienza nell'esercizio di reti e nella commercializzazione di prestazioni, in particolare nel campo di applicazione di 1800 MHz. La sua rete costituisce una piattaforma ideale per nuovi servizi molto innovativi. Con la Orange Communications SA si lancia un nuovo operatore che saprà dinamizzare il mercato delle telecomunicazioni svizzero a favore dei consumatori e delle consumatrici.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;La ComCom ha indetto la pubblica gara per le due nuove concessioni nel novembre 1997. Per evitare sfavoreggiamenti nei confronti di Swisscom, essa ha deciso di rilasciare le concessioni fissando una serie di criteri e non secondo il principio della messa all'asta. In base alla legge, Swisscom ha infatti ottenuto la sua concessione senza dover pagare un prezzo d'asta.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;II 13 febbraio 1998, ultimo termine per l'inoltro delle candidature, l'Ufficio federale delle comunicazioni (UFCOM) aveva ricevuto 5 candidature per ciascuna concessione messa a concorso. In due mesi, e con l'aiuto di esperti esterni, I'UFCOM ha esaminato le candidature, assai dettagliate e complesse. La ComCom ha preso la sua decisione basandosi sui risultati di tale valutazione, sulla proposta dell'UFCOM e sui colloqui con i candidati.Dal 1 ° gennaio 1998 la ComCom opera in qualità di autorità di regolamentazione indipendente sul mercato delle telecomunicazioni liberalizzato.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact/>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>ComCom awards diAx AG and Orange Communications SA one mobile radio licence each</title>
      <teaser>The Federal Communications Commission (ComCom) has decided to award diAx AG and Orange Communications SA one licence each for a new national mobile telephone network. With this decision, the dynamic market of mobile telephony will also be opened up to competition.</teaser>
      <lead>The Federal Communications Commission (ComCom) has decided to award diAx AG and Orange Communications SA one licence each for a new national mobile telephone network. With this decision, the dynamic market of mobile telephony will also be opened up to competition.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;In the near future, a total of three country-wide mobile radio networks will be available to the consumer. By virtue of the law, Swisscom receives a licence for the operation of GSM Dualband networks (at frequencies in the 900 MHz and 1800 MHz bands). ComCom is now also awarding a new operator, diAx AG, the right to use the same number of frequencies as Swisscom. The other new licensee, Orange Communications SA, will operate its network in the 1800 MHz frequency band; this enables it to achieve approximately equal coverage along with very high quality of provision - although at rather higher cost and at a later point in time. For::tel SA, diAx AG, Orange Communications SA and Sunrise tendered for the two new licences. Unlimitel submitted an application only for the first new licence, and CheaperNet a bid only for the second. All the applications were of high quality with the exception of CheaperNet and this application was eliminated during the evaluation procedure because of an inadequate bid. The applications were evaluated according to a competitive criteria-based procedure. In the evaluation, ComCom relied on the criteria of performance, technical concept and implementation, the business and service plan, the obligation of provision and the innovation content.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The two winners distinguished themselves by the following strong points: DiAx AG will enter the market quickly, on the basis of fundamental planning which is already well advanced. The risks associated with construction were deemed to be low, thanks to extensive preparation. Of the bidders, this company envisages the widest area coverage. Furthermore, its network is characterised by high quality (good signal strength provision even in buildings and rural locations). By choosing diAx, ComCom also anticipates a positive stimulus to competition in fixed networks. Notwithstanding the somewhat slower establishment of its network and later market launch, Orange Communications SA will provide excellent national provision with a very good level of service. It is considered to be very experienced in the network field and in the marketing of services, especially with regard to the 1800 MHz frequencies application. Its network constitutes a good platform for new services with a high innovation content. Orange Communications SA will be a new player on the Swiss telecommunications market and will invigorate it to the benefit of the consumer.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;ComCom had published the invitation to tender for the two new licences in November 1997. To avoid unequal treatment of the new licensees compared to Swisscom, ComCom decided to award on the basis of a criteria-based competition rather than an auction. Swisscom, in fact, receives its licence by application of the law, without having to pay an auction price. By 13 February 1998 (the deadline for submission) the Federal Office for Communication (OFCOM) had received 5 bids for each licence put out to tender. BAKOM evaluated the extensive documentation within two months, with external technical support. In its intensive deliberations, ComCom relied on this evaluation, on BAKOM's proposal and on hearings with the bidders. Since 1 January 1998, ComCom has been exercising the functions of an independent regulatory authority in the liberalised telecommunications market.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact/>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="28">
        <name lang="de">Telekommunikation</name>
        <name lang="fr">Télécommunications</name>
        <name lang="it">Telecomunicazione</name>
        <name lang="en">Telecommunications</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
