<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="85135" revoked="no">
    <version>2</version>
    <pubdate>2021-09-16</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="1080" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>701</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Staatssekretariat für Bildung, Forschung und Innovation</name>
      <name lang="fr">Secrétariat d'Etat à la formation, à la recherche et à l'innovation</name>
      <name lang="it">Segreteria di Stato per la formazione, la ricerca e l'innovazione</name>
      <name lang="en">State Secretariat for Education, Research and Innovation</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.sbfi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.sbfi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.sbfi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.sbfi.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@sbfi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@sbfi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@sbfi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@sbfi.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="701">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Wirtschaft, Bildung und Forschung</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'économie, de la formation et de la recherche</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'economia, della formazione e della ricerca</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Economic Affairs, Education and Research</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Schweiz und Deutschland tauschen sich in Berlin über Bildung, Forschung und Innovation aus</title>
      <lead>Am 16. und 17. September 2021 erfolgte in Berlin der jährliche Austausch zwischen dem Staatssekretariat für Bildung, Forschung und Innovation (SBFI) und dem Bundesministerium für Bildung und Forschung (BMBF). Die Delegationsleiterinnen Maria Peyro Voeffray, Abteilungsleiterin Internationale Beziehungen a.i beim SBFI und Susanne Burger, Leiterin der Abteilung Europäische und internationale Zusammenarbeit in Bildung und Forschung beim BMBF, begrüssten die etablierte enge Zusammenarbeit in Bildung, Forschung und Innovation. Das Treffen bot auch die Gelegenheit der ersten Kontaktnahme zwischen Innosuisse und der Ende 2019 gegründeten Bundesagentur für Sprunginnovationen SPRIN-D.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Beim 14. Arbeitstreffen in Berlin tauschten sich die Delegationsteilnehmenden über politische Entwicklungen aus, welche einen Einfluss auf das Geschehen im Bereich Bildung, Forschung und Innovation (BFI) haben und über die bilaterale Zusammenarbeit Schweiz – Deutschland. Die wichtigsten Punkte auf der Agenda waren diese: Die Massnahmen im BFI-Bereich zur Bewältigung der Corona-Lage, der Europäische Forschungsraum und eine künftig mögliche Assoziierung der Schweiz an Erasmus+ sowie am europäischen Rahmenprogramm für Forschung und Innovation «Horizon Europe» sowie aussereuropäische Kooperationsformen. Im Rahmen des Treffens fanden auch Gespräche zwischen der Schweizerischen Agentur für Innovationsförderung Innosuisse und der noch jungen deutschen Bundesagentur für Sprunginnovationen SPRIN-D statt.&lt;br /&gt;Weiter besprachen die beiden Delegationen die Berufsbildungszusammenarbeit und das von Staatssekretärin Martina Hirayama und Bildungsministerin Anja Karliczek im Februar 2021 unterzeichnete und am 1. September in Kraft gesetzte modernisierte Abkommen zur gegenseitigen Anerkennung von Berufsabschlüssen.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Deutschland ist der mit Abstand wichtigste Partner der Schweiz im BFI-Bereich. Zeugnis für die zahlenmässig bedeutende Zusammenarbeit und die exzellente Vernetzung zwischen Forschenden und Forschungs- und Innovationsinstitutionen der beiden Staaten legen die rund 1650 deutsch-schweizerischen Projektkooperationen ab, die unter dem EU-Rahmenprogramm für Forschung und Innovation «Horizon 2020» (2014-2020) gefördert wurden. Der Schweizerische Nationalfonds unterstützte zwischen 2016 und 2021 rund 4700 Projekte, Innosuisse knapp 110 Projekte mit deutscher Beteiligung. Mit rund 12'000 an der Zahl (2020/21; nur Bildungsausländer) bilden deutsche Studierende die grösste ausländische Gruppe an den Schweizer Hochschulen. Umgekehrt studieren derzeit rund 3700 Schweizerinnen und Schweizer in Deutschland.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Kommunikation Staatssekretariat für Bildung, Forschung und Innovation SBFI medien@sbfi.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Rencontre annuelle à Berlin entre la Suisse et l’Allemagne sur la formation, la recherche et l’innovation</title>
      <lead>La rencontre annuelle entre le Secrétariat d’État à la formation, à la recherche et à l’innovation (SEFRI) et le ministère allemand de l’éducation et de la recherche (BMBF) s’est tenue à Berlin les 16 et 17 septembre 2021. Les cheffes de délégation Maria Peyro Voeffray, qui dirige par intérim la division Relations internationales du SEFRI, et Susanne Burger, directrice de la coopération européenne et internationale au ministère allemand de l’éducation et de la recherche (BMBF), se sont félicitées des relations étroites et bien établies des deux pays dans le domaine de la formation, de la recherche et de l’innovation. Cette rencontre a été l’occasion d’une première prise de contact entre Innosuisse et l’agence fédérale allemande SPRIN-D, fondée à la fin de l’année 2019 pour soutenir les innovations disruptives.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;La 14e réunion de travail entre le SEFRI et le BMBF, qui s’est tenue à Berlin, a permis aux délégations suisse et allemande de discuter du contexte politique, de son influence sur la formation, la recherche et l’innovation (FRI) et de la coopération bilatérale entre la Suisse et l’Allemagne. À l’agenda : les mesures dans le domaine FRI pour surmonter la situation liée au coronavirus, l’Espace européen de la recherche et l’éventualité d’une association de la Suisse à Erasmus+ et à Horizon Europe, le programme-cadre européen de recherche et d’innovation, ainsi que des formes de coopération hors du cadre européen. Pendant cette rencontre, des discussions ont également eu lieu entre Innosuisse, l’agence suisse pour l’encouragement de l’innovation, et la récente agence allemande SPRIN-D, créée pour soutenir les innovations disruptives.&lt;br /&gt;Les deux délégations se sont aussi entretenues de la coopération en matière de formation professionnelle et de l’accord signé en février 2021 par la secrétaire d’État Martina Hirayama et la ministre de l’éducation Anja Karliczek, qui est entré en vigueur le 1er septembre. Cet accord a été modernisé pour une meilleure reconnaissance mutuelle des diplômes professionnels.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;L’Allemagne est de loin le partenaire le plus important de la Suisse dans le domaine FRI. Preuve en sont, en termes chiffrés, l’ampleur de la coopération et l’excellent réseau constitué par les chercheurs et les institutions de recherche et d’innovation des deux pays, avec quelque 1650 projets de coopération germano-suisses qui ont été encouragés par le programme-cadre européen de recherche et d’innovation Horizon 2020 (de 2014 à 2020). Le Fonds national suisse a soutenu environ 4700 projets entre 2016 et 2021; quant à Innosuisse, elle a soutenu presque 110 projets avec des participations allemandes. Avec quelque 12'000 étudiants (2020/21; uniquement les étudiants qui ont effectué leur scolarité en Allemagne), les Allemands constituent le plus grand groupe d’étudiants étrangers dans les hautes écoles de Suisse; de leur côté, les étudiants suisses sont environ 3700 à étudier en Allemagne.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Communication Secrétariat d’État à la formation, à la recherche et à l’innovation (SEFRI) medien@sbfi.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Svizzera e Germania si sono incontrate a Berlino per discutere di educazione, ricerca e innovazione</title>
      <lead>Il 16 e il 17 settembre si è tenuto a Berlino l'incontro annuale tra la Segreteria di Stato per la formazione, la ricerca e l'innovazione (SEFRI) e il Ministero dell'istruzione e della ricerca tedesco (Bundesministerium für Bildung und Forschung, BMBF). La capodelegazione Maria Peyro Voeffray, responsabile ad interim della divisione Relazioni internazionali della SEFRI, e Susanne Burger, responsabile della divisione Cooperazione europea e internazionale del BMBF, hanno espresso la loro soddisfazione per la consolidata collaborazione nel settore dell'educazione, della ricerca e dell'innovazione. L'incontro è stata l'occasione per una prima serie di colloqui tra rappresentanti di Innosuisse e SPRIN-D, l'agenzia federale tedesca per l'innovazione, creata alla fine del 2019.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Nel corso del 14o incontro di lavoro, che si è svolto a Berlino, i membri delle delegazioni hanno discusso degli sviluppi politici che possono influire sulle attività in corso nel settore dell'educazione, della ricerca e dell'innovazione (ERI) e sulla cooperazione bilaterale Svizzera‒Germania. I temi principali in agenda: le misure attuate nel settore ERI per superare le difficoltà legate alla pandemia; lo Spazio europeo della ricerca e la possibilità di una futura associazione della Svizzera a Erasmus+ e al programma quadro europeo per la ricerca e l'innovazione Horizon Europe; e le forme di cooperazione extraeuropea. Nel quadro dell'incontro si sono svolti colloqui anche tra rappresentanti di Innosuisse, l'Agenzia svizzera per la promozione dell'innovazione, e SPRIN-D, la neocostituita agenzia federale tedesca per l'innovazione.&lt;br /&gt;Le due delegazioni hanno inoltre discusso della collaborazione in ambito di formazione professionale e del nuovo accordo per il riconoscimento reciproco dei titoli professionali, sottoscritto in febbraio dalla segretaria di Stato Martina Hirayama e dalla ministra tedesca dell'educazione Anja Karliczek, ed entrato in vigore il 1o settembre.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;La Germania è sicuramente il partner più importante della Svizzera nel settore ERI. Sul piano quantitativo, l'importanza di questa collaborazione e l'eccellenza della rete di collaborazione tra ricercatori e istituzioni di ricerca e di innovazione dei due Stati sono testimoniate dai circa 1650 progetti di cooperazione congiunta promossi in virtù del programma quadro dell'Unione europea per la ricerca e l'innovazione Horizon 2020 (2014‒2020). Se si considerano i progetti a cui hanno partecipato ricercatori tedeschi, tra il 2016 e il 2020 il Fondo nazionale per la ricerca scientifica ne ha finanziati circa 4700, Innosuisse quasi 110. Nell'anno accademico in corso le scuole universitarie svizzere ospitano circa 12'000 studenti tedeschi (considerati soltanto gli studenti in possesso di un titolo estero): si tratta del gruppo di studenti stranieri più numeroso. Attualmente gli studenti svizzeri in Germania sono invece circa 3700.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Comunicazione Segreteria di Stato per la formazione, la ricerca e l’innovazione SEFRI medien@sbfi.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Switzerland and Germany exchange views on education, research and innovation in Berlin</title>
      <lead>On 16 and 17 September 2021, the annual exchange between the Swiss State Secretariat for Education, Research and Innovation (SERI) and the German Federal Ministry of Education and Research (BMBF) took place in Berlin. The heads of delegation Maria Peyro Voeffray, acting Head of International Relations at SERI, and Susanne Burger, Director General of European and International Cooperation in Education and Research at the BMBF, welcomed the well-established close collaboration in education, research and innovation. The meeting also provided the opportunity for Innosuisse and the German Federal Agency for Disruptive Innovation SPRIND, which was founded at the end of 2019, to meet for the first time.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;At the 14th working meeting in Berlin, delegation participants exchanged views on political developments that influence events in the field of education, research and innovation (ERI) and which have an impact on bilateral cooperation between Switzerland and Germany. The most important points on the agenda were ERI measures to address the COVID-19 situation, the European Research Area and a possible future association of Switzerland to Erasmus+, the European framework programme for research and innovation Horizon Europe, as well as non-European forms of cooperation. The meeting also included talks between the Swiss innovation agency Innosuisse and the recently established German Federal Agency for Disruptive Innovation SPRIND.&lt;br /&gt;The two delegations also discussed international cooperation in vocational and professional education and training, and the updated agreement on the mutual recognition of higher education qualifications, which was signed in February 2021 by SERI State Secretary Martina Hirayama and Federal Education Minister Anja Karlicze. The agreement came into force on 1 September.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Germany is by far Switzerland's most important partner in the field of ERI. Approximately 1,650 German–Swiss collaborative projects were funded under the EU’s 8th research framework programme Horizon 2020 (2014–2020) and these are testimony to the significant amount of cooperation and excellent ties between scientists and research and innovation institutions in the two countries. The Swiss National Science Foundation supported around 4,700 projects between 2016 and 2021, while Innosuisse funded almost 110 projects in which Germany participated. German students form the largest group of foreigners studying at Swiss higher education institutions, there being around 12,000 in number (foreign-educated only in 2020–2021). In comparison, there are around 3,700 Swiss currently studying in Germany.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>State Secretariat for Education, Research and Innovation SERI Communication medien@sbfi.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <keywords>
      <keyword id="325.18" org-id="1080">
        <name lang="de">Akademie der Naturwissenschaften Schweiz</name>
        <name lang="fr">Académie suisse des sciences naturelles</name>
        <name lang="it">Accademia svizzera di scienze naturali</name>
        <name lang="en">Swiss Academy of Sciences</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="325.6" org-id="1080">
        <name lang="de">Bildungsprogramme</name>
        <name lang="fr">Programmes d'éducation</name>
        <name lang="it">Programmi di educazione</name>
        <name lang="en">Educational programmes</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="325.11" org-id="1080">
        <name lang="de">Eidgenössische Technische Hochschule ETH</name>
        <name lang="fr">Ecole polytechnique fédérale EPF</name>
        <name lang="it">Politecnico federale</name>
        <name lang="en">Federal Institutes of Technology</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="325.25" org-id="1080">
        <name lang="de">Euresearch</name>
        <name lang="fr">Euresearch</name>
        <name lang="it">Euresearch</name>
        <name lang="en">Euresearch</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="325.20" org-id="1080">
        <name lang="de">Forschungsförderung</name>
        <name lang="fr">Encouragement de la recherche</name>
        <name lang="it">Promozione della ricerca</name>
        <name lang="en">Research promotion</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="325.9" org-id="1080">
        <name lang="de">Forschungsrahmenprogramme</name>
        <name lang="fr">Programmes-cadre de recherche</name>
        <name lang="it">Programmi quadro di ricerca</name>
        <name lang="en">Research framework programmes</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="325.27" org-id="1080">
        <name lang="de">Institution</name>
        <name lang="fr">Institution</name>
        <name lang="it">Istituzione</name>
        <name lang="en">Institution</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="325.22" org-id="1080">
        <name lang="de">Raumfahrt</name>
        <name lang="fr">Affaires spatiales</name>
        <name lang="it">Questioni spaziali</name>
        <name lang="en">Space affairs</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="325.13" org-id="1080">
        <name lang="de">Ressortforschung</name>
        <name lang="fr">Recherche de l'administration publique fédérale</name>
        <name lang="it">Ricerca dell'Amministrazione federale</name>
        <name lang="en">Research in government departments</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="325.16" org-id="1080">
        <name lang="de">Schweizerische Akademie der Geistes- und Sozialwissenschaften</name>
        <name lang="fr">Académie suisse des sciences humaines et sociales</name>
        <name lang="it">Accademia svizzera di scienze morali e sociali</name>
        <name lang="en">Swiss Academy of Humanities and Social Sciences</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="325.17" org-id="1080">
        <name lang="de">Schweizerische Akademie der medizinischen Wissenschaften</name>
        <name lang="fr">Académie suisse des sciences médicales</name>
        <name lang="it">Accademia svizzera delle scienze mediche</name>
        <name lang="en">Swiss Academy of Medical Sciences</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="325.19" org-id="1080">
        <name lang="de">Schweizerische Akademie der technischen Wissenschaften</name>
        <name lang="fr">Académie suisse des sciences techniques</name>
        <name lang="it">Accademia svizzera delle scienze tecniche</name>
        <name lang="en">Swiss Academy of Engineering Sciences</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="325.15" org-id="1080">
        <name lang="de">Schweizerischer Nationalfonds</name>
        <name lang="fr">Fonds national suisse</name>
        <name lang="it">Fondo nazionale Svizzero</name>
        <name lang="en">Swiss National Science Foundation</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="325.8" org-id="1080">
        <name lang="de">Technologie</name>
        <name lang="fr">Technologie</name>
        <name lang="it">Tecnologia</name>
        <name lang="en">Technology</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="325.1" org-id="1080">
        <name lang="de">Universitäten</name>
        <name lang="fr">Universités</name>
        <name lang="it">Università</name>
        <name lang="en">Universities</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="325.23" org-id="1080">
        <name lang="de">Weltraum</name>
        <name lang="fr">Espace</name>
        <name lang="it">Spazio</name>
        <name lang="en">Space</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="325.10" org-id="1080">
        <name lang="de">Wissenschaft</name>
        <name lang="fr">Science</name>
        <name lang="it">Scienza</name>
        <name lang="en">Science</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="325.21" org-id="1080">
        <name lang="de">Wissenschaftsaussenpolitik</name>
        <name lang="fr">Politique scientifique extérieure</name>
        <name lang="it">Politica scientifica dell'esterno</name>
        <name lang="en">Foreign scientific policy</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="325.30" org-id="1080">
        <name lang="de">Bildung</name>
        <name lang="fr">Education</name>
        <name lang="it">Educazione</name>
        <name lang="en">Education</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="325.31" org-id="1080">
        <name lang="de">Berufsbildung</name>
        <name lang="fr">Formation professionnelle</name>
        <name lang="it">Formazione professionale</name>
        <name lang="en">Vocational and Professional Education and Training</name>
      </keyword>
    </keywords>
    <topics>
      <topic id="8">
        <name lang="de">Bildung und Forschung</name>
        <name lang="fr">Formation et recherche</name>
        <name lang="it">Formazione e ricerca</name>
        <name lang="en">Education and Research</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="45">
        <name lang="de">Technologie</name>
        <name lang="fr">Technologie</name>
        <name lang="it">Tecnologia</name>
        <name lang="en">Technology</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
