<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="85267" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2021-09-27</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="323" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>701</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidg. Materialprüfungs- und Forschungsanstalt</name>
      <name lang="fr">Laboratoire fédéral d'essai des matériaux et de recherche</name>
      <name lang="it">Laboratorio federale di prova dei materiali e di ricerca</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Laboratory for Materials Testing and Research</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.empa.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.empa.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.empa.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.empa.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">contact@empa.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">contact@empa.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">contact@empa.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">contact@empa.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="701">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Wirtschaft, Bildung und Forschung</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'économie, de la formation et de la recherche</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'economia, della formazione e della ricerca</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Economic Affairs, Education and Research</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Dübendorf, St. Gallen und Thun</city>
      <title>Demenz im Blut aufspüren</title>
      <lead>Empa-Forscher Peter Nirmalraj will Proteine in nie gekannter Präzision ablichten – und damit Einblicke in das molekulare Krankheitsgeschehen von Alzheimer gewinnen. Dies soll den Weg zu einer früheren und vereinfachten Diagnose der Demenzerkrankung über einen Bluttest ermöglichen. Gemeinsam mit der Klinik für Neurologie des Kantonsspital St.Gallen konnte nun eine erfolgreiche Pilotstudie abgeschlossen werden.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Schleicht sich der Verdacht auf eine Alzheimer-Erkrankung ein, müssen sich die Betroffenen auf langwierige und aufwändige Prozeduren einstellen, bis der Fall klar ist. Ein Team der Empa und des Kantonsspital St. Gallen ist nun dabei, einen Bluttest zu entwickeln, der die Diagnose mittels Rasterkraftmikroskopie (AFM) ermöglichen soll. Nun haben die Forscher Ergebnisse einer erfolgreichen Pilotstudie im Fachmagazin «Science Advances» publiziert.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3&gt;&lt;b&gt;Tiefe Blicke ins molekulare Universum&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/h3&gt; &lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Am Anfang stand für den Physiker Peter Nirmalraj der Wunsch, das Krankheitsgeschehen von Alzheimer zu verstehen, um neue Wege in Diagnostik und Therapie zu ermöglichen. Einen Schritt weiter wäre man, wenn die genaue Rolle der Beta-Amyloid-Peptide und der Tau-Proteine, die im Zusammenhang mit der neurodegenerativen Krankheit stehen, entschlüsselt wäre. Nirmalraj hatte sich daher vorgenommen, nicht nur die blosse Anwesenheit der verdächtigen Eiweisse zu registrieren, sondern auch ihre veränderbare Gestalt und Form sowie ihre Anzahl zu bestimmen.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Gängige Methoden ermöglichen es zwar, die Gesamtmenge der beiden Eiweisse in Körperflüssigkeiten zu bestimmen. Allerdings erlauben es diese Techniken nicht, Unterschiede in der Gestalt und dem Zustand der Proteinansammlungen sichtbar zu machen. Der Forscher arbeitet darum an Technologien, welche Beobachtungen im Nanometerbereich im Blut ermöglichen und dennoch die Struktur und Morphologie der Eiweisse nicht zerstören.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Gemeinsam mit Neurologen am Kantonsspital St. Gallen konnte Nirmalraj nun eine erste Studie erfolgreich abschliessen. Für die Pilotstudie untersuchte er Blutproben von 50 Patientinnen und Patienten und 16 gesunden Versuchspersonen. Mittels AFM-Technologie analysierte der Empa-Forscher hierzu die Oberfläche von rund 1000 rote Blutkörperchen pro Person, ohne jedoch Informationen über deren Gesundheitszustand zu kennen. «Nur so konnte garantiert werden, dass die Interpretation der Daten objektiv blieb», sagt Nirmalraj.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt; &lt;h3&gt;&lt;b&gt;Eiweissfasern als Indikator&lt;/b&gt; &lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Der Empa-Forscher vermass Grösse, Struktur und Beschaffenheit von Protein-Ansammlungen, die sich auf den Blutkörperchen befanden. Nach Tausenden von roten Blutkörperchen erwartete das Team gespannt den Abgleich der Ergebnisse aus Nirmalraj's Zählungen mit den klinischen Daten der Neurologen. Und tatsächlich konnten die Forscher ein Muster erkennen, das zum Krankheitsstadium der Versuchspersonen passt: Menschen, die an Alzheimer erkrankt waren, wiesen grosse Mengen von Proteinfasern aus Beta-Amyloid-Peptiden und Tau-Proteinen auf. Dabei konnten sich die Proteine zu Fasern von mehreren hundert Nanometern Länge zusammenfügen. Bei gesunden Personen oder jenen mit beginnenden Hirnleistungsstörungen zählte Nirmalraj hingegen lediglich wenige Fasern.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Damit sei die Machbarkeit einer Blutanalyse mittels AFM-Technologie erwiesen, freut sich der Empa-Forscher: «Sollte sich mit dieser Methode ein zuverlässiger Bluttest entwickeln lassen, bliebe Menschen mit Verdacht auf Alzheimer die unangenehme Punktion des Rückenmarkkanals erspart, um die Krankheit eindeutig diagnostizieren zu können.»&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Bis ein einfacher Bluttest im Spital zur Verfügung steht, ist es allerdings noch ein weiter Weg. Als nächstes möchte das Team nun die Daten durch die Untersuchung einer grösseren Zahl an Versuchspersonen in verschiedenen Krankheitsstadien mittels AFM und chemischen Analysen erhärten. &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Dr. Peter Nirmalraj, Empa Transport at Nanoscale Interfaces Tel. +41 58 765 42 61 peter.nirmalraj@empa.ch Dr. Ansgar Felbecker, Kantonsspital St. Gallen Klinik für Neurologie Tel. +41 71 494 11 11 ansgar.felbecker@kssg.ch Redaktion / Medienkontakt: Dr. Andrea Six Kommunikation Tel. +41 58 765 6133 redaktion@empa.ch</contact>
      <attachment id="221433">
        <title>Empa-Forscher Peter Nirmalraj untersucht Blutproben mittels Rasterkraftmikroskopie (AFM). Bild: Empa</title>
        <format>jpg</format>
        <size-kb>1582</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/68354.jpg</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <link id="221434">
        <title>Empa-Medienmitteilung DE EN FR</title>
        <uri>https://www.empa.ch/web/s604/alzheimer-diagnostics</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="221435">
        <title>Youtube Video Peter Nimalraj (englisch)</title>
        <uri>https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=0Fk5tSMnZH8</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Dübendorf, St. Gallen und Thun</city>
      <title>Détecter la démence dans le sang</title>
      <lead>Le chercheur de l'Empa Peter Nirmalraj veut obtenir des images de protéines avec une précision sans précédent - et ainsi mieux comprendre le processus pathologique moléculaire de la maladie d'Alzheimer. Cela devrait ouvrir la voie à un diagnostic plus précoce et simplifié de la maladie d'Alzheimer par le biais d'un test sanguin.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;En cas de soupçon de maladie d'Alzheimer, les personnes concernées doivent se préparer à des procédures longues et complexes jusqu'à ce que le diagnostic soit catégorique. Une équipe de l'Empa et de l'Hôpital cantonal de Saint-Gall est en train de développer un test sanguin qui permettra de poser un diagnostic par microscopie à force atomique (AFM). Les chercheurs ont maintenant publié les résultats d'une étude pilote réussie dans la revue scientifique "Science Advances".&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Un regard profond sur l'univers moléculaire&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;/b&gt; Au départ, le physicien Peter Nirmalraj voulait comprendre le processus pathologique de la maladie d'Alzheimer afin de trouver de nouveaux moyens de diagnostic et de thérapie. Une étape supplémentaire serait de déchiffrer le rôle exact des peptides bêta-amyloïdes et des protéines tau associés à la maladie neurodégénérative. Peter Nirmalraj avait donc entrepris non seulement d'enregistrer la simple présence des protéines suspectes, mais aussi de déterminer leur forme changeante ainsi que leur nombre.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Les méthodes actuelles permettent de déterminer la quantité totale de ces deux protéines dans les fluides corporels. Cependant, ces techniques ne permettent pas de visualiser les différences dans la forme et l'état des accumulations de protéines. Le chercheur travaille donc sur des technologies qui permettent des observations de l'ordre du nanomètre dans le sang sans pour autant détruire la structure et la morphologie des protéines.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;En collaboration avec des neurologues de l'hôpital cantonal de Saint-Gall, Peter Nirmalraj a maintenant mené à bien une première étude. Pour l'étude pilote, il a examiné les échantillons de sang de 50 patients et de 16 sujets sains. Grâce à la technologie AFM, le chercheur de l'Empa a analysé la surface d'environ 1000 globules rouges par personne, mais sans avoir d'information sur leur état de santé au préalable. "C'était le seul moyen de garantir que l'interprétation des données restait objective", déclare Peter Nirmalraj.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3&gt;&lt;b&gt;Les fibres protéiques comme indicateur&lt;/b&gt; &lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Le chercheur de l'Empa a mesuré la taille, la structure et la texture des accumulations de protéines présentes sur les cellules sanguines. Après des milliers de globules rouges, l'équipe attendait avec impatience la comparaison des résultats des numérations de Peter Nirmalraj avec les données cliniques des neurologues. Et en effet, les chercheurs ont pu discerner un schéma qui correspondait au stade de la maladie des sujets testés : Les personnes atteintes de la maladie d'Alzheimer présentaient de grandes quantités de fibres protéiques composées de peptides bêta-amyloïdes et de protéines tau. Les protéines étaient capables de s'assembler en fibres de plusieurs centaines de nanomètres de long. Chez les personnes en bonne santé ou celles présentant des troubles cérébraux naissants, en revanche, Peter Nirmalraj n'a compté que quelques fibres.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Cela prouve la faisabilité de l'analyse du sang à l'aide de la technologie AFM, se réjouit le chercheur de l'Empa : "Si un test sanguin fiable peut être développé à l'aide de cette méthode, les personnes soupçonnées d'être atteintes d'Alzheimer seraient épargnées de la désagréable ponction du canal rachidien afin de pouvoir diagnostiquer la maladie."&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Cependant, il reste encore un long chemin à parcourir avant qu'un simple test sanguin soit disponible dans les hôpitaux. La prochaine étape de l'équipe consiste à corroborer ces données en examinant un plus grand nombre de sujets à différents stades de la maladie à l'aide de l'AFM et d'analyses chimiques. &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Dr. Peter Nirmalraj, Empa Transport at Nanoscale Interfaces Tél. +41 58 765 42 61 peter.nirmalraj@empa.ch Dr. Ansgar Felbecker, Kantonsspital St. Gallen Klinik für Neurologie Tél. +41 71 494 11 11 ansgar.felbecker@kssg.ch Rédaction / Contact médias Dr. Andrea Six Communication Tél. +41 58 765 6133 redaktion@empa.ch</contact>
      <attachment id="221433">
        <title>Empa-Forscher Peter Nirmalraj untersucht Blutproben mittels Rasterkraftmikroskopie (AFM). Bild: Empa</title>
        <format>jpg</format>
        <size-kb>1582</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/68354.jpg</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <link id="221434">
        <title>Empa-Medienmitteilung DE EN FR</title>
        <uri>https://www.empa.ch/web/s604/alzheimer-diagnostics</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="221435">
        <title>Youtube Video Peter Nimalraj (englisch)</title>
        <uri>https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=0Fk5tSMnZH8</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Dübendorf, St. Gallen und Thun</city>
      <title>Detecting dementia in the blood</title>
      <lead>Empa researcher Peter Nirmalraj wants to image proteins with unprecedented precision – and thus gain insights into the molecular pathogenesis of Alzheimer's. This should pave the way for an earlier diagnosis of the dementia disorder via a simple blood test. Together with neurologists from the Kantonsspital St.Gallen, a successful pilot study has now been completed.</lead>
      <text link="no">If the suspicion of Alzheimer's disease creeps up, those affected must prepare themselves for lengthy and complex procedures until the case is clear. A team from Empa and the Cantonal Hospital of St. Gallen is now in the process of developing a blood test that will enable a reliable diagnosis using atomic force microscopy (AFM). The researchers have recently published their first results of a successful pilot study in the journal Science Advances. - A deep look into the molecular universe - In the beginning, physicist Peter Nirmalraj wanted to understand the molecular pathogenesis of Alzheimer's in order to enable new approaches in diagnostics and therapy. One step further would be to decipher the exact role of beta-amyloid peptides and tau proteins associated with the neurodegenerative disease. Nirmalraj therefore set out not only to detect the mere presence of the suspicious proteins, but also to determine their variable shape and form as well as their amounts. Current methods allow the determination of the total amount of both proteins in body fluids. However, these techniques do not allow the visualization of differences in the shape and condition of protein accumulations. The researcher is therefore working on technologies that allow nanometer-scale observations in blood and yet do not destroy the structure and morphology of the proteins. Together with neurologists at the Cantonal Hospital in St. Gallen, Nirmalraj has now successfully completed an initial study. For their pilot study, he examined blood samples from 50 patients and 16 healthy subjects. Using AFM technology, the Empa researcher analyzed the surface of around 1000 red blood cells per person without knowing anything about their state of health. "This was the only way to make sure the interpretation of the data remained objective," says Nirmalraj. - Protein fibers as an indicator - The Empa researcher measured the size, structure and texture of protein accumulations found on the blood cells. After thousands of red blood cells, the team eagerly awaited the comparison of the results from Nirmalraj's counts with the clinical data from the neurologists. And indeed, the researchers were able to discern a pattern that matched the patients' disease stage: People who had Alzheimer's disease had large amounts of protein fibers made up of beta-amyloid peptides and tau proteins. The proteins were able to assemble into fibers several hundred nanometers long. In healthy individuals or those with incipient brain disorders, however, Nirmalraj counted only few fibers. This proves the feasibility of blood analysis using AFM technology, the Empa researcher says: "If a reliable blood test can be developed based on this method, people with suspected Alzheimer's would be spared the unpleasant puncture of the spinal canal in order to be able to diagnose the disease reliably." However, there is still a long way to go before a simple blood test is available in hospitals. The team's next step is to corroborate the data by studying a larger number of subjects at different stages of the disease using AFM and chemical analysis. </text>
      <contact>Dr. Peter Nirmalraj, Empa Transport at Nanoscale Interfaces Tel. +41 58 765 42 61 peter.nirmalraj@empa.ch Dr. Ansgar Felbecker, Kantonsspital St. Gallen Klinik für Neurologie Tel. +41 71 494 11 11 ansgar.felbecker@kssg.ch Editor / Media contact Dr. Andrea Six Communication Phone +41 58 765 6133 redaktion@empa.ch</contact>
      <attachment id="221433">
        <title>Empa-Forscher Peter Nirmalraj untersucht Blutproben mittels Rasterkraftmikroskopie (AFM). Bild: Empa</title>
        <format>jpg</format>
        <size-kb>1582</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/68354.jpg</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <link id="221434">
        <title>Empa-Medienmitteilung DE EN FR</title>
        <uri>https://www.empa.ch/web/s604/alzheimer-diagnostics</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="221435">
        <title>Youtube Video Peter Nimalraj (englisch)</title>
        <uri>https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=0Fk5tSMnZH8</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="8">
        <name lang="de">Bildung und Forschung</name>
        <name lang="fr">Formation et recherche</name>
        <name lang="it">Formazione e ricerca</name>
        <name lang="en">Education and Research</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="15">
        <name lang="de">Gesundheit</name>
        <name lang="fr">Santé</name>
        <name lang="it">sanità</name>
        <name lang="en">Health</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
