<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="85304" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2021-09-30</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="yes" id="1060" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>601</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Staatssekretariat für internationale Finanzfragen</name>
      <name lang="fr">Secrétariat d'Etat aux questions financières internationales</name>
      <name lang="it">Segreteria di Stato per le questioni finanziarie internazionali</name>
      <name lang="en">State Secretariat for International Financial Matters</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.sif.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.sif.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.sif.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.sif.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@sif.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@sif.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@sif.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@sif.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="601">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Finanzdepartement</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des finances</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale delle finanze</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Finance</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.efd.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.dff.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.efd.admin.ch/efd/it/home.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.efd.admin.ch/efd/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Vernehmlassung zur Änderung der Liquiditätsverordnung eröffnet</title>
      <lead>Das Eidgenössische Finanzdepartement (EFD) hat am 30. September 2021 die Vernehmlassung zur Änderung der Liquiditätsverordnung eröffnet. Die Revision soll sicherstellen, dass systemrelevante Banken ausreichend Liquidität halten, um Liquiditätsschocks besser als die übrigen Banken zu absorbieren und den Bedarf auch für eine Sanierung oder Liquidation zu decken. Die Vernehmlassung dauert bis am 13. Januar 2022.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt; Die globale Finanzkrise 2007-2009 hat gezeigt, wie bedeutend die Liquidität für die Stabilität einer systemrelevanten Bank beziehungsweise für die gesamte Volkswirtschaft ist. Eine Notlage oder ein Ausfall einer systemrelevanten Bank kann aufgrund deren Grösse, Marktbedeutung und Vernetzung zu erheblichen Verwerfungen im Finanzsystem führen. Die Wahrscheinlichkeit einer staatlichen Intervention – mit möglichen Kostenfolgen für die Steuerpflichtigen – ist zu minimieren. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; Eine Analyse des EFD in Zusammenarbeit mit der Finanzmarktaufsicht FINMA und der Schweizerischen Nationalbank hat gezeigt, dass die heute geltenden besonderen Anforderungen für systemrelevante Banken nicht durchgehend zu einer höheren Liquiditätshaltung führen. Die vom Bankengesetz verlangte höhere Widerstandsfähigkeit gegen Liquiditätsschocks ist nicht gewährleistet und der Liquiditätsbedarf für den Fall einer Sanierung oder Liquidation ist nicht angemessen gedeckt.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; Das neue Regulierungskonzept für systemrelevante Banken umfasst Grund- und Zusatzanforderungen. Die Grundanforderungen decken gewisse Risiken ab, die in den für alle Banken geltenden Bestimmungen zu wenig berücksichtigt sind. Die FINMA kann zusätzlich institutsspezifische Zuschläge erheben.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; Massnahmen wie beispielsweise der Verkauf marktgängiger Wertpapiere, mit denen eine Bank während einer Krise Liquidität beschaffen kann, sollen bis zu einer Obergrenze angerechnet werden können. Wenn bestimmte Voraussetzungen erfüllt sind, können die Liquiditätsanforderungen auch durch eine kantonale Staatsgarantie oder einen ähnlichen Mechanismus erfüllt werden.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Kommunikation Staatssekretariat für internationale Finanzfragen SIF Tel. +41 58 462 46 16, info@sif.admin.ch</contact>
      <attachment id="221516">
        <title>Entwurf des Regulierungstextes (E-LiqV)</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>1048</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/68381.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="221519">
        <title>Erläuternder Bericht</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>964</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/68384.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="221522">
        <title>Brief an die Kantone</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>580</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/68387.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="221525">
        <title>Brief an die Organisationen</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>138</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/68390.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="221528">
        <title>Liste der Vernehmlassungsadressaten - Liste des destinataires - Elenco dei destinatari</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>577</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/68393.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Ouverture de la consultation concernant la modification de l'ordonnance sur les liquidités</title>
      <lead>Le 30 septembre 2021, le Département fédéral des finances (DFF) a ouvert la consultation concernant la modification de l'ordonnance sur les liquidités. La révision proposée vise à garantir que les banques d'importance systémique détiennent suffisamment de liquidités pour absorber les chocs de liquidités mieux que les autres banques et couvrir leur besoin en cas d'assainissement ou de liquidation. La procédure de consultation se terminera le 13 janvier 2022.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;La crise financière mondiale de 2007-2009 a révélé l'importance des liquidités pour la stabilité des banques d'importance systémique et pour l'ensemble de l'économie. Une situation d'urgence ou la défaillance d'une telle banque peut, eu égard à sa taille, à sa position sur le marché et aux réseaux qu'elle entretient, ouvrir de graves failles dans le système financier. Il y a lieu de réduire au minimum la probabilité que l'État doive intervenir aux frais du contribuable.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Une analyse réalisée par le DFF en collaboration avec l'Autorité fédérale de surveillance des marchés financiers (FINMA) et la Banque nationale suisse a montré que les exigences particulières auxquelles sont soumises les banques d'importance systémique ne les amènent pas nécessairement à détenir davantage de liquidités. La résistance accrue face aux chocs de liquidités qu'exige la loi sur les banques n'est pas garantie, et le besoin de liquidités en cas d'assainissement ou de liquidation n'est pas suffisamment couvert. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;La nouvelle réglementation applicable aux banques d'importance systémique établit des exigences de base et des exigences supplémentaires. Les premières visent certains risques que les dispositions en vigueur pour toutes les banques prennent trop peu en considération. Par ailleurs, la FINMA pourra fixer des majorations spécifiques à l'établissement.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Le projet prévoit la possibilité de prendre en compte jusqu'à un plafond donné les mesures comme la vente de titres négociables permettant à une banque de se procurer des liquidités en période de crise. Lorsque certaines conditions seront réunies, les exigences de liquidités pourront être remplies également au moyen d'une garantie du canton (garantie étatique) ou d'un mécanisme similaire.&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Communication Secrétariat d'État aux questions financières internationales SFI no de tél. +41 58 462 46 16, info@sif.admin.ch</contact>
      <attachment id="221517">
        <title>Projet d'ordonnance (P-OLiq)</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>1049</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/68382.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="221520">
        <title>Rapport explicatif</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>932</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/68385.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="221523">
        <title>Lettres aux cantons</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>151</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/68388.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="221526">
        <title>Lettre aux organisations</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>149</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/68391.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="221528">
        <title>Liste der Vernehmlassungsadressaten - Liste des destinataires - Elenco dei destinatari</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>577</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/68393.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Avvio della procedura di consultazione concernente la modifica dell’ordinanza sulla liquidità</title>
      <lead>Il 30 settembre 2021 il Dipartimento federale delle finanze (DFF) ha avviato la procedura di consultazione concernente la modifica dell’ordinanza sulla liquidità (OLiq). La revisione si propone di garantire che le banche di rilevanza sistemica detengano sufficiente liquidità per assorbire le oscillazioni di liquidità più efficacemente delle altre banche e per coprire il fabbisogno anche in caso di risanamento o liquidazione. La consultazione terminerà il 13 gennaio 2022.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;La crisi finanziaria globale degli anni 2007–2009 ha dimostrato l’importanza della liquidità per la stabilità di una banca di rilevanza sistemica e per l’intera economia. Una situazione d’emergenza o il fallimento di una tale banca può, date le dimensioni, l’importanza sul mercato e le interconnessioni, comportare notevoli squilibri nel sistema finanziario. È quindi indispensabile ridurre al minimo la probabilità che lo Stato debba intervenire in casi simili con possibili ripercussioni finanziarie per i contribuenti. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Da un’analisi condotta dal DFF in collaborazione con l’Autorità federale di vigilanza sui mercati finanziari (FINMA) e la Banca nazionale svizzera è emerso che le attuali esigenze particolari per le banche di rilevanza sistemica non portano sistematicamente a maggiori riserve di liquidità. La maggiore capacità di resistenza agli shock di liquidità richiesta dalla legge sulle banche non è garantita e il fabbisogno di liquidità in caso di risanamento o liquidazione non è sufficientemente coperto.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Il nuovo approccio normativo per le banche di rilevanza sistemica comprende esigenze di base ed esigenze aggiuntive. Le esigenze di base coprono determinati rischi che non sono sufficientemente considerati nelle disposizioni applicabili a tutte le banche. Inoltre, la FINMA può accrescere le esigenze imponendo supplementi specifici all’istituto.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Il progetto prevede anche la possibilità di computare fino a un limite massimo la liquidità che una banca è in grado di generare durante una crisi, ad esempio con la vendita di titoli negoziabili. Se sono adempiute determinate condizioni, le esigenze in materia di liquidità possono essere soddisfatte anche con una garanzia dello Stato rilasciata da un Cantone o con un meccanismo analogo.&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Comunicazione Segreteria di Stato per le questioni finanziarie internazionali SFI Tel. +41 58 462 46 16, info@sif.admin.ch</contact>
      <attachment id="221518">
        <title>Avamprogetto OLiq</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>1044</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/68383.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="221521">
        <title>Rapporto esplicativo</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>886</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/68386.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="221524">
        <title>Lettera ai cantoni</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>145</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/68389.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="221527">
        <title>Lettera alle organizzazioni</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>145</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/68392.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="221528">
        <title>Liste der Vernehmlassungsadressaten - Liste des destinataires - Elenco dei destinatari</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>577</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/68393.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Consultation initiated on amendments to Liquidity Ordinance</title>
      <lead>On 30 September 2021, the Federal Department of Finance (FDF) initiated the consultation on amendments to the Liquidity Ordinance. The revision is intended to ensure that systemically important banks hold sufficient liquidity, in order to absorb liquidity shocks better than other banks and cover their needs in the event of restructuring or liquidation. The consultation will last until 13 January 2022.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;The 2007-2009 global financial crisis showed the significance of liquidity for the stability of a systemically important bank, and for the entire economy. A distressed or defaulting systemically important bank can lead to considerable financial system turbulence, owing to its size, market share and interconnectedness. The likelihood of state intervention – with potential cost implications for taxpayers – should be reduced to a minimum.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;A study carried out by the FDF in conjunction with the Swiss Financial Market Supervisory Authority (FINMA) and the Swiss National Bank showed that the existing special requirements for systemically important banks do not lead to higher liquidity holdings in all cases. The higher resilience to liquidity shocks required in the Banking Act is not ensured and the liquidity needs in the event of restructuring or liquidation are not appropriately covered.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The new regulatory concept for systemically important banks encompasses both basic and additional requirements. The basic requirements cover certain types of risk that are not sufficiently taken into account in the regulatory provisions applying to all banks. FINMA may also impose institution-specific surcharges.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The revision also envisages the possibility for certain measures, such as the sale of marketable securities that a bank can use to generate liquidity during a crisis, to be recognised up to an upper limit. If certain conditions are met, the liquidity requirements can also be fulfilled by a cantonal guarantee or similar mechanism.&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Communications State Secretariat for International Finance SIF Tel. +41 58 462 46 16, info@sif.admin.ch</contact>
      <attachment id="221516">
        <title>Entwurf des Regulierungstextes (E-LiqV)</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>1048</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/68381.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="221519">
        <title>Erläuternder Bericht</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>964</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/68384.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="221522">
        <title>Brief an die Kantone</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>580</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/68387.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="221525">
        <title>Brief an die Organisationen</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>138</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/68390.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="221528">
        <title>Liste der Vernehmlassungsadressaten - Liste des destinataires - Elenco dei destinatari</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>577</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/68393.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <offers>
      <offer id="291" org-id="1060">
        <name lang="de">Wirtschaft, Währung, Finanzplatz</name>
        <name lang="fr">Economie, monnaie, place financière</name>
        <name lang="it">Economia, Moneta, Piazza finanziaria</name>
        <name lang="en">Economic, Monetary and Financial Affairs</name>
      </offer>
    </offers>
    <keywords>
      <keyword id="118" org-id="1060">
        <name lang="de">Finanzmarktregulierung und -aufsicht</name>
        <name lang="fr">Réglementation et surveillance des marchés financiers</name>
        <name lang="it">Regolamentazione e vigilanza dei mercati finanziari</name>
        <name lang="en">Financial market regulation and supervision</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="126" org-id="1060">
        <name lang="de">Finanzplatz Schweiz</name>
        <name lang="fr">Place financière suisse</name>
        <name lang="it">Piazza finanziaria svizzera</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland as a financial centre</name>
      </keyword>
    </keywords>
    <topics>
      <topic id="5">
        <name lang="de">Behörden</name>
        <name lang="fr">Autorités</name>
        <name lang="it">Autorità</name>
        <name lang="en">Authorities</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="35">
        <name lang="de">Finanzplatz</name>
        <name lang="fr">Place financière</name>
        <name lang="it">Piazza finanziaria</name>
        <name lang="en">Financial Centre</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="44">
        <name lang="de">Steuern</name>
        <name lang="fr">Impôts</name>
        <name lang="it">Imposte</name>
        <name lang="en">Taxation</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="47">
        <name lang="de">Wirtschaft</name>
        <name lang="fr">Économie</name>
        <name lang="it">Economia</name>
        <name lang="en">Economic Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
