<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="97875" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2023-09-26</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="408" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>408</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Bundesanwaltschaft</name>
      <name lang="fr">Ministère public de la Confédération</name>
      <name lang="it">Ministero pubblico della Confederazione</name>
      <name lang="en">Office of the Attorney General of Switzerland</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.ba.admin.ch/ba/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.ba.admin.ch/ba/fr/home.html</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.ba.admin.ch/ba/it/home.html</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.ba.admin.ch/</www>
      <email lang="de">info@ba.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@ba.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@ba.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@ba.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="408">
      <name lang="de">Bundesanwaltschaft</name>
      <name lang="fr">Ministère public de la Confédération</name>
      <name lang="it">Ministero pubblico della Confederazione</name>
      <name lang="en">Office of the Attorney General of Switzerland</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.ba.admin.ch/ba/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.ba.admin.ch/ba/fr/home.html</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.ba.admin.ch/ba/it/home.html</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.ba.admin.ch/</www>
      <email lang="de">info@ba.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@ba.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@ba.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@ba.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Anklageschrift gegen einen ehemaligen Mitarbeiter von Gunvor eingereicht</title>
      <lead>Die Bundesanwaltschaft hat beim Bundesstrafgericht Anklage gegen einen ehemaligen Mitarbeiter des Rohstoffhändlers Gunvor eingereicht. Dem Beschuldigten wird vorgeworfen, mindestens zwischen dem 14. Juni 2010 und dem 14. Dezember 2011 aktiv an der Bezahlung von Bestechungsgeldern mitgewirkt zu haben. Dies mit dem Ziel, dem Genfer Unternehmen Zugang zum Erdölmarkt der Republik Kongo zu verschaffen. </lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Die Anklage, welche die Bundesanwaltschaft am 19.09.2023 beim Bundesstrafgericht (BStGer) eingereicht hat, basiert auf Erkenntnissen, die in einem seit Oktober 2015 laufenden Verfahren gewonnen werden konnten. Diese wiederum stehen in Zusammenhang mit dem am 14 Oktober 2019 ergangenen Strafbefehl, mit dem der Genfer Rohstoffhändler Gunvor (Gunvor International BV durch ihre Genfer Niederlassung und die Gunvor AG in Genf) zur Zahlung von insgesamt rund 94 Millionen Franken, davon 4 Millionen Franken Busse, verurteilt worden war. Dies weil das Unternehmen in Folge schwerer Mängel in der internen Organisation die Bestechung von Amtsträgern zugelassen hatte (Art. Art. 322septies Strafgesetzbuch [StGB] in Verbindung mit 102 Abs. 2 StGB) - (&lt;i&gt;Siehe Medienmitteilung der BA vom 17.10.201&lt;/i&gt;9). &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;b&gt;Straftatbestand und Rolle des Beschuldigten&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Der Beschuldigte war gemäss Anklageschrift verantwortlich für die finanziellen Aspekte im Zusammenhang mit dem Markt Kongo-Brazzaville. Ihm wird im zuvor erwähnten Kontext vorgeworfen, mindestens zwischen dem 14.06.2010 und dem 14.12.2011 aktiv an der Bezahlung von Bestechungsgeldern an ausländische Amtsträger mitgewirkt zu haben, respektive die reibungslose Abwicklung der Zahlungen kontrolliert zu haben. Ziel sei es dabei gewesen, den Abschluss von Verträgen im Zusammenhang mit Lieferungen von kongolesischem Erdöl zu Gunsten seines Arbeitgebers zu erreichen.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Nachdem die geschäftlichen Beziehungen mit Kongo zwischenzeitlich abgebrochen waren, soll der Beschuldigte versucht haben, einen neuen Korruptionsplan umzusetzen. Dazu sei er im Frühling 2014 nach Paris gereist, um sich mit einem kongolesischen Beamten zu treffen und ihm im Gegenzug für neue kongolesische Rohöltransporte zu Gunsten von Gunvor ungerechtfertigte Vorteile anzubieten, respektive zu versprechen. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Dieser Sachverhalt erfüllt gemäss den Ermittlungen den Tatbestand der Bestechung ausländischer Amtsträger gemäss von Art. 322septies StGB. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Für den Beschuldigten gilt die Unschuldsvermutung bis zum rechtskräftigen Urteil. Mit Einreichung der Anklage ist das BStGer für weitere Informationen zuständig.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Originalversion des Textes auf Französisch.&lt;/i&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;/b&gt;</text>
      <contact>Kommunikationsdienst der Bundesanwaltschaft, info@ba.admin.ch, +41 58 464 32 40</contact>
      <link id="262925">
        <title>Medienmitteilung der BA vom 17.10.2019</title>
        <uri>https://www.bundesanwaltschaft.ch/mpc/de/home/medien/archiv-medienmitteilungen/news-seite.msg-id-76725.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Dépôt de l’acte d'accusation contre un ancien collaborateur de la société Gunvor</title>
      <lead>Le Ministère public de la Confédération a déposé auprès du Tribunal pénal fédéral un acte d'accusation contre un ancien employé de la société Gunvor. Le prévenu est soupçonné d’avoir pris part activement, à tout le moins entre le 14 juin 2010 et le 14 décembre 2011, à l’exécution de paiements corruptifs afin de permettre à la so-ciété de négoce en matières premières genevoise d’accéder au marché pétrolier de la République du Congo. </lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;L'acte d'accusation déposé le 19 septembre 2023 auprès du Tribunal pénal fédéral (TPF) se fonde sur des éléments établis au cours d’une instruction que le Ministère public de la Confédé-ration (MPC) mène depuis octobre 2015. Ces faits sont en relation avec la condamnation par ordonnance pénale du MPC du 14 octobre 2019 du négociant genevois Gunvor (Gunvor Inter-national BV par sa succursale de Genève et Gunvor SA à Genève) au paiement d’un montant de près de CHF 94 millions, dont CHF 4 millions d’amende pour corruption d’agents publics étran-gers au sens de l’art. 322septies du Code pénal (CP) en relation avec l’art. 102 al. 2 CP (&lt;i&gt;voire communiqué de presse du MPC du 17.10.2019&lt;/i&gt;).&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;b&gt;Faits reprochés et rôle du prévenu&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Dans le contexte susmentionné, il est reproché au prévenu, en tant que responsable en charge des aspects financiers liés au marché du Congo-Brazzaville, à tout le moins entre le 14 juin 2010 et le 14 décembre 2011, d’avoir pris part activement aux versements corruptifs, respectivement au bon déroulement et à la supervision de leur exécution, à destination d’agents publics étrangers. Le but était d’obtenir la conclusion de contrats en lien avec des livraisons de pétrole brut congolais, cela pour le compte de son employeur. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Le prévenu aurait ensuite tenté de developper un nouveau schéma corruptif avec le but de reconstruire les relations avec le Congo qui avaient entre-temps été interrompues. Selon l’acte d’accusation, il se serait rendu à Paris, au printemps 2014 afin d’y rencontrer un officiel congolais et lui offrir, respectivement lui promettre, le versement d’avantages indus, en échange de l’obtention par Gunvor de nouvelles cargaisons de pétrole brut au Congo.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Dans son acte d’accusation, le MPC a retenu que ces faits sont constitutifs de corruption d’agents publics étrangers au sens de l’art. 322septies CP. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;La présomption d'innocence prévaut pour les prévenus jusqu'au prononcé d'un jugement défini-tif. Dès le dépôt de l'acte d'accusation, le TPF est seul compétent pour toute autre information. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Service de communication du Ministère public de la Confédération, info@ba.admin.ch, +41 58 464 32 40</contact>
      <link id="262926">
        <title>Communiqué de presse du MPC du 17.10.2019</title>
        <uri>https://www.bundesanwaltschaft.ch/mpc/fr/home/medien/archiv-medienmitteilungen/news-seite.msg-id-76725.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Promossa l'accusa contro un ex dipendente di Gunvor</title>
      <lead>Il Ministero pubblico della Confederazione ha promosso presso il Tribunale penale federale l'accusa contro un ex dipendente di Gunvor. L'imputato è sospettato di aver svolto un ruolo attivo, quanto meno tra il 14 giugno 2010 e il 14 dicembre 2011, nell'effettuare pagamenti a fini corruttivi, con l’obiettivo di consentire alla società ginevrina attiva nel commercio di materie prime di accedere al mercato petrolifero della Repubblica del Congo.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;L'atto d'accusa depositato presso il Tribunale penale federale (TPF) in data 19 settembre 2023 si basa su elementi accertati nel corso di un’inchiesta che il Ministero pubblico della Confedera-zione (MPC) ha condotto dal mese di ottobre 2015. Tali fatti sono legati al decreto d’accusa del MPC del 14 ottobre 2019 nell’ambito del quale il commerciante ginevrino Gunvor (Gunvor Inter-national BV attraverso la sua filiale di Ginevra e Gunvor SA a Ginevra) è stato condannato al pa-gamento di una somma di circa 94 milioni di franchi, di cui 4 milioni di franchi di multa, per corru-zione di pubblici ufficiali stranieri ai sensi dell’art. 322septies del Codice penale (CP) in combinato disposto con l'art. 102 cpv. 2 CP (&lt;i&gt;si veda comunicato stampa del MPC del 17.10.2019&lt;/i&gt;).&lt;br /&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Fatti contestati e ruolo dell'imputato&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Secondo l’atto d’accusa, nel contesto sopra menzionato l'imputato avrebbe, in qualità di responsabile delle attività finanziarie nell’ambito del contratto Congo-Brazzaville, quanto meno tra il 14 giugno 2010 e il 14 dicembre 2011, partecipato attivamente a pagamenti corruttivi destinati a funzionari pubblici stranieri o alla corretta attuazione e supervisione dei pagamenti stessi. L'obiettivo era quello di ottenere contratti per la consegna di greggio congolese per conto del suo datore di lavoro.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;L'imputato avrebbe altresì cercato di sviluppare un nuovo schema corruttivo con l'obiettivo di ricostruire le relazioni con il Congo, nel frattempo interrotte. Secondo l'accusa, nella primavera del 2014 si sarebbe recato a Parigi per incontrare un funzionario congolese e offrirgli o promettergli il pagamento di vantaggi indebiti in cambio dell'ottenimento da parte di Gunvor di nuove forniture di greggio in Congo.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Nell’atto d’accusa il MPC ha ritenuto i fatti sopra menzionati costitutivi del reato di corruzione di pubblici ufficiali stranieri ai sensi dell’art. 322septies CP.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;La presunzione di innocenza prevale per gli imputati fino alla sentenza definitiva. Dal momento del deposito dell'atto d'accusa, il TPF è l’autorità competente per qualsiasi ulteriore informazione.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Testo originale in francese.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;/b&gt;</text>
      <contact>Servizio comunicazione del Ministero pubblico della Confederazione, info@ba.admin.ch, T +41 58 464 32 40</contact>
      <link id="262927">
        <title>Comunicato stampa del MPC del 17.10.2019</title>
        <uri>https://www.bundesanwaltschaft.ch/mpc/it/home/medien/archiv-medienmitteilungen/news-seite.msg-id-76725.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Indictment filed against former Gunvor employee</title>
      <lead>The Office of the Attorney General of Switzerland has filed an indictment in the Federal Criminal Court against a former employee of the company Gunvor. The accused is alleged to have participated actively, at least from 14 June 2010 to 14 December 2011, in the payment of bribes to enable the Geneva commodities trading company to gain access to the petroleum market in the Republic of the Congo. </lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;The indictment filed on 19 September 2023 in the Federal Criminal Court (FCC) is based on evidence secured in the course of an investigation that the Attorney General of Switzerland (OAG) has been conducting since October 2015. The facts of the case are related to the convic-tion by summary penalty order issued by the OAG on 14 October 2019 of the Geneva trading company Gunvor (Gunvor International BV represented by its Geneva branch and Gunvor SA in Geneva), which resulted in Gunvor paying an amount close to CHF 94 million, including a fine of CHF 4 million for bribery of foreign public officials in terms of Article 322septies of the Swiss Crim-inal Code (SCC) in conjunction with Article 102 paragraph 2 SCC (&lt;i&gt;see OAG press release dated 17.10.2019&lt;/i&gt;).&lt;br /&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Allegations and role of the accused&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In the abovementioned context, the accused is alleged, in his capacity as the person responsible for financial matters relating to the market in Congo-Brazzaville, at least between 14 June 2010 and 14 December 2011, of participating actively in the bribery of foreign public officials, or in ensuring that the process ran smoothly and in supervsing the payments. The aim was to secure contracts connected with the supply of Congolese crude oil on behalf of his employer. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The accused is also alleged to have attempted to develop a further corrupt scheme with the aim of restoring relations with the Congo that had been the meantime broken down. According to the indictment, he travelled to Paris in the spring of 2014 in order to meet a Congolese official and to offer or promise him the payment of undue advantages in exchange for Gunvor obtaining further shipments of crude oil in the Congo.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;With the filing of indictment, the OAG concludes that this constituted bribery of foreign public officials in terms of Article 322septies SCC. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The presumption of innocence applies to the accused until a final judgment has been issued. With the filing of indictment, the FCC has sole responsibility for providing further information. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;i&gt;Original version of the text in French&lt;/i&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;/b&gt;</text>
      <contact>Communications Service of the Office of the Attorney General of Switzerland, info@ba.admin.ch, +41 58 464 32 40</contact>
      <link id="262928">
        <title>OAG press release dated 17.10.2019</title>
        <uri>https://www.bundesanwaltschaft.ch/mpc/en/home/medien/archiv-medienmitteilungen/news-seite.msg-id-76725.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="17">
        <name lang="de">Kriminalität</name>
        <name lang="fr">Criminalité</name>
        <name lang="it">Criminalità</name>
        <name lang="en">Criminality</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
