<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="97922" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2023-09-27</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="201" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>201</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="201">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Genf</city>
      <title>Sicherheitspolitik im Fokus: Vorbereitung auf den nächsten Gipfel der «Europäischen Politischen Gemeinschaft» (EPG)</title>
      <lead>Das Eidgenössische Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten (EDA) hat heute in Genf zusammen mit dem European Council on Foreign Relations (ECFR) und dem Geneva Center for Security Policy (GCSP) einen Workshop zur Rolle der Europäischen Politischen Gemeinschaft (EPG) in der europäischen Sicherheitsordnung durchgeführt. Die Schweiz engagiert sich aktiv in der EPG als Plattform für den Dialog und die Zusammenarbeit in Europa. Der Workshop fand im Vorfeld des nächsten Gipfeltreffens der EPG in Granada statt. </lead>
      <text link="no">Beim nächsten Zusammentreffen der Europäischen Politischen Gemeinschaft in Spanien Anfang Oktober werden unter anderem der Multilateralismus sowie sicherheits- und geopolitische Entwicklungen thematisiert. Der in Genf abgehaltene Workshop zielt darauf ab, einen Beitrag zu den thematischen Diskussionen der Staats- und Regierungschefs an diesem 3. EPG-Gipfel vom 5. Oktober 2023 und darüber hinaus zu leisten. Der Krieg hat die europäische Sicherheitsordnung grundlegend verändert. Europa ist mit einer Vielzahl sich überlappender, komplexer Krisen konfrontiert. «Es liegt an uns, die verfügbaren Instrumente zu nutzen, um die gemeinsamen Herausforderungen zu meistern. Unsere Geschichte zeigt, dass Lösungen auch in scheinbar ausweglosen Situationen gefunden werden können, wenn alle gleichgesinnten Kräfte zusammenspannen», sagte EDA-Staatssekretär Alexandre Fasel in seiner Eröffnungsrede vor den Teilnehmenden. Die Schweiz sei daran interessiert, gemeinsame Antworten zu finden und werde sich weiterhin aktiv in der Europäischen Politischen Gemeinschaft einbringen.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;b&gt;EPG als Plattform für den politischen Dialog&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Der Workshop in Genf brachte rund 30 politische Entscheidungsträgerinnen und Experten aus den EPG-Ländern und den relevanten Institutionen wie der EU, NATO und der OSZE zusammen, um über die Zukunft der europäischen Sicherheitsarchitektur und den bereits aus dem Krieg gegen die Ukraine gezogenen Lehren zu diskutieren. Der Anlass bot Gelegenheit, um Ideen auszutauschen und gemeinsam nach Antworten auf schwierige sicherheitspolitische Fragen zu suchen.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;An den Treffen der Europäischen Politischen Gemeinschaft kommen zweimal im Jahr fast 50 europäische Staaten – sowohl EU- als auch Nicht-EU-Mitglieder – zusammen. Die Schweiz war bereits beim ersten Gipfeltreffen letztes Jahr in Tschechien wie auch bei der zweiten Ausgabe im vergangenen Juni in Moldova auf höchster Ebene durch den jeweiligen Bundespräsidenten vertreten. Ziel dieses noch jungen Formats ist es, Staaten auf dem europäischen Kontinent zu verbinden, um den politischen Dialog und die Zusammenarbeit in Europa zu fördern. Die Schweiz sieht darin eine Chance, den Austausch unter europäischen Partnern auch im Bereich Sicherheit zu vertiefen und wird sich aktiv in den Diskussionen in Granada, Spanien, einbringen. </text>
      <contact>Kommunikation EDA Bundeshaus West CH-3003 Bern Tel. Medienstelle: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <link id="263046">
        <title>European Council on Foreign Relations ECFR (en)</title>
        <uri>https://www.ecfr.eu</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="263047">
        <title>Geneva Centre for Security Policy GCSP (en)</title>
        <uri>https://www.gcsp.ch/</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Genève</city>
      <title>La politique de sécurité au cœur des préoccupations: préparatifs en vue du prochain sommet de la Communauté politique européenne (CPE)</title>
      <lead>Le Département fédéral des affaires étrangères (DFAE) a organisé aujourd’hui à Genève, en collaboration avec le Conseil européen pour les relations internationales (European Council on Foreign Relations, ECFR) et le Centre de politique de sécurité de Genève (Geneva Center for Security Policy, GCSP), un séminaire sur le rôle de la Communauté politique européenne (CPE) au sein de l’ordre sécuritaire européen. La Suisse s’investit de manière active dans la CPE, plateforme de dialogue et de coopération en Europe. Le séminaire a eu lieu à la veille du prochain sommet de la CPE qui doit se tenir à Grenade. </lead>
      <text link="no">Le multilatéralisme et l’évolution de la situation géopolitique et sécuritaire feront partie des sujet abordés lors du prochain sommet de la CPE qui se déroulera début octobre en Espagne. Le séminaire qui a eu lieu à Genève avait pour objet de contribuer aux discussions thématiques prévues entre chefs d’État et de gouvernement lors de ce 3e sommet de la CPE du 5 octobre 2023 et au-delà. La guerre a profondément modifié l’ordre de sécurité européen. L’Europe est confrontée à une superposition de crises complexes. «Il nous incombe d’exploiter les instruments qui sont à notre disposition pour relever les défis auxquels nous faisons tous face. Notre histoire a montré que, même dans des situations paraissant inextricables, des solutions ont été trouvées grâce à l’union des forces convergentes», a déclaré le secrétaire d’État du DFAE Alexandre Fasel dans son discours d’ouverture devant l’assemblée des participants. La Suisse privilégie la recherche de réponses communes et continuera de s’impliquer activement au sein de la CPE.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;b&gt;La CPE, plateforme de dialogue politique&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Le séminaire a rassemblé une trentaine de responsables politiques et d’experts issus des pays représentés au sein de la CPE et de grandes institutions telles que l’UE, l’OTAN et l’OSCE, pour évoquer l’avenir de l’architecture de sécurité européenne et discuter des enseignements tirés de la guerre contre l’Ukraine. Au cours de ce séminaire, les participants ont échangé des idées et cherché ensemble des réponses à des questions complexes en matière de politique de sécurité. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Le sommet de la Communauté politique européenne réunit deux fois par an une cinquantaine d’États européens, membres ou non de l’UE. La Suisse était déjà présente lors du premier sommet qui s’est tenu l’an dernier en Tchéquie. Elle était représentée au plus haut niveau, par le président de la Confédération Alain Berset, lors du deuxième sommet qui a eu lieu en Moldova en juin dernier. L’objectif de ce nouveau format de rassemblement encore récent est de relier les États du continent européen pour favoriser le dialogue politique et la coopération en Europe. La Suisse y voit une chance d’approfondir les échanges entre partenaires européens, également dans le domaine de la sécurité, et participera activement aux discussions prévues à Grenade. </text>
      <contact>Communication DFAE Palais fédéral ouest CH-3003 Berne Tél. Service de presse: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <link id="263046">
        <title>European Council on Foreign Relations ECFR (en)</title>
        <uri>https://www.ecfr.eu</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="263047">
        <title>Geneva Centre for Security Policy GCSP (en)</title>
        <uri>https://www.gcsp.ch/</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Ginevra</city>
      <title>La politica di sicurezza in primo piano: lavori preparatori in vista del prossimo vertice della Comunità politica europea</title>
      <lead>Il Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri (DFAE), con il Consiglio europeo per le relazioni estere (European Council on Foreign Relations; ECFR) e il Centro ginevrino per la politica di sicurezza (GCSP), ha tenuto oggi a Ginevra un workshop sul ruolo della Comunità politica europea (CPE) nell’ordine di sicurezza europeo. La Svizzera partecipa attivamente alla CPE in quanto piattaforma di dialogo e cooperazione in Europa. Il workshop si è svolto in vista del prossimo vertice CPE di Granada. </lead>
      <text link="no">Nel prossimo incontro della Comunità politica europea, che si terrà in Spagna a inizio ottobre, saranno affrontati temi quali il multilateralismo e gli sviluppi in ambito di sicurezza e geopolitica. Il workshop tenutosi a Ginevra mira a fornire un contributo la cui rilevanza non sia limitata alle discussioni tematiche dei capi di Stato e di Governo previste in occasione del terzo vertice CPE del 5 ottobre 2023. La guerra ha infatti cambiato radicalmente l’ordine di sicurezza europeo e l’Europa si trova ad affrontare una moltitudine di crisi complesse e sovrapposte. «Spetta a noi utilizzare gli strumenti disponibili per affrontare le sfide comuni. La nostra storia dimostra che è possibile trovare soluzioni anche in situazioni apparentemente disperate, se tutte le forze con vedute affini si uniscono» ha dichiarato nel suo discorso di apertura il segretario di Stato del DFAE Alexandre Fasel, il quale ha precisato che la Svizzera è interessata a trovare risposte comuni e continuerà a partecipare attivamente alla CPE.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;b&gt;La CPE come piattaforma per il dialogo politico&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Il workshop di Ginevra ha riunito una trentina di persone tra decisori politici ed esperti dei Paesi della CPE e delle istituzioni competenti come l’UE, la NATO e l’OSCE per discutere del futuro dell’architettura di sicurezza europea e degli insegnamenti già tratti dalla guerra contro l’Ucraina. L’evento ha offerto una piattaforma per lo scambio di idee e l’opportunità di cercare insieme risposte a difficili questioni di politica di sicurezza.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Gli incontri della CPE riuniscono due volte l’anno quasi 50 Paesi europei, anche non facenti parte dell’UE. La Svizzera è stata rappresentata ai massimi livelli dai rispettivi presidenti della Confederazione sia al primo vertice dello scorso anno nella Repubblica Ceca che al secondo di giugno in Moldova. L’obiettivo di questo formato, ancora ai blocchi di partenza, è connettere gli Stati del continente europeo per promuovere il dialogo politico e la cooperazione in Europa. La Svizzera ritiene che questa sia un’opportunità per approfondire lo scambio tra i partner europei anche nel settore della sicurezza e parteciperà attivamente alle discussioni a Granada, in Spagna. </text>
      <contact>Comunicazione DFAE Palazzo federale ovest CH-3003 Berna Tel. Servizio stampa: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <link id="263046">
        <title>European Council on Foreign Relations ECFR (en)</title>
        <uri>https://www.ecfr.eu</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="263047">
        <title>Geneva Centre for Security Policy GCSP (en)</title>
        <uri>https://www.gcsp.ch/</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Geneva</city>
      <title>Focus on security policy in run-up to EPC summit</title>
      <lead>The FDFA, together with the European Council on Foreign Relations and the Geneva Centre for Security Policy, held a workshop today in Geneva on the role of the European Political Community (EPC) in the European security architecture. Switzerland is actively involved in the EPC as a platform for dialogue and cooperation in Europe. The workshop took place in the run-up to the next EPC summit in Granada, Spain. </lead>
      <text link="no">The next EPC summit, to be held in Spain in early October, will focus among other topics on multilateralism, security and geopolitical developments. The Geneva workshop aimed to contribute to the thematic discussions of heads of state and government at the upcoming third EPC summit on 5 October 2023 and beyond. The war in Ukraine has fundamentally changed the European security order. Europe is facing a multitude of complex, overlapping crises. "It is up to us to use the tools available to us to tackle the common challenges. Our history has demonstrated that when all like-minded actors join forces, they can find solutions even in situations that seem hopeless," said the FDFA's state secretary, Alexandre Fasel, in his opening address. Switzerland is committed to finding common answers and will continue to play an active role in the EPC. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;EPC: a platform for political dialogue&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The workshop in Geneva brought together around 30 policymakers and experts from EPC countries and key stakeholders such as the EU, NATO and the OSCE to discuss the future of the European security architecture and the lessons to be drawn from Russia's war against Ukraine. The workshop was an opportunity to exchange ideas and work together to find answers to difficult security policy questions. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;EPC meetings bring together representatives from nearly 50 EU and non-EU member states twice a year. Switzerland was represented at the highest level by the president of the Confederation at the first summit last year in the Czech Republic and at the second summit last June in Moldova. The aim of the forum, which is still in its infancy, is to bring together states from across the European continent in order to promote political dialogue and cooperation. Switzerland sees this as an opportunity to step up exchanges among European partners, including in the area of security, and intends to take an active part in the discussions in Granada. </text>
      <contact>FDFA Communication Federal Palace West Wing CH-3003 Bern, Switzerland Tel. Press service: +41 58 460 55 55 E-mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @SwissMFA</contact>
      <link id="263046">
        <title>European Council on Foreign Relations ECFR (en)</title>
        <uri>https://www.ecfr.eu</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="263047">
        <title>Geneva Centre for Security Policy GCSP (en)</title>
        <uri>https://www.gcsp.ch/</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <offers>
      <offer id="312" org-id="201">
        <name lang="de">Bilaterale Abkommen Schweiz-EU</name>
        <name lang="fr">Accords bilatéraux Suisse-UE</name>
        <name lang="it">Accordi bilaterali Svizzera-UE</name>
        <name lang="en">Bilateral Agreements Switzerland-EU</name>
      </offer>
      <offer id="313" org-id="201">
        <name lang="de">Schweizerische Europapolitik</name>
        <name lang="fr">Politique européenne de la Suisse</name>
        <name lang="it">Politica europea della Svizzera</name>
        <name lang="en">Swiss policy on the EU</name>
      </offer>
    </offers>
    <topics>
      <topic id="3">
        <name lang="de">Armee</name>
        <name lang="fr">Armée</name>
        <name lang="it">Esercito</name>
        <name lang="en">Armed Forces</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="30">
        <name lang="de">Ausserordentliche Lagen</name>
        <name lang="fr">Situations extraordinaires</name>
        <name lang="it">Situazioni straordinarie</name>
        <name lang="en">Special Situations</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="34">
        <name lang="de">Europa</name>
        <name lang="fr">Europe</name>
        <name lang="it">Europa</name>
        <name lang="en">Europe</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="40">
        <name lang="de">Sicherheit</name>
        <name lang="fr">Sécurité</name>
        <name lang="it">Sicurezza</name>
        <name lang="en">Security</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="47">
        <name lang="de">Wirtschaft</name>
        <name lang="fr">Économie</name>
        <name lang="it">Economia</name>
        <name lang="en">Economic Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
