<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="86101" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2021-11-25</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="201" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>201</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="201">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Bundesrat Cassis reist zur Weiterführung des strategischen Dialogs nach China</title>
      <lead>Bundesrat Ignazio Cassis trifft am 27. November 2021 seinen chinesischen Amtskollegen Wang Yi in Anji (Provinz Zhejiang). Im Mittelpunkt der Gespräche stehen die bilateralen Beziehungen vor dem Hintergrund der Covid-19-Pandemie sowie aktuelle internationale Entwicklungen und die Menschenrechte. Zudem wird der EDA-Vorsteher die China-Strategie des Bundesrats vorstellen. </lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Das Treffen der beiden Amtskollegen findet im Rahmen des strategischen Dialogs mit China statt. Dieser Dialog auf Aussenministerebene wurde 2017 etabliert, um die Beziehungen zwischen den beiden Ländern zu stärken. Er findet jedes Jahr abwechselnd in der Schweiz und in China statt. Der Dialog umfasst zahlreiche Bereiche der Zusammenarbeit und ermöglicht einen direkten und offenen Austausch über alle Themen, wie zum Beispiel bilateraler Handel, Menschenrechte und multilaterale Zusammenarbeit. Es ist das erste physische Treffen der beiden Amtskollegen seit dem Ausbruch der Covid-19-Pandemie.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Bundesrat Ignazio Cassis wird Aussenminister Wang Yi die China-Strategie vorstellen, die der Bundesrat am 19. März 2021 verabschiedet hat. Die Strategie anerkennt China als wichtigen Partner der Schweizer Aussenpolitik und bildet den Rahmen für die vielfältigen Beziehungen zwischen den beiden Ländern. Die Schweiz möchte einen konstruktiven Dialog mit China führen und dabei auch kritische Fragen ansprechen. Der EDA-Vorsteher wird mit seinem Amtskollegen verschiedene Themen des aktuellen Weltgeschehens besprechen, unter anderem auch die Einhaltung der Menschenrechte.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Bundesrat Cassis wird bei diesem Treffen auch die bedeutenden bilateralen Beziehungen in den Bereichen Wirtschaft und Innovation sowie die Rolle Chinas bei der Lösung von globalen Problemen wie dem Klimawandel hervorheben. &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Kommunikation EDA Bundeshaus West CH-3003 Bern Tel. Kommunikationsservice: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Medienstelle: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <link id="224016">
        <title>China Strategie 2021-2024</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/dam/eda/de/documents/publications/SchweizerischeAussenpolitik/Strategie_China_210319_DE.pdf</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Le conseiller fédéral Cassis se rend en Chine pour la poursuite du dialogue stratégique</title>
      <lead>Le conseiller fédéral Ignazio Cassis rencontrera son homologue chinois Wang Yi, le 27 novembre à Anji, dans la province du Zhejiang. Les discussions porteront sur les relations bilatérales à la lumière de la pandémie de Covid-19, les développements internationaux récents et les droits de l'homme. Le conseiller fédéral présentera en outre la Stratégie Chine du Conseil fédéral. </lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;La rencontre entre Ignazio Cassis et Wang Yi s’inscrit dans le cadre du dialogue stratégique avec la Chine. Ce dialogue au niveau des ministres des affaires étrangères a été établi en 2017 afin de renforcer les relations entre la Suisse et la Chine. Il a lieu chaque année, en alternance entre les deux pays. Il tient compte des multiples domaines de coopération et permet un échange direct et ouvert sur tous les sujets, comme le commerce bilatéral, les droits de l’homme et la coopération dans le domaine multilatéral. Il s’agit de la première rencontre physique entre les deux homologues depuis le début de la pandémie de Covid-19.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Le conseiller fédéral Ignazio Cassis présentera à son interlocuteur la Stratégie Chine, adoptée le 19 mars 2021 par le Conseil fédéral. La stratégie reconnaît la Chine comme un partenaire incontournable de la politique étrangère suisse et donne un cadre aux liens multiples qu’entretiennent les deux pays. La Suisse souhaite mener un dialogue constructif avec la Chine et y aborder également les questions critiques. Le chef du DFAE échangera avec son interlocuteur sur différents thèmes d’actualité internationale ainsi que sur la question du respect des droits de l’homme.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Lors de la rencontre, le conseiller fédéral Cassis soulignera l'importance des relations économiques bilatérales et dans le domaine de l’innovation, ainsi que le rôle de la Chine dans la résolution de problèmes globaux, tel que le changement climatique.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Communication DFAE Palais fédéral ouest CH-3003 Berne Tél. Service de communication: +41 58 462 31 53 Tél. Service de presse: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <link id="224017">
        <title>Stratégie Chine 2021-2024</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/dam/eda/fr/documents/publications/SchweizerischeAussenpolitik/Strategie_China_210319_FR.pdf</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Il consigliere federale Cassis si reca in Cina per proseguire il dialogo strategico</title>
      <lead>Il consigliere federale Ignazio Cassis incontrerà il suo omologo cinese Wang Yi il 27 novembre ad Anji, nella provincia dello Zhejiang. Le discussioni saranno incentrate sulle relazioni bilaterali nel quadro della pandemia di COVID-19, sui recenti sviluppi internazionali e sui diritti umani. Cassis presenterà inoltre la Strategia Cina adottata dal Consiglio federale. </lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;L’incontro tra Ignazio Cassis e Wang Yi fa parte del dialogo strategico con la Cina, che è stato istituito nel 2017 a livello di ministri degli esteri per rafforzare le relazioni tra i due Paesi e viene organizzato ogni anno alternativamente dai due Stati. Il dialogo, che spazia in vari settori di cooperazione, consente uno scambio di opinioni diretto e aperto su tutti i temi, dal commercio bilaterale ai diritti umani e alla cooperazione in campo multilaterale. Dall’inizio della pandemia, questa è la prima volta che le due parti si incontrano dal vivo.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Il consigliere federale Cassis presenterà al suo interlocutore la Strategia Cina adottata dal Consiglio federale il 19 marzo 2021. La Strategia riconosce la Cina come un partner chiave nella politica estera svizzera e definisce un quadro per i molteplici legami tra i due Paesi. La Svizzera vuole condurre un dialogo costruttivo e affrontare anche i nodi critici. Il capo del DFAE discuterà con la controparte di vari temi di attualità internazionale e anche della questione del rispetto dei diritti umani.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Durante l’incontro, Cassis sottolineerà l’importanza delle relazioni economiche bilaterali e nell’ambito dell’innovazione nonché del ruolo della Cina nel trovare una soluzione a problemi globali come il cambiamento climatico. &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Comunicazione DFAE Palazzo federale ovest CH-3003 Berna Tel. Servizio di comunicazione: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Servizio stampa: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <link id="224015">
        <title>Strategia Cina 2021-2024</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/dam/eda/it/documents/publications/SchweizerischeAussenpolitik/Strategie_China_210319_IT.pdf</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Ignazio Cassis visits China to pursue strategic dialogue</title>
      <lead>On 27 November, Federal Councillor Ignazio Cassis will meet with fellow foreign minister Wang Yi in Anji in the province of Zhejiang. Their discussions will focus on bilateral relations in light of the COVID-19 pandemic, recent international developments and human rights. The head of the FDFA will also present the Federal Council's China Strategy. </lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;The meeting between Ignazio Cassis and Wang Yi is part of Switzerland's strategic dialogue with China, a ministerial-level dialogue established in 2017 to strengthen the two countries' relations. The annual meeting between foreign ministers is hosted alternately by Switzerland and China. It covers many areas of Swiss–China cooperation and allows for a direct and open exchange of views in all matters, including bilateral trade, human rights and multilateral cooperation. This is the first physical meeting between the two foreign ministers since the start of the COVID-19 pandemic.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;At the meeting, Ignazio Cassis will present Switzerland's China Strategy, which the Federal Council adopted on 19 March. The strategy recognises China as an important partner for Switzerland's foreign policy and provides a framework for the many ties between the two countries. Switzerland wishes to engage in constructive dialogue with China and to use this dialogue to broach issues of major importance. The head of the FDFA and his counterpart will discuss various current international issues and respect for human rights.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mr Cassis will use the meeting to highlight the importance of the two countries' economic relations and ties with respect to innovation, and the role that China plays in meeting global challenges, such as that of climate change.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>FDFA Communication Federal Palace West Wing CH-3003 Bern, Switzerland Tel. Communication service: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Press service: +41 58 460 55 55 E-mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @SwissMFA</contact>
      <link id="224018">
        <title>China Strategy 2021-24</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/dam/eda/en/documents/publications/SchweizerischeAussenpolitik/Strategie_China_210319_EN.pdf</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
