<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="15982" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2007-11-28</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="405" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>401</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Staatssekretariat für Migration</name>
      <name lang="fr">Secrétariat d’Etat aux migrations</name>
      <name lang="it">Segreteria di Stato della migrazione</name>
      <name lang="en">State Secretariat for Migration</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.sem.admin.ch/sem/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.sem.admin.ch/sem/fr/home.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.sem.admin.ch/sem/it/home.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.sem.admin.ch/sem/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@sem.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@sem.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@sem.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@sem.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="401">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Justiz- und Polizeidepartement</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de justice et police</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale di giustizia e polizia</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Justice and Police</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.ejpd.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.ejpd.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.ejpd.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.ejpd.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-ejpd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">Info@gs-ejpd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-ejpd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-ejpd.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern-Wabern</city>
      <title>Sensibilisierungskampagne über illegale Migration in Afrika</title>
      <lead>Das Bundesamt für Migration führt in Kamerun und Nigeria eine Informationskampagne für die einheimische Bevölkerung durch. Das Ziel der Kampagne besteht darin, auf die negativen Folgen der illegalen Migration aufmerksam zu machen. Die Europäische Union beteiligt sich inzwischen ebenfalls an dem Pilotprojekt.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Wer kennt sie nicht, die Bilder von überfüllten Booten und Menschen, die von rücksichtslosen Schleppern über Bord geworfen werden. Bilder von Booten, die kentern und Menschen, die nur noch tot geborgen werden können. Das Fehlen einer wirtschaftlichen Perspektive führt oft dazu, dass Menschen aus afrikanischen Ländern ihr Glück in der Schweiz und Europa versuchen.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Oftmals erliegen sie illusorischen Erwartungen, die der tatsächlichen Alltagsrealität als illegal Anwesende&amp;nbsp; im Zielland nicht standhalten.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Um auf diese Gefahren und negativen Folgen der illegalen Migration hinzuweisen, startete die das Bundesamt für Migration zu Beginn des Jahres 2006 Informationskampagnen in Kamerun und Nigeria. Die Informationsveranstaltungen, gerade auch auf lokaler Ebene, fanden reges Interesse. Inzwischen beteiligt sich auch die Europäische Union an dem schweizerischen Pilotprojekt.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Die Informationskampagnen des BFM werden in Ländern durchgeführt, in denen das Migrationspotential aufgrund der wirtschaftlich instabilen Lage gross ist. Die Kampagnen richten sich an Menschen, die aus wirtschaftlichen und nicht aus asylrelevanten Gründen ihr Land verlassen. Hilfswerke beurteilen die Initiative des BFM positiv. Mit der Internationalen Organisation für Migration (IOM) verfügt das BFM über einen international renommierten Partner, der seit Jahren mit Büros vor Ort präsent und institutionell hervorragend vernetzt ist.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Jonas Montani, Bundesamt für Migration, T + 41 (0) 31 325 98 80 Jean-Philippe Chauzy, Internationale Organisation für Migration, T + 41 (0) 79 285 43 66</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne-Wabern</city>
      <title>Campagne de sensibilisation en Afrique sur la migration irrégulière</title>
      <lead>L'Office fédéral des migrations mène au Cameroun et au Nigéria une campagne d'information destinée à la population locale. Le but de cette campagne consiste à attirer l'attention des migrants potentiels sur les conséquences né-gatives de la migration irrégulière. L'Union européenne a également décidé de se joindre à ce projet pilote.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Qui ne connaît pas ces images de bateaux surchargés, d'êtres humains jetés par-dessus bord par des passeurs sans scrupules? Des images d'embarcations qui chavirent et de victimes qui meurent avant l'arrivée des secours. Le manque de perspectives économiques pousse bon nombre d'Africains à tenter leur chance en Suisse et en Europe.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Or, ceux-ci nourrissent des espoirs illusoires, qui n'ont rien à voir avec la réalité quotidienne d'un clandestin dans le pays de destination.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Afin de faire connaître les conséquences négatives et les dangers de la migration irrégulière, l'Office fédéral des migrations a lancé au début de l'année 2006 des campagnes d'information au Cameroun et au Nigéria. Ces séances d'information ont été accueillies avec un grand intérêt, particulièrement au niveau local. L'Union européenne participe désormais également au projet pilote lancé par la Suisse.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Les campagnes d'information de l'ODM sont menées dans des pays où le potentiel de migration est élevé à cause de la situation économique instable. Elles s'adressent à des personnes qui veulent quitter leur pays pour des raisons économiques et non pour des motifs liés à l'asile. Les œuvres d'entraide ont salué cette initiative. L'ODM peut en outre s'appuyer sur l'Organisation internationale pour les migrations (OIM), un partenaire de renommée internationale qui dispose depuis des années d'antennes sur place et entretient un excellent réseau de contacts.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Jonas Montani, Office fédéral des migrations, tél. + 41 (0) 31 325 98 80 Jean-Philippe Chauzy, International Organisation of Migration, tél. + 41 (0) 79 285 43 66</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna-Wabern</city>
      <title>Migrazione illegale: campagna di sensibiliz-zazione in Africa</title>
      <lead>L’Ufficio federale della migrazione sta conducendo in Camerun e Nigeria una campagna informativa destinata alla popolazione locale. Tale campagna punta a richiamare l’attenzione sulle conseguenze negative della migrazione illegale. Nel frattempo anche l’Unione europea ha aderito al progetto pilota.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Tutti abbiamo presente le immagini di imbarcazioni stracolme e di gente gettata in mare da passatori senza scrupoli; immagini di imbarcazioni capovolte e di persone che hanno potuto essere recuperate soltanto ormai prive di vita. L'assenza di prospettive economiche spinge spesso persone provenienti da Paesi africani a cercare fortuna in Svizzera e in Europa.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Sovente le loro aspettative illusorie si infrangono nella realtà quotidiana di clandestino nel Paese di destinazione.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Con l'intento di richiamare l'attenzione su tali pericoli e sulle conseguenze negative della migrazione illegale, all'inizio del 2006 l'Ufficio federale della migrazione (UFM) ha avviato campagne informative in Camerun e Nigeria. Tali campagne, effettuate soprattutto su scala locale, hanno suscitato vivo interesse. Nel frattempo anche l'Unione europea ha aderito al progetto pilota svizzero.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Le campagne informative dell'UFM sono condotte in Paesi che, trovandosi in una situazione economica instabile, presentano un elevato potenziale migratorio. Esse sono destinate a persone che lasciano il loro Paese per motivi economici e non rilevanti dal profilo dell'asilo. Le istituzioni di soccorso giudicano in modo positivo l'iniziativa dell'UFM. Con l'Organizzazione internazionale per le migrazioni (IOM) l'UFM è secondato da un partner rinomato a livello internazionale, che da anni è presente con uffici in loco e dispone di eccellenti relazioni sul piano istituzionale.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Jonas Montani, Ufficio federale della migrazione, T + 41 (0) 31 325 98 80 Jean-Philippe Chauzy, Organizzazione internazionale per le migrazioni, T + 41 (0) 79 285 43 66</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Berne-Wabern</city>
      <title>Awareness campaign in Africa against illegal migration</title>
      <lead>The Federal Office for Migration has been conducting an awareness campaign among the people in Cameroon and Nigeria to inform them about the negative consequences of illegal migration. The European Union has joined the federal office in this pilot project.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;There is hardly anybody who has not seen pictures showing overcrowded vessels and people jettisoned into the sea by ruthless migrant smugglers, pictures of ships capsized, of people brought out of the water dead. For want of an economic perspective, people from Africa head to European countries such as Switzerland in search of a better life.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;These people often cherish expectations of a prosperous future abroad-expectations doomed to disappointment because the everyday life of illegal immigrants inevitably falls short of their hopes.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Pointing out the risks and negative consequences of illegal migration, the Federal Office for Migration in early 2006 launched an awareness campaign in Nigeria and Cameroon. The information events have met with interest, especially on the local level. The European Union has meanwhile joined the Swiss campaign in these two countries.&lt;/p&gt; The Federal Office for Migration conducts information campaigns in countries whose people, faced with an unstable economy, are most tempted to leave and become illegal migrants. These campaigns address those people who might consider leaving a country not for reasons making them eligible for asylum, but for economic reasons. Relief organizations commend the Swiss approach to prevent illegal migration. Backed by the International Organization for Migration (IOM), the Federal Office for Migration has a reliable partner of worldwide renown. The IOM has had agencies in many countries for years and is represented institutionally worldwide.</text>
      <contact>Jonas Montani, Federal Office for Migration phone ++ 41 (0)31 325 98 80 Jean-Philippe Chauzy, International Organization for Migration Phone ++ 41 (0)79 285 43 66</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="20">
        <name lang="de">Migration</name>
        <name lang="fr">Migrations</name>
        <name lang="it">Migrazione</name>
        <name lang="en">Migration</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="31">
        <name lang="de">Bund und Kantone</name>
        <name lang="fr">Confédération et cantons</name>
        <name lang="it">Confederazione e Cantoni</name>
        <name lang="en">Confederation and Cantons</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
