<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="35461" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2010-10-06</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="201" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>201</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="yes" id="703" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>701</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Staatssekretariat für Wirtschaft</name>
      <name lang="fr">Secrétariat d'Etat à l'économie</name>
      <name lang="it">Segreteria di Stato dell'economia</name>
      <name lang="en">State Secretariat for Economic Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.seco.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.seco.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.seco.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.seco.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@seco.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@seco.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@seco.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@seco.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="201">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <department id="701">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Wirtschaft, Bildung und Forschung</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'économie, de la formation et de la recherche</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'economia, della formazione e della ricerca</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Economic Affairs, Education and Research</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Schweiz unterzeichnet Kooperationsabkommen mit Kosovo</title>
      <lead>Die Schweiz und Kosovo haben am 6. Oktober 2010 in Pristina ein Abkommen über technische und finanzielle Zusammenarbeit sowie humanitäre Hilfe unterzeichnet. Das Abkommen schafft einen neuen rechtlichen Rahmen für die Kooperation der beiden Staaten bei der Umsetzung politischer und wirtschaftlicher Reformen in Kosovo. Die Direktion für Entwicklungszusammenarbeit DEZA und das Staatssekretariat für Wirtschaft SECO unterstützen den Transformationsprozess Kosovos jährlich im Umfang von rund 15 Millionen Franken.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Am Mittwoch, 6. Oktober 2010, haben der Botschafter der Schweiz in Kosovo, Lukas Beglinger, und der kosovarische Aussenminister Skender Hyseni in Pristina ein Abkommen über technische und finanzielle Zusammenarbeit sowie humanitäre Hilfe unterzeichnet. Ziel der Zusammenarbeit ist die Förderung politischer, wirtschaftlicher und sozialer Reformen in Kosovo. &amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Besonderes Gewicht erhalten dabei der Aufbau des Rechtstaates, die Stärkung der lokalen Behörden, des Gemeindeverbandes und der Zivilgesellschaft, der Aufbau nachhaltiger Infrastrukturen insbesondere im Bereich der Wasserversorgung, die Unterstützung des Privatsektors sowie die Berufsbildung. Dadurch soll der Transformationsprozess Kosovos unterstützt werden. Dies ist für die Schweiz aufgrund ihrer engen Beziehungen zu Kosovo von grossem Interesse. &amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Die Schweiz hat Kosovo am 27. Februar 2008 als Staat anerkannt. Mit dem neuen bilateralen Abkommen wird die mit der interimistischen UNO-Verwaltung UNMIK unterzeichnete Vereinbarung („Umbrella Memorandum of Understanding“) aus dem Jahr 2000 ersetzt. Die Zusammenarbeit mit Kosovo basiert nun auf direkt mit den kosovarischen Behörden vereinbarten Grundsätzen und Bedingungen.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Kontakt / Rückfragen:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Information EDA Tel. +41 31 322 31 53&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Jean-Luc Bernasconi, SECO, stv. Leiter Wirtschaftliche Zusammenarbeit und Entwicklung, Tel. +41 31 324 08 18.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Information EDA Bundeshaus West CH-3003 Bern Tel.: +41 (0)31 322 31 53 Fax: +41 (0)31 324 90 47 E-Mail: info@eda.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="75202">
        <title>Engagement der Schweiz in Kosovo</title>
        <uri>http://www.deza.admin.ch/de/Home/Laender/Westbalkan/Kosovo</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>La Suisse signe un accord de coopération avec le Kosovo</title>
      <lead>La Suisse et le Kosovo ont signé le 6 octobre 2010 à Pristina un accord concernant la coopération technique et financière et l’aide humanitaire. Cet accord crée un nouveau cadre juridique pour la coopération entre les deux Etats dans la mise en œuvre de réformes politiques et économiques au Kosovo. La Direction du développement et de la coopération (DDC) et le Secrétariat d’Etat à l’économie (SECO) apportent un soutien financier, à hauteur de 15 millions de francs environ par an, au processus de transformation en cours au Kosovo.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Le mercredi 6 octobre 2010, l’ambassadeur de Suisse au Kosovo, M.&amp;nbsp;Lukas Beglinger, et le ministre des affaires étrangères du Kosovo, M.&amp;nbsp;Skender Hyseni, ont signé à Pristina un accord concernant la coopération technique et financière et l’aide humanitaire. Cette coopération vise à promouvoir les réformes politiques, économiques et sociales au Kosovo.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;L’accent est mis en particulier sur l’édification de l’Etat de droit, sur le renforcement des autorités locales, de l’association des communes et de la société civile, sur la construction d’infrastructures durables, en particulier dans le domaine de l’approvisionnement en eau, sur le soutien du secteur privé et sur la formation professionnelle. Le but est de soutenir le processus de transformation engagé au Kosovo, qui revêt un grand intérêt pour la Suisse en raison des relations étroites qu’elle entretient avec le Kosovo. &amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;La Suisse a reconnu le Kosovo en tant qu’Etat le 27 février 2008. Le nouvel accord bilatéral remplace l’«&amp;nbsp;Umbrella Memorandum of Understanding&amp;nbsp;» conclu en 2000 avec la Mission d'administration intérimaire des Nations Unies au Kosovo (MINUK). La coopération avec le Kosovo repose maintenant sur des principes et des conditions qui ont été convenus directement avec les autorités kosovares.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contact / questions&amp;nbsp;:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Information DFAE, tél.&amp;nbsp;: +41 31 322 31 53&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Jean-Luc Bernasconi, SECO, suppléant de la cheffe du centre de prestations Coopération et développement économiques, tél.&amp;nbsp;: +41 31 324 08 18. &amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Information DFAE Palais fédéral ouest CH-3003 Berne Tél.: (+41) 031 322 31 53 Fax: (+41) 031 324 90 47 E-Mail: info@eda.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="75203">
        <title>L’engagement de la Suisse au Kosovo</title>
        <uri>http://www.deza.admin.ch/fr/Accueil/Pays/Balkans_occidentaux/Kosovo</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>La Svizzera firma un accordo di cooperazione con il Kosovo</title>
      <lead>Il 6 ottobre 2010 a Pristina la Svizzera e il Kosovo hanno firmato un accordo di cooperazione tecnica e finanziaria nonché di aiuto umanitario. L’accordo crea un nuovo quadro giuridico per la cooperazione tra i due Stati nell’attuazione delle riforme economiche e politiche in Kosovo. La Direzione dello sviluppo e della cooperazione DSC e la Segreteria di Stato dell’economia SECO sostengono il processo di trasformazione del Kosovo con un contributo annuo di circa 15 milioni di franchi.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Mercoledì 6 ottobre 2010, l’ambasciatore della Svizzera in Kosovo, Lukas Beglinger, e il ministro degli esteri kosovaro, Skender Hyseni, hanno firmato a Pristina un accordo di cooperazione tecnica e finanziaria nonché di aiuto umanitario. Tale cooperazione ha lo scopo di promuovere riforme politiche, economiche e sociali in Kosovo. &amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Particolare rilievo in questo contesto assumono la costituzione dello stato di diritto, il consolidamento delle autorità locali, dell’associazione dei Comuni e della società civile, la costruzione di infrastrutture durevoli soprattutto nel settore dell’approvvigionamento idrico, il sostegno al settore privato nonché la formazione professionale. Queste misure permetteranno di sostenere il processo di trasformazione del Kosovo. Le strette relazioni intrattenute con il Kosovo rendono questo processo di grande interesse per la Svizzera.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Il 27 febbraio 2008 la Svizzera ha riconosciuto il Kosovo come Stato. Il nuovo accordo bilaterale sostituisce la convenzione («Umbrella Memorandum of Understanding») del 2000 firmata con l’amministrazione ad interim delle Nazioni Unite UNMIK. La cooperazione con il Kosovo si basa quindi da ora sulle condizioni e sui principi concordati direttamente con le autorità kosovare.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contatti/domande:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Informazione DFAE, tel. +41 31 322 31 53&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Jean-Luc Bernasconi, SECO, capo sostituto Cooperazione e sviluppo economici, tel. +41 31 324 08 18.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Informazione DFAE Palazzo federale ovest CH-3003 Berna Tel.: (+41) 031 322 31 53 Fax: (+41) 031 324 90 47 E-Mail: info@eda.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="75204">
        <title>L’impegno della Svizzera in Kosovo</title>
        <uri>http://www.deza.admin.ch/it/Pagina_iniziale/Paesi/Balcani_occidentali/Kosovo</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Switzerland signs a cooperation agreement with Kosovo</title>
      <lead>On 6 October 2010, Switzerland and Kosovo signed an agreement in Pristina on technical and financial cooperation, and humanitarian aid. The agreement creates a new legal framework for cooperation between the two states in the context of the political and economic reforms currently being implemented in Kosovo. The Swiss Agency for Development and Cooperation (SDC) and the State Secretariat of Economic Affairs (SECO) are supporting the transformation process with an annual amount of approximately 15 million Swiss francs.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;On Wednesday, 6 October 2010, the Swiss Ambassador in Kosovo, Lukas Beglinger, and the Foreign Minister of Kosovo, Skender Hyseni, signed an agreement in Pristina on technical and financial cooperation, and humanitarian aid. The aim of the cooperation is to promote political, economic and social reforms in Kosovo. &amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Special priority is being given to consolidating implementation of the rule of law, strengthening municipalities and their umbrella association, and supporting the development of civil society, as well as the construction of sustainable infrastructure, in particular in the fields of water supply, support for the private sector and vocational training. The overall aim is to support the transformation process in Kosovo, which Switzerland considers to be strongly in its interests due to its close relationhip with Kosovo. &amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Switzerland recognised Kosovo as an independent state on 27 February 2008. The new bilateral agreement replaces the Umbrella Memorandum of Understanding that was signed with the interim UN administration, UNMIK, in 2000. As of now, cooperation with Kosovo will be based on principles and conditions that have been agreed directly with the Kosovar authorities.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contact / Questions:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;FDFA Information Tel. +41 31 322 31 53&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Jean-Luc Bernasconi, SECO, deputy-head, Economic Cooperation and Development, &amp;nbsp;Tel. +41 31 324 08 18.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Information FDFA Bundeshaus West CH-3003 Bern Tel.: (+41) 031 322 31 53 Fax: (+41) 031 324 90 47 E-Mail: info@eda.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="75205">
        <title>Switzerland’s commitment to Kosovo</title>
        <uri>http://www.deza.admin.ch/en/Home/Countries/Western_Balkans/Kosovo</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
