<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="69890" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2018-02-26</pubdate>
    <blocking-period>2018-02-26</blocking-period>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="318" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>301</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Bundesamt für Statistik</name>
      <name lang="fr">Office fédéral de la statistique</name>
      <name lang="it">Ufficio federale di statistica</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Statistical Office</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.statistik.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.statistique.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.statistica.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.statistics.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@bfs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@bfs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@bfs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@bfs.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="301">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement des Innern</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'intérieur</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'interno</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Home Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Neuchâtel</city>
      <title>Effektiv- und Mindestlöhne sind 2017 um 0,5% bzw. 0,8% gestiegen</title>
      <lead>(BFS) – Die unterzeichnenden Sozialpartner der wichtigsten Gesamtarbeitsverträge (GAV) in der Schweiz haben für das Jahr 2017 eine nominale Erhöhung der Effektivlöhne (+0,5%) und der Mindestlöhne (+0,8%) beschlossen. Von der Effektivlohnerhöhung wurden 0,1% generell und 0,4% individuell zugesichert. Dies geht aus der Erhebung über die gesamtarbeitsvertraglichen Lohnabschlüsse hervor, die vom Bundesamt für Statistik (BFS) durchgeführt wurde.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Diese Medienmitteilung und weitere Informationen zum Thema finden Sie auf der Website des BFS (siehe Link unten)&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Didier Froidevaux, BFS, Sektion Löhne und Arbeitsbedingungen, Tel.: +41 58 463 67 56, E-Mail: didier.froidevaux@bfs.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="175321">
        <title>Kompletter Text und Mediendossier</title>
        <uri>https://www.bfs.admin.ch/news/de/2017-0306</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Neuchâtel</city>
      <title>Les salaires effectifs et minimaux ont augmenté respectivement de 0,5% et 0,8% en 2017</title>
      <lead>(OFS) – Les partenaires sociaux signataires des principales conventions collectives de travail (CCT) de Suisse ont convenu pour 2017 d’une augmentation nominale des salaires effectifs de 0,5% et de 0,8% des salaires minimaux. Les salaires effectifs ont augmenté de 0,1% à titre collectif et de 0,4% à titre individuel. Ce sont là quelques résultats de l'enquête sur les accords salariaux conclus dans les domaines conventionnels, réalisée par l'Office fédéral de la statistique (OFS).</lead>
      <text link="no">Vous trouverez ce communiqué de presse et d'autres informations sur ce thème sur le site web de l'OFS (cf. lien ci-dessous).</text>
      <contact>Didier Froidevaux, OFS, Section Salaires et conditions de travail, tél. : +41 58 463 67 56, e-mail : Didier.Froidevaux@bfs.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="175322">
        <title>Texte intégral et dossier de presse</title>
        <uri>https://www.bfs.admin.ch/news/fr/2017-0306</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Neuchâtel</city>
      <title>I salari effettivi e i salari minimi sono aumentati rispettivamente dello 0,5% e dello 0,8% nel 2017</title>
      <lead> (UST) – Le parti sociali firmatarie dei principali contratti collettivi di lavoro (CCL) della Svizzera hanno concordato per il 2017 un aumento nominale dei salari effettivi dello 0,5% e dello 0,8% per i salari minimi. I salari effettivi sono aumentati dello 0,1% a titolo collettivo e dello 0,4% a titolo individuale. Sono questi i principali risultati che emergono dall’indagine sugli accordi salariali conclusi nei settori convenzionali condotta dall’Ufficio federale di statistica (UST).</lead>
      <text link="no">Il presente comunicato stampa e ulteriori informazioni sul tema sono reperibili sulla pagina Internet dell'UST (link sotto).</text>
      <contact>Didier Froidevaux, UST, Sezione Salari e condizioni di lavoro, tel.: +41 58 463 67 56, e-mail: didier.froidevaux@bfs.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="175323">
        <title>Testo integrale e dossier per i media</title>
        <uri>https://www.bfs.admin.ch/news/it/2017-0306</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Neuchâtel</city>
      <title>Real and minimum wages increased by 0.5% and 0.8% respectively in 2017</title>
      <lead>(FSO) – The social partners signatory to Switzerland's main collective labour agreements (CLA) agreed a nominal rise in real wages of 0.5% and a nominal rise in minimum wages of 0.8% for 2017. Real wages increased by 0.1% at collective level and by 0.4% at individual level. These are the some of the results of the wage agreements survey carried out by the Federal Statistical Office (FSO).</lead>
      <text link="no">This press release and further information on this topic can be found on the FSO website (see link below).</text>
      <contact>Didier Froidevaux, FSO, Wages and Working Conditions Section, tel. : +41 58 463 67 56, e-mail : Didier.Froidevaux@bfs.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="175324">
        <title>Complete text and press kit - Please note that the English version only includes the release's lead</title>
        <uri>https://www.bfs.admin.ch/news/en/2017-0306</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="2">
        <name lang="de">Arbeit</name>
        <name lang="fr">Travail</name>
        <name lang="it">Lavoro</name>
        <name lang="en">Labour</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="43">
        <name lang="de">Statistik</name>
        <name lang="fr">Statistiques</name>
        <name lang="it">Statistica</name>
        <name lang="en">Statistics</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
