<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="70043" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2018-03-08</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="302" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>301</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Generalsekretariat EDI</name>
      <name lang="fr">Secrétariat général DFI</name>
      <name lang="it">Segreteria generale DFI</name>
      <name lang="en">General Secretariat FDHA</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="201" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>201</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="301">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement des Innern</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'intérieur</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'interno</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Home Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <department id="201">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Die Schweiz und Bhutan bekräftigen ihre Verbundenheit</title>
      <lead>Bei einem Arbeitsbesuch des bhutanischen Premierministers Tshering Tobgay bei Bundespräsident Alain Berset am Donnerstag, 8. März 2018, in Bern haben beide Seiten die anhaltende Verbundenheit ihrer Länder bekräftigt. Bhutan war bis vor zehn Jahren ein Schwerpunktland der schweizerischen Entwicklungszusammenarbeit, Ende 2016 zog sich die Direktion für Entwicklung und Zusammenarbeit (DEZA) definitiv aus dem Land zurück. Im Zentrum des offiziellen Gesprächs standen die Perspektiven und Chancen des neuen Kapitels in den bilateralen Beziehungen. </lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Bundespräsident Berset würdigte die Entwicklungsstrategie Bhutans und die erfolgreiche Demokratisierung des Landes seit Inkrafttreten der neuen Verfassung im Jahre 2008. Beide Seiten betonten, dass der Ausbau der früher vor allem auf Entwicklungsfragen fokussierten bilateralen Zusammenarbeit zu einer Partnerschaft mit politischen, wirtschaftlichen, wissenschaftlichen und kulturellen Aspekten im Gange sei. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Eine Vereinbarung zu regelmässigen politischen Konsultationen wurde vor wenigen Wochen unterzeichnet. Demnächst soll zudem ein Honorarkonsulat der Schweiz in Bhutan etabliert werden. Zur Sprache kam am Donnerstag unter anderem auch die Herausforderung durch den Klimawandel. Des Weiteren unterhielten sich die Delegationen über die Zusammenarbeit beider Länder auf internationaler Ebene. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Die engen Beziehungen zwischen dem Alpenland Schweiz und dem Himalayastaat Bhutan reichen in die 1950er-Jahre zurück und hatten ihren Ursprung in persönlichen Kontakten zwischen dem damaligen bhutanischen König und einem Schweizer Industriellen. Ab 1978 engagierte sich auch der Bund in Bhutan, in den 1980er- und 1990er-Jahren zählte die Schweiz zu den wichtigsten Geberländern. &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Nicole Lamon, Informationsdienst EDI +41 (0)78 756 44 49, media@gs-edi.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="175693">
        <title>Bilaterale Beziehungen Schweiz–Bhutan</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home/vertretungen-und-reisehinweise/bhutan/bilatereale-beziehungenschweizbhutan.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>La Suisse et le Bhoutan confirment leurs liens</title>
      <lead>À l’occasion d’une visite de travail à Berne le jeudi 8 mars 2018 du premier ministre du Bhoutan, le président de la Confédération Alain Berset et Tshering Tobgay ont souligné la continuité des liens entre les deux États. Il y a dix ans encore, la coopération suisse au développement était très active au Bhoutan. Fin 2016, la Direction du développement et de la coopération (DDC) a décidé de s’en retirer définitivement. Les entretiens officiels ont principalement porté sur les perspectives et les chances des nouvelles relations bilatérales entre les deux États.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Alain Berset a salué la stratégie de développement du Bhoutan et sa démocratisation depuis l'entrée en vigueur de sa nouvelle constitution en 2008. Les deux parties ont affirmé que la coopération bilatérale fondée auparavant sur le développement se transformait petit à petit en partenariat sur les plans politique, économique, scientifique et culturel.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Une convention portant sur une consultation politique régulière a été signée il y a quelques semaines. L'établissement d'un consulat honoraire suisse au Bhoutan est en outre prévu prochainement. Lors de la visite de jeudi, les discussions ont en outre porté sur les défis posés par les changements climatiques et sur la coopération entre les deux États au niveau international.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Les relations étroites entre le pays alpin qu'est la Suisse et cet État de l'Himalaya datent des années 1950 et tiraient leur origine de contacts personnels entre le roi de l'époque et un industriel suisse. Dès 1978, la Confédération s'est elle aussi engagée au Bhoutan. Dans les années 1980 et 1990, la Suisse figurait parmi les principaux pays donateurs.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Nicole Lamon, cheffe de la communication du DFI +41 (0)78 756 44 49, media@gs-edi.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="175692">
        <title>Relations bilatérales Suisse–Bhoutan</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae/representations-et-conseils-aux-voyageurs/bhoutan/suisse-bhoutan.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>La Svizzera e il Bhutan rafforzano i loro legami</title>
      <lead>In occasione dell’odierna visita di lavoro del primo ministro del Bhutan Tshering Tobgay al presidente della Confederazione Alain Berset a Berna, entrambe le Parti hanno ribadito la solidità delle loro relazioni. Fino a dieci anni or sono, il Bhutan era un Paese prioritario della cooperazione svizzera allo sviluppo. A fine 2016, la Direzione dello sviluppo e della cooperazione (DSC) si è definitivamente ritirata da questo Paese. Tema centrale del colloquio ufficiale: le prospettive e le opportunità del nuovo capitolo nelle relazioni bilaterali. </lead>
      <text link="no">Il presidente della Confederazione Berset ha espresso apprezzamenti per la strategia di sviluppo del Bhutan e la democratizzazione in atto nel Paese dall'entrata in vigore della nuova Costituzione nel 2008. Entrambi i Paesi hanno sottolineato che la cooperazione bilaterale incentrata in passato soprattutto su questioni inerenti allo sviluppo sta evolvendo verso un partenariato improntato su aspetti politici, economici, scientifici e culturali. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Alcune settimane fa è stato firmato un accordo concernente consultazioni politiche regolari. Prossimamente nel Bhutan sarà insediato un Consolato onorario svizzero. Giovedì si è discusso fra l'altro anche della sfida posta dai cambiamenti climatici. Le delegazioni hanno inoltre affrontato il tema della cooperazione dei due Paesi a livello internazionale. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Risalenti agli Anni Cinquanta, le strette relazioni fra il Paese alpino della Svizzera e lo Stato himalayano del Bhutan sono iniziate grazie ai contatti personali fra l'allora sovrano del Bhutan e un industriale svizzero. Dal 1978 anche la Confederazione si è impegnata nel Bhutan, diventando negli anni Ottanta e Novanta uno dei principali Paesi donatori. </text>
      <contact>Nicole Lamon, Servizio delle informazioni DFI +41 (0)78 756 44 49, media@gs-edi.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="175691">
        <title>Relazioni bilaterali Svizzera–Bhutan</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae/rappresentanze-e-consigli-di-viaggio/bhutan/svizzera-bhutan.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Switzerland and Bhutan reaffirm their close ties</title>
      <lead>During a working visit to Bern on Thursday, 8 March, President Alain Berset and Bhutanese Prime Minister Tshering Tobgay reaffirmed the continuing close ties between their two countries. Up until ten years ago, Bhutan was a Swiss development cooperation priority country, but at the end of 2016 the Swiss Agency for Development and Cooperation (SDC) ended its activities in the country. The official talks focused on prospects and opportunities under this new chapter in bilateral relations. </lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;President Berset praised Bhutan's development strategy and the country's successful democratisation since the entry into force of the new constitution in 2008. Both sides stressed that bilateral cooperation, previously based on development, was in the process of being broadened to a partnership encompassing political, economic, scientific and cultural aspects.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;An agreement on regular political consultations was signed a few weeks ago. In addition, a Swiss honorary consulate is to be established in Bhutan in the near future. Other topics discussed on Thursday included the challenges presented by climate change. The delegations also discussed cooperation between the two countries at international level.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The close ties between Switzerland and Bhutan date back to the 1950s and began thanks to the personal contacts between the king of Bhutan and a Swiss industrialist. From 1978 the Swiss government also became involved in Bhutan and during the 1980s and 1990s Switzerland was one of the leading donor countries. &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Nicole Lamon, FDHA Information Service +41 (0)78 756 44 49, media@gs-edi.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="175690">
        <title>Bilateral relations Switzerland–Bhutan</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home/representations-and-travel-advice/bhutan/switzerland-bhutan.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
