<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="70910" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2018-05-28</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="323" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>701</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidg. Materialprüfungs- und Forschungsanstalt</name>
      <name lang="fr">Laboratoire fédéral d'essai des matériaux et de recherche</name>
      <name lang="it">Laboratorio federale di prova dei materiali e di ricerca</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Laboratory for Materials Testing and Research</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.empa.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.empa.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.empa.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.empa.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">contact@empa.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">contact@empa.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">contact@empa.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">contact@empa.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="701">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Wirtschaft, Bildung und Forschung</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'économie, de la formation et de la recherche</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'economia, della formazione e della ricerca</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Economic Affairs, Education and Research</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Dübendorf, St. Gallen und Thun</city>
      <title>Damit Ronaldo und Co. verlässlich «zaubern» können</title>
      <lead>Der offizielle Ball für die FIFA-Fussball-WM 2018 in Russland hat nach zahlreichen Tests das «OK» der Empa erhalten. Manche Torhüter sehen dessen Flugeigenschaften zwar eher kritisch; Die Ursache ihrer Kritik könnte jedoch ganz woanders liegen – am eher unkonventionellen Äusseren des neuen Balls.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Fussball lebt von Emotionen. Wenn es um den diesjährigen WM-Ball geht, sind die Experten der Empa allerdings völlig emotionslos. Fragt man sie nach ihrem Eindruck zu den bereits des Öfteren bemängelten Flugeigenschaften des Adidas-Modells «Telstar 18» wehren sie ab: «Eindrücke sind etwas Subjektives», sagt Martin Camenzind vom «Laboratory for Biomimetic Membranes and Textiles». «Wir verlassen uns auf objektive Parameter, die den Telstar 18 charakterisieren.» Dass Kritiker, wie Spaniens Torhüter David De Gea und Pepe Reina oder der Deutsche Goalie Mark-Andre ter Stegen dem Ball «Flatterhaftigkeit» unterstellen, beeindruckt Camenzind daher kaum. Die eigens an der Empa in St. Gallen für offizielle Turnierfussbälle entwickelte Testreihe hat der Telstar 18 jedenfalls erfolgreich bestanden, und nur das zählt für den Empa-Forscher.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Seit 22 Jahren führt die Empa im Auftrag der FIFA die unbestechlichen Versuchsreihen mit Fussbällen durch, die das Gütesiegel des FIFA-Qualitätsprogramms anstreben. Längst nicht jeder Ball besteht die Probe. Hier werden nicht nur Umfang und Gewicht des Balls gemessen. Er darf ausserdem trotz 250-maligem Quetschen in einem Wasserbehälter nur minimale Mengen an Flüssigkeit aufnehmen, muss seine Luft halten können und immer wieder gleich hoch abspringen, wenn er aus zwei Metern Höhe aufprallt. Um zu beweisen, dass es sich um eine perfekte Kugel handelt, wird der Ball zudem an sage und schreibe 4000 Punkten vermessen. Und schliesslich muss diese Kugel ihre Form auch behalten, wenn sie 2000 Mal mit 50 Stundenkilometern gegen eine Stahlwand geschossen wurde.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Derartige Standards entscheiden mit über die Qualität und Konsistenz der Sportart. Als die Testreihen eingeführt wurden, gelang es noch nicht allen Herstellern, die verlangten Eigenschaften zu erzielen: «Es fielen immer wieder Exemplare durch», erinnert sich Camenzind. Mancher Lederball hätte etwa deutlich an Grösse zugenommen nach der Prozedur oder zu viel Wasser aufgesogen. Die heutigen Bälle seien denn auch geklebt oder geschweisst, da Nähte mit der Zeit nachgeben könnten. Ebenso ist das traditionelle Leder mehrheitlich Kunststoffen gewichen, deren Oberfläche gezielt strukturiert wird, was besonders bei Nässe auf dem Feld eine griffigere Führung des Balls ermöglichen soll.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Angewandte Physik statt Magie&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Und eben diese Oberfläche sei es, melden Kritiker, die für den unberechenbaren Flug des Balles sorge. Telstar 18 sei ein merkwürdiges, flatterndes Exemplar, behaupten Torhüter verschiedener WM-Teams, die den Ball bereits testen durften. Doch Camenzind kontert: «Hier kommt auch die Optik mit ins Spiel», erklärt der Ingenieur. Telstar 18 ist nicht aus den traditionellen Sechs- und Fünfecken aufgebaut, sondern aus unregelmässigen Elementen, die unsymmetrisch bedruckt sind. So könne der fliegende Ball bei entsprechenden Lichtverhältnissen durchaus ein ungewohnter Anblick sein. «Wir konnten in einer Studie mit einem computergesteuerten Fuss zeigen, dass Bälle, bei denen ein flatterndes Flugverhalten bemängelt wurde, sich im Experiment bei definierten Verhältnissen keineswegs so verhielten.»&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Dass die Flugbahn eines Fussballs ohnehin eine komplexe und mitunter, gemäss Theorie der Aerodynamik auch chaotische Angelegenheit ist, machen sich die wahren Könner zu nutze. Denn anders als ein stromlinienförmiges Geschoss, das eine perfekte Parabel beschreibt, verformt sich der Ball, beispielsweise wenn ihn der Spieler tritt. «Die Deformation durch den auftreffenden Fuss gibt dem Ball zunächst eine etwas wabbelige Bewegung», erklärt Camenzind. Gute Spieler machten sich diesen Effekt zu Nutze, nach dem Motto «bend it like Beckham». Hierbei handele es sich jedoch eigentlich nicht um Zauberkunst, sondern um akkurat angewandte Physik. Und die muss gut einstudiert sein, denn sobald der Fuss wenige Millisekunden am Ball ist, kann der Spieler seine Bewegung nicht mehr willentlich beeinflussen. Die Zeit reicht einfach nicht aus, um Nervenimpulse vom Fuss bis ins Gehirn zu leiten und ein taktisch ausgefeiltes Feedback an die Muskulatur des Spielers zu senden. Und so muss in der Kürze des Schusses die Physik von Fuss und Ball perfekt sitzen. Bälle von gleichbleibender Qualität tragen dazu bei, dass dies gelingt.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Martin Camenzind Laboratory for Biomimetic Membranes and Textiles Tel. +41 58 765 7342 martin.camenzind@empa.ch Redaktion /Medienkontakt Dr. Andrea Six Kommunikation Tel. +41 58 765 61 33 redaktion@empa.ch</contact>
      <attachment id="178079">
        <title>Empa-Forscher untersuchen Turnier-Fussbälle – auch für die WM 2018 in Russland.D</title>
        <format>jpg</format>
        <size-kb>6323</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/52508.jpg</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <link id="178081">
        <title>Empa-Medienmitteilung</title>
        <uri>https://www.empa.ch/web/s604/fussball-wm-2018</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Dübendorf, St. Gallen und Thun</city>
      <title>Pour que Ronaldo et Cie. puissent opérer leur magie</title>
      <lead>Le ballon officiel de la Coupe du Monde de la FIFA 2018 en Russie a reçu le "OK" de l'Empa après de nombreux tests. Certains gardiens de but peuvent être critiques à l'égard de ses caractéristiques de vol, mais la raison de leurs critiques devrait se trouver ailleurs - l'apparence plutôt peu conventionnelle du nouveau ballon.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Le football vit d'émotions. En ce qui concerne le ballon de la Coupe du monde de cette année, les experts de l'Empa sont peu critiques. Interrogés sur leur impression des caractéristiques de vol du modèle Adidas "Telstar 18", qui ont déjà fait l'objet de nombreuses critiques : "Les impressions sont subjectives", déclare Martin Camenzind du "Laboratoire des Membranes et Textiles Biomimétiques". "Nous nous appuyons sur des paramètres objectifs qui caractérisent le Telstar 18." Que des critiques comme les gardiens de but espagnols David De Gea et Pepe Reina ou le gardien de but allemand Mark-Andre ter Stegen accusent le ballon de " flottant " n'est donc guère impressionnant pour Camenzind. Dans tous les cas, le Telstar 18 a passé avec succès la série de tests spécialement développés à l'Empa à Saint-Gall pour les ballons de football officiels, et c'est ce qui compte pour le chercheur de l'Empa.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Depuis 22 ans, l'Empa réalise pour le compte de la FIFA la série incorruptible de tests sur les ballons de football en vue d'obtenir le label de qualité du programme de qualité de la FIFA. Toutes les balles ne réussissent pas le test. Ce n'est pas seulement la circonférence et le poids de la balle qui sont mesurés ici. De plus, bien qu'il soit pressé 250 fois dans un réservoir d'eau, il ne doit absorber qu'une quantité minimale de liquide, doit être capable de retenir son air et toujours rebondir à la même hauteur lorsqu'il est lâché d'une hauteur de deux mètres. Pour prouver qu'il s'agit d'une balle parfaite, la balle est également mesurée à pas moins de 4000 points. Et enfin, cette balle doit conserver sa forme même si elle a été tirée contre un mur d'acier 2000 fois à 50 kilomètres à l'heure.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Ces normes déterminent également la qualité et l'uniformité du sport. Lors de l'introduction de la série d'essais, tous les fabricants n'ont pas réussi à obtenir les propriétés requises : "Les spécimens ont échoué à maintes reprises", se souvient Camenzind. Certaines balles en cuir auraient augmenté considérablement en taille après l'intervention ou auraient absorbé trop d'eau. Les balles d'aujourd'hui sont collées ou soudées, car les coutures peuvent céder avec le temps. De même, la plupart des cuirs traditionnels ont cédé la place aux plastiques, dont la surface est spécifiquement texturée, ce qui devrait permettre de guider la balle plus facilement, surtout lorsqu'elle est mouillée sur le terrain.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;La physique appliquée à défaut de de la magie&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Et c'est précisément cette surface qui est responsable du vol imprévisible de la balle, rapportent les critiques. Telstar 18 est une copie étrange et voltigeante, revendiquent les gardiens de but des différentes équipes de la Coupe du Monde qui ont déjà été autorisés à tester le ballon. Mais Camenzind a répondu : "L'optique entre aussi en jeu ici", explique l'ingénieur. Telstar 18 n'est pas constitué d'hexagones et de pentagones traditionnels, mais d'éléments irréguliers aux empreintes asymétriques. Ainsi, la boule volante peut être un spectacle assez inhabituel dans des conditions d'éclairage appropriées. "Dans une étude avec un pied contrôlé par ordinateur, nous avons pu démontrer que les balles, réputéesd’un comportement de vol flottant, ne l’étaient pas dans l'expérience dans des conditions définies.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Le fait que la trajectoire d'un ballon de football est de toute façon complexe et parfois chaotique, selon la théorie de l'aérodynamique, est expliquée par de vrais experts. Contrairement à un projectile aérodynamique qui décrit une trajectoire parabolique parfaite, la balle se déforme, par exemple lorsque le joueur tire. "La déformation causée par l'impact du pied donne d'abord à la balle un mouvement quelque peu bancal ", explique Camenzind. Les bons joueurs ont profité de cet effet, selon la devise "Bend it like Beckham". Cependant, ce n'est pas vraiment une question de magie, mais de physique appliquée avec précision. Et cela doit être bien répété, car dès que le pied est sur la balle pendant quelques millisecondes, le joueur ne peut plus influencer délibérément son mouvement. Il n'y a tout simplement pas assez de temps pour diriger les impulsions nerveuses du pied vers le cerveau et pour envoyer une rétroaction tactiquement sophistiquée aux muscles du joueur. Et ainsi, dans la brièveté du tir, la physique du pied et de la balle doit s'adapter parfaitement. Des balles de qualité constante contribuent à la magie du football.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Martin Camenzind Laboratory for Biomimetic Membranes and Textiles Tél. +41 58 765 7342 martin.camenzind@empa.ch Rédaction/ Contact Medias Dr. Andrea Six Communication Tél +41 58 765 61 33 redaktion@empa.ch</contact>
      <attachment id="178079">
        <title>Empa-Forscher untersuchen Turnier-Fussbälle – auch für die WM 2018 in Russland.D</title>
        <format>jpg</format>
        <size-kb>6323</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/52508.jpg</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <link id="178081">
        <title>Empa-Medienmitteilung</title>
        <uri>https://www.empa.ch/web/s604/fussball-wm-2018</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Dübendorf, St. Gallen und Thun</city>
      <title>So that Ronaldo and Co. can perform their magic</title>
      <lead>The official ball for the 2018 FIFA World Cup in Russia has received Empa's «stamp of approval» after numerous rigorous tests. Some goalkeepers had been critical of its flight characteristics, but the reason for this may lie somewhere else – the rather unconventional appearance of the new ball.</lead>
      <text link="no">Football lives on emotions. When it comes to this year's FIFA World Cup ball, however, Empa's experts are completely unemotional. When asked about their impression of the flight characteristics of the Adidas model «Telstar 18», which had already been criticized after initial test matches: «Impressions are subjective,» says Martin Camenzind of the «Laboratory for Biomimetic Membranes and Textiles». «We rely on objective parameters to characterize the Telstar 18.“ Remarks by Spain’s goalkeepers David De Gea and Pepe Reina or the German goalie Mark-Andre ter Stegen that the ball is «fluttering» is, therefore, hardly impressive for Camenzind. In any case, the Telstar 18 has successfully passed the test series that was specially developed by Empa experts in St. Gallen for official tournament footballs – and that's all that matters to the Empa researcher. On behalf of FIFA, Empa has been conducting the incorruptible series of tests on footballs striving for the FIFA quality program's seal of approval for 22 years. Not every ball passes the test. It is not only the circumference and weight of the ball that are measured precisely. In addition, despite being crushed 250 times in a water tank, it may only absorb a minimal amount of liquid, must be able to hold its air and always jump off at the same height when it impacts from a height of two meters. To prove that it is a perfect sphere, the ball is also measured at no less than 4’000 points. And finally, the ball must retain its shape even if shot against a steel wall 2’000 times at 50 kilometers per hour. Such standards also determine the quality and consistency of the sport. When the test series were introduced, not all manufacturers succeeded in achieving the required properties: «Time and again, specimens failed, » recalls Camenzind. Some leather balls had increased in size considerably after the procedure or absorbed too much water. Today's balls are glued or welded, because traditional seams could give way over time. Likewise, most of the traditional leather has given way to plastics, the surface of which is specifically textured, which should enable the ball to be guided more easily, especially when the field is wet. Applied physics instead of magic And it is precisely this surface that is responsible for the unpredictable flight of the ball, critics report. Telstar 18 is a strange, fluttering copy, claim goalkeepers of various World Cup teams who have already been allowed to test the ball. But Camenzind counters: «Optics also comes into play here. » Telstar 18 is not made up of the traditional hexagons and pentagons, but of irregular elements with asymmetrical prints. Thus, the flying ball can be quite an unusual sight under appropriate lighting conditions. «In a study with a computer-controlled foot, we were able to show that balls accused of fluttering flight behavior behaved by no means like this in experiments under defined conditions. » The fact that the trajectory of a football is a complex and, according to the theory of aerodynamics, sometimes chaotic matter is taken advantage of by professional players. Unlike a streamlined projectile that describes a perfect parabola, the ball deforms, for example when the player kicks it. «The deformation caused by the impacting foot initially gives the ball a somewhat wobbly movement, » explains Camenzind. Experienced players take advantage of this effect and „bend it like Beckham“. However, this is not actually a matter of magic, but of applied physics. And this must be perfectly well rehearsed, because as soon as the foot is on the ball for a few milliseconds, the player can no longer deliberately influence his movement. There is simply not enough time to direct nerve impulses from the foot to the brain and to send tactically sophisticated feedback to the muscles of the player. And so, in the brevity of the shot, the physics of foot and ball must fit perfectly. It is thus balls of consistent quality that allow us to enjoy so many memorable magic moments on the field. </text>
      <contact>Martin Camenzind Laboratory for Biomimetic Membranes and Textiles Phone +41 58 765 7342 martin.camenzind@empa.ch Media Contact Media Contact Dr. Andrea Six Communication Phone +41 58 765 61 33 redaktion@empa.ch</contact>
      <attachment id="178079">
        <title>Empa-Forscher untersuchen Turnier-Fussbälle – auch für die WM 2018 in Russland.D</title>
        <format>jpg</format>
        <size-kb>6323</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/52508.jpg</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <link id="178081">
        <title>Empa-Medienmitteilung</title>
        <uri>https://www.empa.ch/web/s604/fussball-wm-2018</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="8">
        <name lang="de">Bildung und Forschung</name>
        <name lang="fr">Formation et recherche</name>
        <name lang="it">Formazione e ricerca</name>
        <name lang="en">Education and Research</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="42">
        <name lang="de">Sport</name>
        <name lang="fr">Sport</name>
        <name lang="it">Sport</name>
        <name lang="en">Sport</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
