<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="71953" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2018-08-27</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="324" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>301</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Swissmedic, Schweizerisches Heilmittelinstitut</name>
      <name lang="fr">Swissmedic, Institut suisse des produits thérapeutiques</name>
      <name lang="it">Swissmedic, Istituto svizzero per gli agenti terapeutici</name>
      <name lang="en">Swiss Agency for Therapeutic Products</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.swissmedic.ch/</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.swissmedic.ch/?lang=3</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.swissmedic.ch/?lang=4</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.swissmedic.ch/?lang=2</www>
      <email lang="de"/>
      <email lang="fr"/>
      <email lang="it"/>
      <email lang="en"/>
    </originator>
    <department id="301">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement des Innern</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'intérieur</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'interno</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Home Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Überprüfung von Arzneimitteln mit Valsartan: Erste Analyseergebnisse liegen vor</title>
      <lead>Nach den Valsartan-Rückrufen in der Schweiz und in anderen Ländern wird der Grad der Verunreinigung in Arzneimitteln und Wirkstoffen untersucht. Aus der Schweiz liegen erste Ergebnisse des Swissmedic-eigenen Labors vor: Auf dem Schweizer Markt zugelassene und aktuell erhältliche Valsartan-Präparate entsprechen gemäss diesen Untersuchungen den Anforderungen.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Anfang Juli wurden weltweit Chargen von Blutdrucksenkern mit dem Wirkstoff Valsartan, der mit N-Nitrosodimethylamin (NDMA) in erhöhter Konzentration verunreinigt war, vorsorglich zurückgerufen. Diese Chargen sind in der Schweiz mittlerweile aus dem Verkauf genommen. Nach den Rückrufen begannen Behörden und Hersteller zu untersuchen, welche weiteren Präparate möglicherweise betroffen sind.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Swissmedic hat dafür Muster der nicht vom Rückruf betroffenen Valsartan-haltigen Medikamente, die aktuell in der Schweiz zugelassen und erhältlich sind, angefordert. Im Swissmedic-eigenen Labor wurde überprüft, ob diese Fertigarzneimittel den Anforderungen entsprechen.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Aktuell auf dem Schweizer Markt verfügbare Valsartan-Präparate sind unbedenklich&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Für die nicht vom Rückzug betroffenen Präparate mit dem Wirkstoff Valsartan liegen jetzt die Ergebnisse des akkreditierten Swissmedic Labors (OMCL) vor: In den geprüften Chargen der Medikamente mit Valsartan auf dem Schweizer Markt konnten keine erhöhten NDMA-Werte nachgewiesen werden.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Swissmedic schafft Sicherheit durch Transparenz&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Das Swissmedic Labor prüft in den nächsten Wochen weitere Arzneimittel, die andere Sartane beinhalten. Ausserdem sollen neue Chargen von Valsartan-Präparaten, die für den Schweizer Markt bestimmt sind, analysiert werden. Das Institut wird deshalb die Firmen auffordern, bis auf weiteres von jeder neuen Charge, die für den Verkauf in der Schweiz vorgesehen ist, Muster an Swissmedic zu senden.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sobald Ergebnisse vorliegen, wird Swissmedic eine Liste der Präparate und Chargen, die durch das Labor analysiert wurden, publizieren. Sollten die gefundenen NDMA-Werte über der Unbedenklichkeitsgrenze von 300 ppb liegen, wird die entsprechende Charge vom Schweizer Markt zurückgerufen.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Weiter werden auch die zurückgerufenen Chargen geprüft, um den tatsächlichen Gehalt an NDMA in den entsprechenden Präparaten zu klären (der Rückruf erfolgte aufgrund von Analysen der Firmen).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Die Publikation der Präparate und Chargen, bei denen die Unbedenklichkeitsgrenze nicht überschritten wird und die somit ohne Bedenken eingenommen werden können, soll Transparenz über die aktuelle Situation schaffen.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Swissmedic Medienstelle Telefon +41 58 462 02 76 media@swissmedic.ch</contact>
      <link id="180534">
        <title>Liste der Rückrufe Valsartan-haltiger Arzneimittel</title>
        <uri>https://www.swissmedic.ch/swissmedic/de/home/news/mitteilungen/valsartane-recall-update-productoverview.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Examen de médicaments à base de valsartan : les premiers résultats d’analyse sont disponibles</title>
      <lead>Après les rappels de valsartan en Suisse et dans d’autres pays, des médicaments et principes actifs sont en cours d’analyse afin de déterminer leur degré d’impureté. Pour la Suisse, le laboratoire de Swissmedic a livré de premiers résultats: selon ces analyses, les préparations de valsartan autorisées et actuellement disponibles sur le marché suisse répondent aux exigences applicables.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Début juillet, des lots d’antihypertenseurs contenant du valsartan contaminé par des concentrations élevées de N-nitrosodiméthylamine (NDMA) ont été rappelés dans le monde entier à titre préventif. En Suisse, ces lots ont été retirés de la vente. Après les rappels de lots, autorités et fabricants ont commencé à réaliser des analyses pour identifier les autres préparations susceptibles d’être concernées.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Dans ce cadre, Swissmedic a demandé à ce qu’on lui fournisse des échantillons des médicaments à base de valsartan qui sont actuellement sur le marché suisse, mais n’étaient pas concernés par les rappels. Le laboratoire de Swissmedic a ensuite contrôlé si ces médicaments prêts à l’emploi répondent aux exigences applicables.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Les préparations à base de valsartan disponibles à ce jour sur le marché suisse sont sans danger&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Les résultats des analyses pratiquées par le laboratoire accrédité de Swissmedic (OMCL) pour les préparations à base de valsartan qui n’étaient pas concernées par le rappel sont désormais disponibles: aucun taux élevé de NDMA n’a pu être détecté dans les lots contrôlés des médicaments à base de valsartan disponibles sur le marché helvétique.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Swissmedic garantit la transparence pour plus de sécurité&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Au cours des prochaines semaines, le laboratoire de Swissmedic contrôlera divers médicaments à base d'autres sartans. De plus, il prévoit d’analyser de nouveaux lots de préparations à base de valsartan qui sont destinés au marché suisse. Swissmedic exigera donc que jusqu’à nouvel ordre, les entreprises lui soumettent des échantillons de tout nouveau lot contenant du valsartan qui est destiné à la vente en Suisse.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Dès que les résultats seront disponibles, Swissmedic publiera une liste des préparations et des lots analysés par son laboratoire. Si le taux de NDMA relevé est supérieur à la limite d’innocuité de 300 ppb, le lot correspondant sera retiré du marché suisse.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;De plus, les lots rappelés à titre préventif seront aussi analysés afin de clarifier la teneur effective en NDMA des préparations correspondantes – le rappel ayant eu lieu sur la base d’analyses réalisées par les entreprises.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;La publication des préparations et des lots pour lesquels la limite d’innocuité n’est pas dépassée et qui peuvent donc être utilisés sans inquiétude a pour objectif de créer de la transparence quant à la situation actuelle.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Swissmedic Service de presse tél. +41 58 462 02 76 media@swissmedic.ch</contact>
      <link id="180535">
        <title>Valsartan - Aperçu des préparations et des lots touchés par le rappel</title>
        <uri>https://www.swissmedic.ch/swissmedic/fr/home/news/mitteilungen/valsartane-recall-update-productoverview.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Verifica dei medicamenti contenenti Valsartan: disponibili i primi risultati delle analisi</title>
      <lead>Dopo i richiami di partite contenenti Valsartan in Svizzera e in altri Paesi, si procede a esaminare il grado di contaminazione di medicamenti e principi attivi. Dalla Svizzera giungono i primi risultati delle analisi effettuate nel laboratorio interno di Swissmedic: I preparati con Valsartan omologati e attualmente disponibili sul mercato svizzero rispondono ai requisiti secondo le presenti indagini.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;All’inizio di luglio sono state ritirate in tutto il mondo, in via precauzionale, partite di medicamenti antipertensivi contenenti il principio attivo Valsartan che era stato contaminato da concentrazioni elevate di N-nitrosodimetilammina (NDMA). Nel frattempo, queste partite di prodotti sono state ritirate dalla vendita in Svizzera. In seguito a tali richiami, autorità e fabbricanti hanno iniziato a effettuare indagini per accertare se altri preparati potessero essere stati contaminati.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Swissmedic ha pertanto richiesto campioni dei medicamenti a base di Valsartan non inclusi nel richiamo e che attualmente sono disponibili sul mercato svizzero. Nel laboratorio interno di Swissmedic sono state effettuate analisi per accertare se questi medicamenti pronti per l’uso sono conformi ai requisiti previsti.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3&gt;I preparati a base di Valsartan attualmente disponibili sul mercato svizzero non sono pericolosi per la salute&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Per i preparati contenenti il principio attivo Valsartan non inclusi nel richiamo, ora sono disponibili i risultati del laboratorio accreditato di Swissmedic (OMCL): nelle partite esaminate di medicamenti contenenti Valsartan presenti sul mercato svizzero non è stato riscontrato un aumento dei valori di NDMA.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Swissmedic crea sicurezza con la trasparenza&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Nel corso delle prossime settimane il laboratorio di Swissmedic passerà al vaglio altri medicamenti che contengono i sartani. Inoltre, saranno analizzate nuove partite di preparati con Valsartan che sono destinate al mercato svizzero. Swissmedic ha pertanto richiesto campioni ai titolari delle omologazioni ed esigerà inoltre dalle aziende che le spediscano, fino a nuova disposizione, campioni di ogni nuova partita di medicamenti a base di Valsartan destinata alla vendita in Svizzera.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Non appena i risultati saranno disponibili, Swissmedic pubblicherà un elenco dei preparati e delle partite analizzate nel suo laboratorio. Qualora i valori di NDMA rilevati dovessero attestarsi al di sopra della soglia di sicurezza fissata a 300 ppb, la partita in questione sarà richiamata dal mercato svizzero.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Anche le partite richiamate dal mercato vengono esaminate per accertare il tenore effettivo di NDMA nei relativi preparati (il richiamo è avvenuto a seguito di analisi condotte dalle aziende).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;La pubblicazione dei preparati e delle partite di medicamenti in cui la soglia di sicurezza non è stata superata e che quindi possono essere assunti senza problemi dovrà servire a creare trasparenza sulla situazione attuale.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Swissmedic Servizio stampa tel. +41 58 462 02 76 media@swissmedic.ch</contact>
      <link id="180536">
        <title>Valsartan - Panoramica delle partite e dei preparati interessati dal richiamo</title>
        <uri>https://www.swissmedic.ch/swissmedic/it/home/news/mitteilungen/valsartane-recall-update-productoverview.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Investigation of medicinal products containing valsartan: First analytical results now available</title>
      <lead>Following the valsartan recalls in Switzerland and other countries, the extent of this impurity in medicines and active substances is under investigation. In Switzerland, the first results from Swissmedic's own laboratory are now available: According to these investigations, valsartan preparations approved for sale in Switzerland and currently obtainable on the Swiss market are compliant.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;At the start of July, batches of antihypertensive medicines containing the active substance valsartan and contaminated with elevated concentrations of N-nitrosodimethylamine (NDMA) were recalled worldwide as a precautionary measure. These batches have since between withdrawn from sale in Switzerland. Following the recalls, authorities and manufacturers started investigating whether other preparations might also be affected.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;To this end, Swissmedic has asked for samples of valsartan-containing medicinal products that are not affected by the recall and that are still on the market in Switzerland. Swissmedic's own laboratory has checked whether these products satisfy the requirements.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Valsartan preparations currently available on the Swiss market are safe&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;The results of the accredited Swissmedic laboratory (OMCL) for those preparations containing valsartan that are not affected by the recall are now available: No increased levels of NDMA were detected in the tested batches of medicinal products containing valsartan on the Swiss market.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Swissmedic ensures safety through transparency&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;In the coming weeks, the Swissmedic laboratory will be testing other medicinal products containing sartans. New batches of valsartan preparations intended for the Swiss market will also be analysed. Swissmedic has therefore requested samples from the authorisation holders, and will also ask the companies to keep sending samples from every new batch of valsartan intended for sale in Switzerland until further notice.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As soon as results are available, Swissmedic will publish a list of preparations and batches that were analysed by the laboratory. If the resulting NDMA levels are above the safety limit of 300 ppb, the corresponding batch will be withdrawn from the Swiss market.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The batches that are recalled as a precaution will also be tested to determine the actual content of NDMA in the corresponding preparations (the recall was based on analyses carried out by companies).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The publication of the preparations and batches for which the safety limit is not exceeded, and can thus be administered without any concerns, is designed to create transparency about the current situation.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Swissmedic Media Unit phone +41 58 462 02 76 media@swissmedic.ch</contact>
      <link id="180537">
        <title>Valsartan - Overview of batches affected by recall</title>
        <uri>https://www.swissmedic.ch/swissmedic/en/home/news/mitteilungen/valsartane-recall-update-productoverview.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="15">
        <name lang="de">Gesundheit</name>
        <name lang="fr">Santé</name>
        <name lang="it">sanità</name>
        <name lang="en">Health</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
