<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="72047" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2018-09-05</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="1070" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>1070</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Der Bundesrat</name>
      <name lang="fr">Conseil fédéral</name>
      <name lang="it">Il Consiglio federale</name>
      <name lang="en">The Federal Council</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.admin.ch/gov/de/start.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.admin.ch/gov/fr/accueil.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.admin.ch/gov/it/pagina-iniziale.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.admin.ch/gov/en/start.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="yes" id="606" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>601</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössische Zollverwaltung</name>
      <name lang="fr">Administration fédérale des douanes</name>
      <name lang="it">Amministrazione federale delle dogane</name>
      <name lang="en">The Federal Customs Administration</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.ezv.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.ezv.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.ezv.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.ezv.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">ozd.zentrale@ezv.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">ozd.zentrale@ezv.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">ozd.zentrale@ezv.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">ozd.zentrale@ezv.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="1070">
      <name lang="de">Der Bundesrat</name>
      <name lang="fr">Conseil fédéral</name>
      <name lang="it">Il Consiglio federale</name>
      <name lang="en">The Federal Council</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.admin.ch/gov/de/start.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.admin.ch/gov/fr/accueil.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.admin.ch/gov/it/pagina-iniziale.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.admin.ch/gov/en/start.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <department id="601">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Finanzdepartement</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des finances</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale delle finanze</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Finance</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.efd.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.dff.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.efd.admin.ch/efd/it/home.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.efd.admin.ch/efd/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Bundesrat für Amtshilfe im Zollbereich mit den USA</title>
      <lead>Der Bundesrat hat an seiner Sitzung vom 5. September 2018 von den Ergebnissen des Vernehmlassungsverfahrens zu einem Amtshilfeabkommen im Zollbereich mit den USA Kenntnis genommen. Er beschloss, die Verhandlungen über das Abkommen weiterzuführen, sofern die Aussenpolitischen Kommissionen der Bundesversammlung dem zustimmen. </lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Im Jahr 2017 wurde ein Vernehmlassungsverfahren zum Entwurf eines Amtshilfeabkommens im Zollbereich mit den USA durchgeführt. An seiner Sitzung vom 5. September 2018 hat der Bundesrat von den Ergebnissen Kenntnis genommen und das weitere Vorgehen beschlossen. Der Abkommensentwurf in der vorliegenden Form wird von der Mehrheit der Wirtschaftsverbände und von sieben Kantonen abgelehnt oder zumindest kritisch beurteilt. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Fortführung der Verhandlungen&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Der Bundesrat hat dennoch beschlossen, die Verhandlungen fortzuführen, sofern die Aussenpolitischen Kommissionen einem angepassten Verhandlungsmandat zustimmen. Er liess sich dabei von folgenden Überlegungen leiten: Sichere Lieferketten sind für den internationalen Warenverkehr sehr wichtig. Solche Lieferketten sind mit Kontrollen verbunden, es sei denn, zwischen den einzelnen Staaten bestehen Abkommen über die gegenseitige Anerkennung zollrechtlicher Sicherheitsmassnahmen, die Erleichterungen bei den Kontrollen vorsehen. Sowohl die Schweiz als auch die USA kennen solche Massnahmen (zugelassener Wirtschaftsbeteiligter beziehungsweise Customs-Trade Partnership against Terrorism). &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ein entsprechendes Abkommen zwischen der Schweiz und den USA besteht heute nicht und wird aktuell auch nicht als erforderlich angesehen. Aus der Sicht der USA kommt ein Abkommen über die gegenseitige Anerkennung zollrechtlicher Sicherheitsmassnahmen aber nur in Frage, wenn auch ein Amtshilfeabkommen im Zollbereich besteht. Um die langfristige Möglichkeit von Verhandlungen betreffend einem Abkommen über die gegenseitige Anerkennung zollrechtlicher Sicherheitsmassnahmen wahren zu können, erachtet es der Bundesrat als wichtig, die Verhandlungen hinsichtlich eines Amtshilfeabkommens im Zollbereich fortzuführen. Im Rahmen der weiteren Verhandlungen sollen Verbesserungen am Abkommenstext im Sinne der Stellungnahmen der Vernehmlassungsteilnehmer erreicht werden.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>David Marquis, stv. Leiter Kommunikation, Eidgenössische Zollverwaltung EZV Tel. 058 462 67 43, medien@ezv.admin.ch</contact>
      <attachment id="180858">
        <title>Ergebnisbericht Vernehmlassung</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>525</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/53533.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Le Conseil fédéral favorable à l'assistance administrative en matière douanière avec les États-Unis</title>
      <lead>Lors de sa séance du 5 septembre 2018, le Conseil fédéral a pris connaissance des résultats de la procédure de consultation concernant un accord d'assistance administrative en matière douanière avec les États-Unis. Il a décidé de poursuivre les négociations sur l'accord pour autant que les Commissions de politique extérieure de l’Assemblée fédérale l'approuvent. </lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;En 2017, une procédure de consultation concernant un projet d'accord d'assistance administrative en matière douanière avec les États-Unis a été menée. Lors de sa séance du 5 septembre 2018, le Conseil fédéral a pris connaissance des résultats et a défini les étapes suivantes. La majorité des associations économiques et sept cantons rejettent le projet d'accord sous sa forme actuelle ou le jugent pour le moins de manière critique. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Poursuite des négociations&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Le Conseil fédéral a cependant décidé de poursuivre les négociations si les Commissions de politique extérieure approuvent un mandat de négociation adapté. Il s'appuie en l'occurrence sur les réflexions suivantes: des chaînes logistiques sûres sont très importantes pour les échanges internationaux de marchandises. Ces chaînes logistiques imposent des contrôles, même s'il existe entre les différents États des accords sur la reconnaissance mutuelle de mesures de sécurité dans le domaine douanier qui prévoient des allégements en matière de contrôles. La Suisse comme les États-Unis connaissent ce genre de mesures (opérateur économique agréé et &lt;i&gt;Customs-Trade Partnership against Terrorism &lt;/i&gt;[partenariat douanier et économique contre le terrorisme]). &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Un accord correspondant entre la Suisse et les États-Unis n'existe pas aujourd'hui et n'apparaît pas nécessaire actuellement. De l'avis des États-Unis, un accord sur la reconnaissance mutuelle de mesures de sécurité dans le domaine douanier n'entre en ligne de compte que s'il existe un accord d'assistance administrative en matière douanière. Pour conserver à long terme la possibilité de négocier un accord sur la reconnaissance mutuelle de mesures de sécurité dans le domaine douanier, le Conseil fédéral estime important de poursuivre les négociations sur un accord d'assistance administrative en matière douanière. Dans le cadre des négociations ultérieures, des améliorations devront être apportées au texte de l'accord pour tenir compte des avis des participants à la consultation. &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>David Marquis, suppléant du responsable de la communication, Administration fédérale des douanes AFD no tél. 058 462 67 43, medien@ezv.admin.ch</contact>
      <attachment id="180859">
        <title>Rapport sur les résultats de la consultation</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>587</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/53534.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Il Consiglio federale è favorevole all’assistenza amministrativa in ambito doganale con gli Stati Uniti</title>
      <lead>In occasione della sua seduta del 5 settembre 2018, il Consiglio federale ha preso atto dei risultati della procedura di consultazione concernente l’Accordo di assistenza amministrativa in ambito doganale con gli Stati Uniti. Esso ha deciso di proseguire i negoziati riguardanti l’Accordo, a condizione che le Commissioni della politica estera dell’Assemblea federale siano favorevoli.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Nel 2017 è stata svolta una procedura di consultazione in merito allʼavamprogetto di Accordo di assistenza amministrativa in ambito doganale con gli Stati Uniti. In occasione della sua seduta del 5 settembre 2018, il Consiglio federale ha preso atto dei risultati e definito l’ulteriore modo di procedere. La maggioranza delle associazioni economiche e sette Cantoni respingono l’avamprogetto nella forma attuale o si esprimono perlomeno in modo critico.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2&gt;Proseguimento dei negoziati&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;Ciononostante, il Consiglio federale ha deciso di proseguire i negoziati, a condizione che le Commissioni della politica estera siano favorevoli a un adeguamento del mandato negoziale. Tale decisione è stata presa sulla base delle seguenti considerazioni: per il traffico internazionale di merci è molto importante che vi siano catene di fornitura sicure. Ciò comporta dei controlli, tranne che tra i singoli Stati vi siano accordi sul riconoscimento reciproco delle misure doganali di sicurezza, i quali prevedono agevolazioni nell’ambito dei controlli. Sia la Svizzera sia gli Stati Uniti conoscono questo tipo di misure (operatore economico autorizzato e Customs-Trade Partnership Against Terrorism [partenariato doganale-commerciale contro il terrorismo]). &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Attualmente non esiste un simile accordo tra Svizzera e Stati Uniti né è considerato necessario. Da parte degli Stati Uniti, un accordo sul riconoscimento reciproco delle misure doganali di sicurezza entra in considerazione soltanto in collegamento con un accordo di assistenza amministrativa in ambito doganale. Al fine di garantire la possibilità di negoziazione a lungo termine per quanto riguarda un accordo sul riconoscimento reciproco delle misure doganali di sicurezza, il Consiglio federale ritiene importante continuare i negoziati relativi a un accordo di assistenza amministrativa in ambito doganale. Nel quadro degli ulteriori negoziati occorre migliorare il testo dell’accordo sulla base dei pareri espressi dai partecipanti alla consultazione.&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>David Marquis, sostituto del capo della Comunicazione Amministrazione federale delle dogane AFD Tel. 058 462 67 43, medien@ezv.admin.ch</contact>
      <attachment id="180860">
        <title>Rapporto sui risultati della consultazione</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>684</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/53535.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Federal Council for administrative assistance in customs area with US</title>
      <lead>During its meeting on 5 September 2018, the Federal Council took note of the results of the consultation procedure on an administrative assistance agreement in the customs area with the US. It decided to continue the negotiations on the agreement provided the Foreign Affairs Committees of the Federal Assembly agree.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;A consultation was carried out on a draft mutual administrative assistance agreement in the customs area with the US in 2017. The Federal Council took note of the results and decided on the next steps during its meeting on 5 September 2018. The draft agreement in its present form is rejected or at least viewed critically by most business associations and seven cantons.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2&gt;Continuation of negotiations&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;The Federal Council has nevertheless decided to continue the negotiations provided the Foreign Affairs Committees agree to an adjusted negotiation mandate. In doing so, it was guided by the following considerations: secure supply chains are very important for the international movement of goods. Such supply chains are associated with controls unless there are agreements between the individual states on the mutual recognition of customs security measures which provide for simpler controls. Both Switzerland and the US are familiar with such measures (authorised economic operator or Customs-Trade Partnership Against Terrorism).&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;A corresponding agreement between Switzerland and the US does not exist at present and is not currently considered necessary. From the US perspective, however, an agreement on the mutual recognition of customs security measures is worth considering only if there is also an administrative assistance agreement in the customs area. The Federal Council believes it is important to continue the negotiations on an administrative assistance agreement in the customs area in order to safeguard the long-term possibility of negotiations on an agreement on the mutual recognition of customs security measures. As part of the further negotiations, improvements are to be made to the text of the agreement in line with the opinions of the consultation participants.&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>David Marquis, Deputy Head of Communications, Federal Customs Administration FCA Tel. 058 462 67 43, medien@ezv.admin.ch</contact>
      <attachment id="180858">
        <title>Ergebnisbericht Vernehmlassung</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>525</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/53533.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <keywords>
      <keyword id="184" org-id="606">
        <name lang="de">Zollverfahren</name>
        <name lang="fr">Procédure douanière</name>
        <name lang="it">Operazioni doganali</name>
        <name lang="en">Customs procedure</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="215" org-id="606">
        <name lang="de">Zoll</name>
        <name lang="fr">Douane</name>
        <name lang="it">Dogana</name>
        <name lang="en">Customs</name>
      </keyword>
    </keywords>
    <topics>
      <topic id="10">
        <name lang="de">Bundesrat</name>
        <name lang="fr">Conseil fédéral</name>
        <name lang="it">Consiglio federale</name>
        <name lang="en">Federal Council</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="47">
        <name lang="de">Wirtschaft</name>
        <name lang="fr">Économie</name>
        <name lang="it">Economia</name>
        <name lang="en">Economic Affairs</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="48">
        <name lang="de">Zoll</name>
        <name lang="fr">Douanes</name>
        <name lang="it">Dogane</name>
        <name lang="en">Customs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
