<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="72415" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2018-10-04</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="323" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>701</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidg. Materialprüfungs- und Forschungsanstalt</name>
      <name lang="fr">Laboratoire fédéral d'essai des matériaux et de recherche</name>
      <name lang="it">Laboratorio federale di prova dei materiali e di ricerca</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Laboratory for Materials Testing and Research</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.empa.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.empa.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.empa.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.empa.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">contact@empa.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">contact@empa.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">contact@empa.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">contact@empa.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="701">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Wirtschaft, Bildung und Forschung</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'économie, de la formation et de la recherche</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'economia, della formazione e della ricerca</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Economic Affairs, Education and Research</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Dübendorf, St. Gallen und Thun</city>
      <title>Warum quillt und reisst Beton?</title>
      <lead>Wenn Brücken, Staumauern und Betonfundamente Risse entwickeln, dann ist oft AAR die Ursache: die Alkali-Aggregat-Reaktion. Sie lässt den Beton quellen und macht Sanierungen oder Neubauten nötig. Ein Projekt, das vom Schweizerischen Nationalfonds (SNF) gefördert und von der Empa koordiniert wird, untersucht die «Beton-Krankheit».</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Beton hält leider nicht ewig. Auch an Betonbauten in der Schweiz nagt der Zahn der Zeit. Betroffen sind nicht nur stahlbewehrte Konstruktionen wie Brücken, sondern auch Betonbauten ohne Bewehrung, wie Staumauern. Einer der Gründe dafür ist die sogenannte Alkali-Aggregat-Reaktion (AAR). Sie kann alle Betonbauten unter freiem Himmel betreffen. Bei der AAR sind die Zutaten des Betons selbst das Problem: Zement – der «Leim» des Betons – enthält Alkalimetalle wie Natrium und Kalium. Die Feuchtigkeit im Beton wird dadurch zu einer Lauge. Die Hauptbestandteile von Beton sind Sand und Kies. Diese wiederum bestehen unter anderem aus Silikaten, beispielsweise Quarz oder Feldspat. Mit diesen Silikaten reagiert nun das alkalische Wasser und führt zur Bildung von Alkali-Kalzium-Silikat-Hydrat. Dieses Mineral lagert mehr und mehr Wassermoleküle in seiner Struktur ein, dehnt sich dadurch aus und sprengt mit der Zeit den Beton von innen.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Bemerkenswert dabei: In zahlreichen Kieskörnern, die im Beton stecken, läuft die gleiche Reaktion ab; die Steinchen werden einzeln gesprengt. Der Druck, der durch diese Mikroreaktion auf ein ganzes Bauwerk ausgeübt werden kann, ist gewaltig: Eine Staumauer etwa kann sich um einige Dezimeter ausdehnen. Das kann zu Schäden an den seitlichen Anschlusspunkten zum Fels oder zu Verformungen im Bereich von Schleusen führen. Die Reaktion verläuft langsam, so dass bei betroffenen Bauwerken erst nach 10 bis 15 Jahren erste Schäden bemerkbar werden. Durch das kontinuierliche Quellen des Betons kann allerdings die Lebensdauer von Bauwerken stark verkürzt werden.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;2015 gelang es einem Team aus Wissenschaftlern der Empa und des Paul-Scherrer-Instituts (PSI) die Struktur des wasserhaltigen Kristalls, der das Quellen im Beton auslöst, erstmals zu identifizieren. Zuvor war die Struktur Gegenstand vieler Spekulationen gewesen.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Die Entdeckung war der Auslöser für ein interdisziplinäres Forschungsprojekt, das vom Schweizerischen Nationalfonds (SNF) finanziert wird. Beteiligt sind neben der Empa und dem PSI zwei Institute der EPFL; die Forschungsaktivitäten koordiniert der Empa-Forscher Andreas Leemann. «Wir wollen die AAR in allen Dimensionen untersuchen und verstehen, von der Atom-Ebene und der Längenskala im Angström-Bereich bis hin zu den Auswirkungen auf ganze Bauwerke in der Zentimeter- und Meterskala», erläutert Leemann.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Sechs Teilprojekte für alle Dimensionen&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Zu diesem Zweck wurden in dem SNF-Synergia-Projekt sechs Teilprojekte definiert: Das PSI untersucht mit Hilfe von Synchro­tron­strah­lung die Struktur der Reaktionsprodukte, um ihr Quellen erklären zu können. An der EPFL werden die massgebenden Rahmenbedingungen für das Auflösen der Silikate und die Zusammensetzung der anfänglich gebildeten Reaktionsprodukte untersucht; zudem werden mit Computersimulationen die Auswirkungen des Quellens auf Bauwerke erforscht. Und an der Empa wird einerseits die Entstehung der Risse im Beton räumlich und zeitaufgelöst mit Computer-Tomografie im Empa-Röntgenzentrum erfasst; andererseits werden die wasserhaltigen Kristalle im Labor synthetisiert. So können die Forscher grössere Mengen des Stoffs erhalten, der gewöhnlich in nano- bis mikrometerkleinen Rissen der Kieskörner steckt. Nur mit grösseren Mengen der fraglichen Substanz lassen sich jedoch physikalische Eigenschaften genau bestimmen. Die so gewonnenen Erkenntnisse sollen nicht nur dazu dienen, die AAR besser zu verstehen, sondern auch Wege aufzeigen, wie sich Schäden – und dadurch Kosten – vermeiden lassen.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;«Wir sind bereits mittendrin, das bislang nur in Teilen bekannte Phänomen zu entschlüsseln», so Leemann. Im Mai 2017 startete das vierjährige Forschungsprojekt. Erste Ergebnisse liegen bereits vor. Im nächsten Schritt geht es nun darum, die einzelnen Arbeitsgruppen stärker zu vernetzen und auf den Ergebnissen der Partnergruppen aufzubauen. So soll am Ende ein vollständiges Bild der AAR entstehen, das es erlaubt, den Zustand und die Gefährdung von Beton-Bauwerken besser abzuschätzen und das Schicksal der angegriffenen Bauten wissenschaftlich fundiert zu begleiten. &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Andreas Leemann Concrete / Construction Chemistry Tel. +41 58 765 44 89 Andreas.Leemann@empa.ch Redaktion / Medienkontakt: Rainer Klose Kommunikation Tel. +41 58 765 47 33 redaktion@empa.ch</contact>
      <link id="181902">
        <title>Empa-Medienmitteilung</title>
        <uri>https://www.empa.ch/web/s604/aar</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Dübendorf, St. Gallen und Thun</city>
      <title>A quoi sont dus le expansion et les fissures du béton?</title>
      <lead>Lorsque les ponts, les murs de soutènement et les fondations de béton se fissurent, la réaction al-calis-granulats, alias RAG, en est souvent la cause. Elle provoque un expansion du béton qui néces-site une remise en état, voire la reconstruction de l´ouvrage. Cette «maladie du béton» est l´objet d´un projet soutenu par le Fonds national suisse (FNS) et coordonné par l´Empa.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Le béton n´est malheureusement pas éternel. Avec le temps, il perd de ses qualités. On l´observe dans les ouvrages en béton armé, comme les ponts, mais aussi en béton non armé, comme les barrages. Fort souvent, c´est la RAG (réaction alcalis-granulats) qui est en cause. Elle concerne tous les travaux de béton à l´air libre. Le problème provient des ingrédients mêmes du béton: le ciment – «colle» du béton – contient des métaux alcalins tels le sodium et le potassium. A leur contact, l´humidité du béton se transforme en solution alcaline. Les principaux composants du béton sont le sable et le gravier qui comprennent des silicates tels que le quartz ou le feldspath. L´eau alcaline réagit avec les silicates pour former dusilicate dàlcalin et calcium hydraté. Ce minéral capte un nombre croissant de molécules d´eau, gonfle et, avec le temps, fait éclater le béton de l´intérieur.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Fait notable: cette réaction se produit également à l´intérieur de nombreux grains du gravier présent dans le béton, lesquels éclatent. La pression exercée par ces micro-réactions sur l´ensemble d´un ouvrage peut être considérable. Certains barrages peuvent se dilater d´un décimètre. Il peut en résulter des dommages aux points de raccord latéraux avec la roche ou des déformations dans les zones d´éclusage. La réaction prend son temps, les premiers dommages ne se font remarquer que dix à quinze ans après le coulage du béton. L’expansioncontinu du béton peut fortement réduire la durée de vie des ouvrages.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;En 2015, une équipe de scientifiques de l´Institut Paul Scherrer (PSI) et de l´Empa a finalement identifié la structure du cristal hydraté provoquant le retrait du béton. Elle avait déjà fait l´objet de nombreuses spéculations. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Cette découverte a été le facteur déclenchant d´un projet de recherche interdisciplinaire financé par le Fonds national (FNS). Outre l´Empa et le PSI, deux instituts de l´EPFL y participent. Les travaux sont coordonnés par un chercheur de l´Empa, Andreas Leemann: «Nous entendons étudier et comprendre la RAG à tous les niveaux, de l´échelle atomique de l´ordre de l´angström, à celui de l´ouvrage, soit du centimètre et du mètre.»&lt;/p&gt; Le projet FNS-Sinergia a été découpé en six sous-projets: Le PSI étudie à l´aide de son faisceau synchrotron la structure des produits de réaction afin d´en expliquer l´origine; l´EPFL se penche sur les conditions générales entraînant la dissolution des silicates et sur la composition des premiers produits de réaction; en outre, l´EPFL simulera numériquement les effets d’expansion sur les ouvrages; le Centre d´analyse par rayons X de l´Empa scrutera par tomographie la formation spatiale et temporelle des fissures du béton; l´Empa va également synthétiser les cristaux hydratés en laboratoire, ce qui permettra aux chercheurs de disposer librement de cette matière qui se dissimule dans les micro-fissures (du nano au micromètre) des grains de gravier. Une nécessité pour en caractériser les propriétés. Les connaissances ainsi acquises permettront non seulement de mieux comprendre la RAG, mais également d´identifier les moyens d´en prévenir les méfaits.«Nous progressons dans le décryptage de ce phénomène mal compris», se réjouit Leemann. Le projet lancé en mai 2017 doit durer quatre ans. Les premiers résultats sont déjà là. La prochaine étape verra le resserrement des liens entre les différents groupes de travail et la cross-fertilisation de leurs résultats. Il devrait en ressortir un portrait en pied de la RAG qui permettra de mieux évaluer les risques auxquels sont exposés les ouvrages qui en sont victimes et de prendre les décisions qui s´imposent de manière scientifiquement fondée.</text>
      <contact>Andreas Leemann Concrete / Construction Chemistry Tél. +41 58 765 44 89 Andreas.Leemann@empa.ch Rédaction / Contact des médias: Rainer Klose Communications Tél. +41 58 765 47 33 redaktion@empa.ch</contact>
      <link id="181902">
        <title>Empa-Medienmitteilung</title>
        <uri>https://www.empa.ch/web/s604/aar</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Dübendorf, St. Gallen und Thun</city>
      <title>Why does concrete swell and crack?</title>
      <lead>When bridges, dam walls and concrete foundations form cracks, AAR is often the cul-prit: the alkali-aggregate reaction. It causes the concrete to swell and renders renova-tions or even reconstructions necessary. A project funded by the Swiss National Sci-ence Foundation (SNSF) and coordinated by Empa is studying the “concrete disease”.</lead>
      <text link="no">Unfortunately, concrete does not last forever. The ravages of time also take their toll on concrete structures in Swit-zerland. Not only are reinforced structures like bridges affected, but also concrete buildings without any reinforce-ment, such as dam walls. One cause is referred to as the alkali-aggregate reaction (AAR). It can affect all concrete structures in open air. With AAR, the basic ingredients in the concrete are actually the problem: Cement – the main component of concrete – contains alkali metals such as sodium and potassium. Moisture in the concrete reacts with these alkali metals to form an alkaline solution. The main components of concrete are sand and gravel, which in turn contain silicates such as quartz or feldspar. The alkaline water reacts with these silicates and forms a so-called alkali calcium silicate hydrate. This mineral accumulates moisture in its structure, which causes it to expand and gradually crack the concrete from within. The striking thing here: The very same chemical reaction takes place in numerous pieces of gravel within the concrete; the small stones crack one by one. The pressure that can be exerted on an entire structure due to this mi-cro-reaction is huge: A dam wall, for instance, can expand by a few decimeters. This can cause damage to the lateral connecting points to the rock or deformations in the sluice area. The reaction takes place gradually, with the first damage only becoming noticeable in affected structures after ten to 15 years. However, the continual swelling of the concrete can seriously reduce the structures’ service life. In 2015 a team of scientists from Empa and the Paul Scherrer Institute (PSI) succeeded in identifying the struc-ture of the aqueous crystal that triggers the swelling in concrete. This structure had previously been the subject of much speculation. The discovery inspired an interdisciplinary research project funded by the Swiss National Science Foundation (SNSF). Besides Empa and PSI, two EPFL institutes are also involved. The research activities are coordinated by Empa researcher Andreas Leemann. “We want to study and understand AAR in every dimension, from the atomic level and length scales in the Angstrom range to entire structures on a centimeter and meter scale,” explains Lee-mann. Six projects cover all dimensions Six sub-projects were defined in the SNSF Sinergia project: PSI is using synchrotron radiation to study the structure of the reaction products in order to explain their sources. The key parameters for triggering the silicates and the composition of the reaction products formed at the outset are being studied at EPFL; moreover, computer simula-tions are being used to investigate the impact of the swelling on structures. And at Empa, the formation of the cracks in the concrete is being investigated at spatial and temporal resolution using computer tomography at the Empa X-Ray Center, and the aqueous crystals are being synthesized in the lab. This enables the researchers to obtain larger quantities of the substance usually found in nano- to micrometer-sized cracks in pieces of gravel. Only with larger quantities of the substance in question can physical properties be deter-mined accurately, however. Not only should the findings help understand AAR much better, they should also reveal ways to avoid damage – and thus costs.“We are already in the throes of decoding the phenomenon, which has only been understood in fragments until now,” says Leemann. The four-year project got underway in May 2017. The first results are already in. The next step will involve linking the individual groups more closely and building on the results of the partners. In the end, this should yield a more complete picture of AAR that enables the condition of and the risk to concrete structures to be gaged more effectively and the fate of the afflicted buildings to be supervised more scientifically. </text>
      <contact>Andreas Leemann Concrete / Construction Chemistry Phone +41 58 765 44 89 Andreas.Leemann@empa.ch Editor / Media contact: Rainer Klose Communications Phone +41 58 765 47 33 redaktion@empa.ch</contact>
      <link id="181902">
        <title>Empa-Medienmitteilung</title>
        <uri>https://www.empa.ch/web/s604/aar</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="8">
        <name lang="de">Bildung und Forschung</name>
        <name lang="fr">Formation et recherche</name>
        <name lang="it">Formazione e ricerca</name>
        <name lang="en">Education and Research</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="24">
        <name lang="de">Öffentliche Beschaffungen</name>
        <name lang="fr">Marchés publics</name>
        <name lang="it">Acquisti pubblici</name>
        <name lang="en">Public Procurement</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
