<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="72480" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2018-10-11</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="323" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>701</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidg. Materialprüfungs- und Forschungsanstalt</name>
      <name lang="fr">Laboratoire fédéral d'essai des matériaux et de recherche</name>
      <name lang="it">Laboratorio federale di prova dei materiali e di ricerca</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Laboratory for Materials Testing and Research</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.empa.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.empa.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.empa.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.empa.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">contact@empa.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">contact@empa.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">contact@empa.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">contact@empa.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="701">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Wirtschaft, Bildung und Forschung</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'économie, de la formation et de la recherche</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'economia, della formazione e della ricerca</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Economic Affairs, Education and Research</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Dübendorf, St. Gallen und Thun</city>
      <title>Medikamente zum Anziehen</title>
      <lead>Textilien, die Medikamente abgeben, könnten etwa Haut­­wunden behandeln. Forscher der Empa entwickeln solche ­Polymerfasern. Den Therapiebedarf erkennen die smarten Fasern von allein und dosieren die Wirkstoffe auch gleich präzis und punktgenau.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Für das Projekt «Self Care Materials» werden Fasern aus biologisch abbaubaren Polymeren mit verschiedenen Verfahren erzeugt. «Die anvisierte Nutzung der Faser entscheidet, welcher Herstellungsprozess optimal ist», erklärt Empa-Forscher und Projektkoordinator René Rossi. Zarte leichte Membranen, die eine grosse Oberfläche aufweisen, entstehen beim sogenannten Elektrospinnen. Werden robuste Fasern, etwa für Schutzbekleidung, benötigt, bietet sich eher das Ziehen der geschmolzenen Inhaltsstoffe an. Am Ende entstehen bei allen Verfahren neuartige Fasern, deren Nanoarchitektur aus mehreren Schichten und Komponenten aufgebaut ist. «Die Eigenschaften dieser neuen Materialien werden derzeit mit Testsubstanzen untersucht», sagt Rossi. Im fertigen Produkt sollen beispielsweise Antibiotika oder Schmerzmittel in die Fasern integriert werden.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Damit die Dosierung der Wirkstoffe präzis abläuft, haben die Forscher einen trickreichen Kontrollmechanismus erdacht: Einige Polymere sind vom Körper unter bestimmten Bedingungen abbaubar. Diese Eigenschaft kann gezielt genutzt werden. «Als Antwort auf einen Reiz aus dem Körper sollen die Fasern ihre Medikamente entsprechend einer kalkulierten Abbaurate an die Umgebung abgeben», so der ­Forscher. Als ein derartiger Reiz kann etwa der veränderte pH-Wert einer Hautwunde dienen, der anzeigt, dass die Gewebeschäden behandelt werden müssen. Als sogenanntes Self-care-Material unterstützen die Fasern in Form eines Pflasters oder Kleidungsstücks somit die Diagnose und Behandlung von Krankheiten.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;«Der Einsatz der Self-care-Fasern ist für enorm viele Anwendungen denkbar», so Rossi. Neben chemischen Signalen aus dem Körper lassen sich aber auch Reize nutzen, die bewusst von aussen gesetzt werden, um die Medikamentenabgabe der Fasern zu steuern. Textilien oder Verbände, die auf leichten Druck oder einen Lichtreiz hin ein Heilmittel freisetzen, können zur Lebensqualität von Patienten beitragen und gleichzeitig die Pflegenden entlasten. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Zudem ist das System in der Vorbeugung einsetzbar. Denn wo Wirkstoffe abgegeben werden, kann man auch umgekehrt Substanzen in die Faser eindringen lassen. «Das Funktionsprinzip lässt sich in der Gegenrichtung nutzen, indem die Fasern als Sensoren wirken und beispielsweise den Zuckerwert im Blut messen», erklärt Rossi. Bei Frühgeborenen droht der Zuckerhaushalt besonders häufig aus dem Gleichgewicht zu geraten. Mit Hilfe von derartigen Sensoren kann der Blutzucker durch die zarte Haut hindurch schmerzfrei überwacht werden, ohne dass die Babys unter einer piksenden Blutentnahme leiden müssten.&lt;/p&gt; Für das Projekt im Rahmen des «Competence Center for Materials Science and Technology», kurz CCMX, forscht das Team aus Empa- und EPFL-Wissenschaftlern gemeinsam bis zum Jahr 2020 an der Weiterentwicklung der smarten Medizinfasern. Als Industriepartner konnten 20 Unternehmen gewonnen werden, darunter Syngenta und – als jüngsten Zuwachs – Nanosurf aus Liestal. Zudem sind der Branchenverband Swiss Textiles und die Forschungsinitiative der schweizerischen Textilhersteller Subitex am Projekt beteiligt.</text>
      <contact>Prof. Dr. René Rossi Biometric Membranes and Textiles Phone +41 58 765 74 00 rene.rossi@empa.ch Redaktion / Medienkontakt Andrea Six Kommunikation Phone 41 58 765 61 33 redaktion@empa.ch</contact>
      <link id="182094">
        <title>Empa Medienmitteilung</title>
        <uri>https://www.empa.ch/web/s604/medication-you-can-wear</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Dübendorf, St. Gallen und Thun</city>
      <title>Des chemises médicinales</title>
      <lead>Un textile capable de libérer un médicament pourrait par exemple contribuer au traitement des plaies cutanées. Une équipe de l´Empa met actuellement au point des fibres synthétiques capables d´inclure des médicaments. Ces fibres détectent d´elles-mêmes le moment où agir et relâchent la quantité exacte de substance active nécessaire à l´endroit voulu. </lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Dans le cadre du projet «Self Care Materials», ils réalisent des polymères biologiquement dégradables en recourant à divers processus. «C´est l´usage visé qui décide du meilleur processus de fabrication» précise René Rossi, chercheur à l´Empa et coordinateur du projet. Ainsi, l´électrofilage permet de réaliser des membranes douces et légères de grande surface. Lorsqu´on a besoin de fibres robustes, par exemple pour des tenues de protection, on préfère l´étirage de la substance active fondue. Au final, tous ces processus fournissent des fibres nouvelles nanoarchitecturées en plusieurs couches de divers composants. «Nous étudions actuellement les caractéristiques de ces nouveaux matériaux en conjonction avec plusieurs substances test» indique Rossi. Les produits finis pourraient par exemple contenir des antibiotiques ou des analgésiques.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Le dosage précis de la substance libérée est assuré par un mécanisme ingénieux: certains types de polymères se décomposent au contact du corps, mais seulement sous certaines conditions. Le phénomène peut être exploité de manière ciblée. «Les fibres doivent réagir au stimulus corporel par un taux de libération du médicament bien calculé». Parmi ces stimuli, on retient par exemple le changement de pH des plaies qui signale que les tissus cutanés concernés doivent être traitées. Les fibres médicinales, également nommées Self-Care-Material, sont mises en œuvre sous forme de pansement ou de pièce intégrée à un vêtement et participent ainsi au diagnostic et au traitement de différentes maladies.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;«Les applications possibles des fibres self-care sont innombrables» remarque Rossi. Pour régler le dosage du médicament, on peut exploiter divers signaux chimiques émanant du corps, mais également des signaux envoyés de l´extérieur. Les textiles et les bandages peuvent réagir à une légère pression ou à un stimulus lumineux. Ce qui permettrait d´améliorer le bien-être des patients et de décharger le personnel soignant.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Cette technique a également sa place dans la prévention. En effet, si l´on peut libérer des substances actives, on peut inversement provoquer l´absorption de substances par les fibres. «Le principe peut être inversé, les fibres agissant comme détecteur et mesurant par exemple la teneur en sucre du sang» explique Rossi. Un exemple: l´équilibre glycémique des nouveaux-nés est souvent menacé. Des capteurs adaptés peuvent en suivre l´évolution à travers la fine peau des bébés, sans douleur, sans la piqure d´une prise de sang. &lt;/p&gt; L´équipe scientifique de l´Empa et de l´EPFL poursuivra sa collaboration sur le projet CCMX de développement de fibres médicinales intelligentes jusqu´en 2020. Vingt partenaires industriels ont déjà rejoint le projet, dont Syngenta et – dernier venu – Nanosurf, de Liestal. L´association professionnelle Swiss Textiles et le réseau d’innovation textile Subitex participent également au projet.</text>
      <contact>Prof. Dr. René Rossi Biometric Membranes and Textiles Tél. +41 58 765 74 00 rene.rossi@empa.ch Rédaction / Contact médias Andrea Six Communications Tél. +41 58 765 61 33 redaktion@empa.ch</contact>
      <link id="182094">
        <title>Empa Medienmitteilung</title>
        <uri>https://www.empa.ch/web/s604/medication-you-can-wear</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Dübendorf, St. Gallen und Thun</city>
      <title>Medication you can wear</title>
      <lead>Drug-releasing textiles could, for instance, be used to treat skin wounds. Empa researchers are currently developing polymer fibers that can be equipped with drugs. The smart fibers recognize the need for therapy all by themselves and dose the active ingredients with precision and accuracy. </lead>
      <text link="no">For the «Self Care Materials» project, fibers are produced from biodegradable polymers using various processes. «The targeted use of the fiber determines which manufacturing process is best,» explains Empa researcher and project coordinator René Rossi. Delicate, light membranes with a large surface are formed during so-called electrospinning. If robust fibers are required, e.g. for protective cloth-ing, it is better to draw the melted ingredients. In the end, all processes produce novel fibers, the nano-architecture of which is made up of several layers and components. «The properties of these new materials are currently being investigated with test substances,» says Rossi. In the finished product, for example, antibiotics or painkillers are to be integrated into the fibers. In order to ensure that the dosage of the active substances is precisely as needed, the researchers have devised a tricky control mechanism: Some polymers are degradable by the body under certain conditions. This property can be used specifically. Rossi: «In response to a stimulus from the body, the fibers should release their drugs into the environment at a calculated degradation rate.» Such an irritation can be the altered pH value of a skin wound, which indicates that the tissue damage must be treated. As a so-called self-care material, the fibers in the form of a plaster or garment thus support the diagnosis and treatment of diseases. «The use of self-care fibers is conceivable for an enormous number of applications,» says Rossi. In addition to chemical signals from the body, however, stimuli can also be used that are deliberately set from the outside to control the release of medication by the fibers. Textiles or dressings that release a remedy under slight pressure or a stimulus of light can contribute to the quality of life of pa-tients and at the same time relieve the burden on health care staff. The system can also be used for preventive measures. The idea behind it: Where active substances can be released, substances are also able to penetrate the fiber in the opposite direction. ”Thus, the fibers can act as sensors and, for instance, measure the sugar level in the blood,» explains Rossi. In the case of premature babies, the sugar balance is particularly likely to be out of balance. With the help of such sensors, blood sugar can be monitored painlessly through the tender skin without the babies having to suffer from a prickly blood sample. For the CCMX project, the team of Empa and EPFL scientists is conducting joint research into the further development of smart medical fibers until 2020. 20 companies have so far been won as industrial partners, including Syngenta and – as the latest addition – Nanosurf from Liestal. The industry association Swiss Textiles and the research initiative of the Swiss textile manufacturers Subitex are also involved in the project. </text>
      <contact>Prof. Dr. René Rossi Biometric Membranes and Textiles Phone +41 58 765 74 00 rene.rossi@empa.ch Editor / Media contact Andrea Six Communications Phone 41 58 765 61 33 redaktion@empa.ch</contact>
      <link id="182094">
        <title>Empa Medienmitteilung</title>
        <uri>https://www.empa.ch/web/s604/medication-you-can-wear</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="8">
        <name lang="de">Bildung und Forschung</name>
        <name lang="fr">Formation et recherche</name>
        <name lang="it">Formazione e ricerca</name>
        <name lang="en">Education and Research</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
