<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="73490" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2018-12-19</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="1070" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>1070</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Der Bundesrat</name>
      <name lang="fr">Conseil fédéral</name>
      <name lang="it">Il Consiglio federale</name>
      <name lang="en">The Federal Council</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.admin.ch/gov/de/start.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.admin.ch/gov/fr/accueil.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.admin.ch/gov/it/pagina-iniziale.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.admin.ch/gov/en/start.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="201" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>201</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="1070">
      <name lang="de">Der Bundesrat</name>
      <name lang="fr">Conseil fédéral</name>
      <name lang="it">Il Consiglio federale</name>
      <name lang="en">The Federal Council</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.admin.ch/gov/de/start.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.admin.ch/gov/fr/accueil.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.admin.ch/gov/it/pagina-iniziale.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.admin.ch/gov/en/start.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <department id="201">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Der Bundesrat verlängert die Sperrung von Vermögenswerten im Zusammenhang mit Tunesien und der Ukraine</title>
      <lead>An seiner Sitzung vom 19. Dezember 2018 hat der Bundesrat beschlossen, die vorsorgliche Sperrung der Vermögenswerte der gestürzten Präsidenten Ben Ali (Tunesien) und Janukowitsch (Ukraine) und ihres engsten Umfelds um ein Jahr zu verlängern. Mit diesem Entscheid soll die justizielle Zusammenarbeit mit den beiden Staaten unterstützt werden. </lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Anfang 2011 hatte der Bundesrat rasch auf die Aufstände in der arabischen Welt reagiert und insbesondere die Vermögenswerte des gestürzten Präsidenten Ben Ali sowie von Personen aus dessen Umfeld vorsorglich gesperrt. Im Februar 2014 verhängte er zudem im Fall der Ukrainekrise eine ähnliche Vermögenssperre. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Das Bundesgesetz über die Sperrung und die Rückerstattung unrechtmässig erworbener Vermögenswerte (SRVG), das am 1. Juli 2016 in Kraft trat, regelt die Dauer der Sperrung und die Bedingungen für deren Verlängerung um jeweils ein Jahr. Eine Verlängerung ist möglich, wenn die Rechtshilfezusammenarbeit Früchte trägt. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Die Sperrung von Vermögenswerten im Zusammenhang mit Tunesien (CHF 56 Mio.) und der Ukraine (CHF 70 Mio.), die vom Bundesrat am 9. Dezember 2016 und am 20. Dezember 2017 um jeweils ein Jahr verlängert wurde, läuft im Januar bzw. im Februar 2019 aus. Es wurden mehrere Verfahren gegen die Hauptakteure eingeleitet, und die Behörden dieser Länder haben bei der gerichtlichen Aufarbeitung der Fälle Fortschritte erzielt. Allerdings sind noch Gerichtsentscheide erforderlich, um festzustellen, ob die gesperrten Vermögenswerte unrechtmässiger Herkunft sind. Da das mit der vorsorglichen Sperrung angestrebte Ziel noch nicht vollumfänglich erreicht wurde und die rechtlichen Voraussetzungen erfüllt sind, ist eine Verlängerung sinnvoll. Die Verlängerung um ein Jahr dürfte auch die Aussichten im Hinblick auf allfällige Vermögensrückführungen verbessern. &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Information EDA Tel. +41 58 462 31 53 info@eda.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Le Conseil fédéral prolonge le blocage de valeurs patrimoniales dans les contextes de la Tunisie et de l’Ukraine</title>
      <lead>Lors de sa séance du 19 décembre 2018, le Conseil fédéral a décidé de prolonger d’une année le blocage préventif des avoirs des présidents déchus Ben Ali (Tunisie) et Yanukovych (Ukraine), ainsi que de leur entourage. Cette décision vise à soutenir la coopération judiciaire avec les deux Etats. </lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Au début de l’année 2011, le Conseil fédéral avait immédiatement réagi aux révoltes arabes en cours, et avait notamment ordonné le blocage à titre préventif des avoirs en Suisse du président déchu Ben Ali, ainsi que de leur entourage. Il a aussi prononcé un blocage similaire dans le contexte de la crise ukrainienne de février 2014. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;La loi fédérale sur les valeurs patrimoniales d’origine illicite (LVP), entrée en vigueur le 1er juillet 2016, réglemente la durée des blocages ainsi que les conditions de leur renouvellement annuel. Un renouvellement est possible lorsque la coopération porte des fruits dans le cadre de l’entraide judiciaire. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Prolongés d’un an par décisions du Conseil fédéral des 9 décembre 2016 et 20 décembre 2017, les blocages dans les contextes de la Tunisie (CHF 56 millions) et de l’Ukraine (CHF 70 millions) arriveront à échéance en janvier et février 2019, respectivement. Plusieurs procédures ont été ouvertes contre les principaux protagonistes et les autorités de ces pays ont activement progressé dans le traitement des cas sur le plan judiciaire. Cependant, des jugements sont encore nécessaires pour déterminer si les avoirs bloqués sont d’origine illicite. Les blocages préventifs du Conseil fédéral n’ayant pas encore pleinement atteint leur objectif et les conditions légales d’un renouvellement étant remplies, il se justifie de les reconduire. Un renouvellement d’une année permettra de favoriser les perspectives de possibles restitutions. &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Information DFAE Tél. +41 58 462 31 53 info@eda.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Il Consiglio federale proroga il blocco dei valori patrimoniali nei contesti di Tunisia e Ucraina</title>
      <lead>Nel corso della seduta di mercoledì 19 dicembre 2018 il Consiglio federale ha deciso di prorogare di un anno il blocco preventivo degli averi dei presidenti decaduti Ben Ali (Tunisia) e Janukovyč (Ucraina) e delle persone del loro entourage. La decisione mira a sostenere la cooperazione giudiziaria in corso con questi due Stati. </lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;All’inizio del 2011 il Consiglio federale aveva immediatamente reagito alle rivolte arabe ordinando, a titolo preventivo, di bloccare gli averi depositati in Svizzera riconducibili al presidente decaduto Ben Ali e alle persone del suo entourage. L’Esecutivo ha deciso un blocco analogo anche nel contesto della crisi ucraina scoppiata nel febbraio del 2014. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;La legge sui valori patrimoniali di provenienza illecita (LVP), entrata in vigore il 1° luglio 2016, regola la durata dei blocchi e le condizioni per il loro rinnovo a cadenza annuale. Questo è possibile se e quando la cooperazione nel quadro dell’assistenza giudiziaria si rivela proficua. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Prorogati di un anno con decisioni del Consiglio federale del 9 dicembre 2016 e del 20 dicembre 2017, i blocchi legati a Tunisia (56 mio. CHF) e Ucraina (70 mio. CHF) scadranno rispettivamente nei mesi di gennaio e febbraio del 2019. Contro i principali protagonisti sono stati aperti vari procedimenti e le autorità dei due Paesi interessati portano avanti i casi sul piano giudiziario. Ciononostante sono ancora necessarie sentenze per stabilire se l’origine degli averi bloccati è illecita. Visto che i blocchi preventivi del Consiglio federale non hanno ancora raggiunto pienamente i loro obiettivi e che le condizioni legali per una proroga sono soddisfatte, il loro prolungamento è giustificato. Il rinnovo di un anno permetterà di agevolare possibili restituzioni. &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Informazione DFAE Tel. +41 58 462 31 53 info@eda.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Federal Council extends freeze on assets relating to Tunisia and Ukraine</title>
      <lead>At its meeting on 19 December 2018, the Federal Council decided to extend for one year the preventive freeze on the assets of ousted presidents Ben Ali (Tunisia) and Yanukovych (Ukraine) and their entourages. The purpose of this decision is to support the judicial cooperation between Switzerland and these two states. </lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;At the beginning of 2011, the Federal Council reacted immediately to the uprisings taking place at the time in a number of Arab countries by ordering, as a preventive measure, a freeze on the assets in Switzerland of ousted president Ben Ali and his entourage. It announced a similar freeze in the context of the crisis in Ukraine in February 2014. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Federal Act on the Freezing and the Restitution of Illicit Assets held by Foreign Politically Exposed Persons (FIAA), which came into force on 1 July 2016, governs the duration of freezes and annual extensions to them. An extension is possible if cooperation within the framework of mutual legal assistance bears fruit. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The freezes on the assets relating to Tunisia (CHF 56 million) and Ukraine (CHF 70 million), which have been extended twice by one year on the basis of Federal Council decisions on 9 December 2016 and 20 December 2017, will expire in January and February 2019 respectively. Several proceedings have been initiated against the main individuals concerned, and the authorities of these countries have taken active steps to advance these cases at the judicial level. Court rulings are, however, still required to determine whether or not the origins of the frozen assets are illicit. The Federal Council's decision to extend the freeze on the assets is warranted because its objective has not yet been fully met while the legal conditions for its extension remain valid. This one-year extension will increase the likelihood of the assets being returned to the country of origin. &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>FDFA Information Tel. +41 58 462 31 53 info@eda.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
