<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="101815" revoked="no">
    <version>2</version>
    <pubdate>2024-07-10</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="1101" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>501</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Bundesamt für Cybersicherheit</name>
      <name lang="fr">Office fédéral de la cybersécurité</name>
      <name lang="it">Ufficio federale della cibersicurezza</name>
      <name lang="en">National Cyber Security Centre</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.bacs.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.ofcs.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.ufcs.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.ncsc.admin.ch/ncsc/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">media@ncsc.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">media@ncsc.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">media@ncsc.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">media@ncsc.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="502" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>501</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Generalsekretariat VBS</name>
      <name lang="fr">Secrétariat général du DDPS</name>
      <name lang="it">Segreteria generale del DDPS</name>
      <name lang="en">General Secretariat DDPS</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.vbs.admin.ch/</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.vbs.admin.ch/</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.vbs.admin.ch/</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.vbs.admin.ch/</www>
      <email lang="de">postmaster.vbs@gs-vbs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">postmaster.vbs@gs-vbs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">postmaster.vbs@gs-vbs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">postmaster.vbs@gs-vbs.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="501">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Verteidigung, Bevölkerungsschutz und Sport</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de la défense, de la protection de la population et des sports</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale della difesa, della protezione della popolazione e dello sport</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Defence, Civil Protection and Sports</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.vbs.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.vbs.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.vbs.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.vbs.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@gs-vbs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@gs-vbs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@gs-vbs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@gs-vbs.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Florian Schütz nimmt am Global Forum on Digital Security for Prosperity der OECD in Seoul teil</title>
      <lead>Florian Schütz, Direktor des Bundesamts für Cybersicherheit (BACS) und Vorsitzender der Arbeitsgruppe Digitale Sicherheit (WPDS) der Organisation für wirtschaftliche Zusammenarbeit und Entwicklung (OECD), nimmt vom 10. bis 11. Juli 2024 am Global Forum on Digital Security for Prosperity in Seoul teil. Er wird unter anderem ein Panel leiten, das sich mit dem Thema Regulation in der digitalen Sicherheit befasst. Ziel der Veranstaltung ist, einen gemeinsamen Dialog zu führen, Erfahrungen auszutauschen und an der Entwicklung öffentlicher Strategien im Bereich der digitalen Sicherheit zu arbeiten.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Das von der OECD organisierte Global Forum on Digital Security for Prosperity findet zum fünften Mal statt und beleuchtet aktuelle Themen rund um die digitale Sicherheit. Das diesjährige Forum in Seoul widmet sich den Themen Open Source, Supply Chains und Zero Trust. Die Ergebnisse der Diskussionen fliessen in die internationalen politischen Debatten ein und führen zur Entwicklung von Analysen, Grundsätzen und internationalen politischen Empfehlungen, sowohl bei der OECD als auch in anderen internationalen Foren.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Panels mit Florian Schütz zur Regulation in der digitalen Sicherheit und zu Zero Trust&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Florian Schütz wird in seiner Rolle als Vorsitzender der Arbeitsgruppe Digitale Sicherheit der OECD unter anderem ein Panel leiten, das sich mit dem Thema Regulation in der digitalen Sicherheit befasst. Die Diskussion soll aufzeigen, wo Regulierung bereits bestehen und wo sie künftig zur Norm werden sollten, um die digitale Sicherheit zu verbessern. Auch wird erörtert, in welchen Bereichen sich die Selbstregulierung als wirksam erwiesen hat und wo nicht. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Der Direktor des BACS wird zudem an einem Panel über Zero Trust teilnehmen. Zero Trust ermöglicht es Unternehmen, den Zugriff auf ihre Systeme, Netzwerke und Daten zu regulieren, ohne die Kontrolle darüber aufgeben zu müssen. Am Panel wird diskutiert, wie Zero Trust insbesondere die Sicherheit von Lieferketten in komplexen Ökosystemen mit vielen Partnern verbessern kann.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Die Teilnahme von Florian Schütz am Global Forum on Digital Security for Prosperity unterstreicht das Engagement der Schweiz, die digitale Sicherheit weltweit zu stärken und mit anderen internationalen Experten zusammenzuarbeiten, um bewährte Praktiken auszutauschen und wirksame Strategien zu entwickeln.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Kommunikation BACS +41 58 465 04 64 media@ncsc.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="277021">
        <title>OECD Global Forum on Digital Security for Prosperity</title>
        <uri>https://www.oecd-events.org/global-forum-digital-security-for-prosperity</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Florian Schütz participe au Global Forum on Digital Security for Prosperity de l’OCDE à Séoul</title>
      <lead>Florian Schütz, directeur de l’Office fédéral de la cybersécurité (OFCS) et président du groupe de travail Sécurité numérique (WPDS) de l’Organisation de coopération et de développement économiques (OCDE), participe du 10 au 11 juillet 2024 au Global Forum on Digital Security for Prosperity à Séoul. Il présidera notamment un panel consacré à la régulation dans le domaine de la sécurité numérique. L’objectif de l’événement est de mener un dialogue commun, d’échanger des expériences et de travailler au développement de stratégies publiques dans le domaine de la sécurité numérique. </lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;La cinquième édition du Global Forum on Digital Security for Prosperity organisé par l’OCDE met en lumière des thèmes actuels autour de la sécurité numérique. Cette année, à Séoul, le forum est consacré à des sujets tels que l’open source, les chaînes d’approvisionnement et la confiance zéro (principe du zero trust). Les résultats des discussions alimenteront les débats politiques internationaux et mèneront à l’élaboration d’analyses, de principes et de recommandations, tant au sein de l’OCDE que dans d’autres forums internationaux.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Panels avec Florian Schütz sur la régulation de la sécurité numérique et sur la confiance zéro&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Florian Schütz, dans son rôle de président du groupe de travail Sécurité numérique de l’OCDE, présidera un panel qui se penchera sur la régulation dans le domaine de la sécurité numérique. La discussion devra montrer où il existe déjà des réglementations et où elles devraient devenir la norme pour améliorer la sécurité numérique. Seront également examinés les domaines dans lesquels l’autorégulation s’est avérée efficace et ceux dans lesquels elle ne l’a pas été.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Le directeur de l’OFCS participera également à un panel sur la confiance zéro. Ce principe permet aux entreprises de réguler l’accès à leurs systèmes, réseaux et données sans devoir renoncer au contrôle. Les participants à ce panel discuteront de la manière dont la confiance zéro peut notamment améliorer la sécurité des chaînes d’approvisionnement dans des écosystèmes complexes avec de nombreux partenaires.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;La participation de Florian Schütz au Global Forum on Digital Security for Prosperity souligne l’engagement de la Suisse en faveur du renforcement de la sécurité numérique à l’échelle mondiale et de la collaboration avec d’autres experts internationaux afin d’échanger les bonnes pratiques et de développer des stratégies efficaces.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Communication OFCS +41 58 465 04 64 media@ncsc.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="277021">
        <title>OECD Global Forum on Digital Security for Prosperity</title>
        <uri>https://www.oecd-events.org/global-forum-digital-security-for-prosperity</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions>
        <revision date="2024-07-10 10:25" type="R"/>
      </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Florian Schütz parteciperà al Global Forum on Digital Security for Prosperity dell’OCSE a Seoul</title>
      <lead>Dal 10 all’11 luglio 2024 Florian Schütz, direttore dell’Ufficio federale della cibersicurezza (UFCS) e presidente del gruppo di lavoro «Digital Security» (WPDS) dell’Organizzazione per la cooperazione e lo sviluppo economico (OCSE), parteciperà al Global Forum on Digital Security for Prosperity a Seoul. Schütz dirigerà tra l’altro una tavola rotonda sul tema della regolamentazione in materia di sicurezza digitale. L’obiettivo dell’evento è quello di consentire il dialogo, lo scambio di esperienze e lo sviluppo di strategie pubbliche nel campo della sicurezza digitale.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Il Global Forum on Digital Security for Prosperity, organizzato dall’OCSE e giunto quest’anno alla sua quinta edizione, affronta tematiche attuali relative alla sicurezza digitale. Il forum di quest’anno avrà luogo a Seul e sarà dedicato ai temi dell’open source, delle supply chain e del modello di sicurezza Zero Trust. I risultati delle discussioni confluiranno nei dibattiti politici internazionali e porteranno allo sviluppo di analisi, principi e raccomandazioni politiche internazionali, presso l’OCSE come pure in altri forum internazionali.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Tavole rotonde con Florian Schütz sulla regolamentazione in materia di sicurezza digitale e sul modello Zero Trust &lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;In qualità di presidente del gruppo di lavoro dell’OCSE sulla sicurezza digitale, Florian Schütz dirigerà tra l’altro un gruppo di lavoro che affronterà il tema della regolamentazione in materia di sicurezza digitale. La discussione è volta a identificare gli ambiti in cui esiste già una regolamentazione e quelli in cui in futuro quest’ultima dovrebbe diventare la norma per migliorare la sicurezza digitale. Si cercherà anche di individuare in quali ambiti l’autoregolamentazione si è rivelata efficace e in quali meno. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Il direttore dell’UFCS parteciperà anche a una tavola rotonda sul tema Zero Trust. Tale modello consente alle aziende di regolare l’accesso ai propri sistemi, alle proprie reti e ai propri dati senza dover rinunciare al loro controllo. Alla tavola rotonda si discuterà su come il modello Zero Trust possa migliorare in particolare la sicurezza delle catene di fornitura in ecosistemi complessi con un gran numero di partner.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;La partecipazione di Florian Schütz al Global Forum on Digital Security for Prosperity sottolinea l’impegno della Svizzera a rafforzare la sicurezza digitale a livello mondiale e a collaborare con altri esperti internazionali per condividere prassi consolidate e sviluppare strategie efficaci.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Comunicazione UFCS +41 58 465 04 64 media@ncsc.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="277021">
        <title>OECD Global Forum on Digital Security for Prosperity</title>
        <uri>https://www.oecd-events.org/global-forum-digital-security-for-prosperity</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Florian Schütz in Seoul to take part in the OECD's Global Forum on Digital Security for Prosperity</title>
      <lead>Florian Schütz, Director of the National Cyber Security Centre (NCSC) and Chairman of the Working Party on Digital Security (WPDS) of the Organisation for Economic Co-operation and Development (OECD), will take part in the Global Forum on Digital Security for Prosperity, which is being held in Seoul from 10 to 11 July 2024. His schedule includes chairing a panel dealing with the topic of regulation in digital security. The aim of the event is to conduct a joint dialogue, exchange experiences and work on the development of public strategies in the field of digital security.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;The Global Forum on Digital Security for Prosperity, organised by the OECD, is being held for the fifth time and highlights current topics relating to digital security. This year's forum in Seoul is dedicated to the topics of open source, supply chains and zero trust, and the results of the discussions will feed into international policy debates and lead to the development of analyses, principles and international policy recommendations, both in the OECD and in other international forums.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Panels with Florian Schütz on regulation in digital security and zero trust&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;As Chairman of the OECD's Working Party on Digital Security, Florian Schütz will chair a panel on the topic of regulation in digital security. The discussion is intended to show where regulation already exists and where it should become the norm in the future in order to improve digital security. It also discusses the areas in which self-regulation has proved effective and where it has not. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Director of the NCSC will also take part in a panel on Zero Trust. Zero Trust enables companies to regulate access to their systems, networks and data without having to give up control over them. The panel will discuss how Zero Trust can improve the security of supply chains in complex ecosystems with many partners in particular.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Florian Schütz's participation in the Global Forum on Digital Security for Prosperity underlines Switzerland's commitment to strengthening digital security worldwide and working with other international experts to share best practices and develop effective strategies.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>NCSC Communication +41 58 465 04 64 media@ncsc.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="277021">
        <title>OECD Global Forum on Digital Security for Prosperity</title>
        <uri>https://www.oecd-events.org/global-forum-digital-security-for-prosperity</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <keywords>
      <keyword id="5127" org-id="502">
        <name lang="de">Dossier Cyber Defence</name>
        <name lang="fr">Dossier Cyber Defence</name>
        <name lang="it">Dossier Cyber Defence</name>
        <name lang="en">Dossier Cyber Defence</name>
      </keyword>
    </keywords>
    <topics>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="40">
        <name lang="de">Sicherheit</name>
        <name lang="fr">Sécurité</name>
        <name lang="it">Sicurezza</name>
        <name lang="en">Security</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
