<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="9633" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2005-10-21</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="703" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>701</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Staatssekretariat für Wirtschaft</name>
      <name lang="fr">Secrétariat d'Etat à l'économie</name>
      <name lang="it">Segreteria di Stato dell'economia</name>
      <name lang="en">State Secretariat for Economic Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.seco.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.seco.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.seco.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.seco.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@seco.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@seco.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@seco.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@seco.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="701">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Wirtschaft, Bildung und Forschung</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'économie, de la formation et de la recherche</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'economia, della formazione e della ricerca</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Economic Affairs, Education and Research</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Arbeitsbesuch von Bundesrat Joseph Deiss in Sofia</title>
      <teaser>Am 24.10.2005 hält sich Bundesrat Joseph Deiss für einen offiziellen Arbeitsbesuch in Sofia auf. Im Zentrum der Gespräche steht die Förderung der Beziehungen zum zweitwichtigsten Handelspartner der Schweiz unter den Transitionsländern Südosteuropas. Der Chef des Eidg. Volkswirtschaftsdepartement wird von einer Delegation wichtiger Schweizer Unternehmer begleitet.</teaser>
      <lead>Am 24.10.2005 hält sich Bundesrat Joseph Deiss für einen offiziellen Arbeitsbesuch in Sofia auf. Im Zentrum der Gespräche steht die Förderung der Beziehungen zum zweitwichtigsten Handelspartner der Schweiz unter den Transitionsländern Südosteuropas. Der Chef des Eidg. Volkswirtschaftsdepartement wird von einer Delegation wichtiger Schweizer Unternehmer begleitet.</lead>
      <text link="no">Im Laufe des rund 24-stündigen Besuchs wird die Schweizer Delegation Gespräche mit Wirtschafts- und Energieminister Rumen Ovcharov, Premierminster Sergei Stanischew sowie der für Europafragen zuständigen Ministerin Meglena Kuneva führen.&lt;br /&gt; Thematische Schwerpunkte dieser Treffen werden das ökonomische Umfeld und die Rahmenbedingungen für Schweizer Unternehmen sein sowie Fragen zur EU-Erweiterung, dem Freizügigkeitsabkommen, den Bilateralen I + II und der WTO.&lt;br /&gt; Über diese offiziellen Gespräche hinaus findet ein Treffen mit Vertretern von Schweizer Firmen in Bulgarien und den beiden Bulgarisch-Schweizerischen Handelskammern statt.&lt;br /&gt; Bulgarien ist der zweitwichtigste Handelspartner der Schweiz unter den Transitionsländern Südosteuropas. Die Schweizer Exporte nach Bulgarien erreichten 2004 283 Mio. CHF. Die Importe aus Bulgarien beliefen sich auf 65 Mio. CHF. 2004 erhöhten sich sowohl Exporte als auch Importe um 58% bzw. 5%.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Bern, 21. Oktober 2005&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; &lt;b&gt;Auskünfte:&lt;br /&gt; &lt;/b&gt;Evelyn Kobelt&lt;br /&gt; Kommunikationsbeauftragte &lt;br /&gt; EVD&lt;br /&gt; Tel. +41 (0)31 322 20 59, +41 (0)79 301 71 72&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Siamak Rouhani&lt;br /&gt; Länderverantwortlicher Zentraleuropa/Bulgarien&lt;br /&gt; SECO&lt;br /&gt; Tel. +41 (0)31 324 08 37</text>
      <contact/>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Visite de travail du conseiller fédéral Joseph Deiss à Sofia</title>
      <teaser>Le chef du Département fédéral de l’économie (DFE), M. Joseph Deiss, se rendra à Sofia le 24.10.2005 pour une visite de travail officielle. Les entretiens porteront principalement sur la promotion de la coopération entre la Suisse et la Bulgarie, notre deuxième partenaire commercial parmi les pays en transition de l’Europe du Sud-Est. Le conseiller fédéral sera accompagné d’une délégation d’entrepreneurs suisses.</teaser>
      <lead>Le chef du Département fédéral de l’économie (DFE), M. Joseph Deiss, se rendra à Sofia le 24.10.2005 pour une visite de travail officielle. Les entretiens porteront principalement sur la promotion de la coopération entre la Suisse et la Bulgarie, notre deuxième partenaire commercial parmi les pays en transition de l’Europe du Sud-Est. Le conseiller fédéral sera accompagné d’une délégation d’entrepreneurs suisses.</lead>
      <text link="no">Dans le cadre de cette visite de 24 heures, la délégation suisse rencontrera M. Rumen Ovcharov, ministre de l’économie et de l’énergie, M. Sergei Stanischew, premier ministre, et Mme Meglena Kuneva, ministre chargée des questions européennes.&lt;br /&gt; Les discussions porteront principalement sur le contexte économique, les conditions-cadre pour les entreprises suisses, l’élargissement de l’UE, l’accord sur la libre circulation des personnes, les bilatérales I &amp;amp; II et l’OMC.&lt;br /&gt; Une rencontre est prévue, en marge des entretiens officiels, avec des représentants d’entreprises suisses implantées en Bulgarie et des deux Chambres de commerce Suisse-Bulgarie.&lt;br /&gt; La Bulgarie est le deuxième partenaire commercial de la Suisse parmi les pays en transition de l’Europe du Sud-Est. Les exportations suisses vers la Bulgarie se sont élevées à 283 millions de francs en 2004 et les importations en provenance de ce pays à 65 millions de francs. En 2004, les exportations et les importations ont progressé, respectivement de 58% et de 5%.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Berne, le 21 octobre 2005&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; &lt;b&gt;Renseignements:&lt;br /&gt; &lt;/b&gt;Evelyn Kobelt&lt;br /&gt; chargée de la communication du DFE&lt;br /&gt; tél. +41 (0)31 322 20 59 ou +41 (0)79 301 71 72&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Siamak Rouhani&lt;br /&gt; responsable par pays – Europe centrale/Bulgarie&lt;br /&gt; SECO&lt;br /&gt; tél. +41 (0)31 324 08 37</text>
      <contact/>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Visita di lavoro del consigliere federale Joseph Deiss a Sofia</title>
      <teaser>Il 24.10.2005, il consigliere federale Joseph Deiss sarà a Sofia per una visita ufficiale di lavoro. I colloqui verteranno sul promovimento dei rapporti con la Bulgaria, secondo partner commerciale della Svizzera in ordine d'importanza in Europa sud-orientale. ll capo del Dipartimento federale dell'economia sarà accompagnato da una delegazione dei più importanti imprenditori svizzeri.</teaser>
      <lead>Il 24.10.2005, il consigliere federale Joseph Deiss sarà a Sofia per una visita ufficiale di lavoro. I colloqui verteranno sul promovimento dei rapporti con la Bulgaria, secondo partner commerciale della Svizzera in ordine d'importanza in Europa sud-orientale. ll capo del Dipartimento federale dell'economia sarà accompagnato da una delegazione dei più importanti imprenditori svizzeri.</lead>
      <text link="no">Nel corso della visita, che durerà un giorno, la delegazione svizzera si intratterrà con il ministro dell'economia e dell'energia Rumen Ovcharov, il primo ministro Sergei Stanischew e il ministro responsabile per le questioni europee Meglena Kuneva.&lt;br /&gt; Le tematiche al centro dell'incontro saranno la situazione economica e le condizioni quadro per le imprese svizzere, nonché l'allargamento dell'UE, l'Accordo sulla libera circolazione, i Bilaterali I + II e l'OMC.&lt;br /&gt; Oltre ai colloqui ufficiali è previsto un incontro con rappresentanti di ditte svizzere in Bulgaria e delle due Camere di commercio Svizzera-Bulgaria.&lt;br /&gt; La Bulgaria è il secondo partner commerciale della Svizzera in ordine d'importanza fra i Paesi in transizione dell'Europa sud-orientale. Nel 2004 le esportazioni svizzere in Bulgaria hanno raggiunto i 283 milioni di franchi svizzeri e le importazioni dalla Bulgaria sono ammontate a 65 milioni di franchi. Sia le esportazioni che le importazioni nel 2004 sono aumentate, rispettivamente del 58% e del 5%.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Berna, 21 ottobre 2005&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; &lt;b&gt;Informazioni:&lt;br /&gt; &lt;/b&gt;Evelyn Kobeltportavoce DFE&lt;br /&gt; tel. +41 (0)31 322 20 59 o +41 (0)79 301 71 72&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Siamak Rouhani&lt;br /&gt; responsabile Paesi dell'Europa centrale/Bulgaria&lt;br /&gt; SECO&lt;br /&gt; tel. +41 (0)31 324 08 37</text>
      <contact/>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Working visit by Federal Councillor Joseph Deiss to Sofia</title>
      <teaser>On 24.10.2005, Federal Councillor Joseph Deiss will travel to Sofia on an official working visit. Discussions will focus on promoting relations with Switzerland’s second most important trade partner among the transition countries of south-eastern Europe. The head of the Federal Department of Economic Affairs will be accompanied on his trip by a delegation of leading Swiss entrepreneurs.</teaser>
      <lead>On 24.10.2005, Federal Councillor Joseph Deiss will travel to Sofia on an official working visit. Discussions will focus on promoting relations with Switzerland’s second most important trade partner among the transition countries of south-eastern Europe. The head of the Federal Department of Economic Affairs will be accompanied on his trip by a delegation of leading Swiss entrepreneurs.</lead>
      <text link="no">In the course of the 24-hour visit, the Swiss delegation will hold talks with Bulgaria’s economy and energy minister, Rumen Ovcharov, Prime Minster Sergei Stanishev and the minister responsible for European affairs, Meglena Kuneva.&lt;br /&gt; The main topics of these meetings will be the economic environment and general conditions for Swiss firms as well as questions relating to EU enlargement, the free trade agreement, the two sets of bilateral agreements between Switzerland and the EU and WTO negotiations.&lt;br /&gt; In addition to these official discussions, there will also be meetings with representatives of Swiss firms in Bulgaria and with the two Bulgarian-Swiss chambers of commerce.&lt;br /&gt; Bulgaria is Switzerland’s second most important trade partner among the transition countries of south-eastern Europe. In 2004, Swiss exports to Bulgaria reached CHF 283 million. Imports from Bulgaria amounted to CHF 65 million. The volume of exports and imports in 2004 rose by 58% and. 5% respectively.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Bern, 21 October 2005&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; &lt;b&gt;Informations:&lt;br /&gt; &lt;/b&gt;Evelyn Kobelt&lt;br /&gt; Press Spokes person DEA&lt;br /&gt; Phone +41 (0)31 322 20 59, +41 (0)79 301 71 72&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Siamak Rouhani&lt;br /&gt; Desk OfficerCentral Europe/Bulgaria&lt;br /&gt; SECO&lt;br /&gt; Phone +41 (0)31 324 08 37</text>
      <contact/>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="10">
        <name lang="de">Bundesrat</name>
        <name lang="fr">Conseil fédéral</name>
        <name lang="it">Consiglio federale</name>
        <name lang="en">Federal Council</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="34">
        <name lang="de">Europa</name>
        <name lang="fr">Europe</name>
        <name lang="it">Europa</name>
        <name lang="en">Europe</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="47">
        <name lang="de">Wirtschaft</name>
        <name lang="fr">Économie</name>
        <name lang="it">Economia</name>
        <name lang="en">Economic Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
