<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="8530" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2005-10-27</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="811" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>801</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Bundesamt für Umwelt BAFU</name>
      <name lang="fr">Office fédéral de l'environnement OFEV</name>
      <name lang="it">Ufficio federale dell'ambiente UFAM</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Office for the Environment FOEN</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.bafu.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.bafu.admin.ch/fr</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.bafu.admin.ch/it</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.bafu.admin.ch/en</www>
      <email lang="de">info@bafu.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@bafu.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@bafu.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@bafu.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="801">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Umwelt, Verkehr, Energie und Kommunikation</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'environnement, des transports, de l'énergie et de la communication</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'ambiente, dei trasporti, dell'energia e delle comunicazioni</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of the Environment, Transport, Energy and Communications</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.uvek.admin.ch/uvek/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.uvek.admin.ch/uvek/fr/home.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.uvek.admin.ch/uvek/it/home.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.uvek.admin.ch/uvek/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-uvek.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-uvek.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-uvek.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-uvek.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Neuer Chef der BUWAL-Abteilung Internationales</title>
      <lead>Thomas Kolly wird per 1. November 2005 neuer Chef der Abteilung Internationales im BUWAL. Kolly ist der Nachfolger von Beat Nobs, der vom Bundesrat zum Botschafter der Schweiz in Neuseeland ernannt worden ist.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Der aus dem luzernischen Pfeffikon stammende Thomas Kolly trat 1988 in den Dienst des Eidgenössischen Departements für auswärtige Angelegenheiten (EDA). Ab 2002 leitete er in Bern das Ressort Sektorielle Politiken im Integrationsbüro (EDA/EVD). Dabei war er zuständig für die Bereiche Personenfreizügigkeit, Landverkehr, Luftverkehr, Forschung, Energie und Umwelt. Vorher war er bei der OECD-Delegation in Paris, im Finanz- und Wirtschaftsdienst des EDA, in der Wirtschaftsabteilung der Schweizer Botschaft in Washington sowie als Erster Mitarbeiter bei der Botschaft in Den Haag tätig.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Der neue Abteilungsleiter ist 47-jährig, verheiratet und Vater von drei Kindern. Er hat an der Universität Freiburg i.Ü. das Lizentiat der Rechtswissenschaften und am Collège d’Europe im belgischen Brügge (B) das Diplôme des hautes études européennes erworben und verfügt über das luzernische Anwaltspatent.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Thomas Kolly übernimmt die Leitung der Abteilung Internationales des BUWAL per 1. November 2005.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Beat Nobs: Vom BUWAL nach Neuseeland&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Kolly löst Beat Nobs ab, der vom Bundesrat zum Botschafter der Schweiz in Neuseeland, in der Republik Fidschi-Inseln, im Unabhängigen Staat Samoa und im Königreich Tonga ernannt worden ist. Nobs hat sein Amt Anfang Oktober angetreten.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Beat Nobs schloss seine Studien in Zürich und Vancouver B.C./Kanada mit dem Doktorat Phil. I und dem Diplom für das Höhere Lehramt ab. 1988 trat er in den Dienst des Eidgenössischen Departements für auswärtige Angelegenheiten. Seit 1997 leitete Beat Nobs die Abteilung Internationales im BUWAL, seit 1999 hat er den Botschaftertitel inne. Während dieser Zeit vertrat er die Interessen der Schweiz an internationalen Konferenzen und Verhandlungen. 2004 wurde er zum Vizepräsidenten der zehnten Vertragsstaatenkonferenz gewählt. Diese bildet das oberste Organ des Übereinkommens der Vereinten Nationen über Klimaänderungen.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Weitere Informationen: Thomas Kolly Leiter Ressort Sektorielle Politiken im Integrationsbüro EDA/EVD Tel. 031 322 22 03 Pressedienst BUWAL Tel. 031 322 90 00</contact>
      <link id="15338">
        <title>Ernennung von Beat Nobs zum Botschafter der Schweiz in Neuseeland. Medienmitteilung des EDA vom 30.9.2005.</title>
        <uri>http://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/g/home/recent/news/press_old/2005/09.html#0009</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="15341">
        <title>BAFU: Internationales</title>
        <uri>http://cms-bafu.root.admin.ch/international/index.html?lang=de</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Nouveau chef de la division Affaires internationales de l'OFEFP</title>
      <lead>Thomas Kolly sera le nouveau chef de la division Affaires internationales de l'OFEFP le 1er novembre 2005. Kolly succède à Beat Nobs, qui a été nommé ambassadeur de Suisse en Nouvelle-Zélande.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Originaire de Pfeffikon (LU), Thomas Kolly est entré au Département fédéral des affaires étrangères (DFAE) en 1988. Depuis 2002, il dirige le secteur Politiques sectorielles du Bureau d'intégration (DFAE/DFE) à Berne. Il est responsable de la libre circulation des personnes, des transports routier et aérien, de la recherche, de l'énergie et de l'environnement. Auparavant, il a fait partie de la délégation suisse auprès de l'OCDE à Paris, du service économique et financier du DFAE, de l'ambassade de Suisse à Washington (division économique) et a été premier collaborateur de l'ambassade de Suisse à la Haye.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Âgé de 47 ans, le nouveau chef de division est marié et père de trois enfants. Il est licencié en droit de l'Université de Fribourg, titulaire du diplôme des hautes études européennes du Collège d’Europe de Bruges (B) et titulaire du brevet d'avocat du canton de Lucerne.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Thomas Kolly prendra la tête de la division Affaires internationales le 1er novembre 2005.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Beat Nobs: de l'OFEFP à la Nouvelle-Zélande&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Thomas Kolly succède à Beat Nobs, qui a été nommé ambassadeur de Suisse en Nouvelle-Zélande, en République des Îles Fidji, en l'État indépendant du Samoa et au Royaume des Tonga par le Conseil fédéral. Il est entré en fonction début octobre.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Beat Nobs a suivi des études à Zurich et à Vancouver (Canada). Il est titulaire d'un doctorat en lettres et d'un diplôme d'enseignement supérieur. Il est entré au Département fédéral des affaires étrangères en 1988. Il dirigeait la division Affaires internationales de l'OFEFP depuis 1997 et possède le titre d'ambassadeur depuis 1999. Il a représenté les intérêts de la Suisse dans les conférences internationales. En 2004, il a été élu vice-président de la dixième Conférence des parties, l'organe suprême de la Convention des Nations-Unies sur les changements climatiques.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Renseignements: M. Thomas Kolly Chef du secteur Politiques sectorielles du Bureau de l'intégration DFAE/DFE Tél. 031 322 22 03 Service de presse de l'OFEFP Tél. 031 322 90 00</contact>
      <link id="15339">
        <title>Nomination de Beat Nobs au poste d'ambassadeur en Nouvelle-Zélande. Communiqué de presse du DFAE du 30.9.2005.</title>
        <uri>http://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/f/home/recent/news/press_old/2005/09.html#0009</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="15342">
        <title>OFEV: Affaires internationales</title>
        <uri>http://cms-bafu.root.admin.ch/international/index.html?lang=fr</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Nuovo capo della divisione Affari internazionali dell'UFAFP</title>
      <lead>Dal 1° novembre 2005 Thomas Kolly sarà il nuovo capo della divisione Affari internazionali dell'UFAFP. Kolly succede a Beat Nobs, designato dal Consiglio federale quale Ambasciatore svizzero in Nuova Zelanda.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Thomas Kolly, di Pfeffikon, Canton Lucerna, è entrato al servizio del Dipartimento degli affari esteri (DFAE) nel 1988. Nel 2002 ha assunto la direzione del settore di attività Politiche settoriali dell'Ufficio dell'integrazione (DFAE/DFE). In tal ambito era responsabile delle politiche settoriali Libera circolazione, Trasporti, Scienza e ricerca, Energia e Ambiente. Precedentemente aveva fatto parte della delegazione OCSE a Parigi, della Divisione degli affari finanziari ed economici del DFAE, della divisione Economia, finanza e commercio dell'Ambasciata svizzera a Washington ed era stato Primo collaboratore dell'Ambasciata svizzera all'Aia.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Il nuovo capo della divisione ha 47 anni, è sposato e padre di tre figli. Licenziato in diritto all'Università di Friburgo, ha ottenuto il Diplôme des hautes études européennes presso il Collège d’Europe nella città belga di Bruges. Possiede inoltre la patente di avvocato del Canton Lucerna.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Thomas Kolly assume la direzione della divisione Affari internazionali dell'UFAFP il 1° novembre 2005.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Beat Nobs: dall'UFAFP alla Nuova Zelanda&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Thomas Kolly succede a Beat Nobs, designato dal Consiglio federale quale Ambasciatore svizzero in Nuova Zelanda, nella Repubblica delle Isole Figi, nello Stato indipendente della Samoa e nel Regno di Tonga. Nobs ha assunto il suo nuovo compito all'inizio di ottobre.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Beat Nobs, dott. phil. I con diploma per l'insegnamento secondario superiore, ha studiato a Zurigo e Vancouver B.C./Canada. È entrato al servizio del Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri nel 1988 e nel 1997 è diventato capo della divisione Affari internazionali dell'UFAFP.&amp;nbsp; Nel 1999 è stato nominato Ambasciatore dal Consiglio federale. Durante tale periodo ha rappresentato gli interessi della Svizzera nell'ambito di conferenze e trattative internazionali. Nel 2004 è stato eletto vicepresidente della decima Conferenza della Parti, la quale costituisce l'organo supremo della Convenzione della Nazioni Unite sui cambiamenti climatici.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Informazioni supplementari: Thomas Kolly Capo del settore di attività Politiche settoriali dell'Ufficio dell'integrazione DFAE/DFE Tel. 031 322 22 03 Servizio stampa UFAFP Tel. 031 322 90 00</contact>
      <link id="15340">
        <title>Nomina di Beat Nobs ad Ambasciatore svizzero in Nuova Zelanda, Comunicato stampa del 30.9.2005 del DFAE.</title>
        <uri>http://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/i/home/recent/news/press_old/2005/09.html#0009</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="15343">
        <title>UFAM: Affari internationali</title>
        <uri>http://cms-bafu.root.admin.ch/international/index.html?lang=it</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>New head of the SAEFL International Affairs Division</title>
      <lead>Thomas Kolly will take over as head of the SAEFL’s International Affairs Division as per 1 November 2005. Kolly succeeds Beat Nobs, who has been appointed Swiss ambassador to New Zealand.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Thomas Kolly who hails from Pfeffikon in canton Lucerne entered the Federal Department of Foreign Affairs DFA in 1988. From 2002 he headed the Sectoral Policies Unit at the Integration Office DFA/DEA in Bern where he was responsible for the dossiers on the free movement of persons, land transport, air transport, research, energy and environment. Prior to that, he held posts at the OECD delegation in Paris, the Economic and Financial Affairs Division of the DFA, the Economic Division at the Swiss Embassy in Washington and deputy head of mission at the embassy in The Hague.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The new division head is 47-years-old and married with three children. He studied law at the University of Fribourg and obtained the Diplôme des hautes études européennes from the Collège d’Europe in Bruges (B). He also passed the bar exam in canton Lucerne.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Thomas Kolly will take over as the head of the International Affairs Division as per 1 November 2005.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Beat Nobs: From the SAEFL to New Zealand&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Thomas Kolly replaces Beat Nobs, whom the Federal Council has appointed Swiss ambassador to New Zealand, the Republic of the Fiji Islands, the independent State of Samoa and the Kingdom of Tonga. Beat Nobs took up his post at the beginning of October.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Beat Nobs completed his studies in Zurich and Vancouver B.C./Canada with a doctorate and teaching degree. In 1988 he entered the Federal Department of Foreign Affairs. Beat Nobs headed the International Affairs Division at the SAEFL from 1997, he has held the title of ambassador since 1999. During this time he represented Switzerland’s interests at international conferences and negotiations. In 2004, he was elected vice-president of the tenth Conference of the Parties, which is the highest body of the United Nations Framework Convention on Climate Change.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Further information: Thomas Kolly, Head Sectoral Policies Unit at the Integration Office DFA/DEA Tel. 031 322 22 03 SAEFL Press Service Tel. 031 322 90 00</contact>
      <link id="15345">
        <title>FOEN: International Affairs</title>
        <uri>http://cms-buwal.root.admin.ch/buwal/eng/news/artikel/20051027/01314/index.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <keywords>
      <keyword id="171" org-id="811">
        <name lang="de">Bundesamt für Umwelt, Wald und Landschaft (BUWAL)</name>
        <name lang="fr">Office fédéral de l´environnement, des forêts et du paysage (OFEFP)</name>
        <name lang="it">Ufficio federale dell´ambiente, delle foreste e del paesaggio</name>
        <name lang="en">Swiss Agency for the Environment, Forests and Landscape SAEFL</name>
      </keyword>
    </keywords>
    <topics>
      <topic id="29">
        <name lang="de">Umwelt und Natur</name>
        <name lang="fr">Environnement et nature</name>
        <name lang="it">Ambiente e natura</name>
        <name lang="en">Environment and Nature</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
