<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="57138" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2015-05-06</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="201" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>201</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="201">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Der Vorsteher des EDA, Bundesrat Didier Burkhalter, empfängt die ghanaische Aussenministerin</title>
      <lead>Anlässlich eines offiziellen Arbeitsbesuchs empfing Bundesrat Didier Burkhalter, Vorsteher des Eidgenössischen Departements für auswärtige Angelegenheiten (EDA), Aussenministerin Hanna Serwaa Tetteh im Von-Wattenwyl-Haus in Bern. Bei den Gesprächen ging es um die wirtschaftlichen Beziehungen und die wirtschaftliche Entwicklungszusammenarbeit zwischen der Schweiz und Ghana. Erörtert wurden auch die Sicherheitslage in dieser Region Afrikas sowie verschiedene aktuelle Themen des Weltgeschehens.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Hanna Serwaa Tetteh stattet als erste Aussenministerin Ghanas überhaupt der Schweiz einen offiziellen Besuch ab. 2010 wurde der mittlerweile verstorbene ghanaische Präsident John Evans Atta Mills in der Schweiz zu einem offiziellen Besuch empfangen. Die beiden Länder unterhalten gute Beziehungen und blicken auf einen langjährigen, für beide Seiten fruchtbaren Austausch zurück. Ghana gehört zu den drei wichtigsten Handelspartnern der Schweiz in Subsahara-Afrika. Das Land ist der wichtigste Kakao- und der zweitwichtigste Ananaslieferant der Schweiz. Angesichts der umfangreichen Kakaoimporte (rund 90% der Gesamteinfuhr) verzeichnet die Schweiz seit Jahren ein Handelsdefizit gegenüber Ghana, das zu den Schwerpunktländern der wirtschaftlichen Entwicklungszusammenarbeit der Schweiz zählt. Das Staatssekretariat für Wirtschaft (SECO) engagiert sich zwischen 2013 und 2016 mit 90 Millionen Franken. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Zur Bekräftigung der bilateralen Beziehungen haben die Schweiz und Ghana am Mittwoch im Rahmen des Arbeitsbesuchs von Aussenministerin Tetteh ein Memorandum of Understanding unterzeichnet. Das Dokument sieht regelmässige politische Gespräche vor, die zu einer Intensivierung und stärkeren Strukturierung der Beziehungen zwischen den beiden Ländern beitragen sollen. Ausserdem schlug der Vorsteher des EDA eine Annäherung zwischen der Schweiz und der Wirtschaftsgemeinschaft der westafrikanischen Staaten, der 15 Länder angehören, vor.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Bundesrat Didier Burkhalter und Aussenministerin Hanna Serwaa Tetteh unterhielten sich ausserdem über verschiedene Themen des regionalen und internationalen Geschehens. Sie besprachen namentlich die Sicherheitslage in den Nachbarstaaten Ghanas, welche durch Boko Haram bedroht ist. Bundesrat Didier Burkhalter äusserte in diesem Zusammenhang die Besorgnis der Schweiz angesichts der Machenschaften dieser terroristischen Gruppierung. Auch die Ebola-Epidemie war Gegenstand der Gespräche. Bundesrat Didier Burkhalter betonte die Notwendigkeit koordinierter Anstrengungen zur Ausrottung der Krankheit und präsentierte das Engagement der Schweiz in diesem Bereich. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Bei den internationalen Themen erörterten der Vorsteher des EDA und die ghanaische Aussenministerin auch die Krise in der Ukraine und die davon ausgehende Gefahr für die Sicherheit in Europa sowie die humanitären Hilfeleistungen, insbesondere für die Bevölkerung in Syrien und im Irak. Die beiden Aussenminister besprachen zudem die Zusammenarbeit der beiden Länder im Rahmen der Vereinten Nationen, namentlich im Hinblick auf die in diesem Jahr anstehenden wichtigen Beschlüsse bei der Post-2015-Entwicklungsagenda und ihren Zielsetzungen, sowie die Rolle der Armutsbekämpfung und der nachhaltigen Entwicklung.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Kommunikation EDA Bundeshaus West CH-3003 Bern Tel. Kommunikationsservice: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Medienstelle: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <link id="135767">
        <title>Bilaterale Beziehungen Schweiz–Ghana</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home/laender-reise-information/ghana/schweiz-ghana.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="135768">
        <title>Wirtschaftliche Zusammenarbeit und Entwicklung mit Ghana (SECO)</title>
        <uri>http://www.seco-cooperation.admin.ch/laender/05148/05157/index.html?lang=de</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Le chef du DFAE Didier Burkhalter reçoit la ministre ghanéenne des affaires étrangères</title>
      <lead>Dans le cadre d’une visite officielle de travail, Mme Hanna Serwaa Tetteh a été reçue à la Maison de Watteville à Berne par le conseiller fédéral Didier Burkhalter, chef du Département fédéral des affaires étrangères (DFAE). Les entretiens ont notamment porté sur les relations et la coopération économiques entre la Suisse et le Ghana. La sécurité dans cette région d’Afrique et diverses questions liées à l’actualité internationale ont également figuré au menu des discussions.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;La visite officielle de Mme Tetteh est la première d’un ministre des affaires étrangères ghanéen en Suisse. En 2010, c’est feu le président ghanéen John Evans Atta Mills qui avait été reçu en Suisse pour une visite officielle. Les deux pays entretiennent de longue date de bonnes relations, basées sur des échanges fructueux pour les deux parties. Le Ghana est l’un des trois principaux partenaires commerciaux de la Suisse en Afrique subsaharienne. Il est notre premier fournisseur pour le cacao et le deuxième pour les ananas. Étant donné le poids des importations de cacao (90% env. des importations totales), la Suisse enregistre depuis des années un déficit commercial vis-à-vis du Ghana, qui est l’un des pays prioritaires de la coopération au développement économique de la Suisse. Le Secrétariat d’Etat à l’économie (SECO) y engage CHF 90 mios entre 2013-2016. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Afin de renforcer leurs relations, la Suisse et le Ghana ont signé mercredi à l’occasion de la visite de Mme Tetteh un protocole d’entente (Memorandum of Understanding). Ce texte institue des consultations politiques régulières qui intensifieront et structureront davantage les liens entre les deux pays. Le chef du DFAE a également proposé un rapprochement de la Suisse avec la Communauté économique des Etats de l'Afrique de l'ouest qui regroupe 15 Etats de la région.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;M. Burkhalter et Mme Tetteh ont par ailleurs abordé diverses questions en lien avec l’actualité régionale et internationale. Ils se sont notamment entretenus de la situation sécuritaire dans les pays voisins du Ghana, menacée par Boko Haram. A cet égard, M. Burkhalter a exprimé la préoccupation de la Suisse face aux agissements de ce groupe terroriste. L’épidémie d’Ebola a également été un sujet de discussion. M. Burkhalter a souligné la nécessité de coordonner les efforts pour parvenir à éradiquer cette maladie et a présenté l’engagement de la Suisse dans ce domaine. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Enfin, sur le plan international, le chef du DFAE et la ministre ghanéenne des affaires étrangères ont évoqué la crise ukrainienne et le défi qu’elle représente pour la sécurité en Europe, ainsi que les moyens humanitaires de venir en aide aux populations syrienne et irakienne notamment. Les deux ministres ont également parlé de la coopération des deux pays au sein des Nations Unies, en particulier les importantes décisions à prendre en 2015 en lien avec l’agenda du développement durable (objectifs post-2015), et de l’importance de la lutte contre la pauvreté et du développement durable.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Communication DFAE Palais fédéral ouest CH-3003 Berne Tél. Service de communication: +41 58 462 31 53 Tél. Service de presse: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <link id="135769">
        <title>Relations bilatérales Suisse-Ghana</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae/representations-et-conseils-aux-voyageurs/ghana/suisse-ghana.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="135770">
        <title>Coopération et développement économique avec le Ghana (SECO)</title>
        <uri>http://www.seco-cooperation.admin.ch/laender/05148/05157/index.html?lang=fr</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Il capo del DFAE Didier Burkhalter riceve la ministra degli affari esteri del Ghana</title>
      <lead>Nel quadro di una visita ufficiale di lavoro, la ministra Hanna Serwaa Tetteh è stata ricevuta nella Casa von Wattenwyl, a Berna, dal consigliere federale Didier Burkhalter, capo del Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri (DFAE). I colloqui si sono concentrati sulle relazioni e sulla cooperazione economica tra Svizzera e Ghana. All’ordine del giorno anche la sicurezza in questa parte dell’Africa e vari temi legati all’attualità internazionale.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;La visita ufficiale di Hanna Serwaa Tetteh è la prima di un ministro degli affari esteri ghanese in Svizzera. Nel 2010 era stato il defunto presidente del Ghana John Evans Atta Mills a essere ricevuto in Svizzera in occasione di una visita ufficiale. I due Paesi intrattengono da lungo tempo buone relazioni, basate su scambi proficui per entrambi. Il Ghana è uno dei tre principali partner commerciali della Svizzera nell’Africa sub-sahariana: è il primo fornitore di cacao e il secondo di ananas. Considerato il peso delle importazioni di cacao (circa il 90 % del totale), la Svizzera registra da anni un deficit commerciale nei confronti del Ghana, che è uno dei Paesi prioritari della cooperazione allo sviluppo economico della Svizzera. La Segreteria di Stato dell’economia (SECO) ha destinato alla cooperazione 90 milioni di franchi per il periodo 2013-2016. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mercoledì, in occasione della visita della ministra Tetteh, la Svizzera e il Ghana hanno sottoscritto un protocollo d’intesa (Memorandum of Understanding) finalizzato al consolidamento delle relazioni. Il testo istituisce consultazioni politiche regolari che intensificheranno e struttureranno meglio i legami tra i due Stati. Il capo del DFAE ha anche proposto un avvicinamento della Svizzera alla Comunità economica degli Stati dell'Africa Occidentale, che raggruppa 15 Paesi della regione.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I ministri Burkhalter e Tetteh hanno inoltre affrontato varie questioni legate all’attualità regionale e internazionale, nello specifico hanno discusso delle condizioni della sicurezza nei Paesi confinanti del Ghana, minacciati da Boko Haram. A questo proposito il consigliere federale Burkhalter ha espresso la preoccupazione della Svizzera di fronte alle azioni di questo gruppo terroristico. Anche l’epidemia di ebola è stata oggetto dei colloqui. Burkhalter ha sottolineato la necessità di coordinare gli sforzi per riuscire a sradicare questa malattia e ha illustrato l’impegno della Svizzera in questo ambito. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sul piano internazionale il capo del DFAE e la ministra degli affari esteri ghanese hanno infine menzionato la crisi ucraina e i problemi che pone per la sicurezza in Europa nonché i mezzi umanitari per aiutare, in particolare, le popolazioni della Siria e dell’Iraq. I ministri hanno anche parlato della cooperazione dei due Stati in seno alle Nazioni Unite, soprattutto delle decisioni importanti che andranno prese nel 2015 in relazione con l’agenda per uno sviluppo sostenibile (obiettivi post-2015), e dell’importanza dello sviluppo sostenibile e della lotta contro la povertà.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Comunicazione DFAE Palazzo federale ovest CH-3003 Berna Tel. Servizio di comunicazione: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Servizio stampa: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <link id="135771">
        <title>Relazioni bilaterali Svizzera–Ghana</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/home/laender-reise-information/ghana/schweiz-ghana.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="135772">
        <title>Cooperazione e sviluppo economico con il Ghana (SECO) (fr)</title>
        <uri>http://www.seco-cooperation.admin.ch/laender/05148/05157/index.html?lang=fr</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Head of the FDFA Didier Burkhalter receives Minister of Foreign Affairs of Ghana</title>
      <lead>Federal Councillor Didier Burkhalter, head of the Federal Department of Foreign Affairs (FDFA), received Ms Hanna Serwaa Tetteh for an official working visit at the Maison de Watteville in Bern. The talks focused on relations between Switzerland and Ghana and economic cooperation. Security in this region of Africa and various current international issues were also on the agenda for discussion.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Ms Tetteh's official visit is the first by a Ghanaian foreign minister to Switzerland. In 2010, the President of Ghana, John Evans Atta Mills, was received in Switzerland for an official visit. The two countries have had long-standing good relations based on mutually beneficial exchanges. Ghana is one of Switzerland's three main trading partners in sub-Saharan Africa and is Switzerland's most important supplier of cocoa and second biggest supplier of pineapples. Given the volume of cocoa imports (approx. 90% of total imports) Switzerland has been running a trade deficit for several years with Ghana, which is one of Switzerland's priority countries of economic development cooperation. The State Secretariat for Economic Affairs (SECO) has earmarked CHF 90 million for Ghana for the years 2013 to 2016. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;To strengthen their relations, Switzerland and Ghana signed a Memorandum of Understanding on Wednesday on the occasion of Ms Tetteh's visit. The text institutionalises regular political consultations which will make relations between the two countries closer and more structured. The head of the FDFA also proposed developing closer relations between Switzerland and the Economic Community of West African States, which comprises 15 countries from this region. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In addition, Mr Burkhalter and Ms Tetteh addressed various current regional and international issues. Specifically they discussed the security situation in Ghana's neighbouring countries that are threatened by Boko Haram. Mr Burkhalter expressed Switzerland's concern about the activities of this terrorist group. The Ebola epidemic was also discussed. Mr Burkhalter emphasised the need to coordinate efforts to eradicate the disease and explained Switzerland's commitment in this field. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Lastly, at the international level, the head of the FDFA and the Ghanaian foreign minister discussed the Ukraine crisis and the challenge it presents to European security, as well as the humanitarian assistance required to help in particular the people of Syria and Iraq. The two ministers also talked about cooperation between the two countries within the United Nations, in particular the important decisions to be taken in 2015 concerning the objectives for the post-2015 sustainable development agenda as well as the importance of sustainable development and the fight against poverty.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>FDFA Communication Federal Palace West Wing CH-3003 Bern, Switzerland Tel. Communication service: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Press service: +41 58 460 55 55 E-mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @SwissMFA</contact>
      <link id="135773">
        <title>Bilateral relations Switzerland–Ghana</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home/laender-reise-information/ghana/schweiz-ghana.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="135774">
        <title>Economic Cooperation and Development with Ghana (SECO)</title>
        <uri>http://www.seco-cooperation.admin.ch/laender/05148/05157/index.html?lang=en</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
