<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="45543" revoked="no">
    <version>2</version>
    <pubdate>2012-08-08</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="703" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>701</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Staatssekretariat für Wirtschaft</name>
      <name lang="fr">Secrétariat d'Etat à l'économie</name>
      <name lang="it">Segreteria di Stato dell'economia</name>
      <name lang="en">State Secretariat for Economic Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.seco.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.seco.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.seco.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.seco.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@seco.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@seco.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@seco.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@seco.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="701">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Wirtschaft, Bildung und Forschung</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'économie, de la formation et de la recherche</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'economia, della formazione e della ricerca</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Economic Affairs, Education and Research</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Negativer eingestellte Konsumenten</title>
      <lead>Die vom Staatssekretariat für Wirtschaft in Auftrag gegebene Umfrage zur Konsumentenstimmung hat sich zwischen April und Juli leicht eingetrübt. Der berechnete Index* erreichte im Juli 2012 einen Wert von -17 Punkten (nach -8 im April). Pessimistischere Erwartungen für die künftige Wirtschaftsentwicklung sowie höhere erwartete Arbeitslosenzahlen liegen diesem Rückgang der Stimmung zugrunde.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Zwei der vier Subindizes, die in die Berechnung des Konsumentenstimmungsindex** einfliessen, haben sich zwischen April und Juli 2012 signifikant verschlechtert. Dies trifft auf die Einschätzung zur Entwicklung der Wirtschaftslage in den kommenden 12 Monaten zu (-20 Punkte im Juli, nach -2 im April) sowie für die Einschätzungen zur Entwicklung der Arbeitsosigkeit (+62 Punkte im Juli nach +49 im April). Demgegenüber verharrte im Juli die Beurteilung zur Entwicklung der persönlichen finanziellen Lage in den kommenden 12 Monate im Bereich der erhobenen Aprilwerte (-3 Punkte im Juli, nach +0 im April). Das gleiche gilt für die Beurteilung der Konsumenten bezüglich ihrer zukünftigen Sparmöglichkeiten (+15 Punkte im Juli nach +20 im April).&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Die restlichen Subindizes der Umfrage, welche nicht in die Berechnung des Gesamtindex einfliessen, haben sich gegenüber April zum Teil signifikant verschlechtert. Negativer beurteilt wurde insbesondere die allgemeine Wirtschaftslage der letzten zwölf Monate (-24 Punkte im Juli gegenüber -18 im April). Schlechter beurteilten die Konsumenten auch die Sicherheit der Arbeitsplätze (-72 Punkte im Juli nach -64 im April). Hingegen veränderte sich die Einstellung bezüglich des Zeitpunkts für grössere Anschaffungen (-2 Punkte gegenüber +1 im April), die Beurteilung der aktuellen Sparmöglichkeiten der Haushalte (+40 Punkte nach +41 im April) und die Beurteilung der vergangenen persönlichen finanziellen Lage (-12 Punkte im Juli nach -9 im April) kaum. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Die vergangene Preisentwicklung der letzten 12 Monatewurde tiefer als im April eingeschätzt (+22 Punkte im Juli nach +32 im April). Die Haushalte gehen von einer ähnlichen Preisentwicklung in den kommenden 12 Monaten aus wie im April (+32 Punkte im Juli nach +34 im April). Die Teuerungserwartungen der Haushalte und die Beurteilung der vergangenen Preisentwicklung liegen seit Anfang 2009im historisch Vergleich auf sehr tiefem Niveau.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Der alte Konsumentenstimmungsindex, wie er vor Oktober 2009 berechnet wurde, hat sich zwischen Juli und April ebenfalls leicht verschlechtert (-13 Punkte im Juli gegenüber -9 im April). &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Anpassung des Erhebungsdesigns&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;br /&gt;Die Befragung der Konsumentenstimmung wird seit April 2012 mit einer Anpassung des Erhebungsdesigns durchgeführt. Ziel der Anpassung war es, eine noch bessere Repräsentativität der Schweizer Bevölkerung in der Stichprobe zu gewährleisten. Vier Anpassungen sollen zu einer verbesserten Abbildung der Grundgesamtheit beitragen:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Während bisher nur die Deutsch- und Westschweiz abgedeckt wurden, wird neu auch das Tessin in die Befragung einbezogen.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Die Anzahl Interviews wurde von 1‘100 auf ca. 1‘200 erhöht. &lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Neu erfolgt die Stichprobenziehung im Stichprobenrahmen für Personen- und Haushaltserhebung (SRPH)*** des Bundesamts für Statistik (BFS). &lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Personen, von denen keine Festnetz-Telefonnummer bekannt ist, haben die Möglichkeit, online oder über eine Gratisnummer die Fragen zu beantworten.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Des Weiteren fand ein Wechsel des Instituts statt, welches die Befragungen durchführt**** und die Befragungswelle wurde von 2 Wochen auf 3 Wochen verlängert. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Trotz Änderungen im Erhebungsdesign und der Revision des Stichprobenumfangs ist die Interpretation des Konsumentenstimmungsindexes nicht grundsätzlich in Frage gestellt. Zu Kontrollzwecken wurden für die Umfragen von April und Juli 2012 doppelte Erhebungen nach alter und neuer Erhebungsmethode durchgeführt. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Keine signifikante Unterschiede wurden während dieser Testphase festgesellt. Die weitere Durchführung der Umfrage mit dem neuen Erhebungsdesigns schränkt demzufolge die Kontinuität und die zeitliche Vergleichbarkeit der Ergebnisse nicht ein. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;* In den Monaten Januar, April, Juli, Oktober werden im Auftrag des SECO ca. 1‘200 Haushalte nach ihrer subjektiven Einschätzung der Wirtschaftslage, ihrer persönlichen finanziellen Lage, der Preisentwicklung, der Sicherheit der Arbeitsplätze usw. befragt.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;**Seit der Publikation der Umfrageergebnisse vom Oktober 2009 werden zwei zusätzliche Fragen veröffentlicht. Es sind dies zum einen die Frage nach den Erwartungen bezüglich der Entwicklung der Arbeitslosigkeit und zum anderen die Frage nach der Wahrscheinlichkeit sparen zu können. Mit Hilfe dieser neuen Fragen wird der neue offizielle, EU-kompatible Index der Konsumentenstimmung berechnet. Die drei neuen Quartalsreihen beginnen ab April 2007 (siehe technische Notiz „Erweiterung der Umfrage“ vom 4.11.2009 unter: http://www.seco.admin.ch/themen/00374/00453/index.html?lang=de).&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;***Für weiter Informationen: http://www.bfs.admin.ch/bfs/portal/de/index/news/00/08.html &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;****Neu führt das Marktforschungsinstitut DemoScope (http://www.demoscope.ch/) im Auftrag des SECO die Befragungen durch.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Staatssekretariat für Wirtschaft SECO Holzikofenweg 36 CH-3003 Bern Tel. +41 58 462 56 56 Fax +41 58 462 56 00</contact>
      <attachment id="156458">
        <title>Tabelle - Konsumentenstimmungsindex</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>22</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/27645.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="156459">
        <title>Grafik - Index der Konsumentenstimmung</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>96</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/27646.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <link id="156460">
        <title>Zahlenreihen und Fragebogen</title>
        <uri>https://www.seco.admin.ch/seco/de/home/wirtschaftslage---wirtschaftspolitik/Wirtschaftslage/Konsumentenstimmung.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Les consommateurs moins optimistes</title>
      <lead>Selon l’enquête sur le climat de consommation établie sur mandat du Secrétariat d’Etat à l’économie, la situation s’est quelque peu assombrie entre avril et juillet derniers. L’indice calculé* a atteint un niveau de −17 points en juillet 2012 (contre −8 points en avril). Ce recul est dû à des perspectives plus pessimistes, exprimées par les ménages, s’agissant de l’évolution économique à venir, ainsi que par une hausse attendue plus marquée des chiffres du chômage.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Parmi les quatre sous-indices entrant dans le calcul de l’indice du climat de consommation**, deux se sont considérablement détériorés entre avril et juillet 2012. Les perspectives pour l’activité économique au cours des douze prochains mois ont été appréciées de manière plus pessimiste (−20 points en juillet, contre −2 en avril) et l’évolution du chômage, durant les douze prochains mois, a été revue à la hausse (+62 points en juillet, contre +49 en avril). En revanche, l’appréciation portée sur le développement de la situation financière personnelle au cours des douze prochains mois est demeurée pratiquement inchangée (−3 points en juillet, contre +0 en avril). Il en va de même de l’appréciation des consommateurs de leur capacité future à épargner, qui n’a aussi que peu varié (+15 points en juillet, contre +20 en avril).&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;D’autres sous-indices de l’enquête, qui ne sont pas intégrés dans le calcul de l’indice général, ont enregistré une évolution négative par rapport à l’enquête d’avril. La situation économique générale au cours des douze derniers mois, en particulier, a été jugée plus négativement (−24 points en juillet, contre −18 en avril). La sécurité de l’emploi a également été jugée moins bonne par les consommateurs (−72 points en juillet, contre −64 en avril). On observe en revanche peu de changements s’agissant de l’opportunité de faire actuellement des grosses dépenses (−2 points en juillet, contre +1 en avril) et de la capacité d’épargne actuelle (+40 points en juillet, contre +41 en avril). L’appréciation de la situation financière personnelle n’a également que peu varié (−12 points en juillet, contre −9 en avril). &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;L’évolution des prix au cours des douze derniers mois a été jugée moins marquée en juillet qu’elle ne l’avait été en avril (+22 points en juillet, contre +32 en avril). Peu de variations ont été enregistrées par contre pour l’anticipation des prix au cours des douze prochains mois (+32 points en juillet, contre +34 en avril). L’appréciation des ménages relative au renchérissement des prix durant les derniers mois écoulés et leur anticipation relative au renchérissement futur demeurent à un niveau historiquement bas en Suisse, et ce depuis le début de l’année 2009. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;L’ancien indice du climat de consommation, tel que calculé avant octobre 2009, a lui aussi connu un léger recul entre avril et juillet 2012 (−13 points en juillet, contre −9 en avril). &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Adaptation de l’organisation et de la structure de l’enquête&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;br /&gt;Le design de l’enquête sur le climat de consommation a été adapté pour les enquêtes menées à partir d’avril 2012. Cette adaptation a eu pour but d’améliorer la représentativité de la population suisse dans l’échantillon retenu pour l’enquête. Les quatre nouveautés suivantes devraient impliquer une plus haute représentativité de l’enquête :&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Alors que jusqu’en janvier 2012 seules la Suisse alémanique et la Suisse romande étaient prises en considération, le Tessin fait désormais aussi partie de l’échantillon à partir d’avril.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Le nombre d’interviews est passé de 1100 à environ 1200. &lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;L’échantillonnage retenu pour l’enquête est tiré dans le même cadre de celui qui est retenu pour les enquêtes auprès des personnes et des ménages (SRPH)*** de l’Office fédéral de la statistique (OFS). &lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Les personnes dont le numéro de téléphone fixe n’est pas connu ont la possibilité de répondre en ligne ou par le biais d’un numéro gratuit.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Par ailleurs, l’exécution des enquêtes a été confiée à un nouvel institut****, et la durée réservée à la réalisation des interviews est passée de deux à trois semaines. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Malgré les changements intervenus dans l’organisation et la structure de l’enquête, l’interprétation, d’une enquête à l’autre, de l’indice du climat de consommation n’est pas remise en question. A des fins de comparaison et de contrôle, les enquêtes d’avril et de juillet 2012 ont été menées à double, dans les deux cadres, selon l’ancienne et la nouvelle méthode. L’analyse des résultats a permis de dégager que les différences observées n’influencent pas l’interprétation des résultats obtenus. Ainsi, la poursuite de la réalisation de l’enquête selon le nouveau schéma n’entrave ni la continuité ni la comparabilité des résultats dans le temps. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;*En janvier, avril, juillet et octobre, environ 1200 ménages sont interrogés sur mandat du SECO quant à leur évaluation personnelle de la situation économique, de leur situation financière, de l’évolution des prix, de la sécurité de l’emploi, etc.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;**Depuis la publication des résultats de l’enquête d’octobre 2009, deux questions ont été ajoutées au questionnaire, l’une portant sur les attentes relatives à l’évolution du chômage et l’autre sur les possibilités d’épargne. Ces deux nouvelles questions permettent de calculer un nouvel indice officiel du climat de consommation, compatible avec celui de l’Union Européenne. Les trois nouvelles séries trimestrielles démarrent en avril 2007 (voir la notice technique « Elargissement de l’enquête » du 4.11.2009 à l’adresse suivante : http://www.seco.admin.ch/themen/00374/00453/index.html?lang=fr).&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;***Renseignements: http://www.bfs.admin.ch/bfs/portal/fr/index/news/00/08.html &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;****Les enquêtes seront dorénavant effectuées, sur mandat du SECO, par l’institut d'étude de marché DemoScope (http://www.demoscope.ch/).&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Secrétariat d'Etat à l'économie SECO Holzikofenweg 36 CH-3003 Berne tél. +41 58 462 56 56 fax +41 58 462 56 00</contact>
      <attachment id="156461">
        <title>Tableau - Indice du climat de consommation</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>25</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/27647.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="156462">
        <title>Graphique - Indice du climat de consommation</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>96</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/27648.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <link id="156463">
        <title>Les données et le questionnaire</title>
        <uri>https://www.seco.admin.ch/seco/fr/home/wirtschaftslage---wirtschaftspolitik/Wirtschaftslage/Konsumentenstimmung.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Diminuzione della fiducia dei consumatori</title>
      <lead>Il sondaggio sul clima di fiducia dei consumatori, svolto su incarico della Segreteria di Stato dell’economia*, ha rilevato una diminuzione della fiducia tra aprile e luglio. L’indice calcolato ha raggiunto a luglio 2012 un valore di -17 punti (dopo i -8 punti registrati ad aprile). Questo peggioramento è dovuto alle aspettative più pessimistiche sul futuro andamento dell’economia e al numero di disoccupati previsti più numerosi per i prossimi 12 mesi.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Tra aprile e luglio 2012 si è registrato un sensibile peggioramento di due dei quattro sottoindici che incidono sul calcolo dell’indice della fiducia dei consumatori**, ossia le previsioni rispettivamente sull’andamento della situazione economica nei prossimi 12 mesi (-20 punti a luglio dopo -2 ad aprile) e sull’andamento della disoccupazione (valore di +62 punti a luglio dopo +49 ad aprile). A luglio, invece, la valutazione sull’evoluzione della situazione finanziaria personale per i prossimi 12 mesi, in rapporto ai valori rilevati ad aprile, è rimasta invariata (-3 punti a luglio dopo +0 ad aprile). Lo stesso vale per la valutazione dei consumatori sulle proprie possibilità di risparmio future (+15 punti a luglio dopo +20 ad aprile).&lt;br /&gt;I rimanenti sottoindici utilizzati nell’indagine, che non contribuiscono al calcolo dell’indice generale, sono parzialmente peggiorati in modo significativo rispetto al mese di aprile. In particolare sono più negative le valutazioni sulla situazione economica generale degli ultimi 12 mesi (-24 punti a luglio contro -18 ad aprile) e sulla sicurezza dei posti di lavoro (-72 punti a luglio dopo -64 ad aprile). Al contrario è stato lieve il cambiamento rilevato riguardo alle valutazioni sull’opportunità di effettuare acquisti importanti (-2 punti contro +1 ad aprile), sulle possibilità di risparmio attuali delle economie domestiche (+40 punti dopo +41 ad aprile) e sulla situazione finanziaria personale passata (-12 punti a luglio dopo -9 ad aprile). &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;L’andamento dei prezzi degli ultimi 12 mesi è stato valutato al ribasso rispetto ad aprile (+22 punti a luglio dopo +32 ad aprile). Le economie domestiche prevedono un andamento quasi simile per i prezzi nei prossimi 12 mesi rispetto ad aprile (+32 punti a luglio dopo +34 ad aprile). Dall’inizio del 2009 le aspettative di rincaro delle economie domestiche e la valutazione dell’andamento dei prezzi passati rimangono, in Svizzera, ai minimi storici.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Il “vecchio” indice di fiducia dei consumatori così come era stato calcolato prima dell’ottobre 2009 è lievemente peggiorato tra luglio e aprile (-13 punti a luglio contro -9 ad aprile). &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Adeguamento del piano della rilevazione &lt;br /&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;Da aprile del 2012 il sondaggio sulla fiducia dei consumatori è svolto con un adeguamento della struttura dell’indagine. L'obiettivo dell'adeguamento era quello di rispecchiare ancora meglio le caratteristiche della popolazione svizzera nel campione rappresentativo utilizzato per il sondaggio. Gli adeguamenti che dovrebbero contribuire a migliorare la rappresentazione dell’insieme di base sono quattro:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;mentre finora il sondaggio ha considerato soltanto la Svizzera tedesca e la Svizzera romanda, in futuro coinvolgerà anche il Ticino;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;il numero delle interviste è aumentato da 1100 a circa 1200; &lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;il rilevamento avviene secondo la “base di campionamento per le indagini presso le persone e le economie domestiche”***dell’Ufficio federale di statistica (UST); &lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;le persone di cui non si conosce il numero di telefono fisso hanno la possibilità di rispondere alle domande online o mediante un numero di telefono gratuito.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;È inoltre cambiato l’istituto che svolge il sondaggio**** e le indagini sono state prolungate da due a tre settimane. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Nonostante le modifiche nella struttura dell’indagine e dell’estensione del campione di rilevazione, in linea di principio l’interpretazione dell’indice di fiducia dei consumatori rimane invariata. A fini di controllo, per i sondaggi da aprile a luglio 2012, è stata condotta una duplice rilevazione, secondo il vecchio e il nuovo metodo d’indagine. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Durante questa fase sperimentale non sono state riscontrate differenze significative. Di conseguenza l’ulteriore conduzione dell’indagine con la nuova struttura non limita la continuità e la comparabilità dei risultati nel tempo. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;* Su mandato della SECO, nei mesi di gennaio, aprile, luglio e ottobre circa 1’200 nuclei familiari vengono interpellati in merito alla loro valutazione soggettiva della situazione economica, delle loro condizioni finanziarie, dell’andamento dei prezzi, della sicurezza dei posti di lavoro, ecc. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;**Dalla pubblicazione dei risultati della rilevazione di ottobre 2009 sono state aggiunte due domande. Una riguarda le aspettative relative all’andamento della disoccupazione, l’altra le possibilità di risparmio. Queste nuove domande permettono di calcolare il nuovo indice della fiducia dei consumatori ufficiale, compatibile con i dati dell’UE. Le tre nuove serie di dati trimestrali iniziano da aprile 2007 (vedi la nota tecnica «Ampliamento del sondaggio» del 4 novembre 2009 all’indirizzo: http://www.seco.admin.ch/themen/00374/00453/index.html?lang=it).&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;***Per ulteriori informazioni: http://www.bfs.admin.ch/bfs/portal/fr/index/news/00/08.html &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;****L’istituto che svolge le indagini di mercato, su incarico della SECO, ora è il DemoScope (http://www.demoscope.ch/).&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Segreteria di Stato dell'economia SECO Holzikofenweg 36 CH-3003 Berna tel. +41 58 462 56 56 fax +41 58 462 56 00</contact>
      <attachment id="156464">
        <title>Tabella - Indice relativo al clima di fiducia dei consumatori</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>24</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/27649.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="156465">
        <title>Grafico - Indice relativo al clima di fiducia dei consumatori</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>96</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/27650.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <link id="156466">
        <title>I dati e il questionario</title>
        <uri>https://www.seco.admin.ch/seco/it/home/wirtschaftslage---wirtschaftspolitik/Wirtschaftslage/Konsumentenstimmung.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Weakening in Consumer Confidence</title>
      <lead>The consumer confidence survey conducted for the State Secretariat for Economic Affairs (SECO) showed a slight deterioration between April and July. The index, calculated on the basis of a quarterly survey*, reached -17 points in July 2012 (compared with -8 in April). This fall in consumer confidence is attributable to the more pessimistic expectations with regard to future economic development, together with an anticipated more pronounced rise in unemployment. </lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Of the four sub-indices which are included in the calculation of the consumer confidence index**, two showed a significant deterioration between April and July 2012. This relates to the assessment regarding the development of the overall economic situation over the next 12 months (-20 points in July, compared with -2 in April) as well as to consumer expectations concerning unemployment (+62 points in July compared with +49 in April). By contrast, the assessment of the future development of consumers’ personal financial situations over the next 12 months persisted around the same level as the April figures (-3 points in July com-pared with 0 in April). The same applies to the assessment by consumers of their future sav-ings opportunities (+15 points in July compared with +20 in April).&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Other sub-indices in the survey which are not included for the purpose of calculating the overall index, showed a deterioration in some areas compared with April. In particular, there was a pessimistic assessment of the general economic situation over the last twelve months (-24 points in July compared with -18 in April) and consumers were also less favourable in their assessment of job security (-72 points in July compared with -64 in April). By contrast there was virtually no change in the attitude towards the timing of larger purchases (-2 points compared with +1 in April), the assessment of consumers’ own current savings opportunities (+40 points compared with +41 in April) nor in the assessment of the past personal financial situation (-12 points in July compared with -9 points in April). &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Consumers changed their assessment of inflation over the last 12 months which they saw as being lower than in April (+22 points in July compared with +32 in April). Expectations of in-flation over the next 12 months remained however at a similar level to those in April (+32 points in July compared with +34 in April). Consumer expectations of inflation and their as-sessment of past inflation remain at a very low level in Switzerland, as they have been since the beginning of 2009. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Between July and April there was also a slight deterioration in the “old” consumer confidence index, as had been calculated prior to October 2009 (-13 points in July compared with -9 in April).&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Amendment to the survey design&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;From April 2012 the consumer confidence survey will be conducted with some amendments. The aim of these was to guarantee a more accurate representative sample of the Swiss pop-ulation used for the survey. The following four amendments are intended to improve the sur-vey's representativeness:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Whilst the consumer confidence survey previously only covered the German and French speaking regions of Switzerland, the Tessin region (the Italian speaking part) will now also be included.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;The number of interviews was increased from 1’100 to approx. 1’200. &lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;The random sampling will now be conducted within the framework set by the Swiss Federal Statistical Office (FSO) “Framework for Random Sampling for Individuals and Households Surveys (SRPH)***“. &lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Individuals whose landline phone details are not available have the option of answer-ing the questions online or by using a free phone number.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;In addition, a different market research institute is in charge of the surveys for the SECO****. The survey period was extended from 2 to 3 weeks. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Despite changes in the survey design and the review of the scope of the sampling, the inter-pretation of the consumer confidence index is fundamentally not called into question. For control purposes duplicated surveys based on old and new methodologies were conducted for the April and July 2012 surveys. There were no significant differences identified during this test phase. Consequently, conducting the survey in future using the new design will not restrict the continuity nor the temporal comparability of the results.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;*In the months of January, April, July and October, about 1’200 households are surveyed on behalf of SECO regarding their subjective assessment of the economic situation, their personal financial situation, inflation, job security etc. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;**Two additional questions were included in the survey in October 2009. One is a question regarding unem-ployment expectations and another is a question about the probability of households being able to save in the future. The new questions help in calculating a new, official, more EU compatible consumer confidence index for Switzerland. The three new quarterly series begin in April 2007 (see technical notes “Extension of survey" dated 4 November 2009 at: http://www.seco.admin.ch/themen/00374/00453/index.html?lang=en. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;***For further information: http://www.bfs.admin.ch/bfs/portal/de/index/news/00/08.html.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;****The market research institute DemoScope (http://www.demoscope.ch/) will now be conducting the surveys on behalf of the SECO.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>State Secretariat for Economic Affairs SECO Holzikofenweg 36 CH-3003 Bern Tel. +41 58 462 56 56 Fax +41 58 462 56 00</contact>
      <attachment id="156467">
        <title>Consumer Confidence Survey Tables</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>22</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/27653.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="156468">
        <title>Graphic - Consumer Confidence Survey</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>96</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/27652.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <link id="156469">
        <title>Number series and questionnaire</title>
        <uri>https://www.seco.admin.ch/seco/en/home/wirtschaftslage---wirtschaftspolitik/Wirtschaftslage/Konsumentenstimmung.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <offers>
      <offer id="156" org-id="703">
        <name lang="de">BIP-Quartalsdaten und Konjunkturtendenzen</name>
        <name lang="fr">Données trimestrielles PIB et tendances conjoncturelles</name>
        <name lang="it">Tendenze congiunturali</name>
        <name lang="en">Quarterly data on GDP and economic trends</name>
      </offer>
    </offers>
    <topics>
      <topic id="47">
        <name lang="de">Wirtschaft</name>
        <name lang="fr">Économie</name>
        <name lang="it">Economia</name>
        <name lang="en">Economic Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
