<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="72264" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2018-09-21</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="1070" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>1070</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Der Bundesrat</name>
      <name lang="fr">Conseil fédéral</name>
      <name lang="it">Il Consiglio federale</name>
      <name lang="en">The Federal Council</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.admin.ch/gov/de/start.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.admin.ch/gov/fr/accueil.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.admin.ch/gov/it/pagina-iniziale.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.admin.ch/gov/en/start.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="yes" id="1080" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>701</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Staatssekretariat für Bildung, Forschung und Innovation</name>
      <name lang="fr">Secrétariat d'Etat à la formation, à la recherche et à l'innovation</name>
      <name lang="it">Segreteria di Stato per la formazione, la ricerca e l'innovazione</name>
      <name lang="en">State Secretariat for Education, Research and Innovation</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.sbfi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.sbfi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.sbfi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.sbfi.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@sbfi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@sbfi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@sbfi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@sbfi.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="1070">
      <name lang="de">Der Bundesrat</name>
      <name lang="fr">Conseil fédéral</name>
      <name lang="it">Il Consiglio federale</name>
      <name lang="en">The Federal Council</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.admin.ch/gov/de/start.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.admin.ch/gov/fr/accueil.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.admin.ch/gov/it/pagina-iniziale.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.admin.ch/gov/en/start.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <department id="701">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Wirtschaft, Bildung und Forschung</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'économie, de la formation et de la recherche</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'economia, della formazione e della ricerca</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Economic Affairs, Education and Research</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Nationales Forschungsprogramm «Digitale Transformation» lanciert</title>
      <lead>Der Bundesrat hat an seiner Sitzung vom 21. September 2018 ein neues Nationales Forschungsprogramm zum Thema „Digitale Transformation“ lanciert. Hauptziel des Programms ist es, Wissen über die Chancen und Risiken der Digitalisierung für die Gesellschaft und Wirtschaft zu erarbeiten. Im Zentrum stehen dabei die Forschungsschwerpunkte «Bildung, Lernen und digitaler Wandel», «Ethik, Vertrauenswürdigkeit und Governance» sowie «Digitale Wirtschaft und Arbeitsmarkt». Die Dauer des Programms beträgt fünf Jahre. Das Budget beläuft sich auf insgesamt 30 Millionen Franken. Das Programm ist eine Massnahme des «Aktionsplans Digitalisierung im Bereich Bildung, Forschung und Innovation in den Jahren 2019-2020».</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Im Rahmen des neuen Nationalen Forschungsprogramms (NFP) werden die Wirkungszusammenhänge sowie die konkreten Auswirkungen der digitalen Transformation in der Schweiz untersucht. Ziel ist es, zu verstehen, welche Voraussetzungen notwendig sind, um die Transformation erfolgreich bewältigen zu können. Dazu werden anhand der drei genannten Forschungsschwerpunkte die Chancen und Risiken, die sich aus der digitalen Transformation für die Schweizer Wirtschaft und Gesellschaft ergeben, erforscht. Darauf basierend werden mögliche Entwicklungswege erarbeitet, wie die Herausforderungen optimal genutzt und allfällige negative Auswirkungen abgefedert werden können. Schliesslich sollen aus dem NFP Grundlagen für optimale Rahmenbedingungen für die Gestaltung des digitalen Wandels herausgearbeitet und Handlungswissen für die verschiedenen Institutionen und Bereiche bereitgestellt werden. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Das Forschungsprogramm umfasst folgende drei aufeinander abgestimmte Forschungsschwerpunkte (Module):&lt;/p&gt; &lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;«Bildung, Lernen und digitaler Wandel»: In diesem Modul werden die Auswirkungen der Digitalisierung auf die Bildung (Inhalte und Kompetenzen sowie Kompetenzvermittlung), auf die lebenslangen Lernprozesse und auf die für die Bildung relevanten Institutionen untersucht. Dabei sollen Chancen und Herausforderungen identifiziert sowie Strategien entwickelt werden, die es ermöglichen, das «Bildungssystem» auf allen Stufen erfolgreich weiterzuentwickeln. Die Forschungsarbeiten in diesem Modul können sämtliche Facetten des Lernens und der Bildung betreffen.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;«Ethik, Vertrauenswürdigkeit und Governance»: Im Zentrum dieses Moduls stehen die ethischen, organisatorischen, rechtlichen und technischen Herausforderungen zur Sicherung und Stärkung des Vertrauens in digitale Infrastrukturen oder digitale Dienstleistungen. Im Speziellen sollen diese Herausforderungen anhand einzelner relevanter Bereiche und aufgrund neuester technologischer Entwicklungen wie beispielsweise «Blockchain», «Internet of Things» oder «Cybersecurity» untersucht werden.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;«Digitale Wirtschaft und Arbeitsmarkt»: Im Zentrum dieses Moduls stehen die Wechselwirkungen und Auswirkungen des digitalen Wandels auf die Wirtschaft (Produktivität und Wettbewerbsfähigkeit des Schweizer Werkplatzes) und den Arbeitsmarkt. Dabei sollen neue digitale Märkte, Organisationsformen, Geschäftsmodelle und die Auswirkungen auf die Arbeitswelt, die Arbeitsorganisation und -inhalte sowie die Regionalentwicklung in der Schweiz untersucht und die damit verbundenen Chancen und Risiken identifiziert werden.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt; &lt;p&gt;Der Bundesrat hat im Rahmen des «Aktionsplan Digitalisierung im Bereich Bildung, Forschung und Innovation in den Jahren 2019-2020» im Juli 2017 das Eidgenössische Departement für Wirtschaft, Bildung und Forschung beauftragt, eine NFP-Serie zum Thema «Digitaler Wandel von Wirtschaft und Gesellschaft» zu prüfen und bis zum 31. Dezember 2018 einen Antrag zur Lancierung zu unterbreiten.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Mit den Nationalen Forschungsprogrammen fördert der Bund Forschungsprojekte, die zur Lösung aktueller Fragen und Herausforderungen von nationaler Bedeutung beitragen können. Für die Durchführung ist der Schweizerische Nationalfonds zuständig. NFP werden nach jeweils rund fünfjähriger Laufzeit abgeschlossen und ihre Ergebnisse der Öffentlichkeit kommuniziert.&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Nicole Schaad SBFI Ressortleiterin Nationale Forschung nicole.schaad@sbfi.admin.ch; Tel. +41 58 463 59 85</contact>
      <link id="181587">
        <title>Weitere Informationen</title>
        <uri>http://www.sbfi.admin.ch/nfp</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Le programme national de recherche « Transformation numérique » est lancé</title>
      <lead>Durant sa séance du 21 septembre 2018, le Conseil fédéral a lancé un nouveau programme national de recherche intitulé «Transformation numérique». L’objectif principal de ce programme est de mieux cerner les chances et les risques de la numérisation pour la société et l’économie. Le programme s’intéresse en particulier aux axes prioritaires de recherche «Formation, apprentissage et tournant numérique», «Éthique, fiabilité et gouvernance» et «Économie numérique et marché du travail». Le programme dure cinq ans et son budget se monte à 30 millions de francs. Il relève du plan d’action «Numérisation pour le domaine FRI durant les années 2019-2020».</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Le nouveau programme national de recherche (PNR) étudie les interactions et l’impact concret de la transformation numérique en Suisse. Son but est de déterminer les conditions préalables permettant de mener à bien ce processus de transformation. Il s’agit d’abord, en s’appuyant sur les trois axes de recherche mentionnés plus haut, d’étudier les chances et les risques de la transformation numérique pour la société et l’économie suisses. En se fondant sur les données recueillies, il faut ensuite esquisser des pistes de développement pour déterminer comment tirer le meilleur parti des défis et limiter les effets négatifs. Dans la perspective du PNR, iI convient enfin, d’une part, de créer des bases servant à l’établissement de conditions-cadres optimales nécessaires à la gestion du tournant numérique et, d’autre part, de mettre le savoir spécifique à la disposition des institutions et des domaines concernés. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Le programme de recherche comprend trois axes prioritaires de recherche (modules) interdépendants:&lt;/p&gt; &lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;«Formation, apprentissage et tournant numérique»: ce module étudie l’impact de la numérisation sur la formation (contenus, compétences et transmission de compétences), sur l’apprentissage tout au long de la vie et sur les principales institutions en charge de la formation. Concrètement, ce module doit permettre d’identifier les chances et les défis et d’élaborer des stratégies assurant le développement futur du système de formation à tous les échelons. Toutes les facettes de l’apprentissage et de la formation sont abordées dans ce module.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;«Éthique, fiabilité et gouvernance»: ce module porte sur les défis éthiques, organisationnels, juridiques et techniques qui garantissent et renforcent la confiance dans les infrastructures ou dans les prestations numériques. Ces défis doivent être notamment examinés en prenant en considération les différents domaines les plus importants et les derniers développements technologiques (blockchain, internet des objets ou cybersécurité).&lt;br /&gt; &lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;«Économie numérique et marché du travail»: ce module traite des interactions et de l’impact du tournant numérique sur l’économie (productivité et compétitivité de la place économique suisse) et sur le marché du travail. Ce module sert non seulement à examiner les marchés émergents du numérique, les formes d’organisation, les modèles d’affaires et les effets sur le monde du travail, les organisations et les contenus propres au monde du travail ainsi que le développement régional dans notre pays, mais aussi à identifier les chances et les risques afférents.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt; &lt;p&gt;Dans le cadre du plan d’action «Numérisation pour le domaine FRI durant les années 2019-2020», le Conseil fédéral a chargé en juillet 2017 le Département fédéral de l’économie, de la formation et de la recherche (DEFR) d’examiner une série de programmes nationaux de recherche sur le thème «Tournant numérique de l’économie et de la société» et de lui soumettre d’ici au 31 décembre 2018 une proposition en vue de leur lancement.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Par les programmes nationaux de recherche, la Confédération encourage des projets de recherche destinés à produire des connaissances scientifiques servant à définir des orientations ou des actions dans un domaine donné ou contribuant à la résolution de problèmes actuels d’importance nationale. Ces programmes, d’une durée d’environ cinq ans, sont dirigés par le Fonds national suisse et leurs résultats sont rendus publics.&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Nicole Schaad SEFRI Responsable de l’unité Recherche nationale nicole.schaad@sbfi.admin.ch, tél. +41 58 463 59 85</contact>
      <link id="181588">
        <title>Informations complémentaires</title>
        <uri>http://www.sbfi.admin.ch/pnr</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Lanciato un nuovo programma nazionale di ricerca sulla svolta digitale</title>
      <lead>Nella riunione del 21 settembre 2018 il Consiglio federale ha lanciato un nuovo programma nazionale di ricerca sulla svolta digitale. L’obiettivo è raccogliere e sviluppare nuove conoscenze sulle opportunità e sui rischi che la digitalizzazione rappresenta per la società e per l’economia. Il programma sarà incentrato sulle priorità di ricerca «formazione, apprendimento e svolta digitale», «etica, fiducia e governance» nonché «economia digitale e mercato del lavoro». Il programma, che durerà cinque anni e assorbirà risorse dell’ordine di 30 milioni di franchi, è una delle misure adottate nell’ambito del «piano d’azione per la formazione, la ricerca e l’innovazione nel periodo 2019‒2020».</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Nell’ambito del nuovo programma nazionale di ricerca (PNR) saranno esaminate le conseguenze e gli effetti concreti della trasformazione digitale in Svizzera. L’obiettivo è capire quali condizioni devono essere soddisfatte per poter affrontare questo fenomeno di petto. In base alle suddette priorità di ricerca saranno studiate le opportunità e i rischi che la digitalizzazione comporta per la società e l’economia svizzera. Si tratterà poi di tracciare i possibili percorsi evolutivi per sfruttare al meglio le nuove opportunità e ammortizzare gli eventuali rischi. Il PNR dovrà permettere di elaborare le fondamenta su cui edificare le migliori condizioni quadro possibili per gestire la trasformazione digitale e di offrire a istituzioni e settori interessati le giuste conoscenze operative.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Il programma comprende le seguenti tre priorità di ricerca coordinate (moduli):&lt;/p&gt; &lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;«formazione, apprendimento e svolta digitale»: questo modulo esamina gli effetti della digitalizzazione sulla formazione (contenuti, competenze e trasmissione delle stesse), sui processi di apprendimento permanente e sulle istituzioni rilevanti. L’obiettivo è identificare le opportunità e le sfide ed elaborare strategie che consentano di sviluppare con successo il «sistema educativo» a tutti i livelli. In questo modulo le attività di ricerca possono coprire tutti gli aspetti dell’apprendimento e dell’educazione;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;«etica, fiducia e governance»: questo modulo si concentra sulle sfide etiche, organizzative, giuridiche e tecniche necessarie per garantire e rafforzare la fiducia nelle infrastrutture o nei servizi digitali. Queste sfide saranno esaminate con particolare riferimento a singoli settori di rilievo e in base agli ultimi sviluppi tecnologici (blockchain, Internet degli oggetti o sicurezza informatica);&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;«economia digitale e mercato del lavoro». Questo modulo verte sulle interazioni e sugli effetti della svolta digitale sull’economia (produttività e competitività della piazza industriale svizzera) e sul mercato del lavoro. Nell’ottica di identificare opportunità e rischi, si tratterà di esaminare i mercati digitali, le forme organizzative e i nuovi modelli di business nonché il loro impatto sul mondo del lavoro, sull’organizzazione e sui contenuti del lavoro e sullo sviluppo regionale in Svizzera.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt; &lt;p&gt;A luglio 2017, nell’ambito del «Piano d’azione per la formazione, la ricerca e l’innovazione nel periodo 2019‒2020», il Consiglio federale aveva incaricato il Dipartimento federale della formazione, della ricerca e dell’innovazione DEFR di esaminare l’ipotesi di lanciare una serie di PNR sull’evoluzione digitale dell’economia e della società e di presentargli una proposta di realizzazione entro il 31 dicembre 2017.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Tramite questi PNR la Confederazione sostiene progetti di sviluppo delle conoscenze finalizzati a definire orientamenti e piani d’intervento per risolvere problemi d’attualità di portata nazionale. La realizzazione di questi programmi, di durata quinquennale, compete al Fondo nazionale svizzero (FNS), che al loro termine ne pubblica i risultati.&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Nicole Schaad SEFRI capounità Ricerca nazionale nicole.schaad@sbfi.admin.ch; tel. +41 58 463 59 85</contact>
      <link id="181589">
        <title>Maggiori informazioni</title>
        <uri>http://www.sbfi.admin.ch/pnr-i</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Launch of National Research Programme on Digital Change</title>
      <lead>At its meeting of 21 September, the Federal Council launched a new National Research Programme into Digital Change. The main aim of this programme is to increase our understanding of the opportunities and risks of digitalisation for society and the economy. There are three core research modules: Education, Learning and Digital Change; Ethics, Reliability and Governance; and Digital Economy and the Labour Market. The programme will run for five years and has a budget of CHF 30 million. It forms part of the Action Plan on Digitalisation in Education, Research and Innovation for the years 2019 to 2020.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;The new National Research Programme (NRP) addresses the interrelationships and concrete effects of digital change in Switzerland. The programme sets out to understand what needs to be done to face up to the challenges of digitalisation. Research will be carried out into the opportunities and risks that digital change poses for society and the economy in Switzerland. This will provide a basis for developing possible ways of making full use of the opportunities, and mitigating any negative effects. Finally, the NRP will provide a basis upon which to develop an optimum framework for effecting digital change in society, including the know-how required by a range of institutions and sectors. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The NRP has three aligned research modules: &lt;/p&gt; &lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Education, Learning and Digital Change: This module looks at the impacts of digitalisation on education (content, skills and skills transfer), at life-long processes and at the institutions pertinent to education. It aims to identify the opportunities and challenges, and develop strategies for developing the education system at all levels. Research in this module may pertain to all facets of learning and education.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Ethics, Reliability and Governance: Central to this module are the ethical, organisational, legal and technical challenges involved in ensuring and building trust in digital infrastructure and digital services. These challenges will be addressed with regard to specific fields and in the light of the latest technological developments such as blockchain, Internet of Things and cybersecurity.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Digital Economy and the Labour Market: This module addresses the key interactions and effects of digital change on the economy (Swiss productivity and competitiveness). It will look at new digital markets, organisational forms and business models, and the effects of these on the world of work, the organisation and content of our work, and regional development in Switzerland, in order to identify the opportunities and risks involved.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt; &lt;p&gt;As part of its Action Plan on Digitalisation in Education, Research and Innovation for the years 2019 to 2020, in July 2017 the Federal Council commissioned the Federal Department of Economic Affairs, Education and Research to report on an NRP series into digital change in the economy and society, and to submit a proposal for the launch of this NRP by 31 December of this year. &lt;/p&gt;The National Research Programmes are a federal instrument to promote research projects which address current issues and challenges of national importance. They are run by the Swiss National Science Foundation. NRPs run for five years and the results are made public. </text>
      <contact>Nicole Schaad SERI Head of National Research nicole.schaad@sbfi.admin.ch; Tel. +41 58 463 59 85</contact>
      <link id="181590">
        <title>Further information</title>
        <uri>http://www.sbfi.admin.ch/nrp</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="8">
        <name lang="de">Bildung und Forschung</name>
        <name lang="fr">Formation et recherche</name>
        <name lang="it">Formazione e ricerca</name>
        <name lang="en">Education and Research</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="10">
        <name lang="de">Bundesrat</name>
        <name lang="fr">Conseil fédéral</name>
        <name lang="it">Consiglio federale</name>
        <name lang="en">Federal Council</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="45">
        <name lang="de">Technologie</name>
        <name lang="fr">Technologie</name>
        <name lang="it">Tecnologia</name>
        <name lang="en">Technology</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
