<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="72174" revoked="no">
    <version>2</version>
    <pubdate>2018-09-14</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="1070" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>1070</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Der Bundesrat</name>
      <name lang="fr">Conseil fédéral</name>
      <name lang="it">Il Consiglio federale</name>
      <name lang="en">The Federal Council</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.admin.ch/gov/de/start.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.admin.ch/gov/fr/accueil.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.admin.ch/gov/it/pagina-iniziale.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.admin.ch/gov/en/start.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="yes" id="1060" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>601</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Staatssekretariat für internationale Finanzfragen</name>
      <name lang="fr">Secrétariat d'Etat aux questions financières internationales</name>
      <name lang="it">Segreteria di Stato per le questioni finanziarie internazionali</name>
      <name lang="en">State Secretariat for International Financial Matters</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.sif.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.sif.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.sif.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.sif.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@sif.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@sif.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@sif.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@sif.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="1070">
      <name lang="de">Der Bundesrat</name>
      <name lang="fr">Conseil fédéral</name>
      <name lang="it">Il Consiglio federale</name>
      <name lang="en">The Federal Council</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.admin.ch/gov/de/start.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.admin.ch/gov/fr/accueil.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.admin.ch/gov/it/pagina-iniziale.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.admin.ch/gov/en/start.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <department id="601">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Finanzdepartement</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des finances</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale delle finanze</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Finance</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.efd.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.dff.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.efd.admin.ch/efd/it/home.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.efd.admin.ch/efd/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Bundesrat verlängert Übergangsfrist für Meldung von Derivatetransaktionen durch kleine nicht-finanzielle Gegenparteien</title>
      <lead>Der Bundesrat hat an seiner Sitzung vom 14. September 2018 beschlossen, die Meldepflicht von Derivatetransaktionen für kleine nicht-finanzielle Gegenparteien per 1. Januar 2024 in Kraft zu setzen. Die Meldepflichten anderer Marktteilnehmer sind vom Entscheid nicht betroffen.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Das Finanzmarktinfrastrukturgesetz (FinfraG) ist zusammen mit der zugehörigen Verordnung am 1. Januar 2016 in Kraft getreten. Es regelt u.a. die Organisation und den Betrieb von Finanzmarktinfrastrukturen und das Marktverhalten im Derivatehandel, einschliesslich einer Meldepflicht für Derivatetransaktionen. Diese Meldepflicht verlangt, dass betroffene Marktakteure solche Transaktionen an zentrale Transaktionsregister melden. Heute gilt die Meldepflicht bereits für finanzielle Gegenparteien (u.a. Banken, Versicherungen) und für gewisse nicht-finanzielle Gegenparteien. Für kleine nicht-finanzielle Gegenparteien (z.B. Industrieunternehmen) wäre die Pflicht am 1. Januar 2019 in Kraft getreten.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Nun hat der Bundesrat an seiner Sitzung vom 14. September 2018 entschieden, die Meldepflicht von Derivatetransaktionen für kleine nicht-finanzielle Gegenparteien per 1. Januar 2024 in Kraft zu setzen und hierzu die entsprechende Übergangsfrist zu verlängern. Die entsprechende Änderung der bundesrätlichen Finanzmarktinfrastrukturverordnung (FinfraV) tritt am 1. Januar 2019 in Kraft. Die bereits geltenden Meldepflichten für andere Marktteilnehmer bleiben unberührt.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Der Bundesrat begründet seinen Entscheid mit der Tatsache, dass das FinfraG in den nächsten Jahren überprüft werden soll. Dies u.a. weil sich bereits heute internationale, z.B. in der Europäischen Union, und technologische Entwicklungen, z.B. im Bereich Fintech, abzeichnen, die Anlass zu einer Revision des FinfraG geben könnten. Diese Arbeiten zur Überprüfung des FinfraG nimmt das Eidgenössische Finanzdepartement (EFD) ab 2019 an die Hand. Vor diesem Hintergrund soll, auch um den administrativen Aufwand zu verringern, die Meldepflicht für kleine nicht-finanzielle Gegenparteien aufgeschoben werden, bis diese Überprüfung – und eine allfällige Anpassung des FinfraG – abgeschlossen sind.&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Frank Wettstein, Kommunikation Staatssekretariat für internationale Finanzfragen SIF Tel. +41 58 462 38 56, frank.wettstein@sif.admin.ch</contact>
      <attachment id="181550">
        <title>Finanzmarktinfrastrukturverordnung (FinfraV)</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>107</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/53652.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Le Conseil fédéral prolonge le délai transitoire pour la déclaration des opérations sur dérivés par les petites contreparties non financières</title>
      <lead>Lors de sa séance du 14 septembre 2018, le Conseil fédéral a décidé de mettre en vigueur au 1er janvier 2024 l’obligation de déclarer les opérations sur dérivés pour les petites contreparties non financières. Les obligations de déclarer d’autres participants aux marchés financiers ne sont pas concernées.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;La loi sur l’infrastructure des marchés financiers (LIMF) et l’ordonnance correspondante sont entrées en vigueur le 1er janvier 2016. La LIMF règle notamment l’organisation et l’exploitation des infrastructures des marchés financiers ainsi que le comportement sur le marché en matière de négociation de dérivés, y compris l’obligation de déclarer les opérations sur dérivés. Cette obligation exige des acteurs des marchés qu’ils déclarent de telles opérations à des référentiels centraux. Actuellement, l’obligation s’applique déjà aux contreparties financières (notamment aux banques et aux assurances) et à certaines contreparties non financières. Pour les petites contreparties non financières (par ex. les entreprises industrielles), il était prévu que l’obligation entre en vigueur le 1er janvier 2019.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Lors de sa séance du 14 septembre 2018, le Conseil fédéral a cependant décidé de mettre en vigueur au 1er janvier 2024 l’obligation pour les petites contreparties non financières de déclarer les opérations sur dérivés; il a donc prolongé le délai transitoire correspondant. La modification concernée de l’ordonnance sur l’infrastructure des marchés financiers entrera en vigueur le 1er janvier 2019. Les obligations de déclarer déjà en vigueur pour d’autres participants aux marchés restent inchangées.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Le Conseil fédéral justifie sa décision par le fait que la LIMF devra être réexaminée ces prochaines années. En effet, l’évolution qui se dessine déjà aux niveaux international (par ex. dans l’Union européenne) et technologique (par ex. dans le domaine des technologies financières) pourraient entraîner une révision de la LIMF. Le Département fédéral des finances commencera les travaux de réexamen de la LIMF en 2019. Dans ce contexte, il convient de reporter l’obligation de déclarer pour les petites contreparties non financières jusqu’à la fin de ce réexamen et de l’éventuelle révision de la LIMF, afin notamment de réduire la charge administrative qui découle de cette obligation.&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Frank Wettstein, Communication du Secrétariat d’État aux questions financières internationales SFI Tél. +41 58 462 38 56, frank.wettstein@sif.admin.ch</contact>
      <attachment id="181551">
        <title>Ordonnance sur l’infrastructure des marchés financiers</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>103</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/53653.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Il Consiglio federale prolunga il termine transitorio per l’obbligo delle piccole controparti non finanziarie di comunicare transazioni in derivati</title>
      <lead>Nella sua seduta del 14 settembre 2018, il Consiglio federale ha deciso di porre in vigore dal 1° gennaio 2024 l’obbligo di comunicazione di transazioni in derivati per le piccole controparti non finanziarie. Questa decisione non tange gli obblighi di comunicazione degli altri partecipanti al mercato.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;La legge del 19 giugno 2015 sull’infrastruttura finanziaria (LInFi) e la relativa ordinanza sono entrate in vigore il 1° gennaio 2016. La LInFi disciplina l’organizzazione e l’esercizio di infrastrutture del mercato finanziario e il comportamento sul mercato nel commercio di derivati, compreso l’obbligo di comunicazione per le transazioni in derivati. Tale obbligo richiede che gli attori interessati comunichino queste transazioni a un repertorio di dati sulle negoziazioni. Attualmente l’obbligo di comunicazione viene già applicato a controparti finanziarie (p. es. banche, assicurazioni) e a determinate controparti non finanziarie. Per le piccole controparti non finanziarie (ad es. imprese industriali) l’obbligo sarebbe entrato in vigore il 1° gennaio 2019.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Nella sua seduta del 14 settembre 2018, il Consiglio federale ha ora deciso di porre in vigore l’obbligo di comunicazione per transazioni in derivati per le piccole controparti non finanziarie dal 1° gennaio 2024 e quindi di prolungarne il termine transitorio. La relativa modifica dell’ordinanza del Consiglio federale sull’infrastruttura finanziaria (OInFi) entra in vigore il 1° gennaio 2019. Gli obblighi di comunicazione già in vigore per gli altri partecipanti al mercato restano invariati.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Il Consiglio federale motiva la sua decisione con il fatto che nei prossimi anni la LInFi dovrà essere sottoposta a verifica, anche perché già oggi si delineano sviluppi a livello internazionale – per esempio nell’Unione europea – e in ambito tecnologico – per esempio nel settore della tecnofinanza – che potrebbero rendere necessaria una revisione della LInFi. Il Dipartimento federale delle finanze (DFF) affronterà questi lavori di verifica della legge dal 2019. Alla luce di quanto precede, e anche per ridurre il dispendio amministrativo, l’obbligo di comunicazione per le piccole controparti non finanziarie sarà posposto fino alla conclusione di questa verifica e di un’eventuale modifica della LInFi.&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Frank Wettstein, Comunicazione, Segreteria di Stato per le questioni finanziarie internazionali SFI tel. +41 58 462 38 56, frank.wettstein@sif.admin.ch</contact>
      <attachment id="181552">
        <title>Ordinanza del Consiglio federale sull’infrastruttura finanziaria (OInFi)</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>101</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/53745.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Federal Council extends transitional period for reporting of derivative transactions by small non-financial counterparties</title>
      <lead>During its meeting on 14 September 2018, the Federal Council decided to bring the derivative transactions reporting duty for small non-financial counterparties into effect on 1 January 2024. The reporting duties of other market participants are not affected by the decision.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;The Financial Market Infrastructure Act (FinMIA), together with the associated ordinance, entered into force on 1 January 2016. Among other things, it regulates the organisation and operation of financial market infrastructures and market conduct concerning derivatives trading, including a reporting duty for derivative transactions. This reporting duty requires affected market players to report such transactions to central trade repositories. At present, the reporting duty already applies for financial counterparties (including banks and insurers) and certain non-financial counterparties. The duty would have come into force on 1 January 2019 for small non-financial counterparties (e.g. industrial companies).&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;During its meeting on 14 September 2018, the Federal Council decided to bring the derivative transactions reporting duty for small non-financial counterparties into effect on 1 January 2024 and to extend the corresponding transitional period. The corresponding amendment to the Federal Council's Financial Market Infrastructure Ordinance (FinMIO) will enter into force on 1 January 2019. The reporting duties already in force for other market participants are unaffected.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The Federal Council based its decision on the fact that the FinMIA is to be reviewed in the coming years. This is partly because we are already witnessing the emergence of international developments, e.g. in the European Union, and technological developments, e.g. in the fintech area, that could give rise to a revision of the FinMIA. The Federal Department of Finance (FDF) will work on reviewing the FinMIA from 2019. Against this backdrop, the reporting duty for small non-financial counterparties is to be postponed until this review – and any adjustment to the FinMIA – have been completed.&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Frank Wettstein, Communications, State Secretariat for International Financial Matters SIF Tel. +41 58 462 38 56, frank.wettstein@sif.admin.ch</contact>
      <attachment id="181550">
        <title>Finanzmarktinfrastrukturverordnung (FinfraV)</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>107</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/53652.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <offers>
      <offer id="291" org-id="1060">
        <name lang="de">Wirtschaft, Währung, Finanzplatz</name>
        <name lang="fr">Economie, monnaie, place financière</name>
        <name lang="it">Economia, Moneta, Piazza finanziaria</name>
        <name lang="en">Economic, Monetary and Financial Affairs</name>
      </offer>
    </offers>
    <keywords>
      <keyword id="118" org-id="1060">
        <name lang="de">Finanzmarktregulierung und -aufsicht</name>
        <name lang="fr">Réglementation et surveillance des marchés financiers</name>
        <name lang="it">Regolamentazione e vigilanza dei mercati finanziari</name>
        <name lang="en">Financial market regulation and supervision</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="126" org-id="1060">
        <name lang="de">Finanzplatz Schweiz</name>
        <name lang="fr">Place financière suisse</name>
        <name lang="it">Piazza finanziaria svizzera</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland as a financial centre</name>
      </keyword>
    </keywords>
    <topics>
      <topic id="35">
        <name lang="de">Finanzplatz</name>
        <name lang="fr">Place financière</name>
        <name lang="it">Piazza finanziaria</name>
        <name lang="en">Financial Centre</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="44">
        <name lang="de">Steuern</name>
        <name lang="fr">Impôts</name>
        <name lang="it">Imposte</name>
        <name lang="en">Taxation</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="47">
        <name lang="de">Wirtschaft</name>
        <name lang="fr">Économie</name>
        <name lang="it">Economia</name>
        <name lang="en">Economic Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
