<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="33169" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2010-05-19</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="201" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>201</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="201">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Bundesrätin Micheline Calmy-Rey in der Republik Moldau</title>
      <lead>Bundesrätin Micheline Calmy-Rey ist am Mittwoch nach Chisinau in der Republik Moldau gereist, wo sie an der regionalen Botschafterkonferenz, dem Treffen der Schweizer Botschafter der südost- und osteuropäischen Länder, teilnimmt. Am Mittwochabend hat sie in Chisinau Iurie Leanca, den stellvertretenden Premierminister und Aussenminister der Republik Moldau, zu offiziellen Gesprächen getroffen. Anlässlich des Treffens wurden ein Rückübernahmeabkommen sowie ein Abkommen zur Visaerleichterung unterzeichnet.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Das Gespräch mit Aussenminister Iurie Leanca in Moldaus Hauptstadt Chisinau diente&amp;nbsp;der Bestandesaufnahme und Weiterentwicklung&amp;nbsp;der bilateralen Beziehungen Schweiz – Moldau. Die Schweiz&amp;nbsp;ist das drittgrösste Geberland in der Republik Moldau und investiert jährlich rund 6,2 Mio. CHF in Projekte in den Bereichen Wasser und Gesundheit. Sie&amp;nbsp;ist mit einem Kooperationsbüro der Direktion für Entwicklung und Zusammenarbeit (DEZA) in Chisinau präsent.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Mit der Unterzeichnung eines Visaerleichterungsabkommens sowie eines Rückübernahmeabkommens wurde die Zusammenarbeit im Migrationsbereich verstärkt. Die Erleichterungen bei der Visaerteilung fördert den persönlichen, kulturellen und wirtschaftlichen Austausch zwischen den beiden Staaten. Mit diesem Abkommen gleicht die Schweiz ihre Praxis bei der Vergabe von Kurzzeitvisa an diejenige der anderen Schengen-Staaten an.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Das Rückübernahmeabkommen stellt sicher, dass Personen mit unbefugtem Aufenthalt ordnungsgemäss und in vereinfachtem Verfahren in die Republik Moldau rückgeführt werden können. Das neue Abkommen passt die Zusammenarbeit an die aktuellen Standards an und ersetzt das bisherige Abkommen von 2003.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Bundesrätin Micheline Calmy-Rey&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;kündigte zudem an, dass Bürger der Republik Moldau ab 25. Mai dieses Jahres Visa für die Schweiz im Visa-Center der ungarischen Botschaft in Chisinau beantragen können und dafür nicht mehr nach Kiev reisen müssen. Das ungarische Visa-Center stellt unter anderem auch für Österreich und Dänemark Visa aus.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Am Donnerstag nimmt Bundesrätin Micheline Calmy-Rey an der regionalen Konferenz der Schweizer Botschafter der südost- und osteuropäischen Länder teil. Thema des Treffens sind Verhältnis und Engagement der Schweiz in Bezug auf diejenigen Staaten der Region, die nicht Mitglieder der EU sind. Im Zentrum steht die Frage nach der Wirksamkeit der aussenpolitischen&amp;nbsp;Instrumente der Schweiz im Vergleich zur Politik anderer Partner und Akteure in dieser Region angefangen bei der EU.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Information EDA Bundeshaus West CH-3003 Bern Tel.: +41 (0)31 322 31 53 Fax: +41 (0)31 324 90 47 E-Mail: info@eda.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Voyage de la Conseillère fédérale Micheline Calmy-Rey en République de Moldavie</title>
      <lead>La Conseillère fédérale Micheline Calmy-Rey s’est rendue mercredi à Chisinau, en République de Moldavie, où elle participe à la conférence régionale des ambassadeurs, la rencontre des ambassadeurs suisses accrédités dans les pays d’Europe orientale et du Sud-Est. Mercredi soir, elle a rencontré à Chisinau, pour un entretien officiel, Iurie Leanca, vice-Premier ministre et ministre des affaires étrangères de la République de Moldavie. Un accord de réadmission et un accord visant à faciliter la délivrance de visas ont été signés à cette occasion.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;L’entretien avec le ministre des affaires étrangères Iurie Leanca, qui a eu lieu à Chisinau, la capitale moldave, avait pour objet de faire le point sur les relations bilatérales entre la Suisse et la Moldavie et de les développer. La Suisse est le troisième pays donateur en République de Moldavie, où elle investit annuellement quelque 6,2 millions de francs dans des projets dans les domaines de l’eau et de la santé. Elle est présente à Chisinau à travers un bureau de coopération de la Direction du développement et de la coopération (DDC).&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;La coopération en matière de migration a été renforcée par la signature d’un accord visant à faciliter la délivrance de visas et d’un accord de réadmission. La facilitation de la délivrance de visas favorise les échanges humains, culturels et économiques entre les deux pays. Par la signature de cet accord, la Suisse aligne sa pratique en matière d’octroi de visas de court séjour sur celle des autres États Schengen.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;L’accord de réadmission garantit que les personnes en situation irrégulière peuvent être rapatriées en République de Moldavie dans les règles et selon une procédure simplifiée. Le nouvel accord adapte la coopération aux normes actuelles et remplace l’accord de 2003.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;La Conseillère fédérale Micheline Calmy-Rey a en outre annoncé qu’à partir du 25 mai 2010, les ressortissants de la République de Moldavie pourraient déposer leurs demandes de visa pour la Suisse au Visa-Center de l’ambassade de Hongrie à Chisinau et qu’ils n’auraient donc plus à se rendre à Kiev. Le Visa-Center hongrois délivre également des visas pour d’autres pays, dont l’Autriche et le Danemark.&lt;/p&gt; Jeudi, Mme Calmy-Rey participera à la conférence régionale des ambassadeurs suisses accrédités dans les pays d’Europe orientale et du Sud-Est. Cette rencontre a pour thème les relations de la Suisse avec les États de la région qui ne sont pas membres de l’UE et son engagement dans ces pays. L’accent est porté sur la question de l’efficacité des instruments de politique extérieure de la Suisse, au regard de la politique menée par d’autres acteurs et partenaires dans cette région, à commencer par l’UE.&amp;nbsp;</text>
      <contact>Information DFAE Palais fédéral ouest CH-3003 Berne Tél.: (+41) 031 322 31 53 Fax: (+41) 031 324 90 47 E-Mail: info@eda.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>La Consigliera federale Micheline Calmy-Rey nella Repubblica di Moldova</title>
      <lead>La Consigliera federale Micheline Calmy-Rey è partita mercoledì per Chisinau, nella Repubblica di Moldova, dove parteciperà alla Conferenza regionale degli ambasciatori, che prevede l’incontro tra gli ambasciatori svizzeri dei Paesi dell’Europa orientale e sudorientale. Mercoledì sera a Chisinau ha incontrato Iurie Leanca, vice primo ministro e ministro degli esteri della Repubblica di Moldova, per un colloquio ufficiale. Durante questo incontro sono stati firmati un accordo di riammissione e un accordo di facilitazione del rilascio di visti.</lead>
      <text link="no">Il colloquio con il ministro degli esteri Iurie Leanca nella capitale moldava Chisinau aveva l’obiettivo di consolidare e sviluppare le relazioni bilaterali tra la Svizzera e la Moldova. La Svizzera è il terzo Paese donatore nella Repubblica di Moldova, dove investe annualmente circa 6,2 milioni di franchi in progetti riguardanti la sanità e le risorse idriche. La Svizzera è presente a Chisinau con un Ufficio di cooperazione della Direzione dello sviluppo e della cooperazione (DSC).&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Con la firma di un accordo di facilitazione del rilascio di visti e di un accordo di riammissione viene potenziata la cooperazione in materia di migrazione. La facilitazione del rilascio di visti promuove lo scambio sociale, culturale ed economico tra i due Stati. Con questo accordo la Svizzera adegua la sua prassi per il rilascio di visti di breve durata a quella degli altri Stati Schengen.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; L’accordo di riammissione garantisce il rimpatrio regolare e semplificato nella Repubblica di Moldova delle persone senza soggiorno autorizzato. Il nuovo accordo adatta la cooperazione ai nuovi standard e sostituisce l’accordo del 2003 finora in vigore.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; La Consigliera federale Calmy-Rey ha inoltre annunciato che a partire dal 25 maggio di quest’anno i cittadini moldavi potranno presentare domanda di visto per la Svizzera presso il centro visti dell’ambasciata ungherese a Chisinau. Non sarà quindi più necessario recarsi a Kiev. Il centro visti ungherese rilascia tra l’altro anche i visti per Austria e Danimarca.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Giovedì la Consigliera federale Micheline Calmy-Rei partecipa alla Conferenza regionale degli ambasciatori svizzeri dei Paesi dell’Europa orientale e sudorientale. L’incontro verte sull’atteggiamento e sull’impegno della Svizzera nei confronti degli Stati di questa regione che non sono membri dell’UE. Al centro della discussione è la questione dell’efficacia degli strumenti di politica estera svizzeri in confronto alla linea politica di altri partner e attori che operano in questa regione, a cominciare dall’UE.</text>
      <contact>Informazione DFAE Palazzo federale ovest CH-3003 Berna Tel.: (+41) 031 322 31 53 Fax: (+41) 031 324 90 47 E-Mail: info@eda.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Federal Councillor Micheline Calmy-Rey in the Republic of Moldova</title>
      <lead>Federal Councillor Micheline Calmy-Rey flew to Chisinau in the Republic of Moldova on Wednesday, where she will take part in a meeting of Swiss ambassadors from countries in South-East and East Europe. On Wednesday evening she held talks with Iurie Leanca, deputy prime minister and foreign minister of the Republic of Moldova. During the meeting a repatriation agreement and an agreement on visa facilitation were signed.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;The talks with foreign minister Iurie Leanca in the Moldovan capital Chisinau focused on stock-taking and on the further development of relations between Switzerland and Moldavia. Switzerland is the third largest donor country in the Republic of Moldova,&amp;nbsp; annually investing about 6.2 million CHF in projects in the areas of water and health. Switzerland is represented by a cooperation office of the Swiss Agency for Development and Cooperation (SDC) in Chisinau.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The signing of a visa facilitation agreement and of a repatriation agreement marks the strengthening of cooperation in the area of migration. Visa facilitations will promote personal, cultural and economic exchanges between the two states. This agreement means that Switzerland is bringing its short-term visa issuance policy into line with that of other Schengen states.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The repatriation agreement ensures that Moldovan nationals illicitly residing in Switzerland can be repatriated to Moldova in an orderly manner and on the basis of a simplified procedure. The new agreement adapts cooperation to current standards, superseding the previous agreement of 2003.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Federal Councillor Micheline Calmy-Rey&amp;nbsp;announced that from 25 May 2010 onwards citizens of the Republic of Moldova will be able to apply for visas in the visa centre of the Hungarian embassy in Chisinau and so will no longer need to travel to Kiev to obtain a visa for Switzerland. The Hungarian visa centre also issues visas for Austria and Denmark.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;On Thursday Mrs Calmy-Rey will take part in the regional conference of Swiss ambassadors from South-East and East European countries. The subject of the meeting is Switzerland's relations to and activities in countries in the region that are not members of the EU. The central issue will be the effectiveness of Switzerland's foreign policy instruments in comparison with those of other partners and actors in the region, starting with the EU. &amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Information FDFA Bundeshaus West CH-3003 Bern Tel.: (+41) 031 322 31 53 Fax: (+41) 031 324 90 47 E-Mail: info@eda.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
