<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="18715" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2008-05-13</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="yes" id="324" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>301</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Swissmedic, Schweizerisches Heilmittelinstitut</name>
      <name lang="fr">Swissmedic, Institut suisse des produits thérapeutiques</name>
      <name lang="it">Swissmedic, Istituto svizzero per gli agenti terapeutici</name>
      <name lang="en">Swiss Agency for Therapeutic Products</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.swissmedic.ch/</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.swissmedic.ch/?lang=3</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.swissmedic.ch/?lang=4</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.swissmedic.ch/?lang=2</www>
      <email lang="de"/>
      <email lang="fr"/>
      <email lang="it"/>
      <email lang="en"/>
    </originator>
    <department id="301">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement des Innern</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'intérieur</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'interno</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Home Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Engere Zusammenarbeit der Swissmedic mit der Heilmittelbehörde in Singapur</title>
      <lead>Im Auftrag des Bundesrates hat gestern Montag (12.5.2008) in Singapur der stellvertretende Schweizer Botschafter Rolf Frei und der Direktor der Health Sciences Authority Singapur (HSA), Dr. John C.W. Lim, ein Memorandum of Understanding (MoU) im Bereich der Heilmittel unterzeichnet. Im Rahmen dieser Vereinbarung wurde eine engere Zusammenarbeit zwischen den Heilmittelbehörden der beiden Länder, dem Schweizerischen Heilmittelinstitut, Swissmedic, und der Health Sciences Authority beschlossen. Das Abkommen umfasst sowohl Arzneimittel als auch Medizinprodukte</lead>
      <text link="no">Künftig können die beiden Behörden sowohl Daten über unerwünschte Wirkungen von Arzneimitteln, Qualitätsdefekte und Rückrufe als auch Einzelheiten aus Zulassungsgesuchen sowie Inspektionsberichte über Arzneimittelhersteller austauschen. Dieser Informationsaustausch ermöglicht das frühzeitige Erkennen von Risiken und damit ein effizienteres Eingreifen der Behörden. Ziel ist dabei, zum Schutz der Patientinnen und Patienten sicherheitsrelevante Massnahmen so schnell wie möglich umzusetzen. Eine weitere wichtige Komponente ist der Austausch von Informationen im Rahmen laufender Zulassungsverfahren und die Möglichkeit auf die Entscheidgrundlagen der jeweiligen Partnerbehörde zurück zu greifen. &amp;nbsp;Die Zusammenarbeit mit der Behörde in Singapur ist – nach dem Abschluss des MoU mit der amerikanischen Food and Drug Administration (FDA) in 2003 und den Abkommen mit der australischen Therapeutic Goods Aministration (TGA) und der kanadischen Health Products and Food Branch, Health Canada in 2006 – ein weiterer Meilenstein, der das internationale Netzwerk der Swissmedic ergänzt. Diese Vernetzung mit anderen international anerkannten Heilmittelbehörden wird nach Auffassung des Eidgenössischen Department des Innern (EDI) im Umfeld global vermarkteter Heilmittel und somit auch weltweiter Herausforderungen immer bedeutender.</text>
      <contact>Joachim Gross, Leiter Medienstelle Swissmedic, joachim.gross@swissmedic.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Swissmedic renforce sa collaboration avec l’autorité de contrôle des produits thérapeutiques de Singapour</title>
      <lead>Sur mandat du Conseil fédéral, Rolf Frei, ambassadeur adjoint de la Suisse, a signé hier lundi (12.5.2008) à Singapour, de concert avec Dr. John C.W. Lim, directeur de la Health Sciences Authority Singapur (HSA), un protocole d’accord (Memorandum of Understanding, MoU) dans le domaine des produits thérapeutiques. Ce document, qui traite aussi bien des médicaments que des dispositifs médicaux, vient entériner le rapprochement de ces deux autorités de contrôle que sont Swissmedic, Institut suisse des produits thérapeutiques, et la Health Sciences Authority</lead>
      <text link="no">Les deux autorités pourront donc à l’avenir échanger des données sur des effets indésirables de médicaments, des défauts de qualité et des retraits de médicaments, mais aussi sur des points plus précis relatifs à des demandes d’autorisation et à des rapports d’inspection de fabricants. Ces échanges d’informations permettront une détection précoce des risques et donc une intervention plus efficace des autorités, l’objectif étant de mettre en œuvre aussi rapidement que possible les mesures de sécurité requises afin d’assurer la protection des patients. L’autre composante essentielle dans ce domaine est l’échange d’informations dans le cadre des procédures d’autorisation en cours et la possibilité d’accéder aux fondements des décisions de l’autorité partenaire. &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;Faisant suite au MoU conclu en 2003 avec les autorités américaines (la Food and Drug Administration ou FDA) ainsi qu’aux accords signés en 2006 avec les autorités australiennes (Therapeutic Goods Aministration ou TGA) d’une part et canadiennes (Health Products and Food Branch, Health Canada) d’autre part, ce protocole avec Singapour constitue une nouvelle étape dans le maillage tissé au plan international par Swissmedic. L’importance de cette interconnexion avec des autorités de contrôle des produits thérapeutiques reconnues partout dans le monde est d’ailleurs, de l’avis du Département fédéral de l’intérieur (DFI), vouée à s’accroître dans le contexte de la globalisation des ventes de produits thérapeutiques et donc des enjeux auxquels les Etats doivent faire face.</text>
      <contact>Joachim Gross, porte parole Swissmedic, joachim.gross@swissmedic.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Rafforzata la collaborazione tra Swissmedic e l’autorità di controllo dei medicamenti di Singapore</title>
      <lead>Ieri, lunedì 12.5.2008 a Singapore, il sostituto ambasciatore svizzero Rolf Frei, su mandato del Consiglio federale, e il direttore della Health Sciences Authority Singapur (HSA), dr. John C.W. Lim, hanno firmato un Memorandum of Understanding (MoU) nel settore degli agenti terapeutici. Nell’ambito di questa intesa è stato deciso di rafforzare la collaborazione tra le autorità di controllo dei medicamenti di entrambi i Paesi, ossia l’Istituto svizzero per gli agenti terapeutici, Swissmedic, e la Health Sciences Authority. L'accordo comprende sia i medicamenti che i dispositivi medici.</lead>
      <text link="no">Le due autorità potranno scambiarsi sia i dati relativi agli effetti indesiderati dei medicamenti, ai difetti della qualità e ai ritiri dal mercato che le informazioni di dettaglio concernenti le domande di omologazione e i rapporti di ispezioni sui fabbricanti di medicamenti. Questo scambio di informazioni permette alle autorità di riconoscere tempestivamente i rischi e quindi intervenire in modo più efficiente. Lo scopo consiste nel mettere in atto il più rapidamente possibile gli opportuni provvedimenti a tutela della sicurezza dei pazienti. Un altro elemento importante è lo scambio di informazioni nell’ambito delle attuali procedure di omologazione e la possibilità di ricorrere alle basi decisionali dell’autorità partner in questione. &amp;nbsp;Dopo la conclusione del MoU con la Food and Drug Administration (FDA) statunitense nel 2003 e gli accordi con l'autorità australiana Therapeutic Goods Aministration (TGA) e quella canadese Health Products and Food Branch, Health Canada nel 2006, la collaborazione con l’autorità di Singapore costituisce un'ulteriore pietra miliare che completa la rete internazionale di Swissmedic. Secondo il Dipartimento federale dell’interno (DFI) questa rete di intese con altre autorità di controllo dei medicamenti riconosciute a livello internazionale acquisirà una crescente importanza nel settore degli agenti terapeutici commercializzati mondialmente e quindi anche in un contesto di sfide globali.</text>
      <contact>Joachim Gross, responsabile Relazioni media Swissmedic, joachim.gross@swissmedic.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Closer collaboration between Swissmedic and the Singapore therapeutic products authorities</title>
      <lead>As mandated by the Swiss Federal Council, the deputy Swiss Ambassador Rolf Frei and the Director of the Singapore Health Sciences Authority (HSA), Dr. John C. W. Lim, signed a Memorandum of Understanding (MoU) relating to therapeutic products in Singapore yesterday (Monday 12 April 2008). Within the framework of this agreement, it was decided that the therapeutic products authorities of the two countries – Swissmedic, Swiss Agency for Therapeutic Products, and the Health Sciences Authority - would collaborated more closely. The MoU encompasses both medicinal products and medical devices.</lead>
      <text link="no">In future, both authorities will be able to exchange not only data regarding adverse drug reactions, quality defects and recalls but also details from applications for authorisations and inspection reports regarding manufacturers of medicines. This information exchange will permit the early identification of risks and thus enable the authorities to intervene more effectively. The objective is to take any safety-related measures that are needed to protect patients as rapidly as possible. A further component of the MoU is the exchange of information within the framework of ongoing authorisation procedures, and the possibility of drawing on the basis for decisions taken by the relevant partner authority. &amp;nbsp;Collaboration with the HSA in Singapore is - following the MoU concluded with the US Food and Drug Administration (FDA) in 2003, the agreement with the Australian Therapeutic Goods Administration (TGA) and Health Canada, the Canadian Health Products and Food Branch, in 2006 – a further milestone in expanding Swissmedic's international network. The Federal Department of Home Affairs (FDHA) considers that this kind of networking with other internationally recognized therapeutic products authorities is becoming increasingly important given the environment of globally marketed medicines and the inherent worldwide challenges.</text>
      <contact>Joachim Gross, Press Relations Officer, Swissmedic, joachim.gross@swissmedic.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
  </message>
</messages>
