<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="61943" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2016-05-31</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="yes" id="805" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>801</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Bundesamt für Verkehr</name>
      <name lang="fr">Office fédéral des transports</name>
      <name lang="it">Ufficio federale dei trasporti</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Office of Transport</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.bav.admin.ch/bav/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.bav.admin.ch/bav/fr/home.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.bav.admin.ch/bav/it/home.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.bav.admin.ch/bav/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">presse@bav.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">presse@bav.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">presse@bav.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">presse@bav.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="801">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Umwelt, Verkehr, Energie und Kommunikation</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'environnement, des transports, de l'énergie et de la communication</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'ambiente, dei trasporti, dell'energia e delle comunicazioni</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of the Environment, Transport, Energy and Communications</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.uvek.admin.ch/uvek/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.uvek.admin.ch/uvek/fr/home.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.uvek.admin.ch/uvek/it/home.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.uvek.admin.ch/uvek/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-uvek.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-uvek.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-uvek.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-uvek.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Treffen der Verkehrsminister in Lugano</title>
      <lead>Bundesrätin Doris Leuthard hat sich heute im Rahmen des „Follow up Zurich“-Prozesses mit den Verkehrsministern der Alpenländer getroffen. Die Konferenz fand aus Anlass der Eröffnungsfeier des Gotthard-Basistunnels in diesem Jahr in Lugano statt. Bei den Treffen der Minister der Alpenländer geht es zum einen um Fragen zur Verkehrssicherheit, zum andern um die Verlagerungspolitik. Der Vorsitz ging vom slowenischen Infrastrukturminister Peter Gašperšič an seinen italienischen Kollegen Graziano Delrio über.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Die Verkehrsminister führten ihre alle zwei Jahre stattfindende Konferenz heute in Lugano durch. Dabei ging es um die während der letzten beiden Jahre unter slowenischem Vorsitz geleisteten Aktivitäten. Im Zentrum standen Berichte zu Umweltauswirkungen und zur Verbesserung der Eisenbahntunnelsicherheit sowie die Verkehrsverlagerung im Alpenraum. Im Rahmen der „Follow up Zurich“-Plattform laufen u.a. Abklärungen für ein nachfrageabhängiges Mautsystem für den Schwerverkehr im Alpenraum (Toll+). Für die nächste Periode unter dem Vorsitz Italiens steht die Erarbeitung eines Berichts zur konkreten Umsetzung von Toll+ im Vordergrund. Ebenso sollen die Umweltauswirkungen des Schwerverkehrs vertieft werden. Dabei geht es zum Beispiel darum, zu ermitteln, wie gross der Anteil des Schwerverkehrs bei der Emission von Luftschadstoffen im Verkehr durch die Alpen ist.&lt;br /&gt;Heute Abend werden sich die Verkehrsminister bei einem Nachtessen mit den Amtskollegen des Güterverkehrskorridors Rotterdam-Genua (BE, LUX), der Verkehrskommissarin der EU sowie den Konzernchefs europäischer Eisenbahnunternehmen treffen. Morgen werden alle Gäste an der Eröffnungsfeier des Gotthard-Basistunnels teilnehmen. &lt;br /&gt;Die „Follow up“-Zurich Plattform war 2001 im Nachgang an die schweren Unfälle in Strassentunnels ins Leben gerufen worden. Zu den Mitgliedern gehören Deutschland, Frankreich, Italien, Liechtenstein, Österreich, Slowenien und die Schweiz. Ein Vertreter der Europäischen Kommission ist als ständiger Beobachter und ein Vertreter der Alpenkonvention als Gast dabei.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Absichtserklärung zur Schifffahrt unterzeichnet&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Bundesrätin Doris Leuthard und der italienische Infrastruktur- und Verkehrsminister Graziano Delrio haben heute am Rande der „Follow up Zurich“-Konferenz in Lugano eine Absichtserklärung (Memorandum of Understanding) zur Schifffahrt auf dem Lago Maggiore und Lago di Lugano unterzeichnet. Die Schifffahrt auf den beiden Seen basiert auf einem Abkommen zwischen der Schweiz und Italien sowie Konzessionen, bei denen die Erneuerung ansteht. Bundesrätin Leuthard und ihr Amtskollege möchten die Attraktivität der touristischen Schifffahrt auf den Tessiner Seen steigern. Die Absichtserklärung sieht vor, dass neue Ansätze wie zum Beispiel eine grenzüberschreitende Zusammenarbeit und die ergänzende Zulassung von privaten Anbietern geprüft werden sollen. Eine gemeinsame Arbeitsgruppe wird nun Vorschläge dazu erarbeiten.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>zur Ministerkonferenz in Lugano: Annetta Bundi, Mediendienst UVEK, 078 646 38 80 zum "Follow up Zurich"-Prozess: Bundesamt für Verkehr, Information, 058 462 36 43, presse@bav.admin.ch</contact>
      <attachment id="151744">
        <title>Hintergrund-Informationen "Follow-up"-Zurich</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>179</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/44184.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Rencontre des ministres des transports à Lugano</title>
      <lead>La conseillère fédérale Doris Leuthard a rencontré aujourd’hui les ministres des transports des pays alpins dans le cadre du Processus de Zurich. La conférence s’est tenue cette année à Lugano à l’occasion de la cérémonie d’ouverture du tunnel de base du Saint-Gothard. L’ordre du jour comportait des questions de sécurité des transports et de politique de transfert. La présidence de cet organe ministériel est passée du ministre slovène des infrastructures, Peter Gašperšič, à son homologue italien Graziano Delrio. </lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Les ministres des transports ont tenu leur conférence biennale aujourd’hui à Lugano. L’ordre du jour comportait le compte-rendu des activités des deux dernières années sous la présidence slovène. Il s’agissait principalement de rapports sur l’impact écologique et sur l’amélioration de la sécurité des tunnels ferroviaires ainsi que du report modal dans la zone alpine. La plate-forme « Processus de Zurich » sert entre autres de cadre à des vérifications en vue d’un système de péage en fonction de la demande pour le trafic lourd dans la zone alpine (Toll+). La prochaine période, sous la présidence de l’Italie, sera consacrée à l’élaboration d’un rapport sur la mise en œuvre pratique de Toll+. De même, il s’agira d’approfondir l’étude de l’impact écologique du trafic lourd, à savoir par exemple de mesurer la proportion du trafic lourd dans les émissions de polluants atmosphériques sur le parcours transalpin.&lt;br /&gt;Ce soir, les ministres des transports sont conviés à un dîner avec leurs homologues du corridor de fret Rotterdam-Gênes (BE, LUX), la commissaire des transports de l’UE et les CEO des entreprises ferroviaires européennes. Demain, tous les invités assisteront à la cérémonie d’ouverture du tunnel de base du Saint-Gothard. &lt;br /&gt;La plate-forme « Processus de Zurich » avait été instaurée en 2001 après les graves accidents survenus dans les tunnels routiers. L’Allemagne, l’Autriche, la France, l’Italie, le Liechtenstein, la Slovénie et la Suisse en sont membres. Un représentant de la Commission Européenne y est observateur permanent et un représentant de la Convention alpine y siège en tant qu’invité.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Signature d’une déclaration d’intention sur la navigation&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;br /&gt;La conseillère fédérale Doris Leuthard et le ministre italien des infrastructures et des transports Graziano Delrio ont signé aujourd’hui, en marge de la conférence « Processus de Zurich » de Lugano, une déclaration d’intention (Memorandum of Understanding) sur la navigation au lac Majeur et au lac de Lugano. La navigation sur les deux lacs est régie par une convention entre la Suisse et l’Italie ainsi que par des concessions qui devront bientôt être renouvelées. La conseillère fédérale Doris Leuthard et son homologue souhaitent accroître l’attrait de la navigation touristique sur les lacs tessinois. La déclaration d’intention prévoit d’envisager de nouvelles approches, par exemple une collaboration transfrontalière et l’autorisation complémentaire de prestataires privés. Un groupe de travail binational présentera des propositions de mise en œuvre. &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Sur la conférence des ministres à Lugano: Annetta Bundi, service de presse DETEC, 078 646 3880 Sur le « Processus de Zurich » : Office fédéral des transports, Information, 058 462 36 43, presse@bav.admin.ch</contact>
      <attachment id="151745">
        <title>Informations générales Processus de Zurich</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>163</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/44185.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Incontro dei ministri dei trasporti a Lugano</title>
      <lead>La Consigliera federale Doris Leuthard ha incontrato oggi i ministri dei trasporti dei Paesi dell’arco alpino nell’ambito delle periodiche conferenze dei «Seguiti di Zurigo». Quest'anno la conferenza, dedicata alla sicurezza dei trasporti e alla politica di trasferimento del traffico, è stata organizzata a Lugano in concomitanza con la cerimonia d’inaugurazione della galleria di base del San Gottardo. In tale occasione il ministro sloveno dell’infrastruttura Peter Gašperšič ha ceduto la presidenza al suo omologo italiano Graziano Delrio. </lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;I ministri dei trasporti dei Paesi dell’arco alpino hanno tenuto oggi a Lugano la loro consueta conferenza biennale. Hanno discusso delle attività svolte nei due anni di presidenza slovena e in particolare dei rapporti dedicati alle conseguenze ecologiche dei trasporti, del miglioramento della sicurezza nelle gallerie ferroviarie e del trasferimento del traffico nell’arco alpino. Nell’ambito della piattaforma «Seguiti di Zurigo» sono inoltre in corso studi di approfondimento sui sistemi di pedaggi differenziati per il traffico pesante basati sul sistema Toll+. Nei prossimi anni di presidenza italiana i ministri si concentreranno sull’elaborazione di uno studio sull’eventuale inserimento di tale sistema e approfondiranno inoltre gli effetti del traffico pesante sull’ambiente. Si tratterà ad esempio di stabilire l’incidenza della quota rappresentata dagli automezzi pesanti rispetto al totale delle emissioni di inquinanti atmosferici nel traffico transalpino. &lt;br /&gt;Questa sera, in occasione di una cena di lavoro, i ministri dei trasporti incontreranno i loro colleghi dei Paesi situati lungo il corridoio del trasporto merci Rotterdam-Genova (BE, LUX), il Commissario europeo dei trasporti e gli amministratori delegati e direttori generali delle imprese ferroviarie europee. Domani tutti gli ospiti presenzieranno alla cerimonia per l‘inaugurazione della galleria di base del San Gottardo. &lt;br /&gt;La piattaforma «Seguiti di Zurigo», costituita nel 2001 a seguito dei gravi incidenti verificatisi nelle gallerie stradali alpine, riunisce la Germania, la Francia, l’Italia, il Liechtenstein, l’Austria, la Slovenia e la Svizzera, oltre a un rappresentante della Commissione europea in veste di osservatore permanente e un rappresentante della Convenzione delle Alpi in qualità di ospite.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Firmato il memorandum d’intesa sulla navigazione&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;La Consigliera federale Doris Leuthard e il Ministro italiano delle Infrastrutture e dei Trasporti Graziano Delrio hanno sottoscritto oggi a Lugano, a margine della conferenza «Seguiti di Zurigo», un memorandum d’intesa concernente la navigazione sul Lago Maggiore e sul Lago di Lugano, disciplinata da un accordo tra i due Paesi e da concessioni in scadenza. I due ministri intendono così incrementare l’attrattiva turistica e dei trasporti su questi laghi. Il memorandum d’intesa prevede l’esame di nuovi approcci, l’individuazione di un piano di sviluppo a lungo termine ed eventuali collaborazioni con società private. Un gruppo di lavoro congiunto elaborerà delle proposte in tal senso. &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>sulla conferenza ministeriale di Lugano: Annetta Bundi, Servizio stampa DATEC, 078 646 38 80 sui «Seguiti di Zurigo»: Ufficio federale dei trasporti, Informazione, 058 462 36 43, presse@bav.admin.ch</contact>
      <attachment id="151746">
        <title>Informazioni generali «Seguiti di Zurigo»</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>335</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/44186.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Meeting of transport ministers in Lugano</title>
      <lead>Federal Councillor Doris Leuthard met the transport ministers of the Alpine countries today as part of the Zurich Process. The conference was held in Lugano this year to mark the opening of the Gotthard Base Tunnel. Transport ministers from the Alpine countries meet regularly to discuss issues of transport safety as well as the modal shift policy. The presidency passed from Slovenian infrastructure minister, Peter Gašperšič, to his Italian colleague Graziano Delrio. </lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;The transport ministers held their biennial conference in Lugano today where they discussed activities carried out over the last two years under the Slovenian presidency. The focus was on environmental impact reports and the improvement of rail tunnel safety, as well as the transfer of goods from road to rail in the Alpine region. Under the Zurich Process platform, work is under way to examine the feasibility of a demand-based toll system for heavy goods vehicles in the Alpine region (Toll+). The priority during the Italian presidency will be to draw up a report on how Toll+ could be implemented in practice. The environmental impacts of HGVs will also be investigated in more depth. Here the emphasis will be on determining the proportion of atmospheric pollutant emissions in transalpine traffic attributable to heavy goods traffic.&lt;br /&gt;At a dinner this evening, the transport ministers will meet their counterparts from the Rotterdam-Genoa freight corridor (BE, LUX), the EU Transport Commissioner, and the heads of European railway undertakings. Tomorrow, all the guests will attend the ceremony to mark the opening of the Gotthard Base Tunnel.&lt;br /&gt;The Zurich Process was set up in 2001 following several serious accidents in road tunnels. The members are Germany, France, Italy, Liechtenstein, Austria, Slovenia and Switzerland. A representative of the European Commission is included as a permanent observer, and a representative of the Alpine Convention attends as a guest.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Memorandum of Understanding on navigation signed&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;On the fringes of the Zurich Process conference in Lugano today, Federal Councillor Doris Leuthard and the Italian infrastructure and transport minister, Graziano Delrio, signed a Memorandum of Understanding concerning navigation on Lake Maggiore and Lake Lugano. Shipping on the two lakes is based on an agreement between Switzerland and Italy, as well as on concessions that are coming up for renewal. Federal Councillor Leuthard and her Italian counterpart would like to boost the appeal of tourist shipping on Ticino’s lakes. The MoU allows new approaches to be tested, such as cross-border cooperation and the approval of additional private service providers. A joint working group will now set about drafting proposals.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>on the ministerial conference in Lugano: Annetta Bundi, DETEC Press and Information Service, 078 646 38 80 on the Zurich Process: Federal Office of Transport, Information, +41 58 462 36 43, presse@bav.admin.ch</contact>
      <attachment id="151747">
        <title>Background information Zurich Process</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>315</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/44187.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="46">
        <name lang="de">Verkehr</name>
        <name lang="fr">Transports</name>
        <name lang="it">Trasporti</name>
        <name lang="en">Transport</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
