<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="47158" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2012-12-12</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="yes" id="1060" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>601</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Staatssekretariat für internationale Finanzfragen</name>
      <name lang="fr">Secrétariat d'Etat aux questions financières internationales</name>
      <name lang="it">Segreteria di Stato per le questioni finanziarie internazionali</name>
      <name lang="en">State Secretariat for International Financial Matters</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.sif.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.sif.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.sif.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.sif.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@sif.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@sif.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@sif.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@sif.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="601">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Finanzdepartement</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des finances</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale delle finanze</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Finance</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.efd.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.dff.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.efd.admin.ch/efd/it/home.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.efd.admin.ch/efd/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Schweiz bedauert Deutschlands Nein zum unterzeichneten Quellensteuerabkommen</title>
      <lead>Das deutsche Parlament hat das von der Bundesregierung unterzeichnete Quellensteuerabkommen mit der Schweiz nicht ratifiziert. Die beiden bereits genehmigten Quellensteuerabkommen mit Grossbritannien und Österreich können am 1. Januar 2013 in Kraft treten. Die Abkommen lösen das Problem unversteuerter Gelder aus diesen Staaten in der Schweiz. Im Verhältnis zu Deutschland bleibt es in Steuerfragen beim bisherigen Zustand.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;„Wir bedauern, dass Deutschland das unterzeichnete schweizerisch-deutsche Quellensteuerabkommen nicht ratifiziert", sagte Bundespräsidentin Eveline Widmer-Schlumpf nach dem Entscheid Deutschlands.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Im Verhältnis zu Deutschland bleibt nach dem Nein der wenig befriedigende Status Quo mit Zufallsfunden auf illegal erworbenen CDs sowie die Amtshilfe auf Anfrage gemäss internationalem Standard. Mit jedem Jahr ohne Abkommen verjährt im Übrigen ein beträchtlicher Teil der ausstehenden Steuerbeträge.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Die Schweiz wird die Quellensteuerabkommen mit Grossbritannien und Österreich am 1. Januar 2013 in Kraft setzen. Damit wird sich zeigen, dass die Abkommen in der Praxis ordnungsgemäss vollzogen werden können und dass konkretes Steuergeld überwiesen wird. Verhandlungen mit Griechenland und Italien über ähnliche Abkommen sind im Gang. Weitere Länder inner- und ausserhalb Europas sind interessiert. Das Quellensteuermodell stellt auf effiziente Art sicher, dass in der Schweiz keine unversteuerten ausländischen Gelder versteckt werden können. Es ist eine Alternative zum automatischen Informationsaustausch.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Mario Tuor, Kommunikation Staatssekretariat für in-ternationale Finanzfragen SIF, +41 31 322 46 16, mario.tuor@sif.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>La Suisse regrette le refus allemand de l’accord signé sur l’imposition à la source</title>
      <lead>Le Parlement allemand n’a pas ratifié l’accord sur l’imposition à la source conclu entre le gouvernement allemand et la Suisse. Déjà approuvés, les deux accords sur l’imposition à la source avec la Grande-Bretagne et l’Autriche pourront quant à eux entrer en vigueur le 1er janvier 2013. Les accords résolvent le problème des avoirs non fiscalisés déposés en Suisse et provenant de ces Etats. En ce qui concerne l’Allemagne, le statu quo est maintenu en matière de fiscalité.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;«Nous regrettons que l'Allemagne ne ratifie pas l'accord sur l'imposition à la source signé avec la Suisse» a déclaré la présidente de la Confédération Eveline Widmer-Schlumpf après la décision de l'Allemagne.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ce refus ne permet pas de mettre fin à la peu satisfaisante situation actuelle, qui se caractérise par la découverte aléatoire de délits fiscaux sur la base de CD obtenus de façon illégale et l'assistance administrative sur demande selon le standard international. En outre, faute d'accord, une part considérable des créances fiscales en suspens se prescrivent chaque année.&lt;/p&gt;Le 1er janvier 2013, la Suisse mettra en vigueur les accords à la source conclus avec la Grande-Bretagne et l'Autriche, montrant ainsi que les accords peuvent être appliqués et que l'argent des impôts est effectivement transmis. Des négociations sur des accords similaires sont actuellement en cours avec la Grèce et l'Italie. D'autres pays européens et non européens sont intéressés. Le modèle de l'imposition à la source permet de garantir efficacement qu'aucun avoir étranger non fiscalisé ne peut être caché en Suisse. Il s'agit d'une solution de rechange à l'échange automatique de renseignements.</text>
      <contact>Mario Tuor, Communication du Secrétariat d’Etat aux questions financières internationales (SFI), +41 31 322 46 16, mario.tuor@sif.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>La Svizzera deplora il NO della Germania alla Convenzione sull’imposizione alla fonte</title>
      <lead>Il Parlamento tedesco non ha ratificato la Convenzione sull’imposizione alla fonte con la Svizzera firmata dal Governo federale tedesco. Le due convenzioni sull’imposizione alla fonte già approvate con il Regno Unito e l’Austria possono entrare in vigore il 1° gennaio 2013. Le convenzioni risolvono il problema degli averi non tassati in Svizzera provenienti da questi Stati. Per quanto riguarda le questioni fiscali con la Germania si rimane allo status quo.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;«Deploriamo la decisione della Germania di non ratificare la Convenzione bilaterale sull'imposizione alla fonte», ha dichiarato la presidente della Confederazione Eveline Widmer-Schlumpf dopo tale decisione. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Dopo il NO tedesco, nei confronti della Germania permane l'insoddisfacente status quo con scoperte casuali di CD acquisiti illegalmente nonché l'assistenza amministrativa su richiesta secondo lo standard internazionale. Inoltre, in mancanza di un accordo, ogni anno una parte considerevole di crediti fiscali cade in prescrizione. &lt;/p&gt;Il 1° gennaio 2013 la Svizzera porrà in vigore le convenzioni sull'imposizione alla fonte con il Regno Unito e l'Austria. Sarà quindi possibile dimostrare che le convenzioni possono essere eseguite correttamente nella prassi e che gli importi fiscali vengono effettivamente versati. Trattative per la conclusione di convenzioni simili sono in corso con Grecia e Italia. Altri Paesi europei ed extraeuropei sono altresì interessati. Il modello dell'imposizione alla fonte impedisce efficacemente che vengano occultati in Svizzera fondi stranieri non tassati. Si tratta di un'alternativa allo scambio automatico di informazioni.</text>
      <contact>Mario Tuor, Comunicazione Segreteria di Stato per le questioni finanziarie internazionali SFI, +41 31 322 46 16, mario.tuor@sif.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Switzerland regrets Germany's "No" to signing of withholding tax agreement</title>
      <lead>The German parliament has not ratified the withholding tax agreement which the German federal government signed with Switzerland. The two withholding tax agreements already approved with the United Kingdom and Austria will enter into force on 1 January 2013. The agreements solve the problem of untaxed funds from these countries in Switzerland. Concerning Germany, the current situation will persist regarding tax matters.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;"We regret that Germany has not ratified the withholding tax agreement signed between Switzerland and Germany", said the President of the Swiss Confederation Eveline Widmer-Schlumpf after Germany's decision. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Concerning Germany, what remains after the "No" is the less than satisfactory status quo with chance finds on CDs which have been acquired illegally and administrative assistance upon request according to the international standard. Furthermore, with each passing year without an agreement, a considerable proportion of the outstanding tax amounts will be subject to the statute of limitations.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Switzerland will bring the withholding tax agreements with the United Kingdom and Austria into force on 1 January 2013. In this way, it will be shown that the agreements can be duly implemented in practice and that actual tax money will be transferred. Negotiations on similar agreements are under way with Greece and Italy. Other countries both within and outside Europe have also shown an interest. The withholding tax model efficiently ensures that no untaxed foreign money can be hidden in Switzerland. It is an alternative to the automatic exchange of information.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Mario Tuor, Communications, State Secretariat for International Financial Matters SIF, tel. +41 31 322 46 16, mario.tuor@sif.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <offers>
      <offer id="291" org-id="1060">
        <name lang="de">Wirtschaft, Währung, Finanzplatz</name>
        <name lang="fr">Economie, monnaie, place financière</name>
        <name lang="it">Economia, Moneta, Piazza finanziaria</name>
        <name lang="en">Economic, Monetary and Financial Affairs</name>
      </offer>
    </offers>
    <keywords>
      <keyword id="235" org-id="1060">
        <name lang="de">Internationale Steuerpolitik</name>
        <name lang="fr">Politique fiscale internationale</name>
        <name lang="it">Politica fiscale internazionale</name>
        <name lang="en">International tax policy</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="126" org-id="1060">
        <name lang="de">Finanzplatz Schweiz</name>
        <name lang="fr">Place financière suisse</name>
        <name lang="it">Piazza finanziaria svizzera</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland as a financial centre</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="137" org-id="1060">
        <name lang="de">Internationale Doppelbesteuerung</name>
        <name lang="fr">Double imposition internationale</name>
        <name lang="it">Doppia imposizione internazionale</name>
        <name lang="en">International double taxation</name>
      </keyword>
    </keywords>
    <topics>
      <topic id="35">
        <name lang="de">Finanzplatz</name>
        <name lang="fr">Place financière</name>
        <name lang="it">Piazza finanziaria</name>
        <name lang="en">Financial Centre</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="44">
        <name lang="de">Steuern</name>
        <name lang="fr">Impôts</name>
        <name lang="it">Imposte</name>
        <name lang="en">Taxation</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
