<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="78298" revoked="no">
    <version>2</version>
    <pubdate>2020-02-28</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="201" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>201</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="201">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Militärische Eskalation in Syrien – Stellungnahme des EDA</title>
      <lead>Das EDA ist sehr besorgt über die militärische Eskalation im Nordwesten Syriens und die schwerwiegenden Folgen für die Zivilbevölkerung. Es ruft alle Konfliktparteien dazu auf, das Völkerrecht, insbesondere das humanitäre Völkerrecht, strikt einzuhalten und an den Verhandlungstisch zurückzukehren, um eine sofortige Einstellung der Kämpfe herbeizuführen. Die Schweiz hat ihre tiefe Besorgnis bereits am 27. Februar 2020 vor dem UNO-Menschenrechtsrat zum Ausdruck gebracht. </lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Das EDA ist sehr besorgt über die militärische Eskalation im Nordwesten Syriens (Provinz Idlib und Umgebung von Aleppo). Laut UNO wurden seit Anfang Februar 2020 mindestens 134 Zivilisten, darunter 44 Kinder, getötet und 11 medizinische Einrichtungen und 15 Schulen getroffen. Das EDA ruft alle Konfliktparteien dazu auf, das Völkerrecht, insbesondere das humanitäre Völkerrecht, strikt einzuhalten, indem sie alle verfügbaren Vorsichtsmassnahmen treffen, um die Bevölkerung und die zivile Infrastruktur zu schützen. Zudem muss die sogenannte Deeskalationszone in Idlib garantiert werden, auf die sich der Iran, Russland und die Türkei geeinigt haben. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Die anhaltende militärische Offensive hat zu einer weiteren Massenflucht mit schwerwiegenden unmittelbaren und langfristigen humanitären Folgen geführt. Laut UNO wurden seit Beginn der neuen Offensive im Dezember 2019 fast eine Million Menschen im Nordwesten Syriens vertrieben, wo sie bei Temperaturen unter dem Gefrierpunkt unter katastrophalen Bedingungen ausharren. Das EDA ruft daher alle Konfliktparteien dringend auf, einen raschen und ungehinderten Zugang der humanitären Hilfe zu ermöglichen, damit die Notleidenden Schutz und Hilfe erhalten. Grenzüberschreitende Hilfsaktionen sind dafür unerlässlich. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Die Schweiz hat ihre Besorgnis bereits am 27. Februar 2020 in einer gemeinsamen Erklärung mit Österreich, Liechtenstein und Slowenien vor dem UNO-Menschenrechtsrat zum Ausdruck gebracht. Sie fordert die in Syrien militärisch engagierten Staaten regelmässig auf, die Feindseligkeiten einzustellen, den Zugang für humanitäre Hilfe zu gewährleisten und die Suche nach einer politischen Lösung fortzusetzen. Das EDA wird seine Besorgnis über die Lage in Syrien entsprechend gegenüber dem Iran, Russland und der Türkei zur Sprache bringen.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Nur eine politische Lösung kann dem Leiden der syrischen Bevölkerung ein Ende setzen und zu einem dauerhaften Frieden beitragen, der die Rechte aller Syrerinnen und Syrer garantiert. Eine Rückkehr an den Verhandlungstisch im Rahmen des UNO-Friedensprozesses in Genf, der vom EDA aktiv unterstützt wird, ist unerlässlich. &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Kommunikation EDA Bundeshaus West CH-3003 Bern Tel. Kommunikationsservice: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Medienstelle: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <revisions>
        <revision date="2020-03-02 13:37" type="R"/>
      </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Escalade militaire en Syrie - prise de position du DFAE</title>
      <lead>Le DFAE est très préoccupé par l’escalade militaire dans le nord-ouest de la Syrie avec de graves conséquences pour la population civile. Il appelle toutes les parties au conflit à respecter strictement le droit international, en particulier le droit international humanitaire, et à retourner à la table des négociations pour faire cesser immédiatement les combats. Le 27 février 2020, la Suisse a déjà fait part de ses préoccupations devant le Conseil des droits de l’homme des Nations Unies.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Le DFAE est très préoccupé par l'escalade militaire dans le nord-ouest de la Syrie (province d'Idlib et campagne d'Alep). Depuis le début du mois de février, au moins 134 civils, y compris 44 enfants, ont été tués et 11 centres médicaux ainsi que 15 écoles ont été touchés par des attaques selon l’ONU. Il appelle toutes les parties au conflit à respecter strictement le droit international, en particulier le droit international humanitaire, en protégeant la population et les infrastructures civiles et en prenant toutes les mesures de précaution possibles. De plus, il est crucial de garantir la zone dite de « désescalade » à Idlib pour laquelle l’Iran, la Russie et la Turquie se sont engagés. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;La poursuite de l'offensive militaire a entraîné de nouveaux déplacements massifs. Elle amplifie ses conséquences humanitaires immédiates et à long terme. Toujours selon l’ONU, depuis le début de la nouvelle offensive en décembre 2019, près d’un million de personnes ont été déplacées dans le nord-ouest de la Syrie, où ils vivent dans des conditions désastreuses à des températures inférieures à zéro. Le DFAE appelle donc instamment toutes les parties au conflit à faciliter un accès humanitaire rapide, sans entrave et durable afin de fournir une assistance et une protection. L'assistance transfrontalière est une des modalités indispensables à ce titre. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;La Suisse a fait part de ses préoccupations devant le Conseil des droits de l'homme des Nations Unies hier, le 27 février, par le biais d'une déclaration commune avec l'Autriche, le Liechtenstein et la Slovénie. Elle appelle régulièrement les Etats impliqués militairement en Syrie à cesser les hostilités, garantir l’accès humanitaire et poursuivre la rechercher d’une solution politique. A cette fin, le DFAE soulèvera ces préoccupations par rapport à la situation actuelle avec l’Iran, la Russie et la Turquie.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Seule une solution politique peut mettre un terme aux souffrances de la population syrienne et conduire à une paix durable qui garantit les droits de tous les Syriens. Il est indispensable de retourner à la table des négociations sous l’égide des Nations Unies à Genève, un processus de paix que le DFAE soutient activement. &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Communication DFAE Palais fédéral ouest CH-3003 Berne Tél. Service de communication: +41 58 462 31 53 Tél. Service de presse: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Escalation militare in Siria: presa di posizione del DFAE</title>
      <lead>Il DFAE è molto preoccupato per l’escalation militare nella Siria nord-occidentale, che ha gravi conseguenze sulla popolazione civile. Invita pertanto tutte le parti in conflitto a rispettare rigorosamente il diritto internazionale, in particolare il diritto internazionale umanitario, e a tornare al tavolo dei negoziati per porre immediatamente fine ai combattimenti. Il 27 febbraio 2020 la Svizzera ha espresso le proprie preoccupazioni dinanzi al Consiglio dei diritti umani dell’ONU. </lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Il DFAE è molto preoccupato per l’escalation militare nella Siria nord-occidentale (provincia di Idlib e campagna di Aleppo). Dall’inizio di febbraio, secondo l’ONU almeno 134 civili, tra cui 44 bambini, sono stati uccisi e 11 strutture sanitarie nonché 15 scuole sono state colpite da attacchi. Il DFAE invita tutte le parti in conflitto a rispettare rigorosamente il diritto internazionale, in particolare il diritto internazionale umanitario, proteggendo la popolazione e le infrastrutture civili e adottando tutte le misure precauzionali possibili. È inoltre fondamentale garantire la cosiddetta «zona di de-escalation» a Idlib, a favore della quale si sono impegnati l’Iran, la Russia e la Turchia. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Il proseguimento dell’offensiva militare ha determinato nuovi massicci sfollamenti forzati, aggravando ulteriormente la situazione umanitaria, sia nell’immediato che a lungo termine. Sempre secondo l’ONU, dall’inizio della nuova offensiva – nel dicembre del 2019 – quasi un milione di persone sono state sfollate nella Siria nord-occidentale, dove vivono in condizioni disastrose con temperature sotto lo zero. Il DFAE invita pertanto tutte le parti in conflitto a garantire con urgenza un accesso umanitario rapido, duraturo e senza ostacoli affinché sia possibile fornire l’assistenza e la protezione necessarie. L’aiuto transfrontaliero è una delle soluzioni indispensabili a tal fine. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Il 27 febbraio 2020 la Svizzera ha espresso le proprie preoccupazioni dinanzi al Consiglio dei diritti umani dell’ONU in una dichiarazione congiunta con l’Austria, il Liechtenstein e la Slovenia. A intervalli regolari invita inoltre gli Stati impegnati militarmente in Siria a cessare le ostilità, a garantire l’accesso umanitario e a continuare nella ricerca di una soluzione politica. A tale scopo, il DFAE discuterà con l’Iran, la Russia e la Turchia in merito a queste preoccupazioni relative alla situazione attuale.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Solo tramite una soluzione politica è possibile porre fine alle sofferenze del popolo siriano e ottenere una pace duratura che garantisca i diritti di tutti i cittadini e le cittadine. È indispensabile tornare al tavolo dei negoziati sotto l’egida delle Nazioni Unite a Ginevra, un processo di pace che il DFAE sostiene attivamente. &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Comunicazione DFAE Palazzo federale ovest CH-3003 Berna Tel. Servizio di comunicazione: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Servizio stampa: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <revisions>
        <revision date="2020-03-02 13:37" type="R"/>
      </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>FDFA statement on military escalation in Syria</title>
      <lead>The FDFA is very concerned about the military escalation in north-western Syria and the serious impact this is having on the civilian population. It calls on all parties to the conflict to comply strictly with international law, in particular international humanitarian law, and to return to the negotiating table with a view to implementing an immediate ceasefire. Switzerland raised its concerns with the UN Human Rights Council on 27 February 2020. </lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;The FDFA is very concerned about the military escalation in north-western Syria (province of Idlib and Aleppo countryside). According to the UN at least 134 civilians, including 44 children, have been killed and 11 healthcare facilities and 15 schools have been targeted since the start of February. Switzerland calls on all parties to the conflict to comply strictly with international law, in particular international humanitarian law, by protecting the population and civic infrastructure and by taking all feasible precautionary measures. It is also essential to secure the Idlib de-escalation zone agreed by Iran, Russia and Turkey. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The continuing military offensive has displaced large numbers of people and aggravated the immediate and long-term humanitarian consequences. The UN also claims that since the start of the latest offensive in December 2019 close to a million people have been displaced in north-western Syria. They are now living in desperate conditions in sub-zero temperatures. The FDFA therefore urges all parties to the conflict to facilitate rapid, unrestricted, sustained access for humanitarian actors to provide assistance and protection to those in need, including across borders, which is one of the key ways that aid is delivered. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Together with Austria, Liechtenstein and Slovenia, Switzerland presented a joint statement setting out its concerns to the UN Human Rights Council on 27 February 2020. Switzerland has consistently called on the countries militarily involved in Syria to cease hostilities, guarantee humanitarian access and work towards a political solution. To this end, Switzerland will also raise its concerns over the current situation with Iran, Russia and Turkey.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Only a political solution can put an end to the suffering of the Syrian people and lead to a lasting peace that guarantees the rights of all Syrians. It is essential that all parties return to the negotiating table as part of a peace process led by the UN in Geneva and actively supported by Switzerland. &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>FDFA Communication Federal Palace West Wing CH-3003 Bern, Switzerland Tel. Communication service: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Press service: +41 58 460 55 55 E-mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @SwissMFA</contact>
      <revisions>
        <revision date="2020-03-02 13:37" type="R"/>
      </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
