<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="60525" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2016-02-01</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="701" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>701</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Wirtschaft, Bildung und Forschung</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'économie, de la formation et de la recherche</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'economia, della formazione e della ricerca</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Economic Affairs, Education and Research</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="701">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Wirtschaft, Bildung und Forschung</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'économie, de la formation et de la recherche</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'economia, della formazione e della ricerca</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Economic Affairs, Education and Research</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Bundespräsident Schneider-Ammann vertritt die Schweiz an Syrien-Konferenz in London</title>
      <lead>Bundespräsident Johann N. Schneider-Ammann nimmt am kommenden Donnerstag, 4. Februar, in London an der Geberkonferenz für Syrien teil. Die Schweiz stellt dieses Jahr angesichts der immensen Herausforderungen 50 Millionen Franken für die Opfer der Syrienkrise bereit. Rund die Hälfte der Hilfe wird in Syrien selber eingesetzt, die andere Hälfte dient der Unterstützung von Betroffenen in den Nachbarländern.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Seit Ausbruch der Krise beläuft sich das Schweizer Engagement in Syrien und den Nachbarländern auf über 250 Millionen Franken. Zu den Prioritäten der Schweizer Hilfe gehört es, im Umfeld Syriens nachhaltige Perspektiven für die betroffenen Menschen zu schaffen. Insgesamt fliessen rund zwei Drittel der Schweizer Hilfe in mehrjährige Projekte. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Über 6 Millionen Kinder benötigen humanitäre Hilfe und fast die Hälfte davon kann nicht mehr zur Schule. Die Schweiz engagiert sich in dieser Situation unter anderem für den Zugang zu Bildung und Ausbildung. Fast 120 Schulen wurden und werden von der Schweiz in Jordanien und Libanon direkt saniert, was über 60‘000 Kindern von Flüchtlingen und Einheimischen den Schulbesuch unter sichereren Bedingungen erlaubt.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;An der Syrien-Konferenz in London werden rund 30 Länder auf Ebene Staats- oder Regierungschef vertreten sein. Der Bundespräsident wird die Gelegenheit nutzen für verschiedene bilaterale Gespräche. Auf der Agenda steht insbesondere die Politik der Schweiz gegenüber der Europäischen Union. &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Informationsdienst WBF 058 462 20 07, info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="147248">
        <title>Zusätzliche Verweise</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/deza/de/home/aktivitaeten_projekte/aktivitaeten/humanitaere_hilfe/schwerpunkte/dossier-syrien.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Le président de la Confédération représentera la Suisse à la conférence de Londres sur la Syrie</title>
      <lead>Jeudi prochain 4 février, le président de la Confédération Johann N. Schneider-Ammann participera à Londres à la conférence des donateurs pour la Syrie. Face à l’ampleur des défis, la Suisse débloquera cette année 50 millions de francs pour les victimes de la crise en Syrie. La moitié environ de cette aide sera utilisée en Syrie même, l’autre moitié servira à soutenir les personnes concernées dans les pays voisins. </lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;L'engagement de la Suisse en Syrie et dans les pays voisins se monte à plus de 250 millions de francs depuis le début de la crise. L'aide suisse vise prioritairement à créer, dans le contexte syrien, des perspectives durables pour les personnes concernées. Dans l'ensemble, deux tiers environ de l'aide suisse sont affectés à des projets pluriannuels. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Plus de 6 millions d'enfants dépendent de l'aide humanitaire, et près de la moitié d'entre eux ne peut plus aller à l'école. Face à cette situation, la Suisse s'engage notamment en faveur de l'accès à l'éducation et à la formation. Ainsi, elle a directement rénové - ou est en train de rénover - près de 120 écoles en Jordanie et au Liban, permettant ainsi à plus de 60 000 enfants de réfugiés ou d'autochtones d'aller à l'école en toute sécurité. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Une trentaine de pays seront représentés au niveau des chefs d'État ou de gouvernement à la conférence de Londres sur la Syrie. Le président de la Confédération saisira cette occasion pour différents entretiens bilatéraux. La politique de la Suisse à l'égard de l'Union européenne figurera à l'ordre du jour, parmi d'autres sujets. &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Service d’information du DEFR 058 462 20 07, info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="147249">
        <title>Infos complémentaires</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/deza/fr/home/aktivitaeten_projekte/aktivitaeten/humanitaere_hilfe/schwerpunkte/dossier-syrien.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Il presidente della Confederazione Schneider-Ammann rappresenterà la Svizzera alla Conferenza di Londra sulla Siria</title>
      <lead>Giovedì prossimo 4 febbraio il presidente della Confederazione Johann N. Schneider-Ammann parteciperà a Londra alla Conferenza dei donatori per la Siria. Di fronte all’ampiezza delle sfide, la Svizzera quest’anno metterà a disposizione 50 milioni di franchi per le vittime della crisi in Siria. Circa la metà di questo contributo sarà impiegato in Siria, mentre l’altra metà servirà a sostenere le persone interessate nei Paesi limitrofi.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Dall'inizio della crisi l'impegno della Svizzera in Siria e nei Paesi limitrofi ammonta a oltre 250 milioni di franchi. L'aiuto svizzero si occupa prioritariamente di creare nel contesto siriano prospettive durevoli per le persone interessate. Circa due terzi degli aiuti svizzeri sono erogati per progetti pluriennali. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Oltre sei milioni di bambini necessitano di aiuto umanitario e quasi la metà di essi non può più frequentare la scuola. In questa situazione la Svizzera si impegna in particolare per favorire l'accesso all'istruzione e alla formazione. Fra le altre misure, ha rinnovato o sta rinnovando direttamente quasi 120 scuole in Giordania e in Libano, permettendo così a oltre 60 000 bambini, figli di rifugiati o scolari locali, di frequentare la scuola in condizioni sicure.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Una trentina di Paesi saranno rappresentati dai loro capi di Stato o di governo alla Conferenza di Londra sulla Siria. Il presidente della Confederazione coglierà l'occasione per avere diversi colloqui bilaterali. Tra i temi in agenda vi sarà anche la politica della Svizzera nei confronti dell'Unione europea. &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Servizio Informazione del DEFR 058 462 20 07, info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="147250">
        <title>Altri rimandi</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/deza/it/home/aktivitaeten_projekte/aktivitaeten/humanitaere_hilfe/schwerpunkte/dossier-syrien.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>President Schneider-Ammann to represent Switzerland at the Syria Donors Conference in London</title>
      <lead>On Thursday, 4 February, President Johann N. Schneider-Ammann will attend the Syria Donors Conference 2016 in London. This year, in light of the immense challenges, Switzerland will commit CHF 50 million towards assisting victims of the Syrian conflict. Around half of the funds will be used in Syria itself, while the other half is intended to help those affected in neighbouring countries.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Since the outbreak of the crisis Switzerland has allocated over CHF 250 million towards assistance in Syria and neighbouring countries. One of the priorities of the assistance provided by Switzerland is to help build a longer term outlook for those affected in the region around Syria. Overall around two-thirds of Switzerland's contribution takes the form of multi-year projects.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Over 6 million children are in need of humanitarian aid and almost half of those are unable to go to school. One area in which Switzerland is active is therefore in enabling access to education and training. So far, Switzerland has refurbished, or is in the process of refurbishing, almost 120 schools in Jordan and Lebanon, thereby providing over 60,000 children, both refugees and locals, with safer access to schools.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The heads of state or government of around 30 countries will be present at the conference in London. The president will take the opportunity to hold different bilateral talks, where the main topic will be Switzerland's policy towards the European Union.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>EAER Information Service 058 462 20 07, info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="147251">
        <title>Additional information</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/deza/en/home/aktivitaeten_projekte/aktivitaeten/humanitaere_hilfe/schwerpunkte/dossier-syrien.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="10">
        <name lang="de">Bundesrat</name>
        <name lang="fr">Conseil fédéral</name>
        <name lang="it">Consiglio federale</name>
        <name lang="en">Federal Council</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="34">
        <name lang="de">Europa</name>
        <name lang="fr">Europe</name>
        <name lang="it">Europa</name>
        <name lang="en">Europe</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="40">
        <name lang="de">Sicherheit</name>
        <name lang="fr">Sécurité</name>
        <name lang="it">Sicurezza</name>
        <name lang="en">Security</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="47">
        <name lang="de">Wirtschaft</name>
        <name lang="fr">Économie</name>
        <name lang="it">Economia</name>
        <name lang="en">Economic Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
    <catalogueElements>
      <catalogueElement id="103">
        <name lang="de">Internationale Flüchtlingskrise</name>
        <name lang="fr">Crise internationale des réfugiés</name>
        <name lang="it">Crisi internazionale dei profughi</name>
        <name lang="en">Internationale Flüchtlingskrise</name>
      </catalogueElement>
    </catalogueElements>
  </message>
</messages>
