<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="37574" revoked="no">
    <version>2</version>
    <pubdate>2011-02-07</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="201" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>201</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="201">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Sudan: Referendumsverlauf als Meilenstein auf dem Weg zum dauerhaften Frieden</title>
      <lead>Gemäss dem offiziellen Resultat des Sezessionsreferendums hat sich die überwiegende Mehrheit der abstimmenden Südsudanesen für die Trennung ihres Landesteils vom Norden ausgesprochen. Die Schweiz begrüsst den relativ ruhigen, friedlichen und geordneten Verlauf des Referendums. „Dieser stellt eine bedeutende politische Leistung auf dem Weg zum dauerhaften Frieden dar“, sagte Bundespräsidentin Micheline Calmy-Rey.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Die Schweiz hat den relativ ruhigen, friedlichen und geordneten Verlauf des Sezessionsreferendums im Sudan mit Befriedigung zur Kenntnis genommen. Das Referendum sei „ein Meilenstein bei der Umsetzung des Friedensabkommens von 2005“, sagte Bundespräsidentin Micheline Calmy-Rey. „Sein Verlauf stellt eine bedeutende politische Leistung auf dem Weg zu einem dauerhaften Frieden dar.“ Gleichzeitig brachte die Bundespräsidentin ihr Bedauern darüber zum Ausdruck, dass es im Zuge des Referendums dennoch in mehreren Fällen zu Gewaltausbrüchen gekommen ist, bei denen Tote und Verletzte zu beklagen waren.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Seit dem Kriegsende unterstützt die Schweiz als neutrale Friedensfördererin beide Verhandlungsparteien bei ihren Bemühungen, Lösungen für einen nachhaltigen Frieden im Sudan zu finden. So vermittelt sie auf Anfrage beider Parteien seit einigen Monaten technische Expertise in den Bereichen der Trennung der Vermögenswerte und Schulden ("Aktiva und Passiva“) sowie Bankenwesen und Währungsfragen zur Unterstützung der laufenden Post-Referendums-Verhandlungen. Nach dem klaren Ausgang des Sezessionsreferendums wird die Schweiz ihr Engagement mit unverminderter Kraft weiterführen.&amp;nbsp;&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Am 9. Juli 2011 endet die Übergangsperiode des Friedensabkommens von 2005 zwischen Nord- und Südsudan, zu dessen Zustandekommen nebst anderen Ländern auch die Schweiz einen wichtigen Beitrag geleistet hat. Das Abkommen beendete den zweiten südsudanesischen Bürgerkrieg nach 22 Jahren. Anschliessend wird der Südsudan voraussichtlich seine Unabhängigkeit vom Norden erklären und zum 193. Land der Welt werden. Die überwiegende Mehrheit der abstimmenden Südsudanesen hat sich im Sezessionsreferendum vom Januar 2011 für die Trennung ihres Landesteils vom Norden ausgesprochen. Die Schweiz nahm im Rahmen der EU-Referendumsbeobachtungsmission ebenfalls mit einem Langzeit- und zwei Kurzzeit-Referendumsbeobachtern teil. Heute wurde das Resultat des Sezessionsreferendums in Khartum offiziell verkündet.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Information EDA Bundeshaus West CH-3003 Bern Tel.: +41 (0)31 322 31 53 Fax: +41 (0)31 324 90 47 E-Mail: info@eda.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="79799">
        <title>Hintergrund zur politischen Situation</title>
        <uri>http://www.news.admin.ch/NSBSubscriber/message/attachments/21843.pdf</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="79800">
        <title>Das Engagement der Schweiz</title>
        <uri>http://www.news.admin.ch/NSBSubscriber/message/attachments/21854.pdf</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Référendum au Soudan : une première étape importante vers une paix durable</title>
      <lead>Comme il ressort des résultats officiels du référendum sur l’indépendance, les électeurs sud-soudanais se sont prononcés à une très forte majorité en faveur de la partition avec le Nord. La Suisse salue le déroulement relativement tranquille, pacifique et ordonné de ce scrutin. La Présidente de la Confédération Micheline Calmy-Rey a relevé à cet égard que ce référendum constituait un pas politique important vers l’instauration d’une paix durable.</lead>
      <text link="no">La Suisse a pris connaissance avec satisfaction du déroulement relativement tranquille, pacifique et ordonné du référendum. La Présidente de la Confédération Micheline Calmy-Rey a qualifié ce référendum d’étape capitale dans la mise en œuvre de l’accord de paix de 2005 et relevé que son déroulement constituait un pas politique important vers l’instauration d’une paix durable. Elle a néanmoins déploré que des violences aient éclaté en marge de la consultation, causant des morts et des blessés.&amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp;&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Dans le cadre de ses activités de promotion de la paix, la Suisse soutient depuis la fin de la guerre, en tant que partenaire neutre, les deux parties dans leurs démarches visant à instaurer une paix durable au Soudan. A la demande des deux parties, la Suisse dispense ainsi depuis quelques mois une expertise technique en matière de répartition des richesses et des dettes (actif/passif) ainsi que dans le secteur bancaire et sur les questions monétaires, afin d’accompagner les négociations post-référendaires en cours. Après l’issue claire du référendum d’indépendance, la Suisse entend poursuivre son engagement avec la même intensité. &amp;nbsp;&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Le 9 juillet prochain prendra fin la période de transition de l’accord de paix conclu en 2005 entre le Nord et le Sud-Soudan, auquel la Suisse a contribué de manière importante aux côtés d’autres pays. L’accord mettait un terme à la deuxième guerre civile du Sud-Soudan, qui a duré 22 ans. Il est à prévoir que le Sud-Soudan proclamera ensuite son indépendance à l’égard du Nord et deviendra ainsi le 193e Etat au monde. La grande majorité des électeurs sud-soudanais se sont prononcés en faveur de la partition du Nord lors du référendum d’indépendance de janvier 2011. La Suisse a également pris part à la mission d’observation du référendum pour l’UE en détachant trois experts à cette fin, dont deux pour une mission de courte durée et un pour une mission de longue durée. Le résultat du référendum d’indépendance a été annoncé aujourd’hui officiellement à Khartoum.&amp;nbsp;</text>
      <contact>Information DFAE Palais fédéral ouest CH-3003 Berne Tél.: (+41) 031 322 31 53 Fax: (+41) 031 324 90 47 E-Mail: info@eda.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="79801">
        <title>Situation politique</title>
        <uri>http://www.news.admin.ch/NSBSubscriber/message/attachments/21844.pdf</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="79802">
        <title>L’engagement de la Suisse</title>
        <uri>http://www.news.admin.ch/NSBSubscriber/message/attachments/21856.pdf</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Sudan: svolgimento del referendum, pietra miliare sulla via di una pace duratura</title>
      <lead>Secondo i risultati ufficiali del referendum nel Sudan meridionale, la stragrande maggioranza dei votanti si è espressa a favore della secessione della regione dal Nord del paese. La Svizzera saluta lo svolgimento tutto sommato calmo, pacifico e ordinato del referendum che, secondo le parole della Presidente della Confederazione Micheline Calmy-Rey, «rappresenta una realizzazione politica importante sulla via di una pace duratura».</lead>
      <text link="no">La Svizzera ha preso atto con piacere dello svolgimento tutto sommato calmo, pacifico e ordinato del referendum sulla secessione in Sudan. Il referendum è «una pietra miliare per l’attuazione dell’accordo di pace del 2005», ha detto la Presidente della Confederazione Micheline Calmy-Rey. «Il suo svolgimento rappresenta una realizzazione politica importante sulla via di una pace duratura». La Presidente della Confederazione ha però anche espresso rammarico per gli episodi di violenza che hanno provocato vari morti e feriti nel corso del referendum.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Dalla fine della guerra, la Svizzera, nel quadro delle sue attività di promozione della pace, sostiene entrambe le parti nei negoziati volti a trovare soluzioni in vista di una pace duratura in Sudan. Su richiesta delle due parti, da alcuni mesi viene eseguita una perizia tecnica negli ambiti della separazione di beni e debiti o «attivi e passivi» e delle questioni bancarie e monetarie, al fine di agevolare le trattative post-referendarie in corso. Dopo l’esito palese del referendum, la Svizzera continuerà ad impegnarsi con inalterato vigore.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Il 9 luglio 2011, si conclude il periodo di transizione sancito dall’accordo di pace del 2005 tra il Nord e il Sud del paese. Accanto ad altri paesi, la Svizzera ha dato un contributo notevole all’esito di questo accordo, che ha messo fine alla seconda guerra civile del Sudan meridionale, durata 22 anni. Il Sudan meridionale dichiarerà poi verosimilmente l’indipendenza dal Nord e diventerà il 193° Stato del mondo. Nel referendum del gennaio 2011, la stragrande maggioranza dei votanti del Sudan meridionale si è espressa a favore della secessione dal Nord del paese. La Svizzera ha inoltre preso parte alla missione di osservazione dell'UE con un osservatore a lungo termine e due a breve termine. Oggi a Khartum, è stato annunciato ufficialmente il risultato del referendum.</text>
      <contact>Informazione DFAE Palazzo federale ovest CH-3003 Berna Tel.: (+41) 031 322 31 53 Fax: (+41) 031 324 90 47 E-Mail: info@eda.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="79803">
        <title>Contesto politico</title>
        <uri>http://www.news.admin.ch/NSBSubscriber/message/attachments/21831.pdf</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="79804">
        <title>L’impegno della Svizzera</title>
        <uri>http://www.news.admin.ch/NSBSubscriber/message/attachments/21896.pdf</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Sudan: Referendum as a milestone on the road to lasting peace</title>
      <lead>According to the official result of the secession referendum, an overwhelming majority of the electorate of South Sudan voted in favour of separation from the north of the country. Switzerland expressed its satisfaction with the relatively smooth, peaceful and orderly progress of the referendum. “This represents significant political progress on the road to lasting peace,” said Federal President Micheline Calmy-Rey.</lead>
      <text link="no">Switzerland expressed its satisfaction with the relatively smooth, peaceful and orderly progress of the secession referendum in Sudan. In the words of Federal President Micheline Calmy-Rey, this was “a milestone in the implementation of the peace agreement of 2005. The referendum represents significant political progress on the road to lasting peace.” At the same time, however, she expressed her regret that in the wake of the referendum there have been several outbreaks of violence resulting in deaths and injuries.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; As a neutral peacebuilding partner, Switzerland has been supporting both sides since the end of the civil war in their efforts to find solutions for securing lasting peace in Sudan. For example, at the request of both parties it has for several months been mediating expertise in the areas of separation of assets and liabilities, banking activities and currency issues in order to support the post-referendum negotiations. Following the clear outcome of the secession referendum, Switzerland intends to continue vigorously pursuing its commitment in Sudan.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; The transitional period of the 2005 peace agreement between North and South Sudan, which came into being thanks to the efforts of a variety of countries including Switzerland, expires on 9 July 2011. This agreement halted the second Sudanese civil war which had raged for 22 years. South Sudan is now expected to declare its independence from the north and thus become the world’s 193rd country. At the secession referendum in January 2011, an overwhelming majority of the electorate of South Sudan voted in favour of separation from the north of the country. Within the scope of the EU referendum monitoring mission, Switzerland deployed one long-term and two short-term observers in Sudan. The result of the secession referendum is to be officially announced in Khartoum today.</text>
      <contact>Information FDFA Bundeshaus West CH-3003 Bern Tel.: (+41) 031 322 31 53 Fax: (+41) 031 324 90 47 E-Mail: info@eda.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="79805">
        <title>The political Situation</title>
        <uri>http://www.news.admin.ch/NSBSubscriber/message/attachments/21845.pdf</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="79806">
        <title>Switzerland’s commitment</title>
        <uri>http://www.news.admin.ch/NSBSubscriber/message/attachments/21858.pdf</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
