<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="103506" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2024-12-06</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="410" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>401</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Institut für Geistiges Eigentum</name>
      <name lang="fr">Institut Fédéral de la Propriété Intellectuelle</name>
      <name lang="it">Istituto Federale della Proprietà Intellettuale</name>
      <name lang="en">Swiss Federal Institute of Intellectual Property</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.ige.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.ige.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.ige.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.ige.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@ipi.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@ipi.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@ipi.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@ipi.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="401">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Justiz- und Polizeidepartement</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de justice et police</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale di giustizia e polizia</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Justice and Police</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.ejpd.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.ejpd.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.ejpd.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.ejpd.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-ejpd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">Info@gs-ejpd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-ejpd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-ejpd.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Caroline Perriard vom Bundesrat in den Institutsrat des IGE gewählt</title>
      <lead>Der Bundesrat hat an seiner Sitzung vom 2. Dezember 2024 Caroline Perriard in den Institutsrat des Instituts für Geistiges Eigentum (IGE) gewählt. Sie folgt per 1. März 2025 auf Béatrice Renggli, deren Amtszeit Ende Februar 2025 nach zwölf Jahren abläuft. Die im Kanton Waadt wohnhafte Caroline Perriard ist Expertin für Datenschutz und Immaterialgüterrecht und seit 2021 Präsidentin von Juristinnen Schweiz. </lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Mit Caroline Perriard wird der Institutsrat des IGE durch eine ausgewiesene Expertin aus der Privatwirtschaft ergänzt. Caroline Perriard ist seit Juni 2023 Director Data Protection &amp; Privacy bei BRP Bizzozero &amp; Partners SA. Davor war sie CEO und Co-Founder Legal in Digital von BrandIT. Während über zehn Jahren war sie in verschiedenen Funktionen für Nestlé tätig, zunächst als Legal Counsel IP im Marken- und Urheberrecht sowie Internetrecht, danach als Senior Legal Counsel Digital &amp; E-Commerce. In dieser Funktion war sie verantwortlich für die rechtlichen Aspekte bei Nestlés weltweiten digitalen Projekten. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Caroline Perriard hatte Jurisprudenz an der Universität Fribourg studiert und ein Auslandjahr an der Universität Köln verbracht. Im Jahr 2000 machte sie ihren Masterabschluss und absolvierte 2005 in Stockholm den LL.M. Von 2008 bis 2014 unterrichtete sie an der Universität Lausanne im Masterkurs IP &amp; Internet und war von 2017 bis 2022 Lehrbeauftragte an der CREA Business School in Genf. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Der neunköpfige Institutsrat ist das oberste betriebliche Leitungsorgan des IGE. Er legt die Höhe der Gebühren fest, genehmigt den Voranschlag, den Geschäftsbericht und die Jahresrechnung. Ausserdem bestimmt er die Zusammensetzung der Direktion, mit Ausnahme der vom Bundesrat gewählten Direktorin oder des Direktors.&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Eidg. Institut für Geistiges Eigentum Regula Gerber, Stv. Leiterin Kommunikation regula.gerber@ipi.ch, T +41 31 377 7138</contact>
      <attachment id="283162">
        <title>Portrait von Caroline Perriard</title>
        <format>jpg</format>
        <size-kb>162</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/91069.jpg</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Caroline Perriard élue par le Conseil fédéral au sein du Conseil de l’Institut de l’IPI</title>
      <lead>Lors de sa séance du 2 décembre 2024, le Conseil fédéral a élu Caroline Perriard au sein du Conseil de l’Institut, l'organe de direction suprême de l’Institut Fédéral de la Propriété Intellectuelle (IPI). Au 1er mars 2025, elle succèdera à Béatrice Renggli, dont le mandat arrive à terme fin février 2025 après douze années. Résidant dans le canton de Vaud, Caroline Perriard est experte en protection des données et en droit de la propriété intellectuelle et, depuis 2021, présidente de Femmes Juristes Suisse. </lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Issue du secteur privé, Caroline Perriard apportera une expertise complémentaire au sein du Conseil de l'Institut de l'IPI. Depuis juin 2023, elle est directrice de la protection des données et de la confidentialité auprès de BRP Bizzozero &amp; Partners SA. Avant, elle a été CEO et co-fondatrice de Legal in Digital, une société de conseil juridique affiliée au groupe BrandIT. Elle a occupé diverses fonctions auprès de Nestlé pendant plus de dix ans, d'abord en tant que conseillère juridique en PI pour le droit des marques, le droit d'auteur et le droit de l'Internet, puis comme conseillère juridique du secteur numérique et commerce électronique. Dans cette fonction, elle était responsable des aspects juridiques relatifs aux projets numériques de Nestlé dans le monde entier. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Caroline Perriard a étudié le droit à l'Université de Fribourg et à l'Université de Cologne, où elle a passé une année. Elle a obtenu son master en 2000 et un LL.M. à Stockholm en 2005. De 2008 à 2014, elle a enseigné à l'Université de Lausanne, dans le cadre du cours de master IP &amp; Internet et a été conférencière de 2017 à 2022 à la CREA Business School de Genève. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Composé de neuf membres, le Conseil de l'Institut est l'organe de direction suprême de l'IPI. Il fixe le montant des taxes et approuve le budget, le rapport de gestion et les comptes annuels. Il détermine en outre la composition de la Direction de l'IPI (à l'exception du directeur ou de la directrice dont la nomination relève du Conseil fédéral).&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Institut Fédéral de la Propriété Intellectuelle Regula Gerber, Responsable adjointe de la communication regula.gerber@ipi.ch, T +41 31 377 7138</contact>
      <attachment id="283163">
        <title>Portrait de Caroline Perriard</title>
        <format>jpg</format>
        <size-kb>162</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/91070.jpg</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Il Consiglio federale nomina Caroline Perriard nuovo membro del Consiglio d’Istituto dell’IPI</title>
      <lead>Nella sua seduta del 2 dicembre 2024, il Consiglio federale ha nominato Caroline Perriard nuovo membro del Consiglio d’Istituto dell’Istituto Federale della Proprietà Intellettuale (IPI). Nella sua funzione, Caroline Perriard subentrerà il 1° marzo 2025 a Béatrice Renggli, il cui mandato giungerà al termine a febbraio 2025 dopo 12 anni. Caroline Perriard vive nel Canton Vaud, è esperta in protezione dei dati e diritto della proprietà intellettuale nonché presidente di Giuriste Svizzera dal 2021.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Annoverando Caroline Perriard, il Consiglio d'Istituto dell'IPI integra nella rosa dei suoi membri un'esperta con comprovata esperienza nell'economia privata. Da giungo 2023, Caroline Perriard è Director Data Protection &amp; Privacy presso BRP Bizzozero &amp; Partners SA. Precedentemente ha ricoperto la posizione di CEO e Co-Founder Legal in Digital presso BrandIT. Per oltre dieci anni ha svolto diverse funzioni per Nestlé: inizialmente quale Legal Counsel IP nel diritto dei marchi, nel diritto d'autore nonché nel diritto di Internet, e in seguito quale Senior Legal Counsel Digital &amp; E-Commerce. In quest'ultima funzione era responsabile degli aspetti giuridici dei progetti digitali internazionali di Nestlé. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Caroline Perriard ha studiato giurisprudenza presso l'Università di Friburgo (Svizzera) e ha svolto un anno all'estero presso l'Università di Colonia. Nel 2000 ha concluso il master e nel 2005 un master in diritto (LL.M.) a Stoccolma. Dal 2008 al 2014 ha tenuto il corso di master IP &amp; Internet presso l'Università di Losanna e dal 2017 al 2022 è stata docente presso la CREA Business School di Ginevra. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Con i suoi nove membri, il Consiglio d'Istituto è l'organo direttivo supremo dell'IPI. Definisce le tasse e approva il bilancio preventivo, il rapporto di gestione e il conto annuale. Determina inoltre la composizione della direzione, ad eccezione del direttore, che è nominato dal Consiglio federale.&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Istituto Federale della Proprietà Intellettuale Regula Gerber, Vice responsabile della comunicazione regula.gerber@ipi.ch, T +41 31 377 7138</contact>
      <attachment id="283164">
        <title>Ritratto di Caroline Perriard</title>
        <format>jpg</format>
        <size-kb>162</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/91071.jpg</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Caroline Perriard elected to the IPI’s Institute Council by the Federal Council</title>
      <lead>At its meeting on 2 December 2024, the Federal Council elected Caroline Perriard to the Institute Council of the Swiss Federal Institute of Intellectual Property (IPI). On 1 March 2025, she will succeed Béatrice Renggli, whose 12-year term of office will expire at the end of February 2025. Caroline Perriard, who lives in the canton of Vaud, is an expert on data protection and intellectual property law and has been the president of Juristinnen Schweiz (Women Lawyers Switzerland) since 2021. </lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;In Caroline Perriard, the IPI's Institute Council is gaining a proven expert from the private sector. Since June 2023, Caroline Perriard has been the Director of Data Protection &amp; Privacy at BRP Bizzozero &amp; Partners SA. Prior to that, she was the CEO of BrandIT Legal in Digital, which she co-founded. For more than ten years, she worked in various roles at Nestlé, initially as a Legal Counsel on IP in Trade mark, Copyright and Internet Law and then as Senior Legal Counsel - Digital &amp; E-Commerce. In this role, she was responsible for the legal aspects of Nestlé's global digital projects. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Caroline Perriard studied law at the University of Fribourg and completed a year abroad at the University of Cologne. She obtained her Master's degree in 2000 and completed a postgraduate LL.M. in international commercial arbitration in Stockholm in 2005. From 2008 to 2014, she lectured on the IP &amp; Internet Master's programme at the University of Lausanne, and from 2017 to 2022, she taught at the CREA Business School in Geneva. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The Institute Council, composed of nine members, is the IPI's chief operational governing body. It sets the IPI's fees and approves the IPI's budget, annual report and financial statements. In addition, the Institute Council determines the composition of the Executive Board, with the exception of the Director General, who is elected by the Federal Council.&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Swiss Federal Institute of Intellectual Property Regula Gerber, Deputy Head of Communications regula.gerber@ipi.ch, T +41 31 377 7138</contact>
      <attachment id="283165">
        <title>Portrait of Caroline Perriard</title>
        <format>jpg</format>
        <size-kb>162</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/91072.jpg</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="10">
        <name lang="de">Bundesrat</name>
        <name lang="fr">Conseil fédéral</name>
        <name lang="it">Consiglio federale</name>
        <name lang="en">Federal Council</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="26">
        <name lang="de">Recht</name>
        <name lang="fr">Droit</name>
        <name lang="it">Diritto</name>
        <name lang="en">Legal Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
