<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="103572" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2024-12-16</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="323" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>701</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidg. Materialprüfungs- und Forschungsanstalt</name>
      <name lang="fr">Laboratoire fédéral d'essai des matériaux et de recherche</name>
      <name lang="it">Laboratorio federale di prova dei materiali e di ricerca</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Laboratory for Materials Testing and Research</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.empa.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.empa.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.empa.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.empa.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">contact@empa.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">contact@empa.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">contact@empa.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">contact@empa.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="701">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Wirtschaft, Bildung und Forschung</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'économie, de la formation et de la recherche</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'economia, della formazione e della ricerca</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Economic Affairs, Education and Research</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Dübendorf, St. Gallen und Thun</city>
      <title>Umfassende Materialflussanalyse veröffentlicht: Was die Schweiz aus ihrem Holz macht</title>
      <lead>Nachhaltig, nachwachsend und gut fürs Klima: Holz ist das Material der Zukunft. Aber wie viel steht uns zur Verfügung, und wie nutzen wir es am besten? Empa- und WSL-Forschende haben nun die Materialflüsse von Holz in der Schweiz genau analysiert – und ungenutzte Möglichkeiten entdeckt.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Die Schweiz hat sich ein so ambitioniertes wie notwendiges Ziel bis 2050 gesetzt: Netto Null. Einer der wichtigsten Rohstoffe auf dem Weg in eine klimaneutrale Zukunft ist Holz. Das erneuerbare Naturmaterial bindet beim Wachstum CO2 aus der Atmosphäre. Sowohl als Material als auch als Energieträger bieten Holz und seine zahlreichen Komponenten Alternativen zu fossilen Rohstoffen. Da verwundert es kaum, dass viele Industriezweige in Zukunft vermehrt auf Holz setzen wollen, sei es im Bau, bei der Produktion von Textilien und sogar in Sektoren wie Elektronik oder Pharma und Chemie.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Doch darüber, wie viel Holz uns für derartige Anwendungen zur Verfügung steht und in welcher Form, ist noch wenig bekannt. Um Klarheit zu schaffen, haben Forschende der Empa und der WSL nun sämtliche dokumentierte Materialflüsse von Holz in der Schweiz umfassenden analysiert. Ihre Studie, die kürzlich in der Zeitschrift «Industrial Ecology» veröffentlicht wurde, entstand im Rahmen von «SCENE», einer gemeinsamen Initiative des ETH-Bereichs (siehe Box).&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Genaues Bild dank guter Datenlage&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Für ihre Analyse nutzen die Forschenden Daten für das Jahr 2020 aus 21 verschiedenen Quellen – eine methodische Herausforderung, denn die Angaben in den unterschiedlichen Quellen stimmten nicht immer überein. Holz ist ein vielfältiger Rohstoff, der auf dem Weg von der Ernte zur Anwendung zahlreiche Formen annehmen kann, die sich oft im Volumen und im Feuchtigkeitsgehalt unterscheiden: Rohholz, Schnittholz, Holzspäne, Holzfasern für die Papierindustrie und vieles mehr. Die Harmonisierung der unterschiedlichen Holzflüsse war daher eine Mammutaufgabe.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Doch der Aufwand hat sich gelohnt. «Vergleichbare Studien aus dem Ausland setzen stark auf Modellierung. Sie haben Daten dazu, wie viel Holz im Wald geerntet wird, und berechnen daraus die weiteren Materialflüsse», erklärt die Erstautorin der Studie, Nadia Malinverno aus dem Empa-Labor «Technologie und Gesellschaft». Das Empa-Team verwendete dagegen fast durchgehend «echte» Daten – von der Holzernte und dem Import/Export über die Verarbeitung bis hin zu Recycling und Entsorgung. Dadurch ergibt sich ein deutlich genaueres Bild – wenn auch kein perfektes, betont Malinverno. «Die gute Datenlage in der Schweiz haben wir vor allem unseren Kolleginnen und Kollegen von der WSL und dem Bundesamt für Umwelt (BAFU) zu verdanken», ergänzt Co-Autorin und Empa-Forscherin Claudia Som.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Holz soll möglichst lange Holz bleiben&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Das Fazit: In der Schweiz besteht noch erhebliches Potenzial, was die nachhaltige Holznutzung betrifft. So beträgt die Recycling-Rate beim Holz gerade einmal knapp acht Prozent – beim Papier sind es an die 70. Ausserdem: «Von den fünf bis sieben Millionen Kubikmetern Holz, die wir in der Schweiz jährlich ernten, werden rund 40 Prozent direkt energetisch genutzt – sprich verbrannt», so Malinverno. Das ist keineswegs ideal, sind sich die zwei Autorinnen einig. Denn: «Damit das Holz seine Funktion als CO2-Speicher erfüllt, sollte es möglichst lange als Material in der Technosphäre verbleiben», erklärt Som.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Die Vision der Forscherinnen und der «SCENE»-Initiative ist die sogenannte Kaskadennutzung von Holz. Darin würde ein gefällter Baum zuerst zu möglichst grossen [mih1] [eta2] und hochwertigen Werkstücken verarbeitet werden – etwa zu Balken und Brettern für den Bau. In dieser Funktion sollten wir das Holz dann so lange wie möglich wiederverwenden. Erst wenn das nicht mehr geht, würde es zerkleinert und in die nächste Materialstufe überführt, beispielsweise als kleinere Bretter, Holzspäne oder Holzwerkstoffe. Und in den Ofen sollte das Holz erst dann kommen, wenn keine weitere Materialnutzung mehr möglich ist.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Diese Kaskade ist nur ein mögliches Beispiel. Welche Holznutzungen ökologisch und wirtschaftlich sinnvoll sind, wollen die Forschenden im Rahmen von «SCENE» noch näher untersuchen. Eines der Ziele ist auch, ausgewählte Materialströme genauer unter die Lupe zu nehmen: In welcher Form liegt das Holz in einem bestimmten Fluss vor? Wo genau fällt es an? Wie ist es behandelt? Und wie könnte man es sonst noch verwenden? All diese Fragen beschäftigen Nadia Malinverno, Claudia Som und ihre Mitforschenden in den nächsten Jahren.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class="nsbtextkasten"&gt;&lt;b&gt;Box: SCENE – eine «Joint Initiative» des ETH-Bereichs &lt;br /&gt;&lt;/b&gt;Das «Swiss Center of Excellence on Net-Zero Emissions» (SCENE) ist eine gemeinsame Initiative aller sechs Institutionen des ETH-Bereichs, die teilweise vom ETH-Rat finanziert wird. Gemeinsam betreiben die Partner interdisziplinäre Forschung, um die Schweiz bei der Erreichung des Netto-Null-Ziels bis ins Jahr 2050 zu unterstützen. Die beiden Empa-Labore «Technologie und Gesellschaft» und «Cellulose and Wood Materials» arbeiten gemeinsam mit dem PSI und der WSL am Arbeitspaket «Biomasse-Kohlenstoffkreislauf».&lt;br /&gt;www.scene-project.ch&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Nadia Malinverno Technologie und Gesellschaft Tel. +41 58 765 73 24 nadia.malinverno@empa.ch Claudia Som Technologie und Gesellschaft Tel. +41 58 765 78 43 claudia.som@empa.ch</contact>
      <attachment id="283440">
        <title>Illustration: Empa</title>
        <format>png</format>
        <size-kb>625</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/91196.png</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <link id="283443">
        <title>N Malinverno, S Buschor, K Vogel, F Schwarze, G Stadelmann, E Thürig, B Nowack, G Nyström, C Som: Resolving complexity: Material flow analysis of a national wood flow system integrating the versatility of wood; Journal of Industrial Ecology (2024).</title>
        <uri>https://doi.org/10.1111/jiec.13560</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="283444">
        <title>Umfassende Materialflussanalyse: Was die Schweiz aus ihrem Holz macht</title>
        <uri>https://www.empa.ch/web/s604/scene-cascading-use-of-wood</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Dübendorf, St. Gallen und Thun</city>
      <title>Analyse complète des flux de matériaux : Ce que la Suisse fait de son bois</title>
      <lead>Durable, renouvelable et bon pour le climat : le bois est le matériau de l'avenir. Mais quelle est la quantité à notre disposition et comment l'utiliser au mieux ? Des chercheurs de l'Empa et du WSL ont analysé avec précision les flux de matériaux en bois en Suisse – et découvert des possibilités inexploitées.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;La Suisse s'est fixé un objectif aussi ambitieux que nécessaire pour 2050 : Zéro net. L'une des matières premières les plus importantes sur la voie d'un avenir climatiquement neutre est le bois. Ce matériau naturel renouvelable absorbe le CO2 de l'atmosphère lors de sa croissance. Tant comme matériau que comme source d'énergie, le bois et ses nombreux composants offrent des alternatives aux matières premières fossiles. Il n'est donc pas étonnant que de nombreux secteurs industriels souhaitent miser davantage sur le bois à l'avenir, que ce soit dans la construction, la production de textiles ou même dans des secteurs comme l'électronique ou la pharmacie et la chimie.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Mais on sait encore peu de choses sur la quantité de bois dont nous disposons pour de telles applications et sous quelle forme. Pour y voir plus clair, des chercheurs de l'Empa et du WSL ont analysé en détail tous les flux de matériaux documentés pour le bois en Suisse. Leur étude, publiée récemment dans la revue « Industrial Ecology », a été réalisée dans le cadre de « SCENE », une initiative commune du Domaine des EPF (voir encadré).&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Une image précise grâce à de bonnes données&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Pour leur analyse, les chercheurs utilisent des données pour l'année 2020 provenant de 21 sources différentes – un défi méthodologique, car les données des différentes sources ne concordaient pas toujours. Le bois est une matière première variée qui peut prendre de nombreuses formes, souvent différentes en termes de volume et de teneur en humidité, entre la récolte et l'utilisation : Bois brut, bois de sciage, copeaux de bois, fibres de bois pour l'industrie du papier et bien d'autres. L'harmonisation des différents flux de bois a donc été une tâche colossale.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Mais l'effort en a valu la peine. « Les études comparables réalisées à l'étranger misent beaucoup sur la modélisation. Elles disposent de données sur la quantité de bois récoltée en forêt et calculent les autres flux de matériaux à partir de ces données », explique Nadia Malinverno, première auteure de l'étude et membre du laboratoire “Technologie et société” de l'Empa. L'équipe de l'Empa a en revanche utilisé presque systématiquement des données « réelles » – de la récolte du bois et de l'import/export au recyclage et à l'élimination, en passant par la transformation. Il en résulte une image nettement plus précise – même si elle n'est pas parfaite, souligne Nadia Malinverno. « Nous devons surtout la bonne situation des données en Suisse à nos collègues du WSL et de l'Office fédéral de l'environnement (OFEV) », ajoute Claudia Som, co-auteur et chercheuse à l'Empa.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Le bois doit rester du bois le plus longtemps possible&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Conclusion : il existe encore un potentiel considérable en Suisse en matière d'utilisation durable du bois. Ainsi, le taux de recyclage du bois atteint à peine huit pour cent, contre 70 pour le papier. En outre, « sur les cinq à sept millions de mètres cubes de bois que nous récoltons chaque année en Suisse, environ 40 pour cent sont directement utilisés à des fins énergétiques, c'est-à-dire brûlés », explique Nadia Malinverno. Ce n'est pas du tout idéal, s'accordent à dire les deux auteurs. En effet, « pour que le bois remplisse sa fonction de réservoir de CO2, il devrait rester le plus longtemps possible dans la technosphère en tant que matériau », explique Claudia Som.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;La vision des chercheuses et de l'initiative « SCENE » est l'utilisation en cascade du bois. Dans ce cadre, un arbre abattu serait d'abord transformé en pièces de la plus grande taille et de la meilleure qualité possible – par exemple en poutres et en planches pour la construction. Dans cette fonction, nous devrions ensuite réutiliser le bois aussi longtemps que possible. Ce n'est que lorsque ce n'est plus possible qu'il serait broyé et transféré vers le niveau de matériau suivant, par exemple sous forme de planches plus petites, de copeaux de bois ou de matériaux en bois. Et le bois ne devrait être mis au four que lorsqu'il n'est plus possible d'utiliser d'autres matériaux.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Cette cascade n'est qu'un exemple parmi d'autres. Dans le cadre de « SCENE », les chercheurs souhaitent étudier plus en détail quelles sont les utilisations du bois les plus judicieuses du point de vue écologique et économique. L'un des objectifs est également d'examiner de plus près certains flux de matériaux : Sous quelle forme le bois se présente-t-il dans un flux donné ? Où se trouve-t-il exactement ? Comment est-il traité ? Et comment pourrait-on l'utiliser autrement ? Toutes ces questions occuperont Nadia Malinverno, Claudia Som et leurs collègues de recherche au cours des prochaines années.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="nsbtextkasten"&gt;&lt;b&gt;Box : SCENE – une « Joint Initiative » du domaine des EPF &lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Le « Swiss Center of Excellence on Net-Zero Emissions » (SCENE) est une initiative commune des six institutions du Domaine des EPF, financée en partie par le Conseil des EPF. Ensemble, les partenaires mènent des recherches interdisciplinaires afin d'aider la Suisse à atteindre l'objectif zéro net d'ici 2050. Les deux laboratoires de l'Empa « Technologie et société » et « Cellulose and Wood Materials » travaillent ensemble avec le PSI et le WSL sur le package de travail « Cycle du carbone de la biomasse ». &lt;br /&gt;www.scene-project.ch&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Informations Nadia Malinverno Technology and Society Tél. +41 58 765 73 24 nadia.malinverno@empa.ch Claudia Som Technology and Society Tél. +41 58 765 78 43 claudia.som@empa.ch</contact>
      <attachment id="283441">
        <title>Illustration : Empa</title>
        <format>png</format>
        <size-kb>623</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/91197.png</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <link id="283443">
        <title>N Malinverno, S Buschor, K Vogel, F Schwarze, G Stadelmann, E Thürig, B Nowack, G Nyström, C Som: Resolving complexity: Material flow analysis of a national wood flow system integrating the versatility of wood; Journal of Industrial Ecology (2024).</title>
        <uri>https://doi.org/10.1111/jiec.13560</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="283446">
        <title>Analyse complète des flux de matériaux : Ce que la Suisse fait de son bois</title>
        <uri>https://www.empa.ch/web/s604/scene-cascading-use-of-wood</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Dübendorf, St. Gallen und Thun</city>
      <title>Comprehensive material flow analysis: Making the most of Switzerland's wood</title>
      <lead>Sustainable, renewable and good for the climate: Wood is the material of the future. But how much of it do we actually have and how do we make best use of it? Researchers from Empa and WSL have now analyzed the material flows of wood in Switzerland in detail – and discovered untapped opportunities.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Switzerland has set itself a goal that is as ambitious as it is necessary: net zero by 2050. One of the most important raw materials on the road to a climate-neutral future is wood. This renewable natural resource binds CO2 from the atmosphere as it grows. Both as a material and as an energy source, wood and its numerous components offer alternatives to fossil fuels and materials. It is therefore hardly surprising that many sectors of industry plan to rely more on wood in future, whether in construction, in textile manufacturing or even in sectors such as electronics, chemicals and pharmaceuticals.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Little is known, however, about how much wood is available for all these desired applications and in what form. In order to shed some light on the matter, researchers from Empa and WSL have now comprehensively analyzed all documented material flows of wood in Switzerland. Their study, which was recently published in the journal Industrial Ecology, was carried out as part of SCENE, a joint initiative of the ETH Domain (see box).&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Extensive data for an accurate assessment&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;For their analysis, the researchers used data for the year 2020 from 21 different sources – a methodological challenge, as the figures in the various sources did not always match. Wood is a diverse raw material that can take many forms on its way from harvest to use, often differing in volume and moisture content: raw timber, sawn wood, wood chips, wood pulp for the paper industry and much more. Harmonizing the different material flows was therefore a Herculean task.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;But the effort was worth it. “Comparable studies from abroad rely heavily on modeling. They have data on how much wood is harvested in the forest, and they use this to calculate the subsequent material flows,” explains Nadia Malinverno from Empa's Technology and Society laboratory, the lead author of the study. The Empa team, on the other hand, used “real” data almost throughout, from timber harvesting and import/export to processing, recycling and disposal. This results in a much more accurate picture – albeit not a perfect one, emphasizes Malinverno. “We have to thank our colleagues at WSL and the Federal Office for the Environment (FOEN) for the good data that is available in Switzerland,” adds co-author and Empa researcher Claudia Som.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Wood should stay wood for as long as possible&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The conclusion: Switzerland still has considerable potential when it comes to sustainable use of wood. For example, the recycling rate for wood is just under eight percent, compared to around 70 percent for paper. What's more: “Of the five to seven million cubic meters of wood that we harvest in Switzerland every year, around 40 percent is used directly for energy – in other words, it is burned,” says Malinverno. The researchers agree that this is far from ideal. Because: “For wood to fulfill its function as a long-term CO2 sink, it should remain in the technosphere as a material for as long as possible,” explains Som.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The vision of the researchers and of the SCENE initiative is a so-called cascading use of wood. In this approach, a harvested tree would first be processed into the largest possible high-quality product – such as beams and boards for construction. This wood should then be (re-)used in this function for as long as possible. Only when reuse is no longer feasible would the wood be broken down into the next material stage, for example as smaller boards, wood chips or wood-based materials. It should only go into the furnace when it can no longer be used as a material.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;This is just one possible example of a wood cascade. As part of SCENE, the researchers want to investigate in more detail which uses of wood make the most sense, both from an ecological and economic perspective. One of their goals is to take a closer look at selected material flows: In what form is wood present in a particular flow? Where exactly is it produced? How is it treated? And how else could it be used? Nadia Malinverno, Claudia Som and their fellow researchers will be looking into these questions in the coming years.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="nsbtextkasten"&gt;&lt;b&gt;Box: SCENE – a Joint Initiative of the ETH Domain&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/b&gt;The Swiss Center of Excellence on Net-Zero Emissions (SCENE) is a joint initiative of all six institutions of the ETH Domain, which is partly funded by the ETH Board. Together, the partners conduct interdisciplinary research to support Switzerland in achieving the net zero target by 2050. The two Empa laboratories Technology and Society and Cellulose and Wood Materials are working together with PSI and WSL in the work package Biomass Carbon Cycle.&lt;br /&gt;www.scene-project.ch&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Further information Nadia Malinverno Technology and Society Phone +41 58 765 73 24 nadia.malinverno@empa.ch Claudia Som Technology and Society Phone +41 58 765 78 43 claudia.som@empa.ch</contact>
      <attachment id="283442">
        <title>Illustration: Empa</title>
        <format>png</format>
        <size-kb>609</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/91198.png</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <link id="283443">
        <title>N Malinverno, S Buschor, K Vogel, F Schwarze, G Stadelmann, E Thürig, B Nowack, G Nyström, C Som: Resolving complexity: Material flow analysis of a national wood flow system integrating the versatility of wood; Journal of Industrial Ecology (2024).</title>
        <uri>https://doi.org/10.1111/jiec.13560</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="283448">
        <title>Comprehensive material flow analysis of Switzerland's wood</title>
        <uri>https://www.empa.ch/web/s604/scene-cascading-use-of-wood</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="8">
        <name lang="de">Bildung und Forschung</name>
        <name lang="fr">Formation et recherche</name>
        <name lang="it">Formazione e ricerca</name>
        <name lang="en">Education and Research</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="11">
        <name lang="de">Energie</name>
        <name lang="fr">Énergie</name>
        <name lang="it">Energia</name>
        <name lang="en">Energy</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="29">
        <name lang="de">Umwelt und Natur</name>
        <name lang="fr">Environnement et nature</name>
        <name lang="it">Ambiente e natura</name>
        <name lang="en">Environment and Nature</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="47">
        <name lang="de">Wirtschaft</name>
        <name lang="fr">Économie</name>
        <name lang="it">Economia</name>
        <name lang="en">Economic Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
