<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="103471" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2024-12-09</pubdate>
    <blocking-period>2024-12-09</blocking-period>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="318" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>301</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Bundesamt für Statistik</name>
      <name lang="fr">Office fédéral de la statistique</name>
      <name lang="it">Ufficio federale di statistica</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Statistical Office</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.statistik.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.statistique.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.statistica.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.statistics.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@bfs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@bfs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@bfs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@bfs.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="1080" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>701</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Staatssekretariat für Bildung, Forschung und Innovation</name>
      <name lang="fr">Secrétariat d'Etat à la formation, à la recherche et à l'innovation</name>
      <name lang="it">Segreteria di Stato per la formazione, la ricerca e l'innovazione</name>
      <name lang="en">State Secretariat for Education, Research and Innovation</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.sbfi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.sbfi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.sbfi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.sbfi.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@sbfi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@sbfi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@sbfi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@sbfi.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="301">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement des Innern</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'intérieur</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'interno</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Home Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <department id="701">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Wirtschaft, Bildung und Forschung</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'économie, de la formation et de la recherche</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'economia, della formazione e della ricerca</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Economic Affairs, Education and Research</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Neuchâtel</city>
      <title>Spezialisierung in der höheren Berufsbildung häufig mit Karriereschritten verbunden</title>
      <lead>Rund die Hälfte der Absolventinnen und Absolventen einer höheren Berufsbildung übernimmt im ersten Jahr nach Abschluss mehr Verantwortung im Betrieb. Während der Ausbildung werden sie häufig von ihrem Arbeitgeber unterstützt. Diese übernehmen nicht nur einen Teil der Ausbildungskosten, sondern unterstützen die Angestellten auch bei der Bewältigung der zeitlichen Belastung durch die Ausbildung. Das zeigen die Ergebnisse der Erhebung zur höheren Berufsbildung des Prüfungsjahrgangs 2022 des Bundesamtes für Statistik (BFS).</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Diese Medienmitteilung und weitere Informationen zum Thema finden Sie auf der Website des BFS (siehe Link unten).&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Miro Bosia, BFS, Sektion Bildungssystem, Tel.: +41 58 46329 43, E-Mail: miro.bosia@bfs.admin.ch Stefan Rüber, BFS, Sektion Bildungssystem, Tel.: +41 58 466 79 03, E-Mail: stefan.rueber@bfs.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="283080">
        <title>Kompletter Text und Mediendossier</title>
        <uri>https://www.bfs.admin.ch/news/de/2024-0168</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Neuchâtel</city>
      <title>La spécialisation dans la formation professionnelle supérieure souvent synonyme de promotion</title>
      <lead>Près de la moitié des personnes ayant achevé une formation professionnelle supérieure assument davantage de responsabilités dans l’entreprise dès la première année qui suit l’obtention de leur diplôme. Pour suivre cette formation, elles ont souvent bénéficié de l’appui de leurs employeurs. Ceux-ci prennent non seulement en charge une partie de leurs frais de formation, mais les aident parfois aussi en leur accordant du temps pour se former. C’est ce qui ressort de l’enquête sur la formation professionnelle supérieure réalisée par l’Office fédéral de la statistique (OFS) auprès des personnes candidates en 2022.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Vous trouverez ce communiqué de presse et d'autres informations sur ce thème sur le site web de l'OFS (cf. lien ci-dessous).&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Miro Bosia, OFS, section Système de formation, tél.: +41 58 46329 43, e-mail: miro.bosia@bfs.admin.ch Stefan Rüber, OFS, Section Système de formation, tél.: +41 58 466 79 03, E-Mail: stefan.rueber@bfs.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="283081">
        <title>Texte intégral et dossier de presse</title>
        <uri>https://www.bfs.admin.ch/news/fr/2024-0168</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Neuchâtel</city>
      <title>Specializzazione nella formazione professionale superiore spesso legata a passi in avanti nella carriera</title>
      <lead>A un anno dal diploma, circa la metà delle persone che hanno seguito una formazione professionale superiore assume maggiori responsabilità nell’impresa in cui lavora. Durante la formazione spesso queste persone ricevono il sostegno del loro datore di lavoro. Non solo questi assume una parte dei costi di formazione, ma sostiene i dipendenti anche nel gestire l’onere della formazione in termini di tempo. Questo è quanto emerge dai risultati dell’indagine sulla formazione professionale superiore della coorte di esame 2022 realizzata dall’Ufficio federale di statistica (UST).</lead>
      <text link="no">Il presente comunicato stampa e ulteriori informazioni sul tema sono reperibili sulla pagina Internet dell'UST (link sotto). </text>
      <contact>Miro Bosia, UST, sezione Sistema di formazione, tel.: +41 58 46329 43, e-mail: miro.bosia@bfs.admin.ch Stefan Rüber, UST, sezione Sistema di formazione, tel.: +41 58 466 79 03, e-mail: stefan.rueber@bfs.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="283082">
        <title>Testo integrale e dossier per i media</title>
        <uri>https://www.bfs.admin.ch/news/it/2024-0168</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Neuchâtel</city>
      <title>Professional education specialisation often linked to career advancement</title>
      <lead>Around half of those who complete a professional education programme take on more responsibility in their company in the first year following completion. They are often supported during their studies by employers, who both contribute to the cost of programmes and offer solutions to help employees combine work and study. These are the results of the Survey on Professional Education of the Federal Statistical Office (FSO) for the 2022 examination year.</lead>
      <text link="no">This press release and further information on the topic can be found on the FSO website (see link below). </text>
      <contact>Miro Bosia, FSO, section Education System, tel.: +41 58 46329 43, email: miro.bosia@bfs.admin.ch Stefan Rüber, FSO, section Education System, tel.: +41 58 466 79 03, email: stefan.rueber@bfs.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="283083">
        <title>Complete text and press kit</title>
        <uri>https://www.bfs.admin.ch/news/en/2024-0168</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="8">
        <name lang="de">Bildung und Forschung</name>
        <name lang="fr">Formation et recherche</name>
        <name lang="it">Formazione e ricerca</name>
        <name lang="en">Education and Research</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="43">
        <name lang="de">Statistik</name>
        <name lang="fr">Statistiques</name>
        <name lang="it">Statistica</name>
        <name lang="en">Statistics</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
