<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="58589" revoked="no">
    <version>4</version>
    <pubdate>2015-09-06</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="yes" id="811" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>801</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Bundesamt für Umwelt BAFU</name>
      <name lang="fr">Office fédéral de l'environnement OFEV</name>
      <name lang="it">Ufficio federale dell'ambiente UFAM</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Office for the Environment FOEN</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.bafu.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.bafu.admin.ch/fr</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.bafu.admin.ch/it</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.bafu.admin.ch/en</www>
      <email lang="de">info@bafu.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@bafu.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@bafu.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@bafu.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="801">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Umwelt, Verkehr, Energie und Kommunikation</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'environnement, des transports, de l'énergie et de la communication</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'ambiente, dei trasporti, dell'energia e delle comunicazioni</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of the Environment, Transport, Energy and Communications</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.uvek.admin.ch/uvek/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.uvek.admin.ch/uvek/fr/home.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.uvek.admin.ch/uvek/it/home.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.uvek.admin.ch/uvek/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-uvek.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-uvek.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-uvek.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-uvek.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Treffen der Geberländer in Paris: Einigung auf einen gemeinsamen Ansatz zur Berichterstattung über private Gelder</title>
      <lead>An einem zweitägigen Treffen in Paris haben die Ministerinnen und Minister von 18 Geberländern bekräftigt, jährlich 100 Milliarden Dollar zur Finanzierung klimapolitischer Massnahmen in Entwicklungsländern bereitzustellen.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Das Treffen der 18 Geberländer stand unter dem Ko-Vorsitz von Bundesrätin Doris Leuthard und Caroline Atkinson, Stellvertretende Nationale Sicherheitsberaterin für Aussenwirtschaft und enge Mitarbeiterin von US-Präsident Barack Obama in Klimafragen. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In einer gemeinsamen Erklärung bekräftigten die Ministerinnen und Minister ihre Entschlossenheit, ab 2020 jährlich 100 Milliarden US-Dollar aus öffentlichen und privaten Quellen zu mobilisieren, um die Entwicklungsländer bei der Durchführung von Massnahmen zur Emissionsverringerung und zur Anpassung an den Klimawandel zu unterstützen. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Die Ministerinnen und Minister kündigten die Fortsetzung der Bemühungen an, die Verfügbarkeit von Daten und die Methode der Berichterstattung über die mobilisierten Gelder für die Klimafinanzierung zu verbessern. Die heute verfügbaren Daten vermitteln kein vollständiges Bild der Beiträge.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Sektion Medien BAFU Telefon: +41 58 462 90 00 Email: mediendienst@bafu.admin.ch</contact>
      <attachment id="141867">
        <title>Joint Statement on Tracking Progress Towards the 100 billion Goal</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>204</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/40866.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="141868">
        <title>Technical Working Group input to the OECD-CPI report</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>528</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/41225.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <link id="141865">
        <title>Dossier des BAFU zur Klimakonferenz von Paris (COP21)</title>
        <uri>http://www.bafu.admin.ch/klima/13805/15238/index.html?lang=de</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="141866">
        <title>Klimakonferenz von Paris (COP21)</title>
        <uri>http://newsroom.unfccc.int/paris/</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Rencontre des Etats donateurs à Paris: approche commune pour mesurer les fonds privés</title>
      <lead>Les ministres des 18 pays donateurs réunis à Paris pour une rencontre de deux jours sont décidés à remplir leur engagement de mobiliser annuellement 100 milliards de dollars pour financer la politique climatique des pays en développement.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;La rencontre des 18 pays donateurs était co-présidée par la conseillère fédérale Doris Leuthard et Mme Caroline Atkinson, conseillère adjointe à la sécurité nationale pour les affaires économiques internationales, collaboratrice directe du président des Etats-Unis Barack Obama pour les questions climatiques. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Dans une déclaration commune, les ministres ont réaffirmé leur détermination de mobiliser, à partir de 2020, annuellement 100 milliards de dollars US de sources publiques et privées afin de soutenir la réduction des émissions et les mesures d'adaptation dans les pays en voie de développement. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Les ministres ont annoncé vouloir poursuivre leurs efforts en vue d'améliorer la mise à disposition des données et la méthode d'évaluation du financement climatique. Les données actuellement disponibles ne représentent pas un tableau complet des contributions.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Section Médias OFEV Téléphone: +41 58 462 90 00 Courriel: mediendienst@bafu.admin.ch</contact>
      <attachment id="141867">
        <title>Joint Statement on Tracking Progress Towards the 100 billion Goal</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>204</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/40866.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="141868">
        <title>Technical Working Group input to the OECD-CPI report</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>528</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/41225.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <link id="141863">
        <title>Dossier de l’OFEV sur la Conférence sur le climat de Paris (COP 21)</title>
        <uri>http://www.bafu.admin.ch/klima/13805/15238/index.html?lang=fr</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="141864">
        <title>Conférence sur le climat de Paris COP21</title>
        <uri>http://newsroom.unfccc.int/paris/</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Vertice dei Paesi donatori a Parigi: adottato un approccio comune per favorire fondi privati</title>
      <lead>I ministri dei 18 Paesi donatori riuniti a Parigi per un incontro di due giorni sono decisi a rispettare il proprio impegno a mobilitare annualmente 100 miliardi di dollari per finanziare la politica climatica dei Paesi in via di sviluppo.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;L'incontro dei 18 Paesi donatori era co-presieduto dalla Consigliera federale Doris Leuthard e da Caroline Atkinson, Consigliera aggiunta alla sicurezza nazionale per gli affari economici internazionali e collaboratrice diretta del Presidente degli Stati Uniti Barack Obama per le questioni climatiche. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In una dichiarazione comune, i ministri hanno riaffermato la propria determinazione a mobilitare annualmente, a partire dal 2020, 100 miliardi di dollari di fondi pubblici e privati per sostenere la riduzione delle emissioni e l'adeguamento delle misure nei Paesi in via di sviluppo. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I ministri hanno annunciato di voler proseguire i lavori volti a migliorare la disponibilità di dati e la metodologia per misurare i fondi mobilitati a favore del clima. I dati attualmente disponibili non forniscono un quadro completo dei contributi.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Sezione Media Telefono: +41 58 462 90 00 E-mail: mediendienst@bafu.admin.ch</contact>
      <attachment id="141867">
        <title>Joint Statement on Tracking Progress Towards the 100 billion Goal</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>204</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/40866.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="141868">
        <title>Technical Working Group input to the OECD-CPI report</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>528</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/41225.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <link id="141861">
        <title>Dossier dell’UFAM sulla Conferenza sul clima di Parigi (COP21)</title>
        <uri>http://www.bafu.admin.ch/klima/13805/15238/index.html?lang=it</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="141862">
        <title>Conferenza sul clima di Parigi (COP21)</title>
        <uri>http://newsroom.unfccc.int/paris/</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Donor States Meeting in Paris: adoption of a common approach to measure mobilised private finance</title>
      <lead>The ministers of the 18 donor countries who met in Paris for a two-day meeting are determined to make good on their commitment to mobilise 100 billion dollars per year in climate finance for developing countries.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;The meeting of 18 donor countries was co-chaired by Swiss Federal Councillor Doris Leuthard and Caroline Atkinson, Deputy National Security Advisor for International Economic Affairs, who works directly with U.S. President Barack Obama on climate issues. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In a joint statement, the ministers reaffirmed their determination to mobilise from 2020 USD $100 billion from public and private sources per year in order to support emissions reduction and adaptation measures in developing countries. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The ministers announced their intention to continue efforts to improve data availability and the methodology for measuring mobilised climate finance. The currently available data does not provide a complete picture of the contributions.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Media Section Telephone: +41 58 462 90 00 E-mail: mediendienst@bafu.admin.ch</contact>
      <attachment id="141867">
        <title>Joint Statement on Tracking Progress Towards the 100 billion Goal</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>204</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/40866.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="141868">
        <title>Technical Working Group input to the OECD-CPI report</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>528</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/41225.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <link id="141859">
        <title>FOEN dossier on the Paris Climate Conference (COP21)</title>
        <uri>http://www.bafu.admin.ch/klima/13805/15238/index.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="141860">
        <title>Paris Climate Conference (COP21)</title>
        <uri>http://newsroom.unfccc.int/paris/</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <offers>
      <offer id="143" org-id="811">
        <name lang="de">Medienmitteilungen des BAFU</name>
        <name lang="fr">Communiqués de l'OFEV</name>
        <name lang="it">Comunicati dell'UFAM</name>
        <name lang="en">Media releases of the FOEN</name>
      </offer>
    </offers>
    <keywords>
      <keyword id="560" org-id="811">
        <name lang="de">Internationales</name>
        <name lang="fr">Affaires internationales</name>
        <name lang="it">Affari Internazionali</name>
        <name lang="en">International Affairs</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="620" org-id="811">
        <name lang="de">Klima</name>
        <name lang="fr">Climat</name>
        <name lang="it">Clima</name>
        <name lang="en">Climate</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="173" org-id="811">
        <name lang="de">Bundesamt für Umwelt: Startseite</name>
        <name lang="fr">Office fédéral de l'environnement: page d'accueil</name>
        <name lang="it">Ufficio federale dell'ambiente: pagina iniziale</name>
        <name lang="en">Federal Office for the Environment: Homepage</name>
      </keyword>
    </keywords>
    <topics>
      <topic id="29">
        <name lang="de">Umwelt und Natur</name>
        <name lang="fr">Environnement et nature</name>
        <name lang="it">Ambiente e natura</name>
        <name lang="en">Environment and Nature</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
