<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="92463" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2023-01-09</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="323" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>701</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidg. Materialprüfungs- und Forschungsanstalt</name>
      <name lang="fr">Laboratoire fédéral d'essai des matériaux et de recherche</name>
      <name lang="it">Laboratorio federale di prova dei materiali e di ricerca</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Laboratory for Materials Testing and Research</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.empa.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.empa.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.empa.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.empa.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">contact@empa.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">contact@empa.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">contact@empa.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">contact@empa.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="701">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Wirtschaft, Bildung und Forschung</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'économie, de la formation et de la recherche</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'economia, della formazione e della ricerca</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Economic Affairs, Education and Research</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Dübendorf, St. Gallen und Thun</city>
      <title>Förderung bewilligt: Zwei weitere Technologietransferzentren für die Schweiz</title>
      <lead>Das Eidgenössisches Departement für Wirtschaft, Bildung und Forschung (WBF) und die «AM-TTC Alliance», der Dachverband der Technologietransferzentren im Bereich fortschrittlicher Fertigungstechnologien, haben im November entschieden, zwei weitere Zentren in den Bereichen der kollaborativen Robotik und der Photonik bis Ende 2024 mit 6.5 Millionen Franken zu fördern.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Die Schweizer Hochschulen und Forschungseinrichtungen sind in vielen Gebieten weltweit führend. Auch hinsichtlich der Forschungsergebnisse und den daraus resultierenden Patenten gehört die Schweiz zu den führenden Nationen. Doch oftmals finden neue Herstellungstechnologien nicht ihren Weg aus den hiesigen Forschungslaboren in die industrielle Anwendung. Ihr Weg endet dann im «Tal des Todes» für Innovationen.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Hier setzt die Initiative zum Aufbau eines Verbunds von Schweizer Technologietransferzentren an, den «Advanced Manufacturing Technologie Transfer Centers» (kurz AM-TTC). Die Initiative ist ein Teil des Aktionsplans «Digitalisierung» des Bundes und hat zum Ziel, die Schweiz langfristig als modernen und qualitativ hochstehenden Produktionsstandort zu erhalten. Die AM-TTC-Initiative will Infrastrukturen aufbauen und zugänglich machen, die es der Schweizer Industrie – insbesondere den hiesigen KMU – ermöglichen, neue Herstellungstechnologien kennenzulernen, auszuprobieren und in ihre Produktion zu transferieren.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Die einzelnen Zentren werden in einer Partnerschaft zwischen der öffentlichen Hand und der Industrie («Public-Private Partnership») gegründet und finanziert. Die Trägerschaft und die Konsortien der Zentren setzen sich aus Schweizer Forschungseinrichtungen und Industrieunternehmen zusammen. Somit sind diese Zentren gleichzeitig auch Orte, an denen die Partner aus Wissenschaft und Industrie neue Herstellungstechnologien gemeinsam weiterentwickeln und industrietauglich machen können.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Erste Zentren 2019 gegründet&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Im Jahr 2019 wurden bereits zwei Zentren gegründet: das «ANAXAM»-Zentrum, das es Industrieunternehmen einfacher macht, die Strahllinien des Paul Scherrer Instituts (PSI) für die Untersuchung ihrer Materialien und Produkte zu nutzen; und das «Swiss m4m Center», das MedTech-Unternehmen Zugang gibt zu einer nach ISO 13485 zertifizierten Pilotproduktionslinie für 3D-gedruckte medizinische Implantate. In der Startphase bis Ende 2020 wurden diese beiden Zentren mit Mitteln des ETH-Rats unterstützt; seit Anfang 2021 werden sie mit Mittel des Bundes als Forschungseinrichtungen von nationaler Bedeutung gefördert (gemäss Art. 15 des Gesetzes zur Förderung von Forschung und Innovation (FIFG)).&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Förderung für zwei weitere Technologiezentren&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Ende November dieses Jahrs haben nun das Eidgenössisches Departement für Wirtschaft, Bildung und Forschung (WBF) und die «AM-TTC Alliance», der Dachverband der AM-TTC-Initiative, nach einem umfassenden Auswahlverfahren entschieden, zwei weitere Zentren aus den Bereichen der kollaborativen Robotik und der Photonik bis Ende 2024 mit Mitteln in Höhe von insgesamt 6.5 Millionen Franken zu fördern. Die Förderung erfolgt zum einen aus Mitteln des ETH-Rats, der den Aufbau der AM-TTC in der Schweiz als Massnahme seiner strategischen Planung 2021-2024 definiert hat. Zum anderen erhalten die Zentren ebenfalls Fördergelder vom Bund gemäss Art. 15 FIFG.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Das «Swiss Cobotics Competence Center» (S3C) in Biel will die Chancen der Zusammenarbeit zwischen Mensch und Roboter aufzeigen. Sein Ziel ist es, die Lücke zwischen den theoretischen Fähigkeiten von Robotern und der industriellen Realität zu schliessen und somit kollaborative Roboter stärker in die industrielle Anwendung zu bringen. Schweizer Unternehmen erhalten mit dem S3C Zugang zu Know-how und einer Demonstrations- und Testplattform für innovative Cobotic-Lösungen. Neben dem Schweizer Innovationspark Biel/Bienne und der dort ansässigen «Swiss Smart Factory» gehört auch die Berner Fachhochschule zu den Gründungsmitgliedern des S3C. Und seit dessen Gründung im November 2022 sind bereits viele weitere Partner aus Industrie und Wissenschaft als Mitglieder hinzugekommen.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Das zweite neu gegründete AM-TTC, das «Swiss Photonics Integration Center» («Swiss PIC»), ist im Schweizer Innovationspark «InnovAare» angesiedelt. Im Fokus dieses Zentrums stehen optische Komponenten und Systeme, die Lichtteilchen, sogenannte Photonen, transportieren und verarbeiten. Das «Swiss PITC» wird Anlagen aufbauen, die es ermöglichen, auch kleinste optische Komponenten in grössere Systeme oder Geräte zu integrieren und sie zu testen. In der Schweiz gibt es viele Unternehmen und Forschungsgruppen, die neue innovative photonische Komponenten entwickeln und herstellen. Oft haben sie keinen Zugang zu solchen Anlagen. Diese Lücke soll das «Swiss PITC» schliessen, in dem es solche Anlagen zugänglich macht und den Unternehmen hilft, eigene Integrations- und Verpackungslösungen in ihrer Produktion aufzubauen.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Infobox: Die &lt;/b&gt;«&lt;b&gt;AM-TTC Alliance&lt;/b&gt;»&lt;b&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Am 4. Februar 2019 haben an der Empa in Dübendorf 22 Schweizer Forschungsinstitutionen und Industrieunternehmen den Verein «AM-TTC Alliance», den Dachverband dieser Technologietransferzentren, gegründet. Zu den Mitgliedern zählen Institutionen des ETH-Bereichs, Fachhochschulen und andere Forschungseinrichtungen, Industrieunternehmen wie ABB, BASF, Bühler, Hilti, Oerlikon, Rolex und Siemens sowie der Industrieverband Swissmem. Geschäftsführer ist aktuell der Empa-Forscher Lars Sommerhäuser.&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Dr. Lars Sommerhäuser Empa, Surface Science &amp; Coating Technologies / Geschäftsführer «AM-TTC Alliance» Tel. +41 58 765 47 87 lars.sommerhaeuser@am-ttc.ch</contact>
      <attachment id="241003">
        <title>Kollaborative Robotik für industrielle Anwendungen – das steht im neu geförderten «Swiss Cobotics Competence Center» (S3C) in Biel im Zentrum. Bild: Envato</title>
        <format>jpg</format>
        <size-kb>308</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/74811.jpg</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="241004">
        <title>Die AM-TTC Alliance wurde auf Initiative der Empa gegründet und hat vom Staatssekretariat für Bildung, Forschung und Innovation den Auftrag, Gesuche zu evaluieren und die Entwicklung von AM-TTC-Zentren zu begleiten. Bild: Envato</title>
        <format>jpg</format>
        <size-kb>121</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/74812.jpg</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="241005">
        <title>Ziel der AM-TTC-Initiative ist es, ein Netzwerk von mehreren Zentren mit unterschiedlichen thematischen Schwerpunkten zu schaffen. Bild: Envato</title>
        <format>jpg</format>
        <size-kb>280</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/74813.jpg</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <link id="241001">
        <title>Empa Homepage</title>
        <uri>https://www.empa.ch/web/s604/am-ttc-alliance-2023</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="241002">
        <title>Mehr Information / De plus amples informations /Further information about the AM-TTC initiative</title>
        <uri>https://www.am-ttc.ch/</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Dübendorf, St. Gallen und Thun</city>
      <title>Soutien approuvé: Deux centres de transfert de technologie supplémentaires pour la Suisse</title>
      <lead>Le Département fédéral de l'économie, de la formation et de la recherche (DEFR) et l'Alliance AM-TTC, l'association faîtière des centres de transfert de technologie dans le domaine des technologies de fabrication avancées, ont décidé en novembre de soutenir deux autres centres dans les domaines de la robotique collaborative et de la photonique à hauteur de 6,5 millions de francs jusqu'à fin 2024.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Les hautes écoles et les instituts de recherche suisses sont des leaders mondiaux dans de nombreux domaines. La Suisse fait également partie des nations leaders en ce qui concerne les résultats de la recherche et les brevets qui en découlent. Pourtant, il arrive souvent que de nouvelles technologies de fabrication ne passent pas des laboratoires de recherche locaux à l'application industrielle. Leur chemin se termine alors dans la "vallée de la mort" pour les innovations.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;C'est là qu'intervient l'initiative visant à créer un réseau de centres suisses de transfert de technologie, les "Advanced Manufacturing Technologie Transfer Centers" (en abrégé AM-TTC). Cette initiative fait partie du plan d'action "numérisation" de la Confédération et a pour objectif de maintenir à long terme la Suisse en tant que site de production moderne et de haute qualité. L'initiative AM-TTC vise à mettre en place et à rendre accessibles des infrastructures qui permettent à l'industrie suisse - en particulier aux PME locales - de découvrir et d'expérimenter de nouvelles technologies de fabrication et de les transférer dans leur production.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Les différents centres sont créés et financés dans le cadre d'un partenariat entre les pouvoirs publics et l'industrie ("Public-Private Partnership"). Les consortiums des centres se composent d'instituts de recherche et d'entreprises industrielles suisses. Ainsi, ces centres sont également des lieux où les partenaires scientifiques et industriels peuvent développer ensemble de nouvelles technologies de fabrication et les rendre compatibles avec l'industrie.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Premiers centres créés en 2019&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Deux centres ont déjà été créés en 2019 : le centre "ANAXAM", qui permet aux entreprises industrielles d'utiliser plus facilement les lignes de faisceau de l'Institut Paul Scherrer (PSI) pour étudier leurs matériaux et produits ; et le "Swiss m4m Center", qui donne aux entreprises MedTech l'accès à une ligne de production pilote certifiée ISO 13485 pour les implants médicaux imprimés en 3D. Durant la phase de démarrage, jusqu'à fin 2020, ces deux centres ont été soutenus par des fonds du Conseil des EPF ; depuis début 2021, ils sont soutenus par des fonds de la Confédération en tant qu'institutions de recherche d'importance nationale (conformément à l'art. 15 de la loi sur l'encouragement de la recherche et de l'innovation (LERI)).&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Soutien à deux autres centres de transfert de technologie&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Fin novembre de cette année, le Département fédéral de l'économie, de la formation et de la recherche (DEFR) et l'Alliance AM-TTC, l'organisation faîtière de l'initiative AM-TTC, ont décidé, à l'issue d'une procédure de sélection approfondie, de soutenir deux autres centres dans les domaines de la robotique collaborative et de la photonique jusqu'à fin 2024 avec des fonds d'un montant total de 6,5 millions de francs. Le soutien provient d'une part des fonds du Conseil des EPF, qui a défini le développement des AM-TTC en Suisse comme une mesure de sa planification stratégique 2021-2024. D'autre part, les centres reçoivent également des subventions de la Confédération conformément à l'art. 15 LERI.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Le "Swiss Cobotics Competence Center" (S3C) de Bienne veut mettre en évidence la collaboration entre l'homme et le robot. Son objectif est de combler l'écart entre les capacités théoriques des robots et la réalité industrielle, et donc d'amener davantage les robots collaboratifs dans l'application industrielle. Grâce au S3C, les entreprises suisses ont accès au savoir-faire et à une plateforme de démonstration et de test pour des solutions "cobotiques" innovantes. Outre le parc suisse d'innovation Biel/Bienne et la "Swiss Smart Factory" qui y est installée, la Haute école spécialisée bernoise fait également partie des membres fondateurs du S3C. Et depuis la création du S3C en novembre 2022, de nombreux partenaires de l'industrie et de la science sont déjà devenus membres.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Le deuxième AM-TTC nouvellement créé, le "Swiss Photonics Integration Center" ("Swiss PIC"), est implanté dans le parc d'innovation suisse "InnovAare". Ce centre se concentre sur les composants et les systèmes optiques qui transportent et traitent les particules de lumière, appelées photons. Le "Swiss PITC" mettra en place des installations qui permettront d'intégrer les plus petits composants optiques dans des systèmes ou appareils plus grands et de les tester. En Suisse, il existe de nombreuses entreprises et groupes de recherche qui développent et fabriquent de nouveaux composants photoniques innovants. Souvent, ils n'ont pas accès à de telles installations. Le "Swiss PITC" vise à combler cette lacune en rendant de telles installations accessibles et en aidant les entreprises à mettre en place leurs propres solutions d'intégration et de conditionnement dans leurs lignes de production.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Info box: L'Alliance AM-TTC&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Le 4 février 2019, 22 institutions de recherche et entreprises industrielles suisses ont fondé à l'Empa à Dübendorf l'Alliance AM-TTC, l'association faîtière de ces centres de transfert de technologie. Parmi les membres figurent des institutions du domaine des EPF, des hautes écoles spécialisées et d'autres instituts de recherche, des entreprises industrielles comme ABB, BASF, Bühler, Hilti, Oerlikon, Rolex et Siemens ainsi que l'association industrielle Swissmem. Le directeur général est actuellement le chercheur de l'Empa Lars Sommerhäuser.&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Dr. Lars Sommerhäuser Empa, Surface Science &amp; Coating Technologies / Directeur, Alliance AM-TTC Tél. +41 58 765 47 87 lars.sommerhaeuser@am-ttc.ch</contact>
      <attachment id="241006">
        <title>La robotique collaborative pour les applications industrielles - c'est ce qui est au centre du "Swiss Cobotics Competence Center" (S3C) nouvellement promu à Bienne. Image : Envato</title>
        <format>jpg</format>
        <size-kb>308</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/74814.jpg</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="241007">
        <title>L'Alliance AM-TTC a été créée à l'initiative de l'Empa et est chargée par le Secrétariat d'Etat à la formation, à la recherche et à l'innovation d'évaluer les demandes et d'accompagner le développement des centres AM-TTC. Image : Envato</title>
        <format>jpg</format>
        <size-kb>121</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/74815.jpg</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="241008">
        <title>L'objectif de l'initiative AM-TTC est de créer un réseau de plusieurs centres avec des priorités thématiques différentes. Image : Envato</title>
        <format>jpg</format>
        <size-kb>280</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/74816.jpg</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <link id="241001">
        <title>Empa Homepage</title>
        <uri>https://www.empa.ch/web/s604/am-ttc-alliance-2023</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="241002">
        <title>Mehr Information / De plus amples informations /Further information about the AM-TTC initiative</title>
        <uri>https://www.am-ttc.ch/</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Dübendorf, St. Gallen und Thun</city>
      <title>Funding approved: Two more technology transfer centers for Switzerland</title>
      <lead>The Federal Department of Economic Affairs, Education and Research (EAER) and the AM-TTC Alliance, the umbrella organization of technology transfer centers in the field of Advanced Manufacturing (AM) technologies, decided in November to fund two more centers in the fields of collaborative robotics and photonics with 6.5 million Swiss francs until the end of 2024.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Swiss universities and research institutions are world leaders in many fields. Switzerland is also among the leading nations in terms of research results and the resulting patents. However, new manufacturing technologies often do not find their way from the research laboratories into industrial applications. Their path ends in the "valley of death" for innovations.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;This is where the initiative to establish a network of Swiss technology transfer centers, the Advanced Manufacturing Technology Transfer Centers (AM-TTC), comes in. The initiative is part of the federal government's action plan for digitization and aims to maintain Switzerland as a modern and high-quality production location in the long term. The AM-TTC initiative aims to establish and make accessible infrastructures that will enable Swiss industry – especially local SMEs – to learn about, try out and transfer new manufacturing technologies into their production.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The individual centers are founded and financed in a public-private partnership between the public sector and industry. The partners and consortia of the centers are made up of Swiss research institutions and industrial companies. Thus, these centers are also places where partners from science and industry can jointly develop new manufacturing technologies and make them suitable for industrial use.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;First centers established in 2019&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Two centers have already been established in 2019: the ANAXAM center, which makes it easier for industrial companies to use the beamlines of the Paul Scherrer Institute (PSI) to study their materials and products; and the Swiss m4m Center, which gives MedTech companies access to an ISO 13485-certified pilot production line for 3D-printed medical implants. In the start-up phase until the end of 2020, these two centers were supported with funding from the ETH Board; since the beginning of 2021, they have been supported with funding from the federal government as research institutions of national importance (in accordance with Art. 15 of the Law on the Promotion of Research and Innovation (FIFG)).&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Funding for two more technology transfer centers&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;At the end of November this year, following a comprehensive selection process, the Federal Department of Economic Affairs, Education and Research (EAER) and the AM-TTC Alliance, the umbrella organization of the AM-TTC initiative, have decided to fund two additional centers in the fields of collaborative robotics and photonics until the end of 2024 with funds totaling 6.5 million Swiss francs. On the one hand, the funding comes from the ETH Board, which has defined the development of AM-TTC in Switzerland as a measure of its strategic planning 2021-2024. On the other hand, the centers also receive funding from the federal government according to Art. 15 FIFG.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The Swiss Cobotics Competence Center (S3C) in Biel aims to demonstrate the opportunities of collaboration between humans and robots. Its goal is to close the gap between the theoretical capabilities of robots and industrial reality and thus to bring more collaborative robots into industrial applications. With the S3C, Swiss companies gain access to know-how and a demonstration and test platform for innovative cobotic solutions. In addition to the Swiss Innovation Park Biel/Bienne and the Swiss Smart Factory, the Bern University of Applied Sciences is also one of the founding members of the S3C. And since the S3C was founded in November 2022, many more partners from industry and science have joined as members.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The second newly founded AM-TTC, the Swiss Photonics Integration Center (Swiss PIC), is located in the Swiss Innovation Park InnovAare. The focus of this center is on optical components and systems that transport and process light particles, so-called photons. The Swiss PITC will build facilities that will make it possible to integrate even the smallest optical components into larger systems or devices and test them. In Switzerland, there are many companies and research groups that develop and manufacture new innovative photonic components. Often they do not have access to such facilities. The Swiss PITC aims to close this gap by making such facilities accessible and helping companies to build their own integration and packaging solutions in their production.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Info box: AM-TTC Alliance&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;On 4 February 2019, 22 Swiss research institutions and industrial companies founded the AM-TTC Alliance, the umbrella organization of these technology transfer centers, at Empa in Dübendorf. Members include institutions of the ETH Domain, universities of applied sciences and other research institutions, industrial companies such as ABB, BASF, Bühler, Hilti, Oerlikon, Rolex and Siemens, as well as the industrial association Swissmem. The current managing director is Empa researcher Lars Sommerhäuser.&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Dr. Lars Sommerhäuser Empa, Surface Science &amp; Coating Technologies / Managing Director «AM-TTC Alliance» Phone +41 58 765 47 87 lars.sommerhaeuser@am-ttc.ch</contact>
      <attachment id="241009">
        <title>Collaborative robotics for industrial applications - this is the focus of the newly funded "Swiss Cobotics Competence Center" (S3C) in Biel. Image: Envato</title>
        <format>jpg</format>
        <size-kb>308</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/74817.jpg</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="241010">
        <title>The AM-TTC Alliance was founded on the initiative of the Empa and has a mandate from the State Secretariat for Education, Research and Innovation to evaluate applications and monitor the development of AM-TTC centers. Image: Envato</title>
        <format>jpg</format>
        <size-kb>121</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/74818.jpg</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="241011">
        <title>The aim of the AM-TTC-initiative is to create a network of several centers with different thematic fo-cuses. Image: Envato</title>
        <format>jpg</format>
        <size-kb>280</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/74819.jpg</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <link id="241001">
        <title>Empa Homepage</title>
        <uri>https://www.empa.ch/web/s604/am-ttc-alliance-2023</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="241002">
        <title>Mehr Information / De plus amples informations /Further information about the AM-TTC initiative</title>
        <uri>https://www.am-ttc.ch/</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="8">
        <name lang="de">Bildung und Forschung</name>
        <name lang="fr">Formation et recherche</name>
        <name lang="it">Formazione e ricerca</name>
        <name lang="en">Education and Research</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="45">
        <name lang="de">Technologie</name>
        <name lang="fr">Technologie</name>
        <name lang="it">Tecnologia</name>
        <name lang="en">Technology</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
