<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="92650" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2023-01-26</pubdate>
    <blocking-period>2023-01-26</blocking-period>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="318" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>301</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Bundesamt für Statistik</name>
      <name lang="fr">Office fédéral de la statistique</name>
      <name lang="it">Ufficio federale di statistica</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Statistical Office</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.statistik.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.statistique.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.statistica.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.statistics.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@bfs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@bfs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@bfs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@bfs.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="301">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement des Innern</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'intérieur</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'interno</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Home Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Neuchâtel</city>
      <title>Das internationale Genf ist aufgerufen, sich für eine faktenbasierte Entscheidfindung zu engagieren</title>
      <lead>Für politische, wirtschaftliche oder persönliche Entscheidungen braucht es Fakten. Anlässlich der Lancierung des Project Rosling in Genf erinnerte Bundespräsident Alain Berset daran, wie wichtig verlässliche Statistiken und Daten für den demokratischen Prozess sind. Dem internationalen Genf kommt dabei eine Schlüsselrolle zu. Indem es Partnerschaften zwischen den internationalen Organisationen stärkt und die Synergien im Bereich der Daten und Statistiken bestmöglich nutzt, kann es sich als Drehscheibe für Daten etablieren und so eine nachhaltigere und gezieltere Politik vorantreiben.</lead>
      <text link="no">Diese Medienmitteilung und weitere Informationen zum Thema finden Sie auf der Website des BFS (siehe Link unten).</text>
      <contact>Project Rosling, BFS, Internationale und nationale Angelegenheiten, E-Mail: projectrosling@bfs.admin.ch Benjamin Rothen, Botschafter, Sektionschef Internationale und nationale Angelegenheiten, Tel.: +41 79 745 34 79</contact>
      <link id="241514">
        <title>Kompletter Text und Mediendossier</title>
        <uri>https://www.bfs.admin.ch/news/de/2023-0623</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Neuchâtel</city>
      <title>La Genève internationale appelée à se mobiliser pour une prise de décisions basées sur des faits</title>
      <lead>Les décisions politiques, économiques ou de particuliers doivent pouvoir se baser sur des faits établis. A l’occasion du lancement du Project Rosling à Genève, le président de la Confédération Alain Berset a souligné l’importance de statistiques et de données fiables dans le processus démocratique. En renforçant les partenariats entre les nombreuses organisations internationales et en exploitant au maximum les synergies en matière de données et de statistiques, la Genève internationale a un rôle clé à jouer pour se positionner comme un centre de données reconnu et permettre ainsi des politiques plus durables et ciblées.</lead>
      <text link="no">Vous trouverez ce communiqué de presse et d'autres informations sur ce thème sur le site web de l'OFS (cf. lien ci-dessous).</text>
      <contact>Project Rosling, OFS, section Affaires internationales et nationales, e-mail: projectrosling@bfs.admin.ch Benjamin Rothen, Ambassadeur, Chef de la section Affaires internationales et nationales, tél.: +41 79 745 34 79</contact>
      <link id="241515">
        <title>Texte intégral et dossier de presse</title>
        <uri>https://www.bfs.admin.ch/news/fr/2023-0623</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Neuchâtel</city>
      <title>La Ginevra internazionale è chiamata a mobilitarsi per definire un processo decisionale basato sui fatti</title>
      <lead>Le decisioni politiche, economiche o private devono potersi basare su fatti concreti. In occasione del lancio del Project Rosling a Ginevra, il presidente della Confederazione Alain Berset ha sottolineato l’importanza di statistiche e dati attendibili per la democrazia. Rafforzando i partenariati tra le numerose organizzazioni internazionali e sfruttando al massimo le sinergie in materia di dati e statistiche, la Ginevra internazionale ha da svolgere un ruolo di primo piano per posizionarsi come centro di dati riconosciuto e permettere così di portare avanti politiche più sostenibili e mirate.</lead>
      <text link="no">Il presente comunicato stampa e ulteriori informazioni sul tema sono reperibili sulla pagina Internet dell'UST (link sotto). </text>
      <contact>Project Rosling, UST, sezione Affari internazionali e nazionali, e-mail: projectrosling@bfs.admin.ch Benjamin Rothen, ambasciatore, capo della sezione Affari internazionali e nazionali, tel.: +41 79 745 34 79</contact>
      <link id="241516">
        <title>Testo integrale e dossier per i media</title>
        <uri>https://www.bfs.admin.ch/news/it/2023-0623</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Neuchâtel</city>
      <title>International Geneva called upon to mobilise itself for evidence-based decision making</title>
      <lead>Political, economic and private decisions must be based on established facts. On the occasion of the launch of Project Rosling in Geneva, the President of the Swiss Confederation, Alain Berset, stressed the importance of reliable statistics and data in the democratic process. By strengthening partnerships between the numerous international organisations and making the most of synergies in data and statistics, International Geneva has a key role to play in positioning itself as a recognised data centre and thus allowing for more sustainable and targeted policies. </lead>
      <text link="no">This press release and further information on the topic can be found on the FSO website (see link below). </text>
      <contact>Project Rosling, FSO, International and National Affairs, e-mail: projectrosling@bfs.admin.ch Benjamin Rothen, Ambassador, Head of International and National Affairs Unit, tel.: +41 79 745 34 79</contact>
      <link id="241517">
        <title>Complete text and press kit</title>
        <uri>https://www.bfs.admin.ch/news/en/2023-0623</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="43">
        <name lang="de">Statistik</name>
        <name lang="fr">Statistiques</name>
        <name lang="it">Statistica</name>
        <name lang="en">Statistics</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
