<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="92581" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2023-01-19</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="301" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>301</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement des Innern</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'intérieur</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'interno</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Home Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="301">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement des Innern</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'intérieur</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'interno</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Home Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Sicherheitslage in Europa und Arbeit des UNO-Sicherheitsrates bei Gesprächen des Bundespräsidenten in Davos im Zentrum</title>
      <lead>Die Sicherheitslage in Europa und das Engagement der Schweiz im UNO-Sicherheitsrat: Diese beiden Themen haben die Agenda von Bundespräsident Alain Berset in Davos wesentlich bestimmt. Er kam am Rande des WEF-Jahrestreffens 2023 mit mehr als einem Dutzend Staats- und Regierungschefs zu längeren bilateralen Gesprächen zusammen. </lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Aus Europa traf der Bundespräsident insbesondere Staats- und Regierungschefinnen und -chefs, deren Länder an Russland oder die Ukraine angrenzen. Es handelt sich um die finnische Premierministerin Sanna Marin, den polnischen Präsidenten Andrzej Duda, die Staatsoberhäupter von Litauen und Lettland, Gitanas Nauseda und Egils Levits, sowie die Präsidentin von Moldova, Maia Sandu, und den georgischen Premier Irakli Gharibashvili. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Wie in seiner Eröffnungsrede am Dienstag,17. Januar 2023, betonte der Bundespräsident in diesen Gesprächen die Solidarität der Schweiz mit der vom Krieg betroffenen Bevölkerung. Er brachte dies auch persönlich in einem Gespräch mit der First Lady der Ukraine, Olena Zelenska, zum Ausdruck. Zudem unterstrich er, dass die russische Aggression nicht nur grosses Leid verursache, sondern auch eine brutale Attacke auf das Völkerrecht sei. In seiner Rede sagte Bundespräsident, dass die zunehmende Fragilität der internationalen Normen alle Staaten bedroht: «Eigeninteresse und Engagement für Schwächere: Lange haben wir das für zwei unterschiedliche Dinge gehalten. Jetzt wissen wir: Es ist dasselbe.»&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Engagement für den Multilateralismus &lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Bei einem Treffen mit UNO-Generalsekretär António Guterres diskutierten der Bundespräsident und die Vizepräsidentin des Bundesrates Viola Amherd unter anderem über die Zukunft des Multilateralismus. Zur Sprache kamen zudem die Verteidigung des Völkerrechts und der Genfer Konventionen sowie die Rolle der Schweiz im UNO-Sicherheitsrat in den Jahren 2023/2024. Ein weiteres zentrales Thema war die globale Herausforderung durch die Klimakrise. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Da Ecuador zeitgleich mit der Schweiz dem UNO-Gremium angehört, war die Ratsarbeit auch ein wichtiges Thema beim Treffen mit Präsident Guillermo Lasso. Mit seinem Amtskollegen aus Ecuador nahm der Bundespräsident zudem an einem Anlass teil, an dem die Zusammenarbeit beim Kampf gegen Plastikmüll im Zentrum stand. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Zusätzlich zu bilateralen Themen wie der wirtschaftlichen Zusammenarbeit bildeten die globale Suche nach Frieden und einer nachhaltigen Entwicklung Schwerpunkte auch bei Treffen mit den Präsidenten Kolumbiens, Gustavo Petro, Costa Ricas, Rodrigo Chaves Robles, und der Demokratischen Republik Kongo, Félix Tshisekedi, sowie der tansanischen Präsidentin Samia Suluhu Hassan. Die tunesische Premierministerin Najla Bouden traf Bundespräsident Berset ebenfalls zu einem bilateralen Gespräch. Ausserdem nahm er gemeinsam mit ihr an einer Diskussionsrunde teil, die unter dem Titel «Realizing Africa’s Century» den Zukunftschancen des afrikanischen Kontinents gewidmet war. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Europapolitik als weiteres Thema &lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Neben der Sicherheitslage in Europa und bilateralen Themen stand in den Gesprächen mit Repräsentanten von EU-Mitgliedsländern wie dem deutschen Bundeskanzler Olaf Scholz und den Premierministern Belgiens, der Niederlande und Luxemburgs, Alexander De Croo, Mark Rutte und Xavier Bettel, auch die Schweizer Europapolitik auf der Agenda. Am Rande der Eröffnung des Jahrestreffens war Bundespräsident Berset auch mit EU-Kommissionspräsidentin Ursula von der Leyen zusammengekommen. Er betonte in den Gesprächen die identischen Werte der Schweiz und der EU und das gemeinsame Engagement in einer Vielzahl von Fragen, die den gesamten Kontinent betreffen. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Thema war auch die ausstehende Assoziierung der Schweiz an den europäischen Programmen Horizon Europe und Erasmus+. Mit dem Ziel, die guten, stabilen und für beide Seiten vorteilhaften Beziehungen zu konsolidieren und auszubauen, hat der Bundesrat vor Jahresfrist einen breiten Paketansatz vorgeschlagen. Dieser konkrete Vorschlag zeige das klare Engagement der Schweiz für eine Weiterführung der guten Beziehungen mit der EU, erklärte der Bundespräsident bei den Gesprächen in Davos. &lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Gianna Blum, Co-Leiterin Kommunikation EDI +41 (0)58 465 09 51, gianna.blum@gs-edi.admin.ch Christian Favre, Co-Leiter Kommunikation EDI +41 (0)79 897 61 91, christian.favre@gs-edi.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>La sécurité en Europe et le travail du Conseil de sécurité des Nations Unies au cœur des entretiens du président de la Confédération à Davos</title>
      <lead>Les deux sujets qui ont dominé l’agenda du président de la Confédération à Davos ont été la sécurité en Europe et l’engagement de la Suisse au Conseil de sécurité des Nations Unies. En marge de la rencontre annuelle du Forum économique mondial (WEF), Alain Berset a mené des entretiens bilatéraux prolongés avec près d’une quinzaine de chefs d’État et de gouvernement.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Le président de la Confédération a en particulier rencontré les chefs d’État et de gouvernement de pays européens limitrophes de la Russie ou de l’Ukraine, notamment la première ministre finnoise, Sanna Marin, le président polonais, Andrzej Duda, le président lituanien, Gitanas Nauseda, et le président letton, Egils Levits, la présidente moldave, Maia Sandu, et le premier ministre géorgien, Irakli Gharibashvili. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Dans ces entretiens, il a réaffirmé la solidarité de la Suisse avec les populations touchées par la guerre, comme il l’avait déjà fait lors de son discours d’ouverture mardi 17 janvier 2023. Il l’a également exprimée personnellement lors d’un entretien avec la première dame d’Ukraine, Olena Zelenska. Il a en outre souligné que l’agression russe non seulement causait de grandes souffrances, mais qu’elle constituait également une grave attaque contre le droit international. Dans son discours, Alain Berset a déclaré que la fragilisation des normes internationales menaçait tous les États : « Longtemps, nous avons considéré que la défense de nos intérêts, d’une part, et la protection des plus vulnérables, de l’autre, étaient deux choses bien distinctes. Aujourd’hui, nous savons que l’une ne va pas sans l’autre. »&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Engagement pour le multilatéralisme &lt;/b&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;À l’occasion d’une rencontre avec le secrétaire général de l’ONU, António Guterres, le président de la Confédération et la vice-présidente du Conseil fédéral, Viola Amherd, ont notamment discuté de l’avenir du multilatéralisme. Ils ont aussi abordé la question de la défense du droit international et des Conventions de Genève ainsi que le rôle de la Suisse au sein du Conseil de sécurité de l’ONU en 2023/2024. Les discussions ont aussi largement porté sur le défi mondial que représente la crise climatique.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Comme l’Équateur fait partie du plus haut organe de l’ONU en même temps que la Suisse, le travail qui y est effectué a été un sujet important lors de la rencontre avec le président Guillermo Lasso. Avec son homologue équatorien, le président de la Confédération a participé à un événement consacré à la coopération dans la lutte contre les déchets plastiques. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Les rencontres avec les présidents de la Colombie, Gustavo Petro, du Costa Rica, Rodrigo Chaves Robles, et de la République démocratique du Congo, Félix Tshisekedi, ainsi qu’avec la présidente tanzanienne, Samia Suluhu Hassan, ont porté sur des questions bilatérales, comme la coopération économique, mais aussi sur la paix dans le monde et le développement durable. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Alain Berset a également rencontré la première ministre tunisienne, Najla Bouden, pour un entretien bilatéral. Avec cette dernière, il a aussi participé à une table ronde sur les perspectives d’avenir du continent africain intitulée « Realizing Africa’s Century ». &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;La question de la politique européenne &lt;/b&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Dans des entretiens avec des représentants de pays de l’UE comme le chancelier allemand, Olaf Scholz, le premier ministre belge, Alexander De Croo, le premier ministre néerlandais, Mark Rutte et le premier ministre luxembourgeois, Xavier Bettel, il a été question de la sécurité en Europe et de sujets bilatéraux, mais aussi de la politique européenne de la Suisse. En marge de l’ouverture du WEF, le président de la Confédération s’était déjà entretenu avec la présidente de la Commission européenne, Ursula von der Leyen. Il a insisté sur le fait que la Suisse et l’Europe partageaient des valeurs identiques et un engagement commun dans de nombreuses questions concernant l’ensemble du continent.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Il a également été question de l’association en suspens de la Suisse aux programmes européens Horizon Europe et Erasmus+. Dans le but de préserver les relations entre la Suisse et l’UE, qui sont bonnes, stables et avantageuses pour les deux parties, le Conseil fédéral avait proposé l’année dernière de préparer une approche par paquet. Cette proposition concrète montre l’engagement clair de la Suisse en faveur de la poursuite des bonnes relations avec l’UE, a expliqué Alain Berset lors des entretiens à Davos. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Gianna Blum, co-responsable de la communication DFI +41 (0)58 465 09 51, gianna.blum@gs-edi.admin.ch Christian Favre, co-responsable de la communication DFI +41 (0)79 897 61 91, christian.favre@gs-edi.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>La situazione della sicurezza in Europa e il lavoro del Consiglio di sicurezza dell’ONU al centro dei colloqui tenuti a Davos dal presidente della Confederazione</title>
      <lead>La situazione della sicurezza in Europa e l’impegno della Svizzera nel Consiglio di sicurezza dell’ONU sono stati i due temi prioritari sull’agenda del presidente della Confederazione Alain Berset a Davos. A margine dell’incontro annuale del WEF 2023, ha avuto modo di condurre approfonditi colloqui bilaterali con oltre una dozzina di capi di Stato e di Governo.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Per quanto riguarda l’Europa, il presidente della Confederazione ha incontrato in particolare capi di Stato e di Governo di Paesi che confinano con la Russia o l’Ucraina: la prima ministra finlandese Sanna Marin, il presidente polacco Andrzej Duda, i capi di Stato di Lituania e Lettonia, Gitanas Nauseda e Egils Levits, nonché la presidente della Moldova Maia Sandu e il primo ministro georgiano Irakli Gharibashvili. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Come aveva già fatto nel suo discorso d’apertura di martedì 17 gennaio 2023, durante questi colloqui il presidente della Confederazione ha riaffermato la solidarietà della Svizzera con le popolazioni colpite dalla guerra, espressa anche personalmente durante un colloquio con la First Lady ucraina, Olena Zelenska. Ha inoltre sottolineato che l’aggressione russa non è soltanto causa di grandi sofferenze, ma anche un brutale attacco al diritto internazionale pubblico. Nel suo discorso il presidente della Confederazione ha affermato che la fragilità crescente delle norme internazionali minaccia tutti gli Stati: «Per lungo tempo abbiamo ritenuto che la difesa dei nostri interessi e l’impegno per i più vulnerabili fossero due cose distinte. Oggi sappiamo che l’una non va senza l’altro».&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Impegno per il multilateralismo &lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Durante un incontro con il segretario generale dell’ONU António Guterres, il presidente della Confederazione e la vicepresidente del Consiglio federale Viola Amherd hanno discusso, fra l’altro, del futuro del multilateralismo. Si è parlato inoltre di difesa del diritto internazionale e delle Convenzioni di Ginevra, nonché del ruolo che la Svizzera sosterrà negli anni 2023/2024 in seno al Consiglio di sicurezza dell'ONU. Un altro tema cruciale è stato quello riguardante le sfide globali poste dalla crisi climatica.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Dato che l'Ecuador fa parte assieme alla Svizzera dell’organo dell’ONU, il lavoro svolto dal Consiglio è stato uno dei principali temi discussi durante l'incontro con il presidente Guillermo Lasso. Con il suo omologo ecuadoregno, il presidente della Confederazione ha anche partecipato a un evento incentrato sulla cooperazione nella lotta ai rifiuti plastici. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Oltre a temi di carattere bilaterale come la cooperazione economica, il perseguimento globale della pace e di uno sviluppo sostenibile sono stati i punti focali anche degli incontri avuti con i presidenti della Colombia, Gustavo Petro, del Costa Rica, Rodrigo Chaves Robles, e della Repubblica democratica del Congo, Félix Tshisekedi, oltre che con la presidente della Tanzania Samia Suluhu Hassan. Anche la prima ministra tunisina Najla Bouden ha incontrato il presidente della Confederazione per un colloquio bilaterale. Insieme a lei Alain Berset ha inoltre partecipato a una tavola rotonda intitolata «Realizing Africa’s Century», dedicata alle prospettive future del continente africano. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Un ulteriore tema: la politica europea &lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Oltre che sulla situazione della sicurezza in Europa e su questioni bilaterali, i colloqui tenuti con i rappresentati di alcuni Stati membri dell’UE come il cancelliere federale tedesco Olaf Scholz e i primi ministri del Belgio, dei Paesi Bassi e del Lussemburgo, Alexander De Croo, Mark Rutte e Xavier Bettel, si sono concentrati sulla politica europea della Svizzera. A margine dell’inaugurazione dell’incontro annuale, il presidente della Confederazione aveva incontrato anche la presidente della Commissione europea Ursula von der Leyen. Nel corso dei colloqui, Alain Berset ha sottolineato gli identici valori condivisi da Svizzera e UE e l’impegno comune profuso su un gran numero di questioni che riguardano l’intero continente. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Un altro tema trattato è stato quello dell’associazione della Svizzera ai programmi europei Horizon Europe ed Erasmus+, al momento sospesa. Nell’intento di consolidare e sviluppare le buone, stabili e reciprocamente vantaggiose relazioni tra la Svizzera e l'UE, un anno fa il Consiglio federale ha proposto un approccio “a pacchetto”. Questa concreta proposta dimostra, come spiegato dal presidente della Confederazione nel corso dei colloqui a Davos, il chiaro impegno della Svizzera a mantenere buone relazioni con l’UE. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Gianna Blum, co-responsabile della comunicazione del DFI +41 (0)58 465 09 51, gianna.blum@gs-edi.admin.ch Christian Favre, co-responsabile della comunicazione del DFI +41 (0)79 897 61 91, christian.favre@gs-edi.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Talks conducted by the President of the Swiss Confederation in Davos focused on security situation in Europe and the work of the UN Security Council</title>
      <lead>The security situation in Europe and Switzerland's commitment to the UN Security Council: these were the two topics that largely dominated President Alain Berset’s agenda in Davos. Mr Berset held lengthy bilateral talks with more than a dozen heads of state and government on the sidelines of the WEF Annual Meeting.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;From Europe, President Berset met with heads of state and government whose countries border Russia or Ukraine. These included Finnish Prime Minister Sanna Marin, Polish President Andrzej Duda, the heads of state of Lithuania and Latvia, Gitanas Nauseda and Egils Levits, as well as the president of Moldova, Maia Sandu, and Georgian Prime Minister Irakli Gharibashvili.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;During these talks, Mr Berset emphasised Switzerland's solidarity with the population affected by the war, as he did in his opening speech on Tuesday,17 January. He also expressed these sentiments personally in a conversation with the First Lady of Ukraine, Olena Zelenska. In addition, he emphasised that Russia’s aggression was not only causing great suffering, but was also a brutal attack on international law. In his speech, President Berset said that the increasing fragility of international norms threatens all states: “Self-interest and supporting those weaker than ourselves. We have long considered these to be two different things. Now we know that they are one and the same.”&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Advocating multilateralism&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;At a meeting with UN Secretary-General António Guterres, President Berset and Vice President of the Federal Council Viola Amherd discussed the future of multilateralism. They also discussed the defence of international law and the Geneva Conventions, as well as Switzerland's role in the UN Security Council in 2023/2024. Another central topic was the global challenge posed by the climate crisis. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;As Ecuador is a member of the Security Council during the same period as Switzerland, the Council's work was also an important topic at the meeting with President Guillermo Lasso. Together with his Ecuadorian counterpart, President Berset also took part in an event focusing on cooperation in the fight against plastic waste.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;In addition to bilateral issues such as economic cooperation, the global search for peace and sustainable development were also focal points in meetings with the presidents of Colombia, Gustavo Petro, Costa Rica, Rodrigo Chaves Robles, and the Democratic Republic of Congo, Félix Tshisekedi, as well as Tanzanian President Samia Suluhu Hassan. President Berset also held bilateral talks with Tunisian Prime Minister Najla Bouden and took part in a panel discussion with her entitled ‘Realising Africa's Century’, which was devoted to the future opportunities of the African continent.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;European policy also on the agenda &lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;In addition to the security situation in Europe and bilateral issues, Switzerland’s policy on Europe was also on the agenda in talks with representatives of EU member states such as German Chancellor Olaf Scholz, and the prime ministers of Belgium, the Netherlands and Luxembourg, Alexander De Croo, Mark Rutte and Xavier Bettel. On the fringes of the opening of the Annual Meeting, Mr Berset also met with European Commission President Ursula von der Leyen. During the talks, he emphasised the values shared by Switzerland and the EU and the common commitment to a wide range of issues that affect the continent as a whole.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;A further topic was the matter of Switzerland's association to the EU’s Horizon Europe and Erasmus+ programmes. With the aim of consolidating and expanding the good, stable and mutually beneficial relations between Switzerland and the EU, the Federal Council last year proposed drawing up a broad package-based approach. This concrete proposal demonstrates Switzerland's clear commitment to continuing the good relations with the EU, said President Berset at the talks in Davos.&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Gianna Blum, Co-head FDHA Communications +41 (0)58 465 09 51, gianna.blum@gs-edi.admin.ch Christian Favre, Co-head FDHA Communications +41 (0)79 897 61 91, christian.favre@gs-edi.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="10">
        <name lang="de">Bundesrat</name>
        <name lang="fr">Conseil fédéral</name>
        <name lang="it">Consiglio federale</name>
        <name lang="en">Federal Council</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="15">
        <name lang="de">Gesundheit</name>
        <name lang="fr">Santé</name>
        <name lang="it">sanità</name>
        <name lang="en">Health</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="20">
        <name lang="de">Migration</name>
        <name lang="fr">Migrations</name>
        <name lang="it">Migrazione</name>
        <name lang="en">Migration</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="33">
        <name lang="de">Bundespräsident/-in</name>
        <name lang="fr">Président/e de la Confédération</name>
        <name lang="it">Presidente della Confederazione</name>
        <name lang="en">President of the Swiss Confederation</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="40">
        <name lang="de">Sicherheit</name>
        <name lang="fr">Sécurité</name>
        <name lang="it">Sicurezza</name>
        <name lang="en">Security</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="47">
        <name lang="de">Wirtschaft</name>
        <name lang="fr">Économie</name>
        <name lang="it">Economia</name>
        <name lang="en">Economic Affairs</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="48">
        <name lang="de">Zoll</name>
        <name lang="fr">Douanes</name>
        <name lang="it">Dogane</name>
        <name lang="en">Customs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
