<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="92536" revoked="no">
    <version>3</version>
    <pubdate>2023-01-13</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="201" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>201</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="201">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Bundesrat Ignazio Cassis trifft US-Aussenminister Antony Blinken</title>
      <lead>Bundesrat Ignazio Cassis reiste am 13. Januar 2023 nach Washington D. C., wo er seinen US-amerikanischen Amtskollegen Antony Blinken traf. Wichtigste Gesprächsthemen waren die Zusammenarbeit im UNO-Sicherheitsrat und die bilateralen Beziehungen zwischen der Schweiz und den USA.</lead>
      <text link="no">Nachdem er am 12. Januar 2023 im UNO-Sicherheitsrat in New York an einer Debatte über Rechtsstaatlichkeit teilgenommen hatte, reiste der Chef der Schweizer Diplomatie weiter nach Washington D. C. Dort sprach er mit Aussenminister Antony Blinken über die Prioritäten der Schweiz im Sicherheitsrat. Ein besonderer Schwerpunkt lag dabei auf der Verbesserung der Rechtsstaatlichkeit im Sanktionsbereich. «Ich bin zuversichtlich, dass wir bei diesem Thema, auf das die Schweiz im UNO-Sicherheitsrat besonderes Gewicht legt, in Zusammenarbeit mit den USA rascher Fortschritte erzielen können», sagte Bundesrat Ignazio Cassis. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Des Weiteren sprachen Bundesrat Cassis und Aussenminister Blinken über die florierenden bilateralen Beziehungen. Der Bundesrat will die Zusammenarbeit mit den USA auf aussenpolitischer Ebene im Einklang mit seiner Amerikas-Strategie 2022–2025 ausbauen. Als zweitwichtigster Handelspartner nach der Europäischen Union sind die USA für die Schweiz von zentraler Bedeutung. Weitere Gesprächsthemen waren Fragen in den Bereichen Bildung, Forschung und neue Technologien. Die Swissnex-Standorte in Boston, New York und San Francisco sowie mehrere Abkommen auf dem Gebiet der Wissenschaft und der Wirtschaft, darunter das vor Kurzem abgeschlossene Memorandum of Understanding über Quantenforschung, zeugen von der engen wissenschaftlichen Zusammenarbeit zwischen der Schweiz und den USA. </text>
      <contact>Nicolas Bideau, Chef Kommunikation EDA, +41 79 667 69 15 Tel. Kommunikationsservice: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Medienstelle: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <link id="241238">
        <title>Bilaterale Beziehungen Schweiz–Vereinigte Staaten von Amerika</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home/vertretungen-und-reisehinweise/vereinigte-staaten/bilatereale-beziehungenschweizvereinigtestaaten.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="241242">
        <title>Newsticker zur Mitgliedschaft der Schweiz im UNO-Sicherheitsrat</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home/das-eda/aktuell/newsuebersicht/2023/uno-sicherheitsrat.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions>
        <revision date="2023-01-17 11:47" type="R"/>
      </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Le Conseiller fédéral Ignazio Cassis rencontre le Secrétaire d’Etat américain aux affaires étrangères Antony Blinken</title>
      <lead>Le Conseiller fédéral Ignazio Cassis s’est rendu le 13 janvier 2023 à Washington, D.C., et y a rencontré son homologue américain Antony Blinken. La coopération au sein du Conseil de sécurité de l'ONU et les relations bilatérales entre les deux pays ont été au centre de l'entretien.</lead>
      <text link="no">Après avoir participé au débat sur l’état de droit au Conseil de sécurité des Nations Unies à New-York le 12.01, le chef de la diplomatie suisse a poursuivi son séjour aux États-Unis. A Washington, D.C., il a échangé avec Antony Blinken, chef du département d’État américain, sur les dossiers prioritaires pour la Suisse au Conseil de Sécurité. Un accent particulier a été mis sur l’amélioration de l’état de droit en lien avec les régimes de sanctions. « Je suis confiant qu’une collaboration avec les Etats-Unis permettra d’avancer plus rapidement sur ce dossier clé pour la Suisse au sein du Conseil de sécurité de l’ONU » a affirmé le conseiller fédéral Ignazio Cassis.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Ensemble, le conseiller fédéral Cassis et Antony Blinken ont évoqué également les relations bilatérales prospères entre les deux pays. Conformément à sa stratégie Amériques 2022 - 2025, le Conseil fédéral veut intensifier la collaboration avec les Etats-Unis au niveau de sa politique étrangère. Deuxième partenaire commercial de la Suisse après l'Union européenne, les Etats-Unis sont un pays de première importance pour notre pays. L’échange a également porté sur les domaines de la formation, la recherche et les nouvelles technologies. Les sites de Swissnex à Boston, New York et San Francisco ainsi que plusieurs accords scientifiques et économiques, dont le récent Memorandum of Understanding sur la recherche quantique, témoignent de l'étroite collaboration scientifique entre les deux pays.</text>
      <contact>Nicolas Bideau, Chef Communication DFAE, +41 79 667 69 15 Tél. Service de communication: +41 58 462 31 53 Tél. Service de presse: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <link id="241239">
        <title>Relations bilatérales Suisse–Etats-Unis d’Amérique</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae/representations-et-conseils-pour-les-voyages/etats-unis/suisse-etats-unis.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="241243">
        <title>Actualités en lien avec le mandat de la Suisse au Conseil de sécurité de l’ONU</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae/dfae/aktuell/news.html/content/eda/fr/meta/news/2023/1/12/92523</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Il consigliere federale Ignazio Cassis incontra il segretario di Stato statunitense Antony Blinken</title>
      <lead>Il 13 gennaio il consigliere federale Ignazio Cassis si è recato a Washington D.C., dove ha incontrato il suo omologo statunitense Antony Blinken per discutere della cooperazione in seno al Consiglio di sicurezza dell’ONU e delle relazioni bilaterali tra i rispettivi Paesi.</lead>
      <text link="no">Dopo aver partecipato, il 12 gennaio scorso, a un dibattito sullo Stato di diritto tenutosi al Consiglio di sicurezza dell’ONU a New York, il capo della diplomazia svizzera ha proseguito il suo soggiorno negli Stati Uniti recandosi a Washington D.C., dove ha incontrato Antony Blinken, capo del Dipartimento di Stato, per discutere dei dossier che la Svizzera considera prioritari durante il suo mandato nel citato organo delle Nazioni Unite. Particolare enfasi è stata data al miglioramento dello Stato di diritto in relazione ai regimi sanzionatori. «Ho fiducia che, collaborando con gli Stati Uniti, riusciremo a compiere più rapidamente progressi su questo dossier cruciale per la Svizzera in seno al Consiglio di sicurezza dell’ONU», ha affermato il consigliere federale Cassis.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Durante il colloquio, il capo del Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri (DFAE) e il suo omologo statunitense hanno anche parlato delle eccellenti relazioni bilaterali tra i loro rispettivi Paesi. Come indicato nella Strategia Americhe 2022–2025 del Consiglio federale, l’Esecutivo intende intensificare la collaborazione con gli Stati Uniti nel settore della politica estera. Gli Stati Uniti, che dopo l’Unione europea rappresentano il secondo partner commerciale della Svizzera per volume di affari, sono di primaria importanza per il nostro Paese. Nell’ambito dell’incontro tra Cassis e Blinken sono stati anche affrontati i temi della formazione, della ricerca e delle nuove tecnologie. La presenza di sedi Swissnex a Boston, New York e San Francisco, così come i vari accordi in ambito scientifico ed economico – tra cui la recente dichiarazione congiunta sulla ricerca quantistica – sono prova dell’intensa collaborazione scientifica tra i due Paesi.</text>
      <contact>Comunicazione DFAE Palazzo federale ovest CH-3003 Berna Tel. Servizio di comunicazione: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Servizio stampa: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <link id="241241">
        <title>Relazioni bilaterali Svizzera–Stati Uniti d’America</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae/rappresentanze-e-consigli-di-viaggio/stati-uniti/ch-usa.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="241244">
        <title>Notizie sul seggio della Svizzera nel Consiglio di sicurezza delle Nazioni Unite</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae/dfae/aktuell/news.html/content/eda/it/meta/news/2023/1/12/92523</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions>
        <revision date="2023-01-17 11:47" type="R"/>
      </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Federal Councillor Ignazio Cassis meets with US Secretary of State Antony Blinken</title>
      <lead>Federal Councillor Ignazio Cassis travelled to Washington, D.C. on 13 January and met with his US counterpart Antony Blinken. The meeting centred on cooperation within the UN Security Council and bilateral relations.</lead>
      <text link="no">After participating in the United Nations Security Council debate on the rule of law in New York on 12 January, the head of Swiss diplomacy continued his visit in the United States. In Washington, he discussed Switzerland's priorities for its term on the Security Council with the head of the US State Department, Antony Blinken. The need to improve rule of law in relation to the sanctions regimes was emphasised in particular. "I am confident that by working with the United States we will be able to make faster progress on this key issue for Switzerland within the UN Security Council," said Cassis.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Cassis and Blinken also discussed their countries' flourishing bilateral relations. In line with its Americas Strategy for 2022–25, the Federal Council is seeking to step up cooperation with the United States in matters of foreign policy. The United States is Switzerland's second most important trading partner after the European Union. The meeting also touched on education, research and new technologies. Swissnex locations in Boston, New York and San Francisco and several scientific and economic agreements, including the recent memorandum of understanding on quantum research, are a reflection of the close scientific ties between the two countries.</text>
      <contact>Nicolas Bideau, Head of Communikation FDFA, +41 79 667 69 15 Tel. Communication service: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Press service: +41 58 460 55 55 E-mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @SwissMFA</contact>
      <link id="241240">
        <title>Bilateral relations Switzerland–United States of America</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/fdfa/representations-and-travel-advice/usa/switzerland-usa.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="241245">
        <title>News platform on Switzerland's membership of the UN Security Council</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/fdfa/fdfa/aktuell/newsuebersicht/2023/uno-sicherheitsrat.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions>
        <revision date="2023-01-17 13:57" type="R"/>
      </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
