<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="2674" revoked="no">
    <version>2</version>
    <pubdate>2006-01-30</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="201" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>201</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="201">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Arbeitsbesuch von Staatssekretär Michael Ambühl in Brüssel</title>
      <lead>Staatssekretär Michael Ambühl wird sich am 2. Februar 2006 zu Gesprächen mit Vertretern der Europäischen Union (EU) in Brüssel aufhalten. Dabei wird er unter anderem mit Eneko Landaburu, dem Generaldirektor der Generaldirektion Aussenbeziehungen (GD RELEX) der EU-Kommission, zusammenkommen.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Dieser Arbeitsbesuch findet im Rahmen der regelmässigen Kontakte zwischen der Schweiz und der EU statt. Themen sind insbesondere die Ratifizierung der neuen bilateralen Abkommen, Bereiche möglicher Verhandlungen zwischen der Schweiz und der EU (Elektrizität, Galileo, etc.) der Bericht des Bundesrates über die verschiedenen europapolitischen Optionen der Schweiz sowie die Prüfung eines Freihandels im Agrarbereich. Zudem sollen auch internationale Themen von gemeinsamem Interesse (Status von Kosovo, Iran, UNO-Reformen) zur Sprache kommen.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Presse- und Informationsdienst Bundeshaus West CH-3003 Bern Tel.: (+41) 031 322 31 53 Fax: (+41) 031 324 90 47 / 48</contact>
      <revisions>
        <revision date="2006-01-30 17:04" type="I"/>
      </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Visite officielle de travail du Secrétaire d’État Michael Ambühl à Bruxelles</title>
      <lead>Le Secrétaire d’État Michael Ambühl sera le 2 février 2006 à Bruxelles pour des entretiens avec des représentants de l’Union européenne (UE). À cette occasion, il rencontrera, entre autres, M. Eneko Landaburu, le Directeur général de la Direction générale des relations extérieures (DG RELEX) de la Commission européenne.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Cette visite de travail s’inscrit dans le cadre des contacts réguliers entre la Suisse et l’UE. Parmi les thèmes abordés figureront notamment la ratification des nouveaux accords bilatéraux, les domaines de négociation possibles entre la Suisse et l’UE (électricité, Galileo, etc.), le rapport du Conseil fédéral sur les options de la politique européenne de la Suisse et l'étude de la faisabilité d'un libre-échange dans la domaine agricole. Des sujets internationaux d’intérêt commun seront également évoqués (statut du Kosovo, Iran, réformes de l’ONU).&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Service de presse et d'information Palais fédéral ouest CH-3003 Berne Tél.: (+41) 031 322 31 53 Fax: (+41) 031 324 90 47 / 48</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Visita di lavoro del Segretario di Stato Michael Ambühl a Bruxelles</title>
      <lead>Il 2 febbraio 2006, il Segretario di Stato Michel Ambühl si recherà a Bruxelles per incontrare rappresentanti dell’Unione Europea (UE). In particolare avrà modo di intrattanersi con Eneko Landaburu, Direttore generale della Direzione per le relazioni estere (GD RELEX) della Commissione europea.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;La visita di lavoro si svolge nell’ambito degli incontri regolari tra la Svizzera e l’UE. Fra i temi in discussione figurano la ratifica dei nuovi accordi bilaterali, ambiti di possibili trattative tra Svizzera e UE (elettricità, Galileo, ecc.), come pure il rapporto del Consiglio federale sulle diverse opzioni di politica europea della Svizzera e lo studio della fattibilità di un libero scambio quanto riguarda l'agricoltura. Saranno inoltre toccati temi a carattere internazionale di comune interesse (statuto del Kosovo, Iran, riforme dell'ONU).&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Servizio stampa e informazione Palazzo federale ovest CH-3003 Berna Tel.: (+41) 031 322 31 53 Fax: (+41) 031 324 90 47 / 48</contact>
      <revisions>
        <revision date="2006-01-30 17:04" type="I"/>
      </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>State Secretary Michael Ambühl to make a working visit to Brussels</title>
      <lead>The State Secretary of Foreign Affairs, Michael Ambühl, will travel to Brussels on 2 February 2006 to hold talks with representatives of the European Union (EU). Among those he will meet will be Eneko Landaburu, General Director for External Relations (GD RELEX) of the European Commission.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;The visit takes place within the framework of the regular contacts between Switzerland and the EU. The issues to be discussed will include in particular the ratification of the nine bilateral agreements, areas for possible future negotiations between Switzerland and the EU, e.g. electricity, Galileo, etc., the report of the Federal Council on the various options for Swiss policy on the Europe Union and an exploration of freetrade in agriculture. In addition, questions of common interest such as the status of Kosovo, Iran, and UN reforms will also be discussed.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Press and Information Service Bundeshaus West CH-3003 Berne Tel.: (+41) 031 322 31 53 Fax: (+41) 031 324 90 47 / 48</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="34">
        <name lang="de">Europa</name>
        <name lang="fr">Europe</name>
        <name lang="it">Europa</name>
        <name lang="en">Europe</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="38">
        <name lang="de">Landwirtschaft</name>
        <name lang="fr">Agriculture</name>
        <name lang="it">Agricoltura</name>
        <name lang="en">Agriculture</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
