<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="49653" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2013-07-11</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="810" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>801</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Bundesamt für Kommunikation</name>
      <name lang="fr">Office fédéral de la communication</name>
      <name lang="it">Ufficio federale delle comunicazioni</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Office of Communications</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.bakom.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.ofcom.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.ufcom.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.ofcom.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">media@bakom.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">media@bakom.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">media@bakom.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">media@bakom.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="801">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Umwelt, Verkehr, Energie und Kommunikation</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'environnement, des transports, de l'énergie et de la communication</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'ambiente, dei trasporti, dell'energia e delle comunicazioni</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of the Environment, Transport, Energy and Communications</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.uvek.admin.ch/uvek/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.uvek.admin.ch/uvek/fr/home.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.uvek.admin.ch/uvek/it/home.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.uvek.admin.ch/uvek/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-uvek.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-uvek.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-uvek.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-uvek.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Biel/Bienne</city>
      <title>Ein Führungsduo für die Abteilung Telecomdienste des BAKOM</title>
      <lead>Die 53-jährige Juristin Annalise Eggimann und der 50-jährige Ökonom René Dönni werden die Abteilung Telecomdienste des Bundesamtes für Kommunikation (BAKOM) gemeinsam leiten. Annalise Eggimann führt heute in dieser Abteilung die Sektion Recht und René Dönni ist Leiter der Sektion Ökonomie und Statistik. Mit dieser Ernennung regelt das Eidgenössische Departement für Umwelt, Verkehr, Energie und Kommunikation (UVEK) die Nachfolge von Philipp Metzger, der das BAKOM Ende März verlassen hat und nun bei der internationalen Fernmeldeunion (ITU) tätig ist. </lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Mit der Ernennung von zwei Personen für die Leitung der Abteilung Telecomdienste hat das UVEK den Vorteil, auf dieser Führungsebene gleichzeitig das Fachwissen einer Juristin und eines Ökonomen nutzen zu können. Annalise Eggimann wird damit zur Vizedirektorin, René Dönni zum Vizedirektor des Bundesamtes für Kommunikation. Mit der Berücksichtigung ihrer gemeinsamen Kandidatur erhalten zwei mit den Abteilungsgeschäften bestens vertraute Persönlichkeiten den Vorzug.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Annalise Eggimann, Fürsprecherin mit einem executive MBA, ist seit 2006 Leiterin der Sektion Recht. Ihren Berufsweg begann sie in der Industrie; danach hat sie zwischen 1991 und 2005 verschiedene Funktionen beim Schweizerischen Nationalfonds (SNF) ausgeübt - so war sie unter anderem als stellvertretende Generalsekretärin verantwortlich für die zentralen Dienste. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;René Dönni ist 1995 ins BAKOM eingetreten und leitet seit 2002 die Sektion Ökonomie und Statistik. Er hat nach seinem Ingenieurstudium Betriebswirtschaft an der Universität Bern studiert und als lic rer pol mit Nebenfach Allgemeine Ökologie abgeschlossen. Seit 2007 ist er stellvertretender Abteilungsleiter Telecomdienste. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Das vom UVEK gewählte Führungsduo Annalise Eggimann und René Dönni wird seine Tätigkeit am 1. August 2013 aufnehmen. Sie folgen auf Philipp Metzger, der das BAKOM verlassen hat, um im April seine neue Tätigkeit als stellvertretender Direktor des Entwicklungsbüros der Internationalen Fernmeldeunion (ITU) aufzunehmen. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Jobsharing&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Annalise Eggimann und René Dönni werden beim BAKOM ein Pensum zu je 90 Prozent ausüben. Ihre Tätigkeit als Abteilungsleitende wird je 60 Prozent umfassen. Das übrige Pensum werden sie strategischen Projekten widmen.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Zum ersten Mal wird im BAKOM eine Abteilungsleitung im Jobsharing geführt. In zwei Sektionen des Amtes wird dieses Führungsmodell bereits umgesetzt.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Bundesamt für Kommunikation BAKOM Medienstelle, +41 58 460 55 50, media@bakom.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Biel/Bienne</city>
      <title>Un duo à la tête de la division Services de télécommunications de l'OFCOM</title>
      <lead>Annalise Eggimann, juriste de 53 ans et René Dönni, économiste de 50 ans, vont se partager le poste de chef de la division Services de télécommunications de l'Office fédéral de la communication (OFCOM). Tous deux travaillent aujourd'hui déjà au sein de cette division: Annalise Eggimann à la tête de la section Droit et René Dönni comme chef de la section Economie et statistiques. Le Département de l'énergie, des transports, de l'environnement et de la communication (DETEC) règle ainsi la succession de Philipp Metzger qui avait quitté l'OFCOM fin mars dernier pour rejoindre l'Union internationale des télécommunications (UIT).</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Le choix du DETEC de nommer deux personnes à la tête de la division Services de télécommunication (TC) de l'OFCOM permet de profiter au niveau de la direction des compétences d'une juriste et d'un économiste. Annalise Eggimann devient ainsi vice-directrice et René Dönni vice-directeur de l'Office fédéral de la communication. En retenant cette candidature commune, le DETEC a donné sa préférence à deux personnalités connaissant parfaitement les activités de la division.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Avocate de formation et titulaire d'une maîtrise en administration des affaires exécutif (executive MBA), Annalise Eggimann a pris la tête de la section Droit de TC en 2006. Après un début de carrière dans l'industrie, elle a occupé entre 1991 et 2005 différentes fonctions au Fonds national suisse (FNS), dont celui de secrétaire générale suppléante, responsable pour les services centraux. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Entré à l'OFCOM en 1995, René Dönni dirige la section Economie et statistiques depuis 2002. Au terme de ses études d'ingénieur, il a étudié l'économie à l'Université de Berne et est diplômé lic rer pol, avec l'écologie générale comme branche secondaire. Depuis 2007, il est chef suppléant de la division Services de télécommunication.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Nommés par le DETEC, Annalise Eggimann et René Dönni prendront leurs fonctions le 1er août 2013. Ils succèderont à Philipp Metzger qui a quitté l'OFCOM pour reprendre en avril le poste de Suppléant du Directeur du Bureau de Développement des Télécommunications de l'UIT. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Partage de poste&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Engagés tous les deux à 90%, Annalise Eggimann et René Dönni travailleront à 60% dans leur fonction de chef de division. Ils consacreront le reste de leur temps à des projets stratégiques. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Pour la première fois dans l'histoire de l'OFCOM, une division sera gérée en partage de poste. Ce mode de gestion existe toutefois déjà à l'office, au sein de deux sections.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Office fédéral de la communication OFCOM Service de presse, +41 58 460 55 50, media@bakom.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Biel/Bienne</city>
      <title>UFCOM: Divisione Servizi di telecomunicazione gestita in tandem</title>
      <lead>Annalise Eggimann, giurista cinquantatreenne, e René Dönni, economista cinquantenne, assumeranno congiuntamente la funzione di capo della Divisione Servizi di telecomunicazione dell'Ufficio federale delle comunicazioni (UFCOM). Entrambi operano già in seno alla Divisione dell'Ufficio: Annalise Eggimann gestisce la Sezione Diritto, mentre René Dönni la Sezione Economia e statistica. Con la loro nomina, il Dipartimento federale dell'ambiente, dei trasporti, dell'energia e delle comunicazioni (DATEC) regola la successione di Philipp Metzger, che ha lasciato l'UFCOM a fine marzo di quest'anno alla volta dell'Unione internazionale delle telecomunicazioni (UIT). </lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;La scelta di nominare due persone a capo della Divisione Servizi di telecomunicazione (TC) offre al DATEC il vantaggio di poter sfruttare, a questo livello di direzione, contemporaneamente le competenze specialistiche di una giurista e un economista. Annalise Eggimann sarà vicedirettrice e René Dönni vicedirettore dell'Ufficio federale delle comunicazioni. Considerando questa candidatura congiunta è data la priorità a due persone di fiducia perfettamente addentro nelle pratiche della Divisione.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Avvocatessa di formazione e titolare di un master in business administration (executive MBA), Annalise Eggimann è a capo della Sezione Diritto dal 2006. Dopo un inizio di carriera nell'industria, tra il 1991 e il 2005 ha rivestito varie funzioni presso il Fondo nazionale svizzero (FNS), tra cui quella di segretaria generale supplente, responsabile per i servizi centrali.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;René Dönni opera in seno all'UFCOM dal 1995 e dirige la Sezione Economia e statistica dal 2002. Conclusa la sua formazione in ingegneria, ha intrapreso degli studi di economia aziendale presso l'Università di Berna conseguendo una licenza rer. pol. con ecologia generale come materia secondaria. Dal 2007 è supplente del capo della Sezione Servizi di telecomunicazione. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Nominati dal DATEC, Annalise Eggimann e René Dönni assumeranno le loro funzioni il 1° agosto 2013. Succedono a Philipp Metzger che ha lasciato l'UFCOM per assumere in aprile la funzione di supplente del direttore dell'Ufficio di sviluppo delle telecomunicazioni presso l'UIT. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Suddivisione del posto&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Entrambi impiegati al 90 per cento, Annalise Eggimann e René Dönni dedicheranno il 60 per cento del loro tempo alla funzione di capodivisione. Il tempo rimanente sarà occupato da progetti strategici.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Per la prima volta nella storia dell'UFCOM, una Divisione sarà gestita in tandem. Questo sistema viene già adottato dall'Ufficio in seno a due Sezioni. &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Ufficio federale delle comunicazioni UFCOM Servizio stampa, +41 58 460 55 50, media@bakom.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Biel/Bienne</city>
      <title>Duo to head OFCOM's Telecom Services Division</title>
      <lead>Annalise Eggimann, a 53 year-old lawyer, and René Dönni, a 50 year-old economist, are to share the position of Head of the Telecom Services Division of the Federal Office of Communications (OFCOM). In this Division, Annalise Eggimann currently heads the Law Section whilst René Dönni is the Head of the Economics and Statistics Section. With this appointment, the Department of the Environment, Transport, Energy and Communications (DETEC) is ensuring the succession of Philipp Metzger, who left OFCOM in late March to return to the International Telecommunication Union (ITU).</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;With the decision to appoint two people to head OFCOM's Telecom Services (TC) Division, DETEC is exploiting the benefit of complementarity between a lawyer and an economist at this management level. Annalise Eggimann and René Dönni will be vice-directors of the office. Their joint candidature has the advantage of two personalities who are intimately acquainted with the business of the Division. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A lawyer by training and holder of an executive MBA master's degree, Annalise Eggimann has been Head of the TC's Law Section since spring 2006. After an early career in industry, between 1991 and 2005 she held various positions in the Swiss National Fund (SNF), including Deputy Secretary General, responsible for central services. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;René Dönni joined OFCOM in 1995 and has been Head of the Economics and Statistics Section since 2002. After graduating as an engineer, he studied business administration at Bern University, gaining a Licentiate in Political Science with General Ecology as a subsidiary subject. Since 2007 he has been Deputy Head of the Telecom Services Division.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Appointed by DETEC, Annalise Eggimann and René Donni will take up their duties on 1st August 2013. They will succeed Philipp Metzger, who left OFCOM to return to the post of Deputy to the Director of the Development Office of the ITU in April. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Job-sharing&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Annalise Eggimann and René Dönni, both employed at 90%, will work 60% in their function as Head of Division. They will devote the rest of their time to strategic projects. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;For the first time in OFCOM's history, a Division will be managed by job-sharing. However, this method of management already exists within the Office, in two Sections.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Federal Office of Communications OFCOM Press service, +41 58 460 55 50, media@bakom.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <offers>
      <offer id="67" org-id="810">
        <name lang="de">Medienmitteilungen Telecom</name>
        <name lang="fr">Communiqués de presse télécommunications</name>
        <name lang="it">Comunicati stampa telecomunicazioni</name>
        <name lang="en">Press releases Telecom</name>
      </offer>
    </offers>
    <keywords>
      <keyword id="890" org-id="810">
        <name lang="de">Personelles</name>
        <name lang="fr">Personelles</name>
        <name lang="it">Personelles</name>
        <name lang="en">Personelles</name>
      </keyword>
    </keywords>
    <topics>
      <topic id="28">
        <name lang="de">Telekommunikation</name>
        <name lang="fr">Télécommunications</name>
        <name lang="it">Telecomunicazione</name>
        <name lang="en">Telecommunications</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="36">
        <name lang="de">Informatik und E-Government</name>
        <name lang="fr">Informatique et cyberadministration</name>
        <name lang="it">Informatica ed e-government</name>
        <name lang="en">IT and E-Government</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
