<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="71168" revoked="no">
    <version>2</version>
    <pubdate>2018-06-18</pubdate>
    <blocking-period>2018-06-18</blocking-period>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="1070" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>1070</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Der Bundesrat</name>
      <name lang="fr">Conseil fédéral</name>
      <name lang="it">Il Consiglio federale</name>
      <name lang="en">The Federal Council</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.admin.ch/gov/de/start.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.admin.ch/gov/fr/accueil.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.admin.ch/gov/it/pagina-iniziale.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.admin.ch/gov/en/start.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="301" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>301</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement des Innern</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'intérieur</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'interno</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Home Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="601" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>601</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Finanzdepartement</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des finances</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale delle finanze</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Finance</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.efd.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.dff.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.efd.admin.ch/efd/it/home.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.efd.admin.ch/efd/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="401" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>401</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Justiz- und Polizeidepartement</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de justice et police</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale di giustizia e polizia</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Justice and Police</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.ejpd.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.ejpd.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.ejpd.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.ejpd.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-ejpd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">Info@gs-ejpd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-ejpd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-ejpd.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="701" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>701</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Wirtschaft, Bildung und Forschung</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'économie, de la formation et de la recherche</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'economia, della formazione e della ricerca</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Economic Affairs, Education and Research</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="201" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>201</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="1070">
      <name lang="de">Der Bundesrat</name>
      <name lang="fr">Conseil fédéral</name>
      <name lang="it">Il Consiglio federale</name>
      <name lang="en">The Federal Council</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.admin.ch/gov/de/start.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.admin.ch/gov/fr/accueil.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.admin.ch/gov/it/pagina-iniziale.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.admin.ch/gov/en/start.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <department id="301">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement des Innern</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'intérieur</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'interno</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Home Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <department id="601">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Finanzdepartement</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des finances</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale delle finanze</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Finance</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.efd.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.dff.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.efd.admin.ch/efd/it/home.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.efd.admin.ch/efd/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <department id="401">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Justiz- und Polizeidepartement</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de justice et police</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale di giustizia e polizia</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Justice and Police</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.ejpd.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.ejpd.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.ejpd.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.ejpd.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-ejpd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">Info@gs-ejpd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-ejpd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-ejpd.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <department id="701">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Wirtschaft, Bildung und Forschung</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'économie, de la formation et de la recherche</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'economia, della formazione e della ricerca</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Economic Affairs, Education and Research</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <department id="201">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Offizieller Besuch des iranischen Präsidenten Hassan Rohani am 2./3. Juli</title>
      <lead>Auf Einladung des Bundesrates weilt der iranische Präsident Hassan Rohani am 2. und 3. Juli zu einem offiziellen Besuch in der Schweiz. Die Beziehungen zwischen der Schweiz und Iran haben sich in den vergangenen Jahren vertieft. Es ist das Ziel beider Seiten, diese positive Entwicklung in die Zukunft fortzuschreiben.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Bundespräsident Alain Berset wird Präsident Hassan Rohani am Montagnachmittag mit militärischen Ehren in Zürich empfangen. Anschliessend ist in Bern ein erster Austausch geplant, an dem auch Bundesrat Ignazio Cassis und der iranische Aussenminister Mohammad Jawad Zarif teilnehmen werden. Die offiziellen Gespräche finden am Dienstag, 3. Juli 2018, statt. Neben dem Bundespräsidenten werden daran seitens der Schweiz der Vizepräsident des Bundesrates Ueli Maurer, Bundesrätin Simonetta Sommaruga und Bundesrat Johann N. Schneider-Ammann teilnehmen. Während des Besuchs sollen auch Absichtserklärungen und Vereinbarungen unterzeichnet werden.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Im Zentrum des Besuchs stehen die jüngsten Entwicklungen um das Iran-Nuklearabkommen (Joint Comprehensive Plan of Action JCPOA). Trotz Ausstieg der USA gilt es Wege zu finden, um dessen Errungenschaften zu sichern und an der Nichtweiterverbreitung von Nuklearwaffen in der Region festzuhalten. Des Weiteren werden die Delegationen die Lage im Nahen und Mittleren Osten erörtern. Zur Sprache kommen dabei auch das Schutzmachtmandat, welches die Schweiz zugunsten der USA in Iran (seit 1980) ausübt sowie jene zugunsten des Iran in Saudi-Arabien, respektive Saudi-Arabiens im Iran, die vor kurzem in Kraft getreten sind. Weiter steht die Frage auf der Agenda, wie angesichts der beschlossenen Wiedereinführung der seit 2016 ausgesetzten US-Sanktionen gegen Iran die bilateralen Beziehungen weiterentwickelt werden können.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Iran ist ein politisch und wirtschaftlich wichtiger Partner für die Schweiz. Ende Februar 2016 verabschiedeten die beiden Länder anlässlich des Besuchs des damaligen Bundespräsidenten Johann N. Schneider-Ammann in Teheran eine Road Map zur Intensivierung der bilateralen Beziehungen. Diese ermöglichte in der Folge die Lancierung bzw. Wiederaufnahme von regelmässigen Dialogen in Bereichen wie Wirtschaft, Finanzen, Menschenrechte und Justiz, nukleare Sicherheit oder Migration. Der Besuch erlaubt es denn auch, eine erste Bilanz zu ziehen und die nächsten Schritte der Umsetzung zu besprechen.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Adressen für Rückfragen: André Simonazzi Bundesratssprecher Tel.: 058 462 37 03 andre.simonazzi@bk.admin.ch Logistik und Organisation: Linda Shepard Information EDA +41 (0)79 544 48 16 info@eda.admin.ch Organisatorische Angaben sind noch nicht verfügbar. Sie werden zu gegebener Zeit zugestellt.</contact>
      <link id="178657">
        <title>Bilaterale Beziehungen Schweiz–Iran</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home/vertretungen-und-reisehinweise/iran/bilatereale-beziehungenschweiziran.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions>
        <revision date="2018-06-18 11:29" type="R"/>
      </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Visite officielle du président iranien Hassan Rohani les 2 et 3 juillet</title>
      <lead>Répondant à l’invitation du Conseil fédéral, le président iranien Hassan Rohani sera en visite officielle en Suisse les 2 et 3 juillet. Les relations entre la Suisse et l’Iran se sont approfondies au cours des années passées. Les deux parties se félicitent de cette évolution positive et entendent poursuivre dans cette voie.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Le président de la Confédération Alain Berset accueillera le président Hassan Rohani lundi après-midi à Zurich, avec les honneurs militaires. Un premier entretien aura ensuite lieu à Berne, en présence du conseiller fédéral Ignazio Cassis et du ministre iranien des affaires étrangères Mohammad Jawad Zarif. Les entretiens officiels auront lieu le mardi 3 juillet. Le vice-président du Conseil fédéral Ueli Maurer, la conseillère fédérale Simonetta Sommaruga et le conseiller fédéral Johann N. Schneider-Ammann y participeront, aux côtés du président de la confédération. Il est prévu que des déclarations d’intention et des conventions soient signées à l’occasion de la visite.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Les derniers développements de l’accord sur le programme nucléaire iranien (&lt;i&gt;Joint Comprehensive Plan of Action, JCPOA&lt;/i&gt;) seront au centre des discussions. Malgré le retrait des Etats-Unis, il convient de préserver les acquis de l’accord et de veiller à la non-prolifération des armes nucléaires dans la région. Les délégations discuteront également de la situation au Proche-Orient et au Moyen-Orient. Il sera par ailleurs question du mandat de puissance protectrice exercé par la Suisse, qui représente les intérêts des Etats-Unis en Iran depuis 1980 et les intérêts de l’Iran en Arabie saoudite et ceux de l’Arabie saoudite en Iran depuis 2017. La question du développement des relations bilatérales, malgré le rétablissement des sanctions des Etats-Unis à l’encontre de l’Iran, levées depuis 2016, sera également à l’ordre du jour.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;L’Iran est un partenaire politique et économique important pour la Suisse. Fin février 2016, la Suisse et l’Iran ont convenu d’une feuille de route destinée à approfondir les relations bilatérales, à l’occasion de la visite à Téhéran du président de la Confédération en exercice Johann N. Schneider-Ammann. Celle-ci a permis de lancer ou de relancer des dialogues réguliers dans différents domaines tels que l’économie, les finances, les droits de l’homme, la justice, la sécurité nucléaire et les questions migratoires. La visite du président iranien permettra en outre de tirer un premier bilan et de discuter des prochaines étapes de la mise en œuvre de la feuille de route.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Renseignements: André Simonazzi porte-parole du Conseil fédéral Tél.: 058 462 37 03 andre.simonazzi@bk.admin.ch Logistique et organisation: Linda Shepard Information DFAE Tél. : +41 (0)79 544 48 16 info@eda.admin.ch Les détails de l’organisation seront communiqués en temps utile.</contact>
      <link id="178658">
        <title>Relations bilatérales Suisse–Iran</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae/representations-et-conseils-aux-voyageurs/iran/suisse-iran.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions>
        <revision date="2018-06-18 11:29" type="R"/>
      </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Visita ufficiale del presidente iraniano Hassan Rohani il 2 e 3 luglio</title>
      <lead>Su invito del Consiglio federale, il 2 e 3 luglio 2018 il presidente iraniano Hassan Rohani sarà in visita ufficiale in Svizzera. Nel corso degli ultimi anni la Svizzera e l’Iran hanno approfondito le loro relazioni e intendono coltivare anche in futuro questo sviluppo positivo.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Nel pomeriggio di lunedì 2 luglio il presidente iraniano Hassan Rohani sarà ricevuto a Zurigo con gli onori militari dal presidente della Confederazione Alain Berset. In seguito è previsto un primo incontro a Berna a cui parteciperanno anche il consigliere federale Ignazio Cassis e il ministro degli esteri iraniano Mohammad Jawad Zarif. I colloqui ufficiali si terranno martedì 3 luglio. Oltre al presidente della Confederazione Berset, per la Svizzera parteciperanno il vicepresidente del Consiglio federale Ueli Maurer, la consigliera federale Simonetta Sommaruga e il consigliere federale Johann N. Schneider-Ammann. Nel quadro della visita è prevista anche la firma di accordi e dichiarazioni di intenti.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;La visita sarà incentrata sugli ultimi sviluppi relativi all'accordo sul nucleare con l'Iran (Joint Comprehensive Plan of Action JCPOA). Nonostante l'uscita degli Stati Uniti dall'accordo occorre trovare modalità che consentano di garantire i risultati ottenuti e perseverare nella non-proliferazione delle armi nucleari nella regione. Le delegazioni discuteranno inoltre della situazione nel Vicino e Medio Oriente, in particolare del mandato di potenza protettrice che la Svizzera esercita per gli Stati Uniti in Iran (dal 1980) e di quelli, assunti recentemente, per l'Iran in Arabia Saudita e per l'Arabia Saudita in Iran. Tra i temi all'ordine del giorno vi è anche la questione di come sviluppare ulteriormente le relazioni bilaterali alla luce della decisione degli Stati Uniti di reintrodurre le sanzioni americane contro l'Iran, sospese dal 2016.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;L'Iran è un partner importante per la Svizzera a livello politico ed economico. Alla fine di febbraio 2016, in occasione della visita a Teheran dell'allora presidente della Confederazione Johann N. Schneider-Ammann, i due Paesi hanno adottato un piano d'azione per il consolidamento delle relazioni bilaterali, il quale ha consentito in seguito di avviare o rilanciare dialoghi periodici in settori quali l'economia, le finanze, i diritti dell'uomo, la giustizia, la sicurezza nucleare e la migrazione. La visita sarà quindi anche l'occasione per tracciare un primo bilancio del piano d'azione e per discutere i prossimi passi della sua attuazione.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Per maggiori informazioni: André Simonazzi portavoce del Consiglio federale Tel.: +41 58 462 37 03 andre.simonazzi@bk.admin.ch Logistica e organizzazione: Linda Shepard, Informazione DFAE Tel.: +41 79 544 48 16 info@eda.admin.ch Le informazioni organizzative non sono ancora disponibili e saranno fornite a tempo debito.</contact>
      <link id="178659">
        <title>Relazioni bilaterali Svizzera–Iran</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae/rappresentanze-e-consigli-di-viaggio/iran/svizzera-iran.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions>
        <revision date="2018-06-18 11:29" type="R"/>
      </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Iranian President Hassan Rouhani to pay official visit to Switzerland on 2 and 3 July</title>
      <lead>At the invitation of the Federal Council, Iranian President Hassan Rouhani will pay an official visit to Switzerland on 2 and 3 July. Relations between Switzerland and Iran have deepened in recent years. It is the aim of both sides to continue on this positive path in the future.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;President Alain Berset will receive President Hassan Rouhani in Zurich on Monday afternoon with military honours. A first meeting will take place in Bern, which will also be attended by Federal Councillor Ignazio Cassis and the Iranian foreign minister, Mohammad Javad Zarif. The official talks will be held on Tuesday, 3 July, where Switzerland will be represented by President Berset, the Vice President of the Federal Council, Ueli Maurer, and federal councillors Simonetta Sommaruga and Johann N. Schneider-Ammann. A number of agreements and declarations of intent are expected to be signed during the visit.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Discussions will focus on the latest developments regarding the Iran nuclear agreement (Joint Comprehensive Plan of Action JCPOA). The aim is to find ways of preserving the progress made as a result of the agreement and of ensuring the non-proliferation of nuclear weapons in the region despite the decision of the USA to withdraw from it. The delegations will also address the situation in the Near and Middle East. Further issues include the protecting power mandate which Switzerland exercises on behalf of the USA in Iran (since 1980), and that on behalf of Iran in Saudi Arabia and of Saudi Arabia in Iran, which recently came into effect. Also on the agenda is the question of how bilateral relations can be further developed in light of the decision by the USA to re-introduce sanctions against Iran, which had been suspended since 2016.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Iran is an important partner for Switzerland both politically and economically. The two countries adopted a road map to intensify bilateral relations at the end of February 2016 when Johann N. Schneider-Ammann paid a visit to Teheran during his year as president. This served as an impetus to launch or resume regular dialogue in the fields of economic and financial affairs, human rights and justice, nuclear safety and migration. The visit by the Iranian president provides an opportunity to take stock and discuss the next steps in implementing the road map. &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Address for enquiries: André Simonazzi Federal Council Spokesperson Tel.: 058 462 37 03 andre.simonazzi@bk.admin.ch Logistics and Organisation: Linda Shepard FDFA Information Service +41 (0)79 544 48 16 info@eda.admin.ch Organisational details are not yet available. Information will be provided in due course.</contact>
      <link id="178660">
        <title>Bilateral relations Switzerland–Iran</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home/representations-and-travel-advice/iran/switzerland-iran.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions>
        <revision date="2018-06-18 11:29" type="R"/>
      </revisions>
    </content>
    <keywords>
      <keyword id="128" org-id="601">
        <name lang="de">Wirtschaftspolitik und Finanzmärkte</name>
        <name lang="fr">Politique économique et marchés financiers</name>
        <name lang="it">Politica economica e mercati finanziari</name>
        <name lang="en">Economic policy and financial markets</name>
      </keyword>
    </keywords>
    <topics>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
