<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="67830" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2017-08-23</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="323" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>701</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidg. Materialprüfungs- und Forschungsanstalt</name>
      <name lang="fr">Laboratoire fédéral d'essai des matériaux et de recherche</name>
      <name lang="it">Laboratorio federale di prova dei materiali e di ricerca</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Laboratory for Materials Testing and Research</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.empa.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.empa.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.empa.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.empa.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">contact@empa.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">contact@empa.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">contact@empa.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">contact@empa.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="701">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Wirtschaft, Bildung und Forschung</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'économie, de la formation et de la recherche</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'economia, della formazione e della ricerca</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Economic Affairs, Education and Research</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Dübendorf, St. Gallen und Thun</city>
      <title>Mit Algen Arthritis behandeln</title>
      <lead>Forschende der ETH Zürich, der Empa und des norwegischen Forschungsinstituts SINTEF sind einem neuen Ansatz zur Behandlung von Arthritis auf der Spur. Basis dafür ist ein Polysaccharid, ein langkettiges Zuckermolekül, aus Braunalgen. Chemisch modifiziert senkt dieses «Alginat» den oxidativen Stress, wirkt in Zellkulturversuchen entzündungshemmend und unterdrückt die Immunreaktion gegen Knorpelzellen, und bekämpft damit Ursachen von Arthritis. Noch steht die Forschung allerdings ganz am Anfang.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Arthritis ist die meistverbreitete Gelenkserkrankung; rund 90 Prozent aller über 65-jährigen Personen sind – in unterschiedlichem Ausmass – davon betroffen. Aber auch bei jüngeren Personen ist die degenerative Erkrankung verbreitet. Bei Arthritis wird das Knorpelgewebe im Gelenk, eine Art Schutzschicht auf den Knochen, das die Gelenke «schmiert», mit der Zeit abgebaut. Dies kann extrem schmerzhafte Folgen für die betroffenen Personen haben, da mit dem Knorpelabbau Entzündungsreaktionen einhergehen. Im späteren Verlauf der Erkrankung sind die Knochen dann nicht mehr ausreichend geschützt und können direkt aufeinander treffen.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Von Arthritis können sämtliche Gelenke des Körpers betroffen sein, am häufigsten ist sie jedoch am Kniegelenk, am Hüftgelenk und in den Fingern. Die Krankheit gilt bis anhin als unheilbar. Gängige Behandlungsmethoden wie Entzündungshemmer und Schmerzmittel bekämpfen in erster Linie die Symptome. Als letzter Ausweg hilft dann oft nur noch eine Operation, bei der das betroffene Gelenk durch ein künstliches ersetzt wird.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Erste Forschungsergebnisse machen Hoffnung&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;In Laboruntersuchungen ist es dem Team um die ETHZ-Forscherin Marcy Zenobi-Wong und die Empa-Forscherin Katharina Maniura nun gelungen, gemeinsam mit dem SINTEF in Norwegen eine Substanz zu identifizieren, die das Potential hat, den Knorpelabbau in den Gelenken aufzuhalten. Dabei handelt es sich um das aus den Stielen von Braunalgen – genauer gesagt aus Palmentang (lat. &lt;i&gt;Laminaria hyperborea&lt;/i&gt;) – gewonnene Polysaccharid Alginat, das bestimmten extrazellulären Biomolekülen aus Knorpelgewebe ähnelt. Die Forscher haben Alginat mit Sulfatgruppen chemisch modifiziert und anschliessend in gelöster Form zu Zellkulturen gegeben, um die Reaktion verschiedener Zelltypen auf das modifizierte Polysaccharid zu untersuchen. Dabei zeigte sich, dass Alginatsulfat den oxidativen Stress – eine häufige Ursache von Zellschäden bzw. sogar Zellsterben – erheblich senken kann, und zwar umso besser, je mehr Sulfatgruppen an das Alginatmolekül angehängt waren.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Ausserdem war Alginatsulfat in der Lage, die Entzündungsreaktion zu unterdrücken, wiederum in Abhängigkeit von der Anzahl der Sulfatgruppen: Sowohl in menschlichen Knorpelzellen, so genannten Chondrozyten, als auch in Makrophagen – den «Fresszellen» unseres Immunsystems – konnte Alginatsulfat die Expression von Genen, die eine Entzündungsreaktion auslösen, herunter regulieren. Die Algenmoleküle sollten damit den Abbau der Gelenkknorpel verlangsamen. «Die Hoffnung ist, dass sie den Abbau sogar stoppen können», so der Empa-Forscher Markus Rottmar.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Weitere Forschungsarbeiten nötig&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Die Alginatsulfate wurden bisher nur &lt;i&gt;in vitro&lt;/i&gt;, also im Labor mit Zellkulturen, untersucht. Aufgrund der ermutigenden Ergebnisse soll die Forschung nun aber weitergehen. Als nächstes müssen die Substanzen im Tierversuch getestet werden. Ist auch dies erfolgreich, können anschliessend klinische Studien mit Testpersonen folgen. Diese Tests sind indes langwierig und aufwändig. Sollte alles einwandfrei funktionieren, dürfte es daher trotzdem noch einige Jahre dauern, bis Arthritispatienten und -patientinnen mit Alginatsulfat behandelt werden können.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Prof. Dr. Marcy Zenobi-Wong, ETH Zürich, Gewebetechnologie und Biofabrikation, Tel. +41 44 632 50 89, marcy.zenobi@hest.ethz.ch Dr. Katharina Maniura, Empa, Biointerfaces Tel. +41 58 765 74 47; katharina.maniura@empa.ch Dr. Markus Rottmar, Empa, Biointerfaces Tel. +41 58 765 11 18, markus.rottmar@empa.ch Redaktion / Medienkontakt Dr. Michael Hagmann, Empa, Kommunikation, Tel. +41 58 765 45 92, redaktion@empa.ch</contact>
      <link id="169769">
        <title>Empa-Medienmitteilung</title>
        <uri>https://www.empa.ch/web/s604/algen_gegen_arthritis</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Dübendorf, St. Gallen und Thun</city>
      <title>Traiter l'arthrite avec les algues</title>
      <lead>Les chercheurs de l'ETH Zurich (École polytechnique fédérale de Zurich), de l'Empa et de l'institut de recherche norvégien SINTEF sont sur la bonne voie en ce qui concerne une nouvelle approche dans le traitement de l'arthrite. Cette approche est basée sur un polysaccharide, une molécule de sucre à longue chaîne issue d'algues brunes. Cet « alginate » chimiquement modifié réduit le stress oxydatif, réduit l'inflammation dans les essais de culture cellulaire et contient la réponse immunitaire vis-à-vis des cellules cartilagineuses, et combat ainsi les causes de l'arthrite. La recherche n'en est pourtant encore qu'à ses débuts.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;L'arthrite est la maladie articulaire la plus fréquente ; environ 90 pour cent des 65 ans sont touchés, à des degrés divers. Mais cette maladie dégénérative est également très répandue chez les jeunes personnes. En cas d'arthrite, le cartilage de l'articulation, sorte de couche protectrice sur les os qui « lubrifie » les articulations, se dégrade au fil du temps. Cela peut avoir des conséquences extrêmement douloureuses pour les personnes concernées, en raison de l'inflammation liée à la dégradation du cartilage. À un stade avancé de la maladie, les os ne sont plus convenablement protégés et risque de frotter directement les uns contre les autres.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;L'arthrite est susceptible de toucher toutes les articulations du corps, mais le plus souvent il s'agit des articulations du genou, de la hanche et des doigts. La maladie est incurable à ce jour. Dans un premier temps, les traitements courants tels que les anti-inflammatoires et les analgésiques permettent de combattre les symptômes. En dernier recours, il arrive souvent que seule une opération consistant à remplacer artificiellement l'articulation puisse aider.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Les premiers résultats de recherche suscite de l'espoir&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Lors de tests en laboratoire, l'équipe de la chercheuse de l'ETHZ, Marcy Zenobi-Wong, et la chercheuse de l'Empa, Katharina Maniura, ont été en mesure d'identifier, en même temps que le SINTEF en Norvège, une substance qui a le potentiel de mettre un terme à la dégradation du cartilage dans les articulations. Cette dernière est choisie parmi les tiges d'algues brunes - plus spécifiquement de laminaires (lat. &lt;i&gt;Laminaria hyperborea&lt;/i&gt;) – l'alginate est un dérivé de polysaccharide similaire à certaines biomolécules extracellulaires du cartilage. Les chercheurs ont modifié chimiquement les alginates à l'aide des groupes composés de sulfates, puis les ont ajoutés sous forme diluée à des cultures de cellules afin d'étudier la réaction de différents types de cellules à la polysaccharide modifiée. Il a été constaté que le sulfate d'alginate peut considérablement réduire le stress oxydatif, une cause fréquente de lésions cellulaires ou même de la mort des cellules, et que plus il y a de groupes composés de sulfates attachés à la molécule d'alginate, mieux c'est.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;En outre, l'alginate a été capable, encore une fois en fonction du nombre de groupes composés de sulfates, de supprimer la réaction inflammatoire : aussi bien dans les cellules de cartilage humain, appelées chondrocytes, que dans les macrophages - les « phagocytes » de notre système immunitaire - le sulfate d'alginate pourrait réguler à la baisse l'expression des gènes, laquelle déclenche une réponse inflammatoire. Les molécules d'algues devraient donc ralentir la dégradation du cartilage articulaire. « Nous avons espoir que ces molécules puissent même stopper la dégradation », explique Markus Rottmar, chercheur à l'Empa.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;D'autres recherches sont nécessaires&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Le sulfate d'alginate n'a jusqu'à présent été étudié qu'&lt;i&gt;in vitro&lt;/i&gt;, en laboratoire, sur des cultures cellulaires. Bien que les résultats soient encourageants, la recherche doit continuer. Les substances doivent ensuite être testées sur les animaux. Si les résultats s'avèrent également prometteurs, des essais cliniques seront ensuite effectués sur des personnes. Ces tests sont cependant longs et coûteux. Si tout fonctionnait correctement, il faudrait toutefois attendre encore quelques années avant que les patientes et patients atteints d'arthrite ne puissent être traités par le sulfate d'alginate.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Prof. Dr. Marcy Zenobi-Wong, ETH Zürich (École polytechnique fédérale de Zurich), technologie des tissus et biofabrication, Tél. +41 44 632 50 89, marcy.zenobi@hest.ethz.ch Dr. Katharina Maniura, Empa, Biointerfaces Tél. +41 58 765 74 47; katharina.maniura@empa.ch Dr. Markus Rottmar, Empa, Biointerfaces Tél. +41 58 765 11 18, markus.rottmar@empa.ch Rédaction / Contact média Dr. Michael Hagmann, Empa, Communication, Tél. +41 58 765 45 92, redaktion@empa.ch</contact>
      <link id="169769">
        <title>Empa-Medienmitteilung</title>
        <uri>https://www.empa.ch/web/s604/algen_gegen_arthritis</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Dübendorf, St. Gallen und Thun</city>
      <title>Treating arthritis with algae</title>
      <lead>Researchers at ETH Zurich, Empa and the Norwegian research institute SINTEF are pursuing a new approach to treating arthritis. This is based on a polysaccharide, a long-chain sugar molecule, originating from brown algae. When chemically modified, this "alginate" reduces oxidative stress, has an anti-inflammatory effect in cell culture tests and suppresses the immune reaction against cartilage cells, thereby combating the causes of arthritis. The research is, however, still in its infancy.</lead>
      <text link="no">Arthritis is the most-widespread joint disease, with around 90 percent of all people over 65 being affected to varying degrees, but this degenerative disease is also widespread amongst younger people. In arthritis, the cartilage in the joint, a type of protective layer on bones that "lubricates" the joint, degenerates over time. This can be extremely painful for sufferers, because inflammatory reactions are associated with cartilage degeneration. In the later stages of the disease, bones are no longer adequately protected and can directly rub against each other. Arthritis can affect all joints in the body, but most often affects the knee joint, hip joint and fingers. The disease has been considered incurable until now. Current treatment methods, such as anti-inflammatory drugs and painkillers, mainly address the symptoms. Often, the only remaining option is an operation to replace the affected joint with an artificial one. Initial research results are encouraging In laboratory tests, the team led by ETHZ researcher Marcy Zenobi-Wong and Empa researcher Katharina Maniura has now succeeded, together with SINTEF in Norway, in identifying a substance with the potential to halt cartilage degeneration in joints. This substance is the polysaccharide alginate extracted from the stems of brown algae - or more precisely cuvie (Lat. Laminaria hyperborea), which is similar to specific extracellular biomolecules in cartilage. The researchers chemically modified the alginate with sulfate groups and then added it in dissolved form to cell cultures to examine the reaction of various cell types to the modified polysaccharide. This revealed that alginate sulfate can significantly reduce oxidative stress, which is a frequent cause of cell damage or even cell death, and the more sulfate groups attached to the alginate molecule, the greater this reduction. Alginate sulfate was also able to suppress the inflammatory reaction, again depending on the number of sulfate groups, and was able to down-regulate the expression of genes that trigger an inflammatory reaction in both human cartilage cells, known as chondrocytes, and in macrophages, the "scavenger cells" of our immune system. The algal molecules should therefore slow down cartilage degeneration. "The hope is that they can even stop this degeneration," says Empa researcher Markus Rottmar. Further research work necessary The alginate sulfates have so far only been tested in vitro, i.e. in the laboratory with cell cultures. However, the encouraging results mean that research will now continue. The next stage is to test the substances on animals. If this is also successful, clinical trials can then be conducted on people. These tests are, however, laborious and time-consuming. If everything were to work perfectly, it would still be a few years before arthritis patients could be treated with alginate sulfate. </text>
      <contact>Prof. Dr. Marcy Zenobi-Wong, ETH Zurich, Tissue Engineering and Biofabrication, Tel. +41 44 632 50 89, marcy.zenobi@hest.ethz.ch Dr. Katharina Maniura, Empa, Biointerfaces Tel. +41 58 765 74 47; katharina.maniura@empa.ch Dr. Markus Rottmar, Empa, Biointerfaces Tel. +41 58 765 11 18, markus.rottmar@empa.ch Editor/Media Contact Dr. Michael Hagmann, Empa, Communikation, Tel. +41 58 765 45 92, redaktion@empa.ch</contact>
      <link id="169769">
        <title>Empa-Medienmitteilung</title>
        <uri>https://www.empa.ch/web/s604/algen_gegen_arthritis</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="8">
        <name lang="de">Bildung und Forschung</name>
        <name lang="fr">Formation et recherche</name>
        <name lang="it">Formazione e ricerca</name>
        <name lang="en">Education and Research</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="15">
        <name lang="de">Gesundheit</name>
        <name lang="fr">Santé</name>
        <name lang="it">sanità</name>
        <name lang="en">Health</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
