<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="14640" revoked="no">
    <version>6</version>
    <pubdate>2007-09-20</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="201" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>201</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="201">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Akademie für humanitäres Völkerrecht in Genf</title>
      <lead>Bundespräsidentin Micheline Calmy-Rey, Vorsteherin des Eidgenössischen Departements für auswärtige Angelegenheiten (EDA), nimmt am Donnerstagabend an der Einweihung der Akademie für humanitäres Völkerrecht und Menschenrechte in Genf teil. Diese neue Akademie, die das Centre universitaire de droit international humanitaire ablöst, ist eine sinnvolle Ergänzung der Genfer Universitätslandschaft neben dem 2006 geschaffenen Schweizer Lehrstuhl für Menschenrechte, der dem Institut universitaire de hautes études internationales (IUHEI) angegliedert ist.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Nach der Schaffung des UNO-Menschenrechtsrats mit Sitz in Genf schien es sinnvoll, die Zusammenarbeit mit der Wissenschaft zu stärken und auszubauen. Die Gründung der neuen Akademie trägt zur Entwicklung eines qualitativ hochstehenden Kompetenzzentrums im Bereich des humanitären Völkerrechts und allgemein der Menschenrechte bei.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Mit der Errichtung des Global Humanitarian Forum Geneva, das auf eine Initiative des EDA zurückgeht und vom ehemaligen UNO-Generalsekretär Kofi Annan geleitet wird, sowie der Gründung der neuen Akademie baut das internationale Genf seine diplomatische und wissenschaftliche Ausstrahlung weiter aus und bleibt seinem Auftrag treu, zur Lösung der Probleme unserer Welt beizutragen.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Presse- und Informationsdienst Bundeshaus West CH-3003 Bern Tel.: +41 (0)31 322 31 53 Fax: +41 (0)31 324 90 47 E-Mail: info@eda.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="31087">
        <title>Für weitere Informationen: Centre Universitaire de Droit International Humanitaire (fr)</title>
        <uri>http://www.cudih.org/</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions>
        <revision date="2007-09-20 15:18" type="R"/>
        <revision date="2007-09-20 15:16" type="R"/>
        <revision date="2007-09-20 15:13" type="R"/>
      </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Académie de droit international humanitaire à Genève</title>
      <lead>La Présidente de la Confédération et cheffe du Département fédéral des affaires étrangères (DFAE), Micheline Calmy-Rey, participera jeudi soir à l’inauguration de l’Académie de droit international humanitaire et de droits humains à Genève. Cette académie, qui remplace le Centre universitaire de droit international humanitaire, vient compléter judicieusement le paysage universitaire genevois, aux côtés de la Chaire suisse des droits humains, créée en 2006 et rattachée à l’Institut universitaire de hautes études internationales (IUHEI).</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Avec l’établissement du Conseil des droits de l’homme de l’ONU à Genève, il était souhaitable de renforcer et de développer les coopérations avec le monde académique. La création de la nouvelle académie contribue à la constitution d’un pôle de compétences de haut niveau dans le domaine du droit international humanitaire et, plus généralement, dans celui des droits humains.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Avec le lancement du Global Humanitarian Forum Geneva, à l’initiative duquel on trouve le Département fédéral des affaires étrangères (DFAE) et qui sera présidé par Monsieur Kofi Annan, ancien Secrétaire général de l’ONU, et l’inauguration de la nouvelle académie, la Genève internationale renforce son rayonnement diplomatique et académique, fidèle à sa vocation de contribuer à la recherche de solutions aux problèmes du monde.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Service de presse et d'information Palais fédéral ouest CH-3003 Berne Tél.: (+41) 031 322 31 53 Fax: (+41) 031 324 90 47 E-Mail: info@eda.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="31088">
        <title>Pour plusieurs informations: Centre Universitaire de Droit International Humanitaire</title>
        <uri>http://www.cudih.org/</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions>
        <revision date="2007-09-20 15:13" type="R"/>
      </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Accademia di diritto internazionale umanitario a Ginevra</title>
      <lead>La Presidente della Confederazione e capo del Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri (DFAE), Micheline Calmy-Rey, parteciperà giovedì sera all'inaugurazione dell'Accademia di diritto internazionale umanitario e di diritti umani a Ginevra. Questa accademia, che sostituisce il Centro universitario di diritto internazionale umanitario, completa il panorama universitario ginevrino di cui fa parte anche la Cattedra svizzera dei diritti umani istituita nel 2006 e annessa all'Istituto universitario di alti studi internazionali (IUHEI).</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Con l'istituzione del Consiglio dei diritti dell'uomo dell'ONU a Ginevra, era auspicabile rafforzare e sviluppare la cooperazione con il mondo accademico. La fondazione della nuova accademia contribuisce a formare un centro di competenze di alto livello nel settore del diritto internazionale umanitario e, più in generale, in quello dei diritti umani.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Con il lancio del Global Humanitarian Forum Geneva, promosso anche dal Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri (DFAE) e che sarà presieduto da Kofi Annan, ex Segretario generale dell'ONU, e con l'inaugurazione della nuova accademia, la Ginevra internazionale consolida il suo ruolo diplomatico e accademico confermando la sua vocazione nel promuovere la ricerca di soluzioni ai problemi del mondo.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Servizio stampa e informazione Palazzo federale ovest CH-3003 Berna Tel.: (+41) 031 322 31 53 Fax: (+41) 031 324 90 47 E-Mail: info@eda.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="31089">
        <title>Per ulteriori informazioni: Centre Universitaire de Droit International Humanitaire (fr)</title>
        <uri>http://www.cudih.org/</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions>
        <revision date="2007-09-20 15:13" type="R"/>
      </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Geneva Academy of International Humanitarian Law and Human Rights</title>
      <lead>The President of the Swiss Confederation and head of the Federal Department of Foreign Affairs (FDFA), Micheline Calmy-Rey, will attend tonight the inauguration of the Geneva Academy of International Humanitarian Law and Human Rights. The Academy, which replaces the University Centre for International Humanitarian Law, completes the constellation of centres of specialist learning in this field at Geneva University together with the HEI Swiss Chair of Human Rights, which was established in 2006 and is attached to the Graduate Institute of International Studies in Geneva (IUHEI).</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;With the establishment of the United Nations Human Rights Council in Geneva, the need was seen to strengthen and to develop cooperation with the academic world. The new institution contributes to the creation of a pole of high-level expertise in international humanitarian law and in human rights more generally. &amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Together with the launch of the Global Humanitarian Forum Geneva, a FDFA's initiative, which will be chaired by Kofi Annan, the former Secretary-General of the United Nations, and the inauguration of the new Academy, International Geneva strengthens its diplomatic and academic reputation in keeping with its vocation to contribute to the search for solutions to world problems.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Press and Information Service Bundeshaus West CH-3003 Berne Tel.: (+41) 031 322 31 53 Fax: (+41) 031 324 90 47 E-Mail: info@eda.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="31090">
        <title>For further information: University Centre for International Humanitarian Law (fr)</title>
        <uri>http://www.ucihl.org/</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
