<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="100703" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2024-04-11</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="201" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>201</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="201">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Konflikte und Krisen führten 2023 zu einem Anstieg der APD</title>
      <lead>Die öffentliche Entwicklungshilfe (APD) der Schweiz entsprach im Jahr 2023 0,60% des Bruttonationaleinkommens (BNE) und belief sich insgesamt auf 4,640 Milliarden Franken, wovon mehr als ein Viertel ins Asylwesen in der Schweiz floss. Ohne Berücksichtigung der Asylkosten betrug die APD/BNE-Quote 0,43%.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Die APD/BNE-Quote, die 2022 noch bei 0,56% lag, hat im Jahr 2023 mit 0,60% einen neuen Höchststand erreicht. Zu diesem Ergebnis führten insbesondere die umfassenden Unterstützungsanstrengungen im Zusammenhang mit dem Krieg in der Ukraine, dem Konflikt im Nahen Osten sowie die Kosten für die Aufnahme von Asylsuchenden, Geflüchteten und Schutzsuchenden während der ersten zwölf Monate ihres Aufenthalts in der Schweiz. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Mit 1,311 Milliarden Franken macht der anrechenbare Anteil der Asylkosten in der Schweiz im Jahr 2023 insgesamt 28% der APD aus. 538 Millionen Franken davon entfallen auf Personen mit Schutzstatus S aus der Ukraine.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Ohne Berücksichtigung der Asylkosten nahmen die der APD anrechenbaren Ausgaben im Vergleich zu 2022 um 242 Millionen Franken zu, was einer APD/BNE-Quote von 0,43% im Jahr 2023 entspricht (0,40% im Jahr 2022). &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Rolle der internationalen Zusammenarbeit der Schweiz &lt;br /&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Die Schweiz trägt mit ihrer internationalen Zusammenarbeit zur Bekämpfung der Armut, zur Förderung des Friedens und der Menschenrechte, zur Bewältigung von globalen Herausforderungen wie Pandemien und Klimawandel sowie zur Beseitigung der Ursachen von Flucht und irregulärer Migration bei. Sie setzt sich zudem für eine umweltverträgliche globale Entwicklung ein und sorgt für eine nachhaltige Bewirtschaftung der natürlichen Ressourcen.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Die internationale Zusammenarbeit der Schweiz wird hauptsächlich von der Direktion für Entwicklung und Zusammenarbeit (DEZA) des EDA, dem Staatssekretariat für Wirtschaft (SECO) des WBF und der Abteilung Frieden und Menschenrechte (AFM) des EDA umgesetzt, deren Budgets zusammen rund zwei Drittel der APD 2023 abdecken. Zu den Ausgaben der internationalen Zusammenarbeit kommen die als APD anrechenbaren Ausgaben der übrigen Bundesstellen (einschliesslich Asylkosten) sowie die Beiträge der Schweizer Kantone und Gemeinden hinzu.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Berechnung der APD und internationaler Vergleich&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Die öffentliche Entwicklungshilfe wird nach den international vereinbarten Richtlinien des Entwicklungshilfeausschusses (DAC) der Organisation für wirtschaftliche Zusammenarbeit und Entwicklung (OECD) berechnet. Um das Engagement der 31 DAC-Mitglieder zu vergleichen, wird der Anteil der APD am Bruttonationaleinkommen jedes Landes berechnet. Im internationalen Vergleich steigt die Schweiz gegenüber 2022 um einen Rang auf und belegt im 2023 den 8. Platz.&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Kommunikation EDA Bundeshaus West CH-3003 Bern Tel. Medienstelle: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <link id="272868">
        <title>International aid rises in 2023 with increased support to Ukraine and humanitarian needs (en)</title>
        <uri>https://www.oecd.org/newsroom/international-aid-rises-in-2023-with-increased-support-to-ukraine-and-humanitarian-needs.htm</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="272869">
        <title>Öffentliche Entwicklungshilfe der Schweiz</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/deza/de/home/deza/portraet/zahlen-statistiken/schweiz-apd.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="272873">
        <title>Die Schweiz im internationalen Vergleich</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/deza/de/home/deza/portraet/zahlen-statistiken/internationaler-vergleich.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Les conflits et crises ont conduit à une hausse de l’APD en 2023</title>
      <lead>L’aide publique au développement (APD) de la Suisse a atteint un taux de 0,60% du revenu national brut (RNB) en 2023 et a totalisé 4,640 milliards de francs, dont plus d’un quart proviennent des coûts liés à l’asile en Suisse. Hors coûts d’asile, le taux APD/RNB s’établit à 0,43%.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Le taux APD/RNB a atteint un nouveau record de 0,60% en 2023, après le taux de 0,56% en 2022. La poursuite des efforts pour répondre aux besoins liés à la guerre en Ukraine, le conflit au Proche Orient ainsi que les coûts liés à l’accueil des requérants d’asile, réfugiés et personnes en quête de protection durant les douze premiers mois de leur séjour en Suisse sont notamment à l’origine de ce résultat. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Avec 1,311 milliards de francs, la part comptabilisable des coûts d’asile en Suisse représente au total 28% de l’APD en 2023, dont 538 millions de francs pour les personnes au bénéfice du statut de protection S en provenance d’Ukraine.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Hors coûts d’asile, les dépenses déclarées dans l’APD ont augmenté de 242 millions de francs par rapport à 2022. Le taux APD/RNB hors coûts d’asile atteint ainsi 0,43% en 2023, contre 0,40% l’année précédente. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Rôle de la coopération internationale suisse&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Par sa coopération internationale, la Suisse contribue à la réduction de la pauvreté, à répondre aux défis globaux tels que la promotion de la paix et des droits de l’homme, les pandémies ou le dérèglement climatique, ainsi qu’à la diminution des causes de la migration forcée et irrégulière. Elle participe également à l’instauration d’un développement mondial respectueux de l’environnement, tout en veillant à une gestion durable des ressources naturelles.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;La coopération internationale de la Confédération est principalement mise en œuvre par la Direction du développement et de la coopération (DDC) du DFAE, le Secrétariat d’État à l’économie (SECO) du DEFR et la Division Paix et droits de l’homme (DPDH) du DFAE, dont les budgets couvrent près des deux tiers de l’APD en 2023.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Aux activités de la coopération internationale s’ajoutent des dépenses éligibles au titre de l’APD provenant d’autres offices fédéraux, dont les coûts comptabilisables liés à l’asile, ainsi que les contributions des cantons et des communes suisses.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Comptabilisation de l’APD et comparaison internationale&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;La comptabilisation de l’APD se base sur les directives du Comité d’aide au développement (CAD) de l’Organisation de coopération et de développement économiques (OCDE). L’engagement des 31 membres du CAD est comparé en mesurant la part du revenu national brut que chacun de ces pays consacre à l’APD. Dans le classement international, la Suisse progresse d’une place par rapport à 2022 et occupe le 8ème rang en 2023.&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Communication DFAE Palais fédéral ouest CH-3003 Berne Tél. Service de presse: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <link id="272868">
        <title>International aid rises in 2023 with increased support to Ukraine and humanitarian needs (en)</title>
        <uri>https://www.oecd.org/newsroom/international-aid-rises-in-2023-with-increased-support-to-ukraine-and-humanitarian-needs.htm</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="272870">
        <title>Aide publique au développement de la Suisse</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/deza/fr/home/ddc/portrait/chiffres-statistiques/apd-suisse.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="272874">
        <title>La Suisse en comparaison internationale</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/deza/fr/home/ddc/portrait/chiffres-statistiques/suisse-comparaison-internationale.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Conflitti e crisi hanno determinato un aumento dell’APS nel 2023</title>
      <lead>L’aiuto pubblico allo sviluppo (APS) della Svizzera ha raggiunto lo 0,60 per cento del reddito nazionale lordo (RNL) nel 2023, per un totale di 4,640 miliardi di franchi, più di un quarto dei quali è riconducibile ai costi legati all’asilo nel nostro Paese. Escludendo questi ultimi, il tasso APS/RNL si attesta allo 0,43 per cento.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Nel 2023 il tasso APS/RNL ha segnato un nuovo record, pari allo 0,60 per cento (2022: 0,56 %). Questo aumento è dovuto ai continui sforzi per rispondere alle esigenze connesse alla guerra in Ucraina, al conflitto in Medio Oriente e ai costi legati all’accoglienza di persone richiedenti l’asilo, profughi e persone in cerca di protezione in Svizzera nei primi 12 mesi del loro soggiorno. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Nel 2023 la parte computabile dei costi di asilo in Svizzera, pari a 1,311 miliardi di franchi, rappresentava complessivamente il 28 per cento dell’APS, compresi i 538 milioni per le persone con lo statuto di protezione S provenienti dall’Ucraina.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Se si escludono i costi di asilo, le spese dichiarate nell’APS sono aumentate di 242 milioni di franchi rispetto al 2022. Il tasso APS/RNL, esclusi i costi di asilo, ha raggiunto quindi lo 0,43 per cento nel 2023, rispetto allo 0,40 per cento dell’anno precedente. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Il ruolo della cooperazione internazionale svizzera&lt;/b&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Attraverso la cooperazione internazionale la Svizzera contribuisce a ridurre la povertà, ad affrontare le sfide globali come la promozione della pace e dei diritti umani, le pandemie e i cambiamenti climatici, e a diminuire le cause della migrazione forzata e irregolare. Favorisce inoltre uno sviluppo globale rispettoso dell’ambiente, fondato su una gestione sostenibile delle risorse naturali.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;La cooperazione internazionale della Confederazione è attuata principalmente dalla Direzione dello sviluppo e della cooperazione (DSC) del Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri (DFAE), dalla Segreteria di Stato dell’economia (SECO) del Dipartimento federale dell’economia, della formazione e della ricerca (DEFR) e dalla Divisione Pace e diritti umani (DPDU) del DFAE, i cui budget hanno coperto quasi due terzi dell’APS nel 2023. Alle attività della cooperazione internazionale si aggiungono spese dichiarabili nell’APS sostenute da altri uffici federali, tra cui i costi computabili legati all’asilo, e i contributi dei Cantoni e dei Comuni svizzeri.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Contabilizzazione dell’APS e confronto internazionale&lt;/b&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;La contabilizzazione dell’APS si basa sulle direttive del Comitato di aiuto allo sviluppo (CAS) dell’Organizzazione per la cooperazione e lo sviluppo economico (OCSE). Per confrontare l’impegno dei 31 Paesi membri del CAS viene calcolata la parte di RNL che ciascuno di essi stanzia per l’APS. Situata all’ottavo posto della classifica internationale in 2023, la Svizzera è salita di un posto rispetto al 2022.&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Comunicazione DFAE Palazzo federale ovest CH-3003 Berna Tel. Servizio stampa: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <link id="272868">
        <title>International aid rises in 2023 with increased support to Ukraine and humanitarian needs (en)</title>
        <uri>https://www.oecd.org/newsroom/international-aid-rises-in-2023-with-increased-support-to-ukraine-and-humanitarian-needs.htm</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="272871">
        <title>Aiuto pubblico allo sviluppo della Svizzera</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/deza/it/home/dsc/ritratto/numeri-statistiche/aps-svizzera.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="272875">
        <title>La Svizzera nel confronto internazionale</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/deza/it/home/dsc/ritratto/numeri-statistiche/svizzera-confronto-internazionale.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Conflicts and crises lead to increase in ODA in 2023</title>
      <lead>In 2023, Switzerland's official development assistance (ODA) amounted to CHF 4.64 billion, equivalent to 0.60% of its gross national income (GNI), more than a quarter of which came from asylum-related costs in Switzerland. Excluding these asylum costs, the ODA/GNI ratio was 0.43%.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;The ODA/GNI ratio reached a new high of 0.60% in 2023, up from 0.56% in 2022. This increase was due to efforts to meet needs related to the war in Ukraine and the Middle East conflict, as well as costs associated with hosting asylum seekers, refugees and people seeking protection in Switzerland during their first twelve months in the country. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The share of asylum costs in Switzerland that are included in ODA amounted to CHF 1.311 billion, equivalent to 28% of total ODA, in 2023. CHF 538 million of this amount was for refugees from the war in Ukraine granted the S protection status. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Excluding asylum costs, ODA spending increased by CHF 242 million compared to 2022. The ODA/GNI ratio, excluding asylum costs, was 0.43% in 2023, compared to 0.40% in 2022. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Role of Swiss international cooperation&lt;/b&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Through its international cooperation, Switzerland helps to reduce poverty and promote peace and respect for human rights, respond to global challenges such as pandemics and climate change, and mitigate the causes of forced displacement and irregular migration. Switzerland also plays a role in establishing sustainable, environmentally-friendly development worldwide, with a focus on the sustainable management of natural resources.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Swiss international cooperation is primarily implemented by the Swiss Agency for Development and Cooperation (SDC) of the FDFA, the State Secretariat for Economic Affairs (SECO) of the EAER and the FDFA's Peace and Human Rights Division (PHRD), whose budgets covered almost two-thirds of ODA in 2023. In addition to international cooperation activities, expenditures incurred by other federal offices – including costs related to asylum – are also counted as ODA, as are contributions by Swiss cantons and communes. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Calculating ODA and cross-country comparison&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;ODA is calculated on the basis of guidelines issued by the Development Assistance Committee (DAC) of the Organisation for Economic Co-operation and Development (OECD). The relative contributions of the 31 donor countries that are members of the DAC is calculated based on the share of GNI that each of these countries spends on ODA. In the international ranking, Switzerland rises one place compared to 2022 and occupies the 8th position in 2023.&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>FDFA Communication Federal Palace West Wing CH-3003 Bern, Switzerland Tel. Press service: +41 58 460 55 55 E-mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @SwissMFA</contact>
      <link id="272868">
        <title>International aid rises in 2023 with increased support to Ukraine and humanitarian needs (en)</title>
        <uri>https://www.oecd.org/newsroom/international-aid-rises-in-2023-with-increased-support-to-ukraine-and-humanitarian-needs.htm</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="272872">
        <title>Swiss official development assistance</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/deza/en/home/sdc/portrait/figures-statistics/swiss-oda.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="272876">
        <title>Switzerland’s performance compared with other countries</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/deza/en/home/sdc/portrait/figures-statistics/ch-performance-compared.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
