<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="77315" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2019-12-02</pubdate>
    <blocking-period>2019-12-02</blocking-period>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="1089" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>701</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Innosuisse – Schweizerische Agentur für Innovationsförderung</name>
      <name lang="fr">Innosuisse – Agence suisse pour l’encouragement de l’innovation</name>
      <name lang="it">Innosuisse – Agenzia svizzera per la promozione dell’innovazione</name>
      <name lang="en">Innosuisse – Swiss Innovation Promotion Agency</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.innosuisse.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.innosuisse.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.innosuisse.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.innosuisse.ch</www>
      <email lang="de"/>
      <email lang="fr"/>
      <email lang="it"/>
      <email lang="en"/>
    </originator>
    <department id="701">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Wirtschaft, Bildung und Forschung</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'économie, de la formation et de la recherche</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'economia, della formazione e della ricerca</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Economic Affairs, Education and Research</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Innosuisse bestimmt neue Anbieter für Start-up Trainingsmodule 1 und 2</title>
      <lead>Innosuisse, die Schweizerische Agentur für Innovationsförderung, hat im Rahmen einer öffentlichen Ausschreibung die Anbieter für ihre ersten beiden Module des «Start-up Trainings» bestimmt: In der Region «West» werden die Kurse in den nächsten vier Jahren von der Fondation EPFL Innovation Parc angeboten, in der Region «Zentral» von der Universität Bern und in der Region «Ost» von der ZHAW School of Management and Law. </lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Im Rahmen der ausgeschriebenen Module 1 und 2 des Trainingsprogramms werden Motivationsveranstaltungen und Sensibilisierungsinitiativen (Module 1) sowie Kurse und zusätzliche Begleitmassnahmen (Modul 2) für Mitglieder und Alumni von Hochschulen und gründungsinteressierte Personen angeboten. Die Kurse sollen helfen, ein gründerfreundliches Klima in der Schweiz zu schaffen. Die Veranstaltungen werden über alle wissenschaftsbasierten Themenfelder hinweg gemeinsam durchgeführt. Sie starten im Januar 2020.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Die ebenfalls zum Trainingsprogramm von Innosuisse gehörenden Module 3 und 4 waren nicht Gegenstand der Ausschreibung. Sie wurden 2017 ausgeschrieben und an zwei Anbieter vergeben (Venturelab AG und ZHAW School of Management and Law).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Innosuisse hat den gesetzlichen Auftrag, das wissenschaftsbasierte Unternehmertum in der Schweiz zu fördern. Die Massnahmen im Bereich Sensibilisierungs- und Schulung, welche Innosuisse unter dem Namen «Innosuisse Start-up Training» anbietet, unterstützen Personen bei der Entwicklung einer innovativen, wissenschaftsbasierten Geschäftsidee, der Geschäftsgründung sowie dem Geschäftsaufbau. Das Trainingsprogramm besteht aus vier einzeln wählbaren Modulen.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mehr Infos auf www.innosuisse.ch/startuptraining&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Lukas Krienbühl und Eliane Kersten, Co-Leitung Kommunikation media@innosuisse.ch +41 58 481 84 73 / +41 58 464 19 95</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Innosuisse nomme de nouveaux prestataires pour les modules de formation 1 et 2 pour start-up</title>
      <lead>Innosuisse, l’Agence suisse pour l’encouragement de l’innovation, a sélectionné les prestataires pour ses deux premiers modules de «Start-up Training», dans le cadre d’un appel d’offres public. Dans la région «Ouest», les cours seront dispensés par la Fondation EPFL Innovation Parc ces quatre prochaines années, dans la région «Centre» ce sera l’Université de Berne et dans la région «Est» la ZHAW School of Management and Law. </lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Dans le cadre des modules 1 et 2 du programme de formation mis au concours, des manifestations de motivation et des initiatives de sensibilisation (module 1) ainsi que des cours et des mesures d’accompagnement supplémentaires (module 2) sont proposés aux membres et aux anciens étudiants des hautes écoles ainsi qu’aux personnes intéressées par la création d’une entreprise. L’objectif de ces cours est de contribuer à instaurer en Suisse un climat favorable à la création d’entreprises et à l’esprit entrepreneurial. Les manifestations rassemblent l’ensemble des domaines scientifiques. Elles débuteront en janvier 2020.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Les modules 3 et 4, qui font également partie du programme de formation d’Innosuisse, n’étaient pas inclus dans l’appel d’offres. Ils ont été mis au concours en 2017 et ont été attribués à deux prestataires, à savoir Venturelab SA et la ZHAW School of Management and Law.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Innosuisse a pour mandat légal d’encourager l’entrepreneuriat basé sur la science en Suisse. Les mesures de sensibilisation et de formation qu’offre Innosuisse sous le nom du programme «Innosuisse Start-up Training» visent à soutenir des personnes dans l’élaboration d’une idée commerciale innovante et basée sur la recherche académique, la création d’une entreprise et le développement des activités. Le programme de formation se compose de quatre modules pouvant être choisis individuellement.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Davantage d’informations sur www.innosuisse.ch/startuptraining&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Lukas Krienbühl et Eliane Kersten, co-responsables communication media@innosuisse.ch +41 58 481 84 73 / +41 58 464 19 95</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Innosuisse nomina nuovi fornitori per i moduli di formazione per start-up 1 e 2</title>
      <lead>Innosuisse, l’Agenzia svizzera per la promozione dell’innovazione, ha selezionato i fornitori per i suoi primi due moduli di «training per start-up» in una gara d’appalto: Nella regione «Ovest», i corsi saranno offerti dalla Fondation EPFL Innovation Parc nei prossimi quattro anni, nella regione «Centrale» dall’ Università di Berna e nella regione «Est» dalla ZHAW School of Management and Law. </lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Nell’ambito dei moduli 1 e 2 del programma di formazione, ai soci e agli alumni delle università e alle persone interessate a costituire una società vengono offerti eventi di motivazione e iniziative di sensibilizzazione (modulo 1), nonché corsi e misure di accompagnamento supplementari (modulo 2). I corsi intendono contribuire a creare in Svizzera un clima favorevole ai fondatori. Gli eventi si svolgono congiuntamente in tutte le aree tematiche scientifiche. Avranno inizio nel gennaio 2020.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I moduli 3 e 4, che facevano anch’essi parte del programma di formazione di Innosuisse, non sono stati inclusi nella gara d’appalto. Sono stati pubblicati nel 2017 e assegnati a due fornitori (Venturelab AG e ZHAW School of Management and Law).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Innosuisse ha il mandato legale di promuovere l’imprenditoria scientifica in Svizzera. Le misure di sensibilizzazione e di formazione che Innosuisse offre con il nome «Training Innosuisse per start-up» sostengono le persone nello sviluppo di un’idea imprenditoriale innovativa e fondata su basi scientifiche, nella creazione e a sviluppo di un’impresa. Il programma di formazione è composto da quattro moduli selezionabili individualmente.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Per saperne di più www.innosuisse.ch/startuptraining&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Lukas Krienbühl e Eliane Kersten, coresponsabili comunicazione media@innosuisse.ch +41 58 481 84 73 / +41 58 464 19 95</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Innosuisse selects new providers for start-up training modules 1 and 2</title>
      <lead>Innosuisse, the Swiss Innovation Agency, has selected the providers for the first two modules of its ‘start-up training’ as part of a public tender procedure. Over the next four years, the courses in the West region will be provided by the Fondation EPFL Innovation Park, in the Central region by the University of Berne and in the East region by the ZHAW School of Management and Law. </lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;As part of modules 1 and 2 of the training programme included in the tender procedure, motivational events, awareness-raising initiatives (module 1) as well as courses and additional support measures (module 2) will be provided for members and alumni of universities as well as anyone interested in setting up a company. The courses are intended to create an entrepreneurial mindset in Switzerland. The events will be carried out together across all science-based subject areas. They will start in January 2020. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Modules 3 and 4 – which are also part of Innosuisse’s training programme – were not included in the tender. They went out to tender in 2017 and were awarded to two providers (Venturelab AG and ZHAW School of Management and Law).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Innosuisse has the legal mandate to promote science-based entrepreneurship in Switzerland. The awareness-raising and training measures that Innosuisse offers under ‘Innosuisse Start-up Training’ support individuals in developing innovative, science-based business ideas and founding and setting up a business. The training programme consists of four individually selectable modules.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;More information can be found at www.innosuisse.ch/startuptraining&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Lukas Krienbühl and Eliane Kersten, co-heads communications media@innosuisse.ch +41 58 481 84 73 / +41 58 464 19 95</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="8">
        <name lang="de">Bildung und Forschung</name>
        <name lang="fr">Formation et recherche</name>
        <name lang="it">Formazione e ricerca</name>
        <name lang="en">Education and Research</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="45">
        <name lang="de">Technologie</name>
        <name lang="fr">Technologie</name>
        <name lang="it">Tecnologia</name>
        <name lang="en">Technology</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
