<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="51197" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2013-12-02</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="601" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>601</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Finanzdepartement</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des finances</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale delle finanze</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Finance</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.efd.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.dff.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.efd.admin.ch/efd/it/home.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.efd.admin.ch/efd/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="601">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Finanzdepartement</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des finances</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale delle finanze</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Finance</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.efd.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.dff.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.efd.admin.ch/efd/it/home.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.efd.admin.ch/efd/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Expertengruppe Brunetti nimmt Arbeit auf</title>
      <lead>Die vom Bundesrat eingesetzte Expertengruppe zur Weiterentwicklung der Finanzmarktstrategie hat ihre erste Sitzung abgehalten. An ihrem Treffen hat die Expertengruppe beschlossen, vier Untergruppen zu bilden, die gewisse Querschnittsthemen vertieft aufarbeiten sollen.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Am 4. September 2013 hat der Bundesrat beschlossen, zur Weiterentwicklung der Finanzmarktstrategie eine breit abgestützte Expertengruppe einzusetzen. Diese wird geleitet von Professor Aymo Brunetti. Neben den Behörden und der Wissenschaft ist auch die Privatwirtschaft vertreten.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Die Expertengruppe soll sich, losgelöst vom Tagesgeschäft und auf der Basis der bestehenden Grundlagen zur Finanzmarktpolitik, sowohl mit den Herausforderungen an den Finanzplatz im Inland als auch mit den Chancen für den Finanzplatz im Ausland befassen.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;An ihrer ersten Sitzung hat die Expertengruppe beschlossen, vier Untergruppen zu bilden. Diese werden die Themen Marktzutritt, volkswirtschaftliche Risiken, steuerliches Umfeld für Finanzgeschäfte sowie Regulierungsprozess und -umsetzung zuhanden der Expertengruppe aufarbeiten. Die Beratungen der Expertengruppe sind nicht öffentlich.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Roland Meier, Mediensprecher EFD +41 31 322 60 86, roland.meier@gs-efd.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Le groupe dʼexperts Brunetti commence son travail</title>
      <lead>Le groupe dʼexperts mis en place par le Conseil fédéral en vue de développer la stratégie en matière de marchés financiers s'est réuni pour la première fois. Lors de sa séance, le groupe dʼexperts a décidé de constituer quatre sous-groupes qui axeront leurs travaux sur des thèmes transversaux spécifiques.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Le 4 septembre 2013, le Conseil fédéral a décidé de mettre en place un groupe dʼexperts dont la tâche consistera à développer la stratégie suisse en matière de marchés financiers. Ce groupe, dirigé par le professeur Aymo Brunetti, est constitué de représentants des autorités, de personnes issues des milieux scientifiques et de lʼéconomie privée.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sans devoir subir la pression des affaires courantes, le groupe dʼexperts sera chargé, en partant de lʼactuelle politique en matière de marchés financiers, dʼexaminer non seulement les défis que la place financière doit relever au niveau national, mais aussi les opportunités qui sʼoffrent à notre pays au niveau international.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Lors de sa première séance, le groupe dʼexperts a décidé de constituer quatre sous-groupes. Leurs travaux, destinés au groupe dʼexperts, porteront sur lʼaccès aux marchés financiers, les risques pour lʼéconomie, la fiscalité des opérations du secteur financier et la réglementation de ce secteur (processus et mise en œuvre). Les discussions du groupe dʼexperts ne sont pas publiques.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Roland Meier, porte-parole du DFF, +41 31 322 60 86, roland.meier@gs-efd.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Il gruppo di esperti Brunetti inizia il proprio lavoro</title>
      <lead>Il gruppo di esperti istituito dal Consiglio federale per l’ulteriore sviluppo della strategia in materia di mercati finanziari ha tenuto la sua prima seduta. In occasione di questo incontro il gruppo di esperti ha deciso di costituire quattro sottogruppi che si occuperanno in modo approfondito di determinate tematiche trasversali.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Il 4 settembre 2013 il Consiglio federale ha deciso di istituire un gruppo di esperti allargato, cui ha affidato il mandato di analizzare l'ulteriore sviluppo della strategia in materia di mercati finanziari. Il gruppo di esperti è diretto dal professor Aymo Brunetti ed è composto da rappresentanti delle autorità, dell'economia privata e degli ambienti scientifici.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Indipendentemente dagli affari quotidiani e sulla base degli esistenti principi sulla politica dei mercati finanziari, il gruppo di esperti dovrà occuparsi sia delle sfide poste alla piazza finanziaria in Svizzera che delle opportunità della piazza finanziaria all'estero.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In occasione della sua prima seduta il gruppo di esperti ha deciso di costituire quattro sottogruppi, che si occuperanno dei seguenti temi all'attenzione del gruppo: accesso al mercato, rischi economici, quadro fiscale per gli affari finanziari nonché processo e attuazione della regolamentazione. I dibattimenti del gruppo di esperti non sono pubblici.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Roland Meier, portavoce del Dipartimento federale delle finanze (DFF), tel. +41 31 322 60 86, roland.meier@gs-efd.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Brunetti group of experts commences work</title>
      <lead>The group of experts appointed by the Federal Council for the further development of the financial market strategy has held its first meeting, during which it decided to form four sub-groups which are to carry out in-depth work on certain cross-cutting topics.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;On 4 September 2013, the Federal Council decided to appoint a broad-based group of experts for the further development of the financial market strategy. This group is led by Professor Aymo Brunetti and is comprised of representatives from the authorities and academia, as well as the private sector.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Isolated from daily business, the group of experts is to address the financial centre's challenges within Switzerland as well as its opportunities abroad based on the existing principles for financial market policy.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;During its first meeting, the group of experts decided to form four sub-groups. These will carry out work on the topics of market access, economic risks, the tax environment for financial transactions, the regulatory process and implementation of regulations for the attention of the group of experts. The group of experts' deliberations are not public.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Roland Meier, Media Spokesperson FDF +41 31 322 60 86, roland.meier@gs-efd.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <keywords>
      <keyword id="112" org-id="601">
        <name lang="de">Finanzaufsicht</name>
        <name lang="fr">Surveillance financière</name>
        <name lang="it">Vigilanza finanziaria</name>
        <name lang="en">Financial supervision</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="118" org-id="601">
        <name lang="de">Finanzmarktregulierung und -aufsicht</name>
        <name lang="fr">Réglementation et surveillance des marchés financiers</name>
        <name lang="it">Regolamentazione e vigilanza dei mercati finanziari</name>
        <name lang="en">Financial market regulation and supervision</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="126" org-id="601">
        <name lang="de">Finanzplatz Schweiz</name>
        <name lang="fr">Place financière suisse</name>
        <name lang="it">Piazza finanziaria svizzera</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland as a financial centre</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="113" org-id="601">
        <name lang="de">Finanzpolitik Diverses</name>
        <name lang="fr">Politique budgétaire: divers</name>
        <name lang="it">Politica finanziaria: diversi</name>
        <name lang="en">Fiscal Policy misc.</name>
      </keyword>
    </keywords>
    <topics>
      <topic id="35">
        <name lang="de">Finanzplatz</name>
        <name lang="fr">Place financière</name>
        <name lang="it">Piazza finanziaria</name>
        <name lang="en">Financial Centre</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
