<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="65263" revoked="no">
    <version>5</version>
    <pubdate>2017-01-15</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="201" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>201</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="201">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Pariser Konferenz: Die Schweiz setzt sich für die Eröffnung einer neuen politischen Perspektive im Nahen Osten ein</title>
      <lead>Bundesrat Didier Burkhalter rief am Sonntag, 15. Januar 2017 an der Pariser Ministerkonferenz über den Frieden im Nahen Osten Israelis und Palästinenser dazu auf, vertrauensbildende Massnahmen zu ergreifen und auf eine Zweistaatenlösung hinzuarbeiten. Für die Israelis «würde dies eine Einstellung der Siedlungstätigkeit im Westjordanland und in Ostjerusalem bedeuten», und die palästinensischen Machthaber «könnten durch eine konsequente Haltung gegen jede Aufforderung zur Gewalt neue Perspektiven eröffnen», erklärte der Vorsteher des Eidgenössischen Departements für auswärtige Angelegenheiten (EDA).</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Didier Burkhalter forderte die Israelis zudem auf, stärker auf die Wirtschaft zu setzen und den Güter- und Personenverkehr zwischen dem Gazastreifen, Israel und dem Westjordanland zu erhöhen. «Durch Massnahmen zur Eindämmung der Arbeitslosigkeit, die im Gazastreifen bei über 50% liegt, können neue Perspektiven geschaffen werden», erklärte Bundesrat Didier Burkhalter, der gleichzeitig an die Palästinenser appellierte, den demokratischen Weg und das Vertrauen in die Institutionen zu stärken: «Mit den palästinensischen Wahlen, zuerst lokalen und dann allgemeinen, soll nicht länger gewartet werden.»&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Der Vorsteher des EDA unterstrich zudem, dass die Entstehung neuer Perspektiven von einer interpalästinensischen Versöhnung und dem Engagement der Zivilgesellschaft abhängt. «Die Schweiz begrüsst die Einrichtung eines Forums der Zivilgesellschaft (...), das es verschiedenen NGO, darunter auch der Genfer Initiative, ermöglicht, sich konkret für die Versöhnung zwischen der israelischen und der palästinensischen Bevölkerung einzusetzen», sagte Didier Burkhalter, der ebenfalls eine regionale Zusammenarbeit im Nahen und Mittleren Osten befürwortet.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Die Schweiz setzt sich in dieser Weltregion für einen auf dem Verhandlungsweg erzielten, gerechten und dauerhaften Frieden zwischen Israelis und Palästinensern auf der Basis einer Zweistaatenlösung ein. Sie wird eine Änderung der Grenzen von 1967, einschliesslich Jerusalem, nicht anerkennen, es sei denn, diese ist das Ergebnis eines zwischen den Parteien ausgehandelten Abkommens. Schliesslich fordert die Schweiz die Parteien auf, das humanitäre Völkerrecht einzuhalten.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Kommunikation EDA Bundeshaus West CH-3003 Bern Tel. Kommunikationsservice: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Medienstelle: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <link id="162745">
        <title>Statement von Bundesrat Didier Burkhalter anlässlich der Pariser Ministerkonferenz über den Frieden im Nahen Osten</title>
        <uri>https://www.admin.ch/gov/de/start/dokumentation/medienmitteilungen.msg-id-65259.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions>
        <revision date="2017-01-16 16:03" type="R"/>
      </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Conférence de Paris : la Suisse s’engage pour la réouverture d’une perspective politique au Proche-Orient</title>
      <lead>Le 15 janvier 2017, Le conseiller fédéral Didier Burkhalter a appelé, dimanche à la Conférence ministérielle de Paris sur la paix au Proche-Orient, Israéliens et Palestiniens à prendre des mesures pour renforcer la confiance et promouvoir la solution des deux Etats. Pour les Israéliens, « il s’agirait de ne pas poursuivre la colonisation en Cisjordanie et à Jérusalem-Est » alors que les dirigeants palestiniens « pourraient rouvrir des perspectives par une prise de position ferme contre toute incitation à la violence », a indiqué le chef du Département fédéral des affaires étrangères (DFAE).</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Didier Burkhalter a également invité les Israéliens à jouer davantage la carte économique, à accroître le flux de biens et de personnes entre Gaza, Israël et la Cisjordanie. « C’est en combattant le chômage qui atteint 50% de personnes à Gaza que l’on reconstruit des perspectives », a estimé le conseiller fédéral qui a par ailleurs appelé les Palestiniens à renforcer l’espace démocratique et la confiance dans les institutions : «il ne faut plus attendre pour tenir des élections palestiniennes, locales puis générales ».&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Le chef du DFAE a également souligné que la naissance de nouvelles perspectives passait par une réconciliation inter palestinienne et par l’engagement de la société civile. « La Suisse salue l’établissement d’un Forum sur la société civile (…) et dans ce cadre, diverses ONG, et notamment l’Initiative de Genève, pourront agir concrètement pour la réconciliation entre les sociétés israélienne et palestinienne », a estimé M. Burkhalter qui prône également la coopération régionale au Proche et au Moyen Orient.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;La Suisse s’engage dans la région pour une paix juste et durable entre Israéliens et Palestiniens reposant sur une solution négociée à deux Etats. Elle ne reconnaîtra pas un changement aux frontières de 1967, y compris concernant Jérusalem, à moins qu’il ne résulte d’un accord négocié entre les parties. Enfin, la Suisse enjoint les parties à respecter le Droit humanitaire international. &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Communication DFAE Palais fédéral ouest CH-3003 Berne Tél. Service de communication: +41 58 462 31 53 Tél. Service de presse: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <link id="162746">
        <title>Déclaration du conseiller fédéral Didier Burkhalter à l’occasion de la Conférence ministérielle de Paris sur la paix au Proche-Orient</title>
        <uri>https://www.admin.ch/gov/fr/accueil/documentation/communiques.msg-id-65259.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Conferenza di Parigi: la Svizzera si impegna per la riapertura di una prospettiva politica in Medio Oriente</title>
      <lead>In occasione della Conferenza ministeriale di Parigi sulla pace in Medio Oriente, il 15 gennaio 2017 il consigliere federale Didier Burkhalter ha esortato Israeliani e Palestinesi a prendere le misure necessarie per rafforzare la fiducia reciproca e promuovere la soluzione dei due Stati. Per gli Israeliani «si tratterebbe di non portare avanti la colonizzazione in Cisgiordania e a Gerusalemme Est», mentre i dirigenti palestinesi «potrebbero contribuire a creare nuove prospettive prendendo fermamente posizione contro ogni incitamento alla violenza», ha detto il capo del Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri (DFAE).</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Didier Burkhalter ha invitato inoltre gli Israeliani a giocare più spesso la carta economica e a incrementare il flusso di beni e di persone tra Gaza, Israele e la Cisgiordania. «È solo combattendo la disoccupazione, che nella striscia di Gaza colpisce il 50% delle persone, che si possono offrire nuove prospettive», ha dichiarato il consigliere federale, che ha anche incoraggiato i Palestinesi a rafforzare la democrazia e la fiducia nelle istituzioni, affermando che «non si può più rimandare l’organizzazione di elezioni, locali e generali».&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Il capo del DFAE ha poi sottolineato l’importanza, in questo ambito, di una riconciliazione interpalestinese e del coinvolgimento della società civile. «La Svizzera approva l’istituzione di un forum sulla società civile (…) nel cui quadro varie ONG, in particolare l’Iniziativa di Ginevra, potranno impegnarsi concretamente per la riconciliazione tra la società israeliana e quella palestinese», ha affermato Didier Burkhalter, che raccomanda anche maggiore cooperazione nella regione.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;In quest’area del mondo, la Svizzera si adopera affinché si giunga a una pace duratura tra Israeliani e Palestinesi basata su una soluzione negoziata a due Stati. Non riconoscerà alcun cambiamento dei confini del 1967, inclusi eventuali cambiamenti relativi a Gerusalemme, a meno che non derivi da un accordo tra le parti. La Svizzera chiede infine che entrambe le parti rispettino il diritto internazionale umanitario. &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Comunicazione DFAE Palazzo federale ovest CH-3003 Berna Tel. Servizio di comunicazione: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Servizio stampa: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <link id="162747">
        <title>Dichiarazione del Consigliere federale Didier Burkhalter in occasione della Conferenza ministeriale di Parigi sulla pace in Medio Oriente</title>
        <uri>https://www.admin.ch/gov/it/pagina-iniziale/documentazione/comunicati-stampa.msg-id-65259.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions>
        <revision date="2017-01-16 16:03" type="R"/>
      </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Paris Conference: Switzerland committed to renewed prospects for a political solution in the Middle East</title>
      <lead>On Sunday, 15 January 2017 at the Paris Ministerial Conference for Peace in the Middle East, Federal Councillor Didier Burkhalter called on the Israelis and Palestinians to take steps to build confidence and advance the two-state solution. For the Israelis “this means not pursuing a policy of settlements on the West Bank and in East Jerusalem,” while the Palestinian leaders “could re-open the prospect of peace by taking a firm stand against all incitements to violence,” said the head of the Federal Department of Foreign Affairs (FDFA).</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Mr Burkhalter also called on the Israelis to play the economic card more strongly and to allow a greater flow of people and goods between Gaza, Israel and the West Bank. He maintained that “it is by fighting unemployment, which has reached 50% in Gaza, that we can rebuild prospects”. He also called on the Palestinians to strengthen democratic processes and confidence in their institutions: “Palestinians must not wait longer to hold both local and general elections.”&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Mr Burkhalter also emphasised that new prospects would be created through inter-Palestinian reconciliation and the involvement of civil society, adding that “Switzerland welcomes the establishment of a civil society forum (…) within which various NGOs, in particular the Geneva Initiative, will be able to take concrete steps towards reconciliation between Israeli and Palestinian society.” Mr Burkhalter also promotes regional cooperation in the Middle East.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Switzerland is working in the region to promote a just and lasting peace between Israelis and Palestinians based on a negotiated two-state solution. It will not recognise changes to the 1967 borders, including with regard to Jerusalem, unless it is the result of a negotiated agreement between the two parties. Lastly, Switzerland urges the parties to respect international humanitarian law.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>FDFA Communication Federal Palace West Wing CH-3003 Bern, Switzerland Tel. Communication service: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Press service: +41 58 460 55 55 E-mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @SwissMFA</contact>
      <link id="162748">
        <title>Statement by the Federal Councillor Didier Burkhalter on the occasion of the Paris Ministerial Conference on Peace in the Middle East – Check against delivery</title>
        <uri>https://www.admin.ch/gov/en/start/documentation/media-releases.msg-id-65259.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions>
        <revision date="2017-01-16 16:03" type="R"/>
      </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
