<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="65528" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2017-02-06</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="1080" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>701</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Staatssekretariat für Bildung, Forschung und Innovation</name>
      <name lang="fr">Secrétariat d'Etat à la formation, à la recherche et à l'innovation</name>
      <name lang="it">Segreteria di Stato per la formazione, la ricerca e l'innovazione</name>
      <name lang="en">State Secretariat for Education, Research and Innovation</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.sbfi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.sbfi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.sbfi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.sbfi.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@sbfi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@sbfi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@sbfi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@sbfi.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="701">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Wirtschaft, Bildung und Forschung</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'économie, de la formation et de la recherche</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'economia, della formazione e della ricerca</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Economic Affairs, Education and Research</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Staatssekretär Dell’Ambrogio auf Einladung des Premierministers Vučić zu Besuch in Serbien</title>
      <lead>Der Staatssekretär für Bildung, Forschung und Innovation Mauro Dell’Ambrogio wurde vom serbischen Premierminister Aleksandar Vučić zu einem offiziellen Besuch nach Belgrad eingeladen. Gemeinsam mit dem Premierminister soll der Staatssekretär dabei offiziell das Projekt «From Education to Employement» lancieren, das von der Direktion für Entwicklung und Zusammenarbeit (DEZA) geleitet wird. Der Staatssekretär wird zudem zwei Vorträge halten, einen vor der serbischen Industrie- und Handelskammer, den anderen an der Universität Belgrad.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Die Berufsbildung steht im Zentrum der Diskussionen mit dem Premierminister Vučić. Dieser wird von einer Delegation aus mehreren Ministern begleitet, darunter der Minister für Bildung, Wissenschaft und Technologie Mladen Šarčević. Staatssekretär Dell’Ambrogio soll im Rahmen einer von der serbischen Industrie- und Handelskammer organisierten öffentlichen Konferenz das schweizerische Berufsbildungssystem vorstellen.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Anlässlich des Besuchs von Staatssekretär Dell’Ambrogio wird ausserdem das Projekt «From Education to Employment (E2E)» offiziell gestartet. Das von der DEZA unterstützte Projekt zielt darauf ab, das Berufsbildungsangebot im Süden und Südwesten Serbiens auszubauen und damit die Rahmenbedingungen für die Beschäftigung zu verbessern. Das Projekt E2E dürfte rund 40'000 jungen Serbinnen und Serben zugutekommen. Staatssekretär Dell’Ambrogio wird sich mit mehreren Partnern des Projekts treffen, das in enger Zusammenarbeit mit verschiedenen Akteuren des öffentlichen und privaten Sektors Serbiens und der Schweiz umgesetzt wird.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Der Besuch ist zudem eine Gelegenheit, die ausgezeichnete Zusammenarbeit zwischen den beiden Ländern im Forschungsbereich hervorzuheben: Zahlreiche schweizerische und serbische Forschende arbeiten insbesondere innerhalb der EU-Forschungsrahmenprogramme zusammen. Vor diesem Hintergrund soll der Staatssekretär Dell’Ambrogio an der Universität Belgrad einen Vortrag halten und den Wissenschafts- und Technologiepark der Stadt besuchen, der rund 36 Unternehmen, darunter auch zwei Schweizer Start-ups, beherbergt. Der Park wurde 2015 im Beisein von Bundesrat Johann Schneider-Ammann eröffnet und hat sich als erste solche Einrichtung in Serbien zu einem unverzichtbaren Akteur im Innovationsbereich entwickelt.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Die Schweiz und Serbien&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Rund 1800 Schweizerinnen und Schweizer leben in Serbien, etwa 69'000 serbische Staatsangehörige in der Schweiz. In Serbien sind rund 200 Schweizer Unternehmen tätig. Die schweizerischen Direktinvestitionen in Serbien generieren etwa 3800 Arbeitsstellen und machen die Schweiz damit zu einem der wichtigsten ausländischen Investoren. Seit 2006 wurden rund 50 Bundes-Exzellenz-Stipendien an junge serbische Forscherinnen und Forscher vergeben.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Anouk De Bast Staatssekretariat für Bildung, Forschung und Innovation Abteilung internationale Beziehungen Tel. +41 58 463 31 76 anouk.de-bast@sbfi.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Le Secrétaire d’Etat Dell’Ambrogio en Serbie sur invitation du Premier ministre Vučić</title>
      <lead>Le Secrétaire d’Etat à la formation, à la recherche et à l’innovation Mauro Dell’Ambrogio est en visite officielle à Belgrade sur invitation du Premier ministre serbe Aleksandar Vučić. En compagnie du Premier ministre, le Secrétaire d’Etat lancera officiellement le projet «From Education to Employement», conduit par la Direction du développement et de la coopération (DDC). Le Secrétaire d’Etat donnera également deux conférences, respectivement à la Chambre du commerce et de l’industrie serbe et à l’Université de Belgrade.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;La formation professionnelle sera au cœur des discussions avec le Premier ministre Vučić, qui sera accompagné d’une délégation comprenant plusieurs ministres, dont le Ministre de l’Education de la Science et de la Technologie, Mladen Šarčević. Le Secrétaire d’Etat Dell’Ambrogio présentera le système de formation professionnelle suisse dans le cadre d’une conférence publique organisée par la Chambre du commerce et de l’industrie serbe.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;La visite du Secrétaire d’Etat Dell’Ambrogio sera l’occasion du lancement officiel du projet «From Education to Employment (E2E)». Soutenu par la DDC, ce projet vise à améliorer les conditions-cadre de l’emploi en augmentant l’offre en termes de formation professionnelle dans le sud et le sud-ouest de la Serbie. Environ 40'000 jeunes Serbes pourraient bénéficier du projet E2E. Le Secrétaire d’Etat Dell’Ambrogio rencontrera plusieurs partenaires du projet, qui est mis en œuvre en étroite collaboration avec différents acteurs des secteurs publics et privés serbes et suisses.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Par ailleurs, la visite permettra également de souligner l’excellente collaboration entre les deux pays dans le domaine de la recherche: de nombreux chercheurs suisses et serbes coopèrent notamment dans le cadre des programmes-cadres de l’Union européenne. Dans cette optique, le Secrétaire d’Etat Dell’Ambrogio prononcera une conférence à l’Université de Belgrade et visitera le Parc scientifique et technologique de la ville, qui accueille 36 entreprises dont 2 start-ups suisses. Inauguré en 2015 par le conseiller fédéral Johann Schneider-Ammann, ce technopark est la première institution de ce type en Serbie et est devenu un acteur incontournable dans l’écosystème d’innovation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;La Suisse et la Serbie&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Environ 1800 Suisses vivent en Serbie, et quelque 69'000 personnes de nationalité serbe vivent en Suisse. Près de 200 entreprises suisses sont actives en Serbie. Les investissements directs suisses en Serbie génèrent quelque 3800 postes de travail et placent la Suisse parmi les principaux investisseurs directs étrangers. Depuis 2006, une cinquantaine de jeunes chercheurs serbes ont bénéficié des bourses d’excellence de la Confédération.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Anouk De Bast Secrétariat d’Etat à la formation, à la recherche et à l’innovation Division Relations internationales T +41 58 463 31 76 anouk.de-bast@sbfi.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Visita in Serbia del Segretario di Stato Dell’Ambrogio su invito del Primo ministro Vučić</title>
      <lead>Il Segretario di Stato per la formazione, la ricerca e l'innovazione Mauro Dell’Ambrogio si trova in visita ufficiale a Belgrado su invito del Primo ministro serbo Aleksandar Vučić, insieme al quale lancerà ufficialmente il progetto «From Education to Employement», sotto l’egida della Direzione dello sviluppo e della cooperazione (DSC). Il Segretario di Stato, inoltre, terrà due conferenze, alla Camera di commercio e dell’industria serba e all’Università di Belgrado.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;La formazione professionale sarà al centro dei colloqui con il primo ministro Vučić e con una delegazione di numerosi ministri, tra cui il ministro dell’educazione, della scienza e della tecnologia Mladen Šarčević. Il Segretario di Stato Dell’Ambrogio presenterà il sistema della formazione professionale svizzera durante una conferenza pubblica organizzata dalla Camera di commercio e dell’industria serba.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In occasione della visita del Segretario di Stato Dell’Ambrogio verrà lanciato ufficialmente il progetto «From Education to Employment (E2E)». Con il sostegno della DSC, questo progetto si prefigge di migliorare le condizioni quadro per l’occupazione e di potenziare la formazione professionale nell’area meridionale e sud-occidentale della Serbia. Circa 40'000 giovani serbi potrebbero fruire del progetto E2E. Il Segretario di Stato Dell’Ambrogio incontrerà numerosi partner del progetto, attuato in stretta collaborazione con diversi operatori pubblici e privati, serbi e svizzeri.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;La visita, inoltre, permetterà di ribadire l’ottima collaborazione tra i due Paesi nel campo della ricerca: numerosi ricercatori svizzeri e serbi, infatti, cooperano nell’ambito dei programmi quadro dell’Unione europea. È in quest’ottica che il Segretario di Stato Dell’Ambrogio terrà una conferenza all’Università di Belgrado e visiterà il Parco scientifico e tecnologico della città che accoglie 36 aziende, tra cui 2 startup svizzere. Inaugurato nel 2015 dal consigliere federale Johann Schneider-Ammann, si tratta del primo technopark in Serbia, diventato nel frattempo il centro nevralgico dell’ecosistema per l’innovazione.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;La Svizzera e la Serbia&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In Serbia vivono circa 1800 cittadini svizzeri, mentre le persone di nazionalità serba in Svizzera sono all’incirca 69'000. In Serbia sono attive quasi 200 aziende svizzere. Gli investimenti diretti svizzeri in Serbia generano circa 3800 posti di lavoro, sicché la Svizzera svetta tra i principali investitori diretti stranieri. Dal 2006, una cinquantina di giovani ricercatori svizzeri ha beneficiato delle borse d’eccellenza della Confederazione.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Anouk De Bast Segreteria di Stato per la formazione, la ricerca e l'innovazione SEFRI Divisione Relazioni internazionali Tel. +41 58 463 31 76 anouk.de-bast@sbfi.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>State Secretary Dell’Ambrogio in Serbia at the invitation of Prime Minister Vučić</title>
      <lead>The State Secretary for Education, Research and Innovation, Mauro Dell’Ambrogio, is on an official visit to Belgrade at the invitation of Serbian Prime Minister Aleksandar Vučić. Together with the prime minister, the state secretary will officially launch the ‘From Education to Employment’ project, led by the Swiss Agency for Development and Cooperation (SDC). The state secretary will also give a talk at the Serbian Chamber of Commerce and Industry and at the University of Belgrade.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Vocational and education and training (VET) will be at the centre of discussions with Mr Vučić, which will also be attended by a number of ministers, including the Minister of Education, Science and Technological Development, Mladen Šarčević. Mr Dell’Ambrogio will present Switzerland’s system of vocational education and training at a public conference organised by the Serbian Chamber of Commerce and Industry.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;During his visit, Mr Dell’Ambrogio will participate in the official launch of the ‘From Education to Employment (E2E)’ project. The project, supported by the SDC, aims to improve the framework conditions for employment by offering more VET programmes in the south and south-west of Serbia. Around 40,000 young Serbs could benefit from the E2E project. Mr Dell’Ambrogio will meet with several partners in the project, which will be implemented in close collaboration with various stakeholders from the Serbian and Swiss public and private sectors.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The visit will also highlight the excellent collaboration between the two countries in the field of research: many Swiss and Serbian researchers are cooperating in particular in the European Union’s Framework Programmes. With this cooperation in mind, Mr Dell’Ambrogio will give a talk at the University of Belgrade, and will visit the city’s Science and Technology Park, which is home to 36 companies, including two Swiss start-ups. The technopark was inaugurated by Federal Councillor Johann Schneider-Ammann in 2015. It is the first institution of its kind in Serbia and has become a major player in the innovation ecosystem.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Switzerland and Serbia&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Around 1,800 Swiss nationals live in Serbia, and some 69,000 Serbian nationals live in Switzerland. Nearly 200 Swiss companies are active in Serbia. Swiss direct investments in Serbia have created around 3,800 jobs, making Switzerland one of the largest foreign direct investors. Since 2006, around fifty young Serbian researchers have benefitted from the Swiss Government Excellence Scholarship.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Anouk De Bast State Secretariat for Education, Research and Innovation International Relations Division Tel. +41 58 463 31 76 anouk.de-bast@sbfi.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <keywords>
      <keyword id="325.6" org-id="1080">
        <name lang="de">Bildungsprogramme</name>
        <name lang="fr">Programmes d'éducation</name>
        <name lang="it">Programmi di educazione</name>
        <name lang="en">Educational programmes</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="325.11" org-id="1080">
        <name lang="de">Eidgenössische Technische Hochschule ETH</name>
        <name lang="fr">Ecole polytechnique fédérale EPF</name>
        <name lang="it">Politecnico federale</name>
        <name lang="en">Federal Institutes of Technology</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="325.9" org-id="1080">
        <name lang="de">Forschungsrahmenprogramme</name>
        <name lang="fr">Programmes-cadre de recherche</name>
        <name lang="it">Programmi quadro di ricerca</name>
        <name lang="en">Research framework programmes</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="325.8" org-id="1080">
        <name lang="de">Technologie</name>
        <name lang="fr">Technologie</name>
        <name lang="it">Tecnologia</name>
        <name lang="en">Technology</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="325.1" org-id="1080">
        <name lang="de">Universitäten</name>
        <name lang="fr">Universités</name>
        <name lang="it">Università</name>
        <name lang="en">Universities</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="325.10" org-id="1080">
        <name lang="de">Wissenschaft</name>
        <name lang="fr">Science</name>
        <name lang="it">Scienza</name>
        <name lang="en">Science</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="325.21" org-id="1080">
        <name lang="de">Wissenschaftsaussenpolitik</name>
        <name lang="fr">Politique scientifique extérieure</name>
        <name lang="it">Politica scientifica dell'esterno</name>
        <name lang="en">Foreign scientific policy</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="325.30" org-id="1080">
        <name lang="de">Bildung</name>
        <name lang="fr">Education</name>
        <name lang="it">Educazione</name>
        <name lang="en">Education</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="325.31" org-id="1080">
        <name lang="de">Berufsbildung</name>
        <name lang="fr">Formation professionnelle</name>
        <name lang="it">Formazione professionale</name>
        <name lang="en">Vocational and Professional Education and Training</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="325.32" org-id="1080">
        <name lang="de">Berufliche Grundbildung</name>
        <name lang="fr">Formation professionnelle initiale</name>
        <name lang="it">Formazione professionale di base</name>
        <name lang="en">Vocational Education and Training</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="325.34" org-id="1080">
        <name lang="de">Berufsmaturität</name>
        <name lang="fr">Maturité professionnelle</name>
        <name lang="it">Maturità professionale</name>
        <name lang="en">Vocational Baccalaureate</name>
      </keyword>
    </keywords>
    <topics>
      <topic id="8">
        <name lang="de">Bildung und Forschung</name>
        <name lang="fr">Formation et recherche</name>
        <name lang="it">Formazione e ricerca</name>
        <name lang="en">Education and Research</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="45">
        <name lang="de">Technologie</name>
        <name lang="fr">Technologie</name>
        <name lang="it">Tecnologia</name>
        <name lang="en">Technology</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
