<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="65753" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2017-02-22</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="1070" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>1070</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Der Bundesrat</name>
      <name lang="fr">Conseil fédéral</name>
      <name lang="it">Il Consiglio federale</name>
      <name lang="en">The Federal Council</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.admin.ch/gov/de/start.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.admin.ch/gov/fr/accueil.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.admin.ch/gov/it/pagina-iniziale.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.admin.ch/gov/en/start.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="yes" id="602" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>601</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Generalsekretariat EFD</name>
      <name lang="fr">Secrétariat général DFF</name>
      <name lang="it">Segreteria generale DFF</name>
      <name lang="en">Secretariat-General FDF</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.efd.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.efd.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.efd.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.efd.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="yes" id="605" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>601</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössische Steuerverwaltung</name>
      <name lang="fr">Administration fédérale des contributions</name>
      <name lang="it">Amministrazione federale delle contribuzioni</name>
      <name lang="en">The Federal Tax Administration</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.estv.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.estv.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.estv.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.estv.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de"/>
      <email lang="fr"/>
      <email lang="it"/>
      <email lang="en"/>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="yes" id="1060" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>601</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Staatssekretariat für internationale Finanzfragen</name>
      <name lang="fr">Secrétariat d'Etat aux questions financières internationales</name>
      <name lang="it">Segreteria di Stato per le questioni finanziarie internazionali</name>
      <name lang="en">State Secretariat for International Financial Matters</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.sif.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.sif.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.sif.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.sif.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@sif.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@sif.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@sif.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@sif.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="1070">
      <name lang="de">Der Bundesrat</name>
      <name lang="fr">Conseil fédéral</name>
      <name lang="it">Il Consiglio federale</name>
      <name lang="en">The Federal Council</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.admin.ch/gov/de/start.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.admin.ch/gov/fr/accueil.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.admin.ch/gov/it/pagina-iniziale.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.admin.ch/gov/en/start.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <department id="601">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Finanzdepartement</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des finances</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale delle finanze</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Finance</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.efd.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.dff.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.efd.admin.ch/efd/it/home.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.efd.admin.ch/efd/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Bundesrat will rasch eine neue Steuervorlage erarbeiten</title>
      <lead>Der Bundesrat hat an seiner Sitzung vom 22. Februar 2017 das Eidgenössische Finanzdepartement (EFD) beauftragt, die inhaltlichen Eckwerte für eine neue Steuervorlage im Nachgang zur Abstimmung über die Unternehmenssteuerreform bis spätestens Mitte 2017 auszuarbeiten. Ziel bleibt die Stärkung der Wettbewerbsfähigkeit der Schweiz. </lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Der Bundesrat stellt fest, dass sich nach der Ablehnung der Unternehmenssteuerreform III in der Volksabstimmung vom 12. Februar 2017 Gegner und Befürworter im Grundsatz einig sind, rasch eine neue Vorlage auszuarbeiten. Das Ziel bleibt weiterhin, die Wettbewerbsfähigkeit des Schweizer Steuersystems zu stärken und die Steuereinnahmen von Bund, Kantonen und Gemeinden zu sichern. Die steuerlichen Sonderregeln zu den Statusgesellschaften sollen abgeschafft werden, wie das die Schweiz international in Aussicht gestellt hat. Der Bundesrat hat das EFD beauftragt, im Laufe des zweiten Quartals 2017 inhaltliche Eckwerte für eine neue Vorlage und Vorschläge für das weitere Vorgehen zu unterbreiten.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Diese Eckwerte sollen nach Gesprächen mit den politischen Parteien sowie in Zusammenarbeit mit den Kantonen und unter Einbezug der Städte und Gemeinden erarbeitet werden. Angehört werden zudem die Dachverbände der Wirtschaft und der Arbeitnehmerschaft.&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Roland Meier, Mediensprecher EFD Tel. +41 58 462 60 86, roland.meier@gs-efd.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Le Conseil fédéral entend préparer rapidement un nouveau projet fiscal</title>
      <lead>Lors de sa séance du 22 février 2017, le Conseil fédéral a chargé le Département fédéral des finances (DFF) de définir, à la suite de la votation sur la réforme de l'imposition des entreprises, les lignes directrices d'un nouveau projet fiscal d'ici à l'été 2017. Le but de ce projet restera de renforcer la compétitivité de la Suisse. </lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Après le rejet de la troisième réforme de l'imposition des entreprises lors de la votation populaire du 12 février 2017, le Conseil fédéral a constaté que les partisans comme les adversaires de la réforme estiment qu'il faut concevoir rapidement un nouveau projet. Le but restera de renforcer la compétitivité du système d'imposition suisse tout en garantissant les recettes fiscales de la Confédération, des cantons et des communes. Les statuts spéciaux dont bénéficient certaines sociétés devront être supprimés, comme l'avait annoncé la Suisse à la communauté internationale. Le Conseil fédéral a donc chargé le DFF de lui soumettre, dans le courant du deuxième trimestre 2017, les lignes directrices d'un nouveau projet et des propositions sur les prochaines étapes.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Les lignes directrices du projet seront définies après discussion avec les partis politiques, en collaboration avec les cantons et avec la participation tant des villes que des communes. Les associations faîtières de l'économie et des employés seront également consultées. &lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Roland Meier, porte-parole du DFF Tél. +41 58 462 60 86, roland.meier@gs-efd.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Il Consiglio federale vuole elaborare rapidamente un nuovo progetto fiscale</title>
      <lead>Nella sua seduta del 22 febbraio 2017 il Consiglio federale ha incaricato il Dipartimento federale delle finanze (DFF) di elaborare, entro la metà del 2017, i parametri sostanziali per un nuovo progetto fiscale a seguito della votazione sulla riforma dell’imposizione delle imprese. L’obiettivo rimane rafforzare la competitività della Svizzera.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Il Consiglio federale constata che dopo il rifiuto della Riforma III dell’imposizione delle imprese in occasione della votazione popolare del 12 febbraio 2017, oppositori e sostenitori della riforma sono in linea di principio concordi sulla necessità di elaborare rapidamente un nuovo progetto. L’obiettivo rimane rafforzare la competitività del sistema fiscale svizzero e garantire le entrate fiscali di Confederazione, Cantoni e Comuni. Le norme fiscali in vigore per le società con statuto speciale devono essere abolite, come prospettato dalla Svizzera a livello internazionale. Il Consiglio federale ha incaricato il DFF di presentare, nel corso del secondo trimestre del 2017, i parametri sostanziali per un nuovo progetto e delle proposte per il prosieguo dei lavori.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;I parametri devono essere elaborati previa consultazione dei partiti politici, in collaborazione con i Cantoni e con il coinvolgimento delle città e dei Comuni. Saranno inoltre interpellati le associazioni mantello dell’economia e i rappresentanti dei lavoratori.&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Roland Meier, portavoce DFF tel. +41 58 462 60 86, roland.meier@gs-efd.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Federal Council wants to swiftly draw up a new tax proposal</title>
      <lead>During its meeting on 22 February 2017, the Federal Council instructed the Federal Department of Finance (FDF) to draw up the substantive parameters for a new tax proposal by mid-2017 at the latest following the vote on corporate tax reforms. The objective remains that of strengthening Switzerland's competitiveness.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;The Federal Council noted that, following the rejection of the third series of corporate tax reforms in the referendum on 12 February 2017, opponents and proponents were generally in agreement that a new tax proposal should be drawn up swiftly. The objective remains that of strengthening Switzerland's competitiveness and safeguarding the tax receipts of the Confederation, cantons and communes. The special tax arrangements for status companies should be abolished, as Switzerland undertook to do internationally. The Federal Council has instructed the FDF to submit substantive parameters during the second quarter of 2017 for a new proposal and suggestions on how to proceed. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;These parameters are to be drawn up following talks with the political parties and in collaboration with the cantons, including the cities and communes. In addition, the business and workforce umbrella associations will be consulted. &lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Roland Meier, Media Spokesperson FDF Tel. +41 58 462 60 86, roland.meier@gs-efd.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <offers>
      <offer id="291" org-id="1060">
        <name lang="de">Wirtschaft, Währung, Finanzplatz</name>
        <name lang="fr">Economie, monnaie, place financière</name>
        <name lang="it">Economia, Moneta, Piazza finanziaria</name>
        <name lang="en">Economic, Monetary and Financial Affairs</name>
      </offer>
    </offers>
    <keywords>
      <keyword id="231" org-id="1060">
        <name lang="de">Steuerwettbewerb</name>
        <name lang="fr">Compétition fiscale</name>
        <name lang="it">Concorrenza fiscale</name>
        <name lang="en">Tax competition</name>
      </keyword>
    </keywords>
    <topics>
      <topic id="35">
        <name lang="de">Finanzplatz</name>
        <name lang="fr">Place financière</name>
        <name lang="it">Piazza finanziaria</name>
        <name lang="en">Financial Centre</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="44">
        <name lang="de">Steuern</name>
        <name lang="fr">Impôts</name>
        <name lang="it">Imposte</name>
        <name lang="en">Taxation</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="47">
        <name lang="de">Wirtschaft</name>
        <name lang="fr">Économie</name>
        <name lang="it">Economia</name>
        <name lang="en">Economic Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
