<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="66144" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2017-03-27</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="yes" id="602" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>601</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Generalsekretariat EFD</name>
      <name lang="fr">Secrétariat général DFF</name>
      <name lang="it">Segreteria generale DFF</name>
      <name lang="en">Secretariat-General FDF</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.efd.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.efd.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.efd.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.efd.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="601">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Finanzdepartement</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des finances</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale delle finanze</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Finance</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.efd.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.dff.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.efd.admin.ch/efd/it/home.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.efd.admin.ch/efd/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Arbeitsbesuch von Bundesrat Ueli Maurer beim polnischen Finanzminister Mateusz Morawiecki</title>
      <lead>Bundesrat Ueli Maurer weilt am 27. März 2017 zu einem Arbeitsbesuch bei seinem polnischen Amtskollegen Mateusz Morawiecki. Erörtert werden beim Treffen finanz- und wirtschaftspolitische Fragen sowie die Zusammenarbeit in den internationalen Finanzinstitutionen. </lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Die beiden Minister werden über die globalen wirtschaftlichen Aussichten sowie über die Entwicklungen in Europa beraten. Zur Sprache kommen wird auch die langjährige Zusammenarbeit der beiden Länder in den internationalen Finanzinstitutionen und insbesondere in der Stimmrechtsgruppe in den Bretton-Woods-Institutionen (Weltbank und Internationaler Währungsfonds).&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Polen ist ein bedeutender Partner der Schweiz in der gemeinsamen Stimmrechtsgruppe. Seit 2014 gilt zwischen den beiden Ländern die wechselweise Besetzung der Position des Exekutivdirektors im IWF. Polen nimmt seit November 2016 erstmals für zwei Jahre diese Position ein; die Schweiz verbleibt während dieser Zeit mit einem stellvertretenden Exekutivdirektor im Exekutivrat des IWF vertreten. Ab 2018 übernimmt die Schweiz wiederum die Position des Exekutivdirektors. Im Ministerrat, dem Internationalen Währungs- und Finanzausschuss, behält die Schweiz ihren permanenten Einsitz bei.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Zwischen der Schweiz und Polen bestehen traditionell enge Verbindungen. In den letzten Jahren haben die beiden Länder ihre allgemeinen bilateralen Beziehungen erheblich ausgebaut und vertieft. &lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Roland Meier, Mediensprecher EFD Tel. 058 462 60 82, roland.meier@gs-efd.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Visite de travail du conseiller fédéral Ueli Maurer au ministre polonais des finances, Mateusz Morawiecki</title>
      <lead>Le chef du Département fédéral des finances, Ueli Maurer, rencontrera le 27 mars 2017 son homologue polonais, Mateusz Morawiecki, dans le cadre d’une visite de travail. Ils aborderont des questions financières et économiques et parleront de leur collaboration au sein des institutions financières internationales. </lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Les deux ministres discuteront des perspectives de l’économie mondiale et de la situation en Europe. Ils évoqueront en outre la collaboration de longue date entre la Suisse et la Pologne au sein des institutions financières internationales, notamment au sein du groupe de vote commun dans les institutions de Bretton Woods (Banque mondiale et Fonds monétaire international).&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;La Pologne est un partenaire important de la Suisse au sein du groupe de vote commun. Depuis 2014, les deux pays occupent alternativement un siège au Conseil d’administration du FMI. En novembre 2016, la Pologne a endossé le rôle d’administrateur pour la première fois, pour une durée de deux ans. Pendant cette période, la Suisse demeurera au sein du groupe en tant qu’administrateur suppléant. Elle occupera de nouveau le siège à partir de 2018. En revanche, la Suisse conserve son siège permanent au sein du Comité monétaire et financier international, comité ministériel du FMI.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Traditionnellement, des liens étroits unissent la Suisse et la Pologne. Les deux pays ont considérablement développé leurs relations bilatérales au cours des dernières années.&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Roland Meier, porte-parole du DFF n° tél. 058 462 60 82, roland.meier@gs-efd.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Il consigliere federale Ueli Maurer in visita di lavoro dal ministro polacco delle finanze Mateusz Morawiecki</title>
      <lead>Il capo del Dipartimento federale delle finanze, Ueli Maurer, si reca il 27 marzo 2017 dal suo omologo polacco Mateusz Morawiecki. In occasione dell’incontro saranno trattate questioni di politica finanziaria ed economica nonché il tema della collaborazione nelle istituzioni finanziarie internazionali.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;I due ministri discuteranno delle prospettive economiche mondiali e degli sviluppi in Europa. Verrà affrontato anche il tema della collaborazione pluriennale dei due Paesi nelle istituzioni finanziarie internazionali, in particolare nel gruppo di voto presso le istituzioni di Bretton Woods (Banca mondiale e Fondo monetario internazionale).&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;La Polonia è un partner importante della Svizzera nel gruppo di voto comune. Dal 2014 i due Paesi occupano in alternanza la carica di direttore esecutivo del Fondo monetario internazionale (FMI). Nel novembre 2016 la Polonia ha assunto tale carica per la prima volta, per due anni. Durante questo periodo la Svizzera sarà rappresentata in seno al Consiglio esecutivo del FMI da un direttore esecutivo supplente, mentre nel 2018 assumerà nuovamente la carica di direttore esecutivo. La Svizzera rimane membro permanente del Comitato monetario e finanziario internazionale, il Consiglio dei ministri del FMI.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;La Svizzera e la Polonia vantano una stretta collaborazione di lunga data. Negli ultimi anni i due Paesi hanno notevolmente ampliato e approfondito le loro relazioni bilaterali generali.&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Roland Meier, portavoce DFF Tel. 058 462 60 82, roland.meier@gs-efd.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Working visit of Federal Councillor Ueli Maurer to Polish Finance Minister Mateusz Morawiecki</title>
      <lead>On 27 March 2017, Federal Councillor Ueli Maurer is on a working visit to his Polish counterpart, Mateusz Morawiecki. During the meeting, financial and economic policy issues will be addressed, as well as collaboration in international financial institutions.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;The two ministers will talk about the global economic outlook and developments in Europe. The long-standing cooperation between the two countries in international financial institutions, particularly the constituency in the Bretton Woods institutions (World Bank and International Monetary Fund), will also be discussed.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Poland is an important partner for Switzerland in the joint constituency. The position of IMF Executive Director has been held by the two countries on an alternating basis since 2014. Poland took up this position for the first time in November 2016, and will hold it for two years. During that time, Switzerland will remain represented by a Deputy Executive Director on the IMF Executive Board. Switzerland will again take over the position of Executive Director in 2018. Switzerland retains its permanent seat in the ministerial committee, i.e. the International Monetary and Financial Committee.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Switzerland and Poland traditionally maintain close ties. In recent years, both countries have greatly expanded and strengthened their overall bilateral relations.&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Roland Meier, Media Spokesperson FDF Tel. 058 462 60 82, roland.meier@gs-efd.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <keywords>
      <keyword id="126" org-id="602">
        <name lang="de">Finanzplatz Schweiz</name>
        <name lang="fr">Place financière suisse</name>
        <name lang="it">Piazza finanziaria svizzera</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland as a financial centre</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="123" org-id="602">
        <name lang="de">IWF und Weltbank</name>
        <name lang="fr">FMI et Banque mondiale</name>
        <name lang="it">FMI e Banca mondiale</name>
        <name lang="en">IMF and World Bank</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="268" org-id="602">
        <name lang="de">Wirtschaftspolitik und Finanzmärkte</name>
        <name lang="fr">Politique économique et marchés financiers</name>
        <name lang="it">Politica economica e mercati finanziari</name>
        <name lang="en">Economic policy and financial markets</name>
      </keyword>
    </keywords>
    <topics>
      <topic id="34">
        <name lang="de">Europa</name>
        <name lang="fr">Europe</name>
        <name lang="it">Europa</name>
        <name lang="en">Europe</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="35">
        <name lang="de">Finanzplatz</name>
        <name lang="fr">Place financière</name>
        <name lang="it">Piazza finanziaria</name>
        <name lang="en">Financial Centre</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="47">
        <name lang="de">Wirtschaft</name>
        <name lang="fr">Économie</name>
        <name lang="it">Economia</name>
        <name lang="en">Economic Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
