<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="66163" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2017-03-28</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="701" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>701</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Wirtschaft, Bildung und Forschung</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'économie, de la formation et de la recherche</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'economia, della formazione e della ricerca</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Economic Affairs, Education and Research</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="701">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Wirtschaft, Bildung und Forschung</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'économie, de la formation et de la recherche</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'economia, della formazione e della ricerca</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Economic Affairs, Education and Research</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Bundesrat Johann N. Schneider-Ammann auf Arbeitsbesuch in Brüssel und London</title>
      <lead>Bundesrat Johann N. Schneider-Ammann, Vorsteher des Eidgenössischen Departements für Wirtschaft, Bildung und Forschung (WBF), wird am 30. März 2017 in Brüssel Gespräche mit den EU-Kommissaren Andrus Ansip und Cecilia Malmström führen. Am 31. März trifft er in London den britischen Handelsminister Liam Fox und Landwirtschaftsministerin Andrea Leadsom.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Im Zentrum des Treffens mit dem für den digitalen Binnenmarkt zuständigen Kommissions-Vizepräsidenten Andrus Ansip stehen die Chancen und Herausforderungen der Digitalisierung und die Strategien der EU und der Schweiz in diesem Themenfeld. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mit Cecilia Malmström, EU-Kommissarin für Handel, wird sich Bundesrat Johann N. Schneider-Ammann über die bilateralen Handelsbeziehungen sowie die Umsetzung der bilateralen Abkommen austauschen. Weitere Themen sind Beziehungen der EU und der Schweiz zu Drittstaaten, die aktuelle Situation des Welthandels und die Herausforderungen der Welthandelsorganisation WTO. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Bilaterale Wirtschaftsbeziehungen mit dem Vereinigten Königreich nach dem Brexit&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Voraussichtlich wird das Vereinigte Königreich am 29. März formell die Austrittsabsicht dem Europäischen Rat mitteilen. Die Schweiz führt mit dem Vereinigten Königreich enge Handelsbeziehungen; der britische Markt war vergangenes Jahr der fünftwichtigste für Schweizer Warenexporte (11,4 Mrd. CHF) und der achtgrösste Herkunftsmarkt für Warenimporte (6,4 Mrd. CHF).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Der WBF-Vorsteher wird in London mit dem britischen Minister für Aussenhandel, Liam Fox, ein Arbeitstreffen über die zukünftige Ausgestaltung der bilateralen Wirtschaftsbeziehungen nach dem Brexit abhalten. Im Rahmen der „Mind the Gap“- Strategie des Bundesrates gilt es, möglichst rasch eine Nachfolgelösung insbesondere für den Handel mit dem Vereinigten Königreich zu finden. Neben Liam Fox trifft Bundesrat Schneider-Ammann auch die für die Landwirtschaft zuständige Ministerin, Andrea Leadsom.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Hinweise für die Medien: Point de Presse in Brüssel und London&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;An beiden Tagen finden kurze Point de Presse für die Korrespondenten statt; in Brüssel am Donnerstag gegen Ende Nachmittag, in London am Freitag gegen Mittag. Die Korrespondenten werden von der Schweizer Mission in Brüssel bzw. von der Botschaft in London direkt eingeladen. Nach beiden Besuchen werden kurze Medienmitteilungen verschickt.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Noé Blancpain, Informationschef WBF, Tel. +41 78 748 61 63, noe.blancpain@wbf.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Visites de travail du conseiller fédéral Schneider-Ammann à Bruxelles et à Londres</title>
      <lead>Le conseiller fédéral Johann N. Schneider-Ammann, chef du Département fédéral de l’économie, de la formation et de la recherche (DEFR), se rendra à Bruxelles le 30 mars 2017 pour un échange avec les commissaires européens Andrus Ansip et Cecilia Malmstöm. Le 31 mars 2017, il sera à Londres pour rencontrer le ministre britannique du Commerce Liam Fox et ministre de l’agriculture Andrea Leadsom.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Lors de la rencontre avec Andrus Ansip, vice-président de la Commission européenne, chargé du marché numérique unique, les échanges porteront essentiellement sur les chances et les défis de la numérisation et sur les stratégies de l’UE et de la Suisse en la matière.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Johann N. Schneider-Ammann s’entretiendra également avec Cecilia Malmström, commissaire européenne au Commerce, au sujet des relations commerciales bilatérales et de la mise en œuvre des accords bilatéraux. D’autres sujets seront abordés, au nombre desquels les relations de l’UE et de la Suisse avec les pays tiers, la situation actuelle du commerce mondial et les défis à relever pour l’Organisation mondiale du commerce (OMC). &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Relations économiques bilatérales avec le Royaume-Uni à la suite du Brexit&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Il est prévu que le gouvernement britannique annonce formellement son retrait du Conseil européen le 29 mars 2017. La Suisse entretient d’étroites relations commerciales avec le Royaume-Uni; en 2016, il était, pour les marchandises, le 5e marché d’exportation (11,4 milliards de francs) et le 8e marché d’importation (6,4 milliards de francs).&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;À Londres, le chef du DEFR rencontrera le ministre britannique du Commerce extérieur Liam Fox pour traiter de l’avenir des relations économiques bilatérales à la suite du Brexit. Dans le cadre de la stratégie «mind the gap» du Conseil fédéral, il s’agit de parvenir à un régime de remplacement avec le Royaume-Uni dans les meilleurs délais, en particulier concernant le commerce. Outre Liam Fox, le conseiller fédéral Johann N. Schneider-Ammann rencontrera Andrea Leadsom, ministre de l’agriculture.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Remarque à l’intention des medias: points de presse à Bruxelles et à Londres&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Un bref point de presse destiné aux correspondants est prévu pour chacune des deux dates: le jeudi en fin d’après-midi à Bruxelles et le vendredi aux alentours de midi à Londres. Les correspondants seront invités directement par la Mission suisse à Bruxelles ou l’ambassade de Suisse à Londres. De courts communiqués seront transmis à l’issue des deux visites.&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Noé Blancpain, chef de l’Information du DEFR +41 78 748 61 63 noe.blancpain@wbf.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Il consigliere federale Schneider-Ammann in visita di lavoro a Bruxelles e Londra</title>
      <lead>Il consigliere federale Johann N. Schneider-Ammann, capo del Dipartimento federale dell’economia, della formazione e della ricerca (DEFR) sarà a Bruxelles il 30 marzo 2017 per colloqui con i commissari UE Andrus Ansip e Cecilia Malmström. Il 31 marzo, invece, incontrerà a Londra il ministro del commercio Liam Fox e la ministra dell’agricoltura Andrea Leadsom. </lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Al centro dell’incontro con Andrus Ansip, vicepresidente della commissione e responsabile del mercato interno digitale, ci sono le sfide e le opportunità della digitalizzazione, così come le strategie dell’Unione e della Svizzera in questo campo. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Con Cecilia Malmström, commissaria UE per il commercio, il consigliere federale Johann N. Schneider-Ammann discuterà delle relazioni commerciali bilaterali e dell’attuazione degli accordi bilaterali. Tra gli altri temi ci sono anche i rapporti dell’Unione europea e della Svizzera con gli Stati terzi, la situazione attuale del commercio mondiale e le sfide per l’Organizzazione mondiale del commercio (OMC). &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Relazioni economiche bilaterali con il Regno Unito dopo la Brexit&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Il 29 marzo il Regno Unito dovrebbe comunicare formalmente al Consiglio europeo le proprie intenzioni per uscire dall’Unione. La Svizzera coltiva strette relazioni commerciali con il Regno Unito: lo scorso anno il mercato britannico occupava il quinto posto nella classifica dei principali Paesi per le esportazioni svizzere (11,4 miliardi di franchi) e l’ottavo invece per quanto riguarda le importazioni (6,4 miliardi di franchi).&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;A Londra l’incontro di lavoro tra il capo del DEFR e il ministro britannico del commercio estero, Liam Fox, sarà dedicato al futuro assetto delle relazioni economiche bilaterali dopo la Brexit. In linea con la strategia «Mind the Gap» del Consiglio federale, è importante delineare al più presto una soluzione post-Brexit specialmente per il commercio con il Regno Unito. Oltre a Liam Fox, il consigliere federale parlerà anche con la ministra dell’agricoltura, Andrea Leadsom.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Informazione per i media: «Point de Presse» a Bruxelles e Londra&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;In entrambi le giornate si terrà un breve «Point de Presse» per i corrispondenti: giovedì a Bruxelles a fine pomeriggio, venerdì a Londra verso mezzogiorno. I corrispondenti riceveranno un invito direttamente dalla Missione svizzera di Bruxelles e dall’ambasciata di Londra. Un breve comunicato stampa sarà pubblicato dopo ogni visita.&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Noé Blancpain, capo Informazione DEFR, tel. +41 78 748 61 63, noe.blancpain@wbf.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Federal Councillor Schneider-Ammann to pay working visits to Brussels and London</title>
      <lead>On 30 March Federal Councillor Johann N. Schneider-Ammann, the head of the Federal Department of Economic Affairs, Education and Research EAER, will hold talks in Brussels with EU commissioners Andrus Ansip and Cecilia Malmström. On 31 March he will meet Liam Fox, the UK Secretary of State for International Trade, and Andrea Leadsom, the Secretary of State for Environment, Food and Rural Affairs, in London.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;The meeting with Andrus Ansip, the European Commission vice president responsible for the digital single market, will focus on the opportunities and challenges of digitalisation and the EU’s and Switzerland’s strategies in this area.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;At the meeting with Cecilia Malmström, EU commissioner for trade, Federal Councillor Johann N. Schneider-Ammann will discuss bilateral trade relations and the implementation of the bilateral agreements. Further topics will include relations of the EU and Switzerland with third countries, the current world trade climate and the challenges facing the World Trade Organization WTO.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Bilateral economic relations with the UK following Brexit&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The United Kingdom is expected to formally give notice to the European Council of its intention to leave the European Union on 29 March. Switzerland has close trade relations with the United Kingdom; last year the UK market was the fifth most important for Swiss goods exports (CHF 11.4bn) and the eighth largest market of origin for imports (CHF 6.4bn).&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;In London the head of the EAER will meet Liam Fox, the Secretary of State for International Trade, for a working meeting on the future shape of bilateral economic relations after Brexit. As part of the Federal Council’s ‘Mind the gap’ strategy the aim is to reach a follow-up arrangement as swiftly as possible, particularly regarding trade with the UK. Mr Schneider-Ammann will also be meeting Andrea Leadsom, the Secretary of State for Environment, Food and Rural Affairs.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Note for journalists: Press call in Brussels and London&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; There will be a brief press call for journalists on both days; on Thursday in Brussels towards the end of the afternoon, and on Friday in London around midday. Journalists will receive an invitation directly from the Swiss mission in Brussels and from the embassy in London. A short press release will be distributed after each visit. </text>
      <contact>Noé Blancpain, Head of Information EAER, Tel. +41 78 748 61 63, noe.blancpain@wbf.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="10">
        <name lang="de">Bundesrat</name>
        <name lang="fr">Conseil fédéral</name>
        <name lang="it">Consiglio federale</name>
        <name lang="en">Federal Council</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="47">
        <name lang="de">Wirtschaft</name>
        <name lang="fr">Économie</name>
        <name lang="it">Economia</name>
        <name lang="en">Economic Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
