<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="66334" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2017-04-10</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="201" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>201</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="201">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>1867-2017: Schweiz feiert 150 Jahre diplomatische Vertretung in Berlin</title>
      <lead>Vor 150 Jahren, am 17. April 1867, beschloss der Bundesrat, provisorisch eine schweizerische diplomatische Vertretung in Berlin zu schaffen. Seither pflegen die Schweiz und Deutschland ununterbrochen diplomatische Beziehungen. Zum Jubiläumsjahr veröffentlicht die schweizerische Botschaft eine Broschüre, die einen Überblick über die bewegte Geschichte der diplomatischen Vertretungen an den verschiedenen Standorten in Deutschland und in Berlin gibt. </lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Der erste Schweizer Gesandte in Berlin war der Glarner Joachim Heer. Der Bundesrat hatte vorgesehen, dass er sich als Vertreter der Schweiz nicht nur beim preussischen Königshof, sondern auch beim König von Bayern, dem König von Württemberg und dem Grossherzog von Baden akkreditieren solle. Es war die erste Mehrfachakkreditierung der Schweiz überhaupt.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Heer traf am 15. Mai 1867 in Berlin ein und überreichte drei Tage darauf König Wilhelm I. das Beglaubigungsschreiben. Dieser war erfreut, weil er sich schon lange gewünscht hatte, dass die Schweiz Gegenrecht üben würde. Preussen war seit dem Jahre 1805 mit einer offiziellen Gesandtschaft in der Schweiz vertreten, auch wenn die zuständigen preussischen Diplomaten zumeist keinen Wohnsitz in der Schweiz hatten. Die Aussenpolitik wurde damals über Neuenburg, das gleichzeitig Mitglied der Eidgenossenschaft und Besitz des preussischen Königs war, und das mit ihm verbündete Bern abgewickelt. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Die Geschichte der Schweizer Vertretung in Deutschland ist bewegt, aufgrund der turbulenten Geschichte. Die Gesandtschaft in Berlin bestand bis 1945, nach dem Zweiten Weltkrieg kümmerte sich die Heimschaffungsdelegation um rückkehrwillige Schweizer und die in Berlin ansässigen Landsleute. Die diplomatische Vertretung wurde 1949 in Bonn (Vertretung in der BRD) eingerichtet und war von 1957-1977 zwischenzeitlich in Köln angesiedelt, bis 1999 wieder in Bonn. Die Schweiz errichtete 1973 auch in der DDR eine Botschaft. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Seit 1999 ist die Schweizerische Botschaft in Berlin am Spreebogen zu Hause. Das Gebäude kaufte die Schweiz vor knapp 100 Jahren (1919). Am Ende des Zweiten Weltkriegs wurde das Quartier im Spreebogen praktisch vollständig zerstört, das Gebäude der Schweizer Vertretung überstand diese Zeit bemerkenswerterweise nahezu unbeschadet. Nach dem Krieg stand das Gebäude in unmittelbarer Nähe zur Mauer und damit als einsamer Monolith im Niemandsland. In dieser Zeit versuchte die Schweiz mehrmals, das Gebäude an dem damals unattraktiven Standort erfolglos zu verkaufen. Erst nach der Wiedervereinigung und dem Entscheid der Bundesregierung, Berlin wieder zur Hauptstadt zu machen, kam wieder Leben in das Umfeld der Botschaft. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Über konsularische Vertretungen verfügte die Schweiz in Bremen, Hamburg und Leipzig bereits vor 1867. Als der moderne Bundesstaat entstand (1848) verfügte die Schweiz über zwei diplomatische Vertretungen: in Paris und in Wien, danach folgten Turin und Florenz. Zum 150-jährigen Jubiläum der Vertretung in Berlin gibt die Botschaft in Deutschland eine Broschüre heraus.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Kommunikation EDA Bundeshaus West CH-3003 Bern Tel. Kommunikationsservice: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Medienstelle: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <link id="165497">
        <title>Broschüre: „150 Jahre: Die Schweizerfahne im Herzen Berlins“</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/countries/germany/de/home/aktuell/news.html/content/countries/germany/de/meta/news/2017/maerz/150-jahre-schweizer-gesandtschaft-in-berlin</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>1867-2017: la Suisse célèbre 150 ans de représentation diplomatique à Berlin</title>
      <lead>Il y a 150 ans, le 17 avril 1867, le Conseil fédéral décidait la création provisoire d’une représentation diplomatique suisse à Berlin. Depuis, la Suisse et l’Allemagne ont entretenu des relations ininterrompues. Pour marquer cet anniversaire, l’ambassade de Suisse édite une brochure retraçant l’histoire mouvementée des représentations diplomatiques dans diverses villes d’Allemagne ainsi qu’à Berlin. </lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Le Glaronnais Joachim Heer a été le premier émissaire de la Suisse à Berlin. Le Conseil fédéral avait prévu son accréditation en qualité de représentant de la Suisse non seulement auprès de la cour du royaume de Prusse, mais également auprès du royaume de Bavière, du royaume de Wurtemberg et du grand-duché de Bade. Pour la Suisse, il s’agissait de la première accréditation multiple jamais accordée.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Arrivé le 15 mai 1867 à Berlin, Joachim Heer a remis ses lettres de créance trois jours plus tard au roi Guillaume Ier. Le souverain en fut ravi, lui qui souhaitait depuis longtemps que la Suisse fasse usage du principe de réciprocité. Une légation officielle représentait en effet la Prusse en Suisse depuis 1805, la plupart de ses diplomates n’étant toutefois pas domiciliés en Suisse. La politique extérieure était alors conduite depuis Neuchâtel, à la fois canton suisse et principauté prussienne, et par le canton de Berne, son allié. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;En raison des turbulences de l’histoire, la représentation de Suisse en Allemagne connaîtra un destin mouvementé. La légation de Berlin s’est maintenue jusqu’en 1945, puis a été remplacée après la deuxième guerre mondiale par la délégation suisse pour le rapatriement de citoyens suisses, qui s’est occupée des Suisses souhaitant rentrer au pays ou établis à Berlin. Établie en 1949 à Bonn, la représentation diplomatique (représentation en République fédérale d’Allemagne) sera provisoirement implantée à Cologne de 1957 à 1977, avant de revenir à Bonn et d’y rester jusqu’en 1999. La Suisse ouvrira également une ambassade en République démocratique allemande en 1973. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;L’ambassade de Suisse à Berlin est installée au Spreebogen, le coude de la Spree, depuis 1999, dans un bâtiment que la Suisse a acquis il y a près d’un siècle (en 1919). Bien que le quartier du Spreebogen ait été presque entièrement détruit pendant la deuxième guerre mondiale, le bâtiment de la représentation suisse est sorti quasiment indemne de l’épreuve de la guerre. Situé à deux pas du mur, il donnera longtemps l’image d’un monolithe solitaire en plein no man’s land. Après la guerre, la Suisse essaiera à plusieurs reprises, en vain, de vendre le bâtiment, alors situé à un endroit peu attractif. Il lui faudra attendre la réunification allemande et la décision du gouvernement de l’Allemagne unifiée de déplacer la capitale à Berlin pour voir à nouveau s’animer les alentours de l’ambassade. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;La Suisse disposait de représentations consulaires à Brême, Hambourg et Leipzig avant 1867 déjà. À la naissance de l’État fédéral (en 1848), elle comptait deux représentations diplomatiques à Paris et à Vienne, auxquelles viendront ensuite s’ajouter Turin et Florence. L’ambassade de Suisse à Berlin édite une brochure à l’occasion du 150e anniversaire de la représentation suisse en Allemagne.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Communication DFAE Palais fédéral ouest CH-3003 Berne Tél. Service de communication: +41 58 462 31 53 Tél. Service de presse: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <link id="165496">
        <title>Brochure: «150 Jahre: Die Schweizerfahne im Herzen Berlins» («150 ans: la Suisse au cœur de Berlin») (de)</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/countries/germany/fr/home/actualite/nouveautes.html/countries/germany/de/meta/news/2017/maerz/150-jahre-schweizer-gesandtschaft-in-berlin</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>1867-2017: la Svizzera festeggia i 150 anni di rappresentanza diplomatica a Berlino</title>
      <lead>150 anni fa, il 17 aprile 1867, il Consiglio federale decise di aprire provvisoriamente una rappresentanza diplomatica svizzera a Berlino. Da allora la Svizzera e la Germania intrattengono relazioni diplomatiche ininterrotte. Nell’anno dell’anniversario l’Ambasciata svizzera pubblica un opuscolo che offre una panoramica sulla vivace storia delle rappresentanze diplomatiche nelle varie sedi in Germania e a Berlino. </lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Il primo ambasciatore svizzero a Berlino fu il glaronese Joachim Heer. Il Consiglio federale aveva previsto che, come rappresentante della Svizzera, doveva accreditarsi non solo presso la corte prussiana, ma anche presso il re di Baviera, il re del Württemberg e il granduca del Baden. Era in assoluto il primo accreditamento multiplo della Svizzera.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Il 15 maggio 1867 Heer giunse a Berlino e tre giorni più tardi fu ricevuto dal re Guglielmo I per la consegna delle credenziali. Il re era soddisfatto poiché si aspettava già da parecchio tempo che la Svizzera esercitasse il diritto di reciprocità. Dal 1805 la Prussia era rappresentata in Svizzera da una legazione ufficiale, anche se i diplomatici prussiani competenti non erano per lo più domiciliati in Svizzera. All’epoca la politica estera veniva condotta da Neuchâtel, che allo stesso tempo era membro della Confederazione e proprietà del re della Prussia, e da Berna, sua alleata. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;La storia della rappresentanza Svizzera in Germania è stata vivace in seguito alle turbolenze istoriche. La legazione a Berlino continuò a esistere fino al 1945; dopo la Seconda guerra mondiale la delegazione per il rimpatrio si occupò dei cittadini svizzeri che volevano rientrare in Patria e di quelli residenti a Berlino. La rappresentanza diplomatica fu istituita nel 1949 a Bonn (rappresentanza nella Repubblica federale di Germania). Tra il 1957 e il 1977 si stabilì a Colonia e fino al 1999 di nuovo a Bonn. Nel 1973 la Svizzera aprì un’ambasciata anche nella Repubblica democratica tedesca. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Dal 1999 l’Ambasciata di Svizzera a Berlino è situata allo Spreebogen. L’edificio fu acquistato dalla Svizzera quasi 100 anni fa (1919). Alla fine della Seconda guerra mondiale il quartiere dello Spreebogen fu pressoché completamente distrutto, mentre l’edificio della rappresentanza svizzera superò questo periodo praticamente senza subire danni. Dopo la guerra l’edificio si ergeva nelle immediate vicinanze del muro, come un monolito abbandonato nella terra di nessuno. In questo periodo la Svizzera cercò più volte senza successo di vendere l’edificio, allora situato in una zona decisamente poco attraente. Solo dopo la riunificazione e la decisione del Governo tedesco di riportare la capitale a Berlino, ricominciò a esserci vita nelle vicinanze dell’ambasciata. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Già prima del 1867 la Svizzera aveva rappresentanze consolari a Brema, Amburgo e Lipzia. Quando fu creato lo Stato federale moderno (1848), la Svizzera aveva due rappresentanze diplomatiche a Parigi e a Vienna, in seguito anche a Torino e Firenze. Per commemorare 150° anniversario della rappresentanza a Berlino l’ambasciata in Germania pubblica un opuscolo.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Comunicazione DFAE Palazzo federale ovest CH-3003 Berna Tel. Servizio di comunicazione: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Servizio stampa: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <link id="165495">
        <title>Opuscolo: «150 Jahre: Die Schweizerfahne im Herzen Berlins» («150 anni: la bandiera svizzera nel cuore di Berlino») (de)</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/countries/germany/it/home/attualita/novita.html/countries/germany/de/meta/news/2017/maerz/150-jahre-schweizer-gesandtschaft-in-berlin</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Swiss embassy in Berlin celebrates 150 years of diplomatic relations</title>
      <lead>On 17 April 1867 the Federal Council decided to establish a temporary Swiss diplomatic mission in Berlin. Switzerland and Germany have maintained uninterrupted diplomatic relations since then. To mark this anniversary, the Swiss embassy in Germany has published a brochure about the eventful history of Switzerland’s representations in Berlin and other German cities.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;The first Swiss envoy in Berlin was Joachim Heer from Glarus. The Federal Council had instructed him to secure accreditation not only to the Prussian court but also to the courts of the King of Bavaria, the King of Wurttemberg and the Grand Duke of Baden. It was the first time a Swiss representative obtained multiple accreditations.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Three days after his arrival in Berlin on 15 May 1867, Heer presented his credentials to William I, the King of Prussia. William I was gratified, as he had for some time wanted a Swiss diplomatic envoy to be accredited to the Prussian court. Prussia had established an official legation in Switzerland as early as 1805, although Prussian diplomats generally did not have a residence in Switzerland. In the first half of the 19th century, Prussian relations with Switzerland were conducted via the Canton of Neuchâtel, which joined the Swiss Confederation in 1815 and remained the property of the Prussian King until 1848. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The history of Switzerland’s representations in Germany is eventful owing to Europe’s turbulent history. Switzerland maintained a legation in Berlin until the end of the Second World War in 1945. After the war, the Swiss Repatriation Delegation was responsible for Swiss nationals living in Berlin and those wishing to return to Switzerland. Switzerland’s diplomatic representation to the Federal Republic of Germany was established in Bonn in 1949, based in Cologne from 1957 to 1977, and again in Bonn until 1999. In 1973, Switzerland also opened an embassy in the German Democratic Republic. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Since 1999 the Swiss embassy in Berlin has been located in the Spreebogen district. Switzerland bought the building in 1919, almost 100 years ago. The Spreebogen district was left almost entirely destroyed at the end of the war but remarkably the building survived almost unscathed. The building became an isolated monolith in the no man’s land after the Berlin Wall was built in 1961. For many years, Switzerland tried to sell the building because of its undesirable location. After the fall of the wall, the government of reunited Germany decided that Berlin would once again become the nation’s capital, bringing life back to the area where the building – and the relocated Swiss embassy – was situated. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Before 1867, Switzerland had already opened consular representations in Bremen, Hamburg and Leipzig. When Switzerland became a modern federal state in 1848, it had two diplomatic representations, in Paris and Vienna, which were followed by representations in Turin and Florence a few years later. The Swiss embassy to Germany has published a brochure to mark the 150th anniversary of the opening of the Swiss representation in Berlin.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>FDFA Communication Federal Palace West Wing CH-3003 Bern, Switzerland Tel. Communication service: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Press service: +41 58 460 55 55 E-mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @SwissMFA</contact>
      <link id="165494">
        <title>Brochure: “150 Jahre: Die Schweizerfahne im Herzen Berlins” (The Swiss flag in the heart of Berlin, 150 years on) (de)</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/countries/germany/en/home/news/news.html/countries/germany/de/meta/news/2017/maerz/150-jahre-schweizer-gesandtschaft-in-berlin</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
