<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="66467" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2017-04-25</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="201" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>201</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="201">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>„Über den Tellerrand“ – die DEZA gibt in Luzern Einblick in die Entwicklungszusammenarbeit</title>
      <lead>Die Direktion für Entwicklung und Zusammenarbeit (DEZA) lädt die Besucherinnen und Besucher der Zentralschweizer Frühlingsmesse LUGA zum Riechen, Schmecken und Entdecken ein. Die Sonderschau „Über den Tellerrand“ zeigt, wie die Schweiz in Ländern wie Kosovo, Vietnam oder Benin zur Reduktion von Armut und Hunger sowie gleichzeitig zu einer umweltschonenden Landwirtschaft beiträgt. Die diesjährige LUGA dauert vom 28. April bis 7. Mai 2017.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;In Halle 4 der LUGA schlendern Besucherinnen und Besucher durch einen bunten Weltmarkt und kosten Kaffee aus Vietnam oder Ajvar aus Kosovo. Das Publikum kann sich mit Pflanzenärzten austauschen, die in 35 Ländern Bäuerinnen und Bauern bei Ernteverlusten oder bei Schädlingsbefall beraten. Mitarbeitende der Humanitären Hilfe erzählen von ihrem Arbeitsalltag in Flüchtlingscamps oder Katastrophengebieten. Schliesslich lädt der „Maquis“, ein typisches westafrikanisches Café, zu Häppchen aus Niger und Benin ein. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ein neues Erlebnis dürften für viele die sogenannten Virtual-Reality-Brillen sein, welche eine nahezu perfekte dreidimensionale Illusion von unbekannten Welten erlauben – auch dies ein Blick über den eigenen Tellerrand hinaus. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Kleinbäuerinnen und Kleinbauern ernähren die Welt&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Es sind hauptsächlich Kleinbäuerinnen und Kleinbauern, Selbstversorger, Hirten und Fischer, welche die Weltbevölkerung ernähren. Weltweit ist ein Drittel aller arbeitenden Menschen in der Landwirtschaft beschäftigt. Davon leben jedoch 70 Prozent in Armut.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ziel der Schweizer Entwicklungszusammenarbeit ist die Armutsreduktion. Bessere Produktionsbedingungen tragen dazu bei, ebenso die Bewältigung von Umweltproblemen und ein einfacher Zugang zu Bildung und Gesundheitsversorgung. Konkrete Beispiele:&lt;br /&gt;• In Vietnam lernen Bauern, wie sie mit weniger Wasser die gleichen Kaffeeerträge erzielen. &lt;br /&gt;• In Niger erhalten Jugendliche eine Berufsbildung, damit sie nicht aus den ländlichen Gegenden abwandern.&lt;br /&gt;• Im Kosovo finden Schulungen zur Verarbeitung, Konservierung und Vermarktung von Lebensmitteln statt, was Arbeitsplätze und Perspektiven vor Ort schafft.&lt;br /&gt;• In weltweit 35 Ländern können Bäuerinnen und Bauern auf eine kostenlose Beratung durch Pflanzenärzte zählen, wenn ihre Pflanzen von Pilzen oder Schädlingen befallen sind. Die Schweiz unterstützt die Ausbildung dieser Pflanzenärzte. &lt;br /&gt;• In Benin schützt ein einfaches Metallsilo die Maisernte vor Insektenbefall. Das generiert ausserdem Aufträge an Metallbauer. &lt;br /&gt;• Die Humanitäre Hilfe der DEZA leistet in Krisen und bei Katastrophen Nothilfe. Nicht selten sind hohe Nahrungsmittelpreise und bewaffnete Konflikte Ursachen von Hunger.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Kommunikation EDA Bundeshaus West CH-3003 Bern Tel. Kommunikationsservice: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Medienstelle: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <link id="165808">
        <title>Entwicklung und Zusammenarbeit DEZA</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/deza/de/home.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="165809">
        <title>DEZA an der LUGA</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/deza/de/home/aktuell/agenda.html/content/deza/de/meta/agenda/2017/4/luga</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>«Voir plus loin que le bord de son assiette»: la DDC présente la coopération au développement à Lucerne</title>
      <lead>La Direction du développement et de la coopération (DDC) invite le public de la foire de printemps de Suisse centrale (LUGA) à venir sentir, goûter et découvrir. L'exposition spéciale « Voir plus loin que le bord de son assiette » montre comment la Suisse contribue à réduire la pauvreté et la famine dans des pays comme le Kosovo, le Vietnam ou le Bénin, tout en favorisant une agriculture respectueuse de l'environnement. Cette année, la LUGA se tiendra du 28 avril au 7 mai.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Dans la halle 4 de la LUGA, des visiteurs flânent parmi les étals colorés d’un marché des pays du monde, en goûtant du café du Vietnam ou de l'ajvar du Kosovo. Le public peut discuter avec des « médecins des plantes » ou phytiatres, qui conseillent des paysans dans 35 pays et les aident à faire face à des pertes de récolte ou à des attaques de nuisibles. Des collaborateurs de l’Aide humanitaire racontent leur quotidien dans les camps de réfugiés ou les régions touchées par des catastrophes. Les curieux peuvent aussi se laisser tenter par les amuse-bouches nigériens et béninois du «Maquis», un café typiquement ouest-africain. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Les visiteurs sont par ailleurs invités à essayer une nouveauté, des lunettes 3D de réalité virtuelle qui donnent l’illusion presque parfaite de se retrouver dans des mondes inconnus: une autre manière de voir plus loin que le bord de son assiette. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Les petits paysans nourrissent le monde&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ce sont principalement les petits paysans, les fermiers qui pratiquent l'agriculture de subsistance, les bergers et les pêcheurs qui nourrissent le monde. Un tiers de la population active mondiale travaille dans l'agriculture. Cela dit, 70% d'entre eux vivent dans la pauvreté.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;La coopération suisse au développement a pour but d'y remédier et de faire reculer la misère. La réalisation de cet objectif passe par l’amélioration des conditions de production ainsi que par la gestion des problèmes environnementaux et un meilleur accès à la formation et aux soins de santé. Voici quelques exemples concrets:&lt;br /&gt;• Au Vietnam, des agriculteurs apprennent à utiliser moins d’eau pour obtenir les mêmes rendements de café. &lt;br /&gt;• Au Niger, des jeunes bénéficient d’une formation professionnelle leur permettant de rester dans les zones rurales.&lt;br /&gt;• Au Kosovo, des formations dans le domaine du traitement, de la conservation et de la commercialisation des aliments ont été mises sur pied, ce qui génère des emplois et des perspectives sur place.&lt;br /&gt;• Dans 35 pays, des fermiers peuvent bénéficier des conseils gratuits de « médecins des plantes » (phytiatres) lorsque leurs plantes sont victimes d’attaques de champignons ou de nuisibles. La Suisse contribue à la formation de ces spécialistes. &lt;br /&gt;• Au Bénin, un simple silo de métal protège les récoltes de maïs des insectes. Cela génère par ailleurs du travail dans le secteur de la construction métallique. &lt;br /&gt;• L’Aide humanitaire de la DDC organise des secours d’urgence en cas de crise et de catastrophe. Trop souvent, les prix élevés des produits alimentaires et les conflits armés provoquent des famines.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Communication DFAE Palais fédéral ouest CH-3003 Berne Tél. Service de communication: +41 58 462 31 53 Tél. Service de presse: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <link id="165807">
        <title>Direction du développement et de la coopération (DDC)</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/deza/fr/home.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="165810">
        <title>La DDC à la LUGA</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/deza/fr/home/actualites/manifestations.html/deza/fr/meta/agenda/2017/4/luga</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>«Oltre i confini gastronomici»: a Lucerna la DSC presenta la cooperazione allo sviluppo</title>
      <lead>La Direzione dello sviluppo e della cooperazione (DSC) invita le visitatrici e i visitatori della fiera primaverile della Svizzera centrale ad annusare, gustare e scoprire. Con la mostra speciale «Oltre i confini gastronomici» («Über den Tellerrand») la DSC illustra in che modo la Svizzera contribuisce a ridurre la povertà e la fame in Paesi come il Kosovo, il Vietnam o il Benin e, al contempo, a diffondere un’agricoltura ecosostenibile. Quest’anno la LUGA si terrà dal 28 aprile al 7 maggio.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Nel padiglione 4 della LUGA le visitatrici e i visitatori possono passeggiare in un variopinto mercato internazionale e gustare specialità come il caffè del Vietnam o l’ajvar del Kosovo. Hanno inoltre la possibilità di parlare con esperti fitosanitari (i cosiddetti «dottori delle piante») che, in 35 Paesi, forniscono consulenza alle coltivatrici e ai coltivatori in caso di perdite di raccolto o infestazioni da parassiti. Le collaboratrici e i collaboratori dell’Aiuto umanitario illustrano il loro lavoro quotidiano nei campi profughi o nelle zone colpite da catastrofi. C’è poi il «Maquis», tipica caffetteria dell’Africa occidentale, che invita a gustare stuzzichini tradizionali del Niger e del Benin.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Un’altra attrazione, forse nuova per molti, è la realtà aumentata, da scoprire indossando appositi occhiali che permettono di vedere virtualmente immagini tridimensionali pressoché perfette di mondi sconosciuti e offrono così un ulteriore sguardo oltre i propri confini. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Le piccole coltivatrici e i piccoli coltivatori nutrono il mondo&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sono soprattutto le piccole coltivatrici e i piccoli coltivatori, la produzione per uso domestico, la pastorizia e la pesca a garantire l’alimentazione della popolazione mondiale. Nel mondo, un terzo di tutti gli occupati lavora nell’agricoltura e il 70 per cento di queste persone vive in condizioni di indigenza.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;L’obiettivo della cooperazione svizzera allo sviluppo è ridurre la povertà. Il miglioramento delle condizioni di produzione contribuisce al raggiungimento di tale scopo, come pure la risoluzione dei problemi ambientali e un facile accesso all’istruzione e all’assistenza sanitaria. Qualche esempio concreto:&lt;br /&gt;• in Vietnam le coltivatrici e i coltivatori imparano a ottenere lo stesso raccolto di caffè con una minore quantità d’acqua; &lt;br /&gt;• in Niger viene offerta una formazione professionale ai giovani affinché non abbandonino le zone rurali;&lt;br /&gt;• in Kosovo si organizzano corsi di formazione per la lavorazione, la conservazione e la commercializzazione di generi alimentari, creando così lavoro e prospettive sul posto;&lt;br /&gt;• in 35 Paesi le coltivatrici e i coltivatori possono usufruire di una consulenza gratuita da parte di esperti fitosanitari se le loro piante sono colpite da funghi o parassiti. La Svizzera sostiene la formazione di questi esperti fitosanitari; &lt;br /&gt;• in Benin, con un semplice silo di metallo si protegge il raccolto di mais dagli insetti e, al contempo, si dà lavoro alle aziende che si occupano di costruzioni metalliche;&lt;br /&gt;• l’Aiuto umanitario della DSC presta aiuto d’emergenza in caso di crisi e catastrofi. Non di rado le carestie sono causate dai prezzi elevati dei generi alimentari e dai conflitti armati.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Comunicazione DFAE Palazzo federale ovest CH-3003 Berna Tel. Servizio di comunicazione: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Servizio stampa: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <link id="165806">
        <title>Direzione dello sviluppo e della cooperazione DSC</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/deza/it/home.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="165811">
        <title>La DSC alla LUGA</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/deza/it/home/novita/eventi.html/deza/it/meta/agenda/2017/4/luga</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>‘Beyond one’s own four kitchen walls’ – the SDC showcases its development cooperation in Lucerne</title>
      <lead>The Swiss Agency for Development and Cooperation (SDC) is inviting visitors at LUGA, the Spring Fair of Central Switzerland, to come and taste, smell and discover some aspects of their work. The special exhibition ‘Beyond one’s own four kitchen walls’ shows how Switzerland contributes to the reduction of poverty and hunger while promoting ecologically sound agriculture in countries such as Kosovo, Vietnam and Benin. This year’s LUGA runs from 28 April to 7 May 2017.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Visitors to LUGA’s Hall 4 are met with a colourful market of foods from all over the world. Here, they can stop and taste the various products on offer, such as coffee from Vietnam or ajvar from Kosovo. They can also meet the ‘plant doctors’ who show farmers in 35 countries how to avoid and deal with crop failures or pest infestations. Swiss Humanitarian Aid employees are there to talk about their day-to-day work in refugee camps and disaster areas. And there is even a typical West African café, the ‘Maquis’, where visitors can snack on delicacies from Niger and Benin.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A new experience for many will be the virtual reality headsets on show, giving visitors an almost lifelike 3D illusion of unfamiliar worlds – and a glimpse beyond the boundaries of their own kitchen walls.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Smallholder farmers feed the world&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The bulk of the world’s food supply is produced by smallholder and subsistence farmers, herders and fishing communities. A third of the world’s working population earn their livelihood from agriculture, but 70% of them live in poverty.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The goal of Swiss development cooperation is to reduce poverty. Better production conditions help to make this a reality, as do measures to overcome environmental issues and to improve access to education and healthcare. Some specific examples:&lt;br /&gt;• In Vietnam, farmers are learning how to achieve the same coffee yields using less water.&lt;br /&gt;• In Niger, young people receive vocational education and training so they do not have to leave their rural communities for work.&lt;br /&gt;• In Kosovo, courses are offered on food processing, preservation and commercialisation, creating new jobs and better prospects for people living there.&lt;br /&gt;• In 35 countries worldwide, farmers can obtain free advice from plant doctors to help control any pests or fungal diseases affecting their crops. Switzerland supports the training of these plant doctors.&lt;br /&gt;• In Benin, corn harvests are now protected from insects with a simple metal silo – a solution that also creates jobs for metalworkers.&lt;br /&gt;• Swiss Humanitarian Aid provides emergency assistance to people affected by crises and natural disasters. The root causes of hunger, however, are often high food prices or armed conflicts.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>FDFA Communication Federal Palace West Wing CH-3003 Bern, Switzerland Tel. Communication service: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Press service: +41 58 460 55 55 E-mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @SwissMFA</contact>
      <link id="165805">
        <title>Development and cooperation (SDC)</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/deza/en/home.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="165812">
        <title>The SDC at LUGA</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/deza/en/home/news/events.html/deza/en/meta/agenda/2017/4/luga</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
