<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="66662" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2017-05-10</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="1070" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>1070</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Der Bundesrat</name>
      <name lang="fr">Conseil fédéral</name>
      <name lang="it">Il Consiglio federale</name>
      <name lang="en">The Federal Council</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.admin.ch/gov/de/start.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.admin.ch/gov/fr/accueil.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.admin.ch/gov/it/pagina-iniziale.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.admin.ch/gov/en/start.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="201" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>201</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="1070">
      <name lang="de">Der Bundesrat</name>
      <name lang="fr">Conseil fédéral</name>
      <name lang="it">Il Consiglio federale</name>
      <name lang="en">The Federal Council</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.admin.ch/gov/de/start.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.admin.ch/gov/fr/accueil.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.admin.ch/gov/it/pagina-iniziale.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.admin.ch/gov/en/start.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <department id="201">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Ernennungen und Versetzungen von Missionschefs, Verleihung eines Botschaftertitels</title>
      <lead>In mehreren Schweizer Vertretungen im Ausland sowie an der Zentrale des Eidgenössischen Departements für auswärtige Angelegenheiten (EDA) kommt es 2017 zu personellen Wechseln. Diese erfolgen im Rahmen der üblichen Versetzungsrhythmen und aufgrund eines Beschlusses des Bundesrats. Die Ernennungen der Missionschefs im Ausland werden mit der Erteilung des Agréments durch den Gaststaat wirksam. </lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt; Stefan Klötzli&lt;/strong&gt;, gegenwärtig Missionschef in Taschkent, wird nach Bern versetzt, wo er eine neue Funktion übernehmen wird.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Olivier Chave&lt;/strong&gt;, gegenwärtig Stellvertreter des Ständigen Vertreters der Schweiz mit Ministertitel bei der Ernährungs- und Landwirtschaftsorganisation der Vereinten Nationen (FAO), beim Internationalen Fonds für landwirtschaftliche Entwicklung (IFAD) und beim Welternährungsprogramm (WFP) in Rom wurde zum ausserordentlichen und bevollmächtigten Botschafter in der Republik Usbekistan ernannt.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Nicolas Lang&lt;/strong&gt;, gegenwärtig Sonderbotschafter für das humanitäre Völkerrecht bei der Ständigen Mission der Schweiz beim Büro der Vereinten Nationen und den anderen internationalen Organisationen in Genf, wurde zum ausserordentlichen und bevollmächtigten Botschafter in der Republik Angola und der Demokratischen Republik São Tomé und Príncipe, mit Sitz in Luanda, ernannt. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Jean-Pierre Reymond&lt;/strong&gt;, gegenwärtig stellvertretender Missionschef in Kairo, wurde zum neuen Sonderbotschafter für das humanitäre Völkerrecht bei der Ständigen Mission der Schweiz beim Büro der Vereinten Nationen und den anderen internationalen Organisationen in Genf ernannt. Für diese Funktion hat ihm der Bundesrat den Botschaftertitel verliehen. &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Information EDA +41 58 462 31 53 info@eda.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Nominations et transferts de chefs de mission, octroi d’un titre d’ambassadeur</title>
      <lead>Des changements de personnel auront lieu en 2017 dans plusieurs représentations suisses à l’étranger ainsi qu’à la centrale du Département fédéral des affaires étrangères (DFAE). Ils coïncident avec la cadence usuelle des transferts et font suite à des décisions du Conseil fédéral. Les nominations de chefs de mission à l’étranger deviendront effectives au moment où les autorités de l’État hôte leur accorderont leur agrément. </lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Stefan Klötzli&lt;/strong&gt;, actuellement Chef de mission à Tachkent, sera transféré à Berne où une autre fonction lui sera confiée.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Olivier Chave&lt;/strong&gt;, actuellement Représentant permanent adjoint de la Suisse, avec le titre de ministre, auprès de l’Organisation pour l’alimentation et l’agriculture (FAO), du Fonds international de développement agricole (FIDA) et du Programme alimentaire mondial (PAM) à Rome, a été nommé ambassadeur extraordinaire et plénipotentiaire en République d’Ouzbékistan.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Nicolas Lang&lt;/strong&gt;, actuellement ambassadeur en mission spéciale pour le droit international humanitaire à la Mission permanente de la Suisse auprès de l’Office des Nations Unies et des autres organisations internationales à Genève, a été nommé ambassadeur extraordinaire et plénipotentiaire en République d’Angola et en République démocratique de São Tomé-et-Principe, avec résidence à Luanda. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Jean-Pierre Reymond&lt;/strong&gt;, actuellement chef de mission suppléant au Caire, a reçu le titre d’ambassadeur pour l’exercice de sa nouvelle fonction comme ambassadeur en mission spéciale pour le droit international humanitaire à la Mission permanente de la Suisse auprès de l’Office des Nations Unies et des autres organisations internationales à Genève. &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Information DFAE +41 58 462 31 53 info@eda.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Nomine e trasferimenti di capimissione, conferimento del titolo di ambasciatore</title>
      <lead>Nel 2017 presso varie rappresentanze della Svizzera all’estero e alla Centrale del Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri (DFAE) avranno luogo avvicendamenti di personale. Tali avvicendamenti si inscrivono nei consueti ritmi di trasferimento e nelle nomine decise dal Consiglio federale. Le nomine dei capimissione all’estero diventeranno effettive nel momento in cui le autorità dello Stato di accreditamento concederanno il proprio gradimento.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Stefan Klötzli&lt;/strong&gt;, attualmente capomissione a Tashkent, sarà trasferito a Berna o gli sarà attribuita un’altra funzione.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Olivier Chave&lt;/strong&gt;, attualmente rappresentante permanente aggiunto della Svizzera, con il titolo di ministro, presso l’Organizzazione delle Nazioni Unite per l’alimentazione e l’agricoltura (FAO), il Fondo internazionale per lo sviluppo agricolo (FISA) e il Programma alimentare mondiale (PAM) a Roma, è stato nominato ambasciatore straordinario e plenipotenziario nella Repubblica dell’Uzbekistan.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Nicolas Lang&lt;/strong&gt;, attualmente ambasciatore in missione speciale per il diritto internazionale umanitario in seno alla Missione permanente della Svizzera presso l’Ufficio delle Nazioni Unite e le altre organizzazioni internazionali a Ginevra, è stato nominato ambasciatore straordinario e plenipotenziario nella Repubblica d’Angola e nella Repubblica democratica di São Tomé e Príncipe, con residenza a Luanda. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Jean-Pierre Reymond&lt;/strong&gt;, attualmente capomissione supplente al Cairo, ha ricevuto il titolo di ambasciatore per l’esercizio della sua nuova funzione di ambasciatore in missione speciale per il diritto internazionale umanitario in seno alla Missione permanente della Svizzera presso l’Ufficio delle Nazioni Unite e le altre organizzazioni internazionali a Ginevra. &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Informazione DFAE +41 58 462 31 53 info@eda.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Appointments and transfers of heads of mission, and conferring of the title of ambassador</title>
      <lead>A number of personnel changes will be made in 2017 in Swiss representations abroad and at the head office of the Federal Department of Foreign Affairs (FDFA). The changes will take place as part of the usual transfer rotation and on the basis of decisions by the Federal Council. The appointments of heads of mission abroad become effective following approval by the respective host state. </lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Stefan Klötzli&lt;/strong&gt;, currently head of mission in Tashkent, will be transferred to Bern where he will be assigned a new function.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Olivier Chave&lt;/strong&gt;, currently Deputy Permanent Representative of Switzerland (with the title of minister) at the Food and Agriculture Organization of the United Nations (FAO), the International Fund for Agricultural Development (IFAD) and the World Food Programme (WFP) in Rome, has been appointed ambassador extraordinary and plenipotentiary to the Republic of Uzbekistan.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Nicolas Lang&lt;/strong&gt;, currently ambassador-at-large for international humanitarian law at the Permanent Mission of Switzerland to the United Nations Office and to the other international organisations in Geneva, has been appointed ambassador extraordinary and plenipotentiary to the Republic of Angola and the Democratic Republic of São Tomé and Príncipe, based in Luanda. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Jean-Pierre Reymond&lt;/strong&gt;, currently deputy head of mission in Cairo, has been conferred with the title of ambassador to allow him to carry out his new function as ambassador-at-large for international humanitarian law at the Permanent Mission of Switzerland to the United Nations Office and to the other international organisations in Geneva. &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>FDFA Information +41 58 462 31 53 info@eda.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
