<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="66771" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2017-05-18</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="1076" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>701</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Rat der Eidgenössischen Technischen Hochschulen</name>
      <name lang="fr">Conseil des écoles polytechniques fédérales</name>
      <name lang="it">Consiglio dei politecnici federali</name>
      <name lang="en">Board of the Swiss Federal Institutes of Technology</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.ethrat.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.ethrat.ch/fr</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.ethrat.ch/it</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.ethrat.ch/en</www>
      <email lang="de">gian.casutt@ethrat.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">gian.casutt@ethrat.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">gian.casutt@ethrat.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">gian.casutt@ethrat.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="701">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Wirtschaft, Bildung und Forschung</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'économie, de la formation et de la recherche</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'economia, della formazione e della ricerca</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Economic Affairs, Education and Research</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern/Zürich</city>
      <title>Kürzungen gefährden die Spitzenpositionen des ETH-Bereichs</title>
      <lead>Der ETH-Rat hat an der Sitzung vom 17. Mai 2017 über seine Finanz- und Investitionsplanung für das Jahr 2018 entschieden. Durch die Sparvorgaben des Bundes steht dem ETH-Bereich 2018 weniger Geld zur Verfügung als im laufenden Jahr. Damit wird ein Leistungsabbau notwendig werden. Der ETH-Rat sieht in diesem Abbau eine Gefahr für den Innovationsstandort Schweiz.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Der ETH-Rat verabschiedete die Zielvereinbarungen mit den Institutionen sowie die Finanz- und Investitionsplanung. Dazu gehören das Budget, der Investitionskredit sowie das Bauprogramm für das kommende Jahr. Nachdem der Bundesrat eine Teuerungskorrektur beschlossen hatte, ist auch der ETH-Rat gehalten, diese Massnahme des Bundes umzusetzen. Die Institutionen des ETH-Bereichs, zu denen die ETH Zürich, die EPFL in Lausanne, das Paul Scherrer Institut PSI, die WSL, die Empa und die Eawag gehören, müssen damit eine Kürzung der Bundesmittel von 3% in Kauf nehmen. Dazu kommt für den ETH-Bereich eine jährliche Verzichtsplanung von zusätzlich 20 Mio. Franken pro Jahr für die Jahre 2018–2020. Damit belaufen sich die Budgeteinsparungen auf rund 90 Mio. CHF pro Jahr im gesamten ETH-Bereich.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Die neuesten Sparvorgaben bereiten dem Präsidenten des ETH-Rats, Fritz Schiesser, Sorgen: «Wir haben im Jahr 2018 weniger Geld zur Verfügung als 2017. Das bedeutet, wir können einige der geplanten Investitionen nicht tätigen. Für die Zukunft hat dies auch negative Auswirkungen auf die Innovationskraft der Schweizer Wirtschaft.» Für den ETH-Rat ist es daher wichtig, dass die beiden ETH und die vier Forschungsanstalten ihre ausgezeichnete internationale Reputation behalten.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2&gt;Der ETH-Bereich als Innovationstreiber der Schweizer Wirtschaft&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;Die Schweiz ist seit neun Jahren Innovationsweltmeister im Ranking von Mercer. Sollten die beiden ETH in den Rankings zurückfallen, wird sich dies auf die Schweizer Wirtschaft auswirken. Der ETH-Bereich bildet Spitzenarbeitskräfte aus, die ihr an den Hochschulen erworbenes Wissen in die Industrie und KMU tragen und dort für technologischen Fortschritt und Innovation sorgen. Die Institutionen des ETH-Bereichs ziehen in ihrem Umfeld immer wieder grosse Firmen an, die Arbeitsplätze schaffen und Wertschöpfung generieren, darunter Firmen wie Google, IBM, Facebook. Zudem profitieren die Schweizer KMU und Industriekonzerne ebenfalls von diesem Wissen durch Technologietransfer. Allein die Empa hat rund 400 laufende Kooperationen, die meisten davon mit Schweizer KMU.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2&gt;Investitionen in die Bildung sind zukunftsweisend&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;In verschiedenen Rankings belegen die beiden ETH in Zürich und Lausanne Spitzenpositionen, welche die Leistungsfähigkeit des Bildungs-, Forschungs- und Innovationsstandorts Schweiz zeigen, und erinnern Fritz Schiesser dabei an Roger Federer und Stanislas Wawrinka: «Sowohl die beiden ETH als auch Federer und Wawrinka zeigen, dass auch ein kleines Land wie die Schweiz es weit bringen kann. Wir müssen aus diesen Qualitäten wirtschaftlich Kapital schlagen», sagt der Präsident des ETH-Rats. «Die Digitalisierung schreitet rasch voran und nur jene Länder, die beste Voraussetzungen für eine innovative Wirtschaft schaffen, werden in einigen Jahren zur Spitze gehören. Die Weltklasse-Forschung aus dem ETH-Bereich stärkt den Industrieplatz und Arbeitsmarkt der Schweiz. Der ETH-Bereich ist somit die Lokomotive der Innovation im digitalen Zeitalter, so wie er es bereits im 19. Jahrhundert bei der Eisenbahn, der chemischen Industrie und im Maschinenbau war.» Damals legten die Politiker mit dem Auftrag an die Eidgenössische Technische Hochschule, Fachkräfte unter anderem in der chemischen Industrie auszubilden, den Grundstein für den Basler Chemiestandort. Dank der liberalen Gesetzgebung und dem Wissen der ETH-Ingenieure wurde die Schweiz schon Anfang des 20. Jahrhunderts zur zweitgrössten Chemienation der Welt, hinter Deutschland und vor Grossbritannien und Frankreich. «Diesen visionären Blick braucht die Politik auch im Zeitalter der Digitalisierung», so Fritz Schiesser.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2&gt;Massnahmen zur Förderung der Gleichstellung im ETH-Bereich&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;Der ETH-Rat hatte vorgegeben, dass rund 0,4% der Finanzmittel für Massnahmen zur Förderung der Gleichstellung von Mann und Frau aufgewendet werden müssen. In ihren Berichten zeigten die sechs Institutionen des ETH-Bereichs die vielfältigen Massnahmen, die sie umgesetzt hatten. Dazu gehört die Finanzierung von Kinderbetreuung, wenn die Forscherinnen ihre Arbeit an einer internationalen Konferenz vorstellen. Die Hochschulen bieten auch mehr Krippenplätze an, veranstalten Workshops darüber, wie Frauen für die Forschung gewonnen werden können, führen Mentoringprogramme für junge Forscherinnen durch und vieles mehr. Insgesamt sind immer noch zu wenige Frauen in den technischen Disziplinen tätig.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2&gt;Forschungsprojekte&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;Der ETH-Rat nahm Kenntnis von den Schlussberichten der Kompetenzzentren «CCES Competence Center Environment and Sustainability» und «CCMX Competence Center for Materials Science and Technology». Beide Kompetenzzentren haben einen grossen Beitrag dazu geleistet, neue Forschungsprojekte und Forschungskooperationen im ETH-Bereich zu ermöglichen. Einerseits beim Thema Umwelt und Nachhaltigkeit und andererseits im Bereich Materialwissenschaften und Technologie. Die Kompetenzzentren sind im Jahr 2006 gegründet worden und haben zu einer stärkeren Zusammenarbeit im ETH-Bereich und in der gesamten Hochschullandschaft Schweiz geführt.&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Gian-Andri Casutt Leiter Kommunikation des ETH-Rats Häldeliweg 15, CH-8092 Zürich gian.casutt@ethrat.ch +41 44 632 20 03</contact>
      <link id="166748">
        <title>Medienmitteilung ETH-Rat vom 18. Mai 2017</title>
        <uri>http://www.ethrat.ch/de/medien-medienmitteilungen-news/kuerzungen-gefaehrden-die-spitzenpositionen-des-eth-bereichs</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne/Zurich</city>
      <title>Les coupes budgétaires compromettent les atouts du Domaine des EPF</title>
      <lead>Le Conseil des EPF a défini la planification financière et la planification des investissements pour 2018 lors de sa séance du 17 mai 2017. Les ressources à la disposition du Domaine des EPF l’an prochain diminueront par rapport à celles de cette année en raison des mesures d’économie fixées par la Confédération. Il s’agira dès lors de réduire les prestations, une évolution que le Conseil des EPF considère néfaste pour la Suisse en tant que creuset de l’innovation.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Le Conseil des EPF a adopté les conventions d’objectifs passées avec les institutions ainsi que la planification financière et la planification des investissements, dont font partie le budget, le crédit d’investissement et le programme des constructions pour l’année à venir. Le Conseil fédéral ayant décidé de procéder à une correction du renchérissement, le Conseil des EPF est lui aussi tenu de mettre en œuvre cette mesure de la Confédération. Les institutions du Domaine des EPF, à savoir l’ETH Zurich, l’EPFL, le PSI, le WSL, l’Empa et l’Eawag, devront par conséquent supporter une réduction des fonds fédéraux de 3%. Le Domaine des EPF devra en outre économiser 20 millions de francs supplémentaires par an entre 2018 et 2020 dans le cadre de la planification annuelle des projets auxquels il faudra renoncer. Les économies budgétaires se chiffreront ainsi à quelque 90 millions de francs par an pour tout le Domaine des EPF.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Les récentes mesures d’économie inquiètent le président du Conseil des EPF, Fritz Schiesser: «Nous aurons moins d’argent à disposition en 2018 qu’en 2017, ce qui signifie que nous ne pourrons pas procéder aux investissements initialement prévus. A plus longue échéance, cela aura aussi des consé­quences néfastes sur la capacité d’innovation de l’économie suisse.» Le Conseil des EPF estime dès lors important que les deux EPF et les quatre établissements de recherche conservent leur excellente réputation internationale.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2&gt;Le Domaine des EPF, moteur de l’innovation pour l’économie suisse&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;Selon l’indice Mercer, la Suisse se trouve en tête des pays les plus innovants du monde depuis neuf ans. Une rétrogradation des deux EPF dans les classements ne resterait pas sans conséquence pour l’économie suisse. Le Domaine des EPF forme des spécialistes hautement qualifiés, qui font ensuite profiter leurs employeurs dans l’industrie et les PME du savoir acquis en milieu universitaire et y favorisent l’innovation ainsi que le progrès technologique. Les institutions du Domaine des EPF attirent régulièrement de grandes entreprises créatrices d’emplois et de valeur ajoutée, telles que Google, IBM et Facebook. Les PME et les groupes industriels suisses profitent également de ce savoir grâce au transfert de technologie. A lui seul, l’Empa participe à quelque 400 coopérations, la plupart avec des PME suisses.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2&gt;Investir dans la formation est un acte visionnaire&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;Plusieurs classements placent les deux EPF de Zurich et Lausanne dans le peloton de tête des hautes écoles, ce qui atteste du fait que la formation, la recherche et l’innovation en Suisse sont performantes. Un constat qui rappelle à Fritz Schiesser certains exploits sportifs: «A l’instar de Roger Federer et Stanislas Wawrinka, nos deux EPF montrent de quoi est capable un petit pays comme le nôtre. Nous devons tirer un bénéfice économique de ces qualités, déclare le président du Conseil des EPF. La révolution numérique progres­se à grands pas et seuls les pays aptes à créer des conditions optimales pour une économie novatrice feront partie des meilleurs dans quelques années. La recherche de pointe au niveau mondial telle qu’elle est pratiquée dans le Domaine des EPF renforce la place industrielle et l’emploi en Suisse. C’est ainsi que le Domaine des EPF est la locomotive de l’innovation à l’ère du numérique, un rôle qui a été le sien dès le XIXe siècle dans des secteurs comme le rail, l’industrie chimique et l’industrie mécanique.» En chargeant l’Ecole polytechnique fédérale de former des spécialistes, entre autres pour l’industrie chimique, les responsables politiques d’alors posaient ainsi la première pierre du bastion de la chimie bâloise. La Suisse a réussi à devenir dès le début du XXe siècle la deuxième plus grande nation chimique du monde, derrière l’Allemagne et devant la Grande-Bretagne et la France, grâce à une législation libérale et au savoir des ingénieurs EPF. «La politique à l’ère du numérique a besoin de cet élan visionnaire», affirme Fritz Schiesser.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2&gt;Mesures d’encouragement de l’égalité dans le Domaine des EPF&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;Sur décision du Conseil des EPF, environ 0,4% des ressources financières doivent être utilisées pour des mesures d’encouragement de l’égalité entre hommes et femmes. Les six institutions du Domaine des EPF ont évoqué dans leurs comptes rendus respectifs les mesures très diverses qu’elles ont réalisées. Il s’agit p. ex. du financement de modèles de gardes d’enfants qui permettent aux chercheuses de se rendre à des conférences dans le monde entier pour présenter leurs travaux. Les hautes écoles proposent aussi, entre autres choses, un plus grand nombre de places de crèche, et elles organisent des workshops sur la façon d’inciter davantage de femmes à s’intéresser à la recherche ainsi que des programmes de mentorat destinés aux jeunes chercheuses. D’une manière générale, les femmes restent sous-représentées dans les disciplines techniques.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2&gt;Projets de recherche&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;Le Conseil des EPF a pris acte des rapports finaux du Centre de compétences en environnement et durabilité (CCES) et du Centre de compétences en science et technologie des matériaux (CCMX), qui ont tous deux largement contribué à la réalisation de nouveaux projets et coopérations de recherche dans le Domaine des EPF. Fondés en 2006, ces centres de compétences ont permis de renforcer la collaboration au sein du Domaine des EPF et dans l’ensemble du paysage suisse des hautes écoles.&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Gian-Andri Casutt Responsable de la communication du Conseil des EPF Häldeliweg 15, CH-8092 Zurich gian.casutt@ethrat.ch +41 44 632 20 03</contact>
      <link id="166749">
        <title>Communiqué de presse du CEPF du 18 mai 2017</title>
        <uri>http://www.ethrat.ch/fr/medien-medienmitteilungen-news/les-coupes-budgetaires-compromettent-les-atouts-du-domaine-des-epf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Berne/Zurich</city>
      <title>Cuts jeopardise top positions of the ETH Domain</title>
      <lead>At its meeting of 17 May 2017, the ETH Board made decisions concerning its financial and investment planning for 2018. Due to the Confederation’s cost-cutting targets, less money will be available to the ETH Domain in 2018 than in the current year. This entails a reduction of services. The ETH Board regards this reduction as a hazard for Switzerland as a centre of innovation.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;The ETH Board adopted the target agreements with the institutions, as well as the financial and investment planning. This includes the budget, the investment loan and the construction programme for the coming year. After the Federal Council had resolved to introduce an inflation adjustment, the ETH Board is also being called upon to implement this federal measure. The institutions of the ETH Domain, which include ETH Zurich, EPFL, the Paul Scherrer Institute PSI, WSL, Empa and Eawag, will have to accept a cut of 3% in federal resources. Furthermore, the ETH Domain is facing annual retrenchment plans of an additional 20m CHF for 2018–2020. Thus the budget cuts amount to approx. 90m CHF annually in the ETH Domain as a whole.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The latest cost-cutting targets worry the President of the ETH Board, Fritz Schiesser: “There will be less money available to us in 2018 than in 2017. This means that we’ll be unable to make some of the investments we planned. In the future, this will also have a negative impact on the Swiss economy’s innovative power.” For this reason, the ETH Board considers it to be important that the two Federal Institutes of Technology and the four research institutes retain their excellent international reputation.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2&gt;The ETH Domain: an innovation driver for the Swiss economy&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;Switzerland has been world innovation champion in the Mercer ranking for nine years. If the two Federal Institutes of Technology should lose ground in the rankings, this will have an impact on the Swiss economy. The ETH Domain educates top-grade employees who transfer the knowledge they have acquired at the universities into industry and SMEs and ensure technological progress and innovation there. Time and again, the environment of the institutions of the ETH Domain attracts big firms which create jobs and generate value creation, among them Google, IBM and Facebook. Moreover, Swiss SMEs and industrial groups are also able to profit from this knowledge thanks to technology transfer. Empa alone is running about 400 cooperation ventures, most of them with Swiss SMEs.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2&gt;Investments in education are future-oriented&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;ETH Zurich and EPFL occupy top positions in various rankings, which display the effectiveness of Switzerland as a centre of education, research and innovation, and they remind Fritz Schiesser of Roger Federer and Stanislas Wawrinka: “Both the two Federal Institutes of Technology and Federer and Wawrinka show that even a small country like Switzerland is able to go far. We must turn these qualities into economic capital,” says the President of the ETH Board. “Digitalisation is proceeding apace, and only those countries which create the best conditions for an innovative economy will be at the top in a few years’ time. World-class research from the ETH Domain strengthens Switzerland’s industry and labour market. Thus the ETH Domain is an engine of innovation in the digital age, just as it was for the railways, the chemical industry and machine-building in the 19th century.” At that time, politicians instructed the Federal Institute of Technology to educate specialists in the field of chemical industry, for example, thus laying the cornerstones for Basel’s chemical industry. Thanks to liberal legislation and the ETH engineers’ knowledge, Switzerland became the world’s second biggest chemical nation already at the beginning of the 20th century, behind Germany and in front of the UK and France. “Politicians also need this visionary perspective in the era of digitalisation,” says Fritz Schiesser.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2&gt;Measures for the promotion of equality in the ETH Domain&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;The ETH Board had set the target that approx. 0.4% of financial resources would have to be expended on measures for the promotion of equality between men and women. In their reports, the six institutions of the ETH Domain reveal the various measures that they implemented. This includes the funding of childcare in cases where women researchers present their work at international conferences. The Universities also offer more crèche places, run workshops on how women can be attracted to research, organise mentoring programmes for young women researchers and much more. All in all, still too few women work in the technical disciplines.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2&gt;Research projects&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;The ETH Board took note of the final reports of the CCES Competence Center Environment and Sustainability and CCMX Competence Center for Materials Science and Technology. Both competence centres have made a great contribution towards the launch of new research projects and research cooperation ventures in the ETH Domain, on the one hand in the field of environment and sustainability, and on the other hand in material sciences and technology. The competence centres were set up in 2006 and have resulted in more intensive cooperation within the ETH Domain and in Switzerland’s university landscape as a whole.&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Gian-Andri Casutt Head of Communication of the ETH Board Häldeliweg 15, CH-8092 Zurich gian.casutt@ethrat.ch +41 44 632 20 03</contact>
      <link id="166750">
        <title>Media Release ETH-Board, 18 May 2017</title>
        <uri>http://www.ethrat.ch/en/medien-medienmitteilungen-news/cuts-jeopardise-top-positions-eth-domain</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="8">
        <name lang="de">Bildung und Forschung</name>
        <name lang="fr">Formation et recherche</name>
        <name lang="it">Formazione e ricerca</name>
        <name lang="en">Education and Research</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
