<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="66783" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2017-05-19</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="201" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>201</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="201">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Ministertreffen des Europarats: Bundesrat Didier Burkhalter plädiert für die Stärkung der gemeinsamen Werte der 47 Mitgliedstaaten</title>
      <lead>Anlässlich der Eröffnung der 127. Tagung des Ministerkomitees des Europarats in Nikosia hat Bundesrat Didier Burkhalter die 47 Mitgliedstaaten am Freitag aufgerufen, die gemeinsamen Werte zu stärken. Gemäss dem Vorsteher des Eidgenössischen Departements für auswärtige Angelegenheiten (EDA) verfügt der Europarat über ein gut ausgebautes Schutzsystem, das die Grundrechte und Grundfreiheiten auf europäischer Ebene verankert, gleichzeitig aber die Souveränität der Staaten wahrt.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Der Europarat ist die wichtigste zwischenstaatliche Organisation zum Schutz der Menschenrechte in Europa. Er beschliesst die einschlägigen Regeln und Standards und ermuntert die Mitgliedstaaten, seinen Übereinkommen beizutreten und die Normen anzuwenden. Zudem wacht er darüber, dass die Staaten ihre Verpflichtungen einhalten. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Nach Ansicht von Bundesrat Burkhalter erfordert die Situation in der Türkei besondere Aufmerksamkeit. «Die Schweiz anerkennt die schwierige Situation der Türkei nach dem dramatischen Putschversuch. Wir setzen uns deshalb für die Weiterführung des Dialogs und der konstruktiven Zusammenarbeit mit Ankara ein», sagte der Vorsteher des EDA. Er forderte die Türkei auf, «den Weg weiterzuverfolgen, den das Land in den letzten Jahren selbst eingeschlagen hat: den Weg der demokratischen Werte, des Rechtsstaats und der Menschenrechte.»&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Bundesrat Burkhalter plädierte auch dafür, Lösungen für die Bevölkerung bestimmter Regionen, etwa der Krim oder von Gebieten mit eingefrorenen Konflikten, zu erarbeiten, damit diese Menschen ebenfalls vom Schutzsystem des Europarats profitieren können. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Des Weiteren verabschiedeten die Ministerinnen und Minister Richtlinien für den Schutz von Terroropfern und einen Aktionsplan zum Schutz von Flüchtlings- und Migrationskindern. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Am Rande der Tagung traf der Vorsteher des Eidgenössischen Departements für auswärtige Angelegenheiten mehrere Amtskollegen, darunter den zypriotischen Aussenminister Ioannis Kasoulides, mit dem er insbesondere die Zypernfrage und den Schutz von Kulturgütern besprach. Des Weiteren diskutierten die beiden Amtskollegen über das Verhältnis zwischen der Schweiz und der Europäischen Union.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Kommunikation EDA Bundeshaus West CH-3003 Bern Tel. Kommunikationsservice: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Medienstelle: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <link id="166778">
        <title>Rede von Bundesrat Didier Burkhalter anlässlich der 127. Jahrestagung des Ministerkomitees des Europarats</title>
        <uri>https://www.admin.ch/gov/de/start/dokumentation/reden/reden-der-bundesraete.msg-id-66776.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Ministérielle du Conseil de l’Europe : le conseiller fédéral Didier Burkhalter plaide pour un renforcement des valeurs communes aux 47 pays membres</title>
      <lead>Le conseiller fédéral Didier Burkhalter a appelé, vendredi à Nicosie lors de l’ouverture de la 127ème session ministérielle du Conseil de l’Europe, les 47 pays membres de l’institution à renforcer ensemble les valeurs communes partagées. Le Conseil de l’Europe a mis sur pied un système développé de protection qui respecte la souveraineté des Etats mais ancre au niveau continental la protection des libertés et des droits fondamentaux, a poursuivi le chef du Département fédéral des affaires étrangères (DFAE).</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Principale organisation intergouvernementale de défense des droits de l’homme sur le continent, le Conseil de l’Europe définit les règles et les standards en la matière. Il encourage les Etats membres à appliquer les normes en adhérant aux conventions qu’il élabore et veille à ce qu’ils respectent leurs engagements. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;M. Burkhalter a estimé que la situation en Turquie demandait une attention particulière. « La Suisse reconnaît la situation difficile de ce pays au moment de la dramatique tentative de coup d’Etat et nous soutenons la voie du dialogue et de la coopération constructive avec Ankara », a-t-il ajouté avant d’encourager la Turquie « à poursuivre le chemin qu’elle avait elle-même tracé ces dernières années : un chemin qui était pavé des valeurs de démocratie, d’Etat de droit et de droits de l’homme. »&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Le conseiller fédéral a aussi plaidé pour que des solutions soient trouvées pour les habitants de certaines régions, comme la Crimée ou les zones de conflits gelés, et qu’ils puissent également jouir du système de protection garanti par le Conseil de l’Europe. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Les ministres réunis à Nicosie ont également adopté des lignes directrices pour la protection des victimes du terrorisme ainsi qu’un plan d’action pour encourager la protection des migrants et des réfugiés mineurs. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;En marge de la conférence, le chef du Département fédéral des affaires étrangères a rencontré plusieurs de ses homologues dont le ministre des affaires étrangères de la République de Chypre, Ioannis Kasoulides, avec qui il a notamment évoqué le règlement de la question chypriote et la protection des biens culturels. M. Burkhalter a également eu avec son collègue un échange de vue sur les relations entre la Suisse et l’Union européenne.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Communication DFAE Palais fédéral ouest CH-3003 Berne Tél. Service de communication: +41 58 462 31 53 Tél. Service de presse: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <link id="166779">
        <title>Discours du Conseiller fédéral Didier Burkhalter À l’occasion de la 127e session ministérielle du Conseil de l’Europe</title>
        <uri>https://www.admin.ch/gov/fr/accueil/documentation/discours/discours-conseillers-federaux.msg-id-66776.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Riunione del Comitato dei Ministri del Consiglio d’Europa: il consigliere federale Didier Burkhalter chiede di rafforzare i valori condivisi dai 47 Paesi membri</title>
      <lead>Venerdì, in occasione dell’apertura della 127a riunione ministeriale del Consiglio d’Europa a Nicosia, il consigliere federale Didier Burkhalter ha esortato i 47 Paesi membri dell’UE a consolidare i valori condivisi e comuni. Il capo del Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri (DFAE) ha inoltre sottolineato l’importanza del sistema avanzato di protezione introdotto dal Consiglio d’Europa, che rispetta la sovranità degli Stati ma radica a livello continentale la protezione delle libertà e dei diritti fondamentali.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;In qualità di principale organizzazione intergovernativa per la difesa dei diritti umani sul continente, il Consiglio d’Europa definisce le regole e gli standard in questo ambito. Incoraggia inoltre gli Stati membri ad attuare le norme e ad aderire alle convenzioni che elabora, vegliando sulla loro attuazione. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Il consigliere federale Burkhalter ha invitato gli astanti a prestare particolare attenzione alla situazione in Turchia. «La Svizzera è consapevole della situazione difficile in Turchia al momento del drammatico tentativo di colpo di Stato; con il Paese stiamo perseguendo la via del dialogo e della cooperazione costruttiva», ha dichiarato il capo del Dipartimento, prima di incoraggiare la Turchia «a portare avanti il processo che lei stessa aveva avviato negli ultimi anni, incentrato su valori quali la democrazia, lo Stato di diritto e i diritti umani».&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Il consigliere federale ha esortato i presenti a trovare soluzioni adeguate per gli abitanti di alcune regioni europee, come la Crimea o le aree in cui covano «conflitti congelati», affinché possano anch’essi beneficiare del sistema di protezione garantito dal Consiglio d’Europa. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I ministri riunitisi a Nicosia hanno inoltre adottato varie linee guida per la protezione delle vittime del terrorismo e un piano d’azione per incoraggiare la protezione dei migranti e dei profughi minorenni. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A margine della conferenza, il capo del Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri ha incontrato vari suoi omologhi, tra cui il ministro degli affari esteri della Repubblica di Cipro, Ioannis Kasoulides, con il quale ha discusso in particolare della questione cipriota e della protezione dei beni culturali e con cui ha avuto uno scambio di opinioni anche sulle relazioni tra la Svizzera e l’Unione europea.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Comunicazione DFAE Palazzo federale ovest CH-3003 Berna Tel. Servizio di comunicazione: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Servizio stampa: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <link id="166780">
        <title>Discorso del Consigliere federale Didier Burkhalter in occasione della 127a riunione ministeriale del Consiglio d’Europa</title>
        <uri>https://www.admin.ch/gov/it/pagina-iniziale/documentazione/discorsi/discorsi-dei-consiglieri-federali.msg-id-66776.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Ministerial session of the Council of Europe: Federal Councillor Didier Burkhalter calls on the 47 member states to strengthen their common values</title>
      <lead>At the opening of the 127th ministerial session of the Council of Europe on Friday, Federal Councillor Didier Burkhalter, head of the Federal Department of Foreign Affairs, called on the 47 member states to strengthen their common values. The Council of Europe has set up a strong protection system that respects the sovereignty of states and enshrines the protection of fundamental rights and freedoms at the continental level, said Mr Burkhalter.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;As the leading intergovernmental organisation for the defence of human rights on the European continent, the Council of Europe defines the rules and standards in this field. It encourages member states to apply existing standards by acceding to the conventions it draws up and ensures that they fulfil their commitments. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mr Burkhalter noted that the situation in Turkey required particular attention. "Switzerland recognises the difficult situation Turkey faced when the dramatic coup attempt took place, and we support a path of dialogue and constructive cooperation with Ankara,” said Burkhalter. He also encouraged Turkey “to pursue the path that it had itself taken in recent years: a path built on the values of democracy, the rule of law and human rights.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mr Burkhalter also called for solutions to be found for the inhabitants of regions such as Crimea or frozen conflict zones to ensure that they can also benefit from the protection system guaranteed by the Council of Europe. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The ministers assembled in Nicosia also adopted guidelines for the protection of victims of terrorism and a plan of action to encourage the protection of migrants and underage refugees. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the margins of the conference, Mr Burkhalter met with several of his counterparts, including the Minister for Foreign Affairs of the Republic of Cyprus, Ioannis Kasoulides, with whom he talked about the settlement of the Cyprus question and the protection of cultural property. The two men also exchanged views on relations between Switzerland and the European Union.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>FDFA Communication Federal Palace West Wing CH-3003 Bern, Switzerland Tel. Communication service: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Press service: +41 58 460 55 55 E-mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @SwissMFA</contact>
      <link id="166781">
        <title>Speech by the Federal Councillor Didier Burkhalter on the occasion of the 127th ministerial session of the Council of Europe (CoE)</title>
        <uri>https://www.admin.ch/gov/en/start/documentation/speeches/speeches-given-by-federal-councillors.msg-id-66776.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
