<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="67248" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2017-06-23</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="711" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>701</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Kommission für Technologie und Innovation KTI – ab 1.1.2018 Innosuisse - Schweizerische Agentur für Innovationsförderung</name>
      <name lang="fr">Commission pour la technologie et l’innovation - dès 1.1.2018 Innosuisse – Agence suisse pour l’encouragement de l’innovation</name>
      <name lang="it">Commissione per la tecnologia e l’innovazione - a partire dal 1.1.2018 Innosuisse – Agenzia svizzera per la promozione dell’innovazione</name>
      <name lang="en">Commission for Technology and Innovation - as of 1.1.2018 Innosuisse – Swiss Innovation Promotion Agency</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.kti.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.kti.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.kti.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.kti.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">media@kti.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">media@kti.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">media@kti.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">media@kti.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="701">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Wirtschaft, Bildung und Forschung</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'économie, de la formation et de la recherche</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'economia, della formazione e della ricerca</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Economic Affairs, Education and Research</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>KTI richtet Trainingsmodule für Jungunternehmen neu aus</title>
      <lead>Die Kommission für Technologie und Innovation KTI bzw. Innosuisse – Schweizerische Agentur für Innovationsförderung ändert auf Anfang 2018 die Ausrichtung der Module 3 und 4 ihres Trainingsangebots für Jungunternehmer. Neu werden branchenspezifische Kurse zu den Themen ICT, Advanced Engineering, Biotechnology/Pharmaceuticals with Medical Technology und Social Entrepreneurship angeboten. Den Zuschlag zur Ausrichtung für die nächsten fünf Jahre erhielten das IFJ Institut für Jungunternehmen AG und die ZHAW School of Management and Law.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Bei den Modulen 3 und 4 des Ausbildungsprogramms für Jungunternehmer handelt es sich um je fünftägige Kurse zu den Themen «Business Creation» und «Business Development». In diesen Kursen erhalten Jungunternehmer konkrete Antworten auf ihre projekt- und unternehmensspezifischen Fragen und festigen ihr Wissen. Zudem analysieren sie die Barrieren, Chancen und Märkte ihrer Branche und entwickeln Wachstumsstrategien.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Die Kurse wurden bis anhin über alle wissenschaftsbasierten Themenfelder hinweg gemeinsam durchgeführt. Um dem Bedürfnis nach Austausch mit Gründern aus der gleichen Branche besser gerecht zu werden, hat sich die KTI entschieden, die Kurse ab 2018 in vier Themenclustern anzubieten. Neu beinhalten die Kurse für jedes Start-up zudem ein dreistündiges Coaching. Die Kurse werden in der ganzen Schweiz angeboten. Jährlich nehmen rund 450 Teilnehmerinnen und Teilnehmer an den Modulen 3 und 4 teil.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Die Kurse zu den Themen ICT, Advanced Engineering, Biotechnology/Pharmaceuticals with Medical Technology werden vom IFJ Institut für Jungunternehmen AG angeboten, die Kurse zu Social Entrepreneurship von der ZHAW School of Management and Law. Die Ausschreibung erfolgte über ein öffentliches Verfahren.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Die Module 1 und 2 des Trainingsangebots werden im Jahr 2019 ausgeschrieben.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Ü&lt;/b&gt;&lt;b&gt;bersicht&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;IFJ Institut für Jungunternehmen AG: &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Anbieter ab 2018 für&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;ICT (Internetapplikationen, Software etc.)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Advanced Engineering (Micro, Nano, Material Science, Robotics, Climate/Energy)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Biotechnology / Pharmaceuticals with Medical Technology (Medtech, Devices, Mobile Health)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;ZHAW School of Management and Law: &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Anbieter ab 2018 für&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Social Entrepreneurship&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Hohe Zufriedenheit mit Trainingsangebot&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Die Trainingsmodule für Jungunternehmer bieten den Teilnehmerinnen und Teilnehmern einen grossen Mehrwert. Eine von der KTI in Auftrag gegebene Studie zeigt, dass die Zufriedenheit mit dem Angebot insgesamt sehr hoch ist. Die Teilnehmenden erwerben laut eigenen Angaben viele nützliche Kompetenzen und knüpfen in den Kursen wertvolle Kontakte zu potentiellen Geschäftspartnern. Rund die Hälfte der Befragten wünscht sich mehr direktes Coaching. Diesem Wunsch wird in der neuen Ausrichtung der Kurse Rechnung getragen. Alle Informationen zur Studie finden Sie auf www.kti.admin.ch/wirkungsanalyse&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Medienstelle KTI media@kti.admin.ch Tel. +41 58 462 83 63</contact>
      <attachment id="168265">
        <title>Medienmitteilung</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>21</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/48810.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>La CTI réoriente ses modules d’entraînement pour jeunes entreprises</title>
      <lead>La Commission pour la technologie et l’innovation CTI, refondée en tant qu’Innosuisse, Agence suisse pour l’encouragement de l’innovation, réorientera début 2018 les modules 3 et 4 de son offre d’entraînement pour jeunes entreprises. Désormais, des cours spécifiques par branche seront proposés sur les thèmes ICT, Advanced Engineering, Biotechnology/Pharmaceuticals with Medical Technology et Social Entrepreneurship. Le mandat pour l’orientation des cinq prochaines années en la matière a été attribué à IFJ Institut für Jungunternehmen AG et à la ZHAW School of Management and Law.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Les modules 3 et 4 du programme de formation pour jeunes entrepreneurs sont des cours de cinq jours portant sur les thèmes «Business Creation» et «Business Development». Les jeunes entrepreneurs y consolident leur savoir et y reçoivent des réponses concrètes à leurs questions spécifiques relatives à leur projet et leur entreprise. De plus, ils y analysent les barrières, les chances et les marchés propres à leur branche et développent des stratégies de croissance.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Jusqu’à présent, les cours étaient organisés en commun pour tous les champs thématiques fondés sur la science. Afin de mieux répondre au besoin d’échange entre créateurs d’entreprise d’une même branche, la CTI a décidé de proposer les cours en quatre groupes thématiques (clusters) dès 2018. De plus, les cours incluront un coaching de trois heures pour chaque start-up. Ils seront proposés dans toute la Suisse. Chaque année, quelque 450 jeunes entrepreneurs participent aux modules 3 et 4.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Les cours sur les thèmes ICT, Advanced Engineering, Biotechnology/Pharmaceuticals with Medical Technology seront organisés par IFJ Institut für Jungunternehmen AG; les cours sur le thème Social Entrepreneurship, par la ZHAW School of Management and Law. Le mandat a été attribué à ces institutions à l’issue d’une procédure d’appel d’offres publique.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Les modules 1 et 2 de l’offre de formation feront l’objet d’un appel d’offres en 2019.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Aperçu général &lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;IFJ Institut für Jungunternehmen AG: prestataire depuis 2018 pour&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;ICT (applications internet, logiciels, etc.)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Advanced Engineering (Micro, Nano, Material Science, Robotics, Climate/Energy) &lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Biotechnology / Pharmaceuticals with Medical Technology (Medtech, Devices, Mobile Health)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;ZHAW School of Management and Law: prestataire depuis 2018 pour&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Social Entrepreneurship&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Degré de satisfaction élevé à l’égard de l’offre d’entraînement&lt;/b&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Les modules d’entraînement pour jeunes entrepreneurs fournissent une grande valeur ajoutée à leurs participants. Une enquête réalisée à la demande de la CTI montre que globalement, la satisfaction par rapport à l’offre est grande. Selon leurs propres déclarations, les participants acquièrent un grand nombre de compétences utiles dans les cours et y nouent des contacts précieux avec des partenaires d’affaires potentiels. Environ la moitié des participants à l’enquête souhaiterait plus de coaching personnel. La nouvelle orientation des cours répond à ce souhait. Toutes les informations relatives à l’enquête se trouvent à l’adresse www.kti.admin.ch/wirkungsanalyse&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Communication CTI media@kti.admin.ch Tél. +41 58 462 83 63</contact>
      <attachment id="168266">
        <title>Communiqué de presse</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>23</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/48811.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>La CTI ridefinisce i moduli di formazione per neoimprenditori</title>
      <lead>All’inizio del 2018 la Commissione per la tecnologia e l’innovazione, futura Innosuisse (Agenzia svizzera per la promozione dell’innovazione), modificherà i moduli 3 e 4 dell’offerta formativa per neoimprenditori. Da quel momento in poi verranno organizzati corsi settoriali specifici sui seguenti temi: ICT, Advanced Engineering, Biotechnology / Pharmaceuticals with Medical Technology e Social Entrepreneurship. Per i prossimi cinque anni il compito di definire i contenuti è stato assegnato all’Istituto per giovani imprenditori (IFJ) AG e alla ZHAW School of Management and Law.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;I moduli 3 e 4 del programma di formazione per neoimprenditori prevedono corsi di cinque giorni sui temi «Business Creation» e «Business Development». Durante i corsi i partecipanti ricevono risposte alle loro domande specifiche su progetti e aspetti imprenditoriali e consolidano le proprie conoscenze. Inoltre, analizzano gli ostacoli, le opportunità e i mercati del loro settore e mettono a punto strategie di crescita.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Finora le persone provenienti dai più svariati settori scientifici frequentavano insieme gli stessi corsi. Tuttavia, per venire incontro all’esigenza dei partecipanti di confrontarsi con imprenditori del loro stesso settore, la CTI ha deciso di suddividere i corsi in quattro cluster tematici a partire dal 2018. Per ogni start-up è previsto un coaching di tre ore. I corsi vengono offerti in tutta la Svizzera. Ai moduli 3 e 4 partecipano ogni anno circa 450 persone.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;I corsi ICT, Advanced Engineering e Biotechnology/Pharmaceuticals with Medical Technology sono organizzati dall’Istituto per giovani imprenditori (IFJ) AG, mentre quelli del settore Social Entrepreneurship dalla ZHAW School of Management and Law. L’aggiudicazione è avvenuta secondo la procedura pubblica.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Il bando di concorso per i moduli di formazione 1 e 2 verrà pubblicato nel 2019. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Sommario&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Istituto per giovani imprenditori (IFJ) AG: organizzatori dal 2018 per&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;ICT (Internetapplikationen, Software etc.)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Advanced Engineering (Micro, Nano, Material Science, Robotics, Climate/Energy)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Biotechnology / Pharmaceuticals with Medical Technology (Medtech, Devices, Mobile Health)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;ZHAW School of Management and Law: organizzatori dal 2018 per&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Social Entrepreneurship&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Grande soddisfazione&lt;/b&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I moduli di formazione per giovani imprenditori offrono ai partecipanti un notevole valore aggiunto. Uno studio commissionato dalla CTI dimostra che riscuotono un ampio successo. I partecipanti, infatti, affermano di aver acquisito molte competenze utili e di aver avviato contatti importanti con potenziali partner commerciali. Circa la metà degli intervistati auspica un coaching più diretto. La nuova impostazione dei corsi tiene conto di questa richiesta. Per maggiori informazioni sullo studio consultare la pagina www.kti.admin.ch/wirkungsanalyse&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Servizio media CTI media@kti.admin.ch Tel. +41 58 462 83 63</contact>
      <attachment id="168267">
        <title>Comunicato stampa</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>21</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/48812.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>CTI adapting training modules for young entrepreneurs</title>
      <lead>The Commission for Technology and Innovation CTI, soon to be known as Innosuisse – the Swiss Agency for Innovation Promotion – will be adapting modules 3 and 4 of its train-ing programme for young entrepreneurs with effect from the beginning of 2018. The programme will offer sector-specific courses tailored to the following clusters: ICT, Advanced Engineering, Biotechnology/Pharmaceuticals, Medical Technology and Social Entrepreneurship. The tenders for the next five years were awarded to IFJ Institut für Jungunternehmen AG and ZHAW School of Management and Law.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Modules 3 and 4 of the training programme for young entrepreneurs consist of five-day courses on the topics of ‘Business Creation’ and ‘Business Development’. In these courses young entrepreneurs receive specific answers to their project and business-related questions and consolidate their knowledge. In addition, they analyse the barriers, opportunities and markets for their sector and develop growth strategies.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Up until now the courses have been run jointly across all science-based fields. In order to better meet the needs of participants to be able to speak with company founders from the same sector, the CTI decided to offer the courses in four clusters from 2018. The courses will now also include a three-hour coaching session for each start-up. The courses will be offered throughout the country. Around 450 entrepreneurs take part in modules 3 and 4 each year.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The courses on the topics of ICT, Advanced Engineering, Biotechnology / Pharmaceuticals with Medical Technology will be provided by &lt;i&gt;IFJ Institut für Jungunternehmen AG&lt;/i&gt; and the courses on Social Entrepreneurship by &lt;i&gt;ZHAW School of Management and Law&lt;/i&gt;. The tenders were awarded to these institutions following a public invitation for bids.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Modules 1 and 2 of the training programme will be advertised for tender in 2019.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Overview&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt; IFJ Institut für Jungunternehmen AG: provider from 2018 for&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;ICT (internet applications, software etc.)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Advanced Engineering (Micro, Nano, Material Science, Robotics, Climate/Energy)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Biotechnology / Pharmaceuticals with Medical Technology (Medtech, Devices, Mobile Health)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;ZHAW School of Management and Law: provider from 2018 for&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Social Entrepreneurship&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;High level of satisfaction with training programme&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The training modules for young entrepreneurs offer participants significant added value. A study commissioned by the CTI shows that satisfaction with the courses available is generally very high. Participants stated that they acquired many useful skills and were able to make valuable contacts with potential business partners in the courses. Around half of those surveyed expressed a desire to see more direct coaching. This wish will be taken into account in the newly adapted courses. Full details of the study can be found at www.kti.admin.ch/wirkungsanalyse&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>CTI Communications media@kti.admin.ch Tel. +41 58 462 83 63</contact>
      <attachment id="168268">
        <title>Press release</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>23</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/48813.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="8">
        <name lang="de">Bildung und Forschung</name>
        <name lang="fr">Formation et recherche</name>
        <name lang="it">Formazione e ricerca</name>
        <name lang="en">Education and Research</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="45">
        <name lang="de">Technologie</name>
        <name lang="fr">Technologie</name>
        <name lang="it">Tecnologia</name>
        <name lang="en">Technology</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="47">
        <name lang="de">Wirtschaft</name>
        <name lang="fr">Économie</name>
        <name lang="it">Economia</name>
        <name lang="en">Economic Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
