<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="67311" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2017-06-28</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="1070" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>1070</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Der Bundesrat</name>
      <name lang="fr">Conseil fédéral</name>
      <name lang="it">Il Consiglio federale</name>
      <name lang="en">The Federal Council</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.admin.ch/gov/de/start.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.admin.ch/gov/fr/accueil.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.admin.ch/gov/it/pagina-iniziale.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.admin.ch/gov/en/start.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="201" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>201</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="401" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>401</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Justiz- und Polizeidepartement</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de justice et police</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale di giustizia e polizia</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Justice and Police</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.ejpd.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.ejpd.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.ejpd.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.ejpd.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-ejpd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">Info@gs-ejpd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-ejpd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-ejpd.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="1070">
      <name lang="de">Der Bundesrat</name>
      <name lang="fr">Conseil fédéral</name>
      <name lang="it">Il Consiglio federale</name>
      <name lang="en">The Federal Council</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.admin.ch/gov/de/start.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.admin.ch/gov/fr/accueil.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.admin.ch/gov/it/pagina-iniziale.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.admin.ch/gov/en/start.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <department id="201">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <department id="401">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Justiz- und Polizeidepartement</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de justice et police</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale di giustizia e polizia</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Justice and Police</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.ejpd.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.ejpd.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.ejpd.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.ejpd.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-ejpd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">Info@gs-ejpd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-ejpd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-ejpd.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Der Bundesrat zieht Bilanz über die Umsetzung der Menschenrechte in der Schweiz</title>
      <lead>Der Bundesrat hat den Dritten Staatenbericht der Schweiz zur allgemeinen regelmässigen Überprüfung (UPR) verabschiedet, der im November 2017 dem UNO-Menschenrechtsrat vorgelegt werden soll. Der Bericht zieht Bilanz über die Menschenrechtssituation in der Schweiz und die wichtigsten Massnahmen, die in den vergangenen Jahren in diesem Bereich ergriffen wurden.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Die allgemeine regelmässige Überprüfung (UPR) ist ein wichtiger internationaler Mechanismus zum Monitoring der Menschenrechtslage. Jeder UNO-Mitgliedstaat wird im Fünfjahresrhythmus in einem sogenannten Peer-Review-Verfahren von den anderen Staaten überprüft. Die Empfehlungen,die gegenüber den einzelnen Staaten formuliert werden, bilden eine wichtige Grundlage, um deren Bemühungen zur Verbesserung der Menschenrechtslage zu stärken. Die dritte Länderprüfung der Schweiz vor dem Menschenrechtsrat findet im November 2017 statt. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Der vom Bundesrat verabschiedete Staatenbericht stützt sich auf die 99 Empfehlungen, welche die Schweiz im Rahmen des Zweiten Evaluationszyklus akzeptiert hatte und die unter anderem die Bereiche Migration, Geschlechtergleichstellung, Minderheitenschutz und Bekämpfung des Menschenhandels betreffen. Der Bericht bietet einen Überblick über die getroffenen rechtlichen, politischen und administrativen Massnahmen und die Fortschritte im Bereich der Menschenrechte, die in der Schweiz seit 2012 erzielt wurden. Daneben werden auch die Herausforderungen genannt, mit denen die Schweiz in einigen Bereichen noch konfrontiert ist, zum Beispiel bei der Bekämpfung der Rassendiskriminierung oder der Lohnungleichheit. Der Bundesrat ist der Auffassung, dass der Schutz der Menschenrechte in der Schweiz insgesamt als gut bezeichnet werden kann. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Der Dritte Staatenbericht der Schweiz zur UPR ist das Ergebnis einer breit angelegten Vernehmlassung bei Bund, Kantonen, der Zivilgesellschaft und Vertretern des Privatsektors. Die ersten beiden UPR-Zyklen (2007 und 2012) und die Weiterverfolgung der Umsetzung der Empfehlungen, die in diesen Zyklen angenommen wurden, haben einen konstruktiven Austausch zwischen den verschiedenen Akteuren im Menschenrechtsbereich in der Schweiz in Gang gesetzt. Der Bundesrat möchte diesen Dialog im Rahmen des dritten UPR-Zyklus nachhaltig verankern.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Information EDA Tel.: +41 58 462 31 53 info@eda.admin.ch</contact>
      <attachment id="168477">
        <title>Bericht</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>734</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/48872.pdf</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </attachment>
      <link id="168481">
        <title>Allgemeine regelmässige Überprüfung des Menschenrechtsrats</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home/aussenpolitik/internationale-organisationen/vereinte-nationen/die-vereinten-nationenundmenschenrechte/allgemeine-regelmaessigeueberpruefungdesmenschenrechtsrats.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Le Conseil fédéral dresse un bilan de la mise en œuvre des droits de l’homme en Suisse</title>
      <lead>Le Conseil fédéral a adopté le Troisième rapport national que la Suisse présentera en novembre 2017 au Conseil des droits de l’homme de l’ONU dans le cadre de l’Examen périodique universel. Le rapport présente un état des lieux de la situation des droits de l’homme en Suisse et les principales mesures prises en la matière au cours des dernières années.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;L’Examen périodique universel (EPU) est un important mécanisme international de suivi de la mise en œuvre des droits de l’homme. Il prévoit que chaque pays membre de l’ONU soit soumis, tous les cinq ans, à un examen par les pairs. Les recommandations émises à l’intention de chaque Etat offrent un cadre politique important pour accompagner les efforts des Etats en vue d’un meilleur respect des droits de l’homme. La Suisse sera soumise pour la troisième fois à cet examen devant le Conseil des droits de l’homme en novembre 2017.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Le rapport adopté par le Conseil fédéral se fonde sur les 99 recommandations acceptées par la Suisse lors de son dernier EPU, en octobre 2012, et qui touchent entre autres à la migration, à l’égalité de genre, à la protection des minorités ou à la lutte contre la traite d’êtres humains. Il présente les mesures juridiques, politiques et administratives prises et les progrès réalisés en matière de droits de l’homme en Suisse depuis 2012. Il relève également les défis auxquels la Suisse doit encore faire face dans certains domaines, par exemple en matière de lutte contre la discrimination raciale ou d’égalité salariale. De manière générale, le Conseil fédéral est d’avis que le niveau de protection des droits de l’homme en Suisse peut être qualifié de bon. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Le Troisième rapport national de la Suisse pour l’EPU est le fruit d’un large processus de consultation mené au sein de la Confédération et auprès des cantons ainsi que de la société civile et des représentants du secteur privé. Les deux premiers passages de I‘EPU de la Suisse (2007 et 2012) et le suivi de la mise en œuvre des recommandations acceptées dans ce cadre ont permis de générer un dialogue constructif entre les différentes parties prenantes quant à la mise en œuvre des droits de l‘homme en Suisse. Le Conseil fédéral souhaite pérenniser ce dialogue dans le cadre du troisième EPU.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Information DFAE Tél. +41 58 462 31 53 info@eda.admin.ch</contact>
      <attachment id="168478">
        <title>Rapport</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>1088</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/48873.pdf</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </attachment>
      <link id="168482">
        <title>Examen périodique universel du Conseil des droits de l’homme</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae/politique-exterieure/organisations-internationales/nu/onu-droits-homme/examen.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Il Consiglio federale traccia un bilancio dell’attuazione dei diritti umani in Svizzera</title>
      <lead>Il Consiglio federale ha adottato il terzo rapporto nazionale che la Svizzera, nel novembre 2017, presenterà al Consiglio dei diritti umani dell’ONU nell’ambito dell’Esame periodico universale (EPU). Il rapporto fa il punto sulla situazione dei diritti umani in Svizzera e sulle principali misure adottate in materia negli ultimi anni.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;L’Esame periodico universale (EPU) è un importante meccanismo internazionale volto a monitorare l’attuazione dei diritti umani. A scadenza di cinque anni, ogni Stato membro dell’ONU deve sottoporsi a questo esame inter pares. Le raccomandazioni formulate per i singoli Paesi costituiscono un quadro politico di peso entro il quale sostenere gli sforzi intrapresi dagli Stati per migliorare il rispetto dei diritti umani. Nel novembre 2017, la Svizzera si sottoporrà per la terza volta all’esame dinanzi al Consiglio dei diritti umani.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Il rapporto adottato dal Consiglio federale si basa sulle 99 raccomandazioni accolte dalla Svizzera in occasione dell’ultimo EPU, risalente all’ottobre del 2012, che riguardando, tra l’altro, la migrazione, la parità di genere, la tutela delle minoranze e la lotta alla tratta degli esseri umani. Il documento illustra le misure giuridiche, politiche e amministrative adottate come pure i progressi realizzati dalla Svizzera in materia di diritti umani dal 2012 a oggi. Fa infine il punto sulle sfide cui la Svizzera deve ancora far fronte in alcuni ambiti specifici, ad esempio in materia di lotta alla discriminazione razziale e di disparità salariale. In linea di massima, il Consiglio federale giudica buono il livello di tutela dei diritti umani in Svizzera.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Il terzo rapporto nazionale della Svizzera per l’EPU è frutto di un’ampia procedura di consultazione condotta in seno alla Confederazione e presso i Cantoni, la società civile e i rappresentanti dell’economia privata. I primi due EPU della Svizzera (2007 e 2012) e il monitoraggio dell’applicazione delle raccomandazioni accolte in quelle occasioni hanno permesso di instaurare un dialogo costruttivo tra le parti sull’attuazione dei diritti umani in Svizzera. Il Consiglio federale vuole mantenere questo dialogo nel quadro del terzo EPU.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Informazione DFAE Tel. +41 58 462 31 53 info@eda.admin.ch</contact>
      <attachment id="168479">
        <title>Rapporto</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>1027</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/48874.pdf</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </attachment>
      <link id="168483">
        <title>Esame periodico universale del Consiglio dei diritti umani</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae/politica-estera/organizzazioni-internazionali/nu/onu-diritti-dell-uomo/esame.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>The Federal Council takes stock of human rights compliance in Switzerland</title>
      <lead>The Federal Council has adopted the third national report that Switzerland will submit to the UN Human Rights Council in November 2017 as part of the Universal Periodic Review. The report gives an overview of the human rights situation in Switzerland and of the most important measures it has taken in this respect in recent years.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;The Universal Periodic Review (UPR) is a key international mechanism for monitoring the implementation of human rights obligations. Every UN member state is required to undergo a UPR by other member states every five years. The recommendations made to each state provide an important political framework to monitor the efforts undertaken by member states to improve their own human rights record. Switzerland will undergo its third UPR at the Human Rights Council in November 2017.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The report adopted by the Federal Council was drawn up on the basis of the 99 recommendations accepted by Switzerland during its last UPR in October 2012. These recommendations deal among other matters with migration, gender equality, protection of minorities and the fight against trafficking in human beings. The report sets out the legal, political and administrative measures taken and the progress made in human rights protection in Switzerland since 2012. It also outlines the challenges that Switzerland still faces in certain areas, such as combating racial discrimination and ensuring equal pay. The Federal Council is of the opinion that the level of human rights protection in Switzerland can generally speaking be described as good. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Switzerland's third national report for the UPR is the result of a wide-ranging consultation process carried out within the federal government and with the cantons, civil society and representatives of the private sector. Switzerland’s first two UPRs (in 2007 and 2012) and the monitoring of its implementation of the recommendations it accepted as part of the UPR process led to constructive dialogue between the different stakeholders concerning human rights compliance in Switzerland. The Federal Council wishes to continue this dialogue during the third UPR.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>FDFA Information Tel. +41 58 462 31 53 info@eda.admin.ch</contact>
      <attachment id="168480">
        <title>Report (de)</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>734</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/48875.pdf</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </attachment>
      <link id="168484">
        <title>The Human Rights Council Universal Periodic Review</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home/foreign-policy/international-organizations/un/un-human-rights/review.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
