<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="67994" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2017-09-06</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="1070" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>1070</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Der Bundesrat</name>
      <name lang="fr">Conseil fédéral</name>
      <name lang="it">Il Consiglio federale</name>
      <name lang="en">The Federal Council</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.admin.ch/gov/de/start.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.admin.ch/gov/fr/accueil.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.admin.ch/gov/it/pagina-iniziale.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.admin.ch/gov/en/start.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="804" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>801</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Generalsekretariat UVEK</name>
      <name lang="fr">Secrétariat général DETEC</name>
      <name lang="it">Segreteria generale DATEC</name>
      <name lang="en">General Secretariat of the Federal Department of Environment, Transport, Energy and Communications; General Secretariat DETEC</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.uvek.admin.ch/uvek/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.uvek.admin.ch/uvek/fr/home.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.uvek.admin.ch/uvek/it/home.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.uvek.admin.ch/uvek/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-uvek.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-uvek.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-uvek.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-uvek.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="811" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>801</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Bundesamt für Umwelt BAFU</name>
      <name lang="fr">Office fédéral de l'environnement OFEV</name>
      <name lang="it">Ufficio federale dell'ambiente UFAM</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Office for the Environment FOEN</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.bafu.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.bafu.admin.ch/fr</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.bafu.admin.ch/it</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.bafu.admin.ch/en</www>
      <email lang="de">info@bafu.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@bafu.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@bafu.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@bafu.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="1070">
      <name lang="de">Der Bundesrat</name>
      <name lang="fr">Conseil fédéral</name>
      <name lang="it">Il Consiglio federale</name>
      <name lang="en">The Federal Council</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.admin.ch/gov/de/start.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.admin.ch/gov/fr/accueil.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.admin.ch/gov/it/pagina-iniziale.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.admin.ch/gov/en/start.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <department id="801">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Umwelt, Verkehr, Energie und Kommunikation</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'environnement, des transports, de l'énergie et de la communication</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'ambiente, dei trasporti, dell'energia e delle comunicazioni</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of the Environment, Transport, Energy and Communications</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.uvek.admin.ch/uvek/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.uvek.admin.ch/uvek/fr/home.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.uvek.admin.ch/uvek/it/home.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.uvek.admin.ch/uvek/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-uvek.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-uvek.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-uvek.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-uvek.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Quecksilber: erste Konferenz des Minamata-Übereinkommens in Genf</title>
      <lead>Die erste Vertragsparteienkonferenz des Minamata-Übereinkommens findet vom 24. bis 29. September in Genf statt. Mit diesem Übereinkommen sollen die von Quecksilber ausgehenden Risiken weltweit vermindert werden. Die Schweiz setzt sich dafür ein, dass das Sekretariat des Übereinkommens in Genf angesiedelt wird. Die Stadt beherbergt bereits das Kompetenzzentrum für Chemikalien und gefährliche Abfälle. Im Rahmen des vom Bundesrat am 6. September 2017 verabschiedeten Mandats unterstützt die Schweiz im Übrigen die vorgeschlagenen technischen Bestimmungen und die Entwicklung der zukünftigen Aktivitäten.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Das Minamata-Übereinkommen (Minamata-Konvention) hat zum Ziel, Menschen und Umwelt weltweit vor Quecksilberemissionen, die von Menschen verursacht werden, zu schützen. Das Übereinkommen regelt die Verwendung dieses Schwermetalls in Herstellungsprozessen und Produkten sowie die Verminderung von Emissionen und die Behandlung von quecksilberhaltigen Abfällen (siehe Kasten).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Die Schweiz ist Gastgeberin der ersten Vertragsparteienkonferenz der Minamata-Konvention über Quecksilber (COP1), die vom 24. bis 29. September 2017 in Genf stattfinden wird. Bundespräsidentin Doris Leuthard wird das Ministersegment der Konferenz am 28. September eröffnen. Marc Chardonnens, Direktor des Bundesamts für Umwelt (BAFU), wird im Rang eines Staatssekretärs die Konferenz präsidieren.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Die COP1 steht unter dem Slogan «Make Mercury History» und bietet Gelegenheit, diesen wichtigen umweltpolitischen Schritt gebührend zu feiern. Neben den anstehenden Entscheidungen über die Umsetzung des Übereinkommens müssen die Mitgliedstaaten auch über den Standort des Sekretariats der neuen Konvention befinden. Die Schweiz setzt sich dafür ein, dass das Sekretariat in Genf angesiedelt wird, wo sich bereits dasjenige der drei Übereinkommen über Chemikalien und gefährliche Abfälle befindet. Würde das neue Sekretariat in das bestehende Kompetenzzentrum integriert, so liessen sich Synergien und Kosteneinsparungen erzielen.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Erste Leitlinien&lt;/b&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;An der COP1 sollen erste technische Leitlinien verabschiedet werden, zum Beispiel über Verfahren des Quecksilberexports, über Standards für Quecksilberemissionen oder über die Ausarbeitung von Umsetzungsplänen für Länder mit kleingewerblichem Goldabbau. Die Schweizer Delegation wird die Beschlussanträge unterstützen und sich für die Weiterführung der technischen Arbeiten aussprechen, welche die Umsetzung des Übereinkommens in den Vertragsstaaten erleichtern.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Anpassung des schweizerischen Rechts&lt;/b&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Dank der bestehenden strikten Bestimmungen erfüllt die Schweiz bereits grösstenteils die Anforderungen des Übereinkommens bezüglich der Eliminierung quecksilberhaltiger Produkte und des Verbots von Quecksilber in Industrieprozessen. Im Hinblick auf das übergeordnete Ziel der Konvention, nämlich die Verminderung der Verwendung von Quecksilber auf globaler Ebene, wurden im November 2016 Änderungsvorschläge zu vier Verordnungen in die Vernehmlassung gegeben. Damit will die Schweiz einen Beitrag zur Reduktion des weltweiten Angebots an rezykliertem Quecksilber leisten und eine definitive und umweltgerechte Lagerung dieses Schwermetalls fördern. Der Bundesrat dürfte sich noch im laufenden Jahr zu diesem Thema äussern.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class="nsbtextkasten"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Das Minamata-Übereinkommen über Quecksilber (Minamata-Konvention)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Quecksilber ist ein hochgiftiges, gesundheits- und umweltschädigendes Schwermetall. Die Minamata-Konvention trägt ihren Namen deshalb, weil sich in der japanischen Stadt Minamata ab den 1940er-Jahren eine sehr schwere Quecksilbervergiftung ereignete. Das Übereinkommen wurde 2013 von der internationalen Staatengemeinschaft angenommen und von der Schweiz am 26. Mai 2016 ratifiziert. Es trat am 16. August 2017 in Kraft.&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Franz Perrez, Chef der Abteilung Internationales, BAFU, +41 79 251 90 15 Sektion Medien, BAFU, +41 58 462 90 00</contact>
      <link id="170243">
        <title>BAFU: Minamata Quecksilber-Übereinkommen</title>
        <uri>https://www.bafu.admin.ch/bafu/de/home/themen/chemikalien/fachinformationen/internationales--chemikalien/minamata-quecksilber-uebereinkommen.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="170244">
        <title>Minamata Convention on Mercury</title>
        <uri>http://www.mercuryconvention.org/Home/tabid/3360/language/en-US/Default.aspx</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Mercure : première conférence de la Convention de Minamata à Genève</title>
      <lead>La première Conférence des Parties à la Convention de Minamata se tiendra du 24 au 29 septembre prochains à Genève. Cette convention vise à réduire les risques liés au mercure au niveau mondial. La Suisse s’engage pour que le secrétariat de la Convention soit localisé à Genève, centre de compétences pour les produits chimiques et des déchets dangereux. La délégation suisse approuvera en outre les dispositions techniques proposées et le développement des activités futures, suivant le mandat adopté par le Conseil fédéral le 6 septembre 2017. </lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;La Convention de Minamata a pour objectif de protéger au niveau mondial les êtres humains et l’environnement des émissions de mercure provenant des activités humaines. L’accord règle l’utilisation de ce métal lourd dans les processus de fabrication et dans les produits, la réduction des émissions et le traitement des déchets qui en contiennent (voir encadré). &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;La Suisse accueillera la première Conférence des Parties à la Convention de Minamata sur le mercure (COP1), du 24 au 29 septembre 2017 à Genève. La présidente de la Confédération, Doris Leuthard, ouvrira la partie ministérielle le 28 septembre. Le directeur de l’Office fédéral de l’environnement, Marc Chardonnens, présidera la conférence au titre de Secrétaire d’Etat. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Placée sous le thème « Make Mercury History », la COP1 sera l’occasion de célébrer cette importante avancée environnementale. Parmi les décisions nécessaires au fonctionnement du nouvel accord, les Etats membres devraient se prononcer sur l’emplacement du Secrétariat de la nouvelle convention. La Suisse s’engage pour que le secrétariat de la Convention de Minamata rejoigne celui des trois conventions traitant des produits chimiques et des déchets dangereux basées à Genève. L’intégration au centre de compétences existant permettrait de profiter des synergies et de diminuer les coûts.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Premières directives à adopter&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;La COP1 devrait adopter des premières directives techniques, par exemple sur les procédures d’exportation du mercure, sur les standards d’émissions de mercure, ou encore sur l’élaboration de plans de mise en œuvre pour les pays ayant des mines d’or artisanales. La délégation suisse approuvera les documents proposés et soutiendra la poursuite des travaux techniques qui facilitent la mise en œuvre de la convention dans les Etats. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Adaptation du droit suisse&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Grâce aux dispositions strictes existantes, la Suisse respecte en grande partie les exigences de la convention en matière d’élimination des produits contenant du mercure et pour ce qui concerne l’abandon du mercure dans les processus industriels. Afin de remplir l’objectif général de la convention, qui est de diminuer l'utilisation du mercure au niveau planétaire, des propositions de modification de quatre ordonnances ont été envoyées en consultation en novembre 2016. La Suisse entend ainsi contribuer à la diminution de l’offre mondiale de mercure recyclé et encourager un stockage définitif et respectueux de l’environnement de ce métal. Le Conseil fédéral devrait se prononcer à ce sujet cette année encore.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class="nsbtextkasten"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;La convention de Minamata sur le mercure&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Le mercure est un métal lourd très toxique, dangereux pour la santé et l’environnement. La Convention de Minamata, du nom de la ville japonaise victime d’une très grave pollution au mercure à partir des années 40, a été adoptée par la communauté internationale en 2013. La Suisse l’a ratifiée le 26 mai 2016. La convention est entrée en vigueur le 16 août 2017.&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>M. l’Ambassadeur Franz Perrez, chef de la division Affaires internationales, OFEV, +41 79 251 90 15 Section médias, OFEV, +41 58 462 90 00</contact>
      <link id="170248">
        <title>OFEV: La Convention de Minamata</title>
        <uri>https://www.bafu.admin.ch/bafu/fr/home/themes/produits-chimiques/info-specialistes/affaires-internationales--produits-chimiques/convention-sur-le-mercure-de-minamata.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="170249">
        <title>Convention de Minamata sur le mercure</title>
        <uri>http://www.mercuryconvention.org/Accueil/tabid/5576/language/fr-CH/Default.aspx</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Mercurio: a Ginevra la prima Conferenza della Convenzione di Minamata</title>
      <lead>La prima Conferenza delle Parti della Convenzione di Minamata si terrà dal 24 al 29 settembre 2017 a Ginevra. Lo scopo della Convenzione è ridurre a livello globale i rischi legati al mercurio. La Svizzera si impegna affinchè il Segretariato della Convenzione abbia sede a Ginevra, il centro di competenza per i prodotti chimici e i rifiuti pericolosi. La delegazione svizzera approverà inoltre le disposizioni tecniche proposte e lo sviluppo delle attività future, secondo il mandato approvato il 6 settembre 2017 dal Consiglio federale.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;L’obiettivo della Convenzione di Minamata è proteggere a livello globale l’uomo e l’ambiente dalle emissioni di mercurio generate dalle attività antropiche. La Convenzione disciplina l’utilizzo di questo metallo pesante nei processi di fabbricazione e nei prodotti come pure la riduzione delle emissioni e il trattamento dei rifiuti che lo contengono (cfr. riquadro).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Dal 24 al 29 settembre 2017, la Svizzera ospiterà a Ginevra la prima Conferenza delle Parti della Convenzione di Minamata sul mercurio (COP1). La presidente della Confederazione Doris Leuthard inaugurerà la parte ministeriale il 28 settembre. Il direttore dell’Ufficio federale dell’ambiente Marc Chardonnens presiederà la Conferenza in qualità di Segretario di Stato.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Intitolata «Make Mercury History», la COP1 sarà l’occasione per celebrare questa tappa fondamentale per il settore ambientale. Tra le decisioni che i Paesi membri dovranno prendere per il buon funzionamento dell’accordo vi è anche la sede del Segretariato della Convenzione. La Svizzera presenterà la candidatura di Ginevra, città in cui si trova già il Segretariato delle altre tre convenzioni concernenti i prodotti chimici e i rifiuti pericolosi. L’integrazione al centro di competenza esistente consentirebbe di sfruttare le sinergie e di ridurre i costi.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Prime direttive da adottare&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Durante la COP1 dovrebbero essere adottate le prime direttive tecniche, ad esempio sulle procedure di esportazione del mercurio, sugli standard di emissione di questo metallo o sull’elaborazione di piani di attuazione per i Paesi con miniere d’oro di tipo artigianale. La delegazione svizzera approverà i documenti proposti e appoggerà il proseguimento dei lavori tecnici volti a facilitare l’attuazione della Convenzione nei Paesi.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Adeguamento del diritto svizzero&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Disponendo di norme severe in materia, la Svizzera soddisfa già gran parte delle esigenze della Convenzione per quanto attiene all’eliminazione dei prodotti contenenti mercurio e all’abbandono del mercurio nei processi industriali. Per adempiere l’obiettivo generale della Convenzione di ridurre l’utilizzo del mercurio a livello globale, nel novembre 2016 sono stati posti in consultazione quattro progetti di revisione di altrettante ordinanze. La Svizzera intende in tal modo contribuire alla riduzione dell’offerta globale di mercurio riciclato e promuovere lo stoccaggio definitivo e rispettoso dell’ambiente di questo metallo. Il Consiglio federale dovrebbe pronunciarsi in merito ancora nel corso di quest’anno.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class="nsbtextkasten"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;La Convenzione di Minamata sul mercurio&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Il mercurio è un metallo pesante altamente tossico, dannoso per la salute dell’uomo e l’ambiente. La Convenzione di Minamata, dal nome della cittadina giapponese colpita da un grave inquinamento da mercurio a partire dagli anni Quaranta, è stata adottata nel 2013 dalla comunità internazionale. La Svizzera ha ratificato la Convenzione il 26 maggio 2016. La Convenzione è entrata in vigore il 16 agosto 2017.&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Franz Perrez, ambasciatore, capo della divisione Affari internazionali, UFAM, +41 79 251 90 15 Sezione Media, UFAM, +41 58 462 90 00</contact>
      <link id="170246">
        <title>UFAM: Convenzione di Minamata sul mercurio</title>
        <uri>https://www.bafu.admin.ch/bafu/it/home/temi/prodotti-chimici/info-specialisti/affari-internazionali--prodotti-chimici/convenzione-di-minamata-sul-mercurio.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="170247">
        <title>Convenzione di Minamata sul mercurio</title>
        <uri>http://www.mercuryconvention.org/Accueil/tabid/5576/language/fr-CH/Default.aspx</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Mercury: first Minamata Convention conference in Geneva</title>
      <lead>The first Conference of the Parties to the Minamata Convention will take place from 24 to 29 September in Geneva. This convention aims to reduce the risks of mercury around the world. Switzerland is working to locate the convention’s secretariat in Geneva, which is already a centre of expertise in hazardous chemical products and wastes. The Swiss delegation will also approve the proposed technical provisions and the development of future activities, following the mandate adopted by the Federal Council on 6 September 2017.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;The objective of the Minamata Convention is to protect humans and the environment around the world from mercury emissions caused by human activities. The agreement regulates the use of this heavy metal in manufacturing processes and products, the reduction of emissions and the management of mercury-containing wastes (see box).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Switzerland will host the first Conference of the Parties to the Minamata Convention on Mercury (COP1), which will take place from 24 to 29 September 2017 in Geneva. President of the Swiss Confederation, Doris Leuthard, will open the ministerial part on 28 September. Director of the Swiss Federal Office for the Environment, Marc Chardonnens, will preside over the conference in his capacity as Secretary of State.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Entitled “Make Mercury History", COP1 will be an opportunity to celebrate this major environmental advance. To ensure that the new convention functions smoothly, member States will need to decide where its secretariat is to be located. Switzerland is working to locate the secretariat of the Minamata Convention in Geneva, along with the secretariat of the three conventions on hazardous chemical products and wastes. Integrating this convention’s secretariat into the existing centre of expertise would make it possible to draw on synergies and reduce costs.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Preliminary guidelines to be adopted&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The COP1 should adopt preliminary technical guidelines for such items as mercury export procedures, mercury emission standards, and the development of implementation plans for countries with artisanal gold mines. The Swiss delegation will approve the proposed documents and support the continuation of technical work that facilitates the implementation of the convention in the States.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Adaptation of Swiss law&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Thanks to the strict legislation currently in force, Switzerland complies with most of the convention’s requirements for eliminating mercury-containing products and phasing out mercury in industrial processes. In order to achieve the convention’s overall aim, which is to reduce mercury use around the world, proposed amendments to four ordinances were submitted for consultation in November 2016. In doing so, Switzerland intends to help reduce the global supply of recycled mercury and encourage permanent, environmentally-friendly storage of this metal. The Federal Council should decide on this matter sometime this year.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class="nsbtextkasten"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Minamata Convention on Mercury&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Mercury is a highly toxic heavy metal that is hazardous to health and the environment. The Minamata Convention, which was named after the Japanese city plagued by very serious mercury pollution starting in the 1940s, was adopted by the international community in 2013. Switzerland ratified it on 26 May 2016. The convention entered into force on 16 August 2017.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Franz Perrez, Ambassador for the Environment and Head of the International Affairs Division, FOEN, +41 79 251 90 15 Media Section, FOEN, +41 58 462 90 00</contact>
      <link id="170244">
        <title>Minamata Convention on Mercury</title>
        <uri>http://www.mercuryconvention.org/Home/tabid/3360/language/en-US/Default.aspx</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="170245">
        <title>FOEN: Minamata Convention</title>
        <uri>https://www.bafu.admin.ch/bafu/en/home/topics/chemicals/info-specialists/international-affairs--chemicals/minamata-convention-on-mercury.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <offers>
      <offer id="143" org-id="811">
        <name lang="de">Medienmitteilungen des BAFU</name>
        <name lang="fr">Communiqués de l'OFEV</name>
        <name lang="it">Comunicati dell'UFAM</name>
        <name lang="en">Media releases of the FOEN</name>
      </offer>
    </offers>
    <keywords>
      <keyword id="230" org-id="811">
        <name lang="de">Chemikalien</name>
        <name lang="fr">Produits chimiques</name>
        <name lang="it">Prodotti chimici</name>
        <name lang="en">Chemicals</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="560" org-id="811">
        <name lang="de">Internationales</name>
        <name lang="fr">Affaires internationales</name>
        <name lang="it">Affari Internazionali</name>
        <name lang="en">International Affairs</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="173" org-id="811">
        <name lang="de">Bundesamt für Umwelt: Startseite</name>
        <name lang="fr">Office fédéral de l'environnement: page d'accueil</name>
        <name lang="it">Ufficio federale dell'ambiente: pagina iniziale</name>
        <name lang="en">Federal Office for the Environment: Homepage</name>
      </keyword>
    </keywords>
    <topics>
      <topic id="29">
        <name lang="de">Umwelt und Natur</name>
        <name lang="fr">Environnement et nature</name>
        <name lang="it">Ambiente e natura</name>
        <name lang="en">Environment and Nature</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
