<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="68253" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2017-09-28</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="323" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>701</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidg. Materialprüfungs- und Forschungsanstalt</name>
      <name lang="fr">Laboratoire fédéral d'essai des matériaux et de recherche</name>
      <name lang="it">Laboratorio federale di prova dei materiali e di ricerca</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Laboratory for Materials Testing and Research</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.empa.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.empa.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.empa.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.empa.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">contact@empa.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">contact@empa.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">contact@empa.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">contact@empa.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="701">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Wirtschaft, Bildung und Forschung</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'économie, de la formation et de la recherche</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'economia, della formazione e della ricerca</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Economic Affairs, Education and Research</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Dübendorf, St. Gallen und Thun</city>
      <title>Neuer Flammhemmer vor Markteintritt</title>
      <lead>Chemiker der Empa haben einen neuen Syntheseweg für umweltfreundliche Flammschutzmittel entwickelt und patentiert. Diese sind für Matratzen und Polstern geeignet. Anders als bisherige Flammschutzmittel aus chlorhaltigen Chemikalien ist die neue Stoffklasse ungiftig und effizient. Zwei Industriepartner der Empa bringen die Neuentwicklung nun auf den Markt.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Das an der Empa entwickelte umweltfreundliche Flammschutzmittel namens EDA-DOPO geht in Serienproduktion. Entscheidend für diesen Erfolg ist das neu entwickelte, besonders ökonomische und ökologische Syntheseverfahren, das auch die Herstellung anderer DOPO-Derivate vereinfacht. Die Firma Metadynea Austria GmbH wird den Stoff herstellen, die weltweit tätige FoamPartner Gruppe wird bei entsprechender Nachfrage daraus flammhemmende Polyurethan-Schaumstoffe (PU) für Polster und Matratzen produzieren. Nachdem das neue Produktionsverfahren für DOPO-Derivate im Juni 2017 patentiert wurde, hat die Metadynea Austria GmbH bis heute bereits rund 1.5 Tonnen des Flammschutzmittels produziert.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Ungiftig – auch im Brandfall&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Damit ist ein erster Schritt getan, um herkömmliche, halogenierte Flammschutzmittel zu ersetzen. Diese bisher gebräuchlichen Mittel sind bisweilen giftig und erzeugen im Brandfall giftige Gase. Das an der Empa entwickelte EDA-DOPO – ein Derivat des bekannten Flammschutzmittels DOPO (9,10-Dihydro-10-oxa-phosphaphenatrenoxid) – tut dies nicht. Dennoch erfüllen Schaumstoffe, die EDA-DOPO enthalten, die höchste Flammschutz-Klassifikation (UL 94 HB).&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Der Flammschutzexperte Sabyasachi Gaan entwickelte EDA-DOPO an der Empa in zwei Jahren Forschungsarbeit im Rahmen des Eureka SUSPUR-Projekts (www.eurekanetwork.org/project/id/8058). Den Anstoss dazu gab die FoamPartner Gruppe, die ihr Sortiment mit umweltfreundlich ausgerüsteten, flammgeschützten PU-Schaumstoffen ausbauen wollte. Derzeit ist die Firma alleiniger Lizenznehmer für EDA-DOPO für die PU-Schaumherstellung. Die Substanz wird ausschliesslich von der Metadynea Austria GmbH hergestellt.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Für öffentliche Räume vorgeschrieben&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Flammhemmende Polster sind vor allem für Bereiche vorgeschrieben, an denen sich viele Menschen aufhalten: Flugzeuge, Bahnen und Busse, Hotels und Gaststätten. Flammschutzmittel verhindern eine Entzündung, etwa mit Zigaretten oder durch Vandalismus. Doch auch hier werden die Umweltstandards immer strenger. Ausdünstungen von Flammschutzmitteln in die Umgebungsluft und die Atmosphäre sind unerwünscht; ebenso werden die giftigen Gase, die beim Brand entstehen können, immer weniger akzeptiert. Viele Staaten haben halogenierte Flammschutzmittel denn auch bereits verboten. Daher wächst auf der ganzen Welt der Bedarf nach modernen, unschädlichen Alternativen.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Obwohl die Schaumstoffproduktion mit dem neuen Flammschutzmittel bereits anläuft, werden Produkte mit EDA-DOPO noch nicht sofort in den Verkauf gelangen; aktuell läuft nämlich die Zertifizierung des Flammschutzmittels nach der europäischen Chemikalienverordnung REACH. Die hergestellten Schaumstoffproben werden gegenwärtig diversen Flammtests unterzogen, damit nach der REACH-Zertifizierung die globalen Märkte möglichst schnell mit den neuen flammhemmenden Schaumstoffen bedient werden können.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Dr. Sabyasachi Gaan, Empa, Advanced Fibers, +41 58 765 76 11, Sabyasachi.Gaan@empa.ch Thomas Zich, Metadynea Austria GmbH, +43 664 94 90 315, Thomas.Zich@metadynea.com Heribert Perler, FoamPartner Fritz Nauer AG, +41 55 253 66 42, Heribert.Perler@foampartner.com Redaktion/Medienkontakt Rainer Klose, Empa, Kommunikation +41 58 765 47 33, rainer.klose@empa.ch</contact>
      <link id="170954">
        <title>Empa-Medienmitteilung</title>
        <uri>https://www.empa.ch/web/s604/eda-dopo-flame-retardant</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Dübendorf, St. Gallen und Thun</city>
      <title>Nouveau retardateur de flamme avant l'entrée sur le marché</title>
      <lead>Les chimistes d'Empa ont développé et fait breveter une synthèse chimique pour produire un agent ignifuge écologique pour les mousses. Celui-ci peut être utilisé dans les matelas et tissus de rembourrage. Contrairement aux agents ignifuges fabriqués jusqu'à présent à partir de produits chimiques contenant du chlore, la nouvelle substance est sans danger et non toxique. Deux partenaires d'Empa issus de l'industrie proposent aujourd'hui le produit récemment développé sur le marché.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;L'agent ignifuge écologique développé à l'Empa du nom d'EDA-DOPO est produit en série. Ce qui est fondamental pour ce succès, c'est le procédé de synthèse particulièrement économique et écologique récemment développé qui simplifie également la fabrication d'autres composés DOPO. La société Metadynea Austria GmbH fabriquera le produit et le groupe de niveau mondial FoamPartner produira ensuite, en fonction de la demande, les mousses de polyuréthane ignifuge (PU) pour les tissus de rembourrage et de matelas. Une fois le procédé breveté en juin 2017, la société Metadynea Austria GmbH a déjà produit jusqu'à présent près d'1,5 tonnes d'agent ignifuge.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Non toxique&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Un premier pas est ainsi franchi vers le remplacement des agents ignifuges halogénés classiques. Ces agents couramment utilisés jusqu'à présent ne sont parfois toxique et dégagent en cas d'incendie des gaz toxiques. Or ce n'est pas le cas avec l'EDA-DOPO, développé à l'EMPA – un dérivé de l'agent ignifuge bien connu DOPO (9,10-dihydro-10-oxa-phosphaphenanthrene-oxyde). L'agent répond toutefois à la classification de protection ignifuge la plus élevée (UL 94 HB).&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;L'expert en protection ignifuge Sabyasachi Gaan a développé EDA-DOPO à l'Empa en deux ans de travaux de recherche dans le cadre du projet Eureka SUSPER (www.eurekanetwork.org/project/id/8058). Ce fut le groupe FoamPartner qui en donna l'impulsion, en voulant élargir sa gamme de produit avec des mousses en PU équipées de façon écologique. Actuellement la société est le seul et unique titulaire de licence pour EDA-DOPO. La substance est fabriquée exclusivement par Metadynea Austria GmbH.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Obligatoire pour les espaces publics&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Les tissus de rembourrage ignifuges sont requis avant tout pour les endroits où se trouve beaucoup de monde : les avions, les trains et les bus, les hôtels et les restaurants. Les agents ignifuges empêchent l'inflammation, comme avec les cigarettes ou par vandalisme. Et ici encore aussi, les normes en termes d'environnement deviennent de plus en plus strictes. Les vapeurs des agents de protection ignifuge dans l'air ambiant ne sont pas souhaitables ; il en va de même pour les gaz toxiques pouvant se dégager en cas d'incendie qui sont de moins en moins acceptés. De nombreux États ont donc déjà interdit les agents de protection ignifuge halogénés. C'est pourquoi le besoin d'alternatives modernes et inoffensives grandit dans le monde entier.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Bien que la production de mousses s'effectue d'ores et déjà avec le nouvel agent de protection ignifuge, les produits EDA-DOPO n'ont pas tout de suite été mis en vente ; en effet, la certification de l'agent de protection ignifuge selon la réglementation européenne sur les produits chimiques REACH est actuellement en cours. Les échantillons de mousse fabriqués sont actuellement soumis à différents essais de feu, afin d'approvisionner le plus rapidement possible les marchés mondiaux en mousses ignifuges, une fois la certification REACH obtenue.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Dr. Sabyasachi Gaan, Empa, Advanced Fibers, +41 58 765 76 11, Sabyasachi.Gaan@empa.ch Thomas Zich, Metadynea Austria GmbH, +43 664 94 90 315, Thomas.Zich@metadynea.com Heribert Perler, FoamPartner Fritz Nauer AG, +41 55 253 66 42, Heribert.Perler@foampartner.com Redaktion/Medienkontakt Rainer Klose, Empa, Communication +41 58 765 47 33, rainer.klose@empa.ch</contact>
      <link id="170954">
        <title>Empa-Medienmitteilung</title>
        <uri>https://www.empa.ch/web/s604/eda-dopo-flame-retardant</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Dübendorf, St. Gallen und Thun</city>
      <title>New flame retardant enters market</title>
      <lead>Chemists from Empa have developed and patented an environmentally friendly way to produce flame retardants for foams that can be used in mattresses and upholstery. Unlike previous flame retardants made of chemicals containing chlorine, the new material is non-toxic and effective. Two of Empa’s industrial partners are now launching the innovation on the market. </lead>
      <text link="no">EDA-DOPO, the environmentally friendly flame retardant developed at Empa, is going into serial production. The newly developed, particularly economic and ecological synthesis method, which also simplifies the production of other DOPO derivatives, is a crucial part of this success story. The company Metadynea Austria GmbH will manufacture the material and, if there is sufficient demand, the global FoamPartner Group will use it to produce flame-retardant polyurethane (PU) foams for upholstery and mattresses. Since the new method of production of DOPO derivatives was patented in June 2017, Metadynea Austria GmbH has already produced around 1.5 tons of the flame retardant. Non-Toxic This constitutes the first step towards replacing conventional, halogenated flame retardants, which are sometime toxic and give off toxic gases in the event of a fire. Empa’s EDA-DOPO – a derivative of the familiar flame retardant DOPO (9,10-dihydro-10-oxa-phosphaphenanthreneoxide) – does not emit these toxins. Furthermore, the foam material containing this flame retardant satisfies the highest flame retardant classification (UL 94 HB). Fire retardant expert Sabyasachi Gaan developed EDA-DOPO at Empa in a two-year research project within the scope of the Eureka SUSPUR project (www.eurekanetwork.org/project/id/8058). It was initiated by the FoamPartner Group, which was looking to expand its range with environmentally friendly flame retardant PU foams. The company is currently the sole license holder for EDA-DOPO for PU applications. The substance is manufactured exclusively by Metadynea Austria GmbH. Mandatory for public areas Flame-retardant upholstery is especially mandatory for areas where many people gather: Planes, trains, buses, hotels and restaurants. Flame retardants prevent materials from being ignited, such as with cigarettes or by vandals. However, the environmental standards keep getting stringent here, too. The evaporation of flame retardants into the ambient air or atmosphere is undesirable and the toxic gases that can form during a fire are also being accepted less and less. Many countries have already banned halogenated flame retardants. Consequently, there is a growing need for modern, harmless alternatives all over the world. Although foam production with the new flame retardant is already underway, products containing EDA-DOPO will not be on sale just yet; the flame retardant is currently being certified in accordance with the European chemical regulation REACH. The foam samples produced are presently undergoing diverse flame tests to enable the new flame-retardant foams to hit the global markets as quickly as possible once they obtain their REACH certification. </text>
      <contact>Dr. Sabyasachi Gaan, Empa, Advanced Fibers, +41 58 765 76 11, Sabyasachi.Gaan@empa.ch Thomas Zich, Metadynea Austria GmbH, +43 664 94 90 315, Thomas.Zich@metadynea.com Heribert Perler, FoamPartner Fritz Nauer AG, +41 55 253 66 42, Heribert.Perler@foampartner.com Editor/media contact Rainer Klose, Empa, Communications +41 58 765 47 33, rainer.klose@empa.ch</contact>
      <link id="170954">
        <title>Empa-Medienmitteilung</title>
        <uri>https://www.empa.ch/web/s604/eda-dopo-flame-retardant</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="8">
        <name lang="de">Bildung und Forschung</name>
        <name lang="fr">Formation et recherche</name>
        <name lang="it">Formazione e ricerca</name>
        <name lang="en">Education and Research</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="29">
        <name lang="de">Umwelt und Natur</name>
        <name lang="fr">Environnement et nature</name>
        <name lang="it">Ambiente e natura</name>
        <name lang="en">Environment and Nature</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
