<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="68540" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2017-10-25</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="1070" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>1070</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Der Bundesrat</name>
      <name lang="fr">Conseil fédéral</name>
      <name lang="it">Il Consiglio federale</name>
      <name lang="en">The Federal Council</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.admin.ch/gov/de/start.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.admin.ch/gov/fr/accueil.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.admin.ch/gov/it/pagina-iniziale.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.admin.ch/gov/en/start.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="201" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>201</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="1070">
      <name lang="de">Der Bundesrat</name>
      <name lang="fr">Conseil fédéral</name>
      <name lang="it">Il Consiglio federale</name>
      <name lang="en">The Federal Council</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.admin.ch/gov/de/start.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.admin.ch/gov/fr/accueil.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.admin.ch/gov/it/pagina-iniziale.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.admin.ch/gov/en/start.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <department id="201">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Gute Dienste: Schweiz übernimmt Schutzmachtmandate für Iran in Saudi-Arabien und Saudi-Arabien im Iran</title>
      <lead>Die Schweizer Botschafter in Riad und in Teheran haben am 25. Oktober 2017 die Verträge zur Vertretung der iranischen Interessen in Saudi-Arabien und der saudischen Interessen im Iran unterzeichnet. Zuvor hatte der Bundesrat an seiner Sitzung vom 25. Oktober 2017 grünes Licht zur Übernahme der entsprechenden Schutzmachtmandate gegeben. </lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Nach Abbruch der Beziehungen zwischen Iran und Saudi-Arabien Anfang Januar 2016 hat die Schweiz mit beiden Staaten vereinbart, dass die Schweiz im Rahmen ihrer traditionellen Politik der Guten Dienste gegenseitige Schutzmachtmandate übernehmen werde. Verhandlungen über die Modalitäten wurden bei Gesprächen von Bundesrat Didier Burkhalter mit den Aussenministern Saudi-Arabiens und Irans im Februar 2016 lanciert. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Nachdem beide Staaten die Übernahme der Schutzmachtmandate durch die Schweiz akzeptiert hatten und der Bundesrat an seiner Sitzung vom 25.10.2017 sein grünes Licht gegeben hat, wurden nun die entsprechenden Verträge in Riad sowie Teheran unterzeichnet. Die Interessenvertretung betrifft konsularische Dienste in Iran und in Saudi-Arabien. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Die Schweiz hat eine lange Tradition der Wahrung fremder Interessen. Bei Abbruch von zwischenstaatlichen Beziehungen übernimmt sie einen Teil der konsularischen und/oder diplomatischen Aufgaben, falls dies von den betroffenen Staaten gewünscht wird. Der Bundesrat hebt die Ausübung solcher Mandate in der Aussenpolitischen Strategie 2016-2019 explizit hervor. &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Information EDA Tel. +41 58 462 31 53 info@eda.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Bons offices : la Suisse investie d’un mandat de puissance protectrice pour représenter les intérêts de l'Iran en Arabie saoudite et inversement</title>
      <lead>Les ambassadeurs de Suisse à Riyad et à Téhéran ont signé le 25 octobre 2017 les accords pour la représentation des intérêts iraniens en Arabie saoudite et pour celle des intérêts saoudiens en Iran. À l'occasion de sa séance du 25 octobre 2017, le Conseil fédéral a accordé son feu vert à l’exercice du mandat de puissance protectrice. </lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Suite à la rupture des relations diplomatiques entre l’Arabie saoudite et l’Iran début janvier 2016, la Suisse a convenu avec les deux États qu’elle assumerait, pour l’un comme pour l’autre, un mandat de puissance protectrice, conformément à sa tradition de bons offices. Les négociations sur les modalités du mandat ont débuté en février 2016, lors des entretiens que le conseiller fédéral Didier Burkhalter a menés avec ses homologues d’Arabie saoudite et d’Iran. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Une fois que les deux pays ont accepté le mandat de puissance protectrice de la Suisse et que le Conseil fédéral a donné son feu vert lors de sa séance du 25 octobre 2017, les accords en ce sens ont pu être signés à Riyad et à Téhéran. La représentation des intérêts porte sur les services consulaires en Iran et en Arabie saoudite. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;La Suisse bénéficie d’une longue tradition en matière de représentation d’intérêts étrangers. Lorsque deux États rompent leurs relations diplomatiques, la Suisse assume s’ils le souhaitent une partie de leurs tâches diplomatiques et/ou consulaires. Le Conseil fédéral souligne explicitement ce type de mandat dans sa Stratégie de politique étrangère 2016–2019. &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Information DFAE Tél. +41 58 462 31 53 info@eda.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Buoni uffici: la Svizzera assume i mandati di potenza protettrice per l’Iran in Arabia Saudita e per l’Arabia Saudita in Iran</title>
      <lead>Il 25 ottobre 2017 gli ambasciatori svizzeri a Riad e a Teheran hanno firmato i trattati per rappresentare gli interessi iraniani in Arabia Saudita e gli interessi sauditi in Iran. In questo modo, Il Consiglio federale ha dato il via libera all’assunzione dei relativi mandati in qualità di potenza protettrice in occasione della sua seduta del 25 ottobre 2017. </lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Dopo la sospensione delle relazioni tra l’Iran e l’Arabia Saudita a inizio gennaio 2016, la Svizzera ha convenuto con entrambi gli Stati che, nell’ambito della sua tradizionale politica dei buoni uffici, avrebbe assunto i reciproci mandati di potenza protettrice. Nel febbraio 2016 sono stati avviati negoziati sulle modalità di questi mandati nel corso di colloqui tra il consigliere federale Didier Burkhalter e i ministri degli esteri dell’Arabia Saudita e dell’Iran. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Il Consiglio federale ha dato il suo via libera durante la seduta del 25 ottobre 2017, dopo che entrambi gli Stati hanno accettato l’assunzione dei mandati in qualità di potenza protettrice da parte della Svizzera. I relativi trattati sono stati in seguito firmati a Riad e a Teheran. La rappresentanza degli interessi riguarda i servizi consolari in Iran e in Arabia Saudita. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;La Svizzera ha una lunga tradizione nell’ambito della tutela degli interessi di terzi. Nel caso di sospensione delle relazioni intergovernative, se auspicato dagli Stati interessati, si assume una parte dei compiti consolari e/o diplomatici. Il Consiglio federale indica tali mandati come punti di forza nella Strategia di politica estera 2016-2019. &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Informazione DFAE Tel. +41 58 462 31 53 info@eda.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Good offices: Switzerland takes on protecting power mandate for Iran and Saudi Arabia</title>
      <lead>On 25 October 2017, the Swiss embassies in Riyadh and Tehran signed the agreements for Switzerland to represent Iranian interests in Saudi Arabia and Saudi interests in Iran. The Federal Council gave the green light for the protecting power mandate at its meeting on 25 October 2017. </lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;After Iran and Saudi Arabia severed relations at the beginning of January 2016, both countries agreed to Switzerland’s offer of its traditional policy of good offices to undertake a protecting power mandate on both sides. Federal Councillor Didier Burkhalter launched negotiations on the terms of the mandate with the Iranian and Saudi foreign ministers on February 2016. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Following the acceptance by both countries of Switzerland’s protecting power mandate and the Federal Council’s approval given at its meeting on 25 October 2017, the relevant agreements have now been signed in Riyadh and Tehran. The mandate will cover consular services in Iran and Saudi Arabia. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Switzerland has a long history of representing foreign interests whereby it covers partial consular services and sometimes diplomatic tasks for countries that have broken off relations, if requested by the states in question. The Federal Council has placed explicit emphasis on protecting power mandates in its 2016-19 foreign policy strategy. &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>FDFA Information Tel. +41 58 462 31 53 info@eda.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
