<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="68843" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2017-11-17</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="201" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>201</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="201">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Bundesrat Ignazio Cassis reist zu einem ersten Auslandsbesuch nach Rom</title>
      <lead>Bundesrat Ignazio Cassis reist am Dienstag zu einem Arbeitsbesuch nach Rom, wo er den italienischen Aussenminister Angelino Alfano treffen wird. Der neue Vorsteher des Eidgenössischen Departements für auswärtige Angelegenheiten (EDA) will seinen ersten Auslandsbesuch nutzen, um bilaterale Fragen und aktuelle Themen der internationalen Politik zu besprechen. Zudem wird er die Bedeutung unterstreichen, welche die Schweiz Italien beimisst, und seinen italienischen Amtskollegen kennenlernen.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Die beiden Aussenminister werden sich über die vielfältigen Beziehungen zwischen der Schweiz und Italien unterhalten. In diesem Rahmen werden sie Steuer- und Finanzfragen besprechen, und Bundesrat Cassis wird sich nach dem Stand beim Marktzugang für Schweizer Finanzdienstleister in Italien und der Besteuerung von Grenzgängern erkundigen. Weitere Gesprächsthemen sind die Beziehungen zwischen der Schweiz und der Europäischen Union (EU), die Vision Italiens für die Zukunft der EU und die aktuellen Herausforderungen der EU.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Zudem werden die beiden Aussenminister die Zusammenarbeit zwischen der Schweiz und Italien im Bereich der Migrationspolitik und insbesondere die Situation im Mittelmeer und in Libyen besprechen. Bundesrat Cassis wird sich auch über den italienischen OSZE-Vorsitz 2018 und dessen Prioritäten informieren.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Italien ist der fünftgrösste Handelspartner der Schweiz. Das bilaterale Handelsvolumen belief sich 2016 auf 34 Milliarden Franken. Rund 320 000 italienische Staatsangehörige leben in der Schweiz. Sie stellen damit die grösste Ausländergemeinde in der Schweiz dar. Ausserdem kommen rund 70 000 Grenzgängerinnen und Grenzgänger aus Italien zur Arbeit in die Schweiz. Etwas mehr als 50 000 Schweizerinnen und Schweizer leben in Italien. Die engen Beziehungen zwischen den beiden Ländern finden ihren Ausdruck in regelmässigen bilateralen Treffen auf allen Ebenen.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Kommunikation EDA Bundeshaus West CH-3003 Bern Tel. Kommunikationsservice: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Medienstelle: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <link id="172604">
        <title>Bilaterale Beziehungen Schweiz - Italien</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home/vertretungen-und-reisehinweise/italien/bilatereale-beziehungenschweizitalien.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Ignazio Cassis à Rome pour sa première visite à l’étranger</title>
      <lead>Le conseiller fédéral Ignazio Cassis sera mardi à Rome pour une visite de travail au cours de laquelle il rencontrera Angelino Alfano, le ministre italien des affaires étrangères. L’objectif de cette première visite du nouveau chef du Département fédéral des affaires étrangères (DFAE) sera de faire le point sur les questions bilatérales et sur les principales questions de politique internationale. M. Cassis souhaite souligner, lors de cette première visite, l’importance que la Suisse accorde à l’Italie et faire connaissance avec le ministre italien des affaires étrangères.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Les deux hommes feront le tour des relations entre les deux pays, qui sont très riches et diversifiées. Dans ce contexte, ils aborderont les questions fiscales et financières, le conseiller fédéral Cassis s’enquerra de l’état des dossiers concernant l’accès au marché italien des prestataires de services financiers et l’imposition des travailleurs frontaliers. Les relations entre la Suisse et l’Union européenne (UE), la vision italienne de l’avenir de l’UE et les défis de cette dernière seront au menu des conversations entre les deux ministres.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;La collaboration entre la Suisse et l’Italie en matière de politique migratoire sera également évoquée. Il feront notamment le point sur la situation en Méditerranée et en Libye. M. Cassis s’intéressera également à la présidence italienne de l’OSCE en 2018. Le chef du DFAE et M. Alfano auront un échange de vues sur les priorités de la présidence italienne dans l’organisation internationale.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;L’Italie est le cinquième partenaire commercial de la Suisse, avec un volume d’échanges commerciaux de 34 milliards de francs en 2016. Aujourd’hui, quelque 320’000 ressortissants italiens vivent en Suisse, formant la plus grande communauté étrangère du pays, et 70’000 frontaliers italiens environ travaillent en Suisse. Plus de 50’000 ressortissants suisses vivent en Italie. Les liens étroits qui unissent les deux pays trouvent leur expression dans les rencontres bilatérales qui sont régulièrement organisées à différents echelons.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Communication DFAE Palais fédéral ouest CH-3003 Berne Tél. Service de communication: +41 58 462 31 53 Tél. Service de presse: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <link id="172605">
        <title>Relations bilatérales Suisse – Italie</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae/representations-et-conseils-aux-voyageurs/italie/suisse-italie.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Ignazio Cassis a Roma per la sua prima visita all’estero</title>
      <lead>Il consigliere federale Ignazio Cassis si recherà martedì a Roma per una visita di lavoro durante la quale incontrerà Angelino Alfano, il ministro italiano degli affari esteri. L’obiettivo di questa prima visita del nuovo capo del Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri (DFAE) sarà di fare il punto sulle questioni bilaterali e sulle principali questioni di politica internazionale. Durante questa prima visita, Ignazio Cassis intende sottolineare l’importanza che la Svizzera accorda all’Italia e fare conoscenza con il ministro italiano degli affari esteri.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;I due ministri faranno il punto delle relazioni tra i due Paesi, molto intense e diversificate. In questo contesto affronteranno le questioni fiscali e finanziarie: il consigliere federale Cassis si informerà sullo stato dei dossier riguardanti l’accesso al mercato italiano dei fornitori di servizi finanziari e l’imposizione dei lavoratori frontalieri. All’ordine del giorno figureranno anche le relazioni tra la Svizzera e l’Unione europea (UE), la visione italiana del futuro dell’UE e le sfide che essa dovrà affrontare.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Anche la collaborazione tra la Svizzera e l’Italia in materia di politica migratoria sarà presa in considerazione. I due ministri tratteranno, infatti, la situazione nel Mediterraneo e in Libia. Ignazio Cassis si interesserà anche della presidenza italiana dell’OSCE nel 2018. Il capo del DFAE e Angelino Alfano avranno uno scambio di vedute sulle priorità della presidenza italiana nell’organizzazione internazionale.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;L’Italia è il quinto partner commerciale della Svizzera, con un volume di scambi commerciali pari a 34 miliardi di franchi nel 2016. Oggi sono circa 320 000 le cittadine e i cittadini italiani che vivono in Svizzera – si tratta della più grande comunità straniera nel Paese – e circa 70 000 i frontalieri che lavorano in Svizzera. Oltre 50 000 cittadine e cittadini svizzeri vivono in Italia. Gli stretti legami che uniscono la Svizzera e l’Italia trovano espressione negli incontri bilaterali organizzati periodicamente a vari livelli.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Comunicazione DFAE Palazzo federale ovest CH-3003 Berna Tel. Servizio di comunicazione: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Servizio stampa: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <link id="172602">
        <title>Relazioni bilaterali Svizzera – Italia</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae/rappresentanze-e-consigli-di-viaggio/italia/svizzera-italia.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Ignazio Cassis in Rome on his first foreign visit</title>
      <lead>Federal Councillor Ignazio Cassis will be in Rome on Tuesday for a working visit, including a meeting with Italian Foreign Minister Angelino Alfano. The goal of this first visit of the new head of the Federal Department of Foreign Affairs (FDFA) will be to review bilateral matters and key issues of international policy. During this first visit, Mr Cassis is keen to underline the importance Switzerland attaches to its relationship with Italy and to become acquainted with the Italian foreign minister.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;The two ministers will cover Swiss-Italian bilateral relations, which are very rich and diverse. This includes tax and financial matters, and Mr Cassis will also enquire about the status of dossiers linked to market access in Italy for financial service providers and the taxation of cross-border workers. Relations between Switzerland and the European Union (EU), Italy’s vision for the future of the EU and the challenges related to this will also be on the ministers’ agenda.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Another topic of discussion will concern cooperation between Switzerland and Italy with regard to migration policy, with a focus on the situation in the Mediterranean and Libya in particular. Mr Cassis is also interested in Italy’s chairmanship of the OSCE in 2018 and will share his views with Mr Alfano on the Italian chairmanship’s priorities for this international organisation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Italy is Switzerland’s fifth-largest trading partner, with a volume of trade of CHF 34 billion in 2016. Some 320,000 Italian citizens currently live in Switzerland, forming the largest group of foreign nationals in the country, while another 70,000 Italians cross the border each day to work in Switzerland. More than 50,000 Swiss nationals live in Italy. The close ties between the two countries are expressed in the bilateral meetings that regularly take place at different levels.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>FDFA Communication Federal Palace West Wing CH-3003 Bern, Switzerland Tel. Communication service: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Press service: +41 58 460 55 55 E-mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @SwissMFA</contact>
      <link id="172603">
        <title>Bilateral relations Switzerland - Italy</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home/representations-and-travel-advice/italy/switzerland-italy.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
