<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="69101" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2017-12-05</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="201" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>201</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="201">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Bundesrat Ignazio Cassis nimmt an der Ministerratskonferenz der OSZE in Wien teil</title>
      <lead>Bundesrat Ignazio Cassis, der Vorsteher des Eidgenössischen Departements für auswärtige Angelegenheiten EDA, wird am 7. Dezember 2017 die Schweiz am Ministerrat der Organisation für Sicherheit und Zusammenarbeit in Europa (OSZE) vertreten. Der Ministerrat ist das wichtigste Beschluss- und Leitungsgremium der OSZE auf Ebene der Aussenminister. Am Rande des Treffens wird Bundesrat Cassis auch bilaterale Gespräche führen.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Auf Einladung des amtierenden Vorsitzenden der OSZE und österreichischen Aussenministers, Sebastian Kurz, reist Bundesrat Ignazio Cassis am kommenden Donnerstag zur Ministerratskonferenz der Organisation nach Wien. Im Zentrum des diesjährigen Treffens stehen unter anderem der laufende „strukturelle Dialog“ über die Sicherheit in Europa und verschiedene regionale Konflikte, darunter die Krise in der Ukraine.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Bundesrat Cassis wird an der Konferenz das Engagement der Schweiz innerhalb der OSZE als wichtiger Plattform für den Dialog über die europäische Sicherheit und die Entwicklung politischer Lösungen von Konflikten unterstreichen. Er wird seinen Aufenthalt in Wien auch zu bilateralen Treffen nutzen, darunter mit dem österreichischen Aussenminister Kurz.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Der Ministerrat stellt jeweils im Dezember die Weichen für die weitere Arbeit der Organisation. In Wien werden rund 40 Aussenministerinnen und Aussenminister erwartet. Am 1. Januar 2018 wird Italien den Vorsitz der OSZE übernehmen.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Kommunikation EDA Bundeshaus West CH-3003 Bern Tel. Kommunikationsservice: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Medienstelle: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <link id="173361">
        <title>EDA: Organisation für Sicherheit und Zusammenarbeit in Europa</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home/aussenpolitik/internationale-organisationen/organisation-fuersicherheitundzusammenarbeitineuropaosze.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Le conseiller fédéral Ignazio Cassis participera au Conseil ministériel de l’OSCE à Vienne</title>
      <lead>Le conseiller fédéral Ignazio Cassis, chef du Département fédéral des affaires étrangères (DFAE), représentera la Suisse le 7 décembre 2017 à la conférence du Conseil ministériel de l’Organisation pour la sécurité et la coopération en Europe (OSCE). Le Conseil ministériel est le principal organe de décision et de direction de l’OSCE au niveau des ministres des affaires étrangères. En marge de la réunion, Ignazio Cassis mènera également des entretiens bilatéraux.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Répondant à l’invitation du président en exercice de l’OSCE et ministre autrichien des affaires étrangères Sebastian Kurz, le conseiller fédéral Ignazio Cassis se rendra jeudi prochain à Vienne pour participer à la conférence du Conseil ministériel de l’organisation. Cette année, la rencontre aura notamment pour thème le «dialogue structurel» en cours sur la sécurité en Europe et différents conflits régionaux, dont la crise ukrainienne.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Lors de la conférence, le conseiller fédéral Ignazio Cassis soulignera l’engagement de la Suisse au sein de l’OSCE en tant que plateforme importante pour le dialogue sur la sécurité en Europe et le développement de solutions politiques aux conflits. Il profitera par ailleurs de son séjour à Vienne pour prendre part à des séances bilatérales, notamment avec le ministre autrichien des affaires étrangères Sebastian Kurz.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Chaque année, en décembre, le Conseil ministériel définit les grandes lignes de l’action future de l’organisation. Près de 40 ministres des affaires étrangères sont attendus à Vienne. Le 1er janvier 2018, l’Italie prendra la présidence de l’OSCE.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Communication DFAE Palais fédéral ouest CH-3003 Berne Tél. Service de communication: +41 58 462 31 53 Tél. Service de presse: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <link id="173360">
        <title>DFAE: Organisation pour la sécurité et la coopération en Europe</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae/politique-exterieure/organisations-internationales/osce.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Il consigliere federale Ignazio Cassis partecipa alla riunione del Consiglio dei ministri dell’OSCE a Vienna</title>
      <lead>Il 7 dicembre 2017 il consigliere federale Ignazio Cassis, capo del Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri (DFAE), rappresenterà la Svizzera al Consiglio dei ministri dell’Organizzazione per la sicurezza e la cooperazione in Europa (OSCE). Il Consiglio dei ministri è il principale organo decisionale e di direzione dell’OSCE a livello di ministri degli esteri. A margine dell’incontro il consigliere federale Cassis avrà alcuni colloqui bilaterali.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Su invito della presidenza in carica dell’OSCE e del ministro degli esteri austrico Sebastian Kurz, il consigliere federale Ignazio Cassis si recherà giovedì a Vienna alla riunione del Consiglio dei ministri dell’Organizzazione. Il «dialogo strutturato» in corso sulla sicurezza in Europa, e vari conflitti regionali, tra cui la crisi in Ucraina, sono alcuni dei temi che l’incontro di quest’anno metterà in primo piano.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Al Consiglio dei ministri il consigliere federale Cassis sottolineerà l’impegno della Svizzera all’interno dell’OSCE in quanto importante piattaforma per il dialogo sulla sicurezza europea e la ricerca di soluzioni politiche ai conflitti. Approfitterà inoltre del soggiorno a Vienna per condurre alcuni colloqui bilaterali, anche con il ministro degli esteri austriaco Kurz.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Nel mese di dicembre il Consiglio dei ministri dell’OSCE getta le basi per il futuro lavoro dell’Organizzazione. A Vienna saranno presenti 40 ministre e ministri degli esteri. Il 1° gennaio 2018 l’Italia assumerà la presidenza dell'OSCE.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Comunicazione DFAE Palazzo federale ovest CH-3003 Berna Tel. Servizio di comunicazione: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Servizio stampa: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <link id="173359">
        <title>DFAE: Organizzazione per la sicurezza e la cooperazione in Europa</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae/politica-estera/organizzazioni-internazionali/osce.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Federal Councillor Ignazio Cassis attends OSCE Ministerial Council in Vienna</title>
      <lead>Federal Councillor Ignazio Cassis, head of the Federal Department of Foreign Affairs (FDFA), will represent Switzerland at the Ministerial Council of the Organization for Security and Co-operation in Europe (OSCE) on 7 December 2017. The Ministerial Council is the most important decision-making and management body of the OSCE at foreign-minister level. In the margins of the meeting, Mr Cassis will also hold bilateral talks.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;At the invitation of OSCE Chairperson-in-Office and Austrian Foreign Minister Sebastian Kurz, Federal Councillor Ignazio Cassis will travel to Vienna for the OSCE's Ministerial Council on Thursday. This year's meeting will focus, among other things, on the ongoing 'structural dialogue' on security in Europe and various regional conflicts, including the crisis in Ukraine.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;At the conference, Mr Cassis will underscore Switzerland's commitment within the OSCE as an important platform for dialogue on European security and the development of political solutions to conflicts. He will also use his visit to Vienna for bilateral meetings, including with Austrian Foreign Minister Sebastian Kurz.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Each December the Ministerial Council sets the course of the organisation's work for the coming year. Around 40 foreign ministers are expected in Vienna. On 1 January 2018, Italy will take over the chairmanship of the OSCE.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>FDFA Communication Federal Palace West Wing CH-3003 Bern, Switzerland Tel. Communication service: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Press service: +41 58 460 55 55 E-mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @SwissMFA</contact>
      <link id="173358">
        <title>FDFA: Organization for Security and Co-operation in Europe</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home/foreign-policy/international-organizations/osce.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
