<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="75253" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2019-05-29</pubdate>
    <blocking-period>2019-05-29</blocking-period>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="324" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>301</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Swissmedic, Schweizerisches Heilmittelinstitut</name>
      <name lang="fr">Swissmedic, Institut suisse des produits thérapeutiques</name>
      <name lang="it">Swissmedic, Istituto svizzero per gli agenti terapeutici</name>
      <name lang="en">Swiss Agency for Therapeutic Products</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.swissmedic.ch/</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.swissmedic.ch/?lang=3</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.swissmedic.ch/?lang=4</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.swissmedic.ch/?lang=2</www>
      <email lang="de"/>
      <email lang="fr"/>
      <email lang="it"/>
      <email lang="en"/>
    </originator>
    <department id="301">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement des Innern</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'intérieur</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'interno</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Home Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Swissmedic Geschäftsbericht 2018</title>
      <lead>«Swissmedic erfüllt ihren Auftrag unabhängig, kompetent und mit Innovationsgeist»: Der Präsident des Institutsrats, Stéphane Rossini, zieht im Geschäftsbericht 2018 eine positive Bilanz. Das Hauptziel ist und bleibt die Sicherstellung einer wirksamen und unabhängigen Heilmittelkontrolle in enger Zusammenarbeit und im Dialog mit nationalen und internationalen Regulierungsbehörden und den anderen Akteuren im Gesundheitswesen.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Dabei gilt es für das Institut, mit der zunehmenden Digitalisierung Schritt zu halten, um die immer komplexer werdenden Aufgaben noch effizienter zu bewältigen. Bei der Ausarbeitung der Strategischen Ziele 2019-2022 hat der Institutsrat letztes Jahr die aktuellen Herausforderungen identifiziert und die Prioritäten festgelegt. Der Bundesrat hat die Ziele genehmigt und damit deren Bedeutung bestätigt.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Leistungsfähigkeit&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Im Jahr 2018 wurden bei Swissmedic 352 Gesuche um innovative Erstzulassungen und wesentliche Änderungen innovativer Arzneimittel eingereicht; 377 Gesuche konnten abgeschlossen werden. Im Berichtsjahr wurden 32 innovative Arzneimittel zugelassen, davon vier im beschleunigten Zulassungsverfahren.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;99,4 Prozent aller eingereichten Zulassungsgesuche konnten 2018 fristgerecht abgeschlossen werden. Bei den innovativen Arzneimitteln wurden 99,7 Prozent und bei den nicht-innovativen 94,3 Prozent der Gesuche innerhalb der vorgegebenen Fristen erledigt.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Umsetzung der überarbeiteten Rechtsgrundlagen&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Die Vorbereitungen für die Inkraftsetzung des revidierten Heilmittelgesetzes prägten auch das Geschäftsjahr 2018. Ziel für Swissmedic war es, am 1. Januar 2019 operativ und funktionell bereit sein, die Geschäftstätigkeit nach den neuen rechtlichen Vorgaben zu erfüllen. Das neue Heilmittelrecht erleichtert den Marktzutritt für Arzneimittel, verbessert die Arzneimittelsicherheit und erhöht die Transparenz.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Änderung der Abgabekategorien&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Der Gesetzgeber hat mit dem neuen Heilmittelrecht entschieden, die Selbst-medikation zu erleichtern und die Fachkompetenz der Abgabestellen besser zu nutzen. Das revidierte Heilmittelgesetz kennt noch vier Abgabekategorien – die bisherige Abgabekategorie C (Apothekenpflicht) entfällt. Rund 650 Arzneimittel dieser Kategorie wurden nach wissenschaftlichen Kriterien und unter Einbezug externer Fachexperten beurteilt, 85 Prozent neu für eine Abgabe in Drogerien oder Apotheken (Abgabekategorie D) vorgeschlagen.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Auch die 540 Arzneimittel der Abgabekategorie D wurden überprüft, 17 Prozent davon neu für eine Abgabe ohne Fachberatung in der Selbstbedienung (Abgabekategorie E) empfohlen. Die Abgabekategorie E wird dadurch auf 240 Arzneimittel erweitert. Die übrigen Präparate sind für Erkrankungen vorgesehen, für die es zwingend eine Fachberatung braucht und sollen in der entsprechenden Abgabekategorie bleiben.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Die eigentliche Umteilung findet 2019 statt. Die rechtskräftigen Umteilungsentscheide werden laufend im Swissmedic Journal publiziert. Während eines Jahres dürfen noch alte Packungen an die Abgabestellen ausgeliefert werden, spätestens zwei Jahre nach der Umteilungsverfügung müssen alle Änderungen auf Packungen und in der Arzneimittelinformation umgesetzt sein.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Swissmedic beschäftigte Ende letzten Jahres 425 (im Vorjahr 424) Mitarbeitende, verteilt auf 350 (349) Vollzeitstellen.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Ende 2018 waren 8'259 (2017: 8'296) Arzneimittel in der Schweiz von Swissmedic zugelassen, davon 715 Tierarzneimittel. Auch die Anzahl der im Meldeverfahren zugelassenen homöopathischen oder anthroposophischen Arzneimittel ohne Indikation (11‘041 Einzelmittel und 1'008 Komplexmittel) blieb nahezu unverändert.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Im letzten Jahr fielen 1479 (1'276) Gesuche um Verlängerung der Zulassung an. Zudem gab es 274 (274) Gesuche um Verzicht auf ein Präparat oder auf eine Dosisstärkennummer eines Präparates. 65 (106) Mal verzichteten die Zulassungsinhaberinnen auf eine Verlängerung der Zulassung.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Swissmedic, Schweizerisches Heilmittelinstitut Medienstelle +41 58 462 02 76 media@swissmedic.ch</contact>
      <link id="190420">
        <title>Swissmedic Geschäftsbericht 2018</title>
        <uri>https://www.swissmedic.ch/swissmedic/de/home/ueber-uns/publikationen/aktueller-geschaeftsbericht/swissmedic-geschaeftsbericht-2018.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Rapport d’activité 2018 de Swissmedic</title>
      <lead>« Swissmedic exécute son mandat en toute indépendance, de manière compétente et dans un esprit d’innovation » : Stéphane Rossini, président du Conseil de l’institut, tire un bilan positif dans le rapport d’activité 2018. L’objectif principal est encore et toujours de garantir un contrôle efficace et indépendant des produits thérapeutiques, en dialoguant et en collaborant étroitement avec les autorités réglementaires nationales et internationales ainsi que d’autres acteurs du secteur de la santé.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Dans ce contexte, l’institut doit s’adapter à la numérisation croissante afin d’assumer de manière encore plus efficace des tâches de plus en plus complexes. L’an dernier, le Conseil de l’institut a identifié les défis actuels et établi les priorités lors de la définition des objectifs stratégiques 2019-2022. Le Conseil fédéral a approuvé ces objectifs, confirmant ainsi leur importance.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Performance&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;En 2018, 352 demandes de première autorisation et de modifications essentielles ont été déposées pour des médicaments novateurs et 377 demandes ont pu être clôturées. Pendant l’année sous revue, l’institut a par ailleurs autorisé 32 médicaments novateurs, dont quatre dans le cadre d’une procédure rapide d’autorisation.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;En 2018, 99,4 % des demandes d’autorisation reçues ont été clôturées dans les délais prescrits. Ce taux atteint 99,7 % pour les médicaments novateurs et 94,3 % pour les médicaments non novateurs.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Application des bases juridiques remaniées&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;L’exercice 2018 a également été marqué par les travaux de préparation de l’entrée en vigueur de la loi révisée sur les produits thérapeutiques. L’objectif de Swissmedic était d’être prêt au 1er janvier 2019, sur les plans opérationnel et fonctionnel, à mener ses activités dans le respect des nouvelles prescriptions légales. La nouvelle législation relative aux produits thérapeutiques facilite la mise sur le marché des médicaments, améliore leur sécurité et augmente la transparence.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Changement dans les catégories de remise&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Dans le cadre de la nouvelle législation sur les produits thérapeutiques, le législateur a décidé de faciliter l’automédication et de mieux utiliser la compétence spécialisée des points de remise des médicaments. La loi révisée sur les produits thérapeutiques reconnaît encore quatre catégories de remise – la catégorie de remise C (remise obligatoire en pharmacie) n’existe plus. Environ 650 médicaments de cette catégorie ont été évalués selon des critères scientifiques définis et en impliquant des experts externes et une remise en droguerie ou en pharmacie (catégorie de remise D) a été recommandée pour 85 % d’entre eux.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;De même, les 540 médicaments appartenant à la catégorie de remise D ont été évalués et une remise en libre-service sans conseil spécialisé (catégorie de remise E) a été recommandée pour 17 % d’entre eux. La catégorie de remise E est ainsi élargie à 240 médicaments. Les préparations restantes sont prévues pour des affections qui nécessitent impérativement un conseil spécialisé et doivent donc rester dans la catégorie de remise correspondante.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;La reclassification effective a lieu en 2019. Les décisions définitives de reclassification sont publiées en continu dans le Journal Swissmedic. Les points de remise peuvent encore recevoir d’anciens emballages pendant un an, mais toutes les modifications devront être apportées sur les emballages et dans les textes d’information sur le médicament au plus tard deux ans après la décision de reclassification.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;À la fin de l’année dernière, Swissmedic employait 425 personnes (contre 424 l’année précédente) réparties sur 350 postes à plein temps (349).&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Fin 2018, 8259 médicaments (2017 : 8296), dont 715 médicaments à usage vétérinaire, étaient autorisés en Suisse par Swissmedic. Le nombre de médicaments homéopathiques ou anthroposophiques sans indication autorisés dans le cadre d’une procédure d’annonce reste également presque inchangé (11 041 unitaires et 1008 complexes).&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;L’institut a reçu 1479 demandes de prolongation d’autorisation (1276) pendant l’année sous revue. De plus, 274 (274) demandes de renonciation à une préparation ou à un numéro de dosage ont été enregistrées. Dans 65 (106) cas, le titulaire de l’autorisation a renoncé à sa prolongation.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Swissmedic, Institut suisse des produits thérapeutiques Service de presse +41 58 462 02 76 media@swissmedic.ch</contact>
      <link id="190421">
        <title>Rapport d’activité 2018 de Swissmedic</title>
        <uri>https://www.swissmedic.ch/swissmedic/fr/home/ueber-uns/publikationen/aktueller-geschaeftsbericht/swissmedic-geschaeftsbericht-2018.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Rapporto di gestione 2018 di Swissmedic</title>
      <lead>«Swissmedic adempie il proprio mandato in modo indipendente, competente e con spirito di innovazione»: nel rapporto di gestione 2018 Stéphane Rossini, presidente del Consiglio dell’Istituto, fa un bilancio positivo. L’obiettivo principale è e rimane quello di garantire un controllo efficace e indipendente degli agenti terapeutici, in stretta collaborazione e dialogo con le autorità di regolamentazione nazionali e internazionali e altri attori del sistema sanitario.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;In tal senso, per l’Istituto è importante tenere il passo con la crescente digitalizzazione, così da affrontare in modo ancora più efficiente i compiti sempre più complessi. Nell’elaborare gli Obiettivi strategici 2019-2022, lo scorso anno il Consiglio dell’Istituto ha identificato le sfide attuali e definito le priorità. Il Consiglio federale ha approvato tali obiettivi, confermandone quindi l’importanza.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Efficienza&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Nel 2018 Swissmedic ha ricevuto 352 domande di prime omologazioni innovative e modifiche sostanziali per medicamenti innovativi e ne ha evase 377. Nell’anno in esame sono stati omologati 32 medicamenti innovativi, quattro dei quali mediante procedura di omologazione accelerata.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Nel 2018, il 99,4 per cento delle domande di omologazione presentate è stato evaso puntualmente. Le domande concernenti i medicamenti innovativi sono state evase al 99,7 per cento entro i termini stabiliti, quelle relative ai medicamenti non innovativi al 94,3 per cento.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Attuazione delle basi giuridiche rielaborate&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Anche l’esercizio 2018 è stato caratterizzato dai preparativi per l’entrata in vigore della revisione della legge sugli agenti terapeutici. Per il 1° gennaio 2019 Swissmedic intendeva essere pronto, sul piano operativo e funzionale, a svolgere la sua attività conformemente alle nuove disposizioni giuridiche. Il nuovo diritto in materia di agenti terapeutici agevola l’accesso al mercato per i medicamenti, ne migliora la sicurezza e incrementa la trasparenza.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Modifica delle categorie di dispensazione&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Con il nuovo diritto in materia di agenti terapeutici, il legislatore ha deciso di semplificare l’automedicazione e sfruttare meglio la competenza specialistica dei punti di dispensazione. La nuova legge sugli agenti terapeutici prevede ora quattro categorie di dispensazione, dal momento che la precedente categoria di dispensazione C (obbligo per le farmacie) è stata abolita. Circa 650 medicamenti di questa categoria sono stati valutati secondo criteri scientifici e con il coinvolgimento di esperti esterni e per l’85 per cento di loro è stata proposta la dispensazione in drogherie o farmacie (categoria di dispensazione D).&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Anche i 540 medicamenti della categoria di dispensazione D sono stati esaminati e per il 17 per cento è stata raccomandata la dispensazione in self-service senza consulenza specialistica (categoria di dispensazione E). La categoria di dispensazione E è così ampliata a 240 medicamenti. I restanti preparati sono invece destinati a malattie per le quali è assolutamente necessaria una consulenza specialistica e in quanto tali devono rimanere nella categoria di dispensazione corrispondente.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;La riassegnazione alle nuove categorie è prevista nel 2019. Le decisioni di riassegnazione divenute vincolanti saranno regolarmente pubblicate nello Swissmedic Journal. Le vecchie confezioni potranno ancora essere fornite ai punti di dispensazione per un anno, ma al più tardi entro due anni dalla decisione di riassegnazione dovranno essere attuate tutte le modifiche sulle confezioni e nelle informazioni sui medicamenti.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Alla fine dello scorso anno Swissmedic impiegava 425 collaboratori (anno precedente: 424), ripartiti su 350 (349) posti a tempo pieno.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;A fine 2018 Swissmedic aveva omologato in Svizzera 8’259 medicamenti (2017: 8’296), di cui 715 per uso veterinario. Anche il numero di medicamenti omeopatici o antroposofici omologati con procedura di notifica senza indicazione è rimasto pressoché invariato (11’041 rimedi singoli e 1’008 rimedi complessi).&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Lo scorso anno sono pervenute 1’479 (1’276) domande di proroga dell’omologazione. Sono inoltre state registrate 274 (274) domande di rinuncia a un preparato o all’indicazione del dosaggio di un preparato. I titolari dell’omologazione hanno rinunciato 65 (106) volte a prorogare l’omologazione.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Swissmedic, Istituto svizzero per gli agenti terapeutici Ufficio stampa +41 58 462 02 76 media@swissmedic.ch</contact>
      <link id="190422">
        <title>Rapporto di gestione 2018 di Swissmedic</title>
        <uri>https://www.swissmedic.ch/swissmedic/it/home/ueber-uns/publikationen/aktueller-geschaeftsbericht/swissmedic-geschaeftsbericht-2018.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Swissmedic Annual Report 2018</title>
      <lead>"Swissmedic performs its mandate independently, professionally and in a spirit of innovation": that was the positive verdict expressed by Stéphane Rossini, Chairman of the Agency Council, in the 2018 Annual Report. The principal aim is, and will remain, to ensure the effective and impartial control of therapeutic products in close cooperation – and as part of an ongoing dialogue – with national and international regulatory authorities and other healthcare stakeholders.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;At the same time, the Agency has to keep up with advancing digitalisation so that it can perform its increasingly complex tasks even more efficiently. Last year, in formulating its strategic objectives for the period 2019-2022, the Agency Council identified the current challenges and fixed its priorities. The Federal Council has approved the objectives and thus confirmed their importance.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Efficiency&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;In 2018, Swissmedic received 352 applications for innovative first authorisations of and major variations to innovative medicinal products; it completed 377 applications. Thirty-two innovative medicinal products were approved during the year, of which four qualified for the fast-track procedure – with the latter, new medicines obtain marketing authorisation within 140 days provided certain conditions are met.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;99.4 percent of all approval applications were completed on schedule in 2018. 99.7 percent of applications for innovative medicinal products and 94.3 percent of applications for non-innovative medicinal products were completed within the prescribed time limits.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Implementation of the revised legal parameters&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Like the previous year, 2018 was dominated by preparations for the entry into force of the revised Therapeutic Products Act. Swissmedic's objective was to be operationally and functionally ready to conduct its business activities in compliance with the new legal requirements as of 1 January 2019. The new therapeutic products legislation simplifies market access for therapeutic products, increases safety and improves transparency.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Changes to dispensing categories&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;In revising the Therapeutic Products Act, the government decided to simplify the rules on self-medication and make fuller use of the dispensing outlets' specialist competencies. Under the revised Act, there are now only four dispensing categories: dispensing category C ("pharmacy only") has been dropped. Around 650 medicinal products in this category were assessed according to scientific criteria and with the involvement of external specialists. It was proposed that 85 percent of these be assigned to dispensing category D (dispensing by pharmacies and druggists).&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The 540 medicinal products in dispensing category D were also examined: it was recommended that 17 percent of these be assigned to dispensing category E (self-serve basis without expert advice). As a result, dispensing category E has been expanded to include 240 medicinal products. All the other products are intended for the treatment of illnesses that require expert advice and must therefore remain in the corresponding dispensing categories.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Reclassification is taking place in 2019, with the individual decisions being published in the Swissmedic Journal as they take legal effect. Existing packaging can continue to be supplied to dispensing outlets for one year, but within two years after reclassification at the latest all changes must have been implemented on packaging and in the product information.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;At the end of last year, Swissmedic employed 425 persons (prior year: 424), and the number of full time equivalent positions was 350 (349).&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;At the end of 2018, 8,259 medicinal products were approved by Swissmedic for the Swiss market, 715 of them veterinary medicinal products. The number of homeopathic and anthroposophic medicinal products without an indication authorised under the notification procedure was also virtually unchanged (11,041 single products and 1,008 combined products).&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;1,479 applications to extend marketing authorisation were received last year (2017: 1,276). In addition, there were 274 (274) applications for the discontinuation of a preparation or a dosage strength. Authorisation holders opted not to extend the authorisations of 65 (106) products.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Swissmedic, Swiss Agency for Therapeutic Products Media Office +41 58 462 02 76 media@swissmedic.ch</contact>
      <link id="190423">
        <title>Swissmedic Annual Report 2018</title>
        <uri>https://www.swissmedic.ch/swissmedic/en/home/ueber-uns/publikationen/aktueller-geschaeftsbericht/swissmedic-geschaeftsbericht-2018.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="15">
        <name lang="de">Gesundheit</name>
        <name lang="fr">Santé</name>
        <name lang="it">sanità</name>
        <name lang="en">Health</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
