<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="75599" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2019-06-26</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="1070" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>1070</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Der Bundesrat</name>
      <name lang="fr">Conseil fédéral</name>
      <name lang="it">Il Consiglio federale</name>
      <name lang="en">The Federal Council</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.admin.ch/gov/de/start.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.admin.ch/gov/fr/accueil.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.admin.ch/gov/it/pagina-iniziale.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.admin.ch/gov/en/start.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="yes" id="1060" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>601</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Staatssekretariat für internationale Finanzfragen</name>
      <name lang="fr">Secrétariat d'Etat aux questions financières internationales</name>
      <name lang="it">Segreteria di Stato per le questioni finanziarie internazionali</name>
      <name lang="en">State Secretariat for International Financial Matters</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.sif.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.sif.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.sif.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.sif.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@sif.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@sif.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@sif.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@sif.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="811" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>801</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Bundesamt für Umwelt BAFU</name>
      <name lang="fr">Office fédéral de l'environnement OFEV</name>
      <name lang="it">Ufficio federale dell'ambiente UFAM</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Office for the Environment FOEN</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.bafu.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.bafu.admin.ch/fr</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.bafu.admin.ch/it</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.bafu.admin.ch/en</www>
      <email lang="de">info@bafu.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@bafu.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@bafu.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@bafu.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="1070">
      <name lang="de">Der Bundesrat</name>
      <name lang="fr">Conseil fédéral</name>
      <name lang="it">Il Consiglio federale</name>
      <name lang="en">The Federal Council</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.admin.ch/gov/de/start.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.admin.ch/gov/fr/accueil.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.admin.ch/gov/it/pagina-iniziale.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.admin.ch/gov/en/start.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <department id="601">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Finanzdepartement</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des finances</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale delle finanze</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Finance</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.efd.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.dff.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.efd.admin.ch/efd/it/home.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.efd.admin.ch/efd/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <department id="801">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Umwelt, Verkehr, Energie und Kommunikation</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'environnement, des transports, de l'énergie et de la communication</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'ambiente, dei trasporti, dell'energia e delle comunicazioni</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of the Environment, Transport, Energy and Communications</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.uvek.admin.ch/uvek/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.uvek.admin.ch/uvek/fr/home.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.uvek.admin.ch/uvek/it/home.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.uvek.admin.ch/uvek/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-uvek.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-uvek.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-uvek.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-uvek.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Bundesrat diskutiert über «Sustainable Finance» und legt das weitere Vorgehen fest</title>
      <lead>Der Bundesrat hat an seiner Sitzung vom 26. Juni 2019 eine Aussprache über einen nachhaltigen Finanzplatz Schweiz geführt. Er sieht in diesem Bereich grosse Chancen für Innovation und Wettbewerbsfähigkeit und hat entschieden, eine Arbeitsgruppe einzusetzen, die verschiedene Abklärungen an die Hand nehmen soll.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Bereits seit 2016 gelten als Grundsätze das Primat marktwirtschaftlicher langfristiger Ansätze und die Subsidiarität staatlichen Handelns. Gefördert werden beim Einbezug von Umweltaspekten und sozialen Themen in der Finanzbranche konkret Transparenz und Freiwilligkeit.[1] Das Bundesamt für Umwelt (BAFU) und das Staatssekretariat für Finanzfragen (SIF) bieten im Jahr 2020 erneut kostenlose Klimaverträglichkeitstests an, die neben Pensionskassen und Versicherungen neu auch Banken und Vermögensverwaltern offenstehen. Sie werden aufzeigen, inwieweit gegenüber den erstmaligen Tests im Jahre 2017 Fortschritte erzielt worden sind. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Der Bundesrat hat sich im Rahmen seiner Aussprache über einen nachhaltigen Finanzmarkt einen Überblick verschafft über die aktuellen Entwicklungen und Initiativen sowie das Engagement der Schweiz auf internationaler Ebene. Insbesondere im Rahmen des Klimaübereinkommens von Paris sowie der Agenda 2030 für Nachhaltige Entwicklung ist die Schweiz internationale Verpflichtungen eingegangen.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Neu wird eine Arbeitsgruppe unter der Leitung des SIF in enger Zusammenarbeit mit dem BAFU und weiteren interessierten Behörden verschiedene Arbeiten an die Hand nehmen. Unter anderem sollen möglichst rasch Beurteilungsgrundlagen vorgelegt werden für eine Klärung der Teilnahme der Schweiz an internationalen Initiativen – wie beispielsweise der von Chile und Finnland ins Leben gerufenen «Coalition of Finance Ministers for Climate Action». Zudem sollen die Auswirkungen geprüft werden, die die Entwicklungen in der EU im Bereich des Aktionsplans für nachhaltige Finanzanlagen für den Schweizer Finanzplatz haben. Bis spätestens im Frühling 2020 soll ein Bericht der Arbeitsgruppe vorliegen, der die Resultate dieser Prüfung sowie Vorschläge für den Finanzmarkt Schweiz enthält. Zur Frage, ob und wie der Finanzmarkt reguliert werden soll, will der Bundesrat bis Ende Jahr erneut eine Aussprache führen. Grundsätzlich sollen die Rahmenbedingungen eruiert werden, die es dem Schweizer Finanzplatz erlauben, im Bereich nachhaltiger Finanzen wettbewerbsfähig zu sein. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Schliesslich soll die Arbeitsgruppe auf einen Abschluss von Branchenvereinbarungen mit den Finanzmarktakteuren hinwirken. Diese sollen insbesondere zur Erhöhung der Transparenz und eine Selbstverpflichtung der Branche zu einer repräsentativen Teilnahme an den oben genannten Klimaverträglichkeitstests im Hinblick auf die Erreichung konkreter Ziele führen. Ziel ist eine Stärkung der Wettbewerbsfähigkeit, so dass Kunden und Anlegern gegenüber klare Informationen und damit Entscheidungsmöglichkeiten geboten werden können. Hierzu wird mit der Branche der Dialog intensiviert. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;[1] Vgl. Medienmitteilung vom 24. Februar 2016 («Internationale Finanzgremien diskutieren Fragen der Nachhaltigkeit: Bundesrat definiert Rolle der Schweiz»)&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Anne Césard, Co-Leiterin Kommunikation SIF Tel. +41 58 462 62 91,anne.cesard@sif.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="191207">
        <title>Medienmitteilung vom 24. Februar 2016 («Internationale Finanzgremien diskutieren Fragen der Nachhaltigkeit: Bundesrat definiert Rolle der Schweiz»)</title>
        <uri>https://www.efd.admin.ch/efd/de/home/dokumentation/nsb-news_list.msg-id-60755.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Le Conseil fédéral discute de finance durable et définit la suite des travaux</title>
      <lead>Lors de sa séance du 26 juin 2019, le Conseil fédéral a mené une discussion sur la finance durable en Suisse. Il voit dans ce domaine une grande chance de promouvoir l'innovation et d'accroître la compétitivité. Il a donc décidé de créer un groupe de travail pour répondre aux différentes questions qui se posent.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;La primauté de solutions à long terme relevant de l'économie de marché et la subsidiarité de l’action publique sont des principes qui s'appliquent depuis 2016 déjà. Concrètement, la transparence et l'engagement volontaire sont essentiels pour intégrer les questions sociales et environnementales dans le secteur financier[1]. En 2020, l'Office fédéral de l'environnement (OFEV) et le Secrétariat d'État aux questions financières internationales (SFI) proposeront de nouveaux tests de compatibilité climatique gratuits, non seulement aux caisses de pensions et aux assurances, mais aussi aux banques et aux gestionnaires de fortune. L'objectif est de mettre en lumière les progrès accomplis depuis les premiers tests effectués en 2017. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Lors de sa discussion sur la finance durable, le Conseil fédéral a pu s'informer des dernières évolutions, des initiatives actuelles et de l'engagement de notre pays à l'étranger. La Suisse a contracté diverses obligations internationales, notamment dans le cadre de l'accord de Paris sur le climat et de l'Agenda 2030 pour le développement durable.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Dirigé par le SFI en étroite collaboration avec l'OFEV et d'autres autorités intéressées, un groupe de travail abordera différentes questions. Il devra notamment élaborer aussi rapidement que possible des bases d'évaluation permettant de clarifier la participation de la Suisse à des initiatives internationales telles que la &lt;i&gt;Coalition of Finance Ministers for Climate Action&lt;/i&gt;, instituée par le Chili et la Finlande. En outre, il devra examiner les effets que la modification du plan d'action européen en faveur de placements financiers durables a sur la place financière suisse. Enfin, il sera chargé de présenter d'ici au printemps 2020 un rapport comprenant les résultats de cet examen et des propositions pour la place financière suisse. Le Conseil fédéral entend mener une nouvelle discussion avant la fin de l'année pour déterminer s'il est nécessaire de réglementer le marché financier et, le cas échéant, de quelle manière. En substance, il faudra fixer le cadre permettant à la place financière suisse d'être compétitive dans le domaine de la finance durable. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Enfin, le groupe de travail devra œuvrer à la conclusion d'accords sectoriels avec les acteurs du marché financier. Ces accords contribueront à accroître la transparence et inciteront les différents secteurs à participer de manière représentative aux tests de compatibilité climatique afin d'atteindre des objectifs concrets. Le but est de renforcer la compétitivité de la place financière suisse et de fournir aux clients et aux investisseurs des informations claires et, par conséquent, la possibilité de prendre des décisions en toute connaissance de cause. Les discussions seront donc intensifiées à cette fin avec le secteur de la finance. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;[1] Voir le communiqué de presse du 24 février 2016 («Les organismes financiers internationaux débattent de la durabilité: le Conseil fédéral définit le rôle de la Suisse»)&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Anne Césard, coresponsable de la communication du Secrétariat d'État aux questions financières internationales SFI n° tél. +41 58 462 62 91, anne.cesard@sif.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="191208">
        <title>Communiqué de presse du 24 février 2016 («Les organismes financiers internationaux débattent de la durabilité: le Conseil fédéral définit le rôle de la Suisse»)</title>
        <uri>https://www.efd.admin.ch/efd/fr/home/dokumentation/nsb-news_list.msg-id-60755.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Il Consiglio federale discute di finanza sostenibile e definisce l’ulteriore modo di procedere</title>
      <lead>Nella sua seduta del 26 giugno 2019 il Consiglio federale ha discusso il tema di una piazza finanziaria svizzera sostenibile. In questo ambito esso intravede grandi opportunità in termini di innovazione e competitività e ha quindi deciso di istituire un gruppo di lavoro incaricato di chiarire diversi aspetti.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Sin dal 2016 si applicano i principi orientati al primato di soluzioni a lungo termine basate sull’economia di mercato e alla sussidiarietà delle attività dello Stato. Nell’includere gli aspetti ambientali e i temi sociali nel settore finanziario si promuovono concretamente la trasparenza e l’azione volontaria.[1] Anche nel 2020 l’Ufficio federale dell’ambiente (UFAM) e la Segreteria di Stato per le questioni finanziarie internazionali (SFI) proporranno esami della compatibilità climatica rivolti per la prima volta, oltre che alle casse pensioni e alle assicurazioni, anche alle banche e ai gestori patrimoniali. I risultati mostreranno i progressi rispetto ai primi test del 2017.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Nel quadro della discussione su un mercato finanziario sostenibile, il Consiglio federale ha tracciato una panoramica sugli sviluppi e sulle iniziative attuali nonché sull’impegno della Svizzera a livello internazionale. Nello specifico, il nostro Paese ha assunto impegni internazionali nell’ambito dell’Accordo di Parigi sul clima e dell’Agenda 2030 per uno sviluppo sostenibile.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;A breve un gruppo di lavoro guidato dalla SFI, in stretta collaborazione con l’UFAM e altre autorità interessate, intraprenderà diversi lavori. Tra le altre cose, dovranno essere presentati al più presto degli elementi per valutare l’eventuale partecipazione della Svizzera a iniziative internazionali, tra cui la «Coalizione mondiale dei ministri delle finanze per l’azione per il clima» («Coalition of Finance Ministers for Climate Action») lanciata dal Cile e dalla Finlandia. Verranno inoltre esaminati gli effetti sulla piazza finanziaria svizzera degli sviluppi nell’UE nel quadro del piano d’azione per investimenti finanziari sostenibili. Al più tardi entro la primavera del 2020 il gruppo di lavoro dovrà presentare un rapporto contenente i risultati di tale verifica e proposte per il mercato finanziario svizzero. Entro la fine dell’anno il Consiglio federale intende discutere ulteriormente se e come regolare il mercato finanziario. In linea di principio dovranno essere individuate le condizioni quadro che consentiranno alla piazza finanziaria svizzera di essere competitiva sul piano delle finanze sostenibili.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Infine, il gruppo di lavoro dovrà adoperarsi per concludere accordi settoriali con gli operatori del mercato finanziario. Tali accordi mirano a ottenere maggiore trasparenza e un maggiore impegno del settore. Lo scopo è quello di raggiungere una partecipazione rappresentativa agli esami di compatibilità ambientale e quindi obiettivi concreti. Si vuole in particolare rafforzare la competitività, in modo da fornire a clienti e investitori informazioni chiare e quindi possibilità decisionali. A tale scopo il dialogo con il settore sarà intensificato.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;[1] Cfr. comunicato stampa del 24 febbraio 2016 («Gli organismi finanziari internazionali discutono di sostenibilità: il Consiglio federale definisce il ruolo della Svizzera»).&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Anne Césard, corresponsabile Comunicazione SFI Tel. +41 58 462 62 91,anne.cesard@sif.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="191209">
        <title>Comunicato stampa del 24 febbraio 2016 («Gli organismi finanziari internazionali discutono di sostenibilità: il Consiglio federale definisce il ruolo della Svizzera»)</title>
        <uri>https://www.efd.admin.ch/efd/it/home/dokumentation/nsb-news_list.msg-id-60755.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Federal Council discusses sustainable finance and sets out next steps</title>
      <lead>During its meeting on 26 June 2019, the Federal Council held a discussion on a sustainable Swiss financial centre. It sees great opportunities for innovation and competitiveness in this area and has decided to set up a working group to carry out various investigations.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Since 2016, the primacy of market-based, long-term approaches and the subsidiarity of government action have already been regarded as principles. The aim is to specifically promote transparency and voluntary participation in the inclusion of environmental aspects and social issues in the financial sector.[1] The Federal Office for the Environment (FOEN) and the State Secretariat for International Finance (SIF) are again offering free climate compatibility tests in 2020, which are now open to banks and asset managers as well as pension funds and insurance companies. They will show to what extent progress has been made compared to the first tests in 2017.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;During its discussion on a sustainable financial market, the Federal Council gained an overview of current developments and initiatives as well as Switzerland's commitment at the international level. In particular, Switzerland has entered into international commitments within the framework of the Paris Convention on Climate Change and the 2030 Agenda for Sustainable Development.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;A new working group headed by SIF, in close cooperation with the FOEN and other interested authorities, will carry out various tasks. Among other things, assessment bases for clarifying Switzerland's participation in international initiatives – such as the Coalition of Finance Ministers for Climate Action launched by Chile and Finland – should be submitted as quickly as possible. In addition, the impact of developments in the EU in the area of the action plan for sustainable financial investments on the Swiss financial centre will be examined. By spring 2020 at the latest, a working group report should be available containing the results of this review and proposals for the Swiss financial market. The Federal Council intends to hold further discussions by the end of the year on the issue of whether and how the financial market should be regulated. The basic aim is to determine the framework conditions that will enable the Swiss financial centre to be competitive in the area of sustainable finance. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Finally, the working group should work towards the conclusion of industry agreements with financial market players. In particular, these should lead to an increase in transparency and a voluntary commitment on the part of the sectors to a representative participation in the aforementioned climate compatibility test with a view to achieving specific targets. The aim is to strengthen competitiveness, so that customers and investors can be offered clear information and thus decision-making options. Dialogue with the industry will be intensified to this end.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;[1] Cf. press release dated 24 February 2016 (International financial bodies discuss sustainability issues: Federal Council defines Switzerland's role)&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Anne Césard, Co-Head of SIF Communications Tel. +41 58 462 62 91, anne.cesard@sif.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="191210">
        <title>Press release dated 24 February 2016 (International financial bodies discuss sustainability issues: Federal Council defines Switzerland's role)</title>
        <uri>https://www.efd.admin.ch/efd/en/home/dokumentation/nsb-news_list.msg-id-60755.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <offers>
      <offer id="143" org-id="811">
        <name lang="de">Medienmitteilungen des BAFU</name>
        <name lang="fr">Communiqués de l'OFEV</name>
        <name lang="it">Comunicati dell'UFAM</name>
        <name lang="en">Media releases of the FOEN</name>
      </offer>
    </offers>
    <keywords>
      <keyword id="173" org-id="811">
        <name lang="de">Bundesamt für Umwelt: Startseite</name>
        <name lang="fr">Office fédéral de l'environnement: page d'accueil</name>
        <name lang="it">Ufficio federale dell'ambiente: pagina iniziale</name>
        <name lang="en">Federal Office for the Environment: Homepage</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="1802" org-id="811">
        <name lang="de">Wirtschaft und Konsum</name>
        <name lang="fr">Economie e consommation</name>
        <name lang="it">Economia e consumo</name>
        <name lang="en">Economy and consumption</name>
      </keyword>
    </keywords>
    <topics>
      <topic id="29">
        <name lang="de">Umwelt und Natur</name>
        <name lang="fr">Environnement et nature</name>
        <name lang="it">Ambiente e natura</name>
        <name lang="en">Environment and Nature</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
