<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="75752" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2019-07-08</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="yes" id="602" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>601</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Generalsekretariat EFD</name>
      <name lang="fr">Secrétariat général DFF</name>
      <name lang="it">Segreteria generale DFF</name>
      <name lang="en">Secretariat-General FDF</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.efd.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.efd.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.efd.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.efd.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="601">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Finanzdepartement</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des finances</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale delle finanze</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Finance</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.efd.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.dff.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.efd.admin.ch/efd/it/home.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.efd.admin.ch/efd/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Enge, dynamische Beziehungen zwischen der Schweiz und Kroatien</title>
      <lead>Die kroatische Präsidentin Kolinda Grabar-Kitarović hat der Schweiz am Montag, 8. Juli 2019, einen offiziellen Besuch abgestattet. Die guten Beziehungen beider Länder zeichnen sich unter anderem dadurch aus, dass rund 30'000 kroatische Staatsangehörige in der Schweiz leben und jährlich 300'000 Schweizer Touristinnen und Touristen Kroatien besuchen. Kroatien ist zudem der zweitwichtigste Handelspartner der Schweiz in Südosteuropa; das bilaterale Handelsvolumen erreichte vergangenes Jahr ein Allzeithoch. Der Besuch von Präsidentin Grabar-Kitarović erfolgte vor der erstmaligen Übernahme der EU-Ratspräsidentschaft durch Kroatien.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Bundespräsident Ueli Maurer und die kroatische Präsidentin würdigten die bilateralen Beziehungen, die in den vergangenen Jahren auch von der Zusammenarbeit im Rahmen des schweizerischen Erweiterungsbeitrags profitieren konnten. Von den zwölf Projekten ist eines abgeschlossen, die restlichen werden bis Ende 2024 fertig gestellt. Schwerpunktthemen sind Trink- und Abwasserinfrastruktur sowie die Berufsbildung und die Forschungszusammenarbeit.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Bundespräsident Maurer erläuterte den Stand der Beziehungen der Schweiz zur Europäischen Union und bekräftigte das Ziel des Bundesrates, eine Lösung der offenen Punkte zu finden und das institutionelle Rahmenabkommen in der Folge abzuschliessen. Zur Sprache kamen auch die Pläne der kroatischen EU-Ratspräsidentschaft im ersten Semester 2020. Die Schweiz begrüsst das Engagement Kroatiens zugunsten einer Integration weiterer Balkanstaaten in die EU, da die Beitrittsperspektive zur Stabilität auf dem Westbalkan beitragen kann. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Ein weiteres Thema war das am 1. Januar 2017 in Kraft getretene Protokoll III zur Ausdehnung des Freizügigkeitsabkommens (FZA) auf Kroatien. Bundespräsident Maurer hielt fest, dass die Anwendung des Protokolls III im Allgemeinen reibungslos verläuft. Dabei erläuterte er die vom Bundesrat im Dezember 2018 beschlossene Verlängerung der Übergangsbestimmungen. Diese ermöglichen in den kommenden Jahren eine schrittweise Öffnung des Zugangs zum Arbeitsmarkt zwischen den beiden Ländern. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Bei den internationalen Themen stand unter anderem ein Austausch über die Lage auf dem Westbalkan auf der Agenda. Präsidentin Grabar-Kitarović erläuterte zudem die von Kroatien mitinitiierte Drei-Meeres-Initiative, die zwölf mitteleuropäische Länder zwischen Adria, Schwarzem Meer und Ostsee verbindet und eine engere Zusammenarbeit bei Wirtschaft, Energie, Transport und Kommunikation zum Ziel hat. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Den Abschluss des offiziellen Besuchs von Präsidentin Grabar-Kitarović bildete gemäss Programm ein Austausch mit Nationalratspräsidentin Marina Carobbio Guscetti im Parlament.&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Peter Minder, Leiter Kommunikation EFD Tel. +41 79 437 73 61, peter.minder@gs-efd.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="191690">
        <title>Schweiz und Kroatien</title>
        <uri>https://www.dfae.admin.ch/countries/croatia/de/home.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>La Suisse et la Croatie, des relations étroites et dynamiques</title>
      <lead>Le lundi 8 juillet 2019, la présidente de la Croatie Kolinda Grabar-Kitarović était en visite officielle en Suisse. Les près de 30 000 citoyens croates qui vivent en Suisse et les quelque 300 000 touristes suisses qui visitent la Croatie chaque année témoignent des bonnes relations qu’entretiennent les deux pays. Par ailleurs, la Croatie est le deuxième partenaire commercial de la Suisse en Europe du Sud-Est ; le volume des échanges commerciaux bilatéraux a atteint un niveau record l’année dernière. La visite de la présidente Kolinda Grabar-Kitarović a eu lieu avant que la Croatie ne prenne pour la première fois la présidence du Conseil de l’UE. </lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Le président de la Confédération Ueli Maurer et la présidente croate se sont félicités des relations qu’entretiennent les deux pays, relations qui ont également profité ces dernières années de la collaboration dans le cadre de la contribution suisse à l’élargissement de l’UE. Sur les douze projets soutenus, un a déjà abouti et les autres s’achèveront en 2024. Les projets portent principalement sur les infrastructures d’approvisionnement en eau potable et de traitement des eaux usées ainsi que sur la formation professionnelle et sur la coopération dans le secteur de la recherche.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Le président de la Confédération a présenté l’état des relations de la Suisse avec l’Union européenne en réaffirmant la volonté du Conseil fédéral de résoudre les questions en suspens afin de conclure ensuite l’accord institutionnel. Le programme de la présidence croate du Conseil de l’UE au premier semestre 2020 a également été abordé. La Suisse salue l’engagement de la Croatie en faveur de l’intégration à l’UE d’autres États balkaniques car la perspective d’adhésion pourrait contribuer à la stabilité dans la région des Balkans occidentaux. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Il a aussi été question du Protocole III concernant l’extension de l’accord sur la libre circulation des personnes à la Croatie entré en vigueur le 1er janvier 2017. Le président de la Confédération a souligné que l’application du protocole ne rencontrait aucun problème particulier. Dans ce contexte, il a expliqué que le Conseil fédéral avait décidé en décembre 2018 de prolonger les dispositions transitoires qui permettront une ouverture progressive de l’accès au marché du travail entre les deux pays au cours des prochaines années.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Parmi les sujets internationaux à l’ordre du jour, il y avait notamment un échange sur la situation dans la région des Balkans occidentaux. La Présidente croate a par ailleurs expliqué l’Initiative des trois mers, co-initiée par la Croatie, qui a pour but de renforcer la coopération dans les domaines de l’économie, de l’énergie, des transports et de la communication entre les douze pays situés en Europe centrale le long d’un axe qui relie la mer Adriatique, la mer Noire et la mer Baltique.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Selon le programme, la visite officielle s’est achevée au Parlement par un entretien entre la présidente Kolinda Grabar-Kitarović et la présidente du Conseil national Marina Carobbio Guscetti.&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Peter Minder, responsable de la communication du DFF Tél. +41 79 437 73 61, peter.minder@gs-efd.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="191691">
        <title>La Suisse et la Croatie</title>
        <uri>https://www.dfae.admin.ch/countries/croatia/fr/home.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Svizzera e Croazia: relazioni strette e dinamiche</title>
      <lead>Lunedì 8 luglio 2019 la presidente croata Kolinda Grabar-Kitarović è giunta in Svizzera per una visita ufficiale. I circa 30 000 cittadini croati che vivono in Svizzera e i 300 000 turisti svizzeri che ogni anno visitano la Croazia sono indice dei buoni rapporti fra i due Paesi. La Croazia è inoltre il secondo più importante partner commerciale della Svizzera nell’Europa sudorientale. Lo scorso anno il volume degli scambi commerciali fra i due Paesi ha raggiunto un livello da record. La visita della presidente Grabar-Kitarović si è svolta prima che la Croazia assumesse per la prima volta il ruolo di presidenza del Consiglio dell’UE.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Il presidente della Confederazione Ueli Maurer e la presidente croata hanno lodato le relazioni fra i due Paesi, relazioni che negli scorsi anni hanno potuto beneficiare anche della collaborazione nell’ambito del contributo della Svizzera all’ampliamento dell’UE. Dei dodici progetti uno è stato attuato e i restanti saranno portati a termine entro fine 2024. I progetti riguardano principalmente le infrastrutture per l’acqua potabile e lo smaltimento delle acque di scarico, la formazione professionale e la collaborazione nel settore della ricerca.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Il presidente della Confederazione Maurer ha presentato lo stato delle relazioni della Svizzera con l’Unione europea e ha confermato l’intenzione del Consiglio federale di trovare una soluzione alle questioni in sospeso, in modo da poter in seguito concludere l’accordo istituzionale. Si è altresì discusso del programma della presidenza croata al Consiglio dell’UE nel primo semestre del 2020. La Svizzera si congratula con la Croazia per il suo impegno a favore dell’integrazione di altri Stati balcanici nell’UE, dal momento che questa prospettiva di adesione potrebbe contribuire alla stabilità nella regione dei Balcani occidentali. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;È stata discussa anche la questione del Protocollo III concernente l’estensione dell’accordo sulla libera circolazione alla Croazia entrato in vigore il 1° gennaio 2017. Il presidente della Confederazione ha ribadito che l’applicazione del Protocollo III non riscontra problemi particolari. In questo contesto, ha spiegato che il Consiglio federale ha deciso a dicembre 2018 di prolungare le disposizioni transitorie, che permetteranno nei prossimi anni una graduale apertura dell’accesso al mercato del lavoro fra i due Paesi.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Fra le varie trattande internazionali all’ordine del giorno vi era la questione della situazione nei Balcani occidentali. La presidente Grabar-Kitarović ha inoltre esposto l’Iniziativa dei Tre Mari co-iniziata dalla Croazia, che collega dodici Paesi dell’Europa centrale situati fra il Mare Adriatico, il Mar Nero e il Mar Baltico, allo scopo di rinforzare la collaborazione sul piano economico, energetico, dei trasporti e delle comunicazioni.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Come da programma, la visita ufficiale si è conclusa nel Parlamento con un incontro tra la presidente Kolinda Grabar-Kitarović e la presidente del Consiglio nazionale Marina Carobbio Guscetti.&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Peter Minder, Responsabile Comunicazioni DFF Tel. +41 79 437 73 61, peter.minder@gs-efd.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="191692">
        <title>La Svizzera e la Croazia</title>
        <uri>https://www.dfae.admin.ch/countries/croatia/it/home.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Close, dynamic relations between Switzerland and Croatia</title>
      <lead>Croatian President Kolinda Grabar-Kitarović paid an official visit to Switzerland on Monday, 8 July. Relations between the two countries are good and this is reflected in the fact that around 30,000 Croatian nationals live in Switzerland and that some 300,000 Swiss tourists visit Croatia every year. Croatia is also Switzerland’s second most important trade partner in southeast Europe; last year, the volume of bilateral trade reached an all-time high. The visit by President Grabar-Kitarović took place prior to Croatia assuming the EU Council presidency for the first time. </lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;President Ueli Maurer and President Grabar-Kitarović&lt;b&gt; &lt;/b&gt;commended relations between the two countries, which have benefitted from cooperation through Switzerland’s contribution to the enlarged EU. Of the twelve projects in place, one has been concluded while the remainder will be completed by the end of 2024. The projects are primarily in the areas of drinking water and wastewater infrastructure, vocational education and training, and research cooperation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mr Maurer set out the state of relations between Switzerland and the European Union and reiterated the Federal Council’s aim to find a solution to a number of open points and to then conclude the institutional agreement. The two presidents also discussed Croatia’s plans for the EU Council presidency in the first half of 2020. Switzerland welcomes Croatia’s efforts to encourage the integration of further western Balkan states into the EU, as the prospect of joining the EU can contribute to stability in the region. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;A further matter that was addressed was Protocol III of the Agreement on the Free Movement of Persons (AFMP) of 1 January 2017 extending the freedom of movement to Croatia. Mr Maurer noted that the application of Protocol III was generally unproblematic, but that the Federal Council had decided in December 2018 to extend the transitional provisions. The provisions will allow the gradual opening of access to the labour market between the two countries in the coming years.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;With regard to international issues, discussions focused on the situation in the Western Balkans. President Grabar-Kitarović outlined the ‘Three Seas Initiative’, of which Croatia is a co-initiator, which brings together twelve central European countries between the Adriatic, Baltic and Black seas with the aim of stimulating economic development through closer cooperation on infrastructure, energy and digital connectivity. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;President Grabar-Kitarović rounded off her official visit with a meeting with National Council president Marina Carobbio Guscetti in Parliament.&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Peter Minder, Head of FDF Communications Tel. +41 79 437 73 61, peter.minder@gs-efd.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="191693">
        <title>Switzerland and Croatia</title>
        <uri>https://www.dfae.admin.ch/countries/croatia/en/home.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="8">
        <name lang="de">Bildung und Forschung</name>
        <name lang="fr">Formation et recherche</name>
        <name lang="it">Formazione e ricerca</name>
        <name lang="en">Education and Research</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="27">
        <name lang="de">Reisen und Tourismus</name>
        <name lang="fr">Voyages et tourisme</name>
        <name lang="it">Viaggi e turismo</name>
        <name lang="en">Travel and Tourism</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="33">
        <name lang="de">Bundespräsident/-in</name>
        <name lang="fr">Président/e de la Confédération</name>
        <name lang="it">Presidente della Confederazione</name>
        <name lang="en">President of the Swiss Confederation</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="34">
        <name lang="de">Europa</name>
        <name lang="fr">Europe</name>
        <name lang="it">Europa</name>
        <name lang="en">Europe</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="47">
        <name lang="de">Wirtschaft</name>
        <name lang="fr">Économie</name>
        <name lang="it">Economia</name>
        <name lang="en">Economic Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
