<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="76047" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2019-08-15</pubdate>
    <blocking-period>2019-08-15</blocking-period>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="318" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>301</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Bundesamt für Statistik</name>
      <name lang="fr">Office fédéral de la statistique</name>
      <name lang="it">Ufficio federale di statistica</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Statistical Office</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.statistik.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.statistique.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.statistica.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.statistics.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@bfs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@bfs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@bfs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@bfs.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="301">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement des Innern</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'intérieur</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'interno</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Home Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Neuchâtel</city>
      <title>Film und Kino in der Schweiz: Taschenstatistik 2019 - Mehr Kinokomplexe und -filme, aber weniger Eintritte</title>
      <lead>Die langfristigen Trends in der Schweizer Kinolandschaft zeigen eine deutliche Zunahme bei der Anzahl Kinokomplexen: sie ersetzen mehr und mehr die Einsaalkinos. Beim Angebot an Filmen ist ebenfalls ein Zuwachs zu verzeichnen, auch wenn viele nur punktuell vorgeführt werden. Rückläufig sind hingegen die jährlichen Kinoeintritte, und auch 3D-Filme lockten jüngst kein zusätzliches Publikum an. Dies zeigt die neuste Taschenstatistik des Bundesamtes für Statistik (BFS) zum Thema Kinoinfrastruktur, Filmangebot und Kinoeintritte in der Schweiz.</lead>
      <text link="no">Diese Medienmitteilung und weitere Informationen zum Thema finden Sie auf der Website des BFS (siehe Link unten).</text>
      <contact>Erdem Karademir, BFS, Sektion Politik, Kultur, Medien, Tel.: +41 58 463 67 59, E-Mail: erdem.karademir@bfs.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="192319">
        <title>Kompletter Text und Mediendossier</title>
        <uri>https://www.bfs.admin.ch/news/de/2019-0388</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Neuchâtel</city>
      <title>Film et cinéma en Suisse: statistique de poche 2019 - Plus de complexes multisalles, plus de films, moins d’entrées</title>
      <lead>On observe dans le paysage cinématographique suisse une tendance nette, sur le long terme, à la hausse du nombre de complexes multisalles, qui remplacent de plus en plus les salles uniques. L’offre de films est également en hausse, même si beaucoup de films ne sont projetés qu’un petit nombre de fois. Le nombre annuel d’entrées, par contre, est en recul, et les films en 3D ne progressent plus. C’est ce que montre la nouvelle statistique de poche de l’Office fédéral de la statistique (OFS) sur l’infrastructure cinématographique, l’offre de films et la fréquentation des salles en Suisse.</lead>
      <text link="no">Vous trouverez ce communiqué de presse et d'autres informations sur ce thème sur le site web de l'OFS (cf. lien ci-dessous).</text>
      <contact>Erdem Karademir, OFS, Section Politique, culture et médias, tél.: +41 58 463 67 59, e-mail: erdem.karademir@bfs.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="192320">
        <title>Texte intégral et dossier de presse</title>
        <uri>https://www.bfs.admin.ch/news/fr/2019-0388</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Neuchâtel</city>
      <title>Film e cinema in Svizzera: prontuario statistico 2019 - Aumento di cinema multisala e film, ma calo degli ingressi</title>
      <lead>La tendenza a lungo termine del panorama cinematografico svizzero denota un netto aumento del numero di cinema multisala, che sostituiscono sempre di più quelli con una sala singola. Anche nell’offerta di film si è riscontrata una crescita, sebbene molti vengano proiettati solo puntualmente. D’altro canto, su base annuale sono diminuiti gli ingressi al cinema, come pure i film in 3D, che recentemente non hanno attratto ulteriori spettatori. È quanto emerge dall’ultima statistica tascabile dell’Ufficio federale di statistica (UST) che verte su temi quali l'infrastruttura cinematografica, l'offerta di film e gli ingressi al cinema in Svizzera.</lead>
      <text link="no">Il presente comunicato stampa e ulteriori informazioni sul tema sono reperibili sulla pagina Internet dell'UST (link sotto).</text>
      <contact>Erdem Karademir, UST, Sezione Politica, cultura e media, tel.: +41 58 463 67 59, e-mail: erdem.karademir@bfs.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="192321">
        <title>Testo integrale e dossier per i media</title>
        <uri>https://www.bfs.admin.ch/news/it/2019-0388</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Neuchâtel</city>
      <title>Film and Cinema in Switzerland: Pocket Statistics 2019 - More cinema complexes and films but fewer admissions</title>
      <lead>Long-term trends in Swiss cinema show a clear increase in the number of cinema complexes: they are increasingly replacing single screen cinemas. An increase in film offerings has also been recorded even if many of these are only selectively shown. In contrast, there has been a decrease in annual cinema admissions and 3D films have also recently failed to draw in additional audiences. These are some of the findings of the latest Pocket Statistics on cinema infrastructure, film offerings and cinema admissions in Switzerland from the Federal Statistical Office (FSO).</lead>
      <text link="no">This press release and further information on this topic can be found on the FSO website (see link below).</text>
      <contact>Erdem Karademir, FSO, Politics, Culture and Media Section, tel.: +41 58 463 67 59, e-mail: erdem.karademir@bfs.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="192322">
        <title>Please note that the English version only includes the release's lead</title>
        <uri>https://www.bfs.admin.ch/news/en/2019-0388</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <keywords>
      <keyword id="317.17" org-id="318">
        <name lang="de">Kultur, Informationsgesellschaft, Sport</name>
        <name lang="fr">Culture, société de l'information, sport</name>
        <name lang="it">Cultura, media</name>
        <name lang="en">Culture, information society, sports</name>
      </keyword>
    </keywords>
    <topics>
      <topic id="18">
        <name lang="de">Kultur</name>
        <name lang="fr">Culture</name>
        <name lang="it">Cultura</name>
        <name lang="en">Culture</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="43">
        <name lang="de">Statistik</name>
        <name lang="fr">Statistiques</name>
        <name lang="it">Statistica</name>
        <name lang="en">Statistics</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
