<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="76300" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2019-09-04</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="1070" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>1070</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Der Bundesrat</name>
      <name lang="fr">Conseil fédéral</name>
      <name lang="it">Il Consiglio federale</name>
      <name lang="en">The Federal Council</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.admin.ch/gov/de/start.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.admin.ch/gov/fr/accueil.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.admin.ch/gov/it/pagina-iniziale.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.admin.ch/gov/en/start.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="yes" id="1076" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>701</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Rat der Eidgenössischen Technischen Hochschulen</name>
      <name lang="fr">Conseil des écoles polytechniques fédérales</name>
      <name lang="it">Consiglio dei politecnici federali</name>
      <name lang="en">Board of the Swiss Federal Institutes of Technology</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.ethrat.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.ethrat.ch/fr</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.ethrat.ch/it</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.ethrat.ch/en</www>
      <email lang="de">gian.casutt@ethrat.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">gian.casutt@ethrat.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">gian.casutt@ethrat.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">gian.casutt@ethrat.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="1070">
      <name lang="de">Der Bundesrat</name>
      <name lang="fr">Conseil fédéral</name>
      <name lang="it">Il Consiglio federale</name>
      <name lang="en">The Federal Council</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.admin.ch/gov/de/start.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.admin.ch/gov/fr/accueil.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.admin.ch/gov/it/pagina-iniziale.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.admin.ch/gov/en/start.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <department id="701">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Wirtschaft, Bildung und Forschung</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'économie, de la formation et de la recherche</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'economia, della formazione e della ricerca</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Economic Affairs, Education and Research</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Michael Hengartner wird neuer Präsident des ETH-Rates</title>
      <lead>Der Bundesrat hat am 4. September 2019 auf Antrag von WBF-Vorsteher Guy Parmelin Michael Hengartner zum neuen Präsidenten des ETH-Rates gewählt. Der 53-Jährige tritt damit die Nachfolge von Fritz Schiesser an, der Ende April 2019 von seinem Amt zurückgetreten war. Hengartner ist seit 2014 Rektor der Universität Zürich. Er wird sein neues Amt am 1. Februar 2020 beginnen.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Michael Hengartner wurde 2014 zum Rektor der Universität Zürich berufen. Seit 2016 amtet er zudem als Präsident von swissuniversities. Michael Hengartner wuchs in Québec City auf. Er ist Doppelbürger Schweiz/Kanada und studierte in Québec City an der Université Laval Biochemie. Er promovierte 1994 am Massachusetts Institute of Technology im Labor von Nobelpreisträger H. Robert Horvitz. Danach leitete er bis 2001 eine Forschungsgruppe am Cold Spring Harbor Laboratory in den USA. Im Jahr 2001 wurde er auf die neu eingerichtete Ernst-Hadorn-Stiftungsprofessur am Institut für Molekulare Biologie der Universität Zürich berufen. Von 2009 bis 2014 war der 53-Jährige Dekan der Mathematisch-naturwissenschaftlichen Fakultät der Universität Zürich.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Fritz Schiesser, der Vorgänger von Hengartner, war Ende April 2019 in den Ruhestand getreten. Seither amtet Vizepräsidentin Beth Krasna und noch bis Ende Januar 2020 ad interim als Präsidentin des ETH-Rates. Bundesrat Guy Parmelin hatte für die Suche des Nachfolgers, bzw. der Nachfolgerin von Fritz Schiesser eine Findungskommission eingesetzt. Die Stelle war öffentlich ausgeschrieben worden. Es hatten sich insgesamt 29 Personen um das Amt beworben. &lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Kommunikation GS WBF, 058 462 20 07</contact>
      <attachment id="192975">
        <title>Portrait Hengartner Michael</title>
        <format>jpg</format>
        <size-kb>1474</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/58293.jpg</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Michael Hengartner, nouveau président du Conseil des EPF</title>
      <lead>Le 4 septembre 2019, le Conseil fédéral a nommé Michael Hengartner à la tête du Conseil des EPF, sur proposition de Guy Parmelin, chef du Département fédéral de l’économie, de la formation et de la recherche (DEFR). Âgé de 53 ans et recteur de l’Université de Zurich depuis 2014, Michael Hengartner succède à Fritz Schiesser, qui s’est retiré fin avril dernier. Il prendra ses nouvelles fonctions le 1er février 2020.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Michael Hengartner a été nommé recteur de l’Université de Zurich en 2014. Il est également président de swissuniversities depuis 2016. Michael Hengartner, qui a grandi à Québec, possède la double nationalité suisse et canadienne et a étudié la biochimie à l’Université Laval de Québec. Il a obtenu son doctorat en 1994 au Massachusetts Institute of Technology, dans le laboratoire du lauréat du prix Nobel H. Robert Horvitz. Il a ensuite dirigé un groupe de recherche au Cold Spring Harbor Laboratory, aux États-Unis, jusqu’en 2001, année où il a été nommé au poste de professeur titulaire de la chaire Ernst Hadorn, nouvellement créée à l’Institut de biologie moléculaire de l’Université de Zurich. De 2009 à 2014, il a été doyen de la Faculté de mathématiques et de sciences naturelles de l’Université de Zurich.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Fritz Schiesser, le prédécesseur de Michael Hengartner, a pris sa retraite fin avril dernier. L’intérim est assuré depuis lors et jusqu’à fin janvier 2020 par Beth Krasna, vice-présidente du Conseil des EPF. Le poste mis au concours public avait donné lieu à 29 candidatures, et le conseiller fédéral Guy Parmelin avait institué une commission de sélection pour trouver la personne apte à succéder à Fritz Schiesser. &lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Communication SG-DEFR, 058 462 20 07</contact>
      <attachment id="192975">
        <title>Portrait Hengartner Michael</title>
        <format>jpg</format>
        <size-kb>1474</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/58293.jpg</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Michael Hengartner, nuovo presidente del Consiglio dei PF</title>
      <lead>Su proposta di Guy Parmelin, capo del Dipartimento federale dell’economia, della formazione e della ricerca (DEFR), il 4 settembre 2019 il Consiglio federale ha nominato Michael Hengartner nuovo presidente del Consiglio dei PF. Il 53enne subentra a Fritz Schiesser, andato in pensione a fine aprile 2019. L’entrata in funzione di Hengartner, dal 2014 rettore dell’Università di Zurigo, è prevista il 1° febbraio 2020.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Nominato rettore dell’Università di Zurigo nel 2014, dal 2016 Michael Hengartner è anche presidente di swissuniversities. Lo svizzero-canadese è cresciuto a Québec City, dove ha studiato biochimica all’Università di Laval. Dopo il dottorato al &lt;i&gt;Massachusetts Institute of Technology&lt;/i&gt; nel 1994, nel laboratorio del premio Nobel Robert Horvitz, ha diretto fino al 2001 un gruppo di ricerca presso il &lt;i&gt;Cold Spring Harbor Laboratory&lt;/i&gt; negli Stati Uniti. Nel 2001 ha assunto la cattedra, allora neoistituita dalla Fondazione Ernst Hadorn, presso l’Istituto di biologia molecolare dell’Università di Zurigo. Dal 2009 al 2014 è stato decano della Facoltà di matematica e scienze naturali dell’Università di Zurigo. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Per trovare il successore di Fritz Schiesser, presidente del Consiglio dei PF fino alla fine di aprile 2019 e ora in pensione, il consigliere federale Guy Parmelin aveva nominato una commissione ad hoc. Per il posto, oggetto di un concorso pubblico, si sono candidate 29 persone. Fino all’entrata in funzione di Michael Hengartner, la carica sarà ricoperta dalla vicepresidente Beth Krasna fino alla fine del gennaio 2020. &lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Comunicazione SG DEFR, 058 462 20 07</contact>
      <attachment id="192975">
        <title>Portrait Hengartner Michael</title>
        <format>jpg</format>
        <size-kb>1474</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/58293.jpg</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Michael Hengartner appointed new president of the ETH Board</title>
      <lead>On 4 September, the Federal Council elected Michael Hengartner as the new president of the ETH Board, at the request of the head of the EAER Guy Parmelin. Michael Hengartner, 53, succeeds Fritz Schiesser, who stepped down from the post at the end of April. Mr Hengartner has been rector of the University of Zurich since 2014. He will take up his new post on 1 February next year.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Michael Hengartner was appointed rector of the University of Zurich in 2014. Since 2016, he has also served as president of swissuniversities. Mr Hengartner grew up in Québec City. He is a dual citizen of Switzerland and Canada. He studied biochemistry at the Université Laval in Québec City. After earning his PhD in 1994 at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology with Nobel Laureate H. Robert Horvitz, he was head of a research group at the Cold Spring Harbor Laboratory in the United States until 2001. In 2001, he was appointed professor of molecular biology at the newly created Ernst Hadorn Chair at the Institute of Molecular Life Sciences at the University of Zurich. From 2009 to 2014, he acted as dean of the Faculty of Science.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Fritz Schiesser, Mr Hengartner’s predecessor, retired at the end of April. Beth Krasna, vice president of the ETH Board, has since served ad interim as president of the ETH Board, and will continue to do so until the end of January next year. Federal Councillor Guy Parmelin appointed a selection committee to find a successor to Mr Schiesser. The position was widely advertised. A total of 29 candidates had applied for the post. &lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>GS-EAER Communications, 058 462 20 07</contact>
      <attachment id="192975">
        <title>Portrait Hengartner Michael</title>
        <format>jpg</format>
        <size-kb>1474</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/58293.jpg</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="8">
        <name lang="de">Bildung und Forschung</name>
        <name lang="fr">Formation et recherche</name>
        <name lang="it">Formazione e ricerca</name>
        <name lang="en">Education and Research</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
