<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="76836" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2019-10-28</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="201" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>201</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="301" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>301</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement des Innern</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'intérieur</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'interno</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Home Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="201">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <department id="301">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement des Innern</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'intérieur</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'interno</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Home Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>25 Jahre Weltfrauenkonferenz von Peking - Starkes Engagement der Schweiz für Lohngleichheit und gegen häusliche Gewalt</title>
      <lead>Am 29. und 30. Oktober 2019 wird Genf zur internationalen Plattform für den Austausch zu Geschlechtergleichstellung und Frauenrechten. Im Rahmen der UN-Wirtschaftskommission für Europa (UNECE) findet an diesen zwei Tagen die europäische Vorbereitungskonferenz für die globale Überprüfung der Pekinger Deklaration und Aktionsplattform statt. Die Schweiz spielt dabei eine zentrale Rolle. Sie nimmt mit einer Delegation aktiv an den Diskussionen teil und stellt mit Staatssekretärin Pascale Baeriswyl eine der beiden Co-Vorsitzenden der Konferenz.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Im März 2020 wird am Sitz der Vereinten Nationen in New York 25 Jahre nach der Verabschiedung der visionären Agenda für die Stärkung von Frauen und Mädchen eine globale Bilanz gezogen über Fortschritte und bestehende Herausforderungen in diesem Bereich. Im Hinblick auf dieses wichtige globale Ereignis finden diesen Herbst in allen fünf Weltregionen Vorbereitungskonferenzen statt.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Die Mitgliedstaaten der UNECE werden ihre konkreten Fortschritte, Erfahrungen und bewährten Praktiken bei der Umsetzung der Pekinger Aktionsplattform vorstellen. Zudem wird darüber diskutiert, wie die systemischen Hindernisse beseitigt werden können, welche Frauen und Mädchen von einer gleichberechtigten Teilhabe in allen Bereichen des Lebens abhalten, im öffentlichen wie im privaten Umfeld. Dabei stehen aus Sicht der Situation von Frauen und Mädchen Themen wie Bildung, Gewalt, bewaffnete Konflikte, wirtschaftliche Autonomie, Beteiligung an Entscheidungsprozessen oder Umweltschutz im Zentrum.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Die Schweiz wird ihr Engagement in den Bereichen Lohngleichheit und Bekämpfung von häuslicher Gewalt hervorheben und ein Projekt der französischsprachigen Kantone zur Gleichstellung in der Schule vorstellen. Ausserdem wird sie einzelne Programmsegmente moderieren und Nebenveranstaltungen organisieren. Zudem wird Staatssekretärin Pascale Baeriswyl die Gelegenheit nutzen, um mehrere bilaterale Treffen mit hochrangigen Staatsvertreterinnen und UNO-Entscheidungsträgerinnen abzuhalten. Die Schweizer Delegation wird geleitet von Frau Sylvie Durrer, Direktorin des Eidgenössischen Büros für die Gleichstellung von Frau und Mann (EBG) sowie Didier Chambovey, ausserordentlicher und bevollmächtigter Botschafter bei der ständigen Vertretung der Schweiz bei der WTO und EFTA in Genf.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Kommunikation EDA Bundeshaus West CH-3003 Bern Tel. Kommunikationsservice: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Medienstelle: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <link id="194273">
        <title>Staatenbericht Schweiz (fr)</title>
        <uri>https://www.unece.org/fileadmin/DAM/Gender/Beijing_20/Switzerland.pdf</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="194274">
        <title>UNECE Beijing+25 (en)</title>
        <uri>https://www.unece.org/beijing25.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="194275">
        <title>Eidgenössisches Büro für die Gleichstellung von Frau und Mann EBG</title>
        <uri>https://www.ebg.admin.ch/ebg/de/home.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="194276">
        <title>EDA-Strategie zu Geschlechtergleichstellung und Frauenrechten</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/dam/deza/de/documents/themen/gender/strategie-gender-2017_DE.pdf</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="194277">
        <title>Women’s Human Rights App (en)</title>
        <uri>http://www.womenshumanrights.ch/overview.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="194278">
        <title>Gleichstellung von Frau und Mann DEZA</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/deza/de/home/themen/gleichstellung_vonfrauundmann.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="194279">
        <title>Twitter Eidgenössisches Büro die Gleichstellung von Frau und Mann</title>
        <uri>https://twitter.com/ebg_bfeg_ufu</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="194280">
        <title>Twitter Schweiz UNO</title>
        <uri>https://twitter.com/swiss_un</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>25e anniversaire de la Conférence mondiale sur les femmes à Beijing: la Suisse s’engage avec résolution pour l’égalité salariale et contre la violence domestique</title>
      <lead>Les 29 et 30 octobre prochains, Genève jouera le rôle de plateforme internationale d’échange sur l’égalité des genres et les droits des femmes. Ces deux journées organisées dans le cadre de la Commission économique des Nations Unies pour l’Europe (CEE-ONU) seront dédiées à la préparation de l’examen global de la Déclaration et du Programme d’action de Beijing. La Suisse jouera un rôle clé lors de cet événement : une délégation suisse participera activement aux débats tandis que la coprésidence de la conférence sera assurée par la secrétaire d’État Pascale Baeriswyl.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Le 25e anniversaire de l’adoption de ce programme visionnaire, qui vise à renforcer le statut des femmes et des filles, sera l’occasion de se réunir, en mars 2020 au siège des Nations Unies à New York, pour tirer un bilan global des progrès réalisés et des défis existants et à venir. Dans la perspective de cet événement d’une importance mondiale, les cinq régions du monde organisent des réunions préparatoires cet automne.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Les États membres de la CEE-ONU seront appelés à présenter leurs progrès, leurs expériences et leurs bonnes pratiques dans le cadre de la mise en œuvre du Programme d’action de Beijing. On se demandera également comment dépasser les obstacles systémiques qui empêchent les femmes et les filles de participer dans tous les domaines de la vie sur un pied d’égalité, que ce soit dans la sphère publique ou privée. Les débats porteront avant tout sur la perspective des femmes et des filles dans des thématiques telles que l’éducation, la violence, les conflits armés, l’autonomie économique, la participation aux processus décisionnels ou la protection de l’environnement.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;La Suisse souhaite mettre en avant son engagement en faveur de l’égalité des salaires et de la lutte contre la violence domestique, et présentera un projet des cantons francophones portant sur l’égalité à l’école. En outre, elle animera différents modules du programme officiel et organisera des manifestations parallèles. La secrétaire d’État Pascale Baeriswyl profitera de l’occasion pour mener plusieurs entretiens bilatéraux avec des représentantes de haut rang de différents États ainsi que des décideuses de l’ONU. La délégation suisse sera conduite par Mme Sylvie Durrer, directrice du Bureau fédéral de l’égalité entre femmes et hommes BFEG et par Didier Chambovey, ambassadeur extraordinaire et plénipotentiaire à la Mission permanente de la Suisse près l’OMC et l’AELE à Genève.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Communication DFAE Palais fédéral ouest CH-3003 Berne Tél. Service de communication: +41 58 462 31 53 Tél. Service de presse: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <link id="194281">
        <title>Rapport suisse</title>
        <uri>https://www.unece.org/fileadmin/DAM/Gender/Beijing_20/Switzerland.pdf</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="194282">
        <title>CEE-ONU Beijing+25 (en)</title>
        <uri>https://www.unece.org/beijing25.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="194283">
        <title>Bureau fédéral de l’égalité entre femmes et hommes BFEG</title>
        <uri>https://www.ebg.admin.ch/ebg/fr/home.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="194284">
        <title>Stratégie Égalité des genres et droits des femmes du DFAE</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/dam/deza/fr/documents/themen/gender/strategie-gender-2017_FR.pdf</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="194285">
        <title>Application pour le renforcement des droits des femmes (Women’s Human Rights App) (en)</title>
        <uri>http://www.womenshumanrights.ch/overview.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="194286">
        <title>DDC: égalité entre femmes et hommes</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/deza/fr/home/themes-ddc/egalite-femmes-hommes.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="194287">
        <title>Compte Twitter du Bureau fédéral de l’égalité entre femmes et hommes</title>
        <uri>https://twitter.com/ebg_bfeg_ufu</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="194288">
        <title>Compte Twitter ONU Suisse</title>
        <uri>https://twitter.com/swiss_un</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Per il 25esimo anniversario della Conferenza mondiale sulle donne di Pechino la Svizzera si impegna per la parità salariale e contro la violenza domestica</title>
      <lead>Il 29 e il 30 ottobre 2019 Ginevra sarà teatro di un incontro internazionale sulla parità di genere e i diritti delle donne. Nell’ambito della Commissione economica per l’Europa delle Nazioni Unite (UNECE), in questi due giorni si svolgerà la conferenza europea di preparazione alla verifica globale della dichiarazione e della piattaforma d’azione di Pechino. In questo contesto, la Svizzera assume un ruolo centrale: una sua delegazione partecipa attivamente ai dibattiti e la segretaria di Stato Pascale Baeriswyl è una delle due copresidenti della conferenza.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Nel marzo del 2020, 25 anni dopo l’adozione dell’agenda visionaria per il rafforzamento del ruolo delle donne e delle bambine, alla sede delle Nazioni Unite di New York si trarrà un bilancio globale dei progressi compiuti e delle sfide ancora aperte. Per preparare questo importante evento internazionale, nell’autunno del 2019 si svolgeranno conferenze nei cinque continenti.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I Paesi membri dell’UNECE presenteranno i progressi compiuti nella concretizzazione della piattaforma d’azione di Pechino, le esperienze acquisite e le buone prassi. Si discuterà inoltre di come superare gli ostacoli sistemici che precludono alle donne e alle bambine una partecipazione equa a tutti gli aspetti della vita, in ambito pubblico e privato. Concentrandosi sulla situazione di donne e bambine, i dibattiti verteranno su temi quali l’istruzione, la violenza, i conflitti armati, l’indipendenza economica, la partecipazione ai processi decisionali e la protezione dell’ambiente.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;La Svizzera metterà in evidenza il suo impegno per la parità salariale e nella lotta alla violenza domestica e presenterà un progetto dei Cantoni francofoni sulla parità nella scuola. Modererà inoltre singole parti del programma e organizzerà eventi collaterali. La segretaria di Stato Pascale Baeriswyl coglierà anche l’occasione per partecipare a vari incontri bilaterali con rappresentanti statali e responsabilidell’ONU di alto livello. La delegazione svizzera è guidata da Sylvie Durrer, direttrice dell’Ufficio federale per l’uguaglianza fra donna e uomo (UFU), e da Didier Chambovey, ambasciatore straordinario e plenipotenziario alla Missione permanente della Svizzera presso l’Organizzazione mondiale del commercio (OMC) e l’Associazione europea di libero scambio (AELS).&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Comunicazione DFAE Palazzo federale ovest CH-3003 Berna Tel. Servizio di comunicazione: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Servizio stampa: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <link id="194289">
        <title>Rapporto nazionale della Svizzera (fr)</title>
        <uri>https://www.unece.org/fileadmin/DAM/Gender/Beijing_20/Switzerland.pdf</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="194290">
        <title>UNECE Beijing+25 (en)</title>
        <uri>https://www.unece.org/beijing25.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="194291">
        <title>Ufficio federale per l’uguaglianza fra donna e uomo (UFU)</title>
        <uri>https://www.ebg.admin.ch/ebg/it/home.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="194292">
        <title>Strategia del DFAE Uguaglianza di genere e diritti delle donne</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/dam/deza/it/documents/themen/gender/strategie-gender-2017_IT.pdf</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="194293">
        <title>Women’s Human Rights App (en)</title>
        <uri>http://www.womenshumanrights.ch/overview.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="194294">
        <title>Uguaglianza tra donne e uomini (DSC)</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/deza/it/home/temi-dsc/uguaglianza-donna-uomo.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="194295">
        <title>Account Twitter dell’Ufficio federale per l’uguaglianza fra donna e uomo</title>
        <uri>https://twitter.com/ebg_bfeg_ufu</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="194296">
        <title>Account Twitter della Svizzera presso l’ONU</title>
        <uri>https://twitter.com/swiss_un</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Celebrating 25 years of the World Conference on Women in Beijing: Switzerland is strongly committed to equal pay and combating domestic violence</title>
      <lead>On 29 and 30 October 2019, Geneva will be transformed into a platform for an international exchange on gender equality and women's rights as the host of the European preparatory conference for the global review of the Beijing Declaration and Platform for Action. The two-day event is taking place within the framework of the United Nations Economic Commission for Europe (UNECE). Switzerland will play a key role, with both a Swiss delegation participating in the debates and State Secretary Pascale Baeriswyl co-chairing the conference.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;25 years after the adoption of a visionary agenda to empower women and girls, the international community is preparing to take stock of the progress that has been made since then in the area and the challenges that remain. The conference will take place in March 2020 at the United Nations headquarters in New York. In the run-up to this important global event, five regional preparatory conferences are organised this autumn.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In Europe, UNECE member states will present the concrete measures they have taken to implement the Beijing Platform for Action and share their experiences and best practices. Conference participants will also address how systemic obstacles which prevent women and girls from equal participation in all areas of public and private life can be removed. This includes such key topics as education and training, violence, armed conflict, economic autonomy, participation in decision-making processes and environmental protection from the perspective of women and girls. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;At the conference, Switzerland will highlight its efforts in the fields of equal pay and combating domestic violence, including a presentation of a project in French-speaking cantons to promote gender equality in schools. Switzerland will also act as moderator on certain programme segments and organise a number of side events. In addition, State Secretary Pascale Baeriswyl, who will be co-chairing the conference, will have a number of bilateral meetings with high-ranking officials and UN decision-makers. The Swiss delegation will be led by Sylvie Durrer, who is the head of the Federal Office for Gender Equality, and Didier Chambovey, ambassador extraordinary and plenipotentiary to the Permanent Mission of Switzerland to the WTO and EFTA in Geneva.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>FDFA Communication Federal Palace West Wing CH-3003 Bern, Switzerland Tel. Communication service: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Press service: +41 58 460 55 55 E-mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @SwissMFA</contact>
      <link id="194297">
        <title>Switzerland's national report (fr)</title>
        <uri>https://www.unece.org/fileadmin/DAM/Gender/Beijing_20/Switzerland.pdf</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="194298">
        <title>UNECE Beijing+25</title>
        <uri>https://www.unece.org/beijing25.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="194299">
        <title>Federal Office for Gender Equality (FOGE)</title>
        <uri>https://www.ebg.admin.ch/ebg/en/home.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="194300">
        <title>FDFA strategy on gender equality and women's rights</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/dam/deza/en/documents/themen/gender/strategie-gender-2017_EN.pdf</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="194301">
        <title>Women’s Human Rights app</title>
        <uri>http://www.womenshumanrights.ch/overview.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="194302">
        <title>SDC – Gender equality</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/deza/en/home/themes-sdc/gender-equality.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="194303">
        <title>Twitter account of the Federal Office for Gender Equality</title>
        <uri>https://twitter.com/ebg_bfeg_ufu</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="194304">
        <title>Twitter account of Switzerland at the United Nations</title>
        <uri>https://twitter.com/swiss_un</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
