<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="76986" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2019-11-07</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="1063" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>701</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Paul Scherrer Institut</name>
      <name lang="fr">Institut Paul Scherrer</name>
      <name lang="it">Istituto Paul Scherrer</name>
      <name lang="en">Paul Scherrer Institut</name>
      <www lang="de"/>
      <www lang="fr"/>
      <www lang="it"/>
      <www lang="en"/>
      <email lang="de">info@psi.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@psi.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@psi.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@psi.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="701">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Wirtschaft, Bildung und Forschung</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'économie, de la formation et de la recherche</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'economia, della formazione e della ricerca</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Economic Affairs, Education and Research</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Villigen</city>
      <title>Faserverstärkte Verbundstoffe schnell und präzise durchleuchten</title>
      <lead>Forschende des Paul Scherrer Instituts PSI haben eine Methode der Röntgenkleinwinkelstreuung so verbessert, dass sie nun bei der Entwicklung oder der Qualitätskontrolle neuartiger faserverstärkter Verbundstoffe eingesetzt werden kann. Dadurch können künftig nicht nur Röntgenstrahlen aus besonders leistungsfähigen Quellen wie der Synchrotron Lichtquelle Schweiz SLS für die Untersuchung entsprechender Materialien genutzt werden, sondern auch jene aus herkömmlichen Röntgenröhren. Ihre Ergebnisse veröffentlichen die Forschenden nun im Fachmagazin Nature Communications.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Neuartige faserverstärkte Verbundstoffe gewinnen als stabile und gleichzeitig leichte Materialien zunehmend an Bedeutung. Ein Beispiel für diese Art von Verbundstoffen sind kohlenstofffaserverstärkte Kunststoffe (CFK), die beispielsweise im Flugzeugbau oder bei der Konstruktion von Formel-1-Rennwagen und Sportfahrrädern eingesetzt werden. Die Eigenschaften dieser Materialien hängen massgeblich davon ab, wie die Fasern ausgerichtet sind und wie sie sich im umgebenden Material zueinander anordnen. Sie beeinflussen beispielsweise das mechanische, optische oder elektromagnetische Verhalten von Verbundstoffen. &lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Will man die Zusammensetzung solcher Verbundstoffe beobachten, muss man zwangsläufig in sie hineinschauen. Dafür kann man die sogenannte Röntgenkleinwinkelstreuung verwenden, Englisch: small angle X-ray scattering (SAXS), und damit ausnutzen, dass Röntgenstrahlen beim Durchdringen von Materie gestreut werden. Aus dem so entstehenden Streuungsmuster lassen sich Informationen über das Innere einer Probe ermitteln und eventuell über die Orientierung der Fasern. Die herkömmlichen Verfahren der SAXS haben allerdings den Nachteil, dass sie sehr langsam sind: Es kann nämlich mehrerer Stunden dauern, um wenige Zentimeter einer Probe fortlaufend in der notwendigen Auflösung zu durchleuchten.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Das Verknoten eines Kohlefaserbandes beobachten&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Forschenden des Paul Scherrer Instituts PSI und der ETH Zürich ist es nun gemeinsam mit Kollegen der EPF Lausanne und dem dänischen Spin-off-Unternehmen Xnovo Technology gelungen, die Technik für die praxisnahe Anwendung weiterzuentwickeln. «Dadurch ist es möglich, mehrere lokale Streuungsmuster zu erkennen, die die räumliche Innenstruktur einer Probe mit nur einem Röntgenbild widerspiegeln, sodass wir eine grosse Anzahl von aufeinanderfolgenden Bildern aufnehmen können", sagt Matias Kagias, Erfinder der Methode und Postdoc in der PSI-Röntgentomografiegruppe unter der Leitung von Marco Stampanoni. Als prinzipiellen Beweis für ihr Funktionieren nutzten die Forscher das neue Verfahren, um die Ausrichtung der Fasern in einem Kohlefaserband während des Knotenprozesses darzustellen. Sie nahmen zeitaufgelöste Röntgenprojektionen mit 25 Bildern pro Sekunde über einen Zeitraum von 11 Sekunden auf. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Anwendung in der Medizin oder für die innere Sicherheit denkbar&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Die neue Methode funktioniert darüber hinaus nicht nur mit Röntgenstrahlen aus Beschleunigeranlagen wie der Synchrotron Lichtquelle Schweiz SLS, sondern auch mit Strahlen aus herkömmlichen Röntgenröhren. «Es wird daher erwartet, dass dieser neuartige Ansatz konkrete Anwendung in Medizinprodukten, bei der zerstörungsfreien Prüfung sowie im Bereich der inneren Sicherheit finden wird", so Marco Stampanoni, Leiter der Forschungsgruppe Röntgentomografie. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Ihre Ergebnisse veröffentlichen die Forschenden nun im Fachmagazin &lt;i&gt;Nature Communications&lt;/i&gt;.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Text: Paul Scherrer Institut/Sebastian Jutzi&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt; &lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt; &lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Über das PSI&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; Das Paul Scherrer Institut PSI entwickelt, baut und betreibt grosse und komplexe Forschungsanlagen und stellt sie der nationalen und internationalen Forschungsgemeinde zur Verfügung. Eigene Forschungsschwerpunkte sind Materie und Material, Energie und Umwelt sowie Mensch und Gesundheit. Die Ausbildung von jungen Menschen ist ein zentrales Anliegen des PSI. Deshalb sind etwa ein Viertel unserer Mitarbeitenden Postdoktorierende, Doktorierende oder Lernende. Insgesamt beschäftigt das PSI 2100 Mitarbeitende, das damit das grösste Forschungsinstitut der Schweiz ist. Das Jahresbudget beträgt rund CHF 407 Mio. Das PSI ist Teil des ETH-Bereichs, dem auch die ETH Zürich und die ETH Lausanne angehören sowie die Forschungsinstitute Eawag, Empa und WSL.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Originalveröffentlichung&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Diffractive small angle X-ray scattering imaging for anisotropic structures&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;Matias Kagias, Zhentian Wang, Mie Elholm Birkbak, Erik Lauridsen, MatteoAbis, Goran Lovric, Konstantins Je_movs, Marco Stampanoni&lt;i&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Nature Communications,&lt;/i&gt; 12.11.2019&lt;br /&gt;DOI: 10.1038/s41467-019-12635-2 &lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Dr. Mirjam van Daalen Verantwortliche für Kommunikation Paul Scherrer Institut 5232 Villigen PSI Telefon: +41 56 310 56 74 mirjam.vandaalen@psi.ch</contact>
      <link id="194803">
        <title>Bilder und weitere Informationen</title>
        <uri>https://www.psi.ch/de/node/31203</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Villigen</city>
      <title>Radiographier rapidement et précisément des matériaux composites renforcés de fibres</title>
      <lead>Des chercheurs de l'Institut Paul Scherrer PSI ont mis au point une méthode de diffusion des rayons X aux petits angles qui peut être utilisée pour le développement ou le contrôle qualité de matériaux composites novateurs renforcés de fibres. Grâce à elle, les analyses de ces matériaux pourraient se faire à l'avenir non seulement par recours aux rayons X issus de sources puissantes comme la Source de Lumière Suisse SLS, mais aussi avec le rayonnement issu de tubes à rayons X conventionnels. Les chercheurs viennent de publier leurs résultats dans la revue spécialisée Nature Communications.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A la fois légers et stables, les matériaux composites novateurs renforcés de fibres de carbone revêtent une importance croissante, à l'instar des plastiques renforcés de fibres de carbone (CFK) qui sont utilisés, par exemple, dans l'aéronautique ainsi que dans la construction de voitures de Formule 1 et de vélos de course. Les propriétés de ces matériaux dépendent largement de la manière dont les fibres sont orientées et s'agencent dans le matériau environnant. Ces caractéristiques influencent notamment le comportement mécanique, optique et électromagnétique des composites. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Si l'on veut pouvoir observer la composition de ce genre de matériaux composites, il faut impérativement pouvoir les scruter à l'intérieur. Pour ce faire, il est possible de recourir à ce qu'on appelle la diffusion des rayons X aux petits angles (small angle X-ray scattering (SAXS) en anglais) et d'exploiter le fait que les rayons X se diffractent lorsqu'ils traversent la matière. Le diagramme de diffraction que l'on obtient ainsi permet de recueillir des informations sur l'intérieur de l'échantillon et éventuellement sur l'orientation des fibres. Mais les méthodes conventionnelles de SAXS ont l'inconvénient d'être très lentes: radiographier en continu quelques centimètres d'échantillon avec la résolution nécessaire peut en effet prendre plusieurs heures.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Observer le nouage d'un ruban en fibre de carbone &lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Avec leurs collègues de l'EPFL et de la spin-off danoise Xnovo Technology, des chercheurs du PSI et de l'ETH Zurich ont à présent réussi à perfectionner cette technologie pour l'application dans la pratique. «Avec ce développement, il devient possible d'identifier au moyen d'une seule radiographie plusieurs diagrammes de diffraction locaux qui reflètent la structure spatiale interne d'un échantillon, ce qui nous permet de réaliser un grande nombre d'images successives», explique Matias Kagias, inventeur de la méthode et postdoc au PSI dans le groupe de recherche Tomographie par rayons X, placé sous la direction de Marco Stampanoni. Pour prouver le principe de fonctionnement, les chercheurs ont utilisé la nouvelle méthode pour visualiser l'orientation des fibres dans un ruban en fibre de carbone pendant le processus de nouage. Ils ont réalisé des radiographies par projection résolues en temps avec 25 images par seconde, pendant un laps de temps de 11 secondes. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Des applications envisageables dans le domaine de la médecine ou de la sécurité intérieure &lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;La nouvelle méthode ne fonctionne pas seulement avec des rayons X issus d'accélérateurs comme la Source de Lumière Suisse SLS, mais aussi avec le rayonnement issu de tubes à rayons X conventionnels. «On peut s'attendre à ce que cette approche novatrice trouve une application concrète dans les dispositifs médicaux, le contrôle non destructif, mais aussi dans le domaine de la sécurité intérieure», détaille Marco Stampanoni, responsable du groupe de recherche Tomographie par rayons X. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Les chercheurs viennent de publier leurs résultats dans la revue spécialisée &lt;i&gt;Nature Communications&lt;/i&gt;.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Texte: Institut Paul Scherrer/Sebastian Jutzi&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;A propos du PSI&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;L'Institut Paul Scherrer PSI développe, construit et exploite des grandes installations de recherche complexes qu'il met à la disposition de la communauté scientifique nationale et internationale. Les domaines de recherche de l'institut sont centrés sur la matière et les matériaux, l'énergie et l'environnement ainsi que la santé humaine. La formation des générations futures est une préoccupation centrale du PSI. C'est pourquoi environ un quart de nos collaborateurs sont des apprentis, des doctorants ou des postdocs. En tout, le PSI emploie 2100 collaborateurs, ce qui fait de lui le plus grand institut de recherche en Suisse. Son budget annuel s'élève à environ 407 millions de francs. Le PSI fait partie du domaine des EPF avec l'ETH Zurich, l'EPF Lausanne et trois autres instituts de recherche: l'Eawag, l'Empa et le WSL.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Publication originale&lt;/b&gt; &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Diffractive small angle X-ray scattering imaging for anisotropic structures&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;Matias Kagias, Zhentian Wang, Mie Elholm Birkbak, Erik Lauridsen, MatteoAbis, Goran Lovric, Konstantins Je_movs, Marco Stampanoni&lt;br /&gt;&lt;i&gt;Nature Communications, &lt;/i&gt;12.11.2019&lt;br /&gt;DOI: 10.1038/s41467-019-12635-2&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Prof. Marco Stampanoni Responsable du groupe de recherche Tomographie par rayons X Institut Paul Scherrer, Forschungsstrasse 111, 5232 Villigen PSI, Suisse Téléphone: +41 56 310 47 24, e-mail: marco.stampanoni@psi.ch [allemand, anglais] Dr Matias Kagias Groupe de recherche Tomographie par rayons X Institut Paul Scherrer, Forschungsstrasse 111, 5232 Villigen PSI, Suisse Téléphone: +41 56 310 51 20, e-mail: matias.kagias@psi.ch [anglais]</contact>
      <link id="194805">
        <title>Images et informations supplémentaires</title>
        <uri>https://www.psi.ch/fr/node/31203</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Villigen</city>
      <title>A fast and precise look into fibre-reinforced composites</title>
      <lead>Researchers at the Paul Scherrer Institute PSI have improved a method for small angle X-ray scattering (SAXS) to such an extent that it can now be used in the development or quality control of novel fibre-reinforced composites. This means that in the future, such materials can be investigated not only with X-rays from especially powerful sources such as the Swiss Light Source SLS, but also with those from conventional X-ray tubes. The researchers have published their results in the journal Nature Communications.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Novel fibre-reinforced composites are becoming increasingly important as stable and lightweight materials. One example of this type of composite is carbon fibre reinforced polymers (CFRP), which are used in aircraft construction or in the construction of Formula 1 racing cars and sports bicycles. The properties of these materials depend to a large extent on how the tiny fibres are aligned and how they are arranged and embedded in the surrounding material, influencing the mechanical, optical, or electromagnetic behaviour of the composites. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;To investigate the fibre's orientation in such composites, researchers must look inside them. One could use small angle X-ray scattering (SAXS), exploiting the fact that X-rays are scattered when they penetrate matter. The resulting scattering pattern can then be used to obtain information about the interior of a sample and potentially the orientation of the fibres. However, the common SAXS methods have the disadvantage of being quite slow: It can take up to several hours to scan centimetre-sized specimens with the required resolution. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Observing the knotting of a carbon fibre ribbon&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Researchers at the Paul Scherrer Institute PSI and ETH Zurich, together with colleagues from EPF Lausanne and the Danish spin-off company Xnovo Technology, have now succeeded in further developing the technology for practical applications. "The decisive factor was that we installed an array of X-ray lenses behind the sample. This makes it possible to detect multiple local scattering patterns that reflect the spatial inner structure of a sample with only one X-ray shot, enabling us to take a large number of consecutive images", says Matias Kagias, the inventor of the method and a postdoctoral researcher in the PSI X-ray tomography group headed by Marco Stampanoni. As a proof of principle, the researchers used the new method to display fibres' orientation in a carbon fibre ribbon during the knotting process. They acquired time-resolved X-ray projections at a rate of 25 images per second over a period of 11 seconds. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Applications in medicine and security are conceivable&lt;/b&gt;&lt;b&gt; &lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The new method works not only with X-rays from synchrotron facilities such as the Swiss Light Source SLS, but also with beams from conventional X-ray tubes. Therefore, says Prof. Marco Stampanoni, "it is expected that this novel approach will find practical applications in medical devices and non-destructive testing as well as the area of homeland security". &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The researchers have published their results in the journal &lt;i&gt;Nature Communications&lt;/i&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Text: Paul Scherrer Institute/Sebastian Jutzi&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;About PSI&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The Paul Scherrer Institute PSI develops, builds and operates large, complex research facilities and makes them available to the national and international research community. The institute's own key research priorities are in the fields of matter and materials, energy and environment and human health. PSI is committed to the training of future generations. Therefore about one quarter of our staff are post-docs, post-graduates or apprentices. Altogether PSI employs 2100 people, thus being the largest research institute in Switzerland. The annual budget amounts to approximately CHF 407 million. PSI is part of the ETH Domain, with the other members being the two Swiss Federal Institutes of Technology, ETH Zurich and EPFL Lausanne, as well as Eawag (Swiss Federal Institute of Aquatic Science and Technology), Empa (Swiss Federal Laboratories for Materials Science and Technology) and WSL (Swiss Federal Institute for Forest, Snow and Landscape Research).&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Dr. Mirjam van Daalen Head of Communications Paul Scherrer Institute CH-5232 Villigen PSI Phone: +41 56 310 56 74 mirjam.vandaalen@psi.ch</contact>
      <link id="194804">
        <title>Images and additional information</title>
        <uri>https://www.psi.ch/en/node/31203</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="19">
        <name lang="de">Medien</name>
        <name lang="fr">Médias</name>
        <name lang="it">Media</name>
        <name lang="en">Media</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
