<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="77440" revoked="no">
    <version>2</version>
    <pubdate>2019-12-07</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="201" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>201</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="201">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>EDA transportiert zwei Anlagen für Trinkwasserproduktion in die Ostukraine</title>
      <lead>Die Humanitäre Hilfe des EDA hat zwei Grossanlangen in die Region Donetsk transportiert, die zur Versorgung der Bevölkerung in der Ostukraine mit Trinkwasser beitragen werden. Es handelt sich um den 11. Einsatz der Humanitären Hilfe seit 2015 zugunsten der Menschen beidseits der Kontaktlinie. </lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Wie bei den früheren Hilfstransporten wurde auch diese humanitäre Aktion in der Ostukraine von einem Expertenteam des Schweizerischen Korps für Humanitäre Hilfe (SKH) durchgeführt, dieses Mal mit logistischer Unterstützung von UNOCHA (UN-Amt für humanitäre Koordination). Der Bedarf ist ausgewiesen, denn die Situation im Trinkwasserbereich ist angespannt: Für die Trinkwasserproduktion fehlen die nötigen Desinfektionsmittel. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mit der 11. humanitären Direktaktion wurden zwei Grossanlagen für die dezentrale Produktion von Hypochlorit, ein Chlorersatz, für 900'000 Menschen an die Wasserwerke in Donetsk und Makeevka übergeben, beides Regionen im nichtregierungskontrollierten Teil der Ukraine. An diverse Zweigstellen der Wasserwerke in der Region wurde zudem Chlor geliefert. Zur Mission gehörte schliesslich auch ein ausgedehntes Monitoring der bisher gelieferten Hypochloritproduktionsanlagen beidseits der Kontaktlinie. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Die Schweiz ist die einzige staatliche Akteurin, welche direkte humanitäre Hilfe auf beiden Seiten der Kontaktlinie leistet. Sie trägt mit ihren Hilfstransporten in die Ostukraine wesentlich dazu bei, dass die Volksgesundheit durch eine Verbesserung der medizinischen Infrastruktur sowie die Produktion von sauberem Trinkwasser nicht zu stark litt. &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Kommunikation EDA Bundeshaus West CH-3003 Bern Tel. Kommunikationsservice: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Medienstelle: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <revisions>
        <revision date="2019-12-09 15:10" type="R"/>
      </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Le DFAE achemine deux stations de production d’eau potable en Ukraine</title>
      <lead>L’Aide humanitaire du DFAE a transporté dans la région de Donetsk deux grandes installations de production d’eau potable pour approvisionner la population de l’est de l’Ukraine. Il s’agit de la 11e intervention menée par l’Aide humanitaire depuis 2015 en faveur des habitants vivant de part et d’autre de la ligne de contact. </lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;À l’instar des précédents transports de matériel de secours, cette opération humanitaire dans l’est de l’Ukraine a été réalisée par une équipe d’experts du Corps suisse d’aide humanitaire (CSA), cette fois-ci avec le soutien logistique du Bureau de la coordination des affaires humanitaires des Nations Unies (OCHA). Les besoins sont avérés: la situation concernant la production d’eau potable est critique, les désinfectants nécessaires faisant actuellement défaut. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Dans le cadre de cette 11e action humanitaire directe, deux grandes installations de production décentralisée d’hypochlorite, un substitut du chlore, ont été acheminées vers les usines hydrauliques de Donetsk et de Makeevka, dans la partie de l’Ukraine contrôlée par les séparatistes. Elles devraient permettre de couvrir les besoins en eau potable de 900’000 personnes. Du chlore a en outre été fourni à diverses installations secondaires des usines hydrauliques de la région. Enfin, la mission comprenait également un monitoring étendu des stations de production d’hypochlorite livrées jusque-là de part et d’autre de la ligne de contact. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;La Suisse est le seul acteur étatique à fournir une aide humanitaire directe des deux côtés de la ligne de contact. Ses transports d’aide humanitaire ont largement contribué à ce que la santé des habitants ne se détériore pas trop grâce à une amélioration de l’infrastructure médicale et à la production d’eau potable. &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Communication DFAE Palais fédéral ouest CH-3003 Berne Tél. Service de communication: +41 58 462 31 53 Tél. Service de presse: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <revisions>
        <revision date="2019-12-09 15:10" type="R"/>
      </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Il DFAE trasporta due impianti per la produzione di acqua potabile nell’Ucraina orientale</title>
      <lead>L’Aiuto umanitario del DFAE ha portato nella regione di Donec’k due grandi impianti che contribuiranno a fornire acqua potabile alla popolazione dell’Ucraina orientale. Si tratta dell’undicesimo intervento dell’Aiuto umanitario dal 2015 a favore delle persone sui due lati della linea di contatto. </lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Come per i precedenti trasporti di aiuto, anche questa operazione umanitaria nell’Ucraina orientale è stata svolta da un gruppo di esperti del Corpo svizzero di aiuto umanitario (CSA), questa volta con il sostegno logistico dell’OCHA (Ufficio delle Nazioni Unite per gli affari umanitari). Il fabbisogno è grande e la situazione per quanto concerne la disponibilità di acqua potabile è tesa poiché mancano i disinfettanti necessari a produrla. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Con questo undicesimo intervento umanitario diretto sono stati consegnati due grandi impianti per la produzione decentralizzata di ipoclorito di sodio (un surrogato del cloro) per circa 900 000 persone, destinato alle centrali idriche a Donec’k e Makiïvka, due regioni situate nella parte del Paese non controllata dal Governo. Varie installazioni secondarie delle centrali nella regione hanno inoltre ricevuto forniture di cloro. Infine la missione comprendeva anche un monitoraggio completo degli impianti per la produzione di ipoclorito di sodio forniti finora a entrambi i lati della linea di contatto. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;La Svizzera è l’unico attore statale a inviare aiuti umanitari diretti su entrambi i lati della linea di contatto. Con i suoi trasporti di materiale umanitario nell’Ucraina orientale ha contribuito in modo significativo a tutelare la salute della popolazione migliorando l’infrastruttura medico- sanitaria ed evitando per quanto possibile difficoltà nella produzione di acqua potabile. &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Comunicazione DFAE Palazzo federale ovest CH-3003 Berna Tel. Servizio di comunicazione: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Servizio stampa: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <revisions>
        <revision date="2019-12-09 15:10" type="R"/>
      </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>FDFA transports two drinking-water production systems to eastern Ukraine</title>
      <lead>Swiss Humanitarian Aid has transported two large-scale installations to the Donetsk region to help supply the population in eastern Ukraine with clean drinking water. This is its 11th mission since 2015 in aid of the people living on both sides of the contact line. </lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;As with previous aid convoys to eastern Ukraine, this latest humanitarian action was carried out by a team of experts from the Swiss Humanitarian Aid Unit (SHA), on this occasion with logistical support from the UN's Office for the Coordination of Humanitarian Affairs (OCHA). There is a great need for clean drinking water in the region, where the situation is tense because there is a lack of disinfectants to treat the water. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This latest consignment contains two large-scale installations that can produce a chlorine substitute known as hypochlorite. The decentralised systems have been sent to the waterworks in Donetsk and Makiivka, both located in the part of Ukraine outside government control, which service around 900,000 people. Chlorine has also been supplied to various branches of the waterworks in the region. The current mission also includes extensive monitoring of the hypochlorite production systems supplied to date on both sides of the contact line. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Switzerland is the only state actor working in a humanitarian capacity in eastern Ukraine on both sides of the contact line. By delivering supplies that improve the local medical infrastructure and help produce clean drinking water, Switzerland's aid convoys are making a major contribution to mitigating the negative impact on public health in the region. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>FDFA Communication Federal Palace West Wing CH-3003 Bern, Switzerland Tel. Communication service: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Press service: +41 58 460 55 55 E-mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @SwissMFA</contact>
      <revisions>
        <revision date="2019-12-09 15:10" type="R"/>
      </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="10">
        <name lang="de">Bundesrat</name>
        <name lang="fr">Conseil fédéral</name>
        <name lang="it">Consiglio federale</name>
        <name lang="en">Federal Council</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="34">
        <name lang="de">Europa</name>
        <name lang="fr">Europe</name>
        <name lang="it">Europa</name>
        <name lang="en">Europe</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="40">
        <name lang="de">Sicherheit</name>
        <name lang="fr">Sécurité</name>
        <name lang="it">Sicurezza</name>
        <name lang="en">Security</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
