<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="42166" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2011-11-11</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="201" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>201</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="201">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Bundespräsidentin Micheline Calmy-Rey zu offiziellem Besuch in Kroatien</title>
      <lead>Bundespräsidentin Micheline Calmy-Rey reist am Montag, 14. November 2011 zu einem offiziellen Besuch in die kroatische Hauptstadt Zagreb. Dort wird sie vom kroatischen Präsidenten Ivo Josipovic sowie vom Parlamentspräsidenten Luka Bebic zu Gesprächen empfangen. Bei dem Besuch handelt es sich um das erste Treffen auf präsidialer Ebene zwischen den beiden Staaten.</lead>
      <text link="no">Im Zentrum stehen die gute Partnerschaft der letzten 20 Jahre, die gemeinsamen Interessen betreffend Frieden, Stabilität und Prosperität in der ganzen südosteuropäischen Region sowie die Perspektiven der bilateralen und multilateralen Zusammenarbeit mit dem künftigen EU-Mitglied. Der Besuch findet in dem Jahr statt, in welchem Kroatien seine zwanzigjährige Unabhängigkeit feiert. Kroatien hat seine EU-Beitrittsverhandlungen zudem im Sommer dieses Jahres erfolgreich abgeschlossen und wird voraussichtlich im Laufe 2013 der 28. Mitgliedsstaat der Europäischen Union. </text>
      <contact>Kommunikation EDA Bundeshaus West CH-3003 Bern Tel. Kommunikationsservice: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Medienstelle: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Visite officielle de la présidente de la Confédération Micheline Calmy-Rey en Croatie</title>
      <lead>La présidente de la Confédération Micheline Calmy-Rey se rendra à Zagreb, capitale de la Croatie, pour une visite officielle le lundi 14 novembre 2011. Elle sera reçue par le président croate Ivo Josipović ainsi que par le président du Parlement Luka Bebić. Il s’agit de la première rencontre au niveau présidentiel entre les deux Etats.</lead>
      <text link="no">Les discussions porteront principalement sur le partenariat qui lie les deux pays depuis vingt ans, sur leurs intérêts communs dans les domaines de la paix, de la stabilité et de la prospérité pour l’ensemble de la région de l’Europe du sud-est ainsi que sur les perspectives de coopération bilatérale et multilatérale entre la Suisse et ce futur Etat membre de l’Union européenne. La visite de la Présidente de la Confédération a lieu en une année où la Croatie fête ses vingt ans d’indépendance. La Croatie a par ailleurs conclu les négociations d’adhésion à l’UE cet été et il est prévu qu’elle devienne le 28ème membre de l’Union dans le courant de l’année 2013. </text>
      <contact>Communication DFAE Palais fédéral ouest CH-3003 Berne Tél. Service de communication: +41 58 462 31 53 Tél. Service de presse: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Visita ufficiale in Croazia della presidente della Confederazione Micheline Calmy-Rey</title>
      <lead>Lunedì 14 novembre 2011 la presidente della Confederazione Micheline Calmy-Rey si recherà in visita ufficiale a Zagabria, dove sarà accolta dal presidente croato Ivo Josipovic e dal presidente del Parlamento Luka Bebic. Si tratta del primo incontro di questo genere tra i vertici dei due Stati.</lead>
      <text link="no">Temi centrali dei colloqui saranno la proficua cooperazione instaurata tra i due Paesi nel corso degli ultimi vent’anni, il comune interesse per la pace, la stabilità e la prosperità dell'intera area dell’Europa sudorientale e le prospettive di una collaborazione bilaterale ed multilaterale tra la Svizzera e il futuro membro dell’UE. La visita si svolge nell'anno in cui la Croazia festeggia i primi vent'anni della propria indipendenza. Questa estate, il Paese ha inoltre portato a buon fine i propri negoziati di adesione all'UE: nel corso del 2013 diventerà molto probabilmente il 28° Stato membro dell'Unione europea. </text>
      <contact>Comunicazione DFAE Palazzo federale ovest CH-3003 Berna Tel. Servizio di comunicazione: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Servizio stampa: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>The President of the Confederation to make an official visit to Croatia</title>
      <lead>On Monday, 14 November 2011, the President of the Swiss Confederation, Micheline Calmy-Rey, will travel to Zagreb, the capital of Croatia, for an official visit. She will be received for talks by the President of Croatia, Ivo Josipovic and the Speaker of the Parliament, Luka Bebic. Mrs Calmy-Rey’s visit will be the first meeting at presidential level between the two countries.</lead>
      <text link="no">The discussions will focus on the good partnership that the two countries have developed over the past 20 years, the shared interest in peace, stability and prosperity for the whole South-Eastern European region, and on the prospects of bilateral and multilateral co-operation with Croatia as a future member of the European Union. The visit takes place in the year in which Croatia celebrates 20 years’ independence. In summer this year, furthermore, Croatia successfully concluded its EU-accession negotiations, and is expected to become the 28th member country of the EU in the course of 2013. </text>
      <contact>FDFA Communication Federal Palace West Wing CH-3003 Bern, Switzerland Tel. Communication service: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Press service: +41 58 460 55 55 E-mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @SwissMFA</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
