<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="42202" revoked="no">
    <version>2</version>
    <pubdate>2011-11-14</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="201" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>201</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="703" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>701</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Staatssekretariat für Wirtschaft</name>
      <name lang="fr">Secrétariat d'Etat à l'économie</name>
      <name lang="it">Segreteria di Stato dell'economia</name>
      <name lang="en">State Secretariat for Economic Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.seco.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.seco.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.seco.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.seco.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@seco.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@seco.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@seco.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@seco.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="201">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <department id="701">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Wirtschaft, Bildung und Forschung</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'économie, de la formation et de la recherche</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'economia, della formazione e della ricerca</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Economic Affairs, Education and Research</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Sauberes Wasser in Südosteuropa dank Erfahrung und Hilfe aus der Schweiz</title>
      <lead>Seit über 20 Jahren unterstützt die Schweiz die Länder Südosteuropas beim Bau zuverlässiger Wasserversorgungen und bei der Entwicklung eines funktionierenden öffentlichen Dienstes. An der Jahreskonferenz der Schweizer Ostzusammenarbeit vom 25. November in Neuenburg diskutieren Fachleute und Behördenvertreter aus dem In- und Ausland anhand von Beispielen aus Moldawien und Albanien über Erreichtes und künftige Herausforderungen. Interessierte sowie Medienschaffende sind herzlich eingeladen.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Den Auftakt der Konferenz bildet eine Ansprache von Bundespräsidentin Micheline Calmy-Rey, gefolgt von den Ausführungen des moldawischen Umweltministers Gheorghe Şalaru. In der Folge werden das Engagement des Staatssekretariats für Wirtschaft SECO zur Verbesserung der Wasserversorgung in den albanischen Städten Pogradec, Lezha und Shkodra sowie das Programm der Direktion für Entwicklung und Zusammenarbeit DEZA zu Gunsten der ländlichen Bevölkerung Moldawiens vorgestellt und diskutiert. An der Diskussion beteiligen sich nebst Vertreterinnen und Vertretern von SECO und DEZA auch Behördenmitglieder aus den beiden Partnerländern sowie Gemeindevertreter aus den Kantonen Waadt und Neuenburg. Im Zentrum stehen dabei die Fragen nach der Vorbildrolle der Schweiz sowie nach Wert und Preis von sauberem Trinkwasser. Zum Abschluss der Veranstaltung werfen DEZA-Direktor Martin Dahinden und Jean-Luc Bernasconi, Chef Operationen Wirtschaftliche Zusammenarbeit und Entwicklung beim SECO, gemeinsam einen Blick in die Zukunft. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Medienschaffende sind auf Anmeldung an der Jahreskonferenz willkommen. Auf Wunsch können Interviews mit den anwesenden Spezialistinnen und Spezialisten vermittelt werden. Detaillierte Informationen zum Thema und zum Programm der Konferenz sind im Internet zu finden.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Anmeldung:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;br /&gt;Information EDA, info@eda.admin.ch&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Adresse für Rückfragen:&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/b&gt;SECO: Nicole Müller, +41 (0)31 324 09 10 EDA: &lt;br /&gt;Stefan von Below, +41 (0)31 322 34 73 &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Kommunikation EDA Bundeshaus West CH-3003 Bern Tel. Kommunikationsservice: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Medienstelle: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <link id="90527">
        <title>Programm der Konferenz</title>
        <uri>http://www.deza.admin.ch/de/Dossiers/Dossier_Zugang_zu_Wasser_in_Suedosteuropa/Jahreskonferenz_der_Ostzusammenarbeit_2011</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions>
        <revision date="2011-11-14 11:32" type="R"/>
      </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>De l’eau propre en Europe du Sud-Est grâce à l’expérience et l’aide de la Suisse</title>
      <lead>Depuis plus de 20 ans, la Suisse soutient les pays d’Europe du Sud-Est dans la construction de systèmes d’approvisionnement en eau fiables et dans le développement de services publics efficaces. Lors de la Conférence annuelle de la coopération suisse avec l’Europe de l’Est, organisée le 25 novembre à Neuchâtel, des experts et des représentants des autorités suisses et étrangères discuteront des résultats déjà obtenus et des défis à venir en prenant comme exemple la Moldavie et l’Albanie. Les journalistes et les personnes intéressées sont les bienvenus.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;La conférence s’ouvrira sur une allocution de la présidente de la Confédération, Micheline Calmy-Rey, et un exposé du ministre moldave de l’environnement, Gheorghe Şalaru. Suivront une présentation et un débat sur les activités menées par le Secrétariat d’Etat à l’économie (SECO) pour améliorer l’approvisionnement en eau dans les villes albanaises de Pogradec, Lezha et Shkodra ainsi que sur le programme mis en œuvre par la Direction du développement et de la coopération (DDC) en faveur de la population rurale de Moldavie. Des représentants du SECO, de la DDC, des autorités des deux pays partenaires et de communes des cantons de Vaud et de Neuchâtel prendront part à la discussion. Le rôle de modèle que joue la Suisse ainsi que la valeur et le prix de l’eau seront au cœur du débat. La conférence se terminera sur les perspectives formulées par le directeur de la DDC, Martin Dahinden, et le chef des opérations du centre de prestations Coopération et développement économiques au sein du SECO, Jean-Luc Bernasconi. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Les journalistes qui se seront au préalable inscrits sont les bienvenus à la conférence. Des interviews avec les spécialistes présents peuvent être organisées. Les informations détaillées sur le sujet et le programme de la conférence figurent sur internet. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Inscription :&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/b&gt;Information DFAE, info@eda.admin.ch&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Renseignements :£&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/b&gt;SECO : Nicole Müller, +41 (0)31 324 09 10 DFAE : &lt;br /&gt;Stefan von Below, +41 (0)31 322 34 73 &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Communication DFAE Palais fédéral ouest CH-3003 Berne Tél. Service de communication: +41 58 462 31 53 Tél. Service de presse: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <link id="90528">
        <title>Programme de la Conférence</title>
        <uri>http://www.deza.admin.ch/fr/Dossiers/Dossier_Acces_a_l_eau_en_Europe_du_Sud_Est/Conference_annuelle_de_la_cooperation_avec_l_Europe_de_l_Est</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions>
        <revision date="2011-11-14 11:32" type="R"/>
      </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Acqua pulita nell'Europa sudorientale grazie all'esperienza e all'aiuto della Svizzera</title>
      <lead>Da più di 20 anni la Svizzera sostiene i Paesi dell'Europa sudorientale nel realizzare un approvvigionamento idrico più affidabile e nello sviluppare un servizio pubblico efficace. Nel corso della Conferenza annuale della cooperazione svizzera con l’Europa dell’Est, che avrà luogo il 25 novembre a Neuchâtel, specialisti e rappresentanti delle autorità provenienti dalla Svizzera e dall'estero discuteranno su quanto raggiunto e sulle sfide future prendendo spunto dagli esempi della Moldova e dell'Albania. Interessati e giornalisti sono cordialmente invitati.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;La conferenza avrà inizio con un discorso della presidente della Confederazione Micheline Calmy-Rey e con le considerazioni del ministro moldavo dell'ambiente Gheorghe Şalaru. In seguito verranno presentati e discussi l'impegno della Segreteria di Stato dell'economia SECO, volto a migliorare l'approvvigionamento idrico nelle città albanesi di Pogradec, Lezha e Shkodra, e il programma della Direzione dello sviluppo e della cooperazione DSC a favore della popolazione rurale della Moldova. Oltre ai rappresentanti della SECO e della DSC, alla discussione parteciperanno anche membri delle autorità dei due Paesi partner e rappresentanti comunali del Cantone di Vaud e del Cantone di Neuchâtel. Verranno trattate soprattuto questioni riguardanti il ruolo esemplare della Svizzera e il valore e il prezzo dell'acqua potabile. Alla fine della manifestazione il direttore della DSC Martin Dahinden e il responsabile Operazioni di cooperazione e sviluppo economico della SECO Jean-Luc Bernasconi si pronunceranno sulle sfide future. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I rappresentanti dei media possono iscriversi alla Conferenza annuale e chiedere l'organizzazione di interviste con gli specialisti presenti. Informazioni dettagliate sul tema e sul programma della Conferenza possono essere consultate su Internet. &lt;b&gt; &lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Iscrizione:&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/b&gt;Informazione DFAE, info@eda.admin.ch &lt;/p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Indirizzo in caso di domande:&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/b&gt;SECO: Nicole Müller, +41 (0)31 324 09 10&lt;br /&gt;DFAE: Stefan von Below, +41 (0)31 322 34 73</text>
      <contact>Comunicazione DFAE Palazzo federale ovest CH-3003 Berna Tel. Servizio di comunicazione: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Servizio stampa: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <link id="90529">
        <title>Programma della Conferenza</title>
        <uri>http://www.deza.admin.ch/it/Dossiers/Dossier_Accesso_all_acqua_nell_Europa_sudorientale/Conferenza_annuale_della_cooperazione_con_l_Europa_dell_Est</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions>
        <revision date="2011-11-14 11:32" type="R"/>
      </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Clean Water in South-Eastern Europe thanks to Swiss Know-how and Assistance</title>
      <lead>For over 20 years, Switzerland has been supporting the countries of South-Eastern Europe in building reliable water-supply systems and in creating properly functioning public utility companies. The Annual Conference on Swiss Cooperation with Eastern Europe and the CIS to be held on 25 November 2011 in Neuchâtel, will bring together experts and government officials from both Switzerland and abroad for a discussion on what has been achieved to date and the challenges still to be met. The focus will be on projects being conducted in Moldova and Albania. Those persons interested as well as representatives of the media are cordially invited to attend.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Keynote speaker at the Conference will be Swiss President Micheline Calmy-Rey, followed by the remarks of the Moldovan Minister of Environment Gheorghe Şalaru. The Conference will continue with the presentation and discussion of, for one thing, the activities conducted by the State Secretariat for Economic Affairs SECO to enhance the provision of water in the Albanian cities of Pogradec, Lezha, and Shkodra, and the programme of the Swiss Agency for Development and Cooperation SDC to the benefit of the rural population in Moldova, for another. Along with representatives from SECO and the SDC, members of the public authorities from both partner countries as well as municipal representatives from the cantons of Vaud and Neuchâtel will be participating in the Conference. Discussions will center on the question of Switzerland’s role as a model for others, as well as the value attached to clean drinking water and the acceptable cost. In concluding the event, SDC Director-General Dahinden and Jean-Luc Bernasconi, Head of Operations at Economic Cooperation and Development SECO, will cast a joint glance at the future challenges. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Media representatives are welcome to register for attendance at the Annual Conference. Their requests for interviews with the experts present will gladly be transmitted. Detailed information on the theme and the programme of this year’s Conference can be found in the internet. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Registration:&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/b&gt;Information FDFA, info@eda.admin.ch&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Queries can be addressed to:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;br /&gt;SECO: Nicole Müller, +41 (0)31 324 09 10&lt;br /&gt;FDFA: Stefan von Below, +41 (0)31 322 34 73&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>FDFA Communication Federal Palace West Wing CH-3003 Bern, Switzerland Tel. Communication service: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Press service: +41 58 460 55 55 E-mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @SwissMFA</contact>
      <link id="90530">
        <title>Programme of the Conference</title>
        <uri>http://www.deza.admin.ch/en/Dossiers/Dossier_Access_to_water_in_South_Eastern_Europe/Annual_Conference_on_Cooperation_with_Eastern_Europe_and_the_CIS</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions>
        <revision date="2011-11-14 11:32" type="R"/>
      </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="47">
        <name lang="de">Wirtschaft</name>
        <name lang="fr">Économie</name>
        <name lang="it">Economia</name>
        <name lang="en">Economic Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
