<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="55996" revoked="no">
    <version>2</version>
    <pubdate>2015-01-25</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="201" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>201</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="201">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Das EDA verurteilt den Angriff auf Zivilisten in der Ostukraine</title>
      <lead>Der Vorsteher des Eidgenössischen Departements für auswärtige Angelegenheiten EDA, Bundesrat Didier Burkhalter, verurteilt den Beschuss von bewohnten Gebieten in der Umgebung von Mariupol, dem am Samstag mindestens 30 Menschen zum Opfer gefallen sind und welcher eine hohe Anzahl Verletzter gefordert hat. Er ruft zur unverzüglichen Aufnahme von Gesprächen auf.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Der Vorsteher des Eidgenössischen Departements für auswärtige Angelegenheiten EDA, Bundesrat Didier Burkhalter, verurteilt den Beschuss von bewohnten Gebieten in der Umgebung von Mariupol, dem am Samstag mindestens 30 Menschen zum Opfer gefallen sind und welcher eine hohe Anzahl Verletzter gefordert hat, aufs Schärfste. Er dankt den Mitgliedern der OSZE-Monitoringmission für ihre rasche und unabhängige Berichterstattung, die auch Angaben über den Ausgangspunkt des Beschusses enthält.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Bundesrat Burkhalter ist besorgt über die jüngste Eskalation der Gewalt in der Ostukraine, zu denen auch Angriffe auf dicht bewohnte Gebiete in Donetsk, Debaltseve und andern Orten entlang der Kontaktlinie gehören, und die zahlreiche zivile Opfer gefordert haben. „Der Tod unschuldiger Männer, Frauen und Kinder ist inakzeptabel“, sagt Bundesrat Burkhalter. Die Schweiz rufe alle Seiten auf, die Prinzipien des humanitären Völkerrechts strikt einzuhalten.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Der Vorsteher des EDA unterstreicht, dass aus Schweizerischer Sicht der Konflikt nicht militärisch gelöst werden kann und ruft die Akteure dazu auf, alle zur Verfügung stehenden diplomatischen Mittel zu nutzen. Er begrüsst die Einberufung eines dringenden Treffens der Trilateralen Kontaktgruppe mit allen Unterzeichnern der Minsk-Abmachungen. Er ruft alle betroffenen Seiten dazu auf, den Verpflichtungen, die sie in den beiden relevanten Dokumenten, dem Minsker Protokoll und dem Minsker Memorandum vom September 2014 eingegangen sind, nachzukommen. Didier Burkhalter bezeichnet ein Ende der Gewalt, rasche Gespräche und Massnahmen zur Deeskalation als vordringliche Basis für eine nachhaltige politische Lösung des Konflikts.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Kommunikation EDA Bundeshaus West CH-3003 Bern Tel. Kommunikationsservice: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Medienstelle: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <revisions>
        <revision date="2015-01-26 11:50" type="R"/>
      </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Le Département fédéral des affaires étrangères exprime sa grande inquiétude sur la détérioration de la situation dans l’est de l’Ukraine</title>
      <lead>Le chef du Département fédéral des affaires étrangères, Didier Burkhalter, a fermement condamné le bombardement de quartiers résidentiels à Mariupol qui ont causé la mort d’au moins 30 civils et fait de nombreux blessés. Il a appelé à une reprise immédiate du dialogue.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Le chef du Département fédéral des affaires étrangères, Didier Burkhalter, a fermement condamné le bombardement de quartiers résidentiels à Mariupol qui ont causé la mort d’au moins 30 civils et fait de nombreux blessés. Il a remercié la mission spéciale d’observation de l’OSCE pour son rapport rapide et impartial - donnant également des indications précises sur l’endroit d’où a été effectué ce bombardement.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Didier Burkhalter a fait part de son inquiétude eu égard à la récente escalade de la violence dans l’est de l’Ukraine en général et aux attaques perpétrées dans des zones habitées comme Donetsk, Debaltseve et d’autres endroits le long de la ligne de contact. « La mort de civils, parmi lesquels figurent des femmes et des enfants est inacceptable », a indiqué le chef du DFAE avant d’ajouter que « la Suisse appelle toutes les parties à respecter les principes du droit international humanitaire ».&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;M. Burkhalter a souligné que pour la Suisse, il n’y avait pas de solution militaire au conflit, qu’il fallait faire usage de tous les instruments de la diplomatie et s’est félicité de la décision de réunir d’urgence le groupe de contact trilatéral comprenant tous les signataires de l’accord de Minsk. Il demande à toutes les parties de prendre d’urgence des mesures visant à mettre en œuvre intégralement les engagements pris à Minsk. La fin immédiate des violences, la reprise rapide du dialogue et des mesures visant à favoriser une désescalade du conflit doivent servir de base à une solution politique durable de ce conflit, a ajouté M. Burkhalter.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Communication DFAE Palais fédéral ouest CH-3003 Berne Tél. Service de communication: +41 58 462 31 53 Tél. Service de presse: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Federal Department of Foreign Affairs expresses its great concern about the deteriorating security situation in eastern Ukraine</title>
      <lead>The Head of the Swiss Federal Department of Foreign Affairs Didier Burkhalter sharply condemns the shelling of residential areas in Mariupol resulting in at least 30 civilians killed and a very high number of injured persons. He calls for the immediate resumption of talks.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;As violence has continued to escalate in Eastern Ukraine in recent days, the Head of the Swiss Federal Department of Foreign Affairs Didier Burkhalter sharply condemns the shelling of residential areas in Mariupol resulting in at least 30 civilians killed and a very high number of injured persons. The Swiss Foreign Minister thanks the OSCE’s Special Monitoring Mission to Ukraine for their swift and impartial report, including their indication about the origin of shelling and commends the SMM for its continuous efforts to fulfill its mandate under challenging circumstances.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Burkhalter expresses concern regarding the recent escalation of violence in Eastern Ukraine, including attacks on densely populated areas in Donetsk, Debaltseve and other places along the contact line which have caused numerous civilian victims. “The death of innocent men, women and children is inacceptable” said Burkhalter and added: “Switzerland calls on all sides to strictly adhere to the principles of International Humanitarian Law.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Burkhalter repeated that in view of Switzerland there is no military solution to the conflict and called all actors to make use of all diplomatic instruments which are currently in place. He welcomes the convening of an urgent meeting of the Trilateral Contact Group with all signatories of the Minsk arrangements. He appeals to all those involved to implement their commitments made in the two relevant documents, i.e. the Minsk Protocol and the Minsk Memorandum of September 2014. An end of violence, urgent talks and measures of de-escalation would be the basis of a sustainable political solution of the conflict, Burkhalter said.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>FDFA Communication Federal Palace West Wing CH-3003 Bern, Switzerland Tel. Communication service: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Press service: +41 58 460 55 55 E-mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @SwissMFA</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
