<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="56493" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2015-03-09</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="201" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>201</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="201">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>20 Jahre nach der 4. Weltfrauenkonferenz: Schweiz zieht an UNO-Session Bilanz</title>
      <lead>Heute beginnt in New York die 59. Sitzung der Kommission für die Stellung der Frau (CSW) des UNO-Wirtschafts- und Sozialrats (ECOSOC). Im Zentrum steht die so genannte „Beijing Deklaration / Aktionsplattform“, die 1995 anlässlich der 4. Weltfrauenkonferenz in Peking verabschiedet worden war. An der diesjährigen Session wird Bilanz gezogen, ob und wie sich die Stellung der Frauen in der Gesellschaft seither verbessert hat. Die Schweiz als stimmberechtigtes Mitglied dieser UNO-Kommission wird u.a. eine Bilanz ihrer Bemühungen im Inland präsentieren und verschiedene Anlässe veranstalten.</lead>
      <text link="no">Die 59. Sitzung der Kommission für die Stellung der Frau (CSW) – sie dauert vom 9. bis 20. März - steht im Zeichen eines wichtigen Jubiläums: Vor 20 Jahren verabschiedeten 189 Staaten an der 4. Weltfrauenkonferenz zu „Gleichstellung, Entwicklung und Frieden“ die so genannte „Beijing Deklaration“ und eine „Aktionsplattform“ mit dem Ziel, die Gleichstellung von Frau und Mann weltweit voranzubringen. Beschlossen wurden u.a. Massnahmen zur Reduktion von Armut, zur Förderung von Bildung, Gesundheit und zur Besserstellung der Frauen in der Arbeitswelt, aber auch Massnahmen zum Schutz von Frauen und Mädchen vor Gewalt, im häuslichen Umfeld und in bewaffneten Konflikten.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Benno Bättig, Generalsekretär des Eidgenössischen Departements für auswärtige Angelegenheiten EDA, leitet die Schweizer Delegation. Vize-Delegationschefin ist Sylvie Durrer, Direktorin des Eidgenössischen Büros für die Gleichstellung von Frau und Mann im Eidgenössischen Departement des Innern EDI. Der Schweizer Delegation gehören Vertreterinnen und Vertreter der Bundesverwaltung und der Zivilgesellschaft sowie eine Jugenddelegierte des EDA-Jugendprogramms „Youth Rep“ an, ein Projekt der Schweizerischen Arbeitsgemeinschaft der Jugendverbände SAJV in Zusammenarbeit mit dem EDA. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;In den nächsten Tagen wird die Schweiz in der Plenardiskussion der CSW den Stand der nationalen Umsetzung der „Beijing-Aktionsplattform“ präsentieren. Die Broschüre „Gleichstellung von Frau und Mann Aktionsplan der Schweiz, Bilanz 1999 – 2014“ gibt Auskunft darüber. Sie wurde aufgrund einer parlamentarischen Interpellation erstellt. Fortschritte erzielt wurden in der Schweiz vor allem beim straffreien Schwangerschaftsabbruch, beim Mutterschafts-Erwerbsersatz sowie bei der Verhinderung von Zwangsheiraten und Genitalverstümmelungen. Zudem sind die Frauen heute wesentlich zahlreicher an den Hochschulen vertreten. Handlungsbedarf besteht dagegen bei der Vereinbarkeit von Beruf und Familie, der Lohnungleichheit sowie bei der Segregation auf dem Arbeitsmarkt. Weitere Herausforderungen sind die nach wie vor weit verbreitete Gewalt an Frauen, ihre Untervertretung in politischen und wirtschaftlichen Entscheidungspositionen sowie die ungleiche Verteilung von Betreuungsaufgaben. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Die CSW ist das zentrale Organ der UNO, das sich mit der Verbesserung der Gleichstellung der Geschlechter befasst. Sie wurde 1946 gegründet, ihr gehören 45 UNO-Mitgliedstaaten an, die sich einmal im Jahr versammeln, um Herausforderungen und Fortschritte zu evaluieren und konkrete Massnahmen zu formulieren.</text>
      <contact>Kommunikation EDA Bundeshaus West CH-3003 Bern Tel. Kommunikationsservice: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Medienstelle: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <link id="133739">
        <title>Publikation: Bilanz Schweiz 1999 – 2014</title>
        <uri>http://www.ebg.admin.ch/dokumentation/00012/00198/index.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="133740">
        <title>UN Women (en)</title>
        <uri>http://www.unwomen.org/en/</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="133741">
        <title>Women’s Human Rights (en)</title>
        <uri>http://www.womenshumanrights.ch</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="133742">
        <title>SDC-Gender Equality Network (en)</title>
        <uri>https://www.shareweb.ch/site/Gender/en</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="133743">
        <title>Eidg. Büro für die Gleichstellung von Frau und Mann</title>
        <uri>http://www.ebg.admin.ch/index.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Bilan de la Suisse à la 59e session de la CSW vingt ans après la Quatrième Conférence des Nations Unies sur les femmes</title>
      <lead>La 59e session de la Commission de la condition de la femme (CSW) du Conseil économique et social des Nations Unies (ECOSOC) ouvre aujourd’hui à New York. Elle a pour thème principal la déclaration et la plate-forme d’action de Beijing adoptées lors de la Quatrième Conférence des Nations Unies sur les femmes en 1995. Cette session sera l’occasion pour la Commission d’examiner si et en quoi la condition féminine s’est améliorée dans la société depuis cette date. En sa qualité de membre de cette commission de l’ONU avec droit de vote, la Suisse présentera notamment un bilan des efforts entrepris au niveau national et organisera différentes manifestations. </lead>
      <text link="no">La 59e session de la Commission de la condition de la femme, qui se tient du 9 au 20 mars 2015, est placée sous le signe d’un anniversaire important. Il y a tout juste vingt ans en effet, lors de la Quatrième Conférence des Nations Unies sur les femmes consacrée à l'égalité, au développement et à la paix, 189 Etats adoptaient la Déclaration et la Plate-forme d’action de Beijing dans l’objectif de faire progresser l’égalité des sexes. Des mesures avaient été décidées notamment en faveur de la réduction de la pauvreté, de l’éducation, de la santé et du statut des femmes dans le monde du travail mais aussi pour la protection des femmes et des filles contre les violences au domicile et dans les conflits armés.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Benno Bättig, secrétaire général du Département fédéral des affaires étrangères (DFAE) conduit la délégation suisse. La vice-cheffe de la délégation est Sylvie Durrer, directrice du Bureau fédéral de l’égalité entre femmes et hommes (BFEG) au Département fédéral de l’intérieur (DFI). La délégation est également composée de représentants de l’administration fédérale et de la société civile ainsi que d’une représentante des jeunes participant au programme Youth Rep, mis en œuvre conjointement par le Conseil suisse des activités de jeunesse (CSAJ) et le DFAE. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Ces prochains jours, la Suisse présentera, dans le cadre de la séance plénière de haut niveau de la CSW, l’état d’avancement de la mise en œuvre de la Plate-forme d’action de Beijing au plan national. La brochure intitulée « Egalité entre femmes et hommes – Plan d'action de la Suisse – Bilan 1999-2014 », qui a été élaborée en réponse à une interpellation parlementaire, fournit des informations à ce sujet. Des progrès ont été réalisés en Suisse, surtout en ce qui concerne la dépénalisation de l’interruption de grossesse, l’allocation pour perte de gain en cas de maternité et la prévention des mariages forcés et des mutilations génitales. Il est un fait également que les femmes sont aujourd’hui bien plus nombreuses dans les hautes écoles. Des efforts restent à faire en ce qui concerne la conciliation entre vie professionnelle et vie de famille, l’inégalité des salaires et la ségrégation sur le marché de l’emploi. En outre, d’autres problématiques demeurent, telles que les violences à l’égard des femmes, toujours très répandues, la sous-représentation de ces dernières à des postes décisionnaires dans les milieux politique et économique ainsi que l’inégale répartition des tâches domestiques. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;La CSW est l’organe central de l’ONU œuvrant à améliorer la parité entre hommes et femmes. Créée en 1946, elle compte en son sein des représentants et représentantes de 45 Etats membres de l’ONU et tient session une fois par an. A cette occasion, elle procède à une analyse des problématiques et des progrès réalisés et formule des mesures concrètes.</text>
      <contact>Communication DFAE Palais fédéral ouest CH-3003 Berne Tél. Service de communication: +41 58 462 31 53 Tél. Service de presse: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <link id="133744">
        <title>Publication: Plan d'action de la Suisse Bilan 1999-2014</title>
        <uri>http://www.ebg.admin.ch/dokumentation/00012/00198/index.html?lang=fr</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="133745">
        <title>ONU Femmes</title>
        <uri>http://www.unwomen.org/fr/csw/csw58-2014</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="133746">
        <title>Women’s Human Rights (EN)</title>
        <uri>http://www.womenshumanrights.ch</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="133747">
        <title>SDC-Gender Equality Network (EN)</title>
        <uri>https://www.shareweb.ch/site/Gender/en</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="133748">
        <title>Bureau fédéral de l’égalité entre femmes et hommes</title>
        <uri>http://www.ebg.admin.ch/index.html?lang=fr</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>A vent'anni dalla quarta Conferenza mondiale sulle donne, la Svizzera stila un bilancio in occasione della sessione dell'ONU</title>
      <lead>Oggi si apre a New York la 59a sessione della Commissione sulla condizione delle donne (CSW) del Consiglio economico e sociale (ECOSOC). Le discussioni si concentrano quest'anno sulla cosiddetta «Dichiarazione di Pechino/piattaforma d'azione», lanciata a Pechino nel 1995 al termine della quarta Conferenza mondiale delle Nazioni Unite sulle donne. In questa sessione si valuterà anche se e in che modo la posizione delle donne all'interno della società sia migliorata in questi ultimi vent'anni. In qualità di membro con diritto di voto, la Svizzera presenterà tra l'altro un bilancio del suo impegno interno e organizzerà vari eventi.</lead>
      <text link="no">La 59a sessione della Commissione sulla condizione delle donne (CSW) dura dal 9 al 20 marzo 2015 e celebra un importante anniversario: vent'anni fa, infatti, in occasione della quarta Conferenza mondiale sulle donne su «Parità, sviluppo e pace», 189 Stati hanno approvato la cosiddetta «Dichiarazione di Pechino» e lanciato una piattaforma d'azione per promuovere l'uguaglianza tra donne e uomini a livello globale. Sono stati inoltre decisi non solo provvedimenti per ridurre la povertà e per migliorare la formazione, la salute e la posizione delle donne nel mercato del lavoro, ma anche misure per proteggere donne e ragazze dalla violenza, sia nel contesto familiare che durante i conflitti armati.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Benno Bättig, segretario generale del Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri (DFAE), sarà a capo della delegazione svizzera, mentre vicecapo sarà Sylvie Durrer, direttrice dell'Ufficio federale per l'uguaglianza fra donna e uomo presso il Dipartimento federale dell'interno (DFI). La delegazione svizzera è composta anche di rappresentanti dell'Amministrazione federale e della società civile, come pure di una delegata del programma per i giovani «Youth Rep», un progetto lanciato dalla Federazione svizzera delle associazioni giovanili (FSAG) in collaborazione con il DFAE. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Nel quadro della discussione plenaria della CSW dei prossimi giorni, la Svizzera presenterà lo stato di attuazione della «piattaforma d'azione di Pechino» nel nostro Paese. L'opuscolo «Uguaglianza fra donna e uomo - Piano d'azione nazionale - Bilancio 1999-2014», redatto in risposta a un'interpellanza parlamentare, fornisce maggiori informazioni a questo proposito. In Svizzera, i principali traguardi raggiunti sono stati l'interruzione non punibile della gravidanza, l'indennità di perdita di guadagno durante la gravidanza, il divieto dei matrimoni forzati e delle mutilazioni genitali. Inoltre, il numero di donne nelle scuole universitarie è aumentato notevolmente. Occorre per contro ancora migliorare la conciliabilità tra lavoro e famiglia, la parità salariale tra uomo e donna e la segregazione nel mercato del lavoro. Altre sfide da vincere sono le questioni legate alla violenza sulle donne, ancora molto diffusa, la loro sotto rappresentazione nelle posizioni decisionali in politica e nell'economia, nonché la disparità nella distribuzione dei compiti di assistenza. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Fondata nel 1946, la CSW è l'organo principale dell'ONU che si occupa di migliorare la parità tra i sessi; vi fanno parte 45 Stati membri dell'ONU, che si riuniscono una volta all'anno per valutare sfide e progressi e per elaborare misure concrete.</text>
      <contact>Comunicazione DFAE Palazzo federale ovest CH-3003 Berna Tel. Servizio di comunicazione: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Servizio stampa: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <link id="133749">
        <title>Pubblicazione: nazionale Bilancio 1999-2014</title>
        <uri>http://www.ebg.admin.ch/dokumentation/00012/00198/index.html?lang=it</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="133750">
        <title>UN Women (EN)</title>
        <uri>http://www.unwomen.org/en/csw/csw58-2014</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="133751">
        <title>Women’s Human Rights (EN)</title>
        <uri>http://www.womenshumanrights.ch</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="133752">
        <title>SDC-Gender Equality Network (EN)</title>
        <uri>https://www.shareweb.ch/site/Gender/en</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="133753">
        <title>Ufficio federale per l'uguaglianza fra donna e uomo</title>
        <uri>http://www.ebg.admin.ch/index.html?lang=it</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>20 years after the 4th World Conference on Women: Switzerland takes stock at the UN session</title>
      <lead>The 59th session of the Commission on the Status of Women (CSW) of the United Nations Economic and Social Council (ECOSOC) begins today in New York. The main focus of the session is the Beijing Declaration and Platform for Action, which was adopted in 1995 at the 4th World Conference on Women in Beijing. The aim of this year's session of the Commission is to examine if and how the position of women in society has improved since then. As a voting member of the CSW, Switzerland will also present the results of its efforts to improve the status of women in Swiss society and organise a number of events.</lead>
      <text link="no">This year's session of the Commission on the Status of Women, which will run from 9 to 20 March, marks an important anniversary – 20 years ago, 189 states at the 4th World Conference on Women: Action for Equality, Development and Peace adopted the Beijing Declaration and Platform for Action, which aims to advance gender equality throughout the world. The measures decided in Beijing include efforts to alleviate poverty and promote education, health and the position of women in the workplace, and to protect women and girls from violence at home and during armed conflict.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Benno Bättig, Secretary-General of the Federal Department of Foreign Affairs (FDFA), is heading the Swiss delegation. The deputy head of the delegation is Sylvie Durrer, Director of the Swiss Federal Office for Gender Equality at the Federal Department of Home Affairs (FDHA). The Swiss delegation comprises representatives of the Federal Administration and civil society as well as a young female delegate from the FDFA's "Youth Rep" programme, a Swiss National Youth Council (SNYC) project carried out in collaboration with the FDFA. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;During the CSW plenary discussions over the next few days, Switzerland will present the current status of the country's efforts to implement the Beijing Platform for Action. Information on this subject is contained in the brochure entitled "Switzerland's gender equality action plan: results 1999-2014" (available in German and French) which was written following a parliamentary interpellation. In Switzerland, the most significant progress has been made in terms of the decriminalisation of abortion, compensation for loss of earnings during maternity leave, and the prevention of forced marriages and female genital mutilation. There has also been a considerable increase in the number of women attending institutions of higher education. On the other hand, action is still needed to improve work-life balance for women, ensure equal pay and reduce gender-based segregation in the labour market. Additional challenges that continue to impact women are widespread gender-based violence, a lack of representation in political and economic decision-making positions, and the unequal distribution of caring responsibilities. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The CSW is the UN's central body that addresses the issue of improving gender equality. It was established in 1946 and comprises 45 UN member states that meet once a year to assess challenges, measure progress, and formulate concrete measures.</text>
      <contact>FDFA Communication Federal Palace West Wing CH-3003 Bern, Switzerland Tel. Communication service: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Press service: +41 58 460 55 55 E-mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @SwissMFA</contact>
      <link id="133754">
        <title>Publication: Balance Switzerland 1999 – 2014 (de)</title>
        <uri>http://www.ebg.admin.ch/dokumentation/00012/00198/index.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="133755">
        <title>UN Women</title>
        <uri>http://www.unwomen.org/en/csw/csw58-2014</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="133756">
        <title>Women’s Human Rights</title>
        <uri>http://www.womenshumanrights.ch</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="133757">
        <title>SDC-Gender Equality Network</title>
        <uri>https://www.shareweb.ch/site/Gender/en</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="133758">
        <title>Federal Office for Gender Equality</title>
        <uri>http://www.ebg.admin.ch/index.html?lang=en</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
