<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="57946" revoked="no">
    <version>3</version>
    <pubdate>2015-07-01</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="1070" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>1070</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Der Bundesrat</name>
      <name lang="fr">Conseil fédéral</name>
      <name lang="it">Il Consiglio federale</name>
      <name lang="en">The Federal Council</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.admin.ch/gov/de/start.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.admin.ch/gov/fr/accueil.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.admin.ch/gov/it/pagina-iniziale.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.admin.ch/gov/en/start.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="yes" id="1060" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>601</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Staatssekretariat für internationale Finanzfragen</name>
      <name lang="fr">Secrétariat d'Etat aux questions financières internationales</name>
      <name lang="it">Segreteria di Stato per le questioni finanziarie internazionali</name>
      <name lang="en">State Secretariat for International Financial Matters</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.sif.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.sif.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.sif.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.sif.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@sif.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@sif.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@sif.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@sif.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="318" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>301</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Bundesamt für Statistik</name>
      <name lang="fr">Office fédéral de la statistique</name>
      <name lang="it">Ufficio federale di statistica</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Statistical Office</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.statistik.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.statistique.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.statistica.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.statistics.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@bfs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@bfs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@bfs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@bfs.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="1070">
      <name lang="de">Der Bundesrat</name>
      <name lang="fr">Conseil fédéral</name>
      <name lang="it">Il Consiglio federale</name>
      <name lang="en">The Federal Council</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.admin.ch/gov/de/start.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.admin.ch/gov/fr/accueil.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.admin.ch/gov/it/pagina-iniziale.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.admin.ch/gov/en/start.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <department id="601">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Finanzdepartement</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des finances</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale delle finanze</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Finance</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.efd.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.dff.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.efd.admin.ch/efd/it/home.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.efd.admin.ch/efd/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <department id="301">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement des Innern</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'intérieur</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'interno</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Home Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Schweiz übernimmt den neuen IWF-Statistikstandard</title>
      <lead>Der Bundesrat hat an seiner heutigen Sitzung beschlossen, die Umsetzung des neuen Statistikstandards des Internationalen Währungsfonds (IWF) in die Wege zu leiten. Der Standard, der den Empfehlungen der G20 folgt und am 18. November 2014 in Kraft getreten ist, soll statistische Lücken beheben und damit für eine bessere Vorbeugung und Lösung von Wirtschafts- und Finanzkrisen sorgen. Mit der Umsetzung des Standards wird die Reputation der Schweiz hinsichtlich der Integrität, Qualität und Transparenz wichtiger Wirtschafts- und Finanzdaten gewahrt.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Die Arbeiten zur Umsetzung des Standards ab 2020 werden vom Staatssekretariat für internationale Finanzfragen (SIF) koordiniert. Gesetzesänderungen im Statistikbereich sind nicht erforderlich. Die Auswirkungen auf die personellen Ressourcen des Bundes sind begrenzt. Die neuen Statistikdaten werden gemeinsam mit dem Bundesamt für Statistik, der Eidgenössischen Finanzverwaltung, dem Staatssekretariat für Wirtschaft, dem Bundesamt für Sozialversicherungen sowie der Schweizerischen Nationalbank und der FINMA erstellt.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Um den neuen Standard «SDDS Plus» («Special Data Dissemination Standard Plus») zu erfüllen, muss die Schweiz neun zusätzliche Datenkategorien in den Bereichen volks­wirtschaftliche Gesamtrechnung, öffentliche Finanzen, Finanzsektor und Aussenhandel bereit­stellen. In den kommenden Jahren werden bestehende Erhebungen angepasst und ergänzt. Der neue Standard zielt insbesondere auf Länder mit systemrelevantem Finanzsektor ab. Neben zusätzlichen Daten zum Bankensektor und Finanzstabilitätsindikatoren (einschliesslich des Immobilienmarkts) wird die Schweiz Angaben zu Nichtbankeninstituten (Pensionskassen, Versicherungen, übrige Finanzintermediäre) herausgeben&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;SDDS Plus ist eine Weiterentwicklung des bisherigen Standards «SDDS». Der IWF hat seine Statistikstandards aufgrund der Empfehlungen der G20 ergänzt. Die Statistikstandards gehören zu den zwölf vom Financial Stability Board (FSB) anerkannten Standards für den Finanzsektor. Wirtschaftliche Transparenz ist ein Grundanliegen des IWF, der verschiedene Statistikstandards zur Wahrung der Reputation der Länder hinsichtlich der Integrität, Qualität und öffentlichen Zugänglichkeit wichtiger Volkswirtschafts- und Finanzdaten erstellt hat. Aktuell setzen über 90 Prozent der IWF-Mitglieder diese Standards um, darunter seit 1996 auch die Schweiz.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Mario Tuor, Kommunikation Staatssekretariat für internationale Finanzfragen SIF Tel. +41 58 462 46 16, mario.tuor@sif.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="146293">
        <title>IMF Standards for Data Dissemination</title>
        <uri>https://www.imf.org/external/np/exr/facts/data.htm</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions>
        <revision date="2015-07-01 11:30" type="R"/>
      </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>La Suisse reprend la nouvelle norme statistique du FMI</title>
      <lead>Lors de sa séance d’aujourd’hui, le Conseil fédéral a décidé d’entreprendre les travaux de mise en œuvre de la nouvelle norme statistique du Fonds monétaire international (FMI). Conformément aux recommandations du G20, cette norme, entrée en vigueur le 18 novembre 2014, vise à combler un certain nombre de lacunes statistiques en vue d’améliorer la prévention et la résolution des crises économiques et financières. L’application de la norme permet ainsi de préserver la réputation de la Suisse s’agissant de l’intégrité, de la qualité et de la transparence d’importantes données économiques et financières.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Le Secrétariat d'Etat aux questions financières internationales (SFI) coordonne les travaux, en vue d'une application de la norme à partir de 2020. Aucune modification de loi dans le domaine de la statistique n'est nécessaire et les conséquences au niveau des ressources en personnel de la Confédération seront limitées. Les nouvelles données statistiques seront établies conjointement par l'Office fédéral de la statistique, l'Administration fédérale des finances, le Secrétariat d'Etat à l'économie, l'Office fédéral des assurances sociales, ainsi que la Banque nationale suisse et l'Autorité fédérale de surveillance des marchés financiers.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Selon la nouvelle norme, nommée «Norme spéciale de diffusion des données» (Special Data Dissemination Standard, SDDS Plus), la Suisse doit diffuser neuf catégories supplémentaires de données concernant les comptes nationaux, les finances publiques, le secteur financier et le commerce extérieur. Ces prochaines années, les enquêtes seront modifiées et complétées. La norme vise particulièrement les pays ayant un secteur financier d'importance systémique. Outre des données supplémentaires sur le secteur bancaire et des indicateurs de stabilité financière, y compris sur le marché immobilier, la Suisse publiera des informations sur les institutions financières non bancaires (caisses de pension, assurances, autres intermédiaires financiers).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;SDDS Plus est un développement de la norme SDDS appliquée jusqu'à présent. Conformément aux recommandations du G20, le FMI a complété ses normes de diffusion statistique. Celles-ci figurent parmi les douze normes pour le secteur financier reconnues par le Conseil de stabilité financière (CSF). Garantir la transparence économique fait partie des objectifs principaux du FMI, lequel a élaboré plusieurs normes statistiques en vue d'assurer la réputation des pays s'agissant de l'intégrité, de la qualité, ainsi que de l'accès du public aux données macroéconomiques et financières importantes. Actuellement, plus de 90 % des membres du FMI, dont la Suisse depuis 1996, mettent en œuvre les normes du FMI.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Mario Tuor, service de communication du Secrétariat d’Etat aux questions financières internationales SFI tél. +41 58 462 46 16, mario.tuor@sif.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="146294">
        <title>Normes du FMI pour la diffusion des données</title>
        <uri>https://www.imf.org/external/np/exr/facts/fre/dataf.htm</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>La Svizzera adotta il nuovo standard statistico del FMI</title>
      <lead>Nella sua seduta odierna il Consiglio federale ha deciso di procedere all’attuazione del nuovo standard statistico del Fondo monetario internazionale (FMI). Fondato sulle raccomandazioni del G20 ed entrato in vigore il 18 novembre 2014, lo standard intende colmare lacune statistiche e provvedere a una migliore prevenzione e risoluzione delle crisi economiche e finanziarie. L’attuazione dello standard consente di tutelare la reputazione della Svizzera per quanto concerne l’integrità, la qualità e la trasparenza di importanti dati economici e finanziari.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;A partire dal 2020 la Segretaria di Stato per le questioni finanziarie internazionali (SFI) coordinerà i lavori di attuazione dello standard. Non si rendono necessarie modifiche di legge in ambito statistico. Le ripercussioni sul personale della Confederazione sono limitate. I nuovi dati statistici saranno allestiti in collaborazione con l'Ufficio federale di statistica (UST), l'Amministrazione federale delle finanze (AFF), la Segreteria di Stato dell'economia (SECO), l'Ufficio federale delle assicurazioni sociali (UFAS), la Banca nazionale e la FINMA.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Per adempiere il nuovo standard «SDDS Plus» («Special Data Dissemination Standard Plus») la Svizzera deve allestire nuove categorie di dati supplementari in ambito di conto economico nazionale, finanze pubbliche, settore finanziario e commercio esterno. Nei prossimi anni le attuali rilevazioni statistiche saranno adeguate e completate. Il nuovo standard è orientato in particolare a Paesi con un settore finanziario di rilevanza sistemica. Oltre a dati supplementari concernenti il settore bancario e gli indicatori di stabilità finanziaria (compreso il mercato immobiliare), la Svizzera pubblicherà informazioni relative a istituti non bancari (casse pensioni, assicurazioni, altri intermediari finanziari).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;SDDS Plus è il risultato dell'ulteriore sviluppo dello standard «SDDS» finora in vigore. Il FMI ha completato i suoi standard statistici integrando le raccomandazioni del G20. Gli standard statistici fanno parte dei 12 standard riconosciuti dal Financial Stability Board (FSB) per il settore finanziario. La trasparenza economica è un obiettivo fondamentale del FMI, il quale ha elaborato diversi standard statistici volti a tutelare la reputazione dei Paesi sotto il profilo dell'integrità, della qualità e del pubblico accesso a importanti dati economici e finanziari. Attualmente oltre il 90 per cento dei membri del FMI attua questi standard, tra cui dal 1996 rientra anche la Svizzera.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Mario Tuor, Comunicazione, Segreteria di Stato per le questioni finanziarie internazionali SFI tel. +41 58 462 46 16, mario.tuor@sif.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="146294">
        <title>Normes du FMI pour la diffusion des données</title>
        <uri>https://www.imf.org/external/np/exr/facts/fre/dataf.htm</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Switzerland adopts new IMF statistical standard</title>
      <lead>During its meeting today, the Federal Council decided to initiate implementation of the new statistical standard of the International Monetary Fund (IMF). The standard, which follows the G20's recommendations and came into effect on 18 November 2014, is designed to address statistical gaps and thus ensure the improved prevention and resolution of economic and financial crises. By implementing the standard, Switzerland will preserve its reputation in terms of the integrity, quality and transparency of key economic and financial data.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;The State Secretariat for International Financial Matters (SIF) will coordinate the work on implementing the standard from 2020. Legislative amendments are not required in the field of statistics, and the Confederation's human resources will be affected only to a limited extent. The new statistical data will be drawn up together with the Federal Statistical Office, the Federal Finance Administration, the State Secretariat for Economic Affairs, the Federal Social Insurance Office as well as the Swiss National Bank and FINMA.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;To meet the requirements of the new SDDS Plus (Special Data Dissemination Standard Plus), Switzerland must provide nine additional data categories in the areas of national accounts, public finances, financial sector and the external sector. Existing censuses will be adapted and expanded over the next few years. The new standard is aimed in particular at countries with a systemically important financial sector. Aside from additional data on the banking sector and financial stability indicators (including the real estate market), Switzerland will also publish details about non-banking institutions (pension funds, insurers, and other financial intermediaries).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;SDDS Plus constitutes a further development of the previous SDDS standard. The IMF has expanded its statistical standards as a result of the G20's recommendations. The standards are part of the twelve key standards for the financial sector recognised by the Financial Stability Board (FSB). Economic transparency is a fundamental concern of the IMF, and it has drawn up various statistical standards for preserving countries' reputations in terms of integrity, quality and the public accessibility of key economic and financial data. Currently, over 90% of IMF members implement these standards, including Switzerland since 1996.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Mario Tuor, Communications, State Secretariat for International Financial Matters SIF Tel. +41 58 462 46 16, mario.tuor@sif.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="146293">
        <title>IMF Standards for Data Dissemination</title>
        <uri>https://www.imf.org/external/np/exr/facts/data.htm</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <offers>
      <offer id="269" org-id="1060">
        <name lang="de">Internationaler Währungsfonds IWF</name>
        <name lang="fr">Fond monétaire international (FMI)</name>
        <name lang="it">Fondo monetario internazionale</name>
        <name lang="en">International Monetary Fund</name>
      </offer>
      <offer id="291" org-id="1060">
        <name lang="de">Wirtschaft, Währung, Finanzplatz</name>
        <name lang="fr">Economie, monnaie, place financière</name>
        <name lang="it">Economia, Moneta, Piazza finanziaria</name>
        <name lang="en">Economic, Monetary and Financial Affairs</name>
      </offer>
    </offers>
    <keywords>
      <keyword id="118" org-id="1060">
        <name lang="de">Finanzmarktregulierung und -aufsicht</name>
        <name lang="fr">Réglementation et surveillance des marchés financiers</name>
        <name lang="it">Regolamentazione e vigilanza dei mercati finanziari</name>
        <name lang="en">Financial market regulation and supervision</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="126" org-id="1060">
        <name lang="de">Finanzplatz Schweiz</name>
        <name lang="fr">Place financière suisse</name>
        <name lang="it">Piazza finanziaria svizzera</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland as a financial centre</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="123" org-id="1060">
        <name lang="de">IWF und Weltbank</name>
        <name lang="fr">FMI et Banque mondiale</name>
        <name lang="it">FMI e Banca mondiale</name>
        <name lang="en">IMF and World Bank</name>
      </keyword>
    </keywords>
    <topics>
      <topic id="35">
        <name lang="de">Finanzplatz</name>
        <name lang="fr">Place financière</name>
        <name lang="it">Piazza finanziaria</name>
        <name lang="en">Financial Centre</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="44">
        <name lang="de">Steuern</name>
        <name lang="fr">Impôts</name>
        <name lang="it">Imposte</name>
        <name lang="en">Taxation</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="47">
        <name lang="de">Wirtschaft</name>
        <name lang="fr">Économie</name>
        <name lang="it">Economia</name>
        <name lang="en">Economic Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
