<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="57976" revoked="no">
    <version>3</version>
    <pubdate>2015-07-01</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="201" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>201</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="201">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Die Schweiz begrüsst die Wiedereröffnung der Botschaften in Havanna und Washington</title>
      <lead>Die Schweiz beglückwünscht Kuba und die USA zur geplanten Wiedereröffnung der kubanischen Botschaft in Washington und der US-Botschaft in Havanna. Dieser Schritt stellt einen wichtigen Meilenstein auf dem Weg der Normalisierung der Beziehungen zwischen Kuba und den USA dar. Mit der Wiedereröffnung der Botschaften gehen auch die Schutzmachtmandate zu Ende, welche die Schweiz seit 1961 für die USA in Kuba und seit 1991 für Kuba in den USA wahrnahm.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Die Schweiz ist überzeugt, dass die Wiedereröffnung der beiden Botschaften und der Normalisierungsprozess insgesamt für beide Seiten nutzbringend sind und zu Sicherheit, Stabilität und Prosperität in der Region beitragen. Wenn sich die Beziehungen zwischen Kuba und den USA normalisieren, ist dies aus Schweizer Sicht sehr positiv – nicht nur für die beiden Länder, sondern auch für die ganze Region und für die Stabilität der Welt.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Für die Schweiz ist die Rolle als Schutzmacht ein Teil der traditionellen Guten Dienste und ihrer verantwortungsvollen Aussenpolitik. Sie hat mit ihrem langjährigen Kuba/USA-Mandat auch einen Beitrag an die Annäherung zwischen den beiden Ländern geleistet. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Das Ende der Mandate tangiert die bilateralen Beziehungen der Schweiz zu den USA beziehungsweise zu Kuba nicht. Der Goodwill und die Wertschätzung für ihre Mandatstätigkeit, die für Zuverlässigkeit und Glaubwürdigkeit steht, werden der Schweiz erhalten bleiben. In einem Brief von Anfang Januar 2015 an Bundesrat Didier Burkhalter gab US-Aussenminister John Kerry seiner «tiefen Dankbarkeit» für die Schweizer Bemühungen und den Einsatz als Schutzmacht der USA in Kuba Ausdruck. Das Engagement der Schweizer Bevölkerung für die Annäherung zwischen den beiden Staaten namentlich während der Zeit des Kalten Krieges sei «eine Inspiration für uns alle und ein Beispiel für geduldiges Wirken im Dienst des Friedens».&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Zwischen 1961 und 1977 war das Schweizer Mandat für die USA - stark geprägt durch die Kubakrise 1962 - intensiv und umfassend. 1977 vereinbarten die USA und Kuba die Eröffnung von Sektionen zur Wahrung der Interessen in der jeweils anderen Hauptstadt. Die amerikanische Interessensektion stand weiterhin unter dem Schutz der Schweizer Botschaft in Havanna. 1991 wurde die kubanische Interessensektion der Schweizer Botschaft in Washington angegliedert. Seit 1977 war das Doppelmandat der Schweiz primär formeller Natur.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Die Schweizer Schutzmachtmandate in Havanna und in Washington sind (nach 1977) nicht vergleichbar mit dem viel umfassenderen Schutzmachtmandat der Schweiz für die USA im Iran. Dort ist die Schweiz viel stärker und direkter involviert. Das Iran-Mandat wird wie bisher weitergeführt.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Kommunikation EDA Bundeshaus West CH-3003 Bern Tel. Kommunikationsservice: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Medienstelle: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <link id="138754">
        <title>EDA – Schutzmachtmandate</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home/aussenpolitik/menschenrechte-menschliche-sicherheit/frieden/schutzmachtmandate.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="138755">
        <title>Studie zum Schweizer Schutzmachtmandat für die USA in Kuba 1961-1977 (en)</title>
        <uri>http://graduateinstitute.ch/files/live/sites/iheid/files/sites/international_history_politics/shared/working_papers/WPIHP-Fischer.pdf</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions>
        <revision date="2015-07-01 17:52" type="R"/>
        <revision date="2015-07-06 15:16" type="R"/>
      </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>La Suisse salue la réouverture des ambassades à La Havane et à Washington</title>
      <lead>La Suisse félicite Cuba et les Etats-Unis pour la réouverture prévue de l'ambassade de Cuba à Washington et de l'ambassade des Etats-Unis à La Havane. Il s'agit-là d'une étape importante vers la normalisation des relations entre Cuba et les Etats-Unis. La réouverture des ambassades met ainsi fin aux mandats de puissance protectrice que la Suisse a exercés depuis 1961 pour les Etats-Unis à Cuba et depuis 1991 pour Cuba aux Etats-Unis.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;La Suisse est convaincue que la réouverture des deux ambassades et le processus de normalisation seront globalement bénéfiques aux deux parties et contribueront à la sécurité, la stabilité et la prospérité dans la région. La Suisse considère la normalisation des relations entre Cuba et les Etats-Unis comme très positive, non seulement pour les deux pays, mais également pour l'ensemble de la région et pour la stabilité dans le monde.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Le rôle de puissance protectrice fait partie des bons offices traditionnels de la Suisse et s'inscrit dans une politique extérieure responsable. Le mandat de puissance protectrice qu'elle a exercé pendant des années pour Cuba et les Etats-Unis a également contribué au rapprochement entre les deux pays. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;La fin des mandats n'aura aucun effet sur les relations bilatérales de la Suisse avec les Etats-Unis et Cuba. Synonymes de fiabilité et de crédibilité, ses bons offices ont valu à la Suisse l’estime et la bonne volonté durables de Cuba et des Etats-Unis. Dans une lettre adressée au conseiller fédéral Didier Burkhalter, datant de début janvier 2015, le ministre américain des affaires étrangères, John Kerry, a exprimé sa profonde reconnaissance à la Suisse pour les efforts qu'elle a fournis et son action en tant que puissance protectrice aux Etats-Unis et à Cuba. Le chef de la diplomatie américaine a salué l'engagement de la population suisse pour le rapprochement entre les deux Etats, notamment pendant la Guerre froide, et l'a qualifié d'inspiration pour tous et d'exemple d'efforts patients au service de la paix.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Entre 1961 et 1977, le mandat de la Suisse pour les USA, fortement marqué par la crise de Cuba en 1962, a été très large et a exigé des efforts intenses. En 1977, les USA et Cuba se sont entendus sur l’ouverture de sections de défense des intérêts dans leurs capitales. Celle des intérêts américains fonctionnait sous protection de l’ambassade de Suisse à La Havane. En 1991, la section des intérêts cubains a été rattachée à l’ambassade de Suisse à Washington. Depuis 1977, le double mandat de la Suisse a principalement été de nature formelle. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Dans les années qui ont suivi, le mandat de puissance protectrice de la Suisse à La Havane et Washington n'a plus été comparable avec celui, bien plus conséquent, que la Suisse exerce pour les Etats-Unis en Iran, où son implication est plus profonde et plus directe. Le mandat iranien se poursuivra sans changement.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Communication DFAE Palais fédéral ouest CH-3003 Berne Tél. Service de communication: +41 58 462 31 53 Tél. Service de presse: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <link id="138756">
        <title>Mandats de puissance protectrice du DFAE</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/home/aussenpolitik/menschenrechte-menschliche-sicherheit/frieden/schutzmachtmandate.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="138757">
        <title>Etude sur le mandat de puissance protectrice exercé par la Suisse pour les Etats-Unis à Cuba entre 1961 et 1977 (en)</title>
        <uri>http://graduateinstitute.ch/files/live/sites/iheid/files/sites/international_history_politics/shared/working_papers/WPIHP-Fischer.pdf</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions>
        <revision date="2015-07-01 17:52" type="R"/>
        <revision date="2015-07-06 15:16" type="R"/>
      </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>La Svizzera si compiace della riapertura delle ambasciate a l’Avana e Washington</title>
      <lead>La Svizzera si congratula con Cuba e gli Stati Uniti per la riapertura prevista dell’Ambasciata di Cuba a Washington e dell’Ambasciata degli Stati Uniti a l’Avana. Questo avvenimento segna un importante traguardo sulla via della normalizzazione delle relazioni tra Cuba e gli Stati Uniti. Con la riapertura delle due ambasciate cessano anche i mandati in qualità di potenza protettrice che la Svizzera aveva assunto dal 1961 in rappresentanza degli Stati Uniti a Cuba e dal 1991 in rappresentanza di Cuba negli Stati Uniti.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;La Svizzera è persuasa che la riapertura delle due ambasciate e il processo di normalizzazione porteranno, nel complesso, benefici a entrambe le Parti, contribuendo a rafforzare la sicurezza, la stabilità e la prosperità nella regione. La Svizzera ritiene che la normalizzazione delle relazioni tra Cuba e gli Stati Uniti sia estremamente positiva non soltanto per i due Stati interessati, ma per l’intera area e per la stabilità mondiale.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Il ruolo di potenza protettrice assunto dalla Svizzera rientra nella sua tradizione dei buoni uffici e di una politica estera responsabile. Inoltre, con il suo mandato pluriennale Cuba/Stati Uniti ha dato un contributo all’avvicinamento dei due Paesi.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;La fine dei mandati non ha un impatto sulle relazioni bilaterali della Svizzera con gli Stati Uniti e con Cuba. La Svizzera continuerà a essere apprezzata per il goodwill di cui gode e per l’attività svolta nell’ambito del suo mandato, riconosciuta come affidabile e credibile. In una lettera inviata al consigliere federale Didier Burkhalter a inizio gennaio 2015, il ministro degli esteri statunitense John Kerry ha espresso «profonda gratitudine» per gli sforzi profusi dalla Svizzera e per il suo intervento in veste di potenza protettrice degli interessi degli Stati Uniti a Cuba. L’impegno della popolazione svizzera per un avvicinamento tra i due Stati, in particolare durante la guerra fredda, è «di ispirazione per tutti noi nonché esempio di azione paziente in favore della pace».&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Tra il 1961 e il 1977 il mandato della Svizzera per gli USA è stato intenso e globale, ed è stato marcato non da ultimo dalla crisi di Cuba nel 1962. Nel 1977 gli USA e Cuba si sono accordati sull’apertura di sezioni a tutela degli interessi nelle rispettive capitali. La sezione a tutela degli interessi americani funzionava sotto la protezione dell’Ambasciata di Svizzera a l’Avana. Nel 1991, la sezione a tutela degli interessi cubani è stata aggregata all’Ambasciata di Svizzera a Washington. Dal 1977 il doppio mandato della Svizzera è stato di natura prevalentemente formale. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I mandati in qualità di potenza protettrice assunti dalla Svizzera a l’Avana e a Washington dopo il 1977 non sono paragonabili con il mandato di potenza protettrice che la Svizzera ha assunto per gli Stati Uniti in Iran, che è molto più esteso. Il coinvolgimento della Svizzera in Iran è molto più forte e diretto. Il mandato in Iran prosegue come in passato. &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Comunicazione DFAE Palazzo federale ovest CH-3003 Berna Tel. Servizio di comunicazione: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Servizio stampa: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <link id="138758">
        <title>DFAE – Mandati in qualità di potenza protettrice</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/home/aussenpolitik/menschenrechte-menschliche-sicherheit/frieden/schutzmachtmandate.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="138759">
        <title>Studio sul mandato di potenza protettrice assunto dalla Svizzera in rappresentanza degli interessi degli Stati Uniti a Cuba 1961-1977 (en)</title>
        <uri>http://graduateinstitute.ch/files/live/sites/iheid/files/sites/international_history_politics/shared/working_papers/WPIHP-Fischer.pdf</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions>
        <revision date="2015-07-01 17:52" type="R"/>
        <revision date="2015-07-06 15:16" type="R"/>
      </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Switzerland welcomes the reopening of the embassies in Havana and Washington</title>
      <lead>Switzerland congratulates Cuba and the United States on their plans to reopen the Cuban embassy in Washington and the US embassy in Havana. This step marks an important milestone towards normalising relations between Cuba and the United States. The reopening of the embassies also brings to an end the protecting power mandates that Switzerland has carried out since 1961 for the United States in Cuba and, since 1991, for Cuba in the United States.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Switzerland strongly believes that the reopening of the two embassies and the normalisation process will overall be beneficial for the two states and contribute to security, stability and prosperity in the region. Switzerland views the normalisation of relations between Cuba and the US as very positive – not only for these two countries but for the whole region and for world stability.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;For Switzerland the role of protecting power is part of the traditional good offices it offers within the scope of a responsible foreign policy. With its long-standing Cuba-US mandate, Switzerland has also contributed to rapprochement between the two countries. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The end of the mandate will have no impact on Switzerland's bilateral relations with the US and with Cuba. The goodwill towards Switzerland and the appreciation of its commitment in fulfilling its mandate, which was characterised by reliability and credibility, will remain. In a letter to Federal Councillor Didier Burkhalter at the beginning of January 2015, the United States secretary of state, John Kerry, expressed his "deep gratitude" for Switzerland's efforts and its commitment as protecting power for the United States in Cuba. The dedication of the people of Switzerland to rapprochement between the two states, especially during the Cold War, was "an inspiration to us all and a monument to patience in the service of peace".&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Between 1961 and 1977 the Swiss mandate for the United States, which was marked in particular by the 1962 Cuban Crisis, was in-depth and comprehensive. In 1977, the United States and Cuba agreed to open up foreign interests' sections in each other's capital. The US foreign interests' section operated under the protection of the Swiss embassy in Havana. In 1991, the Cuban foreign interests' section was attached to the Swiss embassy in Washington. Since 1977, Switzerland’s double mandate has been primarily of a formal nature.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The Swiss protecting power mandates in Havana and Washington cannot (after 1977) be compared with Switzerland's far more comprehensive protecting power mandate for the United States in Iran, where Switzerland is much more closely and directly involved. The Iran mandate will continue as before.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>FDFA Communication Federal Palace West Wing CH-3003 Bern, Switzerland Tel. Communication service: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Press service: +41 58 460 55 55 E-mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @SwissMFA</contact>
      <link id="138760">
        <title>FDFA – Protecting power mandates</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home/aussenpolitik/menschenrechte-menschliche-sicherheit/frieden/schutzmachtmandate.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="138761">
        <title>Study on Switzerland's mandate to represent United States interests in Cuba (1961-1977)</title>
        <uri>http://graduateinstitute.ch/files/live/sites/iheid/files/sites/international_history_politics/shared/working_papers/WPIHP-Fischer.pdf</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions>
        <revision date="2015-07-01 17:52" type="R"/>
        <revision date="2015-07-06 15:16" type="R"/>
      </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
