<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="59350" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2015-11-05</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="yes" id="502" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>501</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Generalsekretariat VBS</name>
      <name lang="fr">Secrétariat général du DDPS</name>
      <name lang="it">Segreteria generale del DDPS</name>
      <name lang="en">General Secretariat DDPS</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.vbs.admin.ch/</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.vbs.admin.ch/</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.vbs.admin.ch/</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.vbs.admin.ch/</www>
      <email lang="de">postmaster.vbs@gs-vbs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">postmaster.vbs@gs-vbs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">postmaster.vbs@gs-vbs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">postmaster.vbs@gs-vbs.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="yes" id="507" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>501</department-id>
      <name lang="de">BABS - Bundesamt für Bevölkerungsschutz</name>
      <name lang="fr">OFPP - Office fédéral de la protection de la population</name>
      <name lang="it">UFPP - Ufficio federale della protezione della popolazione</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Office for Civil Protection</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.bevoelkerungsschutz.admin.ch/</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.bevoelkerungsschutz.admin.ch/</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.bevoelkerungsschutz.admin.ch/</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.bevoelkerungsschutz.admin.ch/</www>
      <email lang="de">info@babs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@babs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@babs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@babs.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="501">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Verteidigung, Bevölkerungsschutz und Sport</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de la défense, de la protection de la population et des sports</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale della difesa, della protezione della popolazione e dello sport</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Defence, Civil Protection and Sports DDPS</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.vbs.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.vbs.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.vbs.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.vbs.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@gs-vbs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@gs-vbs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@gs-vbs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@gs-vbs.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Biologische Spitzenlabors für die Vereinten Nationen</title>
      <lead>Die UNO hat die Mitgliedstaaten aufgefordert, Analyselabors zu bestimmen, welche die Überprüfung mutmasslicher Einsätze chemischer und biologischer Waffen unterstützen können. Vom 9. bis 11. November 2015 werden im Rahmen eines vom Labor Spiez organisierten internationalen Workshops die erforderlichen Massnahmen erörtert, um ein globales Netzwerk von Analyselabors auf dem Gebiet der biologischen Waffen einzurichten.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Auf Antrag eines UNO-Mitglieds ist der UNO-Generalsekretär autorisiert, Untersuchungen über einen vermuteten Einsatz chemischer und biologischer Waffen einzuleiten, wie etwa 2013 im Fall der Giftgaseinsätze in Syrien. Dieser so genannte United Nations Secretary-General’s Mechanism (UNSGM) stützt sich im Kern auf eine Liste von Experten und spezialisierten Labors, die von den Mitgliedstaaten bereitgestellt werden.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Defizite bei der Überwachung des B-Waffen-Verbots&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Für ihre Erkundungsmission in Syrien stützte sich die UNO auf das Labornetzwerk der Organisation für das Verbot chemischer Waffen (OPCW). Die designierten Labors der OPCW – darunter auch das Labor Spiez im Bundesamt für Bevölkerungsschutz BABS – sind international akkreditiert und werden jedes Jahr strengen Qualitätskontrollen unterzogen. Seit dem Inkrafttreten des Chemiewaffenübereinkommens 1997 haben diese Labors ihre Analyseverfahren validiert und Kriterien für die Meldung der Analyseergebnisse zur Identifizierung genau festgehalten. Aufgrund dieser strengen und unbestrittenen Qualitätskontrollen wurden die Ergebnisse der UNO-Erkundungsmission in Syrien auch politisch und wissenschaftlich uneingeschränkt akzeptiert. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Im Gegensatz zu den strengen Qualitätsstandards auf dem Gebiet der chemischen Waffen fehlen entsprechende Kontrollen im biologischen Bereich. Bei einer UNO-Mission zur Abklärung eines möglichen Einsatzes biologischer Waffen ist daher die Akzeptanz der Analyseergebnisse der beauftragten Labors nicht sichergestellt. Damit die Labors im Bereich der biologischen Waffen uneingeschränkt anerkannt werden, müssen sie dieselben hohen Anforderungen erfüllen wie im Bereich der chemischen Waffen.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Im Hinblick darauf startet das Labor Spiez vom 9. bis 11. November 2015 eine internationale Konferenzreihe, welche sich mit den Anforderungen an die Qualitätssicherung und Berichterstattung der Labors beschäftigt, mit dem Ziel, dass in Zukunft potenzielle Erkundungsmissionen der UNO auch im biologischen Bereich von Politik und Wissenschaft uneingeschränkt anerkannt werden.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Die Konferenz wird vom Bundesamt für Bevölkerungsschutz BABS (Labor Spiez) zusammen mit dem Eidgenössischen Departement für Auswärtige Angelegenheiten (EDA) und dem Armeestab Internationale Beziehungen (IB V) organisiert.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Andreas Bucher Information Labor Spiez 058 468 15 98</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Laboratoires biologiques de pointe pour les Nations Unies</title>
      <lead>L’ONU demande aux Etats membres de désigner des laboratoires chargés d’analyser des échantillons dans le cadre des enquêtes sur l’emploi présumé d’armes chimiques ou biologiques menées par le United Nations Secretary-General’s Mechanism (UNSGM). Le Laboratoire Spiez organise du 9 au 11 novembre 2015 un atelier international qui débattra des mesures nécessaires pour mettre en place un réseau mondial opérationnel de laboratoires d’analyse dans le domaine des armes biologiques. Afin d’être reconnu sans restriction, un tel réseau doit satisfaire à des exigences sévères, comme c’est déjà le cas dans le domaine chimique. </lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;A la demande d’un membre de l’ONU, le secrétaire général de l’organisation est autorisé à ouvrir une enquête sur un usage présumé d’armes biologiques ou chimiques, comme ce fut le cas en 2013 lors de l’emploi de gaz toxiques en Syrie. Ce processus appelé « mécanisme du secrétaire général des Nations Unies », se fonde sur une liste d’experts et de laboratoires spécialisés mis à disposition par les Etats membres.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;La mission de reconnaissance de l’ONU en Syrie a recouru au réseau de laboratoires de l’Organisation pour l’interdiction des armes chimiques (OIAC). Les laboratoires désignés par l’OIAC, dont fait partie le Laboratoire Spiez, bénéficient d’une accréditation internationale et sont soumis annuellement à des contrôles de qualité draconiens. Depuis l’entrée en vigueur de la Convention sur les armes chimiques, en 1997, ils ont validé des méthodes d’analyse et ont mis au point des critères pour la communication des résultats de l’identification de toxiques chimiques de combat et d’agents similaires. Les résultats des analyses réalisées suite à la mission en Syrie ont d’ailleurs été reconnus sans réserve par les scientifiques et les politiques.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Une qualité équivalente fondée sur des standards fait cependant défaut à l’heure actuelle dans le domaine biologique. Si l’UNSGM ouvrait aujourd’hui une enquête sur l’usage d’armes biologiques, les analyses des laboratoires pourraient être remises en question, voire rejetées. C’est pour combler cette lacune que la Laboratoire Spiez donne le coup d’envoi, du 9 au 11 novembre 2015, d’une série de conférences internationales dédiées aux exigences relatives à l’assurance qualité et à l’établissement des rapports d’analyse, dont le but est d’obtenir la pleine reconnaissance des milieux politiques et scientifiques afin d’appuyer les Nations Unies lors d’investigations sur des emplois présumés d’armes biologiques. &lt;br /&gt;La conférence est organisée par l’Office fédéral de la protection de la population OFPP (Laboratoire Spiez) en coopération avec le Département fédéral des affaires étrangères DFAE et l’Etat-major de l’Armée Relations Internationales.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Andreas Bucher Information Laboratoire Spiez 058 468 15 98</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Laboratori biologici d'eccellenza per le Nazioni Unite</title>
      <lead>L'ONU ha invitato gli Stati membri a designare dei laboratori d'analisi a sostegno del Meccanismo del Segretario Generale delle Nazioni Unite (United Nations Secretary-General’s Mechanism, UNSGM) per la verifica del presunto uso di armi chimiche e biologiche. Un workshop internazionale organizzato dal 9 all'11 novembre 2015 dal Laboratorio Spiez discuterà i passi necessari per creare una rete globale e funzionale di laboratori d'analisi nel campo delle armi biologiche, in grado di conquistare il pieno consenso e di soddisfare i severi requisiti già richiesti in campo chimico.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Su richiesta di un membro, il Segretario generale dell'ONU è autorizzato ad avviare delle indagini relative a un presunto uso di armi chimiche e biologiche, come il probabile uso di gas tossici nel 2013 in Siria. Questo cosiddetto meccanismo del Segretario generale delle Nazioni Unite si basa essenzialmente su un elenco di esperti e di laboratori specializzati allestito dagli Stati membri.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Per la sua missione d’inchiesta in Siria, l'ONU ha fatto ricorso alla rete dei laboratori designati dall'Organizzazione per la proibizione delle armi chimiche (OPAC), fra cui figura anche il Laboratorio Spiez. Questi laboratori sono accreditati a livello internazionale e sottoposti annualmente a severi controlli di qualità. Dall'entrata in vigore della Convenzione sulle armi chimiche (CAC) nel 1997, questi laboratori hanno convalidato metodi analitici e determinato con precisione i criteri per il reporting dei risultati analitici per l'identificazione di aggressivi chimici. Sulla base di questi controlli di qualità severi e incontestati, i risultati riportati dalla missione d'inchiesta dell'ONU in Siria hanno conquistato il pieno consenso politico e scientifico.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mentre per le armi chimiche esistono degli standard di qualità rigorosi, i rispettivi controlli mancano in campo biologico. Le analisi di laboratorio relative a una missione ONU per accertare un possibile uso di armi biologiche, potrebbero quindi essere messe in discussione o addirittura non essere riconosciute. Per ovviare a questa mancanza, dal 9 all'11 novembre 2015 il Laboratorio Spiez inizia una serie di conferenze internazionali per trattare i requisiti concernenti la garanzia della qualità e la stesura dei rapporti dei laboratori con l'obiettivo di ottenere, anche in campo biologico, il pieno consenso politico e scientifico delle eventuali future missioni d'inchiesta.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Andreas Bucher Informazione Laboratorio Spiez 058 468 15 98</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Leading biological laboratories for the United Nations</title>
      <lead>The UN has invited member states to designate analytical laboratories that are able to support an investigation of alleged use of chemical or biological weapons in accordance with the United Nations Secretary-General’s Mechanism (UNSGM). An international workshop from 9 to 11 November 2015, organised by Spiez Laboratory, will discuss the necessary steps to establish a global and functional network of analytical laboratories for biological weapons. To gain full acceptance, such a network must meet similarly stringent requirements as are existing for analytical laboratories for chemical weapons.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;At the request of a UN member the UN Secretary-General is authorised to carry out investigations of alleged use of chemical and biological weapons, as was the case in 2013 when poison gas was used in Syria. The United Nations Secretary-General’s Mechanism draws upon a list of experts and specialised laboratories that are nominated by the member states.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;For their fact-finding mission in Syria the UN relied on the laboratory network of the Organisation for the Prohibition of Chemical Weapons (OPCW). These designated OPCW laboratories – including Spiez Laboratory – are internationally accredited and are subjected to stringent quality controls every year. Since the Chemical Weapons Convention entered into force in 1997, these laboratories have validated their analytical procedures and have meticulously laid down how analytical results must be reported for identification. Due to such a strict and undisputed quality control system, the results of the UN fact-finding mission in Syria were accepted both politically and scientifically without any objections.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Contrary to the stringent quality standards that apply to chemical warfare agents, there are no equivalent quality controls for the biological sector. In the event of a UN fact-finding mission to investigate the alleged use of biological weapons, laboratory results might therefore be pulled into question or even rejected. Spiez Laboratory is therefore conducting the first of a series of international workshops, that will focus on quality assurance and reporting requirements for laboratories. The goal is to establish a system that ensures full political and scientific acceptance of laboratory results, also in the biological field, of future UN fact-finding missions.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The workshop is organized by the Federal Office for Civil Protection FOCP (Spiez Laboratory), in cooperation with the Federal Department of Foreign Affairs FDFA and the Staff of the Armed Forces - International Relations.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Andreas Bucher Information Spiez Laboratory 058 468 15 98</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <keywords>
      <keyword id="506" org-id="507">
        <name lang="de">Kooperation</name>
        <name lang="fr">Coopération</name>
        <name lang="it">Cooperazione</name>
        <name lang="en">Cooperation</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="5200" org-id="507">
        <name lang="de">ABC-Massnahmen / Kampfstoffe</name>
        <name lang="fr">Mesures ABC / armes ABC</name>
        <name lang="it">Misure NBC / aggressivi NBC</name>
        <name lang="en">NBC Measures / Agents</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="5360" org-id="507">
        <name lang="de">Technologie / Wissenschaft / Forschung</name>
        <name lang="fr">Technologies / Sciences / Recherche</name>
        <name lang="it">Tecnologia / Scienza / Ricerca</name>
        <name lang="en">Technology / Science / Research</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="5380" org-id="507">
        <name lang="de">Bevölkerungsschutz</name>
        <name lang="fr">Protection de la population</name>
        <name lang="it">Protezione della popolazione</name>
        <name lang="en">civil protection</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="5440" org-id="507">
        <name lang="de">Veranstaltung</name>
        <name lang="fr">Manifestation</name>
        <name lang="it">Manifestazione</name>
        <name lang="en">Event</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="5610" org-id="507">
        <name lang="de">Entwicklung / Planung / Reform</name>
        <name lang="fr">Développement / Planification / Réforme</name>
        <name lang="it">Sviluppo / Pianificazione / Riforma</name>
        <name lang="en">development / planning / reform</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="5930" org-id="507">
        <name lang="de">Internationale Beziehungen</name>
        <name lang="fr">Relations internationales</name>
        <name lang="it">Relazioni internazionali</name>
        <name lang="en">international relations</name>
      </keyword>
    </keywords>
    <topics>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="40">
        <name lang="de">Sicherheit</name>
        <name lang="fr">Sécurité</name>
        <name lang="it">Sicurezza</name>
        <name lang="en">Security</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="45">
        <name lang="de">Technologie</name>
        <name lang="fr">Technologie</name>
        <name lang="it">Tecnologia</name>
        <name lang="en">Technology</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
