<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="59399" revoked="no">
    <version>2</version>
    <pubdate>2015-11-11</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="1070" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>1070</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Der Bundesrat</name>
      <name lang="fr">Conseil fédéral</name>
      <name lang="it">Il Consiglio federale</name>
      <name lang="en">The Federal Council</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.admin.ch/gov/de/start.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.admin.ch/gov/fr/accueil.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.admin.ch/gov/it/pagina-iniziale.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.admin.ch/gov/en/start.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="yes" id="1060" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>601</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Staatssekretariat für internationale Finanzfragen</name>
      <name lang="fr">Secrétariat d'Etat aux questions financières internationales</name>
      <name lang="it">Segreteria di Stato per le questioni finanziarie internazionali</name>
      <name lang="en">State Secretariat for International Financial Matters</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.sif.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.sif.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.sif.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.sif.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@sif.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@sif.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@sif.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@sif.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="yes" id="605" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>601</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössische Steuerverwaltung</name>
      <name lang="fr">Administration fédérale des contributions</name>
      <name lang="it">Amministrazione federale delle contribuzioni</name>
      <name lang="en">The Federal Tax Administration</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.estv.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.estv.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.estv.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.estv.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de"/>
      <email lang="fr"/>
      <email lang="it"/>
      <email lang="en"/>
    </originator>
    <department id="1070">
      <name lang="de">Der Bundesrat</name>
      <name lang="fr">Conseil fédéral</name>
      <name lang="it">Il Consiglio federale</name>
      <name lang="en">The Federal Council</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.admin.ch/gov/de/start.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.admin.ch/gov/fr/accueil.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.admin.ch/gov/it/pagina-iniziale.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.admin.ch/gov/en/start.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <department id="601">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Finanzdepartement</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des finances</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale delle finanze</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Finance</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.efd.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.dff.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.efd.admin.ch/efd/it/home.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.efd.admin.ch/efd/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Steueramtshilfe: Verordnung präzisiert die Einzelheiten der Kostenauferlegung</title>
      <lead>Der Bundesrat hat an seiner heutigen Sitzung eine Revision der Steueramtshilfeverordnung beschlossen. Die neue Bestimmung präzisiert die im Gesetz vorgesehene Möglichkeit, die Kosten der internationalen Amtshilfe auf die betroffene Person oder das Finanzinstitut abzuwälzen. </lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Die neue Bestimmung in der Steueramtshilfeverordnung tritt am 1. Januar 2016 in Kraft. Die Eidgenössische Steuerverwaltung kann nach dem Steueramtshilfegesetz Kosten überwälzen, wenn diese einen ausserordentlichen Umfang erreichen und die betroffene Person oder der Informationsinhaber durch eigenes Fehlverhalten wesentlich zur Entstehung der Kosten beigetragen hat. Die neue Bestimmung der Steueramtshilfeverordnung umschreibt, wann ein ausserordentlicher Umfang gegeben ist, und führt die Bestandteile auf, aus denen sich die auferlegbaren Kosten zusammensetzen.&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Anne Césard, Kommunikation Staatssekretariat für internationale Finanzfragen SIF Tel. +41 58 462 62 91, anne.cesard@sif.admin.ch</contact>
      <attachment id="143128">
        <title>Verordnung über die internationale Amtshilfe in Steuersachen</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>23</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/41696.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Assistance administrative en matière fiscale: l’ordonnance précise les modalités de l’imputation des frais</title>
      <lead>Lors de sa séance d’aujourd’hui, le Conseil fédéral a adopté une révision de l’ordonnance sur l’assistance administrative fiscale. La nouvelle disposition précise la possibilité, prévue par la loi, de facturer les frais occasionnés par l’assistance administrative internationale aux personnes concernées ou aux établissements financiers. </lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;La nouvelle disposition de l’ordonnance sur l’assistance administrative fiscale entre en vigueur le 1er janvier 2016. En vertu de la loi sur l’assistance administrative fiscale, l’Administration fédérale des contributions peut facturer les frais engendrés par l’échange de renseignements à la personne concernée ou au détenteur des renseignements, lorsque ces frais atteignent une ampleur exceptionnelle et lorsque le comportement inapproprié de la personne concernée ou du détenteur des renseignements a notablement contribué à engendrer ces frais. La nouvelle disposition de l’ordonnance sur l’assistance administrative fiscale définit les critères applicables pour déterminer quand l’ampleur des frais est considérée comme exceptionnelle et énumère les éléments qui composent les frais pouvant être imputés. &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Anne Césard, Communication du Secrétariat d’Etat aux questions financières internationales SFI Tél. +41 58 462 62 91, anne.césard@sif.admin.ch</contact>
      <attachment id="143129">
        <title>Ordonnance sur l’assistance administrative internationale en matière fiscale</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>24</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/41697.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Assistenza amministrativa fiscale: l’ordinanza precisa i dettagli dell’addossamento delle spese</title>
      <lead>In occasione della sua seduta odierna il Consiglio federale ha decretato una revisione dell’ordinanza sull’assistenza amministrativa fiscale. La nuova disposizione precisa la possibilità prevista dalla legge di addossare le spese dell’assistenza amministrativa internazionale alla persona interessata o all’istituto finanziario. </lead>
      <text link="no">La nuova disposizione dell’ordinanza sull’assistenza amministrativa fiscale (OAAF) entrerà in vigore il 1° gennaio 2016. Secondo la legge sull’assistenza amministrativa fiscale, l’Amministrazione federale delle contribuzioni (AFC) può addossare alla persona interessata o al detentore delle informazioni le spese sostenute se esse raggiungono un importo eccezionale e se con il suo comportamento inadeguato la persona interessata o il detentore delle informazioni ha contribuito in maniera determinante all'insorgere delle spese. La nuova disposizione dell’OAAF definisce le spese di importo eccezionale ed elenca le componenti delle spese che possono essere addossate.</text>
      <contact>Anne Césard, Comunicazione, Segreteria di Stato per le questioni finanziarie internazionali SFI Tel. +41 58 462 62 91, anne.cesard@sif.admin.ch</contact>
      <attachment id="143130">
        <title>Ordinanza sull’assistenza amministrativa internazionale in materia fiscale</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>23</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/41698.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Tax administrative assistance: detailed rules on costs established in ordinance</title>
      <lead>During its meeting today, the Federal Council adopted a revision of the Tax Administrative Assistance Ordinance. The new provision defines in greater detail the possibility of passing on the costs of international administrative assistance to the person or financial institution concerned, as provided for in the Act.</lead>
      <text link="no">The new provision of the Tax Administrative Assistance Ordinance will come into force on 1 January 2016. Under the Tax Administrative Assistance Act, the Federal Tax Administration can pass on costs if they are extraordinarily high and the person concerned or the information holder contributed substantially to the costs generated through their inappropriate behaviour. The new provision of the Tax Administrative Assistance Ordinance describes what is to be deemed an extraordinarily high sum and lists the components of the costs that can be passed on.</text>
      <contact>Anne Césard, Communications, State Secretariat for International Financial Matters SIF Tel. +41 462 62 91, anne.cesard@sif.admin.ch</contact>
      <attachment id="143128">
        <title>Verordnung über die internationale Amtshilfe in Steuersachen</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>23</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/41696.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <offers>
      <offer id="9" org-id="605">
        <name lang="de">Steuern allgemein</name>
        <name lang="fr">Impôts en général</name>
        <name lang="it">Imposte in generale</name>
        <name lang="en">Taxes in general</name>
      </offer>
    </offers>
    <keywords>
      <keyword id="235" org-id="605">
        <name lang="de">Internationale Steuerpolitik</name>
        <name lang="fr">Politique fiscale internationale</name>
        <name lang="it">Politica fiscale internazionale</name>
        <name lang="en">International tax policy</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="1000" org-id="605">
        <name lang="de">Amts- und Rechtshilfe</name>
        <name lang="fr">Assistance administrative et entraide judiciaire internationale</name>
        <name lang="it">Assistenza amministrativa e giudiziaria</name>
        <name lang="en">Administrative and mutual assistance</name>
      </keyword>
    </keywords>
    <topics>
      <topic id="35">
        <name lang="de">Finanzplatz</name>
        <name lang="fr">Place financière</name>
        <name lang="it">Piazza finanziaria</name>
        <name lang="en">Financial Centre</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="44">
        <name lang="de">Steuern</name>
        <name lang="fr">Impôts</name>
        <name lang="it">Imposte</name>
        <name lang="en">Taxation</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="47">
        <name lang="de">Wirtschaft</name>
        <name lang="fr">Économie</name>
        <name lang="it">Economia</name>
        <name lang="en">Economic Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
