<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="59427" revoked="no">
    <version>2</version>
    <pubdate>2015-11-12</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="201" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>201</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="201">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Schweiz will Mediation stärken</title>
      <lead>Die Schweiz will sich in der Mediation stärker engagieren. Bundesrat Didier Burkhalter bekräftigte diesen Willen an der Jahreskonferenz der Abteilung Menschliche Sicherheit AMS des Eidgenössischen Departements für auswärtige Angelegenheiten EDA in Bern. Die Schweiz könne dabei auf ihre langjährige Tradition als Vermittlerin aufbauen. </lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Die Guten Dienste der Schweiz und insbesondere die Mediation seien Grundpfeiler der schweizerischen Friedenspolitik, sagte der EDA-Vorsteher in seiner Rede. Die Mediation sei ein Bereich, in dem die Schweiz nachhaltig zur Stärkung von Frieden und Sicherheit in der Welt beitragen könne. Aus diesem Grunde liege sie ihm ganz besonders am Herzen. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Wo Krieg und Konflikt, Hoffnungslosigkeit, Verzweiflung, Not, und Schmerz den Alltag prägen, ist Mediation oft Ausweg und Strohhalm der Hoffnung – sei dies im Mittleren Osten, in Südsudan oder in der Ukraine. Sie erlaubt es der Schweiz in Einklang mit der Bundesverfassung einen Beitrag zum friedlichen Zusammenleben der Völker zu leisten. Die Schweiz hat im Rahmen ihrer Guten Dienste eine lange Tradition als Vermittlerin in solchen Situationen. Die Chefin der AMS, Botschafterin Heidi Grau, betonte die Bedeutung und Notwendigkeit von Mediation, die weltweit wirksam zur Lösung von Konflikten beigetragen könne. Die Schweiz bringe dafür die besten Voraussetzungen mit.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Die Mediation den neuen Situationen anpassen&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Da sich Naturell und Hintergrund von Konflikten verändern, muss die Schweiz ihre Guten Dienste an die neuen Bedingungen anpassen und die Mediation professionalisieren. Heute agieren extremistische Gruppen grenzüberschreitend, Konflikte drehen sich um Grenzen oder entzünden sich am Verteilkampf um Wasserressourcen. Dementsprechend verändern sich auch Herangehensweise und Lösungsansätze. Bundesrat Burkhalter betonte das heutige, vielfältige Mediationsengagement der Schweiz. Sie müsse diese Stärke jedoch noch weiter ausbauen und besser nutzen. In Zukunft soll die Schweiz vermehrt eigene Mediationen leiten und beispielsweise der UNO und der OSZE eigene hochrangige Mediatorinnen und Mediatoren zur Verfügung stellen. Dafür soll die Mediationsausbildung entsprechend ausgebaut werden. Das EDA will mit Hilfe spezialisierter Karrieren den Mediationsnachwuchs fördern und verstärkt mit Partnern, anderen Staaten und Organisationen zusammenarbeiten. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Jeder Konflikt und jede Mediationserfahrung ist anders&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;An der AMS-Jahreskonferenz berichteten hochrangige Diplomatinnen und Diplomaten sowie Experten und Expertinnen von ihren Mediationserfahrungen. Der Sondergesandte für Syrien, Staffan de Mistura, erläuterte in einer Videobotschaft die Perspektive der UNO. David Harland, Direktor der Genfer Mediationsorganisation Humanitarian Dialogue Centre, sprach aus Sicht einer Nicht-Regierungsorganisation über die Mediation. Alexander Hug, erster stellvertretender Chefmonitor der OSZE-Sonderbeobachtungsmission in der Ukraine, berichtete von seinen Erfahrungen. Botschafterin Christine Schraner Burgener und Botschafter Günther Bächler erzählten von ihrer Mediationsarbeit in Thailand, Nepal oder Georgien. Chief Fortune Charumbira, simbabwischer Stammesführer und Senator, legte dar, wie traditionelle Methoden der Konfliktschlichtung mit modernen Mediationskonzepten verbunden werden können. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Beispiele für eine erfolgreiche Schweizer Vermittlungstätigkeit sind die Verträge von Évian, die das Ende des algerischen Bürgerkriegs markierten und Algerien die Unabhängigkeit sicherten, oder in jüngerer Zeit die Waffenstillstandsverhandlungen zum Konflikt in den sudanesischen Nuba-Bergen (2002), die Vermittlung zwischen der Türkei und Armenien (2009), die Vermittlung zwischen Georgien und Russland (2010-2011) oder das Ukraine-Engagement der Schweiz im Rahmen der Organisation für Sicherheit und Zusammenarbeit in Europa (OSZE). &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Kommunikation EDA Bundeshaus West CH-3003 Bern Tel. Kommunikationsservice: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Medienstelle: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <link id="143206">
        <title>Die Guten Dienste der Schweiz</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home/aussenpolitik/menschenrechte-menschliche-sicherheit/frieden/die-guten-dienstederschweiz.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="143207">
        <title>Jahreskonferenz 2015</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home/aktuell/agenda.html/content/eda/de/meta/agenda/2015/4/jahreskonferenz-eda-menschliche-sicherheit</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="143208">
        <title>Ansprache Bundesrat Didier Burkhalter (fr/de)</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home/das-eda/departementsvorsteherdidierburkhalter/reden.html/content/eda/de/meta/speeches/2015/11/12/59423</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>La Suisse entend renforcer ses activités de médiation</title>
      <lead>La Suisse veut s’engager plus activement sur le terrain de la médiation. Le conseiller fédéral Didier Burkhalter a souligné cette volonté lors de la Conférence annuelle de la Division Sécurité humaine (DSH) du Département fédéral des affaires étrangères (DFAE) à Berne. La Suisse peut s’appuyer à cet égard sur sa longue tradition en tant que médiatrice. </lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Les bons offices de la Suisse, et en particulier la médiation, sont les pierres angulaires de la politique suisse en matière de paix, a déclaré le chef du DFAE dans son discours. Selon lui, la Suisse peut contribuer durablement à la consolidation de la paix et de la sécurité dans le monde grâce à la médiation. Cette approche lui tient donc particulièrement à cœur. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;La médiation constitue souvent un moyen pour sortir des guerres et des conflits. Elle redonne espoir aux populations qui sont en proie à la détresse et à la souffrance, que ce soit au Moyen-Orient, au Soudan du Sud ou en Ukraine. Elle permet à la Suisse de contribuer à la coexistence pacifique des peuples, conformément à son mandat constitutionnel. Dans le cadre de ses bons offices, la Suisse jouit d’une longue tradition en tant que médiatrice dans pareilles situations. L’ambassadrice Heidi Grau, cheffe de la DSH, a insisté sur l’importance et la nécessité de la médiation. Celle-ci, affirme-t-elle, peut contribuer efficacement à résoudre les conflits à travers le monde. La Suisse présente toutes les qualités requises pour assumer cette tâche.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Adapter la médiation aux nouvelles situations&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Face à l’évolution de la nature et de l’origine des conflits, la Suisse doit adapter ses bons offices et professionnaliser ses services de médiation. De nos jours, des groupes extrémistes opèrent au niveau international, les guerres se déroulent par-delà les frontières et des conflits éclatent pour des questions de répartition des ressources en eau. Les approches et les propositions de solution doivent donc elles aussi évoluer. S’il s’est réjoui de l’engagement diversifié de la Suisse en matière de médiation, le conseiller fédéral Didier Burkhalter a aussi insisté sur la nécessité de développer et de mieux exploiter cet atout. A l’avenir, la Suisse devrait mener plus souvent ses propres opérations de médiation en mettant, par exemple, à la disposition de l’ONU ou de l’Organisation pour la sécurité et la coopération en Europe (OSCE) ses propres médiatrices et médiateurs de haut rang. A cet effet, il conviendra de renforcer la formation en médiation. Le DFAE entend promouvoir la relève dans ce domaine à l’aide de filières spécialisées, mais aussi multiplier les collaborations avec des partenaires, des organisations et d’autres Etats. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A chaque conflit sa médiation&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Lors de la Conférence annuelle de la DSH, des diplomates de haut rang et des experts ont présenté leurs expériences en tant que médiateurs. Staffan de Mistura, envoyé spécial des Nations Unies pour la Syrie, a exposé la perspective de l’ONU par message vidéo. David Harland, directeur du Centre pour le dialogue humanitaire, organisation de médiation basée à Genève, a expliqué la médiation du point de vue d’une organisation non gouvernementale. Alexander Hug, premier responsable adjoint de la Mission spéciale d’observation de l’OSCE en Ukraine, a fait état de ses expériences. L’ambassadrice Christine Schraner Burgener et l’ambassadeur Günther Bächler ont évoqué leur travail de médiation en Thaïlande, au Népal et en Géorgie. Pour finir, Fortune Charumbira, chef coutumier et sénateur du Zimbabwe, a expliqué comment associer méthodes traditionnelles de règlement de conflits et approches de médiation modernes. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;L’activité de médiation de la Suisse a enregistré de nombreux succès à ce jour. Citons, entre autres, les Accords d’Evian, qui ont mis fin à la guerre civile en Algérie et ouvert la voie à l’indépendance du pays ou, plus récemment, les négociations de cessez-le-feu dans le conflit qui faisait rage dans les monts Nuba au Soudan du Sud (2002), la médiation entre la Turquie et l’Arménie (2009) et celle entre la Géorgie et la Russie (2010-2011) ou encore l’engagement de la Suisse en Ukraine dans le cadre de l’OSCE. &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Communication DFAE Palais fédéral ouest CH-3003 Berne Tél. Service de communication: +41 58 462 31 53 Tél. Service de presse: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <link id="143209">
        <title>Les bons offices de la Suisse</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/home/aussenpolitik/menschenrechte-menschliche-sicherheit/frieden/die_guten_dienstederschweiz.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="143210">
        <title>Conférence annuelle 2015</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/home/aktuell/agenda.html/eda/fr/meta/agenda/2015/4/jahreskonferenz-eda-menschliche-sicherheit</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="143211">
        <title>Allocution du Conseiller fédéral Didier Burkhalter (fr/de)</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/home/das_eda/departementsvorsteherdidierburkhalter/reden.html/eda/fr/meta/speeches/2015/11/12/59423</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>La Svizzera vuole rafforzare la mediazione</title>
      <lead>La Svizzera vuole rafforzare il suo impegno nell’ambito della mediazione. Durante la Conferenza annuale della Divisione Sicurezza umana (DSU) del Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri (DFAE), il consigliere federale Didier Burkhalter ha rimarcato tale volontà, aggiungendo che la Svizzera può fare appoggio sulla sua lunga tradizione di mediatrice. </lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Nel suo discorso il capo del DFAE ha affermato che i buoni uffici della Svizzera e in particolare la mediazione sono il fondamento della politica di pace della Svizzera. Poiché la mediazione è uno dei settori in cui la Svizzera può contribuire sostenibilmente al rafforzamento della pace e della sicurezza nel mondo, Burkhalter ha sottolineato quanto questo ambito gli stia a cuore. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Nei luoghi in cui la quotidianità è segnata da guerre, conflitti, mancanza di prospettive, disperazione, indigenza e dolore, la mediazione è spesso l’unica via di scampo e rappresenta un segnale di speranza, come in Medio Oriente, Sudan del Sud o Ucraina. Permette alla Svizzera di contribuire alla convivenza pacifica tra i popoli, in sintonia con la Costituzione federale. Nel quadro dei suoi buoni uffici, la Svizzera ha una lunga tradizione di mediatrice in tali contesti. L’ambasciatrice Heidi Grau, capo della DSU, ha sottolineato l’importanza e la necessità della mediazione, strumento efficace in tutto il mondo nella risoluzione dei conflitti. Ha dichiarato inoltre che la Svizzera presenta i presupposti ideali in materia.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Adattare la mediazione a nuovi scenari&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;La natura e le ragioni dei conflitti mutano, la Svizzera deve pertanto adattare i suoi buoni uffici alle nuove situazioni e professionalizzare la mediazione. Oggi le attività dei gruppi estremisti eludono i confini nazionali, i conflitti sono incentrati sulla delimitazione di frontiere o hanno origine nella contesa per le risorse idriche. Di conseguenza cambiano anche gli approcci e le soluzioni possibili. Il consigliere federale Burkhalter ha posto l’accento sull’attuale impegno di mediazione della Svizzera, particolarmente vario, ricordando che questo punto di forza va potenziato ulteriormente e sfruttato meglio. In futuro la Svizzera dovrà lanciare più frequentemente iniziative di mediazione proprie e, al contempo, mettere a disposizione di organi come l’ONU e l’OSCE mediatori e mediatrici svizzeri di alto livello. A questo scopo la formazione nel settore va sviluppata adeguatamente. Offrendo possibilità di carriera specialistiche, il DFAE vuole promuovere nuove leve nell’ambito della mediazione e collaborare maggiormente con partner, altri Stati e organizzazioni. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ogni conflitto e ogni esperienza di mediazione sono diversi&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Alla Conferenza annuale della DSU diplomatici ed esperti di alto livello hanno parlato delle loro esperienze di mediazione. L’inviato speciale dell’ONU per la Siria, Staffan de Mistura, ha illustrato il punto di vista dell’ONU in un messaggio video. David Harland, direttore del Centro per il dialogo umanitario (Humanitarian Dialogue Centre), organizzazione con sede a Ginevra che opera nel campo della mediazione, ha parlato della mediazione dal punto di vista di un’organizzazione non governativa. Alexander Hug, capo osservatore supplente della missione speciale di osservazione dell’OSCE in Ucraina, ha raccontato le sue esperienze. L’ambasciatrice Christine Schraner Burgener e l’ambasciatore Günther Bächler hanno riferito del loro lavoro di mediazione in Thailandia, in Nepal e in Georgia. Fortune Charumbira, capo tribù e senatore zimbabwese, ha illustrato come si possono combinare metodi tradizionali di risoluzione dei conflitti con strategie di mediazione moderne. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Tra gli esempi di attività di mediazione di successo della Svizzera vi sono gli accordi di Évian, che hanno segnato la fine della guerra civile algerina e hanno sancito l’indipendenza dell’Algeria, oppure, più recentemente, le trattative sull’armistizio del conflitto nei Monti Nuba sudanesi (2002), la mediazione tra la Turchia e l’Armenia (2009) e tra la Georgia e la Russia (2010-2011) o l’impegno della Svizzera in Ucraina nel quadro dell’Organizzazione per la sicurezza e la cooperazione in Europa (OSCE). &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Comunicazione DFAE Palazzo federale ovest CH-3003 Berna Tel. Servizio di comunicazione: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Servizio stampa: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <link id="143212">
        <title>I buoni uffici della Svizzera</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/home/aussenpolitik/menschenrechte-menschliche-sicherheit/frieden/die_guten_dienstederschweiz.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="143213">
        <title>Conferenza annuale 2015</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/home/aktuell/agenda.html/eda/it/meta/agenda/2015/4/jahreskonferenz-eda-menschliche-sicherheit</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="143214">
        <title>Allocuzione del Consigliere federale Didier Burkhalter (fr/de)</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/home/das_eda/departementsvorsteherdidierburkhalter/reden.html/eda/it/meta/speeches/2015/11/12/59423</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Strengthening Swiss mediation</title>
      <lead>Switzerland wants to be more actively involved in mediation. This commitment was reaffirmed by Federal Councillor Didier Burkhalter in Bern at the annual conference of the Human Security Division of the Federal Department of Foreign Affairs (FDFA), who stated that the country could build upon its long-standing tradition as a mediator to this end. </lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Speaking as head of the FDFA, Mr Burkhalter said that Switzerland's good offices, in particular its role as a mediator, formed the cornerstone of Swiss peace policy. He went on to say that mediation was an area in which Switzerland could make a lasting contribution to strengthening global peace and security, which is why the subject was particularly important to him. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mediation is often a way out or a last ray of hope where daily life is plagued by war, conflict, helplessness, despair, need and pain - whether in the Middle East, South Sudan or Ukraine. In keeping with the spirit of the Federal Constitution, mediation is a means by which Switzerland can contribute to helping people live together peaceably. Switzerland has a long-standing tradition as a mediator as part of the country's good offices. Ambassador Heidi Grau, who heads the Human Security Division (HSD), stressed how important and necessary mediation was to help resolve conflicts effectively worldwide, stating that Switzerland was ideally placed for such efforts.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Adapting mediation to new situations&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As the nature and context of conflicts are in flux, Switzerland must adapt its good offices to these changing conditions and professionalise its mediation practices. Today, there are extremist groups who operate across borders; conflicts revolve around borders or are sparked by competition over water resources. Consequently, possible approaches and solutions also have to change. Mr Burkhalter emphasised Switzerland's diverse involvement in mediation today but stated that the country's strengths must continue to be developed and put to better use. Switzerland should increasingly lead more of its own mediation proceedings and provide high-level Swiss mediators to the UN and OSCE, for example. For this, training in mediation should be developed accordingly. The FDFA wants to encourage young people into mediation with the help of specialist careers in the field and strengthen cooperation with partners, other states and organisations. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Every conflict and every mediation process is different&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;At the HSD annual conference, high-level diplomats and experts were given the floor to talk about their experiences in the field of mediation. The UN special envoy for Syria, Staffan de Mistura, explained the UN's viewpoint on mediation via video message. David Harland, Director of the Humanitarian Dialogue Centre, a mediation organisation based in Geneva, spoke about the subject from an NGO perspective. Alexander Hug, Deputy Chief Monitor of the OSCE Special Monitoring Mission to Ukraine, talked about his experiences in the field. Ambassadors Christine Schraner Burgener and Günther Bächler also spoke about their mediation work in Thailand, Nepal and Georgia. Chief Fortune Charumbira, a Zimbabwean tribal leader and senator, illustrated how traditional methods of conflict arbitration can be combined with modern mediation methods. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Examples of Switzerland's mediation successes are the Évian Accords, marking the end of the Algerian civil war and ensuring the country's independence, the more recent ceasefire negotiations on the conflict in southern Sudan's Nuba Mountains (2002), mediation between Turkey and Armenia (2009), between Georgia and Russia (2010-2011) and Switzerland's engagement in Ukraine as part of the Organization for Security and Co-operation in Europe (OSCE). &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>FDFA Communication Federal Palace West Wing CH-3003 Bern, Switzerland Tel. Communication service: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Press service: +41 58 460 55 55 E-mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @SwissMFA</contact>
      <link id="143215">
        <title>Good offices</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home/aussenpolitik/menschenrechte-menschliche-sicherheit/frieden/die_guten_dienstederschweiz.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="143216">
        <title>Annual Conference 2015</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home/aktuell/agenda.html/eda/en/meta/agenda/2015/4/jahreskonferenz-eda-menschliche-sicherheit</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="143217">
        <title>Address by Federal Councillor Didier Burkhalter (fr/de)</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home/das_eda/departementsvorsteherdidierburkhalter/reden.html/eda/en/meta/speeches/2015/11/12/59423</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="40">
        <name lang="de">Sicherheit</name>
        <name lang="fr">Sécurité</name>
        <name lang="it">Sicurezza</name>
        <name lang="en">Security</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
