<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="37446" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2011-01-31</pubdate>
    <blocking-period>2011-01-31</blocking-period>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="815" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>801</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössische Kommunikationskommission ComCom</name>
      <name lang="fr">Commission fédérale de la communication ComCom</name>
      <name lang="it">Commissione federale delle comunicazioni ComCom</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Communications Commission ComCom</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.comcom.admin.ch/</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.comcom.admin.ch/</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.comcom.admin.ch/</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.comcom.admin.ch/</www>
      <email lang="de">comcom@comcom.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">comcom@comcom.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">comcom@comcom.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">comcom@comcom.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="810" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>801</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Bundesamt für Kommunikation</name>
      <name lang="fr">Office fédéral de la communication</name>
      <name lang="it">Ufficio federale delle comunicazioni</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Office of Communications</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.bakom.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.ofcom.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.ufcom.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.ofcom.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">media@bakom.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">media@bakom.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">media@bakom.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">media@bakom.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="801">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Umwelt, Verkehr, Energie und Kommunikation</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'environnement, des transports, de l'énergie et de la communication</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'ambiente, dei trasporti, dell'energia e delle comunicazioni</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of the Environment, Transport, Energy and Communications</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.uvek.admin.ch/uvek/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.uvek.admin.ch/uvek/fr/home.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.uvek.admin.ch/uvek/it/home.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.uvek.admin.ch/uvek/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-uvek.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-uvek.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-uvek.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-uvek.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Ausschreibung von Mobilfunkfrequenzen: Verlängerte Bewerbungsfrist</title>
      <teaser>Die ComCom verlängert die Bewerbungsfrist für die Teilnahme an der Auktion für Mobilfunkfrequenzen. Sie hat zudem entschieden, die interessierten Unternehmen zu einem Hearing einzuladen, um verschiedene Aspekte im Zusammenhang mit der Auktion zu vertiefen.</teaser>
      <lead>Die ComCom verlängert die Bewerbungsfrist für die Teilnahme an der Auktion für Mobilfunkfrequenzen. Sie hat zudem entschieden, die interessierten Unternehmen zu einem Hearing einzuladen, um verschiedene Aspekte im Zusammenhang mit der Auktion zu vertiefen.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Im Rahmen der Ausschreibung von Mobilfunkfrequenzen, die am 26.11.2010 eröffnet wurde, hatten die interessierten Unternehmen in einem ersten Schritt Gelegenheit, Fragen zu stellen. Eine sorgfältige Beantwortung der eingegangenen Fragen nimmt mehr Zeit in Anspruch als ursprünglich geplant. Die Eidgenössische Kommunikationskommission (ComCom) wird zur Vertiefung einzelner Aspekte am 28. Februar 2011 zudem eine Anhörung der interessierten Unternehmen durchführen. Teilnahmebedingungen, Form und Inhalt sowie Ort und Zeit der Veranstaltung werden in den nächsten Tagen auf der Webseite des BAKOM kommuniziert.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Der ursprünglich für den 18. März 2011 vorgesehene Termin zur Eingabe der Bewerbungsunterlagen für die Auktion der Mobilfunkfrequenzen wird deshalb verschoben. Das neue Eingabedatum und der angepasste Terminkalender des Vergabeverfahrens werden später bekannt gegeben.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Urs von Arx, Leiter Sektion Mobil- und Satellitenfunkdienste, Bundesamt für Kommunikation (BAKOM), Tel. +41(0)32 327 58 56</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Mise au concours des fréquences de téléphonie mobile: nouveau délai de candidature</title>
      <teaser>La ComCom a prolongé le délai de dépôt des candidatures pour la procédure d'adjudication des fréquences de téléphonie mobile. En outre, elle a décidé de rencontrer les entreprises intéressées afin d'approfondir plusieurs aspects en lien avec l'adjudication.</teaser>
      <lead>La ComCom a prolongé le délai de dépôt des candidatures pour la procédure d'adjudication des fréquences de téléphonie mobile. En outre, elle a décidé de rencontrer les entreprises intéressées afin d'approfondir plusieurs aspects en lien avec l'adjudication.</lead>
      <text link="no">Dans le cadre de la mise au concours des fréquences de téléphonie mobile ouverte le 26 novembre 2010, les entreprises étaient invitées dans un premier temps à poser des questions. Or, répondre aux questions reçues prend davantage de temps que prévu. En outre, afin d'approfondir certains aspects, la Commission fédérale de la communication (ComCom) souhaite procéder à une audition des entreprises intéressées le 28 février 2011. Les conditions de participation, la forme, le contenu ainsi que le lieu et l’heure seront communiqués dans les prochains jours sur le site internet de l'OFCOM.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Par conséquent, le délai de dépôt des dossiers de participation à la procédure d'adjudication, initialement fixé au 18 mars 2011 est prolongé. La nouvelle date ainsi que le nouveau calendrier de la procédure seront communiqués ultérieurement.</text>
      <contact>Urs von Arx, chef de la section Services mobiles et par satellite, Office fédéral de la communication (OFCOM), tél. +41(0)32 327 58 56</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Posticipato il termine di inoltro delle candidature alla pubblica gara per l'attribuzione delle frequenze di telefonia mobile</title>
      <teaser>La ComCom posticipa il termine di inoltro delle candidature per l’attribuzione all’asta di frequenze da destinare alla telefonia mobile. Ha inoltre deciso di invitare le aziende interessate a un hearing durante il quale verranno approfonditi vari aspetti legati allo svolgimento dell’asta.</teaser>
      <lead>La ComCom posticipa il termine di inoltro delle candidature per l'attribuzione all'asta di frequenze da destinare alla telefonia mobile. Ha inoltre deciso di invitare le aziende interessate a un hearing durante il quale verranno approfonditi vari aspetti legati allo svolgimento dell'asta.</lead>
      <text link="no">La pubblica gara per l'attribuzione delle frequenze di telefonia mobile, avviata il 26 novembre 2010, prevedeva innanzitutto la possibilità per le aziende interessate di porre domande per eventuali chiarimenti. Per dare adeguata risposta a tutte le domande inoltrate occorrerà più tempo rispetto a quanto inizialmente preventivato. A questo proposito, il 28 febbraio 2011 la Commissione federale delle comunicazioni (ComCom) ha inoltre previsto un incontro con le aziende interessate, volto ad approfondire determinati aspetti. Condizioni di partecipazione, forma, contenuto nonché luogo e ora dell'incontro verranno comunicati nei prossimi giorni attraverso il sito Internet dell'UFCOM.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Viste le circostanze, il termine per l'inoltro dei dossier di candidatura originariamente fissato al 18 marzo 2011 è stato posticipato. La nuova scadenza e il calendario rivisto dell’intera procedura di attribuzione delle frequenze saranno resi noti in data successiva.</text>
      <contact>Urs von Arx, caposezione Servizi mobili e via satellite, Ufficio federale delle comunicazioni (UFCOM), tel. +41(0)32 327 58 56</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Invitation to tender for mobile radio frequencies: candidature period extended</title>
      <teaser>ComCom is extending the candidature period for participation in the auction for mobile radio frequencies. It has also decided to invite interested companies to a hearing in order to clarify various aspects related to the auction.</teaser>
      <lead>ComCom is extending the candidature period for participation in the auction for mobile radio frequencies. It has also decided to invite interested companies to a hearing in order to clarify various aspects related to the auction.</lead>
      <text link="no">Within the framework of the invitation to tender for mobile radio frequencies, which was launched on 26.11.2010, interested parties had an opportunity to ask questions in an initial stage. Providing thorough answers to the questions received is taking more time than was originally envisaged. The Federal Communications Commission (ComCom) will also be holding a hearing with interested undertakings on 28 February 2011 to clarify individual aspects. Conditions for participation, the form and content, plus the time and place of the event will be communicated in the next few days on the OFCOM website.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; The deadline for submission of candidature documents for the auction of mobile radio frequencies, originally scheduled for 18 March 2011, is therefore being extended. The new submission date and the modified schedule for the award procedure will be notified at a later date.</text>
      <contact>Urs von Arx, Head of Section Mobile and Satellite Services, Federal Office of Communication (OFCOM), tel. +41(0)32 327 58 56</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <offers>
      <offer id="120" org-id="815">
        <name lang="de">Medienmitteilungen</name>
        <name lang="fr">Communiqués de presse</name>
        <name lang="it">Comunicati stampa</name>
        <name lang="en">Press releases</name>
      </offer>
    </offers>
    <keywords>
      <keyword id="140" org-id="815">
        <name lang="de">Bundesamt für Kommunikation (BAKOM)</name>
        <name lang="fr">Office fédéral de la communication (OFCOM)</name>
        <name lang="it">Ufficio federale delle comunicazioni (UFCOM)</name>
        <name lang="en">Federal Office of Communications (OFCOM)</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="630" org-id="815">
        <name lang="de">Kommunikationskommission, Eidg. ComCom</name>
        <name lang="fr">Commission fédérale de la communication ComCom</name>
        <name lang="it">Commissione federale delle comunicazioni ComCom</name>
        <name lang="en">Federal Communications Commission ComCom</name>
      </keyword>
    </keywords>
    <topics>
      <topic id="19">
        <name lang="de">Medien</name>
        <name lang="fr">Médias</name>
        <name lang="it">Media</name>
        <name lang="en">Media</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="28">
        <name lang="de">Telekommunikation</name>
        <name lang="fr">Télécommunications</name>
        <name lang="it">Telecomunicazione</name>
        <name lang="en">Telecommunications</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="36">
        <name lang="de">Informatik und E-Government</name>
        <name lang="fr">Informatique et cyberadministration</name>
        <name lang="it">Informatica ed e-government</name>
        <name lang="en">IT and E-Government</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
