<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="81928" revoked="no">
    <version>2</version>
    <pubdate>2021-01-14</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="606" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>601</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössische Zollverwaltung</name>
      <name lang="fr">Administration fédérale des douanes</name>
      <name lang="it">Amministrazione federale delle dogane</name>
      <name lang="en">The Federal Customs Administration</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.ezv.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.ezv.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.ezv.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.ezv.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">ozd.zentrale@ezv.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">ozd.zentrale@ezv.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">ozd.zentrale@ezv.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">ozd.zentrale@ezv.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="601">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Finanzdepartement</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des finances</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale delle finanze</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Finance</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.efd.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.dff.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.efd.admin.ch/efd/it/home.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.efd.admin.ch/efd/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Erster EETS-Lastwagen fährt in die Schweiz</title>
      <lead>EETS ist der europaweit kompatible elektronische Mautdienst der EU – neu mit Anschluss in die Schweiz. Das vereinfacht und beschleunigt den Warenverkehr an der Grenze. Die Anbindung an EETS ist ein Meilenstein des Digitalisierungs- und Transformationsprogramms DaziT.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Die Eidgenössische Zollverwaltung (EZV) schafft die Voraussetzungen für die Anbindung der Schweiz an EETS, den europaweit kompatiblen elektronischen Mautdienst der EU (European Electronic Toll Service, EETS). Damit müssen Fahrer von ausländischen Transportfahrzeugen nicht mehr an der Grenze aussteigen, um die Leistungsabhängige Schwerverkehrsabgabe (LSVA) zu entrichten. Dies kann jetzt durchgängig digitalisiert anhand eines kleinen On-Board-Erfassungsgeräts geschehen. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Neu arbeitet die EZV dazu mit privaten Erfassungsdienstleistern, sogenannten EETS-Providern zusammen. Ein erster EETS-Provider, die Telepass, hat das erforderliche mehrstufige Zulassungsverfahren bestanden. Die erste offizielle EETS-Fahrt in die Schweiz fand heute in Chiasso statt.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Die Ablösung des bestehenden LSVA-Erfassungssystems für inländische Fahrzeuge (emotach) ist gemäss der Roadmap des Transformationsprogramms DaziT auf Anfang 2024 vorgesehen. Die Liste von weiteren zugelassenen EETS-Providern wird auf der Webseite der EZV laufend publiziert.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Mediendienst Eidgenössische Zollverwaltung EZV Tel. +41 58 462 67 43 , medien@ezv.admin.ch</contact>
      <attachment id="211067">
        <title>Symbolbild EETS-Lastwagen 01</title>
        <format>jpg</format>
        <size-kb>1988</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/64908.jpg</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="211068">
        <title>Symbolbild EETS-Lastwagen 02</title>
        <format>jpg</format>
        <size-kb>1814</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/64912.jpg</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <link id="211066">
        <title>Film: European Electronic Toll Service - now available for Switzerland</title>
        <uri>https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=IPC3Dex3McQ</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="211069">
        <title>Transformationsprogramm DaziT: www.dazit.admin.ch</title>
        <uri>https://www.ezv.admin.ch/ezv/de/home/themen/projekte/dazit.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="211070">
        <title>Rechtliche Grundlage: EETS- und Tankkarten-Anbieter-Verordnung EFD (SR 641.811.423)</title>
        <uri>https://www.admin.ch/opc/de/classified-compilation/20192059/index.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Le premier camion équipé d'un appareil de saisie SET entre en Suisse</title>
      <lead>Le SET est le service de télépéage de l'UE, compatible à l'échelle européenne, auquel la Suisse est désormais raccordée. Il contribue à simplifier et à accélérer la circulation des marchandises à la frontière. Le raccordement au SET représente une étape importante du programme de numérisation et de transformation DaziT.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;L'Administration fédérale des douanes (AFD) crée les conditions nécessaires pour raccorder la Suisse au SET, le service de télépéage de l'UE, compatible à l'échelle européenne (European Electronic Toll Service, EETS). Grâce à ce système, les chauffeurs de véhicules de transport étrangers ne doivent plus sortir à la frontière pour s'acquitter de la redevance sur le trafic des poids lourds liée aux prestations (RPLP). Cette opération peut maintenant être effectuée de manière entièrement numérique à l'aide d'un petit appareil de saisie embarqué.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;L'AFD coopère désormais avec des intermédiaires privés, appelés prestataires du SET. Un premier prestataire du SET, Telepass, a réussi la procédure d'agrément ad hoc à plusieurs étapes. Lors du premier trajet SET officiel à destination de la Suisse, un camion a traversé aujourd'hui la frontière à Chiasso.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Le remplacement du système de saisie actuel destiné aux véhicules suisses (emotach) est prévu pour début 2024, conformément à la feuille de route du programme de transformation DaziT. La liste des autres prestataires agréés du SET, publiée sur le site Internet de l'AFD, sera régulièrement mise à jour.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Service Médias, Administration fédérale des douanes AFD no tél. +41 58 462 67 43, medien@ezv.admin.ch</contact>
      <attachment id="211072">
        <title>Symbole représentant un camion équipé d'un appareil de saisie SET 01</title>
        <format>jpg</format>
        <size-kb>1988</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/64909.jpg</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="211073">
        <title>Symbole représentant un camion équipé d'un appareil de saisie SET 02</title>
        <format>jpg</format>
        <size-kb>1814</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/64913.jpg</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <link id="211071">
        <title>Film: European Electronic Toll Service - now available for Switzerland</title>
        <uri>https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=IPC3Dex3McQ</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="211074">
        <title>Programme de transformation DaziT (www.dazit.admin.ch)</title>
        <uri>https://www.ezv.admin.ch/ezv/fr/home/themes/projets/dazit.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="211075">
        <title>Bases légales: ordonnance du DFF sur les prestataires du SET et les prestataires de cartes de carburant (RS 641.811.423)</title>
        <uri>https://www.admin.ch/opc/fr/classified-compilation/20192059/index.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Primo autocarro munito di apparecchio SET entra in Svizzera</title>
      <lead>Il SET è il servizio dell’UE destinato al pagamento dei pedaggi compatibile a livello europeo ed è ora disponibile anche in Svizzera. Ciò semplifica e rende più veloce il traffico delle merci al confine. L’integrazione nel sistema SET rappresenta una tappa importante del programma di digitalizzazione e trasformazione DaziT.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;L’Amministrazione federale delle dogane (AFD) crea le condizioni per integrare la Svizzera nel SET (Servizio europeo di telepedaggio; in inglese: European Electronic Toll Service, EETS), ovvero il servizio dell’UE per il pagamento dei pedaggi compatibile a livello europeo. Grazie a questa integrazione, i conducenti di autocarri esteri non devono più fermarsi al confine per pagare la tassa sul traffico pesante commisurata alle prestazioni (TTPCP). Ciò può ora avvenire in modo interamente digitalizzato mediante un piccolo apparecchio di rilevazione a bordo del veicolo. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;A tal fine l’AFD collabora ora con fornitori di servizi di rilevazione privati, cosiddetti fornitori (o provider) del SET. Un primo fornitore, la Telepass, ha superato la procedura di autorizzazione costituita da più fasi. In data odierna a Chiasso è avvenuta la prima entrata ufficiale in Svizzera di un veicolo munito di apparecchio SET.&lt;/p&gt; La sostituzione dell’odierno sistema di rilevamento della TTPCP per i veicoli svizzeri (emotach) è prevista, secondo il piano d’azione del programma di trasformazione DaziT, per l’inizio del 2024. L’elenco dei fornitori del SET viene costantemente aggiornato e pubblicato sul sito dell’AFD. </text>
      <contact>Servizio stampa dell’Amministrazione federale delle dogane AFD Tel. +41 58 462 67 43, medien@ezv.admin.ch</contact>
      <attachment id="211077">
        <title>Immagine di autocarro munito di apparecchio SET 01</title>
        <format>jpg</format>
        <size-kb>1988</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/64910.jpg</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="211078">
        <title>Immagine di autocarro munito di apparecchio SET 02</title>
        <format>jpg</format>
        <size-kb>1814</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/64914.jpg</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <link id="211076">
        <title>Filmato: European Electronic Toll Service - now available for Switzerland</title>
        <uri>https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=IPC3Dex3McQ</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="211079">
        <title>Programma di trasformazione Dazit www.dazit.admin.ch</title>
        <uri>https://www.ezv.admin.ch/ezv/it/home/temi/progetti/dazit.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="211080">
        <title>Base legale: ordinanza del DFF sui fornitori di SET e sui fornitori di carte-carburante (RS 641.811.423)</title>
        <uri>https://www.admin.ch/opc/it/classified-compilation/20192059/index.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>First EETS lorry enters Switzerland</title>
      <lead>EETS is the EU's harmonised electronic toll service throughout Europe – and now Switzerland has joined as well. This service simplifies and accelerates the movement of goods at the border. Joining the EETS network is a milestone in the DaziT digitalisation and transformation programme.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;The Federal Customs Administration (FCA) has created the prerequisites for connecting Switzerland to the European Electronic Toll Service, EETS for short, the EU's harmonised electronic toll service throughout Europe. With this, the drivers of foreign transport vehicles will no longer have to get out at the border to pay the performance-related heavy vehicle charge (performance-related HVC). This can now be done entirely digitally with a small on-board unit. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The FCA works with private recording service providers, so-called EETS providers. Telepass is the first EETS providers to have successfully completed the required multi-stage approval procedure. The first official EETS journey to Switzerland took place in Chiasso today.&lt;/p&gt; According to the roadmap for the DaziT transformation programme, it is planned to replace the existing performance-related HVC recording system for domestic vehicles (emotach) by early 2024. The list of other approved EETS providers is posted on the FCA's website on an ongoing basis.</text>
      <contact>This information is available in German, French and Italian</contact>
      <attachment id="211082">
        <title>Symbolic pictures of EETS lorries 01</title>
        <format>jpg</format>
        <size-kb>1988</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/64911.jpg</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="211083">
        <title>Symbolic pictures of EETS lorries 02</title>
        <format>jpg</format>
        <size-kb>1814</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/64915.jpg</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <link id="211081">
        <title>Film: European Electronic Toll Service – now available for Switzerland</title>
        <uri>https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=IPC3Dex3McQ</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="211084">
        <title>DaziT transformation programme www.dazit.admin.ch</title>
        <uri>https://www.ezv.admin.ch/ezv/en/home/topics/projects/dazit.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="211085">
        <title>Legal basis: FDF EETS and Fuel Card Providers Ordinance (SR 641.811.423) (only in German)</title>
        <uri>https://www.admin.ch/opc/it/classified-compilation/20192059/index.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions>
        <revision date="2021-01-14 10:52" type="R"/>
      </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="46">
        <name lang="de">Verkehr</name>
        <name lang="fr">Transports</name>
        <name lang="it">Trasporti</name>
        <name lang="en">Transport</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="48">
        <name lang="de">Zoll</name>
        <name lang="fr">Douanes</name>
        <name lang="it">Dogane</name>
        <name lang="en">Customs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
