<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="99654" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2024-01-10</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="323" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>701</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidg. Materialprüfungs- und Forschungsanstalt</name>
      <name lang="fr">Laboratoire fédéral d'essai des matériaux et de recherche</name>
      <name lang="it">Laboratorio federale di prova dei materiali e di ricerca</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Laboratory for Materials Testing and Research</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.empa.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.empa.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.empa.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.empa.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">contact@empa.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">contact@empa.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">contact@empa.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">contact@empa.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="701">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Wirtschaft, Bildung und Forschung</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'économie, de la formation et de la recherche</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'economia, della formazione e della ricerca</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Economic Affairs, Education and Research</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Dübendorf, St. Gallen und Thun</city>
      <title>Neue NEST-Unit in Planung: CO2-Fänger im NEST</title>
      <lead>Sind Gebäude, die einen positiven Effekt auf das Klima haben, bald Realität? Um das ambitionierte Netto-Null-Ziel bis 2050 zu erreichen, ist in vielen Bereichen ein Umdenken nötig – speziell im Bausektor. Denn Gebäude könnten schon bald als Kohlenstoffsenken dienen und so dazu beitragen, dass die CO2-Konzentration der Atmosphäre nicht länger ansteigt, ja bestenfalls sogar abnimmt. Im NEST, dem Innovationsgebäude der Empa und Eawag, sollen daher in einer neuen Unit stark CO2-reduzierte und gar CO2-negative Innovationen aus den Empa-Laboren in einer realen Umgebung verbaut werden. </lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;In der Schweiz verursacht der Bausektor rund 28% der CO2-Emissionen, was ihm eine Schlüsselrolle beim ehrgeizigen Ziel, bis 2050 keine Triebhausgase mehr in die Atmosphäre auszustossen, zukommen lässt. Neben einem emissionsarmen Bau und Betrieb von Gebäuden existiert ein weiterer, vielversprechender Lösungsansatz: CO2 aus der Atmosphäre soll zukünftig in Baustoffen gebunden und somit in Gebäuden langfristig gespeichert werden. Das ist das Ziel der gross angelegten Empa-Forschungsinitiative «Mining the Atmosphere». Mit einer neuen Unit namens «Beyond Zero» soll im NEST nun bis 2026 aufgezeigt werden, wie ein Gebäude, das als Langzeitspeicher für CO2 dient, gebaut und betrieben werden kann.&lt;/p&gt;Netto-Null nur als Zwischenstopp&lt;p&gt;Mit emissionsarmen Betonkonstruktionen oder Kohlenstoff-negativen Isolationsmaterialien existieren bereits vielversprechende Technologien auf dem Markt. «Im NEST wollen wir nun einen Schritt weitergehen und Netto-Null nur als Zwischenziel betrachten. Unsere Vision ist es, Gebäude in Zukunft als CO2-Senken zu nutzen - sie sollen also unter dem Strich eine negative CO2-Bilanz aufweisen», erklärt Reto Largo, Geschäftsführer NEST. «Dabei sehen wir gerade bei neuen Technologien für mineralische Baustoffe wie Beton ein riesiges Potential, da diese zu den meistverbauten Baumaterialien gehören.»&lt;/p&gt;Technologien vorantreiben und verbauen&lt;p&gt;Um neue CO2-negative Baumaterialien zu entwickeln, diese zu verbauen und hinsichtlich der Emissionen zu beurteilen, müssen unterschiedliche Kompetenzen gebündelt werden. Neben der Unterstützung aus diversen Empa-Laboren unter der Leitung von Mateusz Wyrzykowski, Gruppenleiter Betontechnologie, wird das NEST-Team bei diesem Bauvorhaben auch vom Architekturbüro OOS unterstützt. Andreas Derrer, Gründungspartner von OOS, ist sich sicher: «Um dieses neue Zeitalter der Bauindustrie einläuten zu können, braucht es neben den neuen mineralischen Baumaterialien vor allem reale Beispiele, die eine ganzheitliche CO2-Bilanzierung zulassen wie auch eine reale Potentialanalyse ermöglichen. Mit der neuen Unit wollen wir Antworten auf die drängende Frage geben, ob und wie Gebäude in Zukunft dazu beitragen können, den CO2-Gehalt in der Atmosphäre zu senken.»&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Dr. Mateusz Wyrzykowski Concrete &amp; Asphalt Tel. +41 58 765 4541 mateusz.wyrzykowski@empa.ch Enrico Marchesi Innovation Manager NEST Tel. +41 58 765 4705 enrico.marchesi@empa.ch</contact>
      <attachment id="269287">
        <title>Die Architekten von OOS treffen auf die Empa-Forschenden, um neue CO2-negative Innovationen aus den Empa-Laboren auf die Anforderungen des Bausektors auszurichten. Bild: Empa</title>
        <format>jpg</format>
        <size-kb>1627</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/85697.jpg</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <link id="269286">
        <title>Empa Homepage</title>
        <uri>https://www.empa.ch/web/s604/nest-unit-zero</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="269290">
        <title>Thema/Sujet/Topic: Beyond Zero</title>
        <uri>https://www.empa.ch/web/nest/beyondzero</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Dübendorf, St. Gallen und Thun</city>
      <title>Nouvelle unité NEST en projet: Attrape-CO2 dans le NEST</title>
      <lead>Les bâtiments qui ont un effet positif sur le climat seront-ils bientôt une réalité ? Pour atteindre l'objectif ambitieux de zéro émission nette d'ici 2050, un changement de mentalité est nécessaire dans de nombreux domaines, en particulier dans le secteur de la construction. En effet, les bâtiments pourraient bientôt servir de puits de carbone et contribuer ainsi à ce que la concentration de CO2 dans l'atmosphère cesse d'augmenter, voire diminue dans le meilleur des cas. Dans le NEST, le bâtiment d'innovation de l'Empa et de l'Eawag, une nouvelle unité doit donc intégrer dans un environnement réel des innovations à faibles émissions de CO2 et même négatives en CO2, issues des laboratoires de l'Empa. </lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;En Suisse, le secteur de la construction est responsable d'environ 28% des émissions de CO2, ce qui lui confère un rôle clé dans l'objectif ambitieux de ne plus rejeter de gaz à effet de serre dans l'atmosphère d'ici 2050. Outre une construction et une exploitation des bâtiments à faibles émissions, il existe une autre solution prometteuse : à l'avenir, le CO2 de l'atmosphère doit être fixé dans les matériaux de construction et donc stocké à long terme dans les bâtiments. C'est l'objectif de la vaste initiative de recherche de l'Empa "Mining the Atmosphere". Avec une nouvelle unité appelée "Beyond Zero", le NEST doit maintenant montrer d'ici 2026 comment un bâtiment servant de puit à long terme pour le CO2 peut être construit et exploité.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Le zéro net n'est qu'une étape&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Des technologies prometteuses existent déjà sur le marché, avec des constructions en béton à faibles émissions ou des matériaux d'isolation à « teneur en carbone négative ». "Dans le NEST, nous voulons maintenant aller plus loin et ne considérer le zéro net que comme un objectif intermédiaire. Notre vision est d'utiliser à l'avenir les bâtiments comme des puits de carbone - ils doivent donc présenter un bilan carbone négatif au bout du compte", explique Reto Largo, directeur de NEST. "Dans ce contexte, nous voyons justement un énorme potentiel dans les nouvelles technologies pour les matériaux de construction minéraux comme le béton, car ceux-ci font partie des matériaux de construction les plus utilisés".&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Faire progresser les technologies et les mettre en œuvre&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Pour développer de nouveaux matériaux de construction neutres en CO2, les mettre en œuvre et les évaluer en termes d'émissions, différentes compétences doivent être réunies. Outre le soutien de divers laboratoires de l'Empa sous la direction de Mateusz Wyrzykowski, chef du groupe Technologie du béton, l'équipe NEST est également soutenue dans ce projet de construction par le bureau d'architecture OOS. Andreas Derrer, partenaire fondateur d'OOS, est catégorique : "Pour pouvoir inaugurer cette nouvelle ère de l'industrie du bâtiment, il faut non seulement de nouveaux matériaux de construction minéraux, mais aussi et surtout des exemples réels qui permettent d'établir un bilan CO2 global et d'analyser le potentiel réel. Avec cette nouvelle unité, nous voulons apporter des réponses à la question urgente de savoir si et comment les bâtiments peuvent contribuer à l'avenir à réduire la teneur en CO2 de l'atmosphère".&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Dr. Mateusz Wyrzykowski Concrete &amp; Asphalt Tél. +41 58 765 4541 mateusz.wyrzykowski@empa.ch Enrico Marchesi Innovation Manager NEST Tél. +41 58 765 4705 enrico.marchesi@empa.ch</contact>
      <attachment id="269288">
        <title>Les architectes d'OOS rencontrent les chercheurs de l'Empa afin d'adapter les nouvelles innovations négatives en termes de CO2 issues des laboratoires de l'Empa aux exigences du secteur de la construction.</title>
        <format>jpg</format>
        <size-kb>1627</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/85698.jpg</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <link id="269286">
        <title>Empa Homepage</title>
        <uri>https://www.empa.ch/web/s604/nest-unit-zero</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="269290">
        <title>Thema/Sujet/Topic: Beyond Zero</title>
        <uri>https://www.empa.ch/web/nest/beyondzero</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Dübendorf, St. Gallen und Thun</city>
      <title>New NEST unit in the making: Beyond zero</title>
      <lead>Are buildings that affect our climate in a positive way soon going to be a reality? In order to achieve the ambitious net zero target by 2050, we as a society need to rethink the standards and procedures we are living by. One of the most impactful sectors is the construction industry. Through the use of advanced technologies, buildings could soon serve as carbon sinks and thus help to ensure that the CO2 concentration in the atmosphere no longer increases, or at best even decreases. A set of innovations from the Empa laboratories that are strongly CO2-reduced and even CO2-negative, are therefore going to be installed and tested in a real environment – inside a new unit at NEST, the innovation building of Empa and Eawag. </lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;In Switzerland, the construction sector is responsible for approximately 28% of total CO2 emissions, which gives it a key role in the ambitious goal of emitting no more greenhouse gases into the atmosphere by 2050. In addition to low-emission construction and operation of buildings, there is another promising solution: CO2 from the atmosphere can be bound in building materials and thus stored in buildings in the long term. Empa's large-scale research initiative Mining the Atmosphere is aimed precisely at this goal. Through the construction of a new unit called Beyond Zero by 2026, NEST will demonstrate how a building that serves as a long-term storage facility for CO2 can be constructed and operated in a real-world environment.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Net zero is just the first stop along the way&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;With low-emission concrete constructions or carbon-negative insulation materials, promising technologies already exist on the market. "At NEST, we now want to go one step further and only see net zero as an interim goal. Our vision is to use buildings as CO2 sinks in the future – in other words, they should have a negative overall CO2 footprint," explains Reto Largo, Managing Director of NEST. "We see huge potential in new technologies for mineral building materials such as concrete in particular, as these are among the most commonly used building materials gobally."&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Advancing and installing new technologies&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In order to develop new CO2-negative building materials, install them and assess them in terms of emissions, different areas of expertise need to be pooled. In addition to support from various Empa laboratories under the direction of Mateusz Wyrzykowski, Group Leader Concrete Technology, the NEST team is also being supported in this project by the architectural firm OOS. Andreas Derrer, founding partner of OOS, says: "In order to usher in this new era in the construction industry, we do not only need new mineral building materials, but above all real examples that allow a holistic CO2 balance and a real analysis of potential. With this new unit, we want to provide answers to the pressing question of whether and how buildings can contribute to reducing the atmospheric CO2 concentration in the future."&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Dr. Mateusz Wyrzykowski Concrete &amp; Asphalt Phone +41 58 765 4541 mateusz.wyrzykowski@empa.ch Enrico Marchesi Innovation Manager NEST Phone +41 58 765 4705 enrico.marchesi@empa.ch</contact>
      <attachment id="269289">
        <title>The architects from OOS cooperate with Empa researchers to align new CO2-negative innovations from the Empa laboratories with the requirements of the construction sector. Bild: Empa</title>
        <format>jpg</format>
        <size-kb>1627</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/85699.jpg</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <link id="269286">
        <title>Empa Homepage</title>
        <uri>https://www.empa.ch/web/s604/nest-unit-zero</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="269290">
        <title>Thema/Sujet/Topic: Beyond Zero</title>
        <uri>https://www.empa.ch/web/nest/beyondzero</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="8">
        <name lang="de">Bildung und Forschung</name>
        <name lang="fr">Formation et recherche</name>
        <name lang="it">Formazione e ricerca</name>
        <name lang="en">Education and Research</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="11">
        <name lang="de">Energie</name>
        <name lang="fr">Énergie</name>
        <name lang="it">Energia</name>
        <name lang="en">Energy</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="25">
        <name lang="de">Raumplanung</name>
        <name lang="fr">Aménagement du territoire</name>
        <name lang="it">Pianificazione del territorio</name>
        <name lang="en">Spatial Planning</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="29">
        <name lang="de">Umwelt und Natur</name>
        <name lang="fr">Environnement et nature</name>
        <name lang="it">Ambiente e natura</name>
        <name lang="en">Environment and Nature</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="45">
        <name lang="de">Technologie</name>
        <name lang="fr">Technologie</name>
        <name lang="it">Tecnologia</name>
        <name lang="en">Technology</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
