<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="99866" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2024-01-30</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="323" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>701</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidg. Materialprüfungs- und Forschungsanstalt</name>
      <name lang="fr">Laboratoire fédéral d'essai des matériaux et de recherche</name>
      <name lang="it">Laboratorio federale di prova dei materiali e di ricerca</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Laboratory for Materials Testing and Research</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.empa.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.empa.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.empa.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.empa.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">contact@empa.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">contact@empa.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">contact@empa.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">contact@empa.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="701">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Wirtschaft, Bildung und Forschung</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'économie, de la formation et de la recherche</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'economia, della formazione e della ricerca</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Economic Affairs, Education and Research</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Dübendorf, St. Gallen und Thun</city>
      <title>Empa-Forschungspreise verliehen: Wenn Zufall und wissenschaftliche Exzellenz aufeinandertreffen</title>
      <lead>2023 wurden gleich zwei herausragende Publikationen von jungen Forschenden mit dem Empa-Forschungspreis ausgezeichnet. Die Preisträger, Amogh Kinikar und Shih-Chi Yang, haben ihre prämierten Arbeiten während ihres Doktorats an der Empa verfasst.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Die ehemaligen Empa-Doktoranden Shih-Chi Yang und Amogh Kinikar haben je einen Empa-Forschungspreis 2023 für herausragende wissenschaftliche Arbeiten erhalten. Beide Jungforscher sind teilweise durch Zufall auf ihre Entdeckungen gestossen – hatten aber auch die Geistesgegenwart und die Beharrlichkeit, um den Zufallsbefund weiterzuverfolgen und dessen Bedeutung zu erkennen.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Eine unerwartete Reaktion&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Als Doktorand im Empa-Labor «nanotech@surfaces» wollte Amogh Kinikar eigentlich bestimmte Arten von Graphen-Nanobändern synthetisieren. Diese flachen Kohlenstoff-Strukturen sind nur eine Atomlage dick und wenige Atome breit, was ihnen einzigartige elektromagnetische Eigenschaften verleiht. Um sie herzustellen, wollte Kinikar Ausgangsmoleküle – Kohlenwasserstoffe mit Brom-Reaktionszentren – auf einer Goldoberfläche zur Reaktion bringen. Doch anstatt sich zu langen Bändchen zusammenzufügen, verbanden sich jeweils zwei der Moleküle zu einem Dimer. Die Reaktion passierte dabei nicht am erwarteten Reaktionszentrum, sondern an einer sogenannten Isopropyl-Gruppe, die lediglich aus Kohlenstoff und Wasserstoff besteht und normalerweise kaum mit etwas reagiert. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Die neu entstandene Struktur in der Mitte des Dimers identifizierte Kinikar mittels Rastertunnelmikroskopie als Benzolring, oder, chemisch genauer gesagt, als Phenylenring. Was der ausgebildete Physiker zu diesem Zeitpunkt noch nicht wusste: Die Synthese von Benzolringen gilt in der organischen Chemie als äusserst schwierig. Die wenigen Reaktionsmechanismen, die bisher bekannt sind, benötigen hochreaktive Ausgangsmoleküle. «Ein Chemiker hätte niemals gewagt zu behaupten, das sei ein Benzolring», lacht Kinikar. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Er sollte dennoch recht behalten: Er hatte einen komplett neuen Synthesepfad für Benzolringe entdeckt. «Dass aus einer Kombination von unreaktiven Gruppen auf einem unreaktiven Metall eine nachweislich schwer zu synthetisierende Verbindung entsteht, war überraschend», sagt der Forscher. Die Chemikerinnen und Chemiker in seinem Team wollten ihm das zunächst gar nicht glauben. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Doch mit der Zeit gelang es Kinikar und seinen Mitforschenden, den Mechanismus hinter der unerwarteten Reaktion zu verstehen. Durch interdisziplinäre Zusammenarbeit – in diesem Fall Chemie, Physik und rechnergestützten Wissenschaften – konnten sie nachweisen, dass sich dabei tatsächlich Benzolringe bilden. Ihre Ergebnisse veröffentlichen die Forschenden in der Zeitschrift «Nature Synthesis». Dafür hat Erstautor Kinikar nun den Empa-Forschungspreis erhalten. Seit seiner Promotion 2022 forscht Amogh Kinikar als Postdoc weiterhin an der Empa, nach wir vor im «nanotech@surfaces»-Labor. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Rekordeffizienz nebenbei erreicht&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Auch Shih-Chi Yang wollte sich in seinem Doktorat ursprünglich auf ein anderes Projekt fokussieren. Er arbeitete im Empa-Labor «Dünnfilme und Photovoltaik» an sogenannten CIGS-Solarzellen. CIGS steht für Kupfer-Indium-Gallium-Diselenid. Diese Dünnschichtzellen sind materialsparend und leicht, und können im Gegensatz zu herkömmlichen Silizium-Solarzellen auf flexiblen Unterlagen hergestellt werden.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Ausserdem ist es theoretisch möglich, zweiseitige CIGS-Solarzellen herzustellen – sogenannte bifaziale Zellen. Die Rückseite kann reflektiertes und diffuses Licht einfangen und so die Leistungsdichte weiter steigern. «Leider gab es in der Praxis eine grosse Hürde», so Yang. «CIGS-Zellen werden normalerweise bei Temperaturen von über 400 bis 500 Grad Celsius hergestellt. Bei diesen Temperaturen bildet sich an der Rückseite Galliumoxid, was die Leistung der Zelle stark beeinträchtigt.»&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Wie es der Zufall wollte, hatte Yang in einem vorangehenden Projekt das Herstellungsverfahren für monofaziale CIGS-Zellen durch Zugabe von Silber so verfeinert, dass es bei einer niedrigeren Temperatur stattfinden konnte. Das Projekt hatte zum Ziel, die Substrattemperatur zu senken und gleichzeitig eine gute Qualität der CIGS-Absorber zu erhalten – doch Yang dachte auch an das Potenzial für die bifazialen Zellen. Er startete ein Nebenprojekt, um mit dem neuen Verfahren bifaziale CIGS-Zellen herzustellen und die Herausforderungen bei ihrer Produktion anzugehen. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Die ersten Ergebnisse waren so überzeugend, dass aus einem Nebenprojekt schnell das Hauptprojekt von Yangs Doktorarbeit wurde. Mit seinem neuen Ansatz erzielte er eine Rekordeffizienz für bifaziale CIGS-Solarzellen. Die Ergebnisse veröffentlichte er gemeinsam mit seinen Mitforschenden in der Zeitschrift «Nature Energy». Für diese Publikation hat Yang nun ebenfalls einen Empa-Forschungspreis erhalten. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Marktreif sind die bifazialen CIGS-Zellen noch nicht. «Für industrielle Anwendungen müssten die Produktionsprozesse noch weiter verfeinert werden», weiss Yang. «Aber wir konnten im Labor zeigen: Es funktioniert. Also lohnt es sich, diese Technologie weiter zu erforschen.» Die weitere Forschung überlässt Yang seinen ehemaligen Kolleginnen und Kollegen bei der Empa. Er selbst arbeitet seit April 2023 als Datenwissenschaftler mit Schwerpunkt Maschinelles Lernen in der Industrie. «Die analytischen Fähigkeiten und das kritische Denken, die ich während des Doktorats entwickelt habe, kann ich jetzt seht gut anwenden», sagt er.&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Dr. Amogh Kinikar Empa, nanotech@surfaces Tel. +41 58 765 40 91 amogh.kinikar@empa.ch Dr. Romain Carron Empa, Thin Films and Photovoltaics Tel. +41 58 765 47 91 romain.carron@empa.ch</contact>
      <attachment id="269903">
        <title>Shih-Chi Yang (links) und Amogh Kinikar haben den Empa-Forschungspreis 2023 erhalten. Bild: Empa</title>
        <format>jpg</format>
        <size-kb>3268</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/85874.jpg</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <link id="269907">
        <title>Empa-Forschungspreise verliehen: Wenn Zufall und wissenschaftliche Exzellenz aufeinandertreffen</title>
        <uri>https://www.empa.ch/web/s604/empa-forschungspreise-2023</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="269909">
        <title>A Kinikar, M Di Giovannantonio, JI Urgel, K Eimre, Z Qiu, Y Gu, E Jin, A Narita, XY Wang, K Müllen, P Ruffieux, CA Pignedoli, R Fasel; On-surface polyarylene synthesis by cycloaromatization of isopropyl substituents; Nature Synthesis (2022);</title>
        <uri>https://doi.org/10.1038/s44160-022-00032-5</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="269910">
        <title>SC Yang, TY Lin, M Ochoa, H Lai, R Kothandaraman, F Fu, AN Tiwari, R Carron; Efficiency boost of bifacial Cu(In,Ga)Se2 thin-film solar cells for flexible and tandem applications with silver-assisted low-temperature process; Nature Energy (2022);</title>
        <uri>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41560-022-01157-9</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Dübendorf, St. Gallen und Thun</city>
      <title>Prix de recherche de l’Empa décernés : Quand hasard et excellence scientifique se rencontrent</title>
      <lead>En 2023, deux publications exceptionnelles de jeunes chercheurs ont été récompensées par le prix de recherche de l'Empa. Les lauréats, Amogh Kinikar et Shih-Chi Yang, ont rédigé leurs travaux primés pendant leur doctorat à l'Empa.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Shih-Chi Yang et Amogh Kinikar, deux anciens doctorants de l'Empa, ont reçu chacun un prix de recherche 2023 de l'Empa pour des travaux scientifiques exceptionnels. Les deux jeunes chercheurs sont en partie tombés sur leurs découvertes par hasard – mais ils ont aussi eu la présence d'esprit et la persévérance de poursuivre la découverte fortuite et d'en reconnaître l'importance.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Une réaction inattendue&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;En tant que doctorant au laboratoire "nanotech@surfaces" de l'Empa, Amogh Kinikar voulait en fait synthétiser certains types de nanobandes de graphène. Ces structures plates en carbone n'ont qu'une couche atomique d'épaisseur et quelques atomes de largeur, ce qui leur confère des propriétés électromagnétiques uniques. Pour les fabriquer, Amogh Kinikar voulait faire réagir des molécules de départ – des hydrocarbures avec des centres de réaction au brome – sur une surface d'or. Mais au lieu de s'assembler en longues bandes, deux des molécules se sont combinées pour former un dimère. La réaction ne s'est pas produite au niveau du centre de réaction attendu, mais au niveau d'un groupe dit isopropyle, composé uniquement de carbone et d'hydrogène et qui ne réagit normalement pas avec grand-chose.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Grâce à la microscopie à balayage à effet tunnel, Amogh Kinikar a identifié la nouvelle structure qui s'est formée au centre du dimère comme étant un cycle benzénique ou, plus précisément d'un point de vue chimique, un cycle phénylène. Ce que ce physicien de formation ne savait pas encore à ce moment-là, c'est que la synthèse de cycles benzéniques est considérée comme extrêmement difficile en chimie organique. Les quelques mécanismes de réaction connus à ce jour nécessitent des molécules de départ très réactives. "Un chimiste n'aurait jamais osé affirmer qu'il s'agissait d'un cycle benzénique", s'amuse Amogh Kinikar.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Il devait néanmoins avoir raison : Il avait découvert une voie de synthèse entièrement nouvelle pour les cycles benzéniques. "Le fait qu'une combinaison de groupes non réactifs sur un métal non réactif donne naissance à un composé dont il a été démontré qu'il était difficile à synthétiser était surprenant", explique le chercheur. Les chimistes de son équipe ne voulaient tout d'abord pas le croire.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Mais au fil du temps, Amogh Kinikar et ses collègues de recherche ont réussi à comprendre le mécanisme derrière cette réaction inattendue. Grâce à une collaboration interdisciplinaire – en l'occurrence la chimie, la physique et les sciences assistées par ordinateur – ils ont pu démontrer que des cycles benzéniques se forment effectivement. Les chercheurs publient leurs résultats dans la revue "Nature Synthesis". Amogh Kinikar, premier auteur, a reçu pour cela le prix de recherche de l’Empa. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Depuis son doctorat en 2022, Amogh Kinikar poursuit ses recherches postdoctorales à l'Empa, toujours dans le laboratoire "nanotech@surfaces".&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Une efficacité record obtenue au passage&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Au départ, Shih-Chi Yang voulait lui aussi se concentrer sur un autre projet pendant son doctorat. Il a travaillé au laboratoire "Thin Films and Photovoltaics" de l'Empa sur ce qu'on appelle les cellules solaires CIGS. CIGS signifie cuivre-indium-gallium-disélénide. Ces cellules en couches minces sont peu gourmandes en matériaux, légères et peuvent être fabriquées sur des supports souples, contrairement aux cellules solaires traditionnelles en silicium.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;En outre, il est théoriquement possible de fabriquer des cellules solaires CIGS à deux faces, appelées cellules bifaciales. La face arrière peut capter la lumière réfléchie et diffuse, ce qui augmente encore la densité de puissance. "Malheureusement, il y avait un gros obstacle dans la pratique", explique Shih-Chi Yang. "Les cellules CIGS sont normalement fabriquées à des températures de plus de 400 à 500 degrés Celsius. À ces températures, de l'oxyde de gallium se forme sur l'interface arrière, ce qui affecte fortement les performances de la cellule".&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Comme par hasard, dans un projet précédent, Shih-Chi Yang avait affiné le processus de fabrication des cellules CIGS monofaciales en ajoutant de l'argent de manière à ce qu'il puisse se faire à une température plus basse. Le projet avait pour but d'abaisser la température du substrat tout en obtenant des absorbeurs CIGS de bonne qualité – mais le chercheur pensait aussi au potentiel des cellules bifaciales. Il a lancé un projet annexe visant à produire des cellules CIGS bifaciales à l'aide du nouveau procédé et à relever les défis liés à leur production.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Les premiers résultats ont été si convaincants qu'un projet secondaire est rapidement devenu le projet principal de la thèse de doctorat de Shih-Chi Yang. Grâce à sa nouvelle approche, il a obtenu une efficacité record pour les cellules solaires CIGS bifaciales. Il a publié ses résultats avec ses collègues de recherche dans la revue "Nature Energy". Pour cette publication, Shih-Chi Yang a également reçu un prix de recherche de l'Empa.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Les cellules CIGS bifaciales ne sont pas encore prêtes à être commercialisées. "Pour les applications industrielles, les processus de production devraient être encore plus affinés", dit Shih-Chi Yang. "Mais nous avons pu le montrer en laboratoire : Cela fonctionne. Cela vaut donc la peine de poursuivre les recherches sur cette technologie". Shih-Chi Yang laisse la poursuite des recherches à ses anciens collègues de l'Empa. Lui-même travaille depuis avril 2023 comme scientifique des données spécialisé dans l'apprentissage automatique dans l'industrie. "Les compétences analytiques et la pensée critique que j'ai développées pendant mon doctorat sont maintenant très utiles", dit-il.&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Dr. Amogh Kinikar Empa, nanotech@surfaces Tél. +41 58 765 40 91 amogh.kinikar@empa.ch Dr. Romain Carron Empa, Thin Films and Photovoltaics Tél. +41 58 765 47 91 romain.carron@empa.ch</contact>
      <attachment id="269904">
        <title>Shih-Chi Yang (à gauche) et Amogh Kinikar ont reçu le prix de recherche 2023 de l'Empa. Image : Empa</title>
        <format>jpg</format>
        <size-kb>3268</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/85875.jpg</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <link id="269908">
        <title>Prix de recherche de l’Empa décernés : Quand hasard et excellence scientifique se rencontrent</title>
        <uri>https://www.empa.ch/web/s604/empa-forschungspreise-2023</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="269909">
        <title>A Kinikar, M Di Giovannantonio, JI Urgel, K Eimre, Z Qiu, Y Gu, E Jin, A Narita, XY Wang, K Müllen, P Ruffieux, CA Pignedoli, R Fasel; On-surface polyarylene synthesis by cycloaromatization of isopropyl substituents; Nature Synthesis (2022);</title>
        <uri>https://doi.org/10.1038/s44160-022-00032-5</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="269910">
        <title>SC Yang, TY Lin, M Ochoa, H Lai, R Kothandaraman, F Fu, AN Tiwari, R Carron; Efficiency boost of bifacial Cu(In,Ga)Se2 thin-film solar cells for flexible and tandem applications with silver-assisted low-temperature process; Nature Energy (2022);</title>
        <uri>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41560-022-01157-9</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Dübendorf, St. Gallen und Thun</city>
      <title>Empa Research Awards 2023: When serendipity meets excellence</title>
      <lead>Two outstanding publications by young researchers were honored with the Empa Research Award. The recipients, Amogh Kinikar and Shih-Chi Yang, wrote their award-winning papers during their doctoral studies at Empa.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Former Empa doctoral students Shih-Chi Yang and Amogh Kinikar received the Empa Research Awards 2023 for their outstanding scientific work. Both researchers came across their discoveries partly by chance – but also had the presence of mind and perseverance to follow up on their lucky punch and to recognize its significance.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;An unexpected reaction&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;As a doctoral student in Empa's nanotech@surfaces laboratory, Amogh Kinikar originally wanted to synthesize certain types of graphene nanoribbons. These flat carbon structures, only one atom thick and a few atoms wide, possess unique and interesting electromagnetic properties. To produce them, Kinikar wanted to make starting molecules – hydrocarbons with bromine reaction centers – react with each other on a gold surface.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Instead of linking to each other to form long ribbons, however, the molecules paired up to form dimers. Nor did the reaction take place at the expected reaction center. Instead, the molecules reacted at so-called isopropyl groups, which consist only of carbon and hydrogen and normally hardly react with anything.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Using scanning tunneling microscopy, Kinikar identified the newly formed structure in the middle of the dimer as a benzene ring, or more technically a phenylene ring. What the trained physicist did not know at the time was that the synthesis of benzene rings is considered extremely difficult in organic chemistry. The few reaction mechanisms known to produce such rings all require highly reactive starting molecules. "A chemist would never have dared to claim that this was a benzene ring," laughs Kinikar.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;However, he was proved right: He had discovered a completely new synthesis pathway for benzene rings. "The fact that a compound that was demonstrably difficult to synthesize was created from a combination of unreactive groups on an unreactive metal surface was indeed a surprise," says the researcher. The chemists in his team initially refused to believe him.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;But over time, Kinikar and his colleagues succeeded in understanding the mechanism behind the unexpected reaction. Through a collaboration between chemists, physicists and computational scientists, they were able to prove that benzene rings do indeed form in the process. The team published their results in the journal Nature Synthesis. First author Kinikar has now been awarded the Empa Research Award for this paper. After completing his doctorate in 2022, Kinikar remained at Empa as a postdoc at the nanotech@surfaces lab.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Side project leads to record efficiency&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Shih-Chi Yang also originally planned to focus on a different project during his doctorate. He worked in Empa's Thin Films and Photovoltaics laboratory on so-called CIGS solar cells. CIGS stands for copper indium gallium diselenide. These thin-film cells are material-saving and lightweight and, unlike conventional silicon solar cells, can be produced on flexible substrates.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;In addition, it is theoretically possible to produce bifacial CIGS solar cells. The rear side can capture reflected and diffuse light and thus further increase the overall efficiency of the cell. "Unfortunately, in practice, there was a major hurdle," says Yang. "CIGS cells are normally produced at temperatures of more than 400 to 500 degrees Celsius. At these temperatures, gallium oxide forms at the back interface, which severely impairs performance."&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;As luck would have it, Yang had refined the manufacturing process for monofacial CIGS cells in a previous project, allowing it to take place at a lower temperature with the help of silver. The project was aimed at reducing the substrate temperature while maintaining good CIGS absorber quality – but Yang also thought of its potential for producing bifacial cells. He began a side project, in which he attempted to use the new process to make bifacial CIGS cells and tackle the long-standing challenges with their production.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The initial results were so convincing that the side project quickly turned into the main project of Yang's doctoral thesis. With his new approach, he achieved a record efficiency for bifacial CIGS solar cells. Together with his colleagues, he published the results in the journal Nature Energy – and now received the Empa Research Award for this publication.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Bifacial CIGS cells are not ready to hit the market yet. "For industrial applications, the production processes still need to be improved," says Yang. "But we were able to show: This technology works, and it's worth exploring even further." Yang, however, is leaving future research to his former colleagues at Empa. He has been working as a Machine Learning data scientist in industry since April 2023. "The analytical skills and critical thinking that I was able to develop during my doctorate at Empa are serving me very well," he says.&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Dr. Amogh Kinikar Empa, nanotech@surfaces Phone +41 58 765 40 91 amogh.kinikar@empa.ch Dr. Romain Carron Empa, Thin Films and Photovoltaics Phone +41 58 765 47 91 romain.carron@empa.ch</contact>
      <attachment id="269905">
        <title>Shih-Chi Yang (left) and Amogh Kinikar have each received an Empa Research Award 2023. Image: Empa</title>
        <format>jpg</format>
        <size-kb>3268</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/85876.jpg</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <link id="269906">
        <title>Empa Research Awards 2023: When serendipity meets excellence</title>
        <uri>https://www.empa.ch/web/s604/empa-forschungspreise-2023</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="269909">
        <title>A Kinikar, M Di Giovannantonio, JI Urgel, K Eimre, Z Qiu, Y Gu, E Jin, A Narita, XY Wang, K Müllen, P Ruffieux, CA Pignedoli, R Fasel; On-surface polyarylene synthesis by cycloaromatization of isopropyl substituents; Nature Synthesis (2022);</title>
        <uri>https://doi.org/10.1038/s44160-022-00032-5</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="269910">
        <title>SC Yang, TY Lin, M Ochoa, H Lai, R Kothandaraman, F Fu, AN Tiwari, R Carron; Efficiency boost of bifacial Cu(In,Ga)Se2 thin-film solar cells for flexible and tandem applications with silver-assisted low-temperature process; Nature Energy (2022);</title>
        <uri>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41560-022-01157-9</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="8">
        <name lang="de">Bildung und Forschung</name>
        <name lang="fr">Formation et recherche</name>
        <name lang="it">Formazione e ricerca</name>
        <name lang="en">Education and Research</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="11">
        <name lang="de">Energie</name>
        <name lang="fr">Énergie</name>
        <name lang="it">Energia</name>
        <name lang="en">Energy</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="45">
        <name lang="de">Technologie</name>
        <name lang="fr">Technologie</name>
        <name lang="it">Tecnologia</name>
        <name lang="en">Technology</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
