<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="66453" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2017-04-24</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="804" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>801</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Generalsekretariat UVEK</name>
      <name lang="fr">Secrétariat général DETEC</name>
      <name lang="it">Segreteria generale DATEC</name>
      <name lang="en">General Secretariat of the Federal Department of Environment, Transport, Energy and Communications; General Secretariat DETEC</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.uvek.admin.ch/uvek/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.uvek.admin.ch/uvek/fr/home.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.uvek.admin.ch/uvek/it/home.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.uvek.admin.ch/uvek/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-uvek.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-uvek.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-uvek.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-uvek.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="801">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Umwelt, Verkehr, Energie und Kommunikation</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'environnement, des transports, de l'énergie et de la communication</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'ambiente, dei trasporti, dell'energia e delle comunicazioni</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of the Environment, Transport, Energy and Communications</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.uvek.admin.ch/uvek/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.uvek.admin.ch/uvek/fr/home.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.uvek.admin.ch/uvek/it/home.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.uvek.admin.ch/uvek/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-uvek.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-uvek.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-uvek.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-uvek.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Bundespräsidentin Leuthard für Gespräche mit kroatischer Regierung in Zagreb</title>
      <lead>Bundespräsidentin Doris Leuthard reist am Dienstag, 25. April 2017, für einen offiziellen Besuch in die kroatische Hauptstadt Zagreb. Im Zentrum der Gespräche mit Präsidentin Kolinda Grabar-Kitarović und Premierminister Andrej Plenković werden bilaterale Fragen sowie die Europapolitik stehen. Die Schweiz und Kroatien feiern dieses Jahr das 25-jährige Jubiläum ihrer diplomatischen Beziehungen. </lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Zur Sprache kommen werden unter anderem Fragen der wirtschaftlichen Zusammenarbeit sowie Umwelt-, Energie- und Forschungsthemen. Mit Blick auf die Politik der Schweiz gegenüber der Europäischen Union (EU) und die europapolitischen Schwerpunkte des EU-Mitglieds Kroatien wird auch die Erweiterung der Personenfreizügigkeit auf Kroatien Gegenstand der Gespräche sein. Der Bundesrat ratifizierte das entsprechende Protokoll III, nachdem das Parlament Mitte Dezember 2016 das Umsetzungsgesetz zu Art. 121a BV (Umsetzung des Zuwanderungsartikels) verabschiedet hatte. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Zu den weiteren Gesprächsthemen zählen die Migration nach Europa, die Lage in Südosteuropa sowie die Zusammenarbeit zwischen der Schweiz und Kroatien auf internationaler Ebene. Das Besuchsprogramm sieht vor, dass Bundespräsidentin Leuthard die neuen Räumlichkeiten der Schweizer Botschaft in Zagreb eröffnet. &lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Kommunikation UVEK, Tel. +41 58 462 55 11</contact>
      <link id="165786">
        <title>EDA: Bilaterale Beziehungen Schweiz–Kroatien</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home/vertretungen-und-reisehinweise/kroatien/bilatereale-beziehungenschweizkroatien.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>La présidente de la Confédération se rendra en visite officielle à Zagreb</title>
      <lead>Le mardi 25 avril 2017, la présidente de la Confédération Doris Leuthard se rendra dans la capitale de la Croatie, pour une visite officielle. Les discussions à Zagreb avec la présidente, Mme Kolinda Grabar-Kitarović, et le premier ministre, M. Andrej Plenković, porteront sur des questions bilatérales et sur la politique européenne. La Suisse et la Croatie célèbrent cette année le 25e anniversaire de leurs relations diplomatiques. </lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Parmi les thèmes évoqués figureront notamment des questions liées à la coopération économique, mais aussi à l’environnement, à l’énergie et à la recherche. S’agissant de la politique de la Suisse à l’égard de l’Union européenne (UE) et des sujets de politique européenne revêtant une importance particulière pour la Croatie en sa qualité de membre de l’UE, il sera aussi question de l’extension de l’accord sur la libre circulation des personnes à la Croatie. Le Conseil fédéral a ratifié le protocole relatif à la Croatie (protocole III) après l’adoption par le Parlement de la loi d’application de l’art. 121a Cst. (mise en œuvre de l’article sur l’immigration) à la mi-décembre 2016. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Les discussions porteront par ailleurs sur la migration vers l’Europe, sur la situation en Europe du Sud-Est et sur la coopération entre la Suisse et la Croatie au plan international. Le programme de la visite prévoit que Mme Leuthard inaugurera les nouveaux locaux de l’ambassade de Suisse à Zagreb. &lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Communication DETEC, tél. +41 58 462 55 11</contact>
      <link id="165787">
        <title>DFAE: Relations bilatérales Suisse–Croatie</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae/representations-et-conseils-aux-voyageurs/croatie/suisse-croatie.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>La presidente della Confederazione Doris Leuthard a Zagabria per colloqui con il Governo croato</title>
      <lead>Il 25 aprile 2017 la presidente della Confederazione Doris Leuthard si recherà per una visita ufficiale nella capitale croata Zagabria. I colloqui con la presidente Kolinda Grabar-Kitarović e il primo ministro Andrej Plenković saranno incentrati su questioni bilaterali e sulla politica europea. La Svizzera e la Croazia celebreranno quest’anno il 25° anniversario delle loro relazioni diplomatiche.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Tra i temi che verranno affrontati figurano tra l’altro la cooperazione economica, l’ambiente, l’energia e la ricerca. Nell’ottica della politica della Svizzera nei confronti dell’Unione europea (UE) e degli aspetti centrali della politica europea della Croazia, membro dell’UE, si esaminerà anche la questione dell’estensione della libera circolazione alla Croazia. Dopo che a metà dicembre 2016 il Parlamento ha adottato la legge di attuazione dell’articolo 121&lt;i&gt;a&lt;/i&gt; della Costituzione (attuazione dell’articolo costituzionale sull’immigrazione), il Consiglio federale ha ratificato il relativo Protocollo III.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Nei colloqui si discuterà anche di migrazione verso l’Europa, della situazione nell’Europa sudorientale e della collaborazione tra la Svizzera e la Croazia a livello internazionale. Il programma della visita prevede inoltre l’inaugurazione dei nuovi locali dell’Ambasciata svizzera di Zagabria da parte della presidente della Confederazione Leuthard.&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Comunicazione DATEC, tel. +41 58 462 55 11</contact>
      <link id="165788">
        <title>DFAE: Relazioni bilaterali Svizzera–Croazia</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae/rappresentanze-e-consigli-di-viaggio/croazia/svizzera-croazia.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>President Leuthard in Zagreb for talks with Croatian government</title>
      <lead>President Doris Leuthard will travel to the Croatian capital Zagreb for an official meeting on Tuesday, 25 April. The talks with President Kolinda Grabar-Kitarović and Prime Minister Andrej Plenković will focus on bilateral relations and European policy. Switzerland and Croatia are celebrating the 25th anniversary of diplomatic relations this year.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Discussions are expected to cover economic cooperation, environmental and energy policy and research. With regard to Switzerland’s policy towards the European Union and Croatia’s European policy priorities, the extension of the freedom of movement to Croatia will also be addressed. The Federal Council ratified the relevant protocol after Parliament adopted the act implementing Art. 121a of the Federal Constitution (implementation of the immigration article) in mid- December 2016.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Further topics of discussion include migration to Europe, the situation in south-eastern Europe as well as cooperation between Switzerland and Croatia at international level. President Leuthard will also open the new offices of the Swiss embassy in Zagreb during her visit. &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Communication DETEC, +41 58 462 55 11</contact>
      <link id="165789">
        <title>FDFA: Bilateral relations Switzerland–Croatia</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home/representations-and-travel-advice/croatia/switzerland-croatia.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <keywords>
      <keyword id="430" org-id="804">
        <name lang="de">Forschung</name>
        <name lang="fr">Recherche</name>
        <name lang="it">Ricerca</name>
        <name lang="en">Research</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="560" org-id="804">
        <name lang="de">Internationales</name>
        <name lang="fr">Affaires internationales</name>
        <name lang="it">Affari Internazionali</name>
        <name lang="en">International Affairs</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="200" org-id="804">
        <name lang="de">Bundespräsident</name>
        <name lang="fr">Président de la Confédération</name>
        <name lang="it">Presidente della Confederazione</name>
        <name lang="en">President of the Confederation</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="1700" org-id="804">
        <name lang="de">Wirtschaft</name>
        <name lang="fr">Economie</name>
        <name lang="it">Economia</name>
        <name lang="en">Economy</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="1600" org-id="804">
        <name lang="de">Umweltpolitik</name>
        <name lang="fr">Umweltpolitik</name>
        <name lang="it">Umweltpolitik</name>
        <name lang="en">Umweltpolitik</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="310" org-id="804">
        <name lang="de">Energiepolitik</name>
        <name lang="fr">Energiepolitik</name>
        <name lang="it">Energiepolitik</name>
        <name lang="en">Energiepolitik</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="121212" org-id="804">
        <name lang="de">Doris Leuthard</name>
        <name lang="fr">Doris Leuthard</name>
        <name lang="it">Doris Leuthard</name>
        <name lang="en">Doris Leuthard</name>
      </keyword>
    </keywords>
    <topics>
      <topic id="11">
        <name lang="de">Energie</name>
        <name lang="fr">Énergie</name>
        <name lang="it">Energia</name>
        <name lang="en">Energy</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="29">
        <name lang="de">Umwelt und Natur</name>
        <name lang="fr">Environnement et nature</name>
        <name lang="it">Ambiente e natura</name>
        <name lang="en">Environment and Nature</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="33">
        <name lang="de">Bundespräsident/-in</name>
        <name lang="fr">Président/e de la Confédération</name>
        <name lang="it">Presidente della Confederazione</name>
        <name lang="en">President of the Swiss Confederation</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="47">
        <name lang="de">Wirtschaft</name>
        <name lang="fr">Économie</name>
        <name lang="it">Economia</name>
        <name lang="en">Economic Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
