<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="66236" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2017-04-04</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="1058" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>401</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidg. Revisionsaufsichtsbehörde</name>
      <name lang="fr">Autorité fédérale de surveillance en matière de révision</name>
      <name lang="it">Autorità federale di sorveglianza dei revisori</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Audit Oversight Authority</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.rab-asr.ch/de/</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.rab-asr.ch/fr/</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.rab-asr.ch/it/</www>
      <www lang="en"/>
      <email lang="de">info@rab-asr.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@rab-asr.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@rab-asr.ch</email>
      <email lang="en"/>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="201" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>201</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="401">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Justiz- und Polizeidepartement</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de justice et police</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale di giustizia e polizia</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Justice and Police</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.ejpd.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.ejpd.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.ejpd.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.ejpd.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-ejpd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">Info@gs-ejpd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-ejpd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-ejpd.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <department id="201">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Wahl von Frank Schneider zum Vize-Vorsitzenden der IFIAR</title>
      <lead>Der Direktor der Eidgenössischen Revisionsaufsichtsbehörde (RAB), Frank Schneider, wurde am Dienstag, den 4. April, als Vize-Vorsitzender des internationalen Forums der unabhängigen Revisionsaufsichtsbehörden (IFIAR) gewählt. </lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Die 54 Mitglieder des internationalen Forums der unabhängigen Revisionsaufsichtsbehörden (International Forum of Independent Audit Regulators, IFIAR) bestimmten anlässlich ihrer Plenarversammlung in Tokio (Japan) einen neuen Vize-Vorsitzenden und wählten dafür zum ersten Mal überhaupt einen Schweizer Vertreter für eine zweijährige Mandatszeit (2017-2019). &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;IFIAR wurde 2006 von unabhängigen Revisionsaufsichtsbehörden aus 17 Ländern gegründet. IFIAR trägt zur Wissensvermittlung im Revisionsbereich und zum Austausch von Praxiserfahrungen aus der unabhängigen Revisionsaufsichtstätigkeit bei, fördert die Zusammenarbeit und Vereinheitlichung der Aufsichtspraxis und stellt eine Plattform für den Austausch mit anderen internationalen Organisationen bereit.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Dank seiner beruflichen Erfahrung, unter anderem als langjähriger Direktor der RAB, verfügt Frank Schneider über ausgewiesene und international anerkannte Kompetenzen im Bereich der Revisionsaufsicht. Die Schweiz begrüsst die Wahl von Frank Schneider zum Vize-Vorsitzenden der IFIAR. Sie stärkt damit die Präsenz von Schweizerinnen und Schweizern in leitenden Funktionen von internationalen Organisationen.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Kommunikation EDA Bundeshaus West CH-3003 Bern Tel. Kommunikationsservice: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Medienstelle: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Élection de Frank Schneider à la vice-présidence de l’IFIAR</title>
      <lead>Le directeur de l’Autorité fédérale de surveillance en matière de révision (ASR) Frank Schneider a été nommé, ce mardi 4 avril, vice-président du Forum international des régulateurs indépendants de l'audit (IFIAR). </lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Lors de leur assemblée plénière qui s’est tenue à Tokyo, au Japon, les 54 membres du Forum international des régulateurs indépendants de l'audit (International Forum of Independent Audit Regulators, IFIAR) ont élu un nouveau vice-président pour un mandat de deux ans (2017-2019). C’est la première fois qu’un représentant suisse est désigné à cette fonction. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;L’IFIAR a été créé en 2006 par des autorités de surveillance indépendantes en matière de révision issues de 17 pays. Il contribue au transfert de connaissances dans le domaine de la révision et aux échanges sur la pratique; il encourage la coopération et l’uniformisation des règles en matière de surveillance; et il met à disposition une plateforme permettant les échanges entre organisations internationales.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;L’expérience qu’il s’est forgée, notamment au poste de directeur de l’ASR (l’autorité fédérale de surveillance en matière de révision) qu’il occupe depuis plusieurs années , a doté Frank Schneider d’excellentes compétences dans le domaine, reconnues au plan international. La Suisse salue son élection à la vice-présidence de l’IFIAR, élection qui assied la présence de ses ressortissants dans des fonctions dirigeantes au sein d’organisations internationals.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Communication DFAE Palais fédéral ouest CH-3003 Berne Tél. Service de communication: +41 58 462 31 53 Tél. Service de presse: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Nomina di Frank Schneider a vicepresidente dell’IFIAR</title>
      <lead>Martedì 4 aprile il direttore dell’Autorità federale di sorveglianza dei revisori (ASR), Frank Schneider, è stato nominato vicepresidente dell’International Forum of Independent Audit Regulators (IFIAR). </lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Durante l’assemblea plenaria, che si è tenuta a Tokyo (Giappone), i 54 membri dell’International Forum of Independent Audit Regulators (IFIAR), il forum internazionale delle autorità di revisione indipendenti, hanno nominato un nuovo vicepresidente e, per la prima volta, hanno scelto un rappresentante svizzero per questo mandato biennale (2017-2019). &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;L’IFIAR è stato istituito nel 2006 dalle autorità di revisione indipendenti di 17 Paesi. Il Forum contribuisce alla trasmissione delle conoscenze nel campo dell’audit e allo scambio di esperienze concernenti le attività di revisione, promuove la collaborazione e la standardizzazione delle procedure e mette a disposizione una piattaforma per i contatti con altre organizzazioni internazionali.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Grazie alla sua esperienza professionale, tra l’altro come direttore da molti anni dell’Autorità federale di sorveglianza dei revisori (ASR), Frank Schneider ha una competenza comprovata e riconosciuta a livello internazionale in questo settore. La Svizzera si congratula con Frank Schneider per la sua nomina a vicepresidente dell’IFIAR. Questa scelta rafforza la presenza di cittadine e cittadini svizzeri nelle funzioni dirigenziali all’interno delle organizzazioni internazionali.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Comunicazione DFAE Palazzo federale ovest CH-3003 Berna Tel. Servizio di comunicazione: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Servizio stampa: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Election of Frank Schneider as vice chair of the IFIAR</title>
      <lead>Frank Schneider, director of the Federal Oversight Audit Authority of Switzerland (FAOA), was elected on 4 April as vice chair of the International Forum of Independent Audit Regulators (IFIAR). </lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;At a plenary meeting in Tokyo, the 54 members of the International Forum of Independent Audit Regulators (IFIAR) have elected Frank Schneider as their organisation’s new vice chair for a two-year term (2017–2019). This is the first time that a Swiss national has been appointed to this post. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The IFIAR was founded in 2006 by independent audit regulators from 18 jurisdictions. The IFIAR contributes to sharing knowledge of the audit market environment and practical experience of independent audit regulatory activity, promotes collaboration and consistency in regulatory activity, and provides a platform for dialogue with other international organisations that have an interest in audit quality.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Thanks to his professional experience, including as director of the FAOA over the past decade, Frank Schneider has proven and internationally recognised expertise in the field of auditing. Switzerland welcomes Frank Schneider’s election as vice chair of the IFIAR, which will strengthen the presence of Swiss nationals in leading positions in international organisations.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>FDFA Communication Federal Palace West Wing CH-3003 Bern, Switzerland Tel. Communication service: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Press service: +41 58 460 55 55 E-mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @SwissMFA</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
