<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="66263" revoked="no">
    <version>2</version>
    <pubdate>2017-04-05</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="1070" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>1070</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Der Bundesrat</name>
      <name lang="fr">Conseil fédéral</name>
      <name lang="it">Il Consiglio federale</name>
      <name lang="en">The Federal Council</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.admin.ch/gov/de/start.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.admin.ch/gov/fr/accueil.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.admin.ch/gov/it/pagina-iniziale.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.admin.ch/gov/en/start.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="yes" id="603" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>601</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidg. Finanzverwaltung</name>
      <name lang="fr">Administration fédérale des finances</name>
      <name lang="it">Amministrazione federale delle finanze</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Finance Administration</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.efv.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.efv.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.efv.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.efv.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@efv.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@efv.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@efv.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@efv.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="1070">
      <name lang="de">Der Bundesrat</name>
      <name lang="fr">Conseil fédéral</name>
      <name lang="it">Il Consiglio federale</name>
      <name lang="en">The Federal Council</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.admin.ch/gov/de/start.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.admin.ch/gov/fr/accueil.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.admin.ch/gov/it/pagina-iniziale.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.admin.ch/gov/en/start.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <department id="601">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Finanzdepartement</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des finances</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale delle finanze</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Finance</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.efd.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.dff.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.efd.admin.ch/efd/it/home.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.efd.admin.ch/efd/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Bundesrat will Umtauschfrist für alte Banknotenserien aufheben</title>
      <lead>Der Bundesrat hat sich an seiner Sitzung vom 5. April 2017 mit der Umtauschfrist für alte Banknotenserien befasst. Im Einvernehmen mit der Schweizerischen Nationalbank (SNB) schlägt er die Aufhebung dieser Frist vor. Das Eidgenössische Finanzdepartement (EFD) wurde beauftragt, bis Ende August 2017 eine Vernehmlassungsvorlage mit den erforderlichen Gesetzesänderungen auszuarbeiten.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Sobald die SNB eine neue Banknotenserie in Umlauf bringt, kann sie die Banknoten der bisherigen Serie zurückrufen. Die zurückgerufenen Banknoten gelten dann nicht mehr als gesetzliches Zahlungsmittel, können jedoch noch während 20 Jahren bei der SNB umgetauscht werden. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Das EFD und die SNB haben aufgrund einer Interpellation von Nationalrat Manuel Tornare (16.3323) die heutige Praxis geprüft und beantragen die Aufhebung der Umtauschfrist. Die Aufhebung der Umtauschfrist wird verhindern, dass jemand Banknoten besitzt, die plötzlich ihren Wert verloren haben. Die Schweiz stellt sich damit auf die in den wichtigsten Industrieländern übliche Praxis ein.&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Philipp Rohr, Kommunikation Eidgenössische Finanzverwaltung EFV Tel. +41 58 465 16 06, kommunikation@efv.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions>
        <revision date="2017-04-05 11:58" type="R"/>
      </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Le Conseil fédéral souhaite supprimer le délai d’échange des billets de banque d’anciennes séries</title>
      <lead>Lors de sa séance du 5 avril 2017, le Conseil fédéral a discuté du délai d’échange des billets de banque d’anciennes séries. Il propose, d’entente avec la Banque nationale suisse (BNS), la suppression de ce délai. C’est pourquoi il a chargé le Département fédéral des finances (DFF) d’élaborer d’ici à fin août 2017 un projet destiné à la consultation portant sur les modifications de loi nécessaires. </lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Dès que la BNS met en circulation une nouvelle série de billets de banque, elle peut rappeler les billets de la série précédente. Les billets rappelés ne sont dès lors plus considérés comme un moyen de paiement légal, mais peuvent encore être échangés auprès de la BNS pendant 20 ans. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;En raison de l’interpellation 16.3323 déposée par le conseiller national Manuel Tornare, le DFF et la BNS ont examiné la pratique actuelle et proposent la suppression du délai d’échange. Le but est d’éviter que des personnes se retrouvent avec des billets de banque sans valeur. La Suisse se conformera ainsi à la pratique des principaux pays industrialisés.&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Philipp Rohr, responsable de la communication, Administration fédérale des finances, n° tél. +41 58 465 16 06, kommunikation@efv.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Il Consiglio federale intende abrogare il termine di cambio delle banconote di vecchie serie</title>
      <lead>Nella seduta del 5 aprile 2017 il Consiglio federale ha esaminato il termine di cambio delle banconote di vecchie serie e, d’intesa con la Banca nazionale svizzera (BNS), ne ha proposto l’abrogazione. Il Dipartimento federale delle finanze (DFF) è stato incaricato di elaborare entro fine agosto 2017 un progetto da porre in consultazione contenente le modifiche di legge necessarie.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Al momento dell’emissione di una nuova serie di banconote la BNS può ritirare le banconote della serie precedente, la cui validità come mezzo di pagamento legale cessa, ma che possono essere cambiate presso la BNS nel corso dei 20 anni successivi.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Il DFF e la BNS hanno verificato la prassi attuale, come proposto nell’interpellanza del consigliere nazionale Manuel Tronare (16.3323), e hanno richiesto l’abrogazione del termine di cambio. In tal modo si eviterà che una persona possa trovarsi in possesso di banconote che da un momento all’altro perdono il proprio valore. La Svizzera si allinea, così, alla prassi diffusa nei principali Paesi industrializzati.&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Philipp Rohr, responsabile della Comunicazione, Amministrazione federale delle finanze AFF tel. +41 58 465 16 06, kommunikation@efv.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Federal Council wishes to eliminate exchange deadline for old banknote series</title>
      <lead>During its meeting on 5 April 2017, the Federal Council addressed the exchange deadline for old banknote series. In agreement with the Swiss National Bank (SNB), it is proposing the elimination of this deadline. The Federal Department of Finance (FDF) has been instructed to prepare a consultation draft with the necessary legislative amendments by the end of August 2017.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Once the SNB brings a new series of banknotes into circulation, it can recall the banknotes from the previous series. The recalled banknotes then cease to be legal tender, but they can be exchanged at the SNB for a period of 20 years. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Based on an interpellation from National Councillor Manuel Tornare (16.3323), the FDF and SNB have reviewed the current practice and are requesting the elimination of the exchange deadline. This will prevent a situation where people find themselves with banknotes that have suddenly lost their value. Switzerland is thus adapting to the customary practice in the main industrialised nations.&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Philipp Rohr, Communications, Federal Finance Administration FFA Tel. +41 58 465 16 06, kommunikation@efv.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <offers>
      <offer id="3" org-id="603">
        <name lang="de">Wirtschaft, Währung</name>
        <name lang="fr">Economie, monnaie</name>
        <name lang="it">Economia, Moneta</name>
        <name lang="en">Economic, Monetary affairs</name>
      </offer>
    </offers>
    <keywords>
      <keyword id="126" org-id="603">
        <name lang="de">Finanzplatz Schweiz</name>
        <name lang="fr">Place financière suisse</name>
        <name lang="it">Piazza finanziaria svizzera</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland as a financial centre</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="198" org-id="603">
        <name lang="de">Münzwesen</name>
        <name lang="fr">Monnaie</name>
        <name lang="it">Monete</name>
        <name lang="en">Coinage</name>
      </keyword>
    </keywords>
    <topics>
      <topic id="5">
        <name lang="de">Behörden</name>
        <name lang="fr">Autorités</name>
        <name lang="it">Autorità</name>
        <name lang="en">Authorities</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="10">
        <name lang="de">Bundesrat</name>
        <name lang="fr">Conseil fédéral</name>
        <name lang="it">Consiglio federale</name>
        <name lang="en">Federal Council</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="47">
        <name lang="de">Wirtschaft</name>
        <name lang="fr">Économie</name>
        <name lang="it">Economia</name>
        <name lang="en">Economic Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
