<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="66504" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2017-04-27</pubdate>
    <blocking-period>2017-04-27</blocking-period>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="318" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>301</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Bundesamt für Statistik</name>
      <name lang="fr">Office fédéral de la statistique</name>
      <name lang="it">Ufficio federale di statistica</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Statistical Office</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.statistik.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.statistique.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.statistica.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.statistics.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@bfs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@bfs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@bfs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@bfs.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="301">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement des Innern</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'intérieur</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'interno</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Home Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Neuchâtel</city>
      <title>Kosten und Finanzierung des Gesundheitswesens 2015: Provisorische Daten - Neuberechnung der Gesamtgesundheitsausgaben 2015</title>
      <lead>(BFS) – Die gesamten Ausgaben für das Gesundheitswesen in der Schweiz betrugen 2015 gemäss OECD-Standards insgesamt 77,8 Milliarden Franken. Diese Summe ergibt sich nach den provisorischen Berechnungen des Bundesamtes für Statistik (BFS). Den Daten 2015 liegen zwei wichtige Einflüsse zugrunde: erstens ein Revisionseffekt und zweitens der Effekt des regulären Wachstums. Der Revisionseffekt beläuft sich für 2014 auf 3,3 Milliarden (+4,6%). Das reguläre Wachstum 2014–2015 auf Basis jeweils revidierter Daten beträgt 3,2 Milliarden (+4,3%). Rund ein Drittel der gesamten Gesundheitskosten (35,3%) wurde 2015 durch die obligatorische Krankenpflegeversicherung getragen.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Diese Medienmitteilung und weitere Informationen zum Thema finden Sie auf der Website des BFS (siehe Link unten)&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Michael Lindner, BFS, Sektion Gesundheitsversorgung, +41 58 463 65 14, michael.lindner@bfs.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="165943">
        <title>Kompletter Text und Mediendossier</title>
        <uri>http://www.bfs.admin.ch/news/de/2017-0082</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Neuchâtel</city>
      <title>Coût et financement du système de santé en 2015: données provisoires - Nouveau calcul des dépenses totales de la santé 2015</title>
      <lead>(OFS) – Les dépenses totales de santé se montaient à 77,8 milliards de francs en 2015 selon les standards de l’OCDE. Cette somme a été définie sur la base des calculs provisoires de l’Office fédéral de la statistique (OFS). Les données 2015 sont influencées par deux facteurs majeurs : un effet lié à la révision du modèle de calcul, d’une part, d’autre part, un effet lié à la croissance ordinaire des dépenses. L’effet de la révision se monte à 3,3 milliards de francs (+4,6%) pour l’année 2014. La croissance ordinaire des dépenses atteignait, elle, 3,2 milliards (+4,3%) en 2015 par rapport à l’année précédente. L’assurance obligatoire des soins a pris en charge environ un tiers des dépenses totales de santé (35,3%).</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Vous trouverez ce communiqué de presse et d'autres informations sur ce thème sur le site web de l'OFS (voir le lien ci-dessous)&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Michael Lindner, OFS, Section Services de santé, +41 58 463 65 14, michael.lindner@bfs.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="165944">
        <title>Texte intégral et dossier de presse</title>
        <uri>http://www.bfs.admin.ch/news/fr/2017-0082</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Neuchâtel</city>
      <title>Costi e finanziamento del sistema sanitario 2015: dati provvisori - Nuovo calcolo dei costi complessivi della salute 2015</title>
      <lead>(UST) – Nel 2015, in Svizzera i costi complessivi del sistema sanitario ai sensi degli standard dell’OCSE ammontavano in totale a 77,8 miliardi di franchi. È quanto risulta dai calcoli provvisori dell’Ufficio federale di statistica (UST). I dati del 2015 hanno subito due sensibili influssi: l’effetto della revisione delle basi di calcolo e quello del regolare aumento dei costi. L’effetto della revisione ammonta per il 2014 a 3,3 miliardi (+4,6%), mentre il regolare aumento dal 2014 al 2015 calcolato in base ai dati rivisti è pari a 3,2 miliardi (+4,3%). Nel 2015 circa un terzo dei costi complessivi della salute (35,3%) sono stati sopportati dall’assicurazione obbligatoria delle cure medico-sanitarie.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Il presente comunicato stampa e ulteriori informazioni sul tema sono reperibili sulla pagina Internet dell'UST (link sotto)&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Michael Lindner, UST, Sezione Sistema sanitario, +41 58 463 65 14, michael.lindner@bfs.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="165945">
        <title>Testo integrale e dossier per i media</title>
        <uri>http://www.bfs.admin.ch/news/it/2017-0082</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Neuchâtel</city>
      <title>Health care costs and financing in 2015: provisional data - New calculations of total health expenditure 2015</title>
      <lead>(FSO) – In 2015, the total health care expenditure in Switzerland according to OECD standards was CHF 77.8 billion. This sum is the result of the provisional calculations of the Federal Statistical Office (FSO). The data for 2015 were influenced by two important factors: firstly the effect of revision and secondly the effect of regular growth. The revision effect for 2014 amounts to CHF 3.3 billion (+4.6%). The regular growth for 2014-2015 on the basis of the revised data is CHF 3.2 billion (+4.3%). In 2015, mandatory health insurance accounted for around one third of total health expenditure (35.3%).</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;This press release and further information on this topic can be found on the FSO website (see link below)&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Michael Lindner, FSO, section health services, +41 58 463 65 14, michael.lindner@bfs.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="165946">
        <title>Please note that the English version only includes the release's lead</title>
        <uri>http://www.bfs.admin.ch/news/en/2017-0082</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <keywords>
      <keyword id="317.15" org-id="318">
        <name lang="de">Gesundheit</name>
        <name lang="fr">Santé</name>
        <name lang="it">Salute</name>
        <name lang="en">Health</name>
      </keyword>
    </keywords>
    <topics>
      <topic id="15">
        <name lang="de">Gesundheit</name>
        <name lang="fr">Santé</name>
        <name lang="it">sanità</name>
        <name lang="en">Health</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="43">
        <name lang="de">Statistik</name>
        <name lang="fr">Statistiques</name>
        <name lang="it">Statistica</name>
        <name lang="en">Statistics</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
