<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="65322" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2017-01-26</pubdate>
    <blocking-period>2017-01-26</blocking-period>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="1082" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>601</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössische Münzstätte Swissmint</name>
      <name lang="fr">Monnaie fédérale Swissmint</name>
      <name lang="it">Zecca federale Swissmint</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Mint Swissmint</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.swissmint.ch/</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.swissmint.ch/swissmint/fr/home.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.swissmint.ch/swissmint/it/home.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.swissmint.ch/swissmint/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@swissmint.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@swissmint.ch</email>
      <email lang="it"/>
      <email lang="en">info@swissmint.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="601">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Finanzdepartement</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des finances</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale delle finanze</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Finance</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.efd.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.dff.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.efd.admin.ch/efd/it/home.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.efd.admin.ch/efd/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern, 26. Januar 2017</city>
      <title>Neue Schweizer Sondermünzen «Enzian» und «500 Jahre Reformation»</title>
      <lead>Am 26. Januar 2017 lanciert die Eidgenössische Münzstätte Swissmint zwei neue Sondermünzen für Sammler und Liebhaber. Mit der Bimetallmünze «Enzian» gelangt die zweite Ausgabe der dreiteiligen Serie «FLORA ALPINA» zur Ausgabe. Thema der Silbermünze ist das Jubiläum «500 Jahre Reformation».</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Von Wittenberg ausgehend, hat die Reformation vor 500 Jahren ganz Europa erfasst und zu kulturellen, gesellschaftlichen und politischen Umwälzungen geführt, die bis heute nachwirken. In der Schweiz wurde – aufgrund des Wirkens von Huldrych Zwingli und Johannes Calvin – die Reformation zu einer zentralen Impulsgeberin auf dem Weg zu Moderne, Demokratie und Menschenrechten. Wie in ganz Europa wird dieses Jahr auch in der Schweiz das Reformationsjubiläum gefeiert. Dabei wird nicht Martin Luthers Thesenanschlag zelebriert, der gemäss Überlieferung 1517 in Wittenberg stattgefunden haben soll. Vielmehr geht es um die Reformation als Bewegung, deren kulturelle, gesellschaftliche und politische Kraft seit 500 Jahren fortwirkt. Im Vordergrund des Jubiläums steht die Frage, was die Reformation für die Generationen von heute und morgen bedeutet und nicht die Rückbesinnung auf ein mystisches Datum. Dazu rückt es die Errungenschaften der Reformation in den Mittelpunkt, ohne dabei deren Schattenseiten zu vergessen und stellt sich in den Dienst des ökumenischen Engagements. Aus Anlass des Jubiläums «500 Jahre Reformation» gibt die Swissmint eine 20-Franken-Sondermünze aus Silber heraus. Diese wurde vom Burgdorfer Grafiker Ben Pfäffli gestaltet. Mehr Informationen unter www.ref-500.ch. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Die einzigartige Pflanzenwelt der Alpen lockt jedes Jahr unzählige Besucher ins Gebirge. Besonders eindrücklich ist der Bergfrühling. Während die letzten Schneefelder langsam dahinschmelzen, spriesst und blüht es überall. Ein besonderer Blickfang in diesem frohen Farbenspiel ist das tiefe Blau des Enzians. Zusammen mit Edelweiss und Alpenrose gehört er zu den beliebtesten Alpenblumen. Landläufig ist mit Enzian der Stängellose Enzian gemeint, von dem es mehrere Unterarten gibt. Am bekanntesten sind die häufig vorkommenden Arten Clusius-Enzian (Gentiana clusii oder Kalk-Enzian) und Kochscher Enzian (Gentiana acaulis oder Silikat-Enzian). Enziane sind eine Pflanzengattung aus der Familie der Enziangewächse (Gentianaceae). Die fast weltweit vorkommenden 300 bis 400 Arten sind vorwiegend in den Gebirgen der gemässigten Zonen der Nordhalbkugel aber auch in den Anden beheimatet. Der Enzian schmückt denn auch die zweite Sondermünze der dreiteiligen Serie «FLORA ALPINA». Der Entwurf für die 10-Franken-Bimetallmünze stammt wiederum von der Berner Grafikerin Jenny Leibundgut.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Die neuen Sonderprägungen sind ab 26. Januar 2017 in limitierter Auflage unter www.swissmintshop.ch sowie bei einzelnen Münzhändlern und Banken erhältlich. Gleichzeitig erscheinen auch die Jahressätze der Schweizer Umlaufmünzen. Neben den Classic-Münzsätzen und dem Babymünzsatz erscheint dieses Jahr zum ersten Mal ein Geburtstagsmünzsatz. Sein farbig illustrierter Schuber macht ihn zum geschätzten Geburtstagspräsent, das in jedem Alter gut ankommt.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class="nsbtextkasten"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Eidgenössische Münzstätte Swissmint&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;Die Eidgenössische Münzstätte Swissmint prägt die Schweizer Umlaufmünzen für den täglichen Zahlungsverkehr. Für den numismatischen Markt gibt die Münzstätte zudem regelmässig Zirkulations- und Sondermünzen in besonderer Qualität heraus. Die Münzen in Bimetall, Silber und Gold sind mit einem offiziellen Nennwert versehen und werden in unterschiedlichen Qualitäten geprägt. Swissmint ist zudem die offizielle Instanz für Echtheitsprüfungen und Expertisen im Auftrag von öffentlichen und privaten Auftraggebern.&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Urs Liechti Bernastrasse 28, 3003 Bern Tel. +41 58 465 12 95 Fax +41 58 462 60 07 urs.liechti@swissmint.ch www.swissmint.ch</contact>
      <attachment id="162852">
        <title>Factsheet Silbermünze «500 Jahre Reformation»</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>192</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/46966.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="162853">
        <title>Factsheet Bimetallmünze «Enzian»</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>199</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/46967.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="162854">
        <title>Factsheet Münzsätze 2017</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>240</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/46968.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <link id="162864">
        <title>Medienbilder</title>
        <uri>http://www.swissmint.ch/d/aktuell/medien/index.php</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne, 26 janvier 2017</city>
      <title>Nouvelles monnaies commémoratives suisses «Gentiane» et «500 ans de la Réforme»</title>
      <lead>Le 26 janvier 2017, la Monnaie fédérale Swissmint émet deux nouvelles monnaies commémoratives à l’intention des collectionneurs et des amateurs. «Gentiane» est la deuxième pièce bimétallique de la série «FLORA ALPINA». La monnaie d’argent a quant à elle pour sujet les «500 ans de la Réforme». </lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Déclenchée à Wittenberg il y a 500 ans, la Réforme a gagné toute l’Europe, entraînant des changements culturels, sociaux et politiques dont les effets se font encore sentir. En Suisse également, par l’action d’Ulrich Zwingli et de Jean Calvin, la Réforme a ouvert la voie vers la modernité, la démocratie et les droits de l’homme. En Suisse comme en Europe, on commémore cette année les 500 ans de la Réforme. Ce ne sont pas tant les thèses publiées selon la tradition en 1517 à Wittenberg qui sont au centre de l’attention, mais plutôt le mouvement dont la force culturelle, sociale et politique perdure depuis un demi-millénaire. Il s’agit avant tout de souligner ce que la Réforme signifie pour les générations actuelles et futures, et non de se remémorer une date mystique. Les festivités se concentrent sur les acquis de la Réforme sans occulter ses zones d’ombre, et visent à renforcer l’engagement œcuménique. À l’occasion de cet anniversaire, Swissmint émet une monnaie commémorative en argent d’une valeur de 20 francs, conçue par le graphiste Ben Pfäffli, de Berthoud. Des informations complémentaires à ce sujet figurent sur le site www.ref-500.ch. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Le monde unique des plantes alpines mène chaque année d’innombrables visiteurs dans les montagnes. Le printemps y est particulièrement spectaculaire. Alors que les derniers champs de neige fondent peu à peu, tout éclot et fleurit partout. Parmi ce camaïeu de couleurs, le bleu profond de la gentiane s’impose. Avec l’edelweiss et le rhododendron, elle compte parmi les fleurs alpines préférées. On entend communément par gentiane la variété sans tige dont il existe plusieurs sous-espèces; les plus connues et répandues sont la gentiane de Clusius (Gentiana clusii) et la gentiane de Koch (Gentiana kochiana). Les gentianes appartiennent à la famille des gentianacées (Gentianaceae) qui compte de 300 à 400 espèces réparties dans presque toutes les régions du monde, avant tout dans les montagnes des zones tempérées de l’hémisphère nord; on la trouve également dans les Andes. La gentiane orne ainsi la deuxième monnaie commémorative de la série de trois «FLORA ALPINA». Le motif de cette pièce bimétallique de 10 francs a été conçu par la graphiste bernoise Jenny Leibundgut.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Les nouvelles monnaies commémoratives seront disponibles en tirage limité dès le 26 janvier 2017 sur notre site www.swissmintshop.ch ainsi qu’auprès de certains négociants en monnaies et banques. Les séries annuelles de monnaies courantes suisses seront disponibles à partir de la même date. Pour la première fois cette année, un jeu de monnaies d’anniversaire vient s’ajouter aux jeux de monnaies annuelles et au jeu de monnaies pour nouveau-né. Le coffret de couleur en fait un cadeau d’anniversaire apprécié qui convient à tout âge.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class="nsbtextkasten"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Monnaie fédérale Swissmint&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;La Monnaie fédérale Swissmint frappe les monnaies courantes de la Suisse, destinées aux opérations de paiement. Pour le marché de la numismatique, la Monnaie fédérale émet aussi régulièrement des monnaies courantes et commémoratives de qualité particulière. Les pièces bimétalliques, en argent ou en or ont une valeur nominale officielle et sont disponibles dans différentes qualités. Enfin, en tant qu’organisation spécialisée officielle, Swissmint est chargée par des personnes privées ou des organismes publics d’effectuer des contrôles d’authenticité et des expertises.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Urs Liechti Bernastrasse 28, 3003 Berne Tél. +41 58 465 12 95 Fax +41 58 462 60 07 urs.liechti@swissmint.ch www.swissmint.ch</contact>
      <attachment id="162855">
        <title>Fiche d’information pièce d’argent «500 ans de la Réforme»</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>241</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/46969.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="162856">
        <title>Fiche d’information pièce bimétallique «Gentiane»</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>249</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/46970.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="162857">
        <title>Fiche d’information jeux de monnaies 2017</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>292</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/46971.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <link id="162865">
        <title>Photos de presse</title>
        <uri>http://www.swissmint.ch/f/aktuell/medien/index.php</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna, 26 gennaio 2017</city>
      <title>Le nuove monete commemorative «Genziana» e «500 anni della Riforma»</title>
      <lead>Il 26 gennaio 2017 la Zecca federale Swissmint emette due nuove monete commemorative per collezionisti e amatori. La moneta bimetallica «Genziana» è la seconda della serie di tre monete commemorative «FLORA ALPINA» a essere emessa. Il tema della moneta d’argento è il giubileo per i 500 anni della Riforma. </lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt; La Riforma protestante è partita da Wittenberg 500 anni or sono per poi diffondersi in tutta Europa, portando con sé una rivoluzione culturale, sociale e politica i cui effetti perdurano ancor oggi. In Svizzera, sotto la guida di Ulrich Zwingli e di Giovanni Calvino, la Riforma ha dato un impulso fondamentale al percorso di apertura verso la modernità, la democrazia e i diritti dell’uomo. Come in tutta Europa, quest’anno anche in Svizzera si festeggia il giubileo della Riforma. Non si celebra l’affissione delle tesi di Martin Lutero, che per tradizione sarebbe avvenuta nel 1517 a Wittenberg, quanto piuttosto un movimento la cui rilevanza culturale, sociale e politica continua a far sentire i suoi effetti dopo cinque secoli. Il giubileo celebra il significato della Riforma per le generazioni attuali e future e non la rievocazione di una data simbolica. Si intende porre al centro le conquiste della Riforma, senza tralasciare i suoi lati oscuri, e rafforzare l’impegno ecumenico. In onore del giubileo «500 anni della Riforma», Swissmint emette una moneta speciale d’argento con un valore nominale di 20 franchi disegnata dal grafico Ben Pfäffli di Burgdorf. Maggiori informazioni sono disponibili sul sito www.ref-500.ch. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ogni anno la straordinaria flora alpina attira moltissimi visitatori sulle nostre montagne. Di particolare effetto è la primavera: mentre l’ultima neve si scioglie lentamente, ovunque è tutto un germogliare e fiorire. In questo allegro gioco di colori lo sguardo è catturato dal blu profondo della genziana, che insieme alla stella alpina e al rododendro è uno dei fiori più amati delle Alpi. Con il termine genziana si intende comunemente la genziana senza stelo, di cui esistono alcune sottospecie. Quelle più note sono anche le più diffuse: la genziana di Clusius (&lt;i&gt;Gentiana clusii&lt;/i&gt; o genzianella dei calcari) e la genziana di Koch (&lt;i&gt;Gentiana acaulis&lt;/i&gt;). La genziana appartiene alla famiglia delle gentianaceae. Le 300 – 400 specie presenti un po’ ovunque in tutto il mondo crescono prevalentemente sulle montagne delle zone temperate dell’emisfero settentrionale, ma le troviamo anche sulle Ande. Alla genziana è dedicata la seconda delle tre monete speciali della serie FLORA ALPINA. Come la prima della serie, anche questa moneta bimetallica da 10 franchi è stata progettata dalla grafica bernese Jenny Leibundgut.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Le nuove monete commemorative sono disponibili dal 26 gennaio 2017 in edizione limitata all’indirizzo www.swissmintshop.ch, in alcuni negozi di numismatica e banche. Allo stesso tempo escono anche le nuove serie di monete divisionali svizzere. Oltre alle serie Classic e Baby, quest’anno viene emessa per la prima volta una serie di monete «Compleanno». La custodia colorata la rende perfetta per un regalo di compleanno che tutti apprezzeranno, indipendentemente dall’età.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class="nsbtextkasten"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Zecca federale Swissmint&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;La Zecca federale Swissmint conia le monete circolanti svizzere destinate al traffico quotidiano dei pagamenti. Per il mercato numismatico la Zecca emette inoltre regolarmente monete speciali e monete circolanti in qualità speciale. Le monete bimetalliche, argento e oro, hanno un valore nominale e sono disponibili in diverse qualità. Swissmint è inoltre l’istanza ufficiale per le valutazioni di autenticità e per le perizie su incarico di committenti pubblici e privati.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Urs Liechti Bernastrasse 28, 3003 Berna Tel. +41 58 465 12 95 Fax +41 58 462 60 07 urs.liechti@swissmint.ch www.swissmint.ch</contact>
      <attachment id="162858">
        <title>Foglio informativo moneta d’argento «500 anni della Riforma»</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>182</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/46972.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="162859">
        <title>Foglio informativo moneta bimetallica «Genziana»</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>139</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/46973.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="162860">
        <title>Foglio informativo serie di monete 2017</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>224</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/46974.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <link id="162866">
        <title>Immagini per la stampa</title>
        <uri>http://www.swissmint.ch/i/aktuell/medien/index.php</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern, 26 January 2017</city>
      <title>New Swiss commemorative coins: "Gentian" and "500 Years of Reformation"</title>
      <lead>On 26 January 2017, the Federal Mint Swissmint will launch two new commemorative coins for coin enthusiasts and collectors. The bimetallic "Gentian" coin is the second coin to be issued in the "FLORA ALPINA" three-part series. The top-ic of the silver coin is the "500 Years of Reformation". </lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Starting in Wittenberg, 500 years ago Europe was in the grip of the Reformation, which led to cultural, social and political upheaval which still has an impact today. In Switzerland, due to the action of Ulrich Zwingli and John Calvin, the Reformation became an important catalyst on the road to the modern age, democracy and human rights. Like in the rest of Europe, the anniversary of the Reformation is also being celebrated in Switzerland. But it is not a celebration of Martin Luther's thesis, which according to tradition saw the light of day in Wittenberg in 1517. It is far more about the Reformation as a movement whose cultural, social and political potency still has an impact 500 years later. The main focus of the anniversary is the question of what the Reformation means for today's generation and those of tomorrow, and not a return to a mystical date in time. This brings the achievements of the Reformation into the spotlight without forgetting the drawbacks and puts it into the service of ecumenical commitment. On the occasion of the "500 Years of Reformation" anniversary, Swissmint is issuing a 20-franc silver commemorative coin. This was designed by the graphic artist Ben Pfäffli from Burgdorf. Further information is available at www.ref-500.ch. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Each year, the unique Alpine flora attracts countless visitors to the mountains. The mountain spring is particularly impressive. While the last snowfields gradually melt away, plants are blossoming and sprouting wherever you look. Particularly eye-catching in this display of colour is the deep blue of the gentian. Together with the edelweiss and Alpine rose, it is one of the most popular Alpine flowers. This is commonly understood to mean the "stemless gentian", of which there are several subspecies. The most well known are the frequently occurring species Clusius' gentian (gentiana clusii or limestone gentian) and Koch's gentian (gentian acaulis or silicaceous gentian). Gentian is a plant species from the gentian family (gentianaceae). The 300 to 400 plant species which are found almost all over the world are predominantly indigenous to the temperate climate zones of the northern hemisphere and also the Andes. The gentian decorates the second commemorative coin in the three-part FLORA ALPINA series. Again, it is the graphic artist Jenny Leibundgut, from Bern, who designed the new 10-franc bimetallic coin.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The new commemorative coins are available from 26 January 2017 as limited editions at www.swissmintshop.ch&lt;u&gt;,&lt;/u&gt; as well from some coin dealers and banks. At the same time, the annual circulation coin sets will also appear. Alongside the classic coin sets and the baby coin set, a birthday coin set will be issued this year for the first time. The colourful, illustrated slipcase makes it a cherished birthday present which will go down well with all ages.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class="nsbtextkasten"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Federal Mint Swissmint&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The Federal Mint Swissmint produces the country's coins for use in everyday payment transactions. The Federal Mint also regularly issues commemorative coins and coinage of a higher standard for the numismatic market. Coins in bimetal, silver and gold bear an official nominal value and are available in various minting qualities. Swissmint is also the official authority for public and private clients seeking authenticity checks and expert opinions.&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Urs Liechti Bernastrasse 28, 3003 Bern Tel. +41 58 465 12 95 Fax +41 58 462 60 07 urs.liechti@swissmint.ch www.swissmint.ch</contact>
      <attachment id="162861">
        <title>Fact sheet silver coin "500 Years of Reformation"</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>134</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/46975.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="162862">
        <title>Fact sheet bimetallic coin "Gentian"</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>139</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/46976.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="162863">
        <title>Fact sheet coin sets 2017</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>182</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/46977.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <link id="162867">
        <title>Press pictures</title>
        <uri>http://www.swissmint.ch/e/aktuell/medien/index.php</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="8">
        <name lang="de">Bildung und Forschung</name>
        <name lang="fr">Formation et recherche</name>
        <name lang="it">Formazione e ricerca</name>
        <name lang="en">Education and Research</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="13">
        <name lang="de">Öffentliche Finanzen</name>
        <name lang="fr">Finances publiques</name>
        <name lang="it">Finanze pubbliche</name>
        <name lang="en">Public Finances</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="18">
        <name lang="de">Kultur</name>
        <name lang="fr">Culture</name>
        <name lang="it">Cultura</name>
        <name lang="en">Culture</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="29">
        <name lang="de">Umwelt und Natur</name>
        <name lang="fr">Environnement et nature</name>
        <name lang="it">Ambiente e natura</name>
        <name lang="en">Environment and Nature</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
