<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="70177" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2018-03-21</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="1070" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>1070</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Der Bundesrat</name>
      <name lang="fr">Conseil fédéral</name>
      <name lang="it">Il Consiglio federale</name>
      <name lang="en">The Federal Council</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.admin.ch/gov/de/start.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.admin.ch/gov/fr/accueil.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.admin.ch/gov/it/pagina-iniziale.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.admin.ch/gov/en/start.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="yes" id="703" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>701</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Staatssekretariat für Wirtschaft</name>
      <name lang="fr">Secrétariat d'Etat à l'économie</name>
      <name lang="it">Segreteria di Stato dell'economia</name>
      <name lang="en">State Secretariat for Economic Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.seco.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.seco.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.seco.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.seco.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@seco.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@seco.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@seco.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@seco.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="1070">
      <name lang="de">Der Bundesrat</name>
      <name lang="fr">Conseil fédéral</name>
      <name lang="it">Il Consiglio federale</name>
      <name lang="en">The Federal Council</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.admin.ch/gov/de/start.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.admin.ch/gov/fr/accueil.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.admin.ch/gov/it/pagina-iniziale.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.admin.ch/gov/en/start.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <department id="701">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Wirtschaft, Bildung und Forschung</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'économie, de la formation et de la recherche</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'economia, della formazione e della ricerca</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Economic Affairs, Education and Research</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Remigi Winzap wird zum Exekutivdirektor der Schweiz bei der EBRD ernannt</title>
      <lead>Der Bundesrat hat am 21. März 2018 Remigi Winzap, gegenwärtig im Staatssekretariat für Wirtschaft (SECO) für den handelspolitischen Dialog zwischen der Schweiz und dem Vereinigten Königreich zuständig, zum Schweizer Exekutivdirektor bei der Europäischen Bank für Wiederaufbau und Entwicklung (EBRD) in London ernannt. Zugleich hat ihm der Bundesrat den Botschaftertitel verliehen. Remigi Winzap wird sein Amt am 1. September 2018 antreten, als Nachfolger von Heinz Kaufmann, der seit Ende 2013 als Exekutivdirektor wirkt.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Remigi Winzap, 1961, lic. iur., ist gegenwärtig im Staatssekretariat für Wirtschaft (SECO) für den handelspolitischen Dialog zwischen der Schweiz und dem Vereinigten Königreich sowie für die Verhandlungsführung im plurilateralen Abkommen über den Handel mit Dienstleistungen (TiSA) zuständig. Von 2012 bis 2016 war er Botschafter und Leiter der Ständigen Mission der Schweiz bei der WTO und anderen internationalen Wirtschaftsorganisationen (EFTA, UNCTAD, ECE/UNO, ITC) in Genf und Mitglied der Geschäftsleitung des SECO. Er war von 2007 bis 2012 Leiter des WTO-Ressorts des SECO. Von 2001 bis 2006 war Remigi Winzap Botschaftsrat bei der Schweizer Mission in Brüssel. Frühere Stationen seiner Tätigkeit umfassten einen Einsatz auf der Schweizer Botschaft in Paris sowie die Teilnahme in den Dienstleistungsverhandlungen der Schweiz im Rahmen der Uruguay-Runde des GATT. Vor seinem Eintritt in die schweizerische Bundesverwaltung arbeitete Remigi Winzap sechs Jahre beim Schweizerischen Bankverein (heute UBS) in Genf, Basel und New York. Remigi Winzap hat in Genf Rechtswissenschaften studiert und an der Ecole Nationale d’Administration (ENA) in Paris ein Nachdiplomstudium in Öffentlicher Verwaltung abgeschlossen. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Die Schweiz ist seit 1991 Mitglied der EBRD. Diese war nach den damaligen politischen Umwälzungen in Osteuropa und der einstigen Sowjetunion gegründet worden, um diese Länder bei der Demokratisierung und der Transformation zur Marktwirtschaft zu unterstützen. Der aus 23 Direktoren bestehende Exekutivrat der Bank legt die Politik im operationellen, finanziellen und administrativen Bereich fest. Die Direktoren entscheiden über die Länder- und Sektorprogramme sowie über Darlehen zur Finanzierung von Entwicklungsprojekten und -programmen. Der Schweizer Exekutivdirektor vertritt nicht nur die Interessen der Schweiz, sondern auch jene der Stimmrechtsgruppe. Die Schweiz bildet bei der EBRD gemeinsam mit dem Fürstentum Liechtenstein, Ukraine, Serbien, Usbekistan, Moldawien, Montenegro und Turkmenistan eine Stimmrechtsgruppe.&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Daniel Birchmeier, Leiter Multilaterale Zusammenarbeit des SECO Tel. 058 464 08 19, daniel.birchmeier@seco.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Remigi Winzap est nommé administrateur de la Suisse (directeur exécutif) auprès de la BERD</title>
      <lead>Le 21 mars 2018, le Conseil fédéral a nommé Remigi Winzap, actuellement responsable au Secrétariat d’État à l’économie (SECO) du dialogue entre la Suisse et le Royaume-Uni en matière de politique commerciale, au poste d’administrateur de la Suisse (directeur exécutif) auprès de la Banque européenne pour la reconstruction et le développement (BERD), à Londres. Il lui a conféré par la même occasion le titre d’ambassadeur. Remigi Winzap prendra ses fonctions le 1er septembre 2018 et succédera à Heinz Kaufmann, qui occupe le poste depuis fin 2013. </lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Remigi Winzap, né en 1961, licencié en droit, est actuellement chargé du dialogue entre la Suisse et le Royaume-Uni en matière commerciale et de la conduite des négociations concernant l’Accord plurilatéral sur le commerce des services (ACS) au SECO. De 2012 à 2016, il a été ambassadeur et chef de la Mission permanente de la Suisse près l’OMC et d’autres organisations économiques internationales (AELE, CNUCED, CEE-ONU, CCI), à Genève, et membre de la direction du SECO. Avant de diriger le secteur OMC du SECO, entre 2007 et 2012, Remigi Winzap a été conseiller d’ambassade auprès de la Mission suisse à Bruxelles (2001 à 2006). Parmi ses activités précédentes, signalons un poste à l’ambassade de Suisse à Paris et la participation aux négociations sur les services pour la Suisse dans le cadre du cycle d’Uruguay du GATT. Avant d’entrer dans l’administration fédérale, Remigi Winzap a travaillé six ans auprès de la Société de Banque Suisse (auj. UBS), à Genève, Bâle et New York. Il a suivi des études de droit à Genève et obtenu un diplôme postgrade en administration publique à l’Ecole Nationale d’Administration (ENA) à Paris.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;La Suisse est membre de la BERD depuis 1991. L’institution a été créée à la suite des bouleversements politiques survenus en Europe de l’Est et dans l’ancienne Union soviétique pour favoriser la démocratisation de ces pays et leur transition vers une économie de marché. Le Conseil d’administration de la banque, qui est composé de 23 administrateurs, définit sa politique sur les plans opérationnel, financier et administratif. Les administrateurs décident également des programmes par pays et par secteur ainsi que des prêts destinés au financement de projets et programmes de développement. L’administrateur de la Suisse (directeur exécutif) représente non seulement les intérêts du pays, mais encore ceux de son groupe de vote. La Suisse forme, avec la Principauté de Liechtenstein, l’Ukraine, la Serbie, l’Ouzbékistan, la Moldavie, le Monténégro et le Turkménistan, un groupe de vote au sein de la BERD. &lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Daniel Birchmeier, Chef Collaboration multilatérale, SECO, tél. 058 464 08 19, daniel.birchmeier@seco.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Remigi Winzap nominato direttore esecutivo per la Svizzera in seno alla BERS</title>
      <lead>Il 21 marzo 2018 Remigi Winzap – attualmente responsabile presso la Segreteria di Stato dell’economia (SECO) del dialogo politico-commerciale con il Regno Unito – è stato nominato dal Consiglio federale direttore esecutivo svizzero in seno alla Banca europea per la ricostruzione e lo sviluppo (BERS), a Londra. Il Consiglio federale gli ha inoltre conferito il titolo di ambasciatore. Remigi Winzap entrerà in carica il 1o settembre 2018 come successore di Heinz Kaufmann, direttore esecutivo dalla fine del 2013.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Remigi Winzap, classe 1961, giurista, attualmente è responsabile SECO del dialogo politico-commerciale con il Regno Unito e dei negoziati nel quadro dell’Accordo plurilaterale sugli scambi di servizi (TiSA). Dal 2012 al 2016 è stato ambasciatore e capo della missione permanente della Svizzera all’ONU e presso altre organizzazioni economiche internazionali (AELS, UNCTAD, ECE/ONU, CCI) con sede a Ginevra, nonché membro della Direzione della SECO. Dal 2001 al 2006 è stato consigliere d’ambasciata della missione svizzera a Bruxelles e dal 2007 al 2012 capo del settore OMC della SECO. In precedenza è stato impiegato presso l’ambasciata svizzera a Parigi e ha partecipato alle attività negoziali della Svizzera sulla liberalizzazione dei servizi nel quadro dell’Uruguay Round del GATT. Prima di entrare a far parte dell’Amministrazione federale ha lavorato sei anni alla Società di banca svizzera (oggi UBS) a Ginevra, Basilea e New York. Remigi Winzap ha studiato diritto a Ginevra e si è specializzato in amministrazione pubblica alla Ecole Nationale d’Administration (ENA) di Parigi. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;La Svizzera è membro della BERS dal 1991. La BERS è stata fondata in seguito agli sconvolgimenti politici avvenuti nell’Europa dell’Est e nell’ex Unione sovietica, per sostenere questi Paesi nel processo di democratizzazione e transizione all’economica di mercato. Il Consiglio esecutivo della Banca, composto da 23 direttori, definisce la politica in ambito operativo, finanziario e amministrativo. I direttori decidono sui programmi previsti per i vari Paesi e i diversi settori nonché in merito ai mutui destinati al finanziamento di progetti e programmi di sviluppo. Il direttore esecutivo svizzero non rappresenta soltanto il nostro Paese, bensì l’intero gruppo di voto. Ne fanno parte – oltre alla Svizzera –, Principato del Liechtenstein, Ucraina, Serbia, Uzbekistan, Moldavia, Montenegro e Turkmenistan.&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Daniel Birchmeier, SECO resbonsabile Cooperazione multilaterale Tel. 058 464 08 19, daniel.birchmeier@seco.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Remigi Winzap appointed Switzerland’s Director at the EBRD</title>
      <lead>On 21 March, the Federal Council appointed Remigi Winzap, currently responsible for trade policy dialogue between Switzerland and the UK at the State Secretariat for Economic Affairs (SECO), as Switzerland’s Director at the European Bank for Reconstruction and Development (EBRD) in London. At the same time, the Federal Council also awarded him the title of ambassador. Mr Winzap will take up his duties on 1 September, succeeding Heinz Kaufmann, who is on the Board of Directors since 2013.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Remigi Winzap from the State Secretariat for Economic Affairs (SECO) is currently responsible for trade policy dialogue between Switzerland and the United Kingdom and for leading negotiations on the Trade in Services Agreement (TiSA). From 2012 to 2016, he was ambassador and head of Switzerland’s Permanent Mission to the WTO and other international economic organisations in Geneva (EFTA, UNCTAD, UNECE, ITC), and a member of SECO’s board of directors. From 2007 to 2012, he was head of SECO’s WTO section. From 2001 to 2006, Mr Winzap was embassy counsellor at the Swiss Mission in Brussels. Earlier stages in his career included a posting at the Swiss Embassy in Paris and participation in the Uruguay Round of GATT negotiations on services. Before joining the Swiss Federal Administration, Mr Winzap worked for six years at the Swiss Bank Corporation (now UBS) in Geneva, Basel and New York. Mr Winzap studied law in Geneva and completed postgraduate studies in public administration at the Ecole Nationale d’Administration (ENA) in Paris. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Switzerland has been a member of the EBRD since 1991. The EBRD was founded after the political upheavals in Eastern Europe and the former Soviet Union in a bid to support these countries in their democratisation and transformation to a market economy. The bank’s Board of Directors, consisting of 23 members, sets operational, financial and administrative policy. The directors decide on country and sector programmes, as well as on loans to finance development projects and programmes. Switzerland’s representative on the Board of Directors not only defends Switzerland’s interests, but also those of its constituency. Switzerland’s constituency at the EBRD consists of the Principality of Liechtenstein, Ukraine, Serbia, Uzbekistan, Moldova, Montenegro and Turkmenistan.&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Daniel Birchmeier, Head, Multilateral Cooperation Tel. 058 464 08 19, daniel.birchmeier@seco.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="47">
        <name lang="de">Wirtschaft</name>
        <name lang="fr">Économie</name>
        <name lang="it">Economia</name>
        <name lang="en">Economic Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
