<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="51897" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2014-02-04</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="408" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>408</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Bundesanwaltschaft</name>
      <name lang="fr">Ministère public de la Confédération</name>
      <name lang="it">Ministero pubblico della Confederazione</name>
      <name lang="en">Office of the Attorney General of Switzerland</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.ba.admin.ch/ba/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.ba.admin.ch/ba/fr/home.html</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.ba.admin.ch/ba/it/home.html</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.ba.admin.ch/</www>
      <email lang="de">info@ba.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@ba.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@ba.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@ba.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="408">
      <name lang="de">Bundesanwaltschaft</name>
      <name lang="fr">Ministère public de la Confédération</name>
      <name lang="it">Ministero pubblico della Confederazione</name>
      <name lang="en">Office of the Attorney General of Switzerland</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.ba.admin.ch/ba/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.ba.admin.ch/ba/fr/home.html</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.ba.admin.ch/ba/it/home.html</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.ba.admin.ch/</www>
      <email lang="de">info@ba.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@ba.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@ba.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@ba.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Anzeige „Angolagate“: Keine Wiederaufnahme des Verfahrens</title>
      <lead>Die Bundesanwaltschaft (BA) hat eine Strafanzeige von angolanische Staatsbürgern und der britischen NGO Corruption Watch in Sachen „Angolagate“ geprüft und nach getätigten Vorabklärungen die Nichtanhandnahme der Anzeige verfügt. Die Vorgänge rund um die Rückzahlung angolanischer Staatsschulden aus der Sowjetzeit an Russland lösen demnach keine weitere Strafuntersuchung in der Schweiz aus.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;„Angolagate" geht auf Ende der 90er Jahre zurück und betrifft Verträge zwischen Russland und Angola, wonach Angola seine Schulden bei Russland durch Erdölverkäufe abbezahlen sollte. Der Bezug zur Schweiz ergibt sich aus mit dem Geschäft verbundenen Geldtransaktionen über Schweizer Bankverbindungen. Die Genfer Justizbehörden waren in den letzten Jahren bereits mit dem Fall „Angolagate" befasst. Die im Kanton Genf geführten Ermittlungen endeten im Jahr 2004 bzw. 2010 mit Verfahrenseinstellungen. Als Folge dieser Genfer Verfahren unterzeichneten die Schweiz und Angola Abkommen über die Rückführung von angolanischen Vermögenswerten im Umfang von 21 Millionen US-Dollar bzw. rund 43 Millionen US-Dollar. Die Gelder sollten für humanitäre Projekte zugunsten der angolanischen Bevölkerung eingesetzt werden.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Die Anzeige vom 15. April 2013 basiert auf einem neu publizierten Bericht über den angolanisch-russischen Schulden-Deal „The Corrupt Angola-Russia Debt Deal", aus dem die Anzeigeerstatter neue Erkenntnisse ableiten, die zum Zeitpunkt der Verfahren im Kanton Genf noch nicht vorhanden waren. Aufgrund neuer Beweismittel soll das Verfahren gegen die am Geschäft beteiligte Personengruppe - bestehend aus angolanischen Amtsträgern, Inhabern einer zwischengeschalteten Firma sowie Schweizer Bankangestellten - wieder aufgenommen und die Korruptionsvorwürfe untersucht werden. Die Anzeigeerstatter zitieren vor allem den Privatgutachter, der den Deal ursprünglich für beide Länder als opportun erachtete und dessen Gutachten zentral für die Genfer Verfahrenseinstellung gewesen sei. Dieser würde heute (mit mehr Informationen über die Hintergründe des Geschäfts) andere Rückschlüsse aus der Sache ziehen. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Die BA teilt diese Einschätzung nicht und sieht in jüngeren Aussagen des Gutachters keinen Widerspruch zu seiner seinerzeitigen Analyse des angolanisch-russischen Schulden-Deals. Im Übrigen hat die Genfer Anklagekammer - ohne Kenntnis des besagten Gutachtens - bereits 2003 kein strafrechtlich relevantes Verhalten erkennen können. Gleichzeitig misst die BA einem Privatgutachten nicht die gleiche Bedeutung zu wie einem Justizgutachten, weshalb dessen Beweiskraft zu relativieren sei. Die BA verneint somit das Vorliegen neuer Tatsachen, welche die Wiederaufnahme des Verfahrens rechtfertigen würden. Sie bezweifelt im Übrigen, dass selbst bei einer allfälligen Wiederaufnahme des Verfahrens ein derart komplexer Sachverhalt in kurzer Zeit (mit Blick auf die absolute Verjährung im Juli 2015) aufgearbeitet und ein erstinstanzlicher Gerichtsentscheid erlangt werden könnte. Kommt dazu, dass die „Bestechung fremder Amtsträger" in der Schweiz erst seit 1. Mai 2000 gesetzlich verankert ist und somit verfolgbar ist. Allfällige Ermittlungen im Fall „Angolagate" hätten infolgedessen nur den Zeitraum von drei Monaten (Mai bis Juli 2000) erfasst. Die BA eröffnet deshalb keine Untersuchung und hat Nichtanhandnahmeverfügung erlassen.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Jeannette Balmer, Mediensprecherin BA, +41 31 324 32 40, info@ba.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Plainte "Angolagate": Pas de reprise de la procédure</title>
      <lead>Le Ministère public de la Confédération (MPC) a examiné une dénonciation pénale de la part de citoyens angolais et de l'ONG britannique "Corruption Watch" dans la cause "Angolagate" et, après avoir procédé à des enquêtes préliminaires, a rendu une décision de non-entrée en matière. Ainsi, les événements entourant le remboursement de dettes de l'Etat d'Angola du temps de l'Union soviétique à la Russie n'engendreront dès lors pas une nouvelle procédure pénale en Suisse.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;L'"Angolagate" remonte à la fin des années 1990 et concerne des contrats entre la Russie et l'Angola, dans le cadre desquels l'Angola devait rembourser ses dettes à l'égard de la Russie par des ventes de pétrole. Le lien avec la Suisse résulte de transactions financières liées à cette opération à travers de comptes bancaires suisses. Au cours de ces dernières années, les autorités judiciaires genevoises se sont déjà penchées sur l'affaire "Angolagate". Les enquêtes conduites dans le canton de Genève se sont soldées par des classements de procédure en 2004, respectivement en 2010. A la suite de ces procédures genevoises, la Suisse et l'Angola ont signé des accords sur le rapatriement de valeurs patrimoniales angolaises à hauteur d'US-Dollars 21 millions, respectivement environ US-Dollars 43 millions. Les fonds devaient être affectés à des projets humanitaires en faveur de la population angolaise.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;La dénonciation pénale du 15 avril 2013 se fonde sur un rapport récemment publié sur l'accord angolo-russe sur les dettes "The Corrupt Angola-Russia Debt Deal". Les dénonciateurs en déduisent l'existence d'éléments nouveaux qui n'existaient pas encore à l'époque des procédures pénales conduites dans le canton de Genève. Selon eux, ces faits nouveaux justifiaient la reprise de la procédure dirigée contre le groupe de personnes impliquées dans l'opération - composé d'agents publics angolais, de propriétaires d'une société intercalée ainsi que d'employés de banque suisses - et l'examen des accusations de corruption. Les dénonciateurs invoquaient principalement un changement d'opinion de l'expert privé qui, à l'origine, avait considéré l'opération comme opportune pour les deux pays et dont le rapport aurait été primordial pour le classement de la procédure genevoise. Aujourd'hui (en disposant de plus amples renseignements sur l'arrière-plan de la transaction), cet expert tirerait de cette affaire des conclusions différentes. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Le MPC ne partage pas cette appréciation et ne voit dans les plus récentes déclarations de l'expert aucune contradiction par rapport à son analyse de l'époque de la transaction angolo-russe sur les dettes. Pour le surplus, en 2003 déjà, la Chambre d'accusation de Genève - sans avoir eu connaissance de ladite expertise - n'avait pu constater un comportement pénalement répréhensible. En même temps, le MPC n'attribue pas la même importance à une expertise privée qu'à une expertise judiciaire si bien que la force probante de l'expertise privée doit être relativisée. Le MPC considère qu'aucun fait nouveau n'a été décrit dans la dénonciation qui justifierait la reprise de la procédure. Par surabondance, si tant est que la reprise de la procédure avait été possible, il doute qu'un état de faits aussi complexe puisse être traité et qu'une décision judiciaire de première instance puisse être obtenue à brève échéance (au vu de la prescription absolue qui sera atteinte en juillet 2015). Il s'y ajoute le fait qu'en Suisse, l'infraction de "corruption d'agents publics étrangers" n'a été introduite dans la loi que le 1er mai 2000 et ne peut dès lors être poursuivie que depuis cette date. Ainsi, toutes éventuelles enquêtes dans l'affaire "Angolagate" n'auraient porté que sur une période de trois mois (mai à juillet 2000). En conséquence, le MPC n'ouvrira pas de procédure pénale et a rendu une décision de non-entrée en matière.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Jeannette Balmer, porte-parole du MPC, +41 31 324 32 40, info@ba.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Denuncia nel caso «Angolagate»: il procedimento non sarà riaperto</title>
      <lead>Il Ministero pubblico della Confederazione (MPC) ha esaminato una denuncia sporta da cittadini angolani e dall’ONG britannica “Corruption Watch” nella vicenda nota come «Angolagate» e dopo accertamenti preliminari ha decretato il non luogo a procedere. I recenti sviluppi inerenti al rimborso alla Russia dei debiti contratti dallo Stato angolano all’epoca del regime sovietico non daranno quindi luogo a nuovi procedimenti penali in Svizzera.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;La vicenda nota come «Angolagate» risale alla fine degli anni ‘90 e riguarda contratti stipulati tra la Russia e l'Angola, in virtù dei quali lo Stato angolano avrebbe dovuto rimborsare i debiti contratti con la Russia con forniture di petrolio. La ramificazione verso la Svizzera è data da transazioni finanziarie legate alla vicenda transitate su conti bancari svizzeri. Le autorità giudiziarie ginevrine si erano già occupate del caso negli anni scorsi. I procedimenti penali svolti dal Cantone di Ginevra sono stati abbandonati nel 2004 e poi nel 2010. In seguito ai procedimenti ginevrini, la Svizzera e l'Angola hanno sottoscritto accordi per la restituzione di averi di origine angolana dell'ordine di rispettivamente 21 milioni e 34 milioni di dollari americani. Le somme dovevano essere investite in progetti umanitari a beneficio della popolazione angolana.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;La denuncia sporta il 15 aprile 2013 si fonda sul rapporto di recente pubblicazione «The Corrupt Angola-Russia Debt Deal», che verte sull'accordo stipulato tra l'Angola e la Russia per il rimborso del debito. Dal rapporto i denuncianti hanno desunto l'esistenza di nuovi elementi di cui non disponevano ancora all'epoca dei procedimenti condotti dal Cantone di Ginevra. A loro parere, nuovi fatti giustificherebbero la riapertura del procedimento svolto nei confronti del gruppo di persone, composto da funzionari angolani, titolari di una società intermediaria e impiegati di banca svizzeri, coinvolto nella vicenda nonché il riesame delle accuse di corruzione. I denuncianti invocano essenzialmente il cambiamento di opinione del perito di parte, che in origine aveva considerato l'accordo opportuno per entrambi i Paesi e la cui perizia avrebbe assunto un'importanza decisiva per l'abbandono dei procedimenti deciso dalle autorità ginevrine. A loro dire, il perito trarrebbe oggi conclusioni diverse sulla vicenda, alla luce di maggiori informazioni disponibili sui retroscena della transazione. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Il MPC non condivide tale valutazione e non ravvisa alcuna contraddizione nelle recenti dichiarazioni del perito rispetto alla precedente analisi dell'accordo russo-angolano sul rimborso del debito. Del resto, anche nel 2003 la Camera d'accusa del Cantone di Ginevra, pur non conoscendo la menzionata perizia, non aveva accertato comportamenti penalmente rilevanti. Inoltre, il MPC riconosce a una perizia di parte un valore probatorio limitato rispetto a una perizia giudiziaria. Ritiene pertanto che la denuncia non comprenda nuovi fatti che giustifichino la riapertura del procedimento. Infine, anche se fosse stato possibile riaprire il procedimento, il MPC dubita che una fattispecie tanto complessa possa essere rivista in tempi stretti e che si possa giungere per tempo a un giudizio di primo grado (poiché la prescrizione assoluta cadrebbe nel luglio 2015). Oltretutto, in Svizzera la «corruzione di pubblici ufficiali stranieri» è un reato previsto dalla legge e, quindi, perseguibile dal 1° maggio 2000. Eventuali indagini sulla vicenda dell'«Angolagate» avrebbero quindi potuto abbracciare solo un periodo di tre mesi (da maggio a luglio 2000). Pertanto, il MPC ha deciso di non avviare alcuna inchiesta e ha decretato il non luogo a procedere.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Jeannette Balmer, portavoce MPC, +41 31 324 32 40, info@ba.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Criminal Complaint „Angolagate“: No Re-opening of Proceedings</title>
      <lead>The Office of the Attorney General of Switzerland has examined a criminal complaint filed by Angolan citizens and the British NGO Corruption Watch regarding the „Angolagate“ case and, having completed their preliminary investigations, ruled that no further action in respect of the complaint shall be taken. The events surrounding the repayment to Russia of Angolan government debts, dating back to Soviet times, shall therefore not result in further criminal investigations in Switzerland.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;„Angolagate" dates back to the end of the ‘90s and concerns contracts between Russia and Angola, whereby Angola was supposed to pay off its debts to Russia through the selling of crude oil. The link to Switzerland stems from the fact that money transfers in connection with these business transactions were conducted through Swiss bank accounts. For the last few years already, the Geneva judicial authorities have been dealing with the "Angolagate" case. The investigations conducted in the Canton of Geneva resulted in the cessation of proceedings in the years 2004 and 2010, respectively. Subsequently, on the basis of the Geneva proceedings, Switzerland signed agreements with Angola on the repatriation of Angolan assets worth 21 million US Dollars and approximately 43 million US Dollars, respectively. It was agreed that these monies must be used for humanitarian purposes for the benefit of the people of Angola.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The criminal complaint of 15th April 2013 was based on a newly published report about the Angolan-Russian debt agreement called "The Corrupt Angolan-Russian Debt Deal", from which the complainants drew new information, which, at the time of the proceedings in the Canton of Geneva, was not yet known. According to the complainants, this new information would justify a re-opening of proceedings against the group of individuals who were involved in this deal - namely Angolan officials, owners of an intermediary company and Swiss bank employees - and conducting investigations into allegations of corruption. The complainants cited principally the change of mind of a privately appointed expert who had originally concluded that the deal was to the benefit of both countries, and whose expert report was supposedly a key element for the ruling of cessation of proceedings by Geneva. The complainants believe that with today's knowledge (further background information&lt;b&gt; &lt;/b&gt;on the deal) he would reach a different conclusion in the matter. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Swiss Federal Prosecution Authorities do not share this belief, and cannot find any contradictions between the expert's recent pronunciations and his earlier analysis of the Angolan-Russian debt deal. Furthermore, already in 2003, without having been in the possession of said expert report, the Geneva prosecution authorities did not find any criminally relevant activities. At the same time, the Swiss Federal Prosecution Authorities do not attach the same weight to a privately commissioned expert report as to a judicial expert report, and therefore the evidential value of the former must be put into perspective. The Swiss Federal Prosecution Authorities are of the opinion that the complaint does not contain any new information that would justify a re-opening of proceedings. Furthermore, if a re-opening of proceedings were possible, there is doubt, taking into consideration the complexity of the case, that it could be concluded within a short period of time, (keeping in mind that the absolute statute of limitations comes into effect in July 2015), and that a ruling by the court of first instance could be achieved. Besides, "bribery of foreign officials" was only anchored into Swiss law as a criminal offence on 1st May 2000, and only since then can it be prosecuted. Any possible investigations into the „Angolagate" case would therefore have encompassed a period of just three months (May to July 2000). Therefore, the Swiss Prosecution Authorities shall not instigate an investigation, and have issued a ruling of non-consideration of the complaint.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Jeannette Balmer, Spokeswoman OAG, +41 31 324 32 40, info@ba.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="17">
        <name lang="de">Kriminalität</name>
        <name lang="fr">Criminalité</name>
        <name lang="it">Criminalità</name>
        <name lang="en">Criminality</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
