<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="31473" revoked="no">
    <version>3</version>
    <pubdate>2010-02-03</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="101" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>101</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Bundeskanzlei</name>
      <name lang="fr">Chancellerie fédérale</name>
      <name lang="it">Cancelleria federale</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Chancellery</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.bk.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.bk.admin.ch/index.html?lang=fr</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.bk.admin.ch/index.html?lang=it</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.bk.admin.ch/index.html?lang=en</www>
      <email lang="de">infokomm@admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">infokomm@admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">infokomm@admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">infokomm@admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="605" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>601</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössische Steuerverwaltung</name>
      <name lang="fr">Administration fédérale des contributions</name>
      <name lang="it">Amministrazione federale delle contribuzioni</name>
      <name lang="en">The Federal Tax Administration</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.estv.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.estv.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.estv.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.estv.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de"/>
      <email lang="fr"/>
      <email lang="it"/>
      <email lang="en"/>
    </originator>
    <department id="101">
      <name lang="de">Bundeskanzlei</name>
      <name lang="fr">Chancellerie fédérale</name>
      <name lang="it">Cancelleria federale</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Chancellery</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.bk.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.bk.admin.ch/index.html?lang=fr</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.bk.admin.ch/index.html?lang=it</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.bk.admin.ch/index.html?lang=en</www>
      <email lang="de">infokomm@admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">infokomm@admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">infokomm@admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">infokomm@admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <department id="601">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Finanzdepartement</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des finances</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale delle finanze</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Finance</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.efd.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.dff.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.efd.admin.ch/efd/it/home.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.efd.admin.ch/efd/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Bundesrat beschliesst weiteres Vorgehen mit Deutschland</title>
      <lead>Der Bundesrat hat an seiner Sitzung von heute Mittwoch über das weitere Vorgehen mit Deutschland entschieden. Dies nachdem bekannt wurde, dass die deutsche Regierung Bereitschaft signalisiert hat, auf das Angebot einzugehen, in den Besitz von Daten von Kunden einer Schweizer Bank zu gelangen. Der Bundesrat lehnt diese Art von Datenbeschaffung ab. Er ist jedoch bereit, weiterhin das Gespräch mit Deutschland zu suchen und auch die Verhandlungen über die Revision des Doppelbesteuerungsabkommens nach OECD-Musterabkommen weiterzuführen.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Der Bundesrat hat an seiner Sitzung von heute Mittwoch seinem Befremden darüber Ausdruck verliehen, dass die deutsche Regierung Bereitschaft signalisiert hat, auf das Angebot einzugehen, in den Besitz von Daten von Kunden einer Schweizer Bank zu gelangen. In letzter Zeit ist es vermehrt zum Diebstahl von Bankkundendaten in der Schweiz gekommen, die im Ausland zum Verkauf angeboten wurden. In der Schweiz ist das eine Straftat. Sie verstösst gegen Treu und Glauben und belastet die Beziehungen zwischen Rechtsstaaten. Der Bundesrat lehnt diese Art von Datenbeschaffung zur Rückführung von Steuersubstrat ab.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Der Bundesrat bekräftigte an seiner Sitzung heute erneut seine Haltung, dass es nicht im Interesse der Schweiz ist, unversteuertes Geld aus dem Ausland anzuziehen. Bereits im März 2009 hatte er entschieden, erleichterte Amtshilfe in Steuersachen zu leisten und gegenüber dem Ausland den Unterschied zwischen Steuerbetrug und Steuerhinterziehung aufzuheben und bei allen Steuerdelikten Amts- und Rechtshilfe zu gewähren. Den Beschluss, Amtshilfe in Steuersachen künftig nach OECD-Standard zu leisten, fällte der Bundesrat zeitgleich mit anderen wichtigen Finanzplätzen. Seither hat die Schweiz mit 17 Staaten Doppelbesteuerungsabkommen (DBA) nach neuem Standard revidiert. Der Bundesrat wird diese Politik weiterführen.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Deutschland ist der wichtigste Handelspartner der Schweiz und ein Nachbarstaat, mit dem traditionell gute Beziehungen gepflegt werden. In diesem Sinn will der Bundesrat auch das Problem der gestohlenen und den deutschen Behörden zum Kauf angebotenen Daten lösen. Er will weiterhin das Gespräch mit Deutschland führen. Er wird jedoch auch gegenüber Deutschland keine Amtshilfe auf Basis gestohlener Daten leisten.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Der Bundesrat ist bereit, die Verhandlungen mit Deutschland über ein neues DBA nach OECD-Musterabkommen weiterzuführen. Dieses liegt vor allem im Interesse des Werkplatzes Schweiz. Das bietet auch Deutschland Gewähr, dass die Schweiz künftig erleichterte Amtshilfe gewährt. Die Frage der Verwendung der Daten wird in den Verhandlungen aufgegriffen und thematisiert&lt;strong&gt;.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Roland Meier, Pressesprecher EFD, Tel 031 322 60 86</contact>
      <revisions>
        <revision date="2010-02-04 16:34" type="R"/>
      </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Le Conseil fédéral décide de la conduite à tenir vis-à-vis de l'Allemagne</title>
      <lead>Le Conseil fédéral a décidé, lors de sa séance d'aujourd’hui, de la conduite à tenir vis-à-vis de l'Allemagne, après que le gouvernement allemand ait annoncé son intention d'acquérir des données relatives à des clients d'une banque suisse. Le Conseil fédéral condamne ce mode d'acquisition de données. Il est toutefois disposé à rechercher le dialogue avec l'Allemagne et à poursuivre les négociations sur la révision de la convention contre la double imposition en suivant le Modèle de convention de l'OCDE.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Lors de sa séance d'aujourd'hui mercredi, le Conseil fédéral a exprimé sa surprise face à la volonté du gouvernement allemand d'acquérir des données relatives à des clients d'une banque suisse. Au cours des derniers mois se sont en effet multipliés les vols de données de clients de banques suisses, lesquelles sont ensuite proposées à la vente à l'étranger. Punissable en Suisse, le vol de données bancaires enfreint le principe de la bonne foi et engendre des tensions dans les relations entre Etats de droit. Le Conseil fédéral condamne ce mode d'acquisition de données visant à récupérer des recettes fiscales.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Lors de sa séance d'aujourd'hui, le Conseil fédéral a réaffirmé sa position selon laquelle il n'est pas dans l'intérêt de la Suisse d'attirer des fonds étrangers non déclarés. En mars 2009 déjà, il avait décidé de fournir une assistance administrative facilitée en matière fiscale, d'abroger, vis-à-vis de l'étranger, la distinction faite entre la fraude fiscale et la soustraction d'impôt et, enfin, d'accorder une assistance administrative ou une entraide judiciaire pour tous les délits fiscaux. Le Conseil fédéral avait pris, en même temps que d'autres places financières importantes, la décision de fournir à l'avenir une assistance administrative en suivant le standard de l'OCDE. Depuis lors, la Suisse a révisé, sur la base du standard de l'OCDE, les conventions contre la double imposition (CDI) passées avec 17 Etats. Le Conseil fédéral entend poursuivre dans cette voie.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Partenaire commercial le plus important de la Suisse, l'Allemagne est aussi un Etat voisin avec lequel notre pays entretient traditionnellement de bonnes relations. C'est dans cet esprit que le Conseil fédéral entend régler le problème des données volées et proposées à la vente aux autorités allemandes. Il souhaite poursuivre ses discussions avec l'Allemagne, mais rejettera une demande d'assistance administrative fondée sur des données volées, même si celle-ci est présentée par l'Allemagne.&lt;/p&gt; Le Conseil fédéral est prêt à poursuivre les négociations avec l'Allemagne concernant une nouvelle convention de double imposition suivant le Modèle de convention de l'OCDE, avant tout dans l'intérêt de la place économique suisse. Cela garantit également à l'Allemagne que la Suisse accordera l'assistance administrative plus facilement à l'avenir. La question de l'utilisation des données sera examinée dans le cadre des négociations.</text>
      <contact>Roland Meier, porte-parole du DFF, tél.: 031 322 60 86</contact>
      <revisions>
        <revision date="2010-02-04 16:34" type="R"/>
      </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Il Consiglio federale decide l'ulteriore modo di procedere con la Germania</title>
      <lead>Nella sua seduta odierna, il Consiglio federale ha deciso l'ulteriore modo di procedere con la Germania, dopo che era stato reso noto che il Governo tedesco sembrava intenzionato a entrare in possesso dei dati - ricevuti in offerta - di clienti di una banca svizzera. Il Consiglio federale respinge questa modalità di acquisizione dei dati, ma è comunque disposto a proseguire il dialogo con la Germania e a portare avanti i negoziati per la revisione della Convenzione di doppia imposizione secondo il modello di convenzione dell'OCSE.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Nella sua seduta odierna, il Consiglio federale ha espresso il suo stupore di fronte al fatto che il Governo tedesco sembrava intenzionato a entrare in possesso dei dati - ricevuti in offerta - di clienti di una banca svizzera. Nel nostro Paese negli ultimi tempi sono sempre più frequenti i furti di dati bancari offerti in vendita all'estero. In Svizzera questo è un reato, poiché viola il principio della buona fede e pregiudica le relazioni tra Stati di diritto. Il Consiglio federale respinge questa modalità di acquisizione dei dati finalizzata al rimpatrio del substrato fiscale.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Nel corso della seduta odierna il Governo ha ribadito nuovamente la sua posizione secondo cui non è nell'interesse della Svizzera attirare dall'estero averi non tassati. Già nel mese di marzo del 2009 esso aveva deciso di adottare una procedura semplificata per l'assistenza amministrativa nelle questioni fiscali come pure, nei confronti dell'estero, di revocare la distinzione tra frode fiscale e sottrazione d'imposta e di concedere l'assistenza amministrativa e giudiziaria per tutti i reati fiscali. La decisione di fornire in futuro l'assistenza amministrativa in ambito fiscale conformemente allo standard dell'OCSE era stata presa dal Consiglio federale simultaneamente ad altre importanti piazze finanziarie. Da allora la Svizzera ha riveduto con 17 Paesi le Convenzioni di doppia imposizione (CDI) secondo il nuovo standard. Il Governo continuerà a perseguire questa politica.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Oltre a essere il principale partner commerciale della Svizzera, la Germania è uno Stato limitrofo con cui i rapporti sono tradizionalmente buoni. In questo senso il Governo intende anche risolvere il problema dei dati rubati e offerti in vendita alle autorità tedesche. Esso vuole continuare il dialogo con la Germania, ma non le fornirà assistenza amministrativa sulla base di dati rubati.&lt;/p&gt; Il Consiglio federale è disposto a proseguire i negoziati con la Germania concernenti una nuova CDI secondo il modello di convenzione dell'OCSE. Questo è soprattutto nell'interesse della piazza di lavoro svizzera. In tal modo la CDI garantisce anche alla Germania che in futuro la Svizzera fornirà l'assistenza amministrativa sulla base di una procedura semplificata. La questione dell'impiego dei dati verrà ripresa e tematizzata nei negoziati.</text>
      <contact>Roland Meier, portavoce del DFF, tel. 031 322 60 86</contact>
      <revisions>
        <revision date="2010-02-04 16:34" type="R"/>
      </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Federal Council takes decision on further course of action concerning Germany</title>
      <teaser>Roland Meier, FDF Press Spokesman, tel. 031 322 60 86</teaser>
      <lead>In its meeting today, the Federal Council took a decision on the further course of action concerning Germany. This was after it became known that the German government had indicated its readiness to take up the offer to obtain data on clients of a Swiss bank. The Federal Council rejects this type of data acquisition. However, it is prepared to continue to seek talks with Germany, as well as to proceed with negotiations on revising the double taxation agreement (DTA) in accordance with the OECD Model Tax Convention.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;In its meeting today, the Federal Council expressed its astonishment at the German government's indication of its readiness to take up the offer to obtain data on clients of a Swiss bank. Recently there has been an increase in the theft of Swiss bank client data which is subsequently sold abroad. This is a criminal offence in Switzerland. It violates public policy and the principle of good faith, and strains relations between constitutional states. The Federal Council rejects this type of data acquisition to increase the tax base.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;In its meeting today, the Federal Council reiterated its stance that it was not in the interests of Switzerland to attract undeclared funds from overseas. In March 2009, the Federal Council took the decision to facilitate administrative assistance in tax matters and, in relation to foreign countries, to remove the distinction between tax fraud and tax evasion and to provide administrative and legal assistance in the case of tax offences. The decision to provide administrative assistance in tax matters in future in accordance with the OECD model was taken by the Federal Council at the same time as by other important financial centres. Since then, Switzerland has revised double taxation agreements (DTAs) with 17 countries on the basis of the new model. The Federal Council will continue with this policy.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Germany is Switzerland's most important trade partner and is a neighbour with which it traditionally enjoys good relations. With this in mind, the Federal Council also wishes to resolve the problem of the stolen data which has been offered for sale to the German authorities. It wants to pursue talks with Germany. Nonetheless, it will not provide administrative assistance based on stolen data, even to Germany.&lt;/p&gt; The Federal Council is prepared to continue negotiations with Germany on a new DTA in accordance with the OECD Model Tax Convention. This is above all in the interests of Switzerland as a workplace. It will also provide Germany with the guarantee that Switzerland will facilitate administrative assistance in future. The issue of the use of the data will be addressed during the negotiations.</text>
      <contact/>
      <revisions>
        <revision date="2010-02-04 16:34" type="R"/>
      </revisions>
    </content>
    <keywords>
      <keyword id="137" org-id="605">
        <name lang="de">Internationale Doppelbesteuerung</name>
        <name lang="fr">Double imposition internationale</name>
        <name lang="it">Doppia imposizione internazionale</name>
        <name lang="en">International double taxation</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="117" org-id="605">
        <name lang="de">Bankgeheimnis</name>
        <name lang="fr">Secret bancaire</name>
        <name lang="it">Segreto bancario</name>
        <name lang="en">Banking secrecy</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="126" org-id="605">
        <name lang="de">Finanzplatz Schweiz</name>
        <name lang="fr">Place financière suisse</name>
        <name lang="it">Piazza finanziaria svizzera</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland as a financial centre</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="235" org-id="605">
        <name lang="de">Internationale Steuerpolitik</name>
        <name lang="fr">Politique fiscale internationale</name>
        <name lang="it">Politica fiscale internazionale</name>
        <name lang="en">International tax policy</name>
      </keyword>
    </keywords>
    <topics>
      <topic id="10">
        <name lang="de">Bundesrat</name>
        <name lang="fr">Conseil fédéral</name>
        <name lang="it">Consiglio federale</name>
        <name lang="en">Federal Council</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="35">
        <name lang="de">Finanzplatz</name>
        <name lang="fr">Place financière</name>
        <name lang="it">Piazza finanziaria</name>
        <name lang="en">Financial Centre</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="44">
        <name lang="de">Steuern</name>
        <name lang="fr">Impôts</name>
        <name lang="it">Imposte</name>
        <name lang="en">Taxation</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
