<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="32385" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2010-03-24</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="yes" id="605" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>601</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössische Steuerverwaltung</name>
      <name lang="fr">Administration fédérale des contributions</name>
      <name lang="it">Amministrazione federale delle contribuzioni</name>
      <name lang="en">The Federal Tax Administration</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.estv.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.estv.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.estv.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.estv.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de"/>
      <email lang="fr"/>
      <email lang="it"/>
      <email lang="en"/>
    </originator>
    <department id="601">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Finanzdepartement</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des finances</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale delle finanze</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Finance</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.efd.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.dff.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.efd.admin.ch/efd/it/home.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.efd.admin.ch/efd/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Die Schweiz und Griechenland paraphieren revidiertes Doppelbesteuerungsabkommen</title>
      <lead>Die Schweiz und Griechenland haben die Verhandlungen über die Ausweitung der Amtshilfe in Steuerfragen nach dem OECD-Standard und über weitere Punkte abgeschlossen und heute ein Änderungsprotokoll zum bestehenden Doppelbesteuerungsabkommen (DBA) paraphiert. Die Amtshilfeklausel entspricht den vom Bundesrat beschlossenen Eckwerten. Das Abkommen mit Griechenland ist das 22. mit einer Amtshilfeklausel nach OECD-Standard.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Seit dem Bundesratsentscheid vom 13. März 2009 über die Ausweitung der Amtshilfe in Steuerfragen hat die Schweiz mit zahlreichen Staaten entsprechende Verhandlungen aufgenommen. Der Bundesrat hat seither auch die ersten zehn Botschaften zu revidierten DBA mit einer Amtshilfeklausel nach Art. 26 des OECD-Musterabkommens verabschiedet und an das Parlament zur Genehmigung weitergeleitet.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Neben der Ausweitung der Amtshilfe in Steuersachen hat die Schweiz in den Verhandlungen mit diesen Staaten verschiedene Vorteile für die Wirtschaft aushandeln können, beispielsweise Quellensteuerreduktionen auf Dividenden, Zinsen und Lizenzzahlungen sowie die Einführung einer Schiedsgerichtsklausel. Zudem konnte die Vermeidung von steuerlichen Diskriminierungen erreicht werden. Diese Politik wird fortgesetzt und weitere Verhandlungen mit wichtigen Ländern sind bereits vorgesehen.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="nsbtextkasten"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Paraphierung und weitere Etappen bis zum Inkrafttreten&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; &lt;strong&gt;Paraphierung&lt;/strong&gt; bezeichnet die Zustimmung zu einem Vertragstext durch Anbringen der Initialen (= Paraphen). Damit legen die Verhandlungsführer bei DBA (und anderen völkerrechtlichen Verträgen) den ausgehandelten Vertragstext vorläufig fest. Dieser paraphierte Text ist vorerst vertraulich. Den Kantonen und den betroffenen Wirtschaftsverbänden wird der Inhalt in einem Kurzbericht bekannt gegeben, damit sie dazu Stellungnahme nehmen können.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Danach wird das Abkommen dem Bundesrat vorgelegt, der die Ermächtigung zur &lt;strong&gt;Unterzeichnung&lt;/strong&gt; erteilt. Nach der Unterzeichnung wird das Abkommen veröffentlicht. Anschliessend verabschiedet der Bundesrat eine Botschaft an den National- und den Ständerat, die für die Genehmigung des DBA zuständig sind. Hat auch der Partnerstaat das Abkommen genehmigt, so kann es &lt;strong&gt;ratifiziert&lt;/strong&gt; werden. Dies ist die Voraussetzung des Inkrafttretens, wobei der &lt;strong&gt;Zeitpunkt des Inkrafttretens&lt;/strong&gt; von der getroffenen Vereinbarung abhängt.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Beat Furrer, Leiter Kommunikation, Eidgenössische Steuerverwaltung, Tel. 031 324 91 29</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>La Suisse et la Grèce paraphent une convention révisée de double imposition</title>
      <lead>La Suisse et la Grèce ont conclu les négociations sur l'élargissement de l'assistance administrative en matière fiscale conformément à la norme de l'OCDE et sur d'autres points en paraphant aujourd'hui un protocole visant à modifier la Convention de double imposition (CDI) en vigueur. La clause sur l'assistance administrative correspond aux directives du Conseil fédéral. La Convention avec la Grèce est la 22e convention négociée comprenant une clause d'assistance administrative conforme à la norme de l'OCDE.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Depuis la décision du Conseil fédéral du 13 mars 2009 sur l'élargissement de l'assistance administrative en matière fiscale, la Suisse a entrepris des négociations dans ce sens avec de nombreux Etats. Le Conseil fédéral a aussi adopté les dix premiers messages concernant des CDI révisées comprenant une clause d'assistance administrative selon l'art. 26 du Modèle de convention de l'OCDE; il les a transmis au Parlement pour approbation.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;En plus d'élargir l'assistance administrative sur des questions fiscales, la Suisse a pu obtenir de nombreux avantages pour son économie lors des négociations avec ces Etats, telles des réductions de l'impôt à la source sur les dividendes, les intérêts et les redevances ainsi que l'introduction d'une clause d'arbitrage. En outre, elle a pu éviter l'apparition de discriminations fiscales. Le Conseil fédéral va poursuivre cette politique et a déjà prévu de mener des négociations avec d'autres Etats importants.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="nsbtextkasten"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Apposition des paraphes et autres étapes jusqu'à l'entrée en vigueur&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; &lt;strong&gt;Parapher&lt;/strong&gt; désigne le fait d'approuver le texte d'un accord en apposant ses initiales (= paraphe). C'est ainsi que les responsables des négociations ratifient provisoirement le texte des CDI (et des autres traités internationaux) qu'ils négocient. Dans un premier temps, le texte paraphé est confidentiel. Le contenu de la CDI est communiqué dans un bref rapport aux cantons et aux milieux économiques intéressés, afin qu'ils puissent donner leur avis.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; La CDI n'est publiée qu'au terme de la signature. Le Conseil fédéral donne l'autorisation de &lt;strong&gt;signer&lt;/strong&gt; la CDI. La CDI doit ensuite être approuvée par les Chambres fédérales. Si l'Etat partenaire a également approuvé la CDI, elle peut être &lt;strong&gt;ratifiée&lt;/strong&gt;. C'est la condition pour son &lt;strong&gt;entrée en vigueur&lt;/strong&gt;, dont la date dépend de l'accord trouvé.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Beat Furrer, chef de la communication, Administration fédérale des contributions, tél. 031 324 91 29</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>La Svizzera e la Grecia parafano la riveduta Convenzione di doppia imposizione</title>
      <lead>La Svizzera e la Grecia hanno concluso le trattative sull'estensione dell'assistenza amministrativa nelle questioni fiscali secondo lo standard OCSE e su altri punti. Inoltre, in data odierna i due Paesi hanno parafato un Protocollo che modifica l'attuale Convenzione di doppia imposizione (CDI). La clausola di assistenza amministrativa soddisfa i parametri decisi dal Consiglio federale. La Convenzione con la Grecia è la ventiduesima contenente una clausola di assistenza amministrativa secondo lo standard dell'OCSE.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Dopo la decisione del Consiglio federale del 13&amp;nbsp;marzo 2009 sull'estensione dell'assistenza amministrativa nelle questioni fiscali, la Svizzera ha avviato con numerosi Paesi corrispondenti negoziati. Da allora il Consiglio federale ha parimenti adottato i primi dieci messaggi sulle rivedute CDI contenenti una clausola di assistenza amministrativa secondo l'articolo 26 del modello di Convenzione dell'OCSE e li ha trasmessi al Parlamento per la relativa approvazione.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Oltre all'estensione dell'assistenza amministrativa in questioni fiscali, nel quadro delle trattative con questi Stati la Svizzera ha ottenuto diversi vantaggi per l'economia, come le riduzioni dell'imposta alla fonte su dividendi, interessi e pagamenti di canoni nonché l'introduzione di una clausola arbitrale. Inoltre è stato possibile raggiungere un accordo per evitare discriminazioni fiscali. Questa politica verrà proseguita e altre negoziazioni con importanti Paesi sono già previste.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="nsbtextkasten"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dalla parafatura all'entrata in vigore&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; La &lt;strong&gt;parafatura&lt;/strong&gt; designa l'adesione a un trattato attraverso l'apposizione delle iniziali (= parafa). In tal modo nei casi delle CDI (e di altri trattati internazionali) i plenipotenziari confermano l'autenticazione del testo. Inizialmente il testo parafato è confidenziale. Il contenuto è successivamente comunicato ai Cantoni e alle associazioni economiche interessate in un breve rapporto, affinché possano prendere posizione al riguardo.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; La convenzione viene in seguito presentata al Consiglio federale che decide in merito all'autorizzazione a firmare. Una volta &lt;strong&gt;firmata&lt;/strong&gt;, la convenzione viene pubblicata. Successivamente il Consiglio federale licenzia un messaggio all'attenzione del Consiglio nazionale e del Consiglio degli Stati, che sono competenti per l'approvazione della CDI. La convenzione può essere &lt;strong&gt;ratificata&lt;/strong&gt; solo se il testo è stato approvato anche dallo Stato contraente. La ratificazione è il presupposto per &lt;strong&gt;l'entrata in vigore&lt;/strong&gt;, che dipende dalla relativa convenzione stipulata.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Beat Furrer, capo della Comunicazione dell'Amministrazione federale delle contribuzioni, tel. 031 324 91 29</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Switzerland and Greece initial revised double taxation agreement</title>
      <lead>Switzerland and Greece have concluded negotiations on extending administrative assistance in tax matters in accordance with the OECD standard and on other points and have today initialled a Protocol of Amendment on the existing double taxation agreement (DTA). The administrative assistance clause is in line with the key points agreed by the Federal Council. The agreement with Greece is the twenty-second with an administrative assistance clause in accordance with the OECD standard.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Since the Federal Council decision of 13 March 2009 on extending administrative assistance in tax matters, Switzerland has started corresponding negotiations with numerous states. Since then, the Federal Council has also approved the first ten dispatches on revised DTAs with an administrative assistance clause in accordance with Art. 26 of the OECD Model Convention, and submitted them to parliament for approval.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Along with extending administrative assistance in tax matters, Switzerland has also been able to negotiate various benefits for the economy in the negotiations with these countries, such as reductions in withholding tax on dividends, interest and royalty payments, as well as the introduction of an arbitration clause. The avoidance of tax discrimination has also been achieved. This policy will be pursued and further negotiations are already envisaged with important countries.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="nsbtextkasten"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Initialling and ensuing stages before entry into force&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; &lt;strong&gt;Initialling&lt;/strong&gt; is defined as the approval of a contractual text by appending initials. Negotiators can in this way provisionally draw up the negotiated contractual text of DTAs (and other agreements based on international law). The initialled text is at first confidential. The cantons and the business associations concerned are notified of the content in a brief report and invited to submit their comments.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; The agreement is then submitted to the Federal Council, which gives authorisation for it to be signed. Once it has been &lt;strong&gt;signed&lt;/strong&gt;, the agreement is published. Subsequently, the Federal Council approves a dispatch for the attention of parliament, which is responsible for approving the DTA. Once the partner state has provided its approval of the agreement, then the agreement can be &lt;strong&gt;ratified&lt;/strong&gt;. This is the requirement for entry into force, although the &lt;strong&gt;point in time of entry into force&lt;/strong&gt; depends upon the agreement reached.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Beat Furrer, Head of FTA Communications, tel. 031 324 91 29</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <offers>
      <offer id="9" org-id="605">
        <name lang="de">Steuern allgemein</name>
        <name lang="fr">Impôts en général</name>
        <name lang="it">Imposte in generale</name>
        <name lang="en">Taxes in general</name>
      </offer>
    </offers>
    <keywords>
      <keyword id="137" org-id="605">
        <name lang="de">Internationale Doppelbesteuerung</name>
        <name lang="fr">Double imposition internationale</name>
        <name lang="it">Doppia imposizione internazionale</name>
        <name lang="en">International double taxation</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="117" org-id="605">
        <name lang="de">Bankgeheimnis</name>
        <name lang="fr">Secret bancaire</name>
        <name lang="it">Segreto bancario</name>
        <name lang="en">Banking secrecy</name>
      </keyword>
    </keywords>
    <topics>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="44">
        <name lang="de">Steuern</name>
        <name lang="fr">Impôts</name>
        <name lang="it">Imposte</name>
        <name lang="en">Taxation</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
