<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="33438" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2010-06-04</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="yes" id="605" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>601</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössische Steuerverwaltung</name>
      <name lang="fr">Administration fédérale des contributions</name>
      <name lang="it">Amministrazione federale delle contribuzioni</name>
      <name lang="en">The Federal Tax Administration</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.estv.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.estv.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.estv.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.estv.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de"/>
      <email lang="fr"/>
      <email lang="it"/>
      <email lang="en"/>
    </originator>
    <department id="601">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Finanzdepartement</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des finances</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale delle finanze</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Finance</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.efd.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.dff.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.efd.admin.ch/efd/it/home.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.efd.admin.ch/efd/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Doppelbesteuerungsabkommen zwischen der Schweiz und Chile in Kraft</title>
      <lead>Das Doppelbesteuerungsabkommen (DBA) zwischen der Schweiz und Chile ist in Kraft getreten, nachdem auch Chile das DBA ratifiziert und die Schweiz darüber offiziell informiert hat. Das Abkommen dient der Vermeidung der Doppelbesteuerung auf dem Gebiet der Steuern von Einkommen und Vermögen.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Das Abkommen enthält Bestimmungen zur Vermeidung der Doppelbesteuerung und trägt zur günstigen Entwicklung der bilateralen wirtschaftlichen Beziehungen bei. Durch das DBA wird namentlich der Rechtsschutz für Unternehmen verbessert und die Quellensteuer auf Dividenden, Zinsen und Lizenzgebühren begrenzt.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Das Abkommen wurde am 2. April 2008 in Santiago unterzeichnet. Entsprechend der Schweizer Praxis zur Zeit der Unterzeichnung des DBA enthält es einen Artikel über den Informationsaustausch, der den Austausch von Informationen zur Anwendung des Abkommens und zur Durchsetzung des internen Rechts im Falle von Steuerbetrug vorsieht. Mit Chile wurde also keine erweiterte Amtshilfe nach dem OECD-Standard vereinbart.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Beide Vertragsstaaten strebten ein möglichst baldiges Inkrafttreten des DBA an und haben deshalb auf eine Wiederaufnahme der Verhandlungen zur Ausweitung der Amtshilfe verzichtet.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Die Bestimmungen des Abkommens finden in der Schweiz Anwendung auf Einkünfte, Vermögen oder Quellensteuern, die am oder nach dem 1. Januar 2011 beginnen.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>François Bastian, Abteilung für Internationales, Eidgenössische Steuerverwaltung, Tel. 031 322 71 52</contact>
      <link id="70171">
        <title>Abkommenstext (Bundesblatt Nr. 47 vom 25. November 2008, Bl 8871)</title>
        <uri>http://www.admin.ch/ch/d/ff/2008/index0_47.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>La convention de double imposition entre la Suisse et le Chili est entrée en vigueur</title>
      <lead>La convention de double imposition (CDI) conclue entre la Suisse et le Chili est entrée en vigueur, après que la Suisse a communiqué officiellement que le Chili l'a également ratifiée. La convention permet d'éviter la double imposition dans le domaine des impôts sur le revenu et sur la fortune.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;La convention contient des dispositions pour éviter la double imposition et contribue ainsi à développer positivement les relations économiques bilatérales. La CDI améliore notamment la sécurité juridique pour les entreprises et limite le prélèvement de l'impôt à la source sur les dividendes, les intérêts et les redevances.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;La convention a été signée le 2 avril 2008 à Santiago. Conformément à la pratique suisse d'alors, elle contient un article qui prévoit l'échange de renseignements à la fin d'appliquer la convention et d'exécuter le droit interne en cas de fraude fiscale. Avec le Chili, la Suisse n'a donc pas convenu d'étendre l'assistance administrative d'après la norme de l'OCDE.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Les deux Etats contractants souhaitent que la CDI entre en vigueur le plus rapidement possible et ont donc renoncé à reprendre des négociations en vue d'étendre l'assistance administrative. &amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;En Suisse, les dispositions de la convention s'appliquent à partir du 1er janvier 2011 aux revenus, à la fortune et aux impôts prélevés à la source.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>François Bastian, Division des affaires internationales, Administration fédérale des contributions, tél. 031 322 71 52</contact>
      <link id="70173">
        <title>Texte de la convention (Feuille fédérale n° 47 du 25 novembre 2008, FF 7981)</title>
        <uri>http://www.admin.ch/ch/f/ff/2008/index0_47.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>La Convenzione per evitare le doppie imposizioni tra la Svizzera e il Cile è in vigore</title>
      <lead>La Convenzione per evitare le doppie imposizioni (CDI) tra la Svizzera e il Cile è entrata in vigore, dopo che anche il Cile ha ratificato la CDI e informato ufficialmente al riguardo la Svizzera. Lo scopo della Convenzione è di evitare le doppie imposizioni in materia di imposte sul reddito e sul patrimonio.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;La Convenzione contiene disposizioni per evitare le doppie imposizioni e contribuisce allo sviluppo favorevole delle relazioni economiche bilaterali. La CDI migliora segnatamente la protezione giuridica delle imprese e limita l'imposta alla fonte su dividendi, interessi e canoni.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;La Convenzione è stata firmata il 2 aprile 2008 a Santiago. Conformemente alla prassi svizzera in vigore al momento della sottoscrizione, la CDI contiene un articolo che prevede lo scambio di informazioni per l'attuazione della Convenzione e l'applicazione del diritto interno nei casi di frode fiscale. Di conseguenza, con il Cile non è stata convenuta l'assistenza amministrativa estesa secondo lo standard dell'OCSE.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Entrambi gli Stati contraenti hanno auspicato un'entrata in vigore possibilmente rapida della CDI e hanno pertanto rinunciato a una ripresa dei negoziati per l'estensione dell'assistenza amministrativa.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Le disposizioni della Convenzione sono applicabili in Svizzera a redditi, patrimoni e imposte alla fonte conseguiti il, o dopo, il 1°&amp;nbsp;gennaio 2011.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>François Bastian, Divisione degli affari internazionali, Amministrazione federale delle contribuzioni, tel. 031 322 71 52</contact>
      <link id="70174">
        <title>Convenzione (Foglio federale N. 47 del 25 novembre 2008, FF 7689)</title>
        <uri>http://www.admin.ch/ch/i/ff/2008/index0_47.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Double taxation agreement between Switzerland and Chile in force</title>
      <lead>The double taxation agreement (DTA) between Switzerland and Chile entered into force after Chile also ratified the DTA and officially notified Switzerland thereof. The agreement is intended to enable the avoidance of double taxation in the field of income tax and assets.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;The agreement contains provisions for avoiding double taxation and will therefore contribute to the favourable development of bilateral economic relations. In particular, the DTA will improve legal protection for companies and limit the withholding tax on dividends, interest and royalty payments.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The agreement was signed in Santiago on 2 April 2008. In accordance with the Swiss practice at the time, it contains an article that provides for the exchange of information for applying the agreement and enforcing domestic law in the case of tax fraud. Consequently, extended administrative assistance in accordance with the OECD standard was not agreed with Chile.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Both contracting countries wish to bring the agreement into effect as soon as possible and have, for this reason, dispensed with resuming negotiations on extending administrative assistance.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The provisions of the agreement will apply in Switzerland to revenues, assets and withholding tax effective from 1 January 2011.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>François Bastian, Division for International Affairs, Federal Tax Administration, tel. 031 322 71 52</contact>
      <link id="70175">
        <title>Text of the agreement (Federal Gazette No. 47 of 25 November 2008, Bl 8871)</title>
        <uri>http://www.admin.ch/ch/d/ff/2008/index0_47.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <offers>
      <offer id="9" org-id="605">
        <name lang="de">Steuern allgemein</name>
        <name lang="fr">Impôts en général</name>
        <name lang="it">Imposte in generale</name>
        <name lang="en">Taxes in general</name>
      </offer>
    </offers>
    <keywords>
      <keyword id="137" org-id="605">
        <name lang="de">Internationale Doppelbesteuerung</name>
        <name lang="fr">Double imposition internationale</name>
        <name lang="it">Doppia imposizione internazionale</name>
        <name lang="en">International double taxation</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="117" org-id="605">
        <name lang="de">Bankgeheimnis</name>
        <name lang="fr">Secret bancaire</name>
        <name lang="it">Segreto bancario</name>
        <name lang="en">Banking secrecy</name>
      </keyword>
    </keywords>
    <topics>
      <topic id="10">
        <name lang="de">Bundesrat</name>
        <name lang="fr">Conseil fédéral</name>
        <name lang="it">Consiglio federale</name>
        <name lang="en">Federal Council</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="44">
        <name lang="de">Steuern</name>
        <name lang="fr">Impôts</name>
        <name lang="it">Imposte</name>
        <name lang="en">Taxation</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
