<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="34832" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2010-08-30</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="yes" id="703" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>701</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Staatssekretariat für Wirtschaft</name>
      <name lang="fr">Secrétariat d'Etat à l'économie</name>
      <name lang="it">Segreteria di Stato dell'economia</name>
      <name lang="en">State Secretariat for Economic Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.seco.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.seco.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.seco.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.seco.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@seco.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@seco.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@seco.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@seco.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="201" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>201</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="806" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>801</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Bundesamt für Zivilluftfahrt</name>
      <name lang="fr">Office fédéral de l'aviation civile</name>
      <name lang="it">Ufficio federale dell'aviazione civile</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Office of Civil Aviation</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.bazl.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.bazl.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.bazl.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.bazl.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@bazl.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@bazl.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@bazl.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@bazl.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="701">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Wirtschaft, Bildung und Forschung</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'économie, de la formation et de la recherche</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'economia, della formazione e della ricerca</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Economic Affairs, Education and Research</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <department id="201">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <department id="801">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Umwelt, Verkehr, Energie und Kommunikation</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'environnement, des transports, de l'énergie et de la communication</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'ambiente, dei trasporti, dell'energia e delle comunicazioni</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of the Environment, Transport, Energy and Communications</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.uvek.admin.ch/uvek/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.uvek.admin.ch/uvek/fr/home.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.uvek.admin.ch/uvek/it/home.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.uvek.admin.ch/uvek/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-uvek.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-uvek.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-uvek.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-uvek.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Offizieller Besuch des ghanaischen Präsidenten Atta Mills in Bern</title>
      <teaser>Bundespräsidentin Doris Leuthard, Vorsteherin des Eidgenössischen Volkswirtschafts-departements (EVD), hat heute den Präsidenten von Ghana, John Evans Atta Mills, zu einem offiziellen Besuch im Landgut Lohn in Kehrsatz empfangen. Der ghanaische Präsident wurde vom Aussenminister sowie den Ministern für Handel &amp;amp; Industrie, für Information und einem Kabinettsminister begleitet. Anlässlich des Treffens wurden ein Abkommen über den Luftlinienverkehr sowie ein Projektabkommen zur Förderung des nachhaltigen öffentlichen Beschaffungswesens in Ghana unterzeichnet.</teaser>
      <lead>Bundespräsidentin Doris Leuthard, Vorsteherin des Eidgenössischen Volkswirtschafts-departements (EVD), hat heute den Präsidenten von Ghana, John Evans Atta Mills, zu einem offiziellen Besuch im Landgut Lohn in Kehrsatz empfangen. Der ghanaische Präsident wurde vom Aussenminister sowie den Ministern für Handel &amp;amp; Industrie, für Information und einem Kabinettsminister begleitet. Anlässlich des Treffens wurden ein Abkommen über den Luftlinienverkehr sowie ein Projektabkommen zur Förderung des nachhaltigen öffentlichen Beschaffungswesens in Ghana unterzeichnet.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Im Zentrum der Gespräche standen die Würdigung der bilateralen Beziehungen zwischen den beiden Ländern, die Wirtschafts- und Handelsbeziehungen sowie die Zusammenarbeit im Bereich der wirtschaftlichen Entwicklungszusammenarbeit. Daneben wurden regionale und multilaterale Themen erörtert.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Im Anschluss an die offiziellen Gespräche wurde einerseits ein Abkommen zwischen dem Schweizerischen Bundesrat und der Regierung der Republik Ghana über den Luftlinienverkehr unterzeichnet. Dieses ersetzt das bisher gültige Abkommen aus dem Jahr 1961. Andererseits unterzeichneten Staatssekretär Jean-Daniel Gerber, SECO-Direktor, sowie der ghanaische Aussenminister Alhaji Muhammad Mumuni ein Abkommen für ein Projekt zur Förderung der nachhaltigen öffentlichen Beschaffung in Ghana. Das im Rahmen der wirtschaftlichen Entwicklungszusammenarbeit des Staatssekretariats für Wirtschaft SECO finanzierte Projekt über USD 2.7 Mio. bezweckt die Einführung der Prinzipien Transparenz, Rechenschaftspflicht und Nachhaltigkeit im öffentlichen Beschaffungswesen. So soll bei öffentlichen Ausschreibungen der freie Zugang zu Informationen für alle interessierten Parteien sichergestellt werden.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Ghana ist seit 2002 eines der Schwerpunktländer der wirtschaftlichen Entwicklungszusammenarbeit der Schweiz. Dabei konzentriert sich die Schweiz mit allgemeiner Budgethilfe und technischer Unterstützung auf die Verbesserung der makroökonomischen Rahmenbedingungen und Transparenz der öffentlichen Finanzen, auf die Entwicklung und Stärkung des Finanzsektors, auf die Förderung handelsfreundlicher Rahmenbedingungen und Verbesserung des&amp;nbsp;Investitionsklimas sowie auf die Stärkung der regulatorischen Rahmenbedingungen im Infrastrukturbereich und die Verbesserung der Effizienz des Energiesektors. Ferner unterstützt die Schweiz das Kofi Annan International Peacekeeping and Training Centre in Accra zur Ausbildung von afrikanischen Teilnehmern an Friedensmissionen in Westafrika.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Evelyn Kobelt, Pressesprecherin EVD, Tel. +41 31 322 20 59, Mobile +41 79 301 71 72 Luftverkehrsabkommen: Anton Kohler, BAZL, Tel. +41 31 325 83 70 Projektabkommen: Hans-Peter Egler, SECO, Tel. +41 31 324 08 13</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Visite officielle du président ghanéen Atta Mills à Berne</title>
      <teaser>La présidente de la Confédération et cheffe du Département fédéral de l’économie, Doris Leuthard, a reçu aujourd’hui le président du Ghana, John Evans Atta Mills, pour une visite officielle au domaine du Lohn, à Kehrsatz. Le président ghanéen était accompagné des ministres des Affaires étrangères, du Commerce et de l’Industrie, de l’Information ainsi que d’un ministre du Cabinet. Un accord relatif au trafic aérien de lignes et un accord de projet en vue de la promotion de marchés publics durables au Ghana ont été signés à l’occasion de cette rencontre.</teaser>
      <lead>La présidente de la Confédération et cheffe du Département fédéral de l’économie, Doris Leuthard, a reçu aujourd’hui le président du Ghana, John Evans Atta Mills, pour une visite officielle au domaine du Lohn, à Kehrsatz. Le président ghanéen était accompagné des ministres des Affaires étrangères, du Commerce et de l’Industrie, de l’Information ainsi que d’un ministre du Cabinet. Un accord relatif au trafic aérien de lignes et un accord de projet en vue de la promotion de marchés publics durables au Ghana ont été signés à l’occasion de cette rencontre.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Les discussions ont porté pour l'essentiel sur les relations bilatérales entre les deux pays, les relations économiques et commerciales, ainsi que sur la collaboration dans le domaine de la coopération économique au développement. Par ailleurs, plusieurs sujets régionaux et multilatéraux ont été évoqués.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Les entretiens officiels ont été suivis de la signature d'un accord entre la Confédération suisse et le gouvernement de la République du Ghana relatif au trafic aérien de lignes, qui remplace celui, en vigueur, de 1961. Par ailleurs, le secrétaire d'Etat à l'économie et directeur du SECO, Jean-Daniel Gerber, et le ministre ghanéen des Affaires étrangères Alhaji Muhammad Mumuni ont signé un accord relatif à un projet de promotion des marchés publics durables au Ghana. Doté d'une enveloppe de plus de 2,7 millions de dollars et financé dans le cadre de la coopération économique au développement du Secrétariat d'Etat à l'économie (SECO), l'accord vise à introduire les principes de la transparence, de l'obligation de rendre des comptes et de la durabilité dans le domaine des marchés publics. Ainsi, l'accès libre aux informations pour toutes les parties intéressées devra être garanti lors des appels d'offres publics.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Depuis 2002, le Ghana est l'un des pays prioritaires de la coopération économique au développement déployée par la Suisse. La Suisse met l'accent sur l'aide budgétaire générale et apporte son soutien technique à l'amélioration des conditions-cadre macroéconomiques et de la transparence des finances publiques, au développement et au renforcement du secteur financier, à la promotion de conditions-cadre favorables au commerce, à l'amélioration du climat d'investissement, au renforcement de conditions-cadre régulatrices dans le domaine des infrastructures, ainsi qu'à l'amélioration de l'efficacité dans le secteur de l'énergie. En outre, la Suisse soutient le Centre international Kofi Annan de formation au maintien de la paix à Accra, qui forme des participants africains aux missions de paix en Afrique de l'Ouest.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Evelyn Kobelt, porte-parole du DFE, tél.: +41 31 322 20 59, tél. portable: +41 79 301 71 72 Accord relatif au trafic aérien de lignes: Anton Kohler, OFAC, tél.: +41 31 325 83 70 Accord de projet: Hans-Peter Egler, SECO, tél.: +41 31 324 08 13</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Visita ufficiale del presidente del Ghana Atta Mills a Berna</title>
      <teaser>La presidente della Confederazione Doris Leuthard, capo del Dipartimento federale dell’economia (DFE), ha accolto oggi il presidente del Ghana, John Evans Atta Mills, in visita ufficiale, nella residenza “Landgut Lohn” a Kehrsatz. Il presidente del Ghana era accompagnato dal ministro degli esteri, dai ministri del commercio e dell’industria, dell’informazione e un ministro di gabinetto. In occasione dell’incontro sono stati firmati un accordo sul traffico aereo di linea e un accordo relativo a un progetto inteso a promuovere il settore degli appalti pubblici sostenibili in Ghana.</teaser>
      <lead>La presidente della Confederazione Doris Leuthard, capo del Dipartimento federale dell’economia (DFE), ha accolto oggi il presidente del Ghana, John Evans Atta Mills, in visita ufficiale, nella residenza “Landgut Lohn” a Kehrsatz. Il presidente del Ghana era accompagnato dal ministro degli esteri, dai ministri del commercio e dell’industria, dell’informazione e un ministro di gabinetto. In occasione dell’incontro sono stati firmati un accordo sul traffico aereo di linea e un accordo relativo a un progetto inteso a promuovere il settore degli appalti pubblici sostenibili in Ghana.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Al centro dei colloqui vi sono stati l'apprezzamento delle relazioni bilaterali tra i due Paesi, le relazioni economiche e commerciali nonché la collaborazione nell'ambito della cooperazione allo sviluppo economico. Inoltre sono stati discussi temi di interesse regionale e multilaterale.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Immediatamente dopo i colloqui ufficiali è stato firmato, da un lato, un Accordo tra il Consiglio federale svizzero e il Governo della Repubblica del Ghana concernente il traffico aereo di linea; esso sostituisce l'Accordo del 1961, attualmente in vigore. D'altro lato il segretario di Stato Jean-Daniel Gerber, direttore della SECO, e il ministro degli esteri del Ghana Alhaji Muhammad Mumuni hanno firmato un accordo relativo a un progetto inteso a promuovere il settore degli appalti pubblici sostenibili in Ghana. Tale progetto, che prevede lo stanziamento di 2,7 milioni di dollari americani ed è finanziato nel quadro della cooperazione allo sviluppo economico dalla Segreteria di Stato dell'economia (SECO), mira all'introduzione dei principi della trasparenza, dell'obbligo di rendiconto e della sostenibilità nel settore degli appalti pubblici. Ciò dovrebbe permettere di garantire, in occasione dei bandi di concorso pubblici, il libero accesso alle informazioni a tutte le parti interessate.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Dal 2002 il Ghana è uno dei Paesi sui quali si concentrano le attività svizzere di cooperazione allo sviluppo economico. In tale ambito la Svizzera si concentra, mediante l'aiuto budgetario generale e il sostegno tecnico, sul miglioramento delle condizioni quadro macroeconomiche e sulla trasparenza delle finanze pubbliche, sullo sviluppo e sul potenziamento del settore finanziario, sulla promozione di condizioni quadro favorevoli agli scambi commerciali e sul miglioramento del&amp;nbsp;clima degli investimenti nonché sul consolidamento delle condizioni quadro regolatrici nel settore delle infrastrutture e sul miglioramento dell'efficienza del settore energetico. Inoltre la Svizzera sostiene il «Kofi Annan International Peacekeeping and Training Centre&lt;strong&gt;»&lt;/strong&gt; ad Accra, destinato alla formazione di partecipanti africani alle missioni di pace nell'Africa occidentale.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Evelyn Kobelt, portavoce DFE, tel. +41 31 322 20 59, cellulare +41 79 301 71 72 Accordo sul traffico aereo di linea, Anton Kohler, UFAC, tel. +41 31 325 83 70 Accordo relativo al progetto: Hans-Peter Egler, SECO, tel. +41 31 324 08 13</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Official visit to Bern by the Ghanaian President, John Evans Atta Mills</title>
      <teaser>President Doris Leuthard, head of the Federal Department of Economic Affairs (FDEA), today received the President of Ghana, John Evans Atta Mills, for an official visit at the Lohn Country Residence in Kehrsatz. The Ghanaian President was accompanied by the Foreign Minister and the Ministers for Trade and Industry, Information and a cabinet minister. At the meeting, agreements were signed on air transport and on a project to promote sustainable public procurement in Ghana.</teaser>
      <lead>President Doris Leuthard, head of the Federal Department of Economic Affairs (FDEA), today received the President of Ghana, John Evans Atta Mills, for an official visit at the Lohn Country Residence in Kehrsatz. The Ghanaian President was accompanied by the Foreign Minister and the Ministers for Trade and Industry, Information and a cabinet minister. At the meeting, agreements were signed on air transport and on a project to promote sustainable public procurement in Ghana.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Discussions focussed on appraising bilateral relations between the two countries, economic and trade relations and cooperation in the field of economic development cooperation. Regional and multilateral issues were also addressed.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Following the official discussions an agreement on air transport was signed between the Swiss Federal Council and the Government of the Republic of Ghana. This replaces the existing agreement dating from 1961. A further agreement regarding a project to promote sustainable public procurement in Ghana was signed by State Secretary Jean-Daniel Gerber, the Director of SECO, and the Ghanaian Foreign Minister, Alhaji Muhammad Mumuni. The project, which is part of the economic development cooperation of the State Secretariat for Economic Affairs with funding of over USD 2.7 million, is intended to introduce the principles of transparency, accountability and sustainability in public procurement. In this way, free access to information should be assured for all interested parties regarding public tenders.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Ghana has been a priority country in Switzerland's economic development cooperation programme since 2002. As such Switzerland is concentrating its efforts via general budget support and technical assistance on the improvement of general macro-economic conditions and the transparency of public finances, the development and strengthening of the financial sector, the promotion of general conditions conducive to trade and the improvement of the investment climate, as well as the strengthening of the regulatory framework in the field of infrastructure and the improvement of efficiency in the energy sector. In addition, Switzerland supports the Kofi Annan International Peacekeeping and Training Centre in Accra which trains African members of peace missions in West Africa.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Evelyn Kobelt, Press Spokesperson FDEA, Tel. +41 31 322 20 59, Mobile +41 79 301 71 72 Air Transport Agreement: Anton Kohler, FOCA, Tel. +41 31 325 83 70 Project Agreement: Hans-Peter Egler, SECO, Tel. +41 31 324 08 13</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <keywords>
      <keyword id="703001" org-id="703">
        <name lang="de">SECO Cooperation</name>
        <name lang="fr">SECO Cooperation</name>
        <name lang="it">SECO Cooperation</name>
        <name lang="en">SECO Cooperation</name>
      </keyword>
    </keywords>
    <topics>
      <topic id="46">
        <name lang="de">Verkehr</name>
        <name lang="fr">Transports</name>
        <name lang="it">Trasporti</name>
        <name lang="en">Transport</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
