<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="35789" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2010-10-26</pubdate>
    <blocking-period>2010-10-26</blocking-period>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="1004" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>301</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Schweizerische Nationalbibliothek</name>
      <name lang="fr">Bibliothèque nationale suisse</name>
      <name lang="it">Biblioteca nazionale svizzera</name>
      <name lang="en">Swiss National Library</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.nb.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.nb.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.nb.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.nb.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@nb.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@nb.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@nb.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@nb.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="301">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement des Innern</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'intérieur</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'interno</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Home Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Die Bibliothek von Jean Starobinski wird dem Schweizerischen Literaturarchiv übergeben</title>
      <lead>Die Stiftung Hans Wilsdorf schenkt dem Schweizerischen Literaturarchiv (SLA) der Nationalbibliothek (NB) die persönliche Bibliothek von Jean Starobinski in einer Geste grosszügigen Mäzenatentums. Dieser Neuzugang vervollständigt das Archiv von Jean Starobinski.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;2003 wurde im Schweizerischen Literaturarchiv ein Archiv Jean Starobinski mit sämtlichen Manuskripten und Notizen sowie der Korrespondenz des grossen Genfer Gelehrten geschaffen. Das Archiv eines Intellektuellen ist jedoch erst dann komplett, wenn seine mit Anmerkungen versehene und signierte Autorenbibliothek konserviert und der Forschung zur Verfügung gestellt wird. Dies gilt in ganz besonderem Masse auch für die umfangreiche Bibliothek von Jean Starobinski (man schätzt sie auf gegen 40'000 Bände). Claude Reichler, Professor an der Universität Lausanne, hat im Auftrag der Schweizerischen Nationalbibliothek den wissenschaftlichen Wert dieser Sammlung evaluiert. Er sieht in ihr „das Zeugnis einer Welt von seltener Reichhaltigkeit und Kostbarkeit, die in ihrer Einheit erhalten und den kommenden Generationen zugänglich bleiben soll“. In Reichlers Worten ist diese „Bibliothek [Jean Starobinskis] Gedächtnis, sein Adressbuch, sein Ideenrepertoire, seine Projektschublade geworden – aber vor allem auch sein geistiges Universum, sein Lebensraum, intim und weitverzweigt, immens und doch beherrscht, worin er sich aufgehoben fühlt“.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;2010 setzte sich die NB mit der Stiftung Hans Wilsdorf in Verbindung. Diese ging in ihrem Entscheid weit über das Anliegen der NB hinaus und schenkte dem Schweizerischen Literaturarchiv die gesamte Bibliothek. „Es liegt uns daran“, sagt Pierre Mottu, der Präsident der Stiftung, „den Studierenden, der Forschung und der Lehre im Schweizerischen Literaturarchiv eine Dokumentation zugänglich zu machen, die sozusagen im Herzen der westlichen Kultur des 20. Jahrhunderts steht“. Diese Ansicht teilt auch Marie-Christine Doffey, Direktorin der NB. „Es freut mich“, sagt sie, „dass auch künftigen Forscherinnen und Forschern in der Schweiz ein so wichtiges kulturelles Erbe als Einheit erhalten bleibt. Als Dank an die Stiftung Hans Wilsdorf wird zum ersten Mal in der Geschichte der Institution am Eingang der NB eine Gedenktafel angebracht.“&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Die Tafel wird in Anwesenheit von Bundesrat Didier Burkhalter an einer geschlossenen Feier in der Schweizerischen Nationalbibliothek enthüllt. Aus Anlass des 90. Geburtstags von Jean Starobinski beginnt gleichzeitig ein öffentliches Kolloquium zum Thema «À distance de loge», das am 19. November 2010 in Bern und am 20. November 2010 in Genf stattfindet. Das Kolloquium ist Teil eines Projekts zur kritischen Literatur und zur Genfer Schule und wird durchgeführt im Rahmen des „Cercle d'études Jean Starobinski“, der vom SLA mit Unterstützung der Universität Genf geleitet wird. Der Cercle publiziert einmal jährlich ein Bulletin und organisiert regelmässig Konferenzen und Tagungen zum Werk von Jean Starobinski und zur Literaturkritik im Allgemeinen.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Adresse für Rückfragen: Marie-Christine Doffey, Direktorin Schweizerische Nationalbibliothek, Tel. 031/ 322 89 01, marie-christine.doffey@nb.admin.ch Stéphanie Cudré-Mauroux (Konservatorin Fonds Starobinski), Schweizerisches Literaturarchiv, Tel. : 031/ 323 23 55 (Montag - Donnerstag), stephanie.cudre-mauroux@nb.admin.ch Serge Bednarczyk, Stiftung Hans Wilsdorf Tel. 022/ 737 30 00, sbednarczyk@hanswilsdorf.ch Interessierte Medienschaffende erhalten auf Anfrage ein Exemplar des „Bulletin du Cercle“.</contact>
      <link id="75774">
        <title>Archiv Jean Starobinski</title>
        <uri>https://www.helveticarchives.ch/detail.aspx?id=290000</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="75775">
        <title>Fotos</title>
        <uri>http://www.nb.admin.ch/aktuelles/medieninformation/03103/index.html?lang=de</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>La Bibliothèque de Jean Starobinski entre aux Archives littéraires suisses</title>
      <lead>La Fondation Hans Wilsdorf, dans un geste de généreux mécénat, fait don de la bibliothèque personnelle de Jean Starobinski aux Archives littéraires suisses (ALS) de la Bibliothèque nationale (BN). La nouvelle acquisition complète le fonds Jean Starobinski.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;En 2003, un fonds Jean Starobinski, réunissant l’ensemble des manuscrits, des notes, de la correspondance du grand professeur genevois, était créé aux Archives littéraires suisses.Or, les archives d’un savant ne sont vraiment complètes que lorsque sa bibliothèque de travail, annotée, truffée, dédicacée, est conservée, et mise à disposition de la recherche. Ceci est particulièrement vrai pour la vaste bibliothèque de Jean Starobinski (on l’estime à quelque 40'000 livres). Claude Reichler, professeur à l’Université de Lausanne, ayant évalué la valeur scientifique de cette collection à la demande de la Bibliothèque nationale suisse, la voit comme «&amp;nbsp;le témoin d’un monde d’une richesse et d’un raffinement rares, dont il faut maintenir l’unité, et dont il faut préserver l’accès aux générations futures&amp;nbsp;». Car, poursuit-il «&amp;nbsp;[cette] bibliothèque est devenue à la fois [la] mémoire [de Jean Starobinski], son carnet d’adresses, son répertoire d’idées, ses tiroirs à projets –&amp;nbsp;et surtout son espace mental et son lieu de vie, un habitat intime et ramifié, immense et maîtrisé, dans lequel il se déplace avec aisance et amour.&amp;nbsp;»&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;En 2010, la Fondation Hans Wilsdorf fut approchée par la BN et décida d’aller bien au-delà de la demande qui lui était faite, en faisant don aux ALS de la totalité de cette bibliothèque. «&amp;nbsp;Il nous importe&amp;nbsp;», dit Pierre Mottu, président de la Fondation, «&amp;nbsp;que les étudiants, les chercheurs, les professeurs aient désormais à disposition, aux Archives littéraires suisses, un vaste ensemble documentaire qui est au cœur de la Culture occidentale du XXe siècle&amp;nbsp;», −&amp;nbsp;sentiment partagé par Marie-Christine Doffey, directrice de la Bibliothèque nationale (BN). «&amp;nbsp;Je suis heureuse&amp;nbsp;», dit-elle, «&amp;nbsp;qu’un objet très important de notre patrimoine puisse être conservé dans son unité, en Suisse, pour les chercheurs futurs. J’en suis très reconnaissante à la Fondation Hans Wilsdorf. Afin de la remercier, nous installerons, pour la première fois dans l’histoire de notre institution, une plaque commémorative à l’entrée de la BN&amp;nbsp;».&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;La plaque sera dévoilée à l’occasion d’une cérémonie privée à la Bibliothèque nationale suisse en présence du Conseiller fédéral Didier Burkhalter. Du même coup, et pour célébrer le 90ème anniversaire de Jean Starobinski, on donnera le coup d’envoi d’un colloque sur le thème «&amp;nbsp;À distance de loge&amp;nbsp;», ouvert à tous, qui se tiendra les 19 et 20 novembre 2010, la première journée à Berne, la seconde à Genève.Le colloque s’inscrit dans un projet ambitieux autour de la littérature critique et de l’École de Genève. Un « Cercle d’études Jean Starobinski », mené conjointement par les ALS et l’Université de Genève, a vu le jour, un « Bulletin du Cercle » paraît chaque année, et des conférences et colloques réguliers sont organisés autour de l’œuvre de Jean Starobinski et de la critique littéraire en général.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Renseignements complémentaires pour la presse : Marie-Christine Doffey, directrice de la Bibliothèque nationale suisse, Tél. 031/ 322 89 01, marie-christine.doffey@nb.admin.ch Stéphanie Cudré-Mauroux (conservateur du fonds Starobinski), Archives littéraires suisses, Tél. : 031/ 323 23 55 (du lundi au jeudi), stephanie.cudre-mauroux@nb.admin.ch Serge Bednarczyk, Fondation Hans Wilsdorf Tél. 022/ 737 30 00, sbednarczyk@hanswilsdorf.ch Des exemplaires du « Bulletin du Cercle » seront envoyés aux journalistes qui le souhaitent.</contact>
      <link id="75776">
        <title>Fonds Jean Starobinski</title>
        <uri>https://www.helveticarchives.ch/detail.aspx?id=290000</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="75777">
        <title>Images</title>
        <uri>http://www.nb.admin.ch/aktuelles/medieninformation/03103/index.html?lang=fr</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>La biblioteca di Jean Starobinski all'Archivio svizzero di letteratura</title>
      <lead>In un gesto di generoso mecenatismo, la Fondazione Hans Wilsdorf ha donato la biblioteca personale di Jean Starobinski all'Archivio svizzero di letteratura della Biblioteca nazionale. La nuova acquisizione viene a completare il fondo di Jean Starobinski.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Nel 2003 è stato creato all'Archivio svizzero di letteratura (ASL) un fondo Jean Starobinski che riunisce l'insieme dei manoscritti, degli appunti e della corrispondenza del grande professore ginevrino. Gli archivi di un intellettuale risultano completi solo se la sua biblioteca di lavoro con appunti, annotazioni, dediche viene conservata e messa a disposizione della ricerca. Questo vale in modo particolare per la vasta biblioteca di Jean Starobinski (si stima che contenga quasi 40&amp;nbsp;000 libri). Claude Reichler, professore all'Università di Losanna, dopo averne rilevato il valore scientifico su richiesta della Bibilioteca nazionale svizzera (BN), la ritiene «la testimonianza di un mondo di rara ricchezza e raffinatezza che deve essere conservata nel suo insieme e resa accessibile alle generazioni future, perché rappresenta la memoria di Jean Starobinski, la sua agenda, il suo repertorio d'idee, i suoi cassetti dei progetti e, soprattutto, il suo spazio mentale e il suo habitat intimo e ramificato, immenso e controllato in cui si muove con agilità e amore».&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Nel 2010, la Fondazione Hans Wilsdorf, interpellata dall'ASL, ha deciso di andare ben oltre la richiesta rivoltale donando all'ASL l'intera biblioteca. Per Pierre Mottu, presidente della Fondazione Hans Wilsdorf, «è importante che studenti, ricercatori e professori trovino all'ASL un vasto insieme documentario al centro della cultura occidentale del Novecento». Questo sentimento è condiviso da Marie-Christine Doffey, direttrice della BN: «sono felice e riconoscente alla Fondazione che un bene di una tale importanza per il patrimonio culturale venga conservato nella sua integralità in Svizzera e messo a disposizione dei ricercatori di domani. A titolo di ringraziamento, la BN affiggerà, per la prima volta nella storia dell'istituzione, una targa commemorativa all'entrata della sua sede».&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;La targa sarà scoperta in occasione di una cerimonia privata alla BN presenziata dal consigliere federale Didier Burkhalter. Per l'occasione e per celebrare il 90° compleanno di Jean Starobinski si terrà il convegno «À distance de loge», articolato su due giorni e aperto a tutti, il 19 novembre a Berna e il 20 novembre a Ginevra.Il convegno s'inserisce in un ambizioso progetto sulla critica letteraria e la Scuola di Ginevra. Il «Cercle d’études Jean Starobinski», istituito e gestito dall'ASL insieme all'Università di Ginevra, pubblica un bollettino annuale e tiene regolarmente conferenze e colloqui sull'opera di Jean Starobinski e la critica letteraria in generale.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Informazioni complementari per la stampa: Marie-Christine Doffey, direttrice della Biblioteca nazionale svizzera, tel. 031 322 89 01, marie-christine.doffey@nb.admin.ch Stéphanie Cudré-Mauroux, conservatrice del fondo Starobinski, Archivio svizzero di letteratura, tel. 031 323 23 55 (dal lunedì al giovedì), stephanie.cudre-mauroux@nb.admin.ch Serge Bednarczyk, Fondazione Hans Wilsdorf, tel. 022 737 30 00, sbednarczyk@hanswilsdorf.ch Ai giornalisti verranno inviate su richiesta copie del «Bulletin du Cercle».</contact>
      <link id="75779">
        <title>Fondo Jean Starobinski</title>
        <uri>https://www.helveticarchives.ch/detail.aspx?id=290000</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="75780">
        <title>Immagini</title>
        <uri>http://www.nb.admin.ch/aktuelles/medieninformation/03103/index.html?lang=it</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Jean Starobinski’s library donated to the Swiss Literary Archives</title>
      <lead>As a gesture of generous patronage, the Hans Wilsdorf Foundation has donated Jean Starobinski’s personal library to the Swiss Literary Archives (SLA) of the Swiss National Library (NL). This accession completes the Jean Starobinski Collection.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;In 2003, a Jean Starobinski Collection was created at the Swiss Literary Archives, bringing together all of the manuscripts, notes and correspondence written by this famous professor from Geneva.However, the archives of a scholar are not truly complete until his working library, complete with notes, clippings and commentaries is preserved and made available for research purposes. This is particularly true of Jean Starobinski’s vast library (containing an estimated 40,000 books). At the request of the Swiss National Library, Claude Reichler, a professor at the University of Lausanne, assessed the scientific value of the collection, which he sees as “evidence of a world of exceptional richness and refinement; its unity should be maintained and it should be made accessible for future generations”. He explains that “[this] library has become [Jean Starobinski’s] memory, his address book, his repertoire of ideas, his project drawers&amp;nbsp;and especially his mental space. It is also a vast and controlled, intimate and ramified environment, where he lives and moves lovingly and with ease.”&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;In 2010, the Hans Wilsdorf Foundation was approached by the NL. Following this initial contact, it decided to extend its generosity beyond the NL’s request by donating the entire library to the SLA. Pierre Mottu, president of the Foundation says, “It is important to us that this vast documentary collection, which is central to western culture of the 20th century, now be available at the Swiss Literary Archives to students, researchers and professors”. Marie-Christine Doffey, Director of the Swiss National Library (NL) is of the same mind. She says: “I am delighted that a very important object of our cultural heritage can be preserved in its entirety in Switzerland for future researchers. I am deeply grateful to the Hans Wilsdorf Foundation. As a token of our gratitude, we will put up a commemorative plaque at the entrance to the NL for the first time in our library’s history.”&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The plaque will be unveiled at a private ceremony held at the Swiss National Library in the presence of Federal Councillor Didier Burkhalter. At the same time, and to celebrate Jean Starobinski’s 90th birthday, a symposium on the subject of “À distance de loge” will be held in Bern on 19 November and in Geneva on 20 November. This symposium is open to the general public.The symposium is part of an ambitious project focussed on critical literature and the Geneva School. The SLA and the University of Geneva have jointly set up a “Jean Starobinski Study Circle”, a Circle Bulletin is published each year, and conferences and symposia are regularly organised to discuss the work of Jean Starobinski and literary criticism in general.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Contacts for the press: Marie-Christine Doffey, Director of the Swiss National Library, Tel.: 031/ 322 89 01, marie-christine.doffey@nb.admin.ch Stéphanie Cudré-Mauroux (curator of the Starobinski Collection), Swiss Literary Archives, Tel.: 031/ 323 23 55 (Monday to Thursday), stephanie.cudre-mauroux@nb.admin.ch Serge Bednarczyk, Hans Wilsdorf Foundation Tel.: 022/ 737 30 00, sbednarczyk@hanswilsdorf.ch Copies of the Circle Bulletin will be sent to any journalists interested in receiving it.</contact>
      <link id="75781">
        <title>Jean Starobinski collection</title>
        <uri>https://www.helveticarchives.ch/detail.aspx?id=290000</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="75782">
        <title>Photographs</title>
        <uri>http://www.nb.admin.ch/aktuelles/medieninformation/03103/index.html?lang=en</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="7">
        <name lang="de">Bibliotheken und Archive</name>
        <name lang="fr">Bibliothèques et archives</name>
        <name lang="it">Biblioteche e archivi</name>
        <name lang="en">Libraries and Archives</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="18">
        <name lang="de">Kultur</name>
        <name lang="fr">Culture</name>
        <name lang="it">Cultura</name>
        <name lang="en">Culture</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
