<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="35790" revoked="no">
    <version>6</version>
    <pubdate>2010-10-21</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="201" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>201</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="201">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Zehn Jahre Global Compact</title>
      <lead>Die Privatwirtschaft in die internationalen Anstrengungen der Entwicklungszusammenarbeit einzubinden, ist die Aufgabe von „Global Compact“. 2010 feiert Global Compact sein zehnjähriges Bestehen. Aus diesem Anlass diskutieren am 26. Oktober Fachleute an einer Veranstaltung der Direktion für Entwicklung und Zusammenarbeit (DEZA) sowie der Novartis Stiftung für nachhaltige Entwicklung über das Erreichte und die bevorstehenden Herausforderungen.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Die Schweiz war seit der Lancierung ein wichtiger und engagierter Begleiter und Förderer von Global Compact, und hat sowohl politisch als auch finanziell und organisatorisch einen wesentlichen Beitrag zur Anerkennung dieser globalen Initiative geleistet. &amp;nbsp;&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Aus Anlass des zehnjährigen Bestehens von Global Compact organisieren die DEZA und die Novartis Stiftung für nachhaltige Entwicklung am 26. Oktober eine öffentliche Veranstaltung, zu der auch die Medien eingeladen sind. Im Paul Klee Zentrum in Bern werden Fachleute aus Verwaltung, Wirtschaft, Nichtregierungsorganisationen und Entwicklungszusammenarbeit über die Bedeutung, den Nutzen und die künftigen Herausforderungen&amp;nbsp;von Global Compact diskutieren. An der Veranstaltung werden unter anderem Georg Kell, Direktor von Global Compact, der Theologe Hans Küng, DEZA-Direktor Martin Dahinden und Klaus M. Leisinger, Präsident der Novartis Stiftung für Nachhaltige Entwicklung, auftreten.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Global Compact ist eine Initiative der UNO. Er wurde vor zehn Jahren vom damaligen Generalsekretär Kofi Annan mit dem Ziel lanciert, den Privatsektor verstärkt in die Umsetzung der UNO-Entwicklungsziele einzubeziehen. Waren beim Start im Jahr 2000 lediglich 40 Unternehmen eingeschrieben, hat sich der Global Compact inzwischen zur wichtigsten Initiative im Bereich der verantwortungsvollen Unternehmensführung („corporate responsibility“) entwickelt und weist mehr als 8000 Teilnehmende aus. &amp;nbsp;&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Die Konferenz zu den Millenniums-Entwicklungszielen vom letzten September in New York hat der Notwendigkeit einer verstärkten Zusammenarbeit der staatlichen Entwicklungszusammenarbeit mit dem Privatsektor das Wort geredet.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Die Schweiz wird sich auch in den kommenden Jahren finanziell an der Umsetzung des Strategischen Dreijahresplans 2011 – 2013 von Global Compact beteiligen.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Information EDA Bundeshaus West CH-3003 Bern Tel.: +41 (0)31 322 31 53 Fax: +41 (0)31 324 90 47 E-Mail: info@eda.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="75820">
        <title>Nähere Angaben zu Anmeldung und Panellisten</title>
        <uri>http://www.deza.admin.ch/de/Home/Agenda/Agenda_Detailansicht?itemID=195761</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions>
        <revision date="2010-10-22 08:45" type="R"/>
        <revision date="2010-10-21 17:36" type="R"/>
      </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Le Pacte mondial fête ses dix ans</title>
      <lead>Associer l’économie privée aux efforts internationaux de la coopération au développement : telle est la mission que s’est fixée le Pacte mondial, qui fête cette année ses 10 dix ans d’existence. Pour marquer l’événement, la Direction du développement et de la coopération (DDC) et la Fondation Novartis pour un développement durable organisent, le 26 octobre prochain, une manifestation au cours de laquelle des experts seront invités à se prononcer sur les résultats atteints à ce jour ainsi que sur les défis actuels et futurs.</lead>
      <text link="no">Dès le lancement du Pacte mondial, la Suisse s’est attachée à accompagner et à promouvoir activement cette initiative, apportant une contribution politique, financière et organisationnelle substantielle à sa reconnaissance. &amp;nbsp;&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; A l’occasion du 10e anniversaire du Pacte mondial, la DDC et la Fondation Novartis pour un développement durable organisent le 26 octobre prochain une manifestation publique à laquelle sont invités les médias. Au Centre Paul Klee de Berne, des experts de l’administration, de l’économie, d’organisations non gouvernementales et de la coopération au développement débattront de l’importance du Pacte mondial, de son utilité ainsi que des défis qu’il devra relever. Prendront notamment la parole le directeur du Pacte mondial Georg Kell, le théologien Hans Küng, le directeur de la DDC Martin Dahinden et le président de la Fondation Novartis pour le développement Klaus M. Leisinger. &amp;nbsp;&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Le Pacte mondial est une initiative de l’ONU, lancée il y a dix ans par l’ancien secrétaire général Kofi Annan dans le but d’associer davantage le secteur privé à la réalisation des Objectifs du Millénaire pour le développement. Si le Pacte ne comptait que 40 entreprises en l’an 2000, il est devenu au fil des ans la principale initiative jamais lancée pour une responsabilisation accrue des entreprises («&amp;nbsp;corporate responsibility&amp;nbsp;») et enregistre à ce jour plus de 8000 entreprises. &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; La Conférence sur les Objectifs du Millénaire pour le développement, qui s’est tenue à New York en septembre dernier, a mis en évidence la nécessité de resserrer les liens entre coopération publique au développement et secteur privé.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; &lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; La Suisse entend maintenir son soutien au cours des années à venir et participera dès lors financièrement à la mise en œuvre du plan stratégique triennal 2011 – 2013 du Pacte mondial.</text>
      <contact>Information DFAE Palais fédéral ouest CH-3003 Berne Tél.: (+41) 031 322 31 53 Fax: (+41) 031 324 90 47 E-Mail: info@eda.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="75822">
        <title>Informations complémentaires sur les modalités d’inscription et les participants</title>
        <uri>http://www.deza.admin.ch/fr/Accueil/Manifestations/Agenda_vue_detaillee?itemID=195761</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Il Global Compact compie dieci anni</title>
      <lead>Il Global Compact persegue l’obiettivo di coinvolgere l’economia privata negli sforzi internazionali a favore della cooperazione allo sviluppo. Nel 2010, questo patto mondiale compie dieci anni. Per l’occasione, il 26 ottobre specialisti in materia si incontreranno in un evento promosso dalla Direzione dello sviluppo e della cooperazione (DSC) e dalla Fondazione Novartis per lo sviluppo sostenibile per discutere sugli obiettivi raggiunti e su quanto resta ancora da compiere.</lead>
      <text link="no">La Svizzera ha promosso e accompagnato il Global Compact sin dal suo lancio, contribuendo dal punto di vista politico, finanziario e organizzativo al riconoscimento dell’iniziativa. &amp;nbsp;&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Per celebrare il decimo anniversario di questo patto mondiale, il 26 ottobre la DSC e la Fondazione Novartis per lo sviluppo sostenibile organizzano un evento pubblico, al quale sono invitati anche gli organi di informazione. Presso il Centro Paul Klee di Berna, specialisti attivi nell’ambito dell’amministrazione, dell’economia, delle organizzazioni non governative e della cooperazione allo sviluppo discuteranno dell’importanza, dell’utilità e delle sfide future del Global Compact. All’evento parteciperanno anche il Direttore del Global Compact Georg Kell, il teologo Hans Küng, il Direttore della DSC Martin Dahinden e il Presidente della Fondazione Novartis per lo sviluppo sostenibile Klaus M. Leisinger. &amp;nbsp;&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Il Global Compact è un’iniziativa dell’ONU lanciata dieci anni or sono dall’allora Segretario generale Kofi Annan allo scopo di coinvolgere maggiormente il settore privato nell’applicazione degli Obiettivi di Sviluppo dell’ONU. Se nel 2000 vi avevano aderito soltanto quaranta aziende, nel frattempo il Global Compact è diventato la maggiore iniziativa nel campo della gestione aziendale responsabile (corporate responsibility) e vanta oltre 8000 partecipanti. &amp;nbsp;&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; La conferenza sugli Obiettivi di Sviluppo del Millennio tenutasi lo scorso settembre a New York ha posto l’accento sulla necessità di potenziare la collaborazione tra la cooperazione statale allo sviluppo e il settore privato.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; &lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Anche negli anni a venire, la Svizzera parteciperà finanziariamente all’attuazione del Piano strategico triennale 2011-2013 del Global Compact.</text>
      <contact>Informazione DFAE Palazzo federale ovest CH-3003 Berna Tel.: (+41) 031 322 31 53 Fax: (+41) 031 324 90 47 E-Mail: info@eda.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="75821">
        <title>Maggiori informazioni sull’iscrizione e il programma (fr)</title>
        <uri>http://www.deza.admin.ch/it/Pagina_iniziale/Eventi/Dettagli_agenda?itemID=195761</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Global Compact marks tenth anniversary</title>
      <lead>“Global Compact” aims to integrate private-sector companies into international efforts in the field of development cooperation. In 2010, Global Compact will celebrate its tenth anniversary. To mark the occasion, experts will take part in a discussion on 26 October organized by the Swiss Agency for Development and Cooperation (SDC) and the Novartis Foundation for Sustainable Development on the achievements to date and the challenges of the future.</lead>
      <text link="no">Since the launch of Global Compact, Switzerland has been a key and committed supporter and promoter and has made a significant contribution towards recognition of this global initiative in political, financial and organizational terms. &amp;nbsp;&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; On the occasion of the tenth anniversary of Global Compact, the SDC and the Novartis Foundation for Sustainable Development are organizing a public event on 26 October to which the media are also invited. Experts in the fields of administration, business, non-governmental organizations and development cooperation will meet at the Paul Klee Centre in Berne to discuss the significance, benefits and future challenges of Global Compact. Attendees will include Georg Kell, Executive Director of Global Compact, theologian Hans Küng, SDC Director General Martin Dahinden and Klaus M. Leisinger, President of the Novartis Foundation for Sustainable Development. &amp;nbsp;&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Global Compact is an initiative of the United Nations. It was launched ten years ago by the then Secretary General Kofi Annan with the aim of integrating the private sector more closely into implementation of the UN development goals. Whereas only 40 companies were members in 2000, Global Compact has since developed into the most important initiative in the field of corporate responsibility and now numbers over 8,000 members. &amp;nbsp;&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; The conference on the millennium development goals held in September in New York highlighted the need for greater cooperation in the field of state-run development cooperation with the private sector.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; &lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Over the next few years, Switzerland will continue to contribute financing to the implementation of Global Compact’s strategic 2011-2013 three-year plan.</text>
      <contact>Information FDFA Bundeshaus West CH-3003 Bern Tel.: (+41) 031 322 31 53 Fax: (+41) 031 324 90 47 E-Mail: info@eda.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="75823">
        <title>Further details of registration and panel lists (fr)</title>
        <uri>http://www.deza.admin.ch/en/Home/Events/Agenda_Detailed_view?itemID=195761</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
