<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="36627" revoked="no">
    <version>4</version>
    <pubdate>2010-12-07</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="408" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>408</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Bundesanwaltschaft</name>
      <name lang="fr">Ministère public de la Confédération</name>
      <name lang="it">Ministero pubblico della Confederazione</name>
      <name lang="en">Office of the Attorney General of Switzerland</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.ba.admin.ch/ba/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.ba.admin.ch/ba/fr/home.html</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.ba.admin.ch/ba/it/home.html</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.ba.admin.ch/</www>
      <email lang="de">info@ba.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@ba.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@ba.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@ba.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="408">
      <name lang="de">Bundesanwaltschaft</name>
      <name lang="fr">Ministère public de la Confédération</name>
      <name lang="it">Ministero pubblico della Confederazione</name>
      <name lang="en">Office of the Attorney General of Switzerland</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.ba.admin.ch/ba/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.ba.admin.ch/ba/fr/home.html</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.ba.admin.ch/ba/it/home.html</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.ba.admin.ch/</www>
      <email lang="de">info@ba.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@ba.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@ba.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@ba.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Rückerstattung von 20 Millionen Schweizer Franken an Taiwan</title>
      <lead>Die Bundesanwaltschaft (BA) hat dem Supreme Prosecutors Office in Taiwan einen Teil der in der Schweiz deponierten Vermögenswerte des in seinem Land wegen Korruption verurteilten ehemaligen taiwanesischen Präsidenten Chen Shui-bian herausgegeben. Die Rückerstattung der rund 20 Millionen Schweizer Franken zeugt einmal mehr vom festen Willen der Schweiz, sich dem Missbrauch ihres Finanzplatzes für kriminelle Zwecke entgegenzustellen und die Gelder kriminellen Ursprungs an die Geschädigten zurückzugeben. Das Schweizer Strafverfahren wird fortgesetzt mit dem Ziel, die Herkunft der restlichen blockierten Gelder zu bestimmen.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Die Bundesanwaltschaft führt seit 7. Januar 2008 ein Strafverfahren gegen den Sohn und die Schwiegertochter von Chen Shui-bian wegen Verdachts auf Geldwäscherei. Der ehemalige taiwanesische Präsident und seine Gattin wurden ihrerseits kürzlich von den taiwanesischen Justizbehörden wegen Korruption zu einer Gefängnisstrafe von insgesamt 19 Jahren verurteilt.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Im Rahmen des in der Schweiz geführten Strafverfahrens sowie des Vollzugs eines Rechtshilfeersuchens der taiwanesischen Justizbehörden wurden rund 37 Millionen Schweizer Franken beschlagnahmt.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Aufgrund der engen und effizienten Zusammenarbeit mit dem taiwanesischen Supreme Prosecutors Office konnte die Bundesanwaltschaft nun einen Teil der in der Schweiz deponierten und mutmasslich aus kriminellen Aktivitäten stammenden Gelder des ehemaligen taiwanesischen Präsidenten vorzeitig an die taiwanesischen Justizbehörden herausgeben. Die beteiligten Parteien haben sich der Rückgabe der rund 20 Millionen Schweizer Franken nicht widersetzt.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Die Bundesanwaltschaft setzt ihr Strafverfahren zwecks Bestimmung der Herkunft der restlichen in der Schweiz beschlagnahmten Vermögenswerte fort.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Jeannette Balmer, Mediensprecherin BA, Tel. +41 (0)31 324 32 40</contact>
      <revisions>
        <revision date="2010-12-07 12:40" type="R"/>
        <revision date="2010-12-07 12:12" type="I"/>
      </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>20 millions de francs suisses restitués à Taïwan</title>
      <lead>Le Ministère public de la Confédération (MPC) a remis au Supreme Prosecutors Office de Taïwan une partie des avoirs déposés en Suisse, environ 20 millions de francs suisses, par l’ancien Président taïwanais, Chen Shui-bian, condamné pour corruption dans son pays. Cette restitution témoigne une fois de plus de la ferme volonté de la Suisse de s’opposer à ce qu’on utilise sa place financière à des fins criminelles et de restituer les fonds d’origine criminelle aux lésés. La procédure nationale se poursuit pour déterminer l’origine du solde des avoirs bloqués en Suisse.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Le MPC conduit depuis le 7 janvier 2008 une procédure pénale à l'encontre du fils de Chen Shui-bian et de sa belle-fille pour des soupçons de blanchiment d'argent. L'ancien Président taïwanais et son épouse ont été condamnés récemment par les autorités judiciaires taïwanaises à une peine totale de 19 ans de prison pour corruption.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Dans le cadre de la procédure pénale conduite en Suisse et en exécution d'une demande d'entraide judiciaire présentée par les autorités judiciaires taïwanaises, quelques 37 millions de francs suisses ont été placés sous séquestre.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Grâce à une collaboration étroite et efficace entre le Supreme Prosecutors Office de Taïwan et le MPC, une partie des fonds déposés en Suisse présumés provenir des activités criminelles de l'ancien Président taïwanais a fait l'objet d'une remise anticipée aux autorités judiciaires taïwanaises. Les parties en cause ne se sont pas opposées à cette remise d'un montant d'environ 20 millions de francs suisses.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;L'enquête nationale se poursuit pour déterminer l'origine du solde des fonds saisis en Suisse.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Jeannette Balmer, porte-parole MPC, tél. +41 (0)31 324 32 40</contact>
      <revisions>
        <revision date="2010-12-07 12:40" type="R"/>
        <revision date="2010-12-07 12:12" type="I"/>
        <revision date="2010-12-07 14:38" type="I"/>
      </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Restituiti 20 milioni di franchi svizzeri a Taiwan</title>
      <lead>Il Ministero pubblico della Confederazione (MPC) ha consegnato al Supreme Prosecutors Office di Taiwan una parte degli averi, pari a circa CHF 20 milioni, depositati in Svizzera dall’ex presidente taiwanese Chen Shui-bian, condannato nel suo Paese per corruzione. La restituzione è l’ulteriore dimostrazione che la Svizzera è fermamente risoluta a opporsi a un uso della sua piazza finanziaria per scopi criminali e a restituire ai danneggiati i fondi di origine criminale. Il procedimento svizzero è ora volto a individuare l’origine dell’altra parte dei fondi bloccati in Svizzera.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Dal 7 gennaio 2008 il MPC conduce un procedimento penale nei confronti del figlio e della nuora di Chen Shui-bian per titolo di riciclaggio di denaro. Le autorità giudiziarie di Taiwan hanno di recente condannato l'ex presidente taiwanese e sua moglie a una pena di complessivamente 19 anni di carcere per corruzione.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Nell'ambito del procedimento penale condotto in Svizzera e in esecuzione a una domanda di assistenza giudiziaria presentata dalle autorità taiwanesi, sono stati messi sotto sequestro circa 37 milioni di franchi svizzeri.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Grazie alla stretta ed efficace collaborazione con il Supreme Prosecutors Office di Taiwan, il MPC ha consegnato anticipatamente una parte dei fondi depositati in Svizzera, che proverrebbero dalle attività criminali dell'ex presidente taiwanese, alle autorità giudiziarie taiwanesi. Le parti in causa non si sono opposte alla consegna dell'importo di circa 20 milioni di franchi svizzeri.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;L'inchiesta svizzera è ora volta a far luce sull'origine dei fondi rimanenti sequestrati in Svizzera.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Jeannette Balmer, portavoce MPC, tel. +41 (0)31 324 32 40</contact>
      <revisions>
        <revision date="2010-12-07 12:40" type="R"/>
        <revision date="2010-12-07 12:12" type="I"/>
        <revision date="2010-12-07 14:38" type="I"/>
      </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>CHF 20 million returned to Taiwan</title>
      <lead>The Attorney General of Switzerland (OAG) has returned some CHF 20 million to the Supreme Prosecutors Office of Taiwan, part of the money that was deposited in Switzerland by the former Taiwanese President, Chen Shui-bian, who was recently convicted of corruption in his homeland. This move once again demonstrates Switzerland’s resolve to take action against those who use its financial centre for criminal purposes and its intention to restore assets of criminal origin to their rightful owners. Proceedings here are continuing in order to establish the origin of the remainder of assets currently frozen in Switzerland.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;The OAG has since 7 January 2008 been conducting criminal proceedings against Chen Shui-bian's son and daughter-in-law on suspicion of money laundering. The former Taiwanese President and his wife were recently sentenced by the Taiwanese courts to a total of 19 years imprisonment for corruption.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;As part of the proceedings conducted in Switzerland and in response to a request for mutual assistance filed by the Taiwanese authorities, some CHF 37 million has been seized.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Thanks to close and effective collaboration between the Taiwanese Supreme Prosecutors Office and the OAG, part of the funds deposited in Switzerland that are presumed to have originated from the criminal activities of the former Taiwanese President have been returned to the Taiwanese authorities as an anticipated handover. No objection was raised by any of the parties to the proceedings to the return of the sum of around CHF 20 million.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The investigation in Switzerland to determine the origin of the remainder of the assets is continuing.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Jeannette Balmer, OAG spokesperson, Tel. +41 (0)31 324 32 40</contact>
      <revisions>
        <revision date="2010-12-07 12:40" type="R"/>
        <revision date="2010-12-07 12:12" type="I"/>
        <revision date="2010-12-07 14:38" type="I"/>
      </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="26">
        <name lang="de">Recht</name>
        <name lang="fr">Droit</name>
        <name lang="it">Diritto</name>
        <name lang="en">Legal Affairs</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="35">
        <name lang="de">Finanzplatz</name>
        <name lang="fr">Place financière</name>
        <name lang="it">Piazza finanziaria</name>
        <name lang="en">Financial Centre</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
