<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="56139" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2015-02-05</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="324" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>301</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Swissmedic, Schweizerisches Heilmittelinstitut</name>
      <name lang="fr">Swissmedic, Institut suisse des produits thérapeutiques</name>
      <name lang="it">Swissmedic, Istituto svizzero per gli agenti terapeutici</name>
      <name lang="en">Swiss Agency for Therapeutic Products</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.swissmedic.ch/</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.swissmedic.ch/?lang=3</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.swissmedic.ch/?lang=4</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.swissmedic.ch/?lang=2</www>
      <email lang="de"/>
      <email lang="fr"/>
      <email lang="it"/>
      <email lang="en"/>
    </originator>
    <department id="301">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement des Innern</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'intérieur</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'interno</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Home Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Zunahme illegaler Arzneimittelimporte im Jahr 2014: Die Risiken werden unterschätzt</title>
      <lead>Die Risiken und Gefahren bei der Einnahme von Medikamenten, die selber beschafft und ohne ärztliche Überwachung eingenommen werden, sind vielfältig. Trotzdem wurden im letzten Jahr an der Schweizer Grenze mehr illegale Arzneimittel beschlagnahmt als im Vorjahr. Dies nach drei Jahren mit sinkenden Zahlen. Über die Hälfte der beschlagnahmten Arzneimittel waren Erektionsförderer. 45 % aller beschlagnahmten Medikamente stammten aus Indien.</lead>
      <text link="no">Im vergangenen Jahr meldete der Schweizer Zoll 1'225 Beschlagnahmungen illegaler Arzneimittelsendungen an Swissmedic. Im Vorjahr waren es 1'096 Meldungen. 53 % dieser Präparate waren Erektionsförderer, 13 % Schlaf- und Beruhigungsmittel und 10 % Schlankheitsmittel. Damit sind starke Schlaf- und Beruhigungsmittel, die auch ein gewisses Abhängigkeitspotenzial haben, neu an zweiter Stelle.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Während die Anzahl illegaler Importe zwischen 2010 (1'852) und 2013 (1'096) gesunken ist, nahm die Anzahl Beschlagnahmungen 2014 um ca. 11 % zu. Trotzdem glaubt Swissmedic noch nicht an eine Trendwende, ist aber wegen dem stark gestiegenen Anteil illegal eingeführter Erektionsförderer besorgt. Während 2012 26 % der beschlagnahmten Medikamente und 2013 bereits 42 % aus dieser Kategorie stammten, stieg deren Anteil letztes Jahr auf 53 %.</text>
      <contact>Swissmedic, Schweizerisches Heilmittelinstitut Peter Balzli, Mediensprecher +41 58 462 02 76 media@swissmedic.ch</contact>
      <link id="132687">
        <title>Mehr Informationen...</title>
        <uri>https://www.swissmedic.ch/aktuell/00673/02623/index.html?lang=de</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="132684">
        <title>Eidgenössische Zollverwaltung EZV - Zoll 2014</title>
        <uri>http://www.ezv.admin.ch/aktuell/04042/04081/05645/index.html?lang=de&amp;msg-id=56131</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Augmentation des importations illégales de médicaments en 2014: les risques encourus sont sous-estimés</title>
      <lead>Les dangers et les risques encourus lors de la prise de médicaments achetés soi-même hors de toute surveillance médicale sont variés. Il n'en reste pas moins que le nombre de médicaments illégaux saisis aux frontières de notre pays a à nouveau augmenté en 2014 par rapport à l'année précédente. Et ce, après trois années consécutives de baisse. Plus de 50 % des médicaments saisis étaient des stimulants de l'érection et 45 % provenaient d'Inde.</lead>
      <text link="no">Les douanes suisses ont annoncé à Swissmedic la saisie de 1225 envois de médicaments illégaux en 2014, contre 1096 l'année précédente. 53 % de ces préparations étaient des stimulants de la fonction érectile, 13 % des somnifères et des calmants et 10 % des produits amincissants. Les somnifères et calmants, qui peuvent entraîner une dépendance, arrivent donc maintenant en deuxième position.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Tandis que le nombre d'importations illégales avait chuté entre 2010 (1852) et 2013 (1096), celui des saisies a augmenté d'environ 11 % en 2014. S'il n'y voit pas encore un renversement de tendance, Swissmedic s'inquiète du net accroissement du nombre d'importations illégales de stimulants de l'érection. Formant 26 % des médicaments saisis en 2012, les stimulants de l'érection représentaient déjà 42 % en 2013 et ont atteint 53 % l'année dernière.</text>
      <contact>Swissmedic, Institut suisse des produits thérapeutiques Peter Balzli, porte-parole +41 58 462 02 76 media@swissmedic.ch</contact>
      <link id="132688">
        <title>Plus d'informations...</title>
        <uri>https://www.swissmedic.ch/aktuell/00673/02623/index.html?lang=fr</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="132685">
        <title>Administration fédérale des douanes AFD - La douane en 2014</title>
        <uri>http://www.ezv.admin.ch/aktuell/04042/04081/05645/index.html?lang=fr&amp;msg-id=56131</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Aumento delle importazioni illegali di medicamenti nel 2014: rischi sottovalutati</title>
      <lead>I rischi e i pericoli di assumere medicamenti acquistati per proprio conto e senza controllo medico sono molteplici. Ciò nonostante, nel corso del 2014, al confine svizzero è stato sequestrato un quantitativo superiore di medicamenti illegali rispetto all'anno precedente e questo dopo tre anni di tendenza in calo. Oltre la metà dei prodotti sequestrati erano stimolanti per l'erezione, il 45% del totale proveniva dall'India.</lead>
      <text link="no">Lo scorso anno, la dogana svizzera ha segnalato a Swissmedic 1'225 sequestri di spedizioni di medicamenti illegali. L'anno precedente le segnalazioni erano state 1'096. Il 53% di questi preparati erano stimolanti per l'erezione, il 13% sonniferi e tranquillanti e il 10% prodotti dimagranti. Sonniferi e tranquillanti, i quali hanno anche un certo potenziale di dipendenza, salgono così al secondo posto.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Mentre il numero di importazioni illegali tra il 2010 (1'852) e il 2013 (1'096) è diminuito, nel 2014 i sequestri sono aumentati dell'11% circa. Swissmedic non è ancora convinto che si tratti di un'inversione di tendenza, ma è preoccupato per il forte aumento della quota di stimolanti per l'erezione importati illegalmente. Nel corso del 2012 il 26% dei medicamenti sequestrati proveniva da questa categoria, ma già nel 2013 si era passati al 42% e nel 2014 addirittura al 53%.</text>
      <contact>Swissmedic, Istituto svizzero per gli agenti terapeutici Peter Balzli, portavoce +41 58 462 02 76 media@swissmedic.ch</contact>
      <link id="132689">
        <title>Ulteriori informazioni...</title>
        <uri>https://www.swissmedic.ch/aktuell/00673/02623/index.html?lang=it</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="132686">
        <title>Amministrazione federale delle dogane AFD - Dogana 2014</title>
        <uri>http://www.ezv.admin.ch/aktuell/04042/04081/05645/index.html?lang=it&amp;msg-id=56131</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Increase in illegal imports of medicinal products in 2014: The risks are underestimated</title>
      <lead>Medicines that people buy and take themselves without medical supervision involve numerous risks and dangers. Nevertheless, more illegal medicinal products were confiscated at the Swiss border last year than in the previous year. This follows a period of three years in which numbers declined. Over half the confiscated medicinal products were erectile stimulants. 45% of all the medicines confiscated originated in India.</lead>
      <text link="no">Last year, Swiss customs reported 1,225 confiscations of illegal shipments of medicinal products to Swissmedic, compared to 1,096 cases in 2013. 53% of the preparations confiscated were erectile stimulants, 13% sleeping pills and tranquillisers and 10% slimming preparations. This puts sleeping pills and tranquillisers, which have a certain potential for dependency, in second place for the first time.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;While the number of illegal imports fell between 2010 (1,852) and 2013 (1,096), the number of confiscations increased in 2014 by approx. 11%. While Swissmedic does not yet believe that this represents a reversal of the trend, it is nevertheless concerned about the sharp rise in the proportion of illegally imported erectile stimulants. Whereas this category accounted for 26% and 42% of seized medicines in 2012 and 2013 respectively, the figure rose to 53% last year.</text>
      <contact>Swissmedic, Swiss Agency for Therapeutic Products Peter Balzli, Acting spokesman +41 58 462 02 76 media@swissmedic.ch</contact>
      <link id="132690">
        <title>More information...</title>
        <uri>https://www.swissmedic.ch/aktuell/00673/02623/index.html?lang=en</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="15">
        <name lang="de">Gesundheit</name>
        <name lang="fr">Santé</name>
        <name lang="it">sanità</name>
        <name lang="en">Health</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
