<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="103304" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2024-11-29</pubdate>
    <blocking-period>2024-11-29</blocking-period>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="318" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>301</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Bundesamt für Statistik</name>
      <name lang="fr">Office fédéral de la statistique</name>
      <name lang="it">Ufficio federale di statistica</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Statistical Office</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.statistik.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.statistique.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.statistica.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.statistics.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@bfs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@bfs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@bfs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@bfs.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="301">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement des Innern</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'intérieur</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'interno</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Home Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Neuchâtel</city>
      <title>Kulturwirtschaft: Kulturunternehmen im Jahr 2022 - Immer mehr, aber kleinere Kulturunternehmen</title>
      <lead>Die Anzahl Kulturunternehmen ist im Jahr 2022 auf über 67 000 angestiegen, die Anzahl Beschäftigte im Kultursektor auf fast 241 000. Beide Werte übertreffen die Zahlen von 2019, dem Jahr vor der Covid-19-Pandemie, und sind sogar neue Höchstwerte seit 2011. Mit 16,3 Milliarden ist auch die Bruttowertschöpfung des Kultursektors höher als vor der Pandemie. Die Kulturunternehmen werden jedoch tendenziell immer kleiner: Die Anzahl Beschäftigte und die Vollzeitäquivalente pro Betrieb sinken im Mehrjahresvergleich. Dies sind einige der Ergebnisse der Statistik der Kulturwirtschaft des Bundesamtes für Statistik (BFS).</lead>
      <text link="no">Diese Medienmitteilung und weitere Informationen zum Thema finden Sie auf der Website des BFS (siehe Link unten).</text>
      <contact>Olivier Moeschler, BFS, Sektion Politik, Kultur und Medien, Tel.: +41 58 463 61 58, E-Mail: poku@bfs.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="282415">
        <title>Kompletter Text und Mediendossier</title>
        <uri>https://www.bfs.admin.ch/news/de/2024-0386</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Neuchâtel</city>
      <title>Économie culturelle: les entreprises culturelles en 2022 - Des entreprises culturelles toujours plus nombreuses, mais plus petites</title>
      <lead>En 2022, le nombre d’entreprises culturelles a dépassé les 67 000 et le nombre d’emplois dans le secteur culturel a presque atteint 241 000. Ces deux chiffres dépassent ceux de 2019, l’année précédant la pandémie de COVID-19, et constituent même de nouveaux records depuis 2011. Atteignant 16,3 milliards, la valeur ajoutée brute de ce secteur est également plus élevée qu’avant la pandémie. La taille des entreprises culturelles a néanmoins tendance à se réduire: le nombre d’emplois et d’équivalents plein temps par entreprise baisse d’année en année. Ce sont-là quelques-uns des résultats de la statistique de l’économie culturelle, de l’Office fédéral de la statistique (OFS). </lead>
      <text link="no">Vous trouverez ce communiqué de presse et d'autres informations sur ce thème sur le site web de l'OFS (cf. lien ci-dessous).</text>
      <contact>Olivier Moeschler, OFS, Section Politique, culture, médias, tél. +41 58 463 61 58, e-mail: poku@bfs.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="282416">
        <title>Texte intégral et dossier de presse</title>
        <uri>https://www.bfs.admin.ch/news/fr/2024-0386</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Neuchâtel</city>
      <title>Economia culturale: imprese culturali nel 2022 - Imprese culturali: sempre di più, ma di più piccole dimensioni</title>
      <lead>Nel 2022 il numero di imprese attive nel settore della cultura è salito a oltre 67 000 come pure quello degli impieghi, che ha quasi raggiunto quota 241 000. Entrambe le cifre sono superiori a quelle del 2019, anno precedente la pandemia di COVID-19, e segnano addirittura nuovi picchi massimi dal 2011. Con 16,3 miliardi, anche il valore aggiunto lordo del settore culturale è superiore a quello precedente la pandemia. Le imprese del settore culturale tendono però a diventare sempre più piccole: hanno infatti visto diminuire di anno in anno sia il numero di impieghi che quello degli equivalenti a tempo pieno per impresa. Questi sono alcuni dei risultati provenienti dalla statistica dell’economia culturale stilata dall’Ufficio federale di statistica (UST).</lead>
      <text link="no">Il presente comunicato stampa e ulteriori informazioni sul tema sono reperibili sulla pagina Internet dell'UST (link sotto).</text>
      <contact>Olivier Moeschler, UST, sezione Politica, cultura, media, tel.: +41 58 463 61 58, e-mail: poku@bfs.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="282417">
        <title>Testo integrale e dossier per i media</title>
        <uri>https://www.bfs.admin.ch/news/it/2024-0386</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Neuchâtel</city>
      <title>Cultural economy: Cultural enterprises in 2022 - More, but smaller, cultural enterprises</title>
      <lead>The number of cultural enterprises rose to over 67 000 in 2022, while the number of jobs in the culture sector increased to almost 241 000. Both figures are higher than in 2019, a year before the COVID-19 pandemic. They are also the highest since 2011. At CHF 16.3 billion, gross value added in the culture sector is also higher than it was before the pandemic. Cultural enterprises are getting smaller, however. The number of jobs and full-time equivalent positions per company has been falling for several years. These are some of the new findings from the Cultural Economy Statistics of the Federal Statistical Office (FSO).</lead>
      <text link="no">This press release and further information on the topic can be found on the FSO website (see link below).</text>
      <contact>Olivier Moeschler, FSO, Culture, media, information society, sport, tel.: +41 58 463 61 58, email: poku@bfs.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="282418">
        <title>Complete text and press kit - Please note that the English version only includes the release's lead</title>
        <uri>https://www.bfs.admin.ch/news/en/2024-0386</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <keywords>
      <keyword id="317" org-id="318">
        <name lang="de">Statistische Grundlagen und Übersichten (Statistische Grundlagen)</name>
        <name lang="fr">Bases statistiques et produits généraux (Bases statistiques)</name>
        <name lang="it">Basi statistiche e presentazioni generali (Basi statistiche)</name>
        <name lang="en">Statistical basis and overviews (Statistical basis)</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="317.17" org-id="318">
        <name lang="de">Kultur, Informationsgesellschaft, Sport</name>
        <name lang="fr">Culture, société de l'information, sport</name>
        <name lang="it">Cultura, media</name>
        <name lang="en">Culture, information society, sports</name>
      </keyword>
    </keywords>
    <topics>
      <topic id="18">
        <name lang="de">Kultur</name>
        <name lang="fr">Culture</name>
        <name lang="it">Cultura</name>
        <name lang="en">Culture</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="43">
        <name lang="de">Statistik</name>
        <name lang="fr">Statistiques</name>
        <name lang="it">Statistica</name>
        <name lang="en">Statistics</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
