<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="103156" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2024-11-15</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="1070" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>1070</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Der Bundesrat</name>
      <name lang="fr">Conseil fédéral</name>
      <name lang="it">Il Consiglio federale</name>
      <name lang="en">The Federal Council</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.admin.ch/gov/de/start.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.admin.ch/gov/fr/accueil.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.admin.ch/gov/it/pagina-iniziale.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.admin.ch/gov/en/start.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="yes" id="703" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>701</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Staatssekretariat für Wirtschaft</name>
      <name lang="fr">Secrétariat d'Etat à l'économie</name>
      <name lang="it">Segreteria di Stato dell'economia</name>
      <name lang="en">State Secretariat for Economic Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.seco.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.seco.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.seco.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.seco.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@seco.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@seco.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@seco.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@seco.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="1070">
      <name lang="de">Der Bundesrat</name>
      <name lang="fr">Conseil fédéral</name>
      <name lang="it">Il Consiglio federale</name>
      <name lang="en">The Federal Council</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.admin.ch/gov/de/start.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.admin.ch/gov/fr/accueil.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.admin.ch/gov/it/pagina-iniziale.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.admin.ch/gov/en/start.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <department id="701">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Wirtschaft, Bildung und Forschung</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'économie, de la formation et de la recherche</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'economia, della formazione e della ricerca</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Economic Affairs, Education and Research</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Abkommen über Klimawandel, Handel und Nachhaltigkeit (ACCTS) unterzeichnet</title>
      <lead>Bundesrat Guy Parmelin und seine Amtskolleginnen und -kollegen aus Costa Rica, Island und Neuseeland haben am 15. November 2024 in einer virtuellen Unterzeichnungszeremonie das Abkommen über Klimawandel, Handel und Nachhaltigkeit (ACCTS) unterzeichnet. </lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Costa Rica, Island, Neuseeland und die Schweiz vereinbaren mit ACCTS erstmals ein rechtsverbindliches Handelsabkommen, das primär umweltpolitischen Zielsetzungen dient. Die vereinbarten Bestimmungen nutzen handelspolitische Instrumente zur Unterstützung des Übergangs zu emissionsarmen, klimaresistenten und nachhaltigen Volkswirtschaften. Das Abkommen stützt sich auf das bestehende internationale Handelsrecht der WTO und entwickelt dieses weiter. Es soll eine Vorreiterfunktion einnehmen und durch den Beitritt zusätzlicher Vertragsparteien wachsen. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Liberalisierung des Handels mit Umweltgütern und -dienstleistungen&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Die mit ACCTS vereinbarte Liberalisierung und erhöhte Rechtssicherheit stärkt international die Wertschöpfungsketten für umweltfreundliche Güter und Dienstleistungen und alle daran beteiligten Sektoren in der Schweiz. Das Abkommen enthält ökologisch fundierte und glaubwürdige Listen von mehr als 300 Umweltgütern und mehr als 100 Umwelt- und umweltbezogene Dienstleistungen und verpflichtet die Parteien, Zölle und andere Handelshemmnisse für diese abzubauen. Von der Liberalisierung profitieren Importe aus allen WTO-Mitgliedern im Sinne des Meistbegünstigungsprinzips.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Regulierung von Subventionen für fossile Energien&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;ACCTS ist das erste internationale Abkommen mit einer Definition für schädliche Subventionen für fossile Energien. Gestützt darauf werden Subventionen für Kohle oder für die Produktion von Öl und Gas verboten. Während die Einführung neuer Subventionen für fossile Energien grundsätzlich untersagt ist, dürfen bestehende, erlaubte Massnahmen nicht ausgeweitet werden. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Leitlinien für freiwillige Umweltzeichen (ecolabels)&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Mit 13 unverbindlichen Leitlinien unterstützt das Abkommen alle Akteure, die freiwillige Umweltzeichen entwickeln oder verwenden, falsche Informationen sowie unnötige Handelshemmnisse und Umsetzungskosten zu vermeiden. Umweltzeichen unterstützen die Konsumenten, Produkte besser anhand ihrer Umweltleistung zu unterscheiden. Den Produzenten erlauben sie, ökologische Mehrwerte ihrer Erzeugnisse im Markt auszuloben.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Ratifikation durch das Parlament&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Das Abkommen wird dem Parlament zur Genehmigung unterbreitet und voraussichtlich Anfang des Jahres 2026 für die Schweiz in Kraft treten.&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Kommunikationsdienst WBF, info@gs-wbf.admin.ch Tel 058 462 20 07</contact>
      <attachment id="281874">
        <title>THE AGREEMENT ON CLIMATE CHANGE, TRADE AND SUSTAINABILITY</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>3042</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/90525.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="281875">
        <title>ACCORD SUR LE CHANGEMENT CLIMATIQUE, LE COMMERCE ET LA DURABILITÉ</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>4238</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/90526.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="281876">
        <title>Joint Statement: Signature of the Agreement on Climate Change, Trade and Sustainability</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>101</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/90527.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <link id="281877">
        <title>Artikel Die Volkswirtschaft</title>
        <uri>https://dievolkswirtschaft.ch/de/?p=204076&amp;v</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="281878">
        <title>Article La Vie économqiue</title>
        <uri>https://dievolkswirtschaft.ch/fr/?p=204079&amp;v</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="281879">
        <title>ACCTS Dossier</title>
        <uri>https://www.seco.admin.ch/seco/de/home/Aussenwirtschaftspolitik_Wirtschaftliche_Zusammenarbeit/internationale_organisationen/WTO/ACCTS.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Signature de l’accord sur le changement climatique, le commerce et la durabilité</title>
      <lead>Le conseiller fédéral Guy Parmelin et ses homologues du Costa Rica, d’Islande et de Nouvelle-Zélande ont signé, le 15 novembre 2024, l’accord sur le changement climatique, le commerce et la durabilité (« Agreement on Climate Change, Trade and Sustainability », ACCTS) dans le cadre d’une cérémonie virtuelle.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;En signant l'ACCTS, le Costa Rica, l'Islande, la Nouvelle-Zélande et la Suisse concluent pour la première fois un accord commercial juridiquement contraignant, servant en premier lieu des objectifs environnementaux. Les dispositions de l'accord tirent parti d'instruments de politique commerciale pour soutenir la transition vers des économies à faibles émissions, résilientes face au changement climatique et durables. L'ACCTS s'appuie sur le droit existant de l'OMC et le développe. Il a vocation de jouer un rôle pionnier et de se développer en ralliant d'autres États.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Libéralisation du commerce des biens et services environnementaux&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;La libéralisation et la sécurité juridique accrue qui vont de pair avec l'ACCTS renforcent, au niveau international, les chaînes de création de valeur pour les biens et services respectueux de l'environnement et tous les secteurs qui y participent en Suisse. L'accord comprend des listes écologiquement fondées et crédibles de plus de 300 biens environnementaux et de plus de 100 services environnementaux ou liés à l'environnement ; il engage les parties à réduire les droits de douane et autres obstacles au commerce frappant ces biens et services. Les importations en provenance de tous les membres de l'OMC profitent de la libéralisation, conformément au principe de la nation la plus favorisée.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Réglementation des subventions aux énergies fossiles&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;L'ACCTS est le premier accord international consacrant le caractère néfaste des subventions aux énergies fossiles et interdisant de ce fait le subventionnement du charbon ou de la production de gaz et de pétrole. Toute nouvelle subvention aux énergies fossiles est en principe proscrite et les mesures existantes autorisées ne peuvent pas être étendues.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Lignes directrices pour les écolabels volontaires&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Au travers de 13 lignes directrices non contraignantes, l'accord vise à permettre aux acteurs qui définissent ou utilisent des écolabels volontaires d'éviter les informations erronées et les obstacles inutiles au commerce et de réduire les coûts de mise en œuvre. Les écolabels aident les consommateurs à mieux discerner entre les produits en fonction de leur performance environnementale, et les producteurs à mettre en avant la valeur ajoutée écologique de leurs produits.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Ratification par le Parlement&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;L'accord sera soumis à l'approbation du Parlement et devrait entrer en vigueur pour la Suisse au début de 2026.&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Communication DEFR info@gs-wbf.admin.ch 058 462 20 07</contact>
      <attachment id="281874">
        <title>THE AGREEMENT ON CLIMATE CHANGE, TRADE AND SUSTAINABILITY</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>3042</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/90525.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="281875">
        <title>ACCORD SUR LE CHANGEMENT CLIMATIQUE, LE COMMERCE ET LA DURABILITÉ</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>4238</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/90526.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="281876">
        <title>Joint Statement: Signature of the Agreement on Climate Change, Trade and Sustainability</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>101</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/90527.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <link id="281877">
        <title>Artikel Die Volkswirtschaft</title>
        <uri>https://dievolkswirtschaft.ch/de/?p=204076&amp;v</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="281878">
        <title>Article La Vie économqiue</title>
        <uri>https://dievolkswirtschaft.ch/fr/?p=204079&amp;v</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="281880">
        <title>Dossier ACCTS</title>
        <uri>https://www.seco.admin.ch/seco/fr/home/Aussenwirtschaftspolitik_Wirtschaftliche_Zusammenarbeit/internationale_organisationen/WTO/ACCTS.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Firmato l’Accordo sul cambiamento climatico, il commercio e la sostenibilità (ACCTS)</title>
      <lead>In occasione di una cerimonia virtuale tenutasi il 15 novembre 2024, il Consigliere federale Guy Parmelin e i suoi omologhi di Costa Rica, Islanda e Nuova Zelanda hanno firmato l’Accordo sul cambiamento climatico, il commercio e la sostenibilità (ACCTS). </lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Grazie alla firma dell'ACCTS, Costa Rica, Islanda, Nuova Zelanda e Svizzera sottoscrivono per la prima volta un accordo commerciale giuridicamente vincolante focalizzato su obiettivi di politica ambientale. Le disposizioni concordate si basano su strumenti di politica commerciale per sostenere la transizione verso economie sostenibili, a basse emissioni e resilienti al cambiamento climatico. L'Accordo si basa sul diritto commerciale internazionale dell'OMC, sviluppandolo ulteriormente. Svolge un ruolo pionieristico ed è destinato a evolvere con l'adesione di nuove parti contraenti. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Liberalizzazione degli scambi di beni e servizi ambientali&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;La liberalizzazione concordata con l'ACCTS e la maggiore certezza del diritto che ne deriva rafforzano le catene del valore internazionali di beni e servizi ambientali e tutti i settori svizzeri ad essi correlati. L'Accordo, che contiene un elenco verosimile e basato su dati ecologici di oltre 300 beni ambientali e di oltre 100 servizi ambientali e legati all'ambiente, impegna le parti a eliminare i relativi dazi e altri ostacoli tariffari. Sulla base della clausola della nazione più favorita, beneficiano della liberalizzazione le importazioni da tutti i membri dell'OMC.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Regolamentazione dei sussidi per i combustibili fossili&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;L'ACCTS è il primo accordo internazionale a contenere una definizione dei sussidi dannosi per le energie fossili. Sono di conseguenza vietati i sussidi per il carbone o per la produzione di petrolio e gas. L'introduzione di nuovi sussidi a favore delle energie fossili è di per sé vietata, e le misure già esistenti e autorizzate non possono essere ampliate. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Linee guida per le etichette ecologiche (&lt;i&gt;ecolabels&lt;/i&gt;)&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Con 13 linee guida non vincolanti, l'Accordo sostiene tutte le parti interessate che sviluppano o utilizzano volontariamente etichette ecologiche in modo da evitare la divulgazione di false informazioni nonché l'insorgere di inutili barriere commerciali e di costi d'implementazione non necessari. Le etichette ecologiche aiutano da un lato i consumatori a distinguere meglio i prodotti in base alle prestazioni ambientali, e dall'altro i produttori a mettere in risalto il valore aggiunto ecologico degli articoli che immettono sul mercato.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Ratifica da parte del Parlamento&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;L'Accordo è sottoposto all'approvazione del Parlamento e dovrebbe entrare in vigore in Svizzera all'inizio del 2026.&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Comunicazione DEFR info@gs-wbf.admin.ch 058 462 20 07</contact>
      <attachment id="281874">
        <title>THE AGREEMENT ON CLIMATE CHANGE, TRADE AND SUSTAINABILITY</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>3042</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/90525.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="281875">
        <title>ACCORD SUR LE CHANGEMENT CLIMATIQUE, LE COMMERCE ET LA DURABILITÉ</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>4238</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/90526.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="281876">
        <title>Joint Statement: Signature of the Agreement on Climate Change, Trade and Sustainability</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>101</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/90527.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <link id="281877">
        <title>Artikel Die Volkswirtschaft</title>
        <uri>https://dievolkswirtschaft.ch/de/?p=204076&amp;v</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="281878">
        <title>Article La Vie économqiue</title>
        <uri>https://dievolkswirtschaft.ch/fr/?p=204079&amp;v</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="281881">
        <title>ACCTS</title>
        <uri>https://www.seco.admin.ch/seco/it/home/Aussenwirtschaftspolitik_Wirtschaftliche_Zusammenarbeit/internationale_organisationen/WTO/ACCTS.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Agreement on Climate Change, Trade and Sustainability (ACCTS) signed</title>
      <lead>On 15 November 2024, Federal Councillor Guy Parmelin and his counterparts from Costa Rica, Iceland and New Zealand signed the Agreement on Climate Change, Trade and Sustainability (ACCTS) in a virtual signing ceremony. </lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;The ACCTS is the first legally binding trade agreement between Costa Rica, Iceland, New Zealand and Switzerland that primarily pursues environmental policy objectives. The agreed provisions use trade policy instruments to support the transition to low-emission, climate-resilient and sustainable economies. The Agreement builds on and expands existing WTO international trade law. It is intended to play a pioneering role and to grow through the accession of additional parties. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Liberalisation of trade in environmental goods and services&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The liberalisation and increased legal certainty agreed through the ACCTS will strengthen international value chains for environmentally friendly goods and services and for all involved sectors in Switzerland. The Agreement contains ecologically sound and credible lists of more than 300 environmental goods and over 100 environmental services. It also commits the parties to eliminate tariffs and other trade barriers for these goods and services. Imports from all WTO members will benefit from liberalisation based on the most-favoured-nation principle.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Reform of fossil fuel subsidies&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The ACCTS is the first international agreement to define harmful subsidies for fossil fuels. Based on this, subsidies for coal or production of oil and gas will not be permitted. Introduction of new subsidies for fossil fuels will be generally prohibited, and no expansion of existing authorised measures will be allowed. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Guidelines for voluntary ecolabels&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;With 13 non-binding guidelines, the Agreement provides all stakeholders who develop or use voluntary ecolabels with support for preventing false information, unnecessary trade barriers and implementation costs. Ecolabels help consumers to better distinguish products based on their environmental performance, while also allowing producers to emphasise the ecological added value of their products on the market.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Ratification by Parliament&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The Agreement will be submitted to Parliament for approval and is expected to enter into force for Switzerland at the start of 2026.&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>EAER Information Service info@gs-wbf.admin.ch tel. 058 462 20 07</contact>
      <attachment id="281874">
        <title>THE AGREEMENT ON CLIMATE CHANGE, TRADE AND SUSTAINABILITY</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>3042</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/90525.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="281875">
        <title>ACCORD SUR LE CHANGEMENT CLIMATIQUE, LE COMMERCE ET LA DURABILITÉ</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>4238</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/90526.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="281876">
        <title>Joint Statement: Signature of the Agreement on Climate Change, Trade and Sustainability</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>101</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/90527.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <link id="281877">
        <title>Artikel Die Volkswirtschaft</title>
        <uri>https://dievolkswirtschaft.ch/de/?p=204076&amp;v</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="281878">
        <title>Article La Vie économqiue</title>
        <uri>https://dievolkswirtschaft.ch/fr/?p=204079&amp;v</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="281882">
        <title>ACCTS</title>
        <uri>https://www.seco.admin.ch/seco/en/home/Aussenwirtschaftspolitik_Wirtschaftliche_Zusammenarbeit/internationale_organisationen/WTO/ACCTS.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="47">
        <name lang="de">Wirtschaft</name>
        <name lang="fr">Économie</name>
        <name lang="it">Economia</name>
        <name lang="en">Economic Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
