<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="93632" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2023-03-10</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="1070" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>1070</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Der Bundesrat</name>
      <name lang="fr">Conseil fédéral</name>
      <name lang="it">Il Consiglio federale</name>
      <name lang="en">The Federal Council</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.admin.ch/gov/de/start.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.admin.ch/gov/fr/accueil.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.admin.ch/gov/it/pagina-iniziale.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.admin.ch/gov/en/start.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="yes" id="1080" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>701</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Staatssekretariat für Bildung, Forschung und Innovation</name>
      <name lang="fr">Secrétariat d'Etat à la formation, à la recherche et à l'innovation</name>
      <name lang="it">Segreteria di Stato per la formazione, la ricerca e l'innovazione</name>
      <name lang="en">State Secretariat for Education, Research and Innovation</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.sbfi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.sbfi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.sbfi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.sbfi.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@sbfi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@sbfi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@sbfi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@sbfi.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="1070">
      <name lang="de">Der Bundesrat</name>
      <name lang="fr">Conseil fédéral</name>
      <name lang="it">Il Consiglio federale</name>
      <name lang="en">The Federal Council</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.admin.ch/gov/de/start.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.admin.ch/gov/fr/accueil.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.admin.ch/gov/it/pagina-iniziale.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.admin.ch/gov/en/start.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <department id="701">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Wirtschaft, Bildung und Forschung</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'économie, de la formation et de la recherche</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'economia, della formazione e della ricerca</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Economic Affairs, Education and Research</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Bundesrat konkretisiert Entscheid zur besseren Begleitung der Projekte des CERN</title>
      <lead>An seiner Sitzung vom 10. März 2023 hat der Bundesrat beschlossen, die Vernehmlassung zur Änderung des Bundesgesetzes über die Förderung der Forschung und der Innovation (FIFG) zu eröffnen. Dieser Entscheid ergibt sich aus dem am 10. Dezember 2021 getroffenen Beschluss, die Erarbeitung eines Sachplans des Bundes über die Projekte der Europäischen Organisation für Kernforschung (CERN) in Angriff zu nehmen. Der Bundesrat will dem Parlament bis Ende 2023 eine Botschaft zu dieser Änderung des FIFG unterbreiten. Das Europäische Laboratorium für Teilchenphysik CERN ist das weltweit grösste Zentrum für physikalische Grundlagenforschung. Die Schweiz gehört zu den Gründerstaaten. </lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Das im französisch-schweizerischen Grenzgebiet gelegene CERN trägt zur internationalen Ausstrahlung der Schweiz bei. Es bringt ihr sowohl aus wissenschaftlicher als auch aus industrieller und wirtschaftlicher Sicht Vorteile. Der Infrastrukturbedarf des CERN entwickelt sich stetig weiter, wobei aktuell mehrere Projekte geplant sind, die sich auf das Schweizer Hoheitsgebiet auswirken werden. Um die Vereinbarkeit dieser Vorhaben mit den Zielen der Schweizer Forschungspolitik, den Aufgaben als Gaststaat sowie den Vorgaben im Bereich Umwelt und Raumplanung sicherzustellen und um beste Voraussetzungen für die administrative Umsetzung zu schaffen, wird nun ein Sachplan erarbeitet. Dieser wird den Rahmen für die Abwägung der verschiedenen auf dem Spiel stehenden Interessen bilden.&lt;b&gt; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Die rechtliche Verankerung dieses Sachplans erfordert eine Änderung des FIFG. Der Änderungsentwurf sieht eine Kompetenzaufteilung zwischen dem Kanton Genf und dem Bund in Bezug auf die Genehmigung der Pläne für Bauten und Anlagen des CERN vor. In einem neuen Abschnitt des Gesetzes wird dieses Genehmigungsverfahren auf Bundesebene festgelegt. Die Vernehmlassung zur Vorlage dauert bis Ende Frühling 2023. Anschliessend will der Bundesrat dem Parlament bis Ende 2023 eine Botschaft zur Änderung des FIFG unterbreiten. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Die engere Begleitung der Projekte des CERN durch die Schweiz betrifft im Übrigen nicht nur die raumplanerische Ebene. Gemeinsam mit dem ETH-Bereich und zahlreichen BFI-Institutionen in der Schweiz unterstützt das Eidgenössische Departement für Wirtschaft, Bildung und Forschung (WBF) den Ausbau des CHART-Verbunds (Swiss Accelerator Research and Technology), der 2018 zur Stärkung der für das CERN relevanten Beschleunigerforschung geschaffen wurde. Derzeit wird ein ähnliches Netzwerk für die Forschung im Bereich der Detektoren aufgebaut. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Das CERN und die Schweiz&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Aufgabe des CERN ist es, die Zusammensetzung und die Funktionsweise des Universums besser zu verstehen. Dazu stellt es Forschenden aus der ganzen Welt Infrastrukturen zur Verfügung, die von der Organisation gebaut und betrieben werden. Das CERN wurde 1954 als zwischenstaatliche Organisation mit Sitz in Genf gegründet. Es zählt 23 Mitgliedstaaten, darunter die Schweiz, und 10 assoziierte Staaten, hauptsächlich aus Europa. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Neben dem beachtlichen und einzigartigen Beitrag zu Wissenschaft und Innovation ist die Präsenz des CERN in der Schweiz auch von grosser wirtschaftlicher Bedeutung, besonders für die Region Genf. Das CERN spielte bei mehreren heute grundlegenden technologischen Errungenschaften eine zentrale Rolle, beispielsweise bei der Entwicklung des World Wide Web oder der Krebsbehandlung mit Protonen (Hadronentherapie). Darüber hinaus bildet das Laboratorium zahlreiche Ingenieurinnen und Ingenieure sowie Wissenschaftlerinnen und Wissenschaftler aus, die zur Deckung des Fachkräftebedarfs im akademischen und industriellen Umfeld beitragen. &lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Kommunikationsdienst GS-WBF info@gs-wbf.admin.ch, +41 58 462 20 07</contact>
      <link id="244048">
        <title>CERN</title>
        <uri>https://www.sbfi.admin.ch/sbfi/de/home/forschung-und-innovation/internationale-f-und-i-zusammenarbeit/internationale-forschungsorganisationen/cern.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="244049">
        <title>CHART</title>
        <uri>https://chart.ch/</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="244050">
        <title>Laufende Vernehmlassungen</title>
        <uri>https://www.sbfi.admin.ch/sbfi/de/home/aktuell/vernehmlassungen.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Le Conseil fédéral concrétise sa décision d’améliorer l’accompagnement des projets du CERN</title>
      <lead>Lors de sa séance du 10 mars 2023, le Conseil fédéral a décidé d’ouvrir la consultation relative au projet de modification de la loi sur l’encouragement de la recherche et de l’innovation (LERI). Cette décision s’inscrit dans le prolongement de celle du 10 décembre 2021 de lancer les travaux d’élaboration d’un plan sectoriel fédéral centré sur les projets du Conseil Européen pour la Recherche Nucléaire (CERN). Le Conseil fédéral prévoit de transmettre au Parlement d’ici à la fin de l’année 2023 un message relatif à cette modification de la LERI. Le CERN, aussi appelé Laboratoire européen pour la physique des particules, est le plus grand centre de recherche fondamentale en physique au monde. La Suisse est l’un de ses Etats fondateurs. </lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Sis à cheval sur la frontière franco-suisse, le CERN participe au rayonnement international de la Suisse et lui bénéficie du point de vue scientifique, mais aussi industriel et économique. Les besoins du CERN en termes d'infrastructure sont en constante évolution et plusieurs projets qui auront une emprise sur le territoire suisse sont envisagés. Afin que ceux-ci restent compatibles avec les objectifs des politiques suisses de la recherche, d'Etat hôte, d'environnement et d'organisation du territoire, et qu'ils soient mis en œuvre dans les meilleures conditions sur le plan administratif, un plan sectoriel est actuellement en cours d'élaboration. Celui-ci constituera le cadre au sein duquel les différents intérêts en jeu seront appréciés.&lt;b&gt; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;L'ancrage légal de ce plan sectoriel rend nécessaire une modification de la LERI. Le projet de modification prévoit un partage de compétences entre le canton de Genève et la Confédération s'agissant de l'approbation des plans des constructions et installations du CERN. Une nouvelle section de la loi détaille la procédure d'approbation des plans au niveau fédéral. La consultation externe sur ce projet se terminera à la fin du printemps 2023. Il est prévu que le Conseil fédéral transmette au Parlement un message relatif à cette modification de la LERI d'ici à la fin de l'année 2023.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;L'amélioration de l'accompagnement par la Suisse des projets du CERN ne se déploie par ailleurs pas seulement sous l'angle des questions territoriales. De concert avec le Domaine des EPF et de nombreuses institutions FRI en Suisse, le Département de l'économie, de la formation et de la recherche (DEFR) soutient le développement du réseau CHART (Swiss Accelerator Research and Technology) mis en place depuis 2018 pour renforcer la recherche sur les accélérateurs pertinentes pour le CERN. Un réseau similaire est en cours de mise en place pour ce qui concerne la recherche sur les détecteurs. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Le CERN et la Suisse&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;La mission du CERN vise à mieux comprendre la composition et le fonctionnement de l'Univers, notamment en mettant à disposition des chercheurs du monde entier les infrastructures qu'il construit et exploite. Le CERN est établi depuis 1954 sous la forme d'une organisation intergouvernementale dont le siège est à Genève. Il compte 23 Etats membres, dont la Suisse, et 10 Etats associés, principalement européens. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Outre son apport considérable et unique pour la science et l'innovation, les retombées économiques de la présence du CERN en Suisse sont importantes, particulièrement pour la région genevoise. Le CERN a joué un rôle central dans plusieurs percées technologiques aujourd'hui essentielles, dont le World Wide Web ou la thérapie de cancers par protons (hadronthérapie). Par ailleurs, le laboratoire forme de nombreux ingénieurs et scientifiques qui nourrissent les besoins en main d'œuvre qualifiée des milieux académiques et industriels. &lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Service de communication du SG DEFR info@gs-wbf.admin.ch, +41 58 462 20 07</contact>
      <link id="244051">
        <title>CERN</title>
        <uri>https://www.sbfi.admin.ch/sbfi/fr/home/recherche-et-innovation/cooperation-internationale-r-et-i/organisations-internationales-de-recherche/cern.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="244052">
        <title>CHART</title>
        <uri>https://chart.ch/</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="244053">
        <title>Consultations en cours</title>
        <uri>https://www.sbfi.admin.ch/sbfi/fr/home/actualite/consultations.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="244055">
        <title>CHART</title>
        <uri>https://chart.ch/</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Il Consiglio federale attua la sua decisione di agevolare i progetti del CERN</title>
      <lead>Nella riunione del 10 marzo 2023 il Consiglio federale ha deciso di aprire la consultazione concernente il progetto di modifica della legge sulla promozione della ricerca e dell’innovazione (LPRI). Questa decisione fa seguito a quella del 10 dicembre 2021 di avviare i lavori relativi a un piano settoriale della Confederazione incentrato sui progetti del Centro europeo per la ricerca nucleare (CERN). Il Consiglio federale intende presentare al Parlamento entro la fine del 2023 un messaggio concernente la modifica della LPRI. Il CERN, noto anche come Laboratorio europeo di fisica delle particelle, è il più grande centro al mondo di ricerca fondamentale nel settore della fisica. La Svizzera è uno dei suoi Stati fondatori. </lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;La presenza del CERN a cavallo della frontiera franco-elvetica, oltre a contribuire alla rinomanza della Svizzera a livello internazionale, giova al nostro Paese anche sul piano scientifico, industriale ed economico. Le esigenze dell'istituto in termini di infrastrutture cambiano costantemente e sono al vaglio diversi progetti che avranno un impatto sul territorio svizzero. Per garantire che questi progetti siano compatibili con gli obiettivi della politica svizzera in materia di ricerca, della Svizzera in quanto Stato ospitante nonché della politica ambientale e di pianificazione territoriale e che siano attuati nel modo migliore dal punto di vista amministrativo è attualmente in fase di elaborazione un piano settoriale, che fornirà un quadro di riferimento per la valutazione dei diversi interessi in gioco.&lt;b&gt; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Per sancire a livello giuridico il piano settoriale è necessaria una modifica della LPRI. Il progetto di modifica prevede una ripartizione delle competenze tra il Cantone di Ginevra e la Confederazione per quanto riguarda l'approvazione dei piani delle costruzioni e degli impianti del CERN. Una nuova sezione della legge specifica la procedura di approvazione dei piani a livello federale. La consultazione esterna su questo progetto si concluderà a fine primavera 2023. Il Consiglio federale intende presentare al Parlamento un messaggio sulla modifica in questione entro la fine del 2023. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;L'agevolazione dei progetti del CERN da parte della Svizzera non si limita solo alle questioni territoriali. Insieme al settore dei PF e a numerose istituzioni ERI in Svizzera, il Dipartimento federale dell'economia, della formazione e della ricerca (DEFR) sostiene lo sviluppo della rete CHART (Swiss Accelerator Research and Technology), creata nel 2018 per rafforzare la ricerca sugli acceleratori rilevanti per il CERN. Una rete simile è in fase di realizzazione per la ricerca sui sensori. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Il CERN e la Svizzera&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;La missione del CERN consiste nel conoscere meglio la composizione e il funzionamento dell'Universo. A tal fine mette a disposizione dei ricercatori di tutto il mondo le sue infrastrutture. Il CERN è stato istituito nel 1954 come organizzazione intergovernativa; ha sede a Ginevra e conta 23 Paesi membri, tra cui la Svizzera, e 10 Paesi associati, principalmente europei. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Oltre a contribuire notevolmente e in maniera specifica alla scienza e all'innovazione, con la sua presenza in Svizzera il CERN genera benefici economici importanti per il Paese, in particolare per la regione di Ginevra. L'istituto ha ricoperto un ruolo chiave in molte delle scoperte tecnologiche oggi considerate essenziali, tra cui il World Wide Web e la terapia protonica contro il cancro (adroterapia). Inoltre il laboratorio forma molti ingegneri e scienziati, contribuendo a soddisfare il fabbisogno di personale qualificato nel settore accademico e industriale. &lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Comunicazione SG DEFR info@gs-wbf.admin.ch, +41 58 462 20 07</contact>
      <link id="244054">
        <title>CERN</title>
        <uri>https://www.sbfi.admin.ch/sbfi/it/home/ricerca-e-innovazione/cooperazione-internazionale-r-e-i/organizzazioni-di-ricerca-internazionali/cern.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="244056">
        <title>Consultazioni in corso</title>
        <uri>https://www.sbfi.admin.ch/sbfi/it/home/attualita/consultazioni.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="244059">
        <title>Ongoing consultations</title>
        <uri>https://www.sbfi.admin.ch/sbfi/fr/home/actualite/consultations.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Federal Council moves forward with decision to improve planning support for CERN projects</title>
      <lead>At its meeting on 10 March 2023, the Federal Council decided to launch a consultation on proposed amendments to the Federal Act on the Promotion of Research and Innovation (RIPA). This decision follows on from the decision reached on 10 December 2021 to initiate work on a federal sectoral plan focusing on projects of the European Organization for Nuclear Research (CERN). The Federal Council intends to submit a dispatch to the Swiss Parliament regarding the amendment of the RIPA by the end of 2023. Often referred to as the European laboratory for particle physics, CERN is an intergovernmental organisation that operates the world’s largest particle physics laboratory. Switzerland is a founding member. </lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Straddling the border region between France and Switzerland, CERN contributes to Switzerland's international reputation and delivers an important scientific, industrial and economic impact. CERN's infrastructure needs are constantly evolving, and several projects that will have a footprint on Swiss territory are envisaged. A sectoral plan is currently being drawn up to ensure that these projects are compatible with the objectives of Swiss research, host state, environmental and spatial planning policies, and that they are implemented in the best possible administrative conditions. This sectoral plan will provide a framework for balancing the various interests at stake.&lt;b&gt; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;In order to provide a legal basis for this sectoral plan, several changes need to be made to the RIPA. The proposed amendment provides for a sharing of competences between the Canton of Geneva and the Confederation with regard to the approval of CERN plans for construction and installation. The amendment bill also includes a new section on the procedure for obtaining federal approval of plans. The external consultation phase for this bill will come to a close at the end of spring 2023. The Federal Council is expected to submit a RIPA amendment bill and corresponding dispatch to the Swiss Parliament by the end of 2023. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Improved planning support for CERN projects is not limited to territorial considerations. Working within the ETH Domain and numerous ERI stakeholders in Switzerland, the Federal Department of Economic Affairs, Education and Research (EAER) is coordinating expansion of the Swiss Accelerator Research and Technology (CHART). This network was established in 2018 to consolidate research on particle accelerators deemed relevant to CERN. A similar network is also being set up for research on detectors. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;CERN and Switzerland&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;CERN's mission is to help uncover what the universe is made of and how it works. This is achieved by building and operating a unique range of facilities that are made accessible to researchers from all over the world. CERN was established as an intergovernmental organisation in the Canton of Geneva in 1954. It has 23 Member States, including Switzerland, and 10 Associate Member States, mostly in Europe. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Apart from the considerable and unique contribution that it makes to science and innovation, CERN's presence on Swiss soil also brings tangible economic benefits, particularly to the Canton of Geneva. CERN has played a key role in several technological breakthroughs that are now considered essential. This includes the World Wide Web and proton beam therapy (Hadron therapy) for cancer patients. In addition, CERN trains a large number of engineers and scientists, which helps to meet university and industry demand for highly skilled labour. &lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>GS EAER Communication Service info@gs-wbf.admin.ch, +41 58 462 20 07</contact>
      <link id="244057">
        <title>CERN</title>
        <uri>https://www.sbfi.admin.ch/sbfi/en/home/research-and-innovation/international-cooperation-r-and-i/international-research-organisations/cern.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="244058">
        <title>CHART</title>
        <uri>https://chart.ch/</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="8">
        <name lang="de">Bildung und Forschung</name>
        <name lang="fr">Formation et recherche</name>
        <name lang="it">Formazione e ricerca</name>
        <name lang="en">Education and Research</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="10">
        <name lang="de">Bundesrat</name>
        <name lang="fr">Conseil fédéral</name>
        <name lang="it">Consiglio federale</name>
        <name lang="en">Federal Council</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="45">
        <name lang="de">Technologie</name>
        <name lang="fr">Technologie</name>
        <name lang="it">Tecnologia</name>
        <name lang="en">Technology</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="47">
        <name lang="de">Wirtschaft</name>
        <name lang="fr">Économie</name>
        <name lang="it">Economia</name>
        <name lang="en">Economic Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
