<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="93973" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2023-03-28</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="323" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>701</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidg. Materialprüfungs- und Forschungsanstalt</name>
      <name lang="fr">Laboratoire fédéral d'essai des matériaux et de recherche</name>
      <name lang="it">Laboratorio federale di prova dei materiali e di ricerca</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Laboratory for Materials Testing and Research</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.empa.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.empa.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.empa.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.empa.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">contact@empa.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">contact@empa.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">contact@empa.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">contact@empa.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="701">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Wirtschaft, Bildung und Forschung</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'économie, de la formation et de la recherche</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'economia, della formazione e della ricerca</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Economic Affairs, Education and Research</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Dübendorf, St. Gallen und Thun</city>
      <title>Empa Young Scientist Fellowship: Wenn Unordnung zur Lösung unserer Energieprobleme beiträgt</title>
      <lead>Empa-Forscherin Amy Knorpp will Systematik in das junge Forschungsfeld der Hochentropie-Oxide bringen. Letzteres sind Kristalle, deren Spezialität nicht Ordnung, sondern Unordnung ist. Mit der Ver-wendung dieser Kristalle möchte Amy Knorpp neue, robustere und effizientere Katalysatoren entwi-ckeln und damit einen wichtigen Beitrag zum Wandel weg von fossilen Energien hin zu CO2-neutralen Lösungen leisten. Ihre Forschung wird mit einem «Empa Young Scientist Fellowship» gefördert.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Hochentropie-Oxide, oder auch sogenannte ungeordnete Kristalle, sind ein sehr junges Forschungsgebiet, in dem es noch viel zu entdecken gibt. Jungforscherin Amy Knorpp sieht in diesen Materialien ein enormes Potential für katalytische Systeme speziell bei der Umwandlung von CO2 und Wasserstoff zu Methanol. Denn Methanol ist ein wichtiger chemischer Grundstoff, der in unserer Gesellschaft in vielen Formen verwendet werden kann – zum Beispiel für Treibstoffe. Um synthetisches Methanol im grossen Stil erzeugen zu können, braucht es jedoch robustere und effizientere Katalysatoren, als zurzeit vorhanden sind. «Ungeordnete Kristalle stellen ein potenzielles Material für diese begehrten Katalysatoren dar. Einerseits kann ihre extreme Unordnung neue Dimensionen der Stabilität in katalytischen Prozessen bringen, was zu einer längeren Lebensdauer des Katalysators führt. Andererseits lässt sich ihre Chemie sehr gut anpassen, um sowohl Defekte als auch Synergien zwischen verschiedenen Elementen zu erzeugen», erklärt Amy Knorpp. Konkret werden in Hochentropie-Oxiden dafür einzelne Positionen innerhalb der genau geordneten Strukturen eines Kristalls durch fremde Elemente ersetzt. Bei einem Mix aus mindestens fünf verschiedenen Elementen können aussergewöhnliche Eigenschaften erwartet werden. Wissenschaftler sprechen dann gerne vom so genannten Cocktaileffekt. Eine entscheidende Eigenschaft eines erfolgreichen Katalysators ist, dass er die Herstellung von Methanol gegenüber anderen Kohlenwasserstoffen bevorzugt. Die gezielte Veränderung bestimmter Stellen in einem Kristall, wie bei Hochentropie-Oxiden, kommt genau dem zugute, indem das CO2 effizient aktiviert und H2 in einer günstigen Anordnung dissoziiert wird.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Licht ins Dunkel bringen&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Doch auf dem Weg dahin sind noch viele Fragen unbeantwortet. Amy Knorpp und die Projektgruppe «Nanopowers and ceramics», unter der Leitung von Michael Stuer, untersucht nun systematisch die verschiedenen Veränderungen, die zu einer neuen Vielfalt von ungeordneten Kristallen führen. Dabei wollen sie unter anderem die Frage beantworten, wie effizient diese neuen Materialien als Katalysatoren funktionieren und wie lange sie halten. «Daraus soll eine Art Landkarte für die systematische Veränderung von Kristallen entstehen mit dem Ziel, die ‹ideale Unordnung› im Kristall zu erzeugen. Dieses Projekt dient der Grundlagenforschung und wird Licht ins Dunkel bringen», erläutert «Empa Young Scientist Fellow» Amy Knorpp.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Talentförderung dank Empa Zukunftsfonds&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Das «Empa Young Scientist Fellowship» ist ein Förderinstrument für aussergewöhnlich begabte Nachwuchs-Wissenschaftlerinnen und -Wissenschaftler. Der Fellow erhält die finanziellen Mittel, während zwei Jahren ein eigenständiges Forschungsprojekt durchzuführen. Die Fellowships werden vom der Empa in einem Wettbewerbsverfahren vergeben, um sicherzustellen, dass die Anträge mit dem höchsten Potenzial ausgewählt werden.&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Dr. Amy Knorpp High Performance Ceramics Tel. +41 58 765 6033 amy.knorpp@empa.ch</contact>
      <attachment id="245353">
        <title>Will Licht ins Dunkel bringen: «Empa Young Scientist Fellowship»-Preisträgerin Amy Knorpp sieht grosses Potential in Hochentropie-Materialien. Bild: Empa</title>
        <format>jpg</format>
        <size-kb>369</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/76387.jpg</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="245354">
        <title>«Empa Young Scientist Fellow» Amy Knorpp und Michael Stuer produzieren Kristallmischungen mit einem sogenannten «Tubular Flow Reactor». Bild: Empa</title>
        <format>jpg</format>
        <size-kb>7706</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/76388.jpg</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <link id="245350">
        <title>Empa Young Scientist Fellowship</title>
        <uri>https://www.empa.ch/web/s604/empa-young-scientist-fellowship1</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Dübendorf, St. Gallen und Thun</city>
      <title>Empa Young Scientist Fellowship : Quand le désordre contribue à résoudre nos problèmes énergé-tiques</title>
      <lead>Amy Knorpp, chercheuse à l'Empa, veut apporter de la systématique dans le jeune domaine de re-cherche des oxydes à haute entropie. Ces derniers sont des cristaux dont la spécialité n'est pas l'ordre, mais le désordre. En utilisant ces cristaux, Amy Knorpp souhaite développer de nouveaux catalyseurs plus robustes et plus efficaces et apporter ainsi une contribution importante à l'abandon des énergies fossiles au profit de solutions neutres en CO2. Sa recherche est soutenue par une "Empa Young Scientist Fellowship".</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Les oxydes à haute entropie, ou cristaux désordonnés, sont un domaine de recherche très récent dans lequel il reste encore beaucoup à découvrir. La jeune chercheuse Amy Knorpp voit dans ces matériaux un énorme potentiel pour les systèmes catalytiques, en particulier pour la transformation du CO2 et de l'hydrogène en méthanol. Le méthanol est en effet une substance chimique de base importante qui peut être utilisée dans notre société sous de nombreuses formes, par exemple pour les carburants. Pour pouvoir produire du méthanol synthétique à grande échelle, il faut toutefois des catalyseurs plus robustes et plus efficaces que ceux qui existent actuellement. "Les cristaux désordonnés représentent un matériau potentiel pour ces catalyseurs très convoités. D'une part, leur extrême désordre peut apporter de nouvelles dimensions de stabilité dans les processus catalytiques, ce qui permet d'allonger la durée de vie du catalyseur. D'autre part, leur chimie peut être très bien adaptée pour créer à la fois des défauts et des synergies entre différents éléments", explique Amy Knorpp. Concrètement, dans les oxydes à haute entropie, certaines positions au sein des structures bien ordonnées d'un cristal sont remplacées par des éléments étrangers. Avec un mélange d'au moins cinq éléments différents, on peut s'attendre à des propriétés extraordinaires. Les scientifiques parlent alors volontiers de ce qu'ils appellent l'effet cocktail. Une caractéristique décisive d'un catalyseur réussi est qu'il favorise la production de méthanol par rapport aux autres hydrocarbures. La modification ciblée de certains endroits d'un cristal, comme dans le cas des oxydes à haute entropie, profite justement à cela en activant efficacement le CO2 et en dissociant le H2 dans une disposition favorable.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Faire la lumière sur l'obscurité&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Mais de nombreuses questions restent encore sans réponse sur ce chemin. Amy Knorpp et le groupe de projet "Nanopowers and ceramics", sous la direction de Michael Stuer, étudient désormais systématiquement les différents changements qui conduisent à une nouvelle variété de cristaux désordonnés. Ils veulent notamment répondre à la question de l'efficacité de ces nouveaux matériaux en tant que catalyseurs et de leur durée de vie. "Il devrait en résulter une sorte de carte pour la modification systématique des cristaux dans le but de créer le "désordre idéal" dans le cristal. Ce projet sert à la recherche fondamentale et permettra de faire la lumière sur le sujet", explique Amy Knorpp, "Empa Young Scientist Fellow". &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Promotion des talents grâce au Fonds d'avenir de l'Empa&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;L'"Empa Young Scientist Fellowship" est un instrument d'encouragement pour les jeunes scientifiques exceptionnellement doués. Le fellow reçoit les moyens financiers nécessaires pour mener à bien un projet de recherche autonome pendant deux ans. Les Fellowships sont attribués par l'Empa dans le cadre d'une procédure de mise en concurrence afin de garantir que les candidatures présentant le meilleur potentiel soient sélectionnées.&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Dr. Amy Knorpp High Performance Ceramics Tél. +41 58 765 6033 amy.knorpp@empa.ch</contact>
      <attachment id="245355">
        <title>La lauréate du "Empa Young Scientist Fellowship" Amy Knorpp voit un grand potentiel dans les matériaux à haute entropie.</title>
        <format>jpg</format>
        <size-kb>369</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/76389.jpg</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="245356">
        <title>Michael Stuer et Amy Knorpp, "Empa Young Scientist Fellow", produisent des mélanges de cristaux avec un "Tubular Flow Reactor". Image : Empa</title>
        <format>jpg</format>
        <size-kb>7706</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/76390.jpg</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <link id="245350">
        <title>Empa Young Scientist Fellowship</title>
        <uri>https://www.empa.ch/web/s604/empa-young-scientist-fellowship1</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Dübendorf, St. Gallen und Thun</city>
      <title>Empa Young Scientist Fellowship: When disorder helps solve our energy problems</title>
      <lead>Empa researcher Amy Knorpp wants to bring systematics into the young research field of high-entropy oxides. The latter are crystals whose specialty is not order, but disorder. By using these crystals, Amy Knorpp aims to develop new, more robust and more efficient catalysts and thus make an important contribution to the shift away from fossil fuels towards CO2-neutral solutions. Her research is supported by an "Empa Young Scientist Fellowship".</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;High-entropy oxides, or so-called disordered crystals, are a very young field of research in which there is still much to discover. Young researcher Amy Knorpp sees enormous potential in these materials for catalytic systems, especially in the conversion of CO2 and hydrogen to methanol. This is because methanol is an important basic chemical substance that can be used in many forms in our society - for fuels, for example. However, to produce synthetic methanol at large scale, more robust and efficient catalysts than currently exist are needed. "Disordered crystals pose as a potential material for these sought-after catalysts. On one hand, their extreme disorder can bring new dimensions of stability in catalytic processes, leading to a longer lifetime of the catalyst. On the other hand, their chemistry is highly tailorable to create both defects and synergies between different elements", explains Amy Knorpp. Specifically, in high-entropy oxides, individual positions within the precisely ordered structures of a crystal are replaced by foreign elements. With a mix of at least five different elements, exceptional properties can be expected. Scientists then like to speak of the so-called cocktail effect. A crucial property of a successful catalyst is to allow for preference to the making of methanol instead to other hydrocarbons. The specific alteration of certain sites in a crystal, as in high-entropy oxides, benefits exactly that, through efficient activation of the CO2 and dissociation of H2 in a favorable arrangement.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Bringing light into the dark&lt;/b&gt; &lt;p&gt;But there are still many unanswered questions along the way. Amy Knorpp and the "Nanopowers and ceramics" project group, led by Michael Stuer, are now systematically investigating in this various changes leading to a new variety of high-entropy oxides. In doing so, they hope to answer questions such as how efficiently this new materials work as catalysts and what their lifespans are. "This will result in a kind of map for the systematic modification of crystals with the goal of creating the "ideal disorder" in a crystal for methanol synthesis. This project serves as basic research and will shed light on the darkness," explains "Empa Young Scientist Fellow" Amy Knorpp.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Talent promotion at Empa &lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The Empa Young Scientist Fellowship is a funding instrument for exceptionally talented young scientists. The Fellow receives the financial means to carry out an independent research project for a period of two years. Fellowships are awarded by Empa in a competitive process to ensure that applications with the highest potential are being selected.&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Dr. Amy Knorpp High Performance Ceramics Phone +41 58 765 6033 amy.knorpp@empa.ch</contact>
      <attachment id="245351">
        <title>Wants to bring light into the dark: Empa Young Scientist Fellowship winner Amy Knorpp sees great potential in high-entropy materials. Image: Empa</title>
        <format>jpg</format>
        <size-kb>369</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/76385.jpg</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="245352">
        <title>"Empa Young Scientist Fellow" Amy Knorpp and Michael Stuer produce different crystal mixtures. Image: Empa</title>
        <format>jpg</format>
        <size-kb>7706</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/76386.jpg</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <link id="245350">
        <title>Empa Young Scientist Fellowship</title>
        <uri>https://www.empa.ch/web/s604/empa-young-scientist-fellowship1</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="11">
        <name lang="de">Energie</name>
        <name lang="fr">Énergie</name>
        <name lang="it">Energia</name>
        <name lang="en">Energy</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="45">
        <name lang="de">Technologie</name>
        <name lang="fr">Technologie</name>
        <name lang="it">Tecnologia</name>
        <name lang="en">Technology</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
