<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="93793" revoked="no">
    <version>12</version>
    <pubdate>2023-03-19</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="1070" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>1070</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Der Bundesrat</name>
      <name lang="fr">Conseil fédéral</name>
      <name lang="it">Il Consiglio federale</name>
      <name lang="en">The Federal Council</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.admin.ch/gov/de/start.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.admin.ch/gov/fr/accueil.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.admin.ch/gov/it/pagina-iniziale.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.admin.ch/gov/en/start.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="602" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>601</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Generalsekretariat EFD</name>
      <name lang="fr">Secrétariat général DFF</name>
      <name lang="it">Segreteria generale DFF</name>
      <name lang="en">Secretariat-General FDF</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.efd.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.efd.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.efd.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.efd.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="1060" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>601</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Staatssekretariat für internationale Finanzfragen</name>
      <name lang="fr">Secrétariat d'Etat aux questions financières internationales</name>
      <name lang="it">Segreteria di Stato per le questioni finanziarie internazionali</name>
      <name lang="en">State Secretariat for International Financial Matters</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.sif.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.sif.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.sif.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.sif.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@sif.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@sif.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@sif.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@sif.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="1070">
      <name lang="de">Der Bundesrat</name>
      <name lang="fr">Conseil fédéral</name>
      <name lang="it">Il Consiglio federale</name>
      <name lang="en">The Federal Council</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.admin.ch/gov/de/start.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.admin.ch/gov/fr/accueil.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.admin.ch/gov/it/pagina-iniziale.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.admin.ch/gov/en/start.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <department id="601">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Finanzdepartement</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des finances</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale delle finanze</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Finance</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.efd.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.dff.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.efd.admin.ch/efd/it/home.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.efd.admin.ch/efd/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Sicherung der Finanzmarktstabilität: Der Bundesrat begrüsst und unterstützt die Übernahme der Credit Suisse durch die UBS</title>
      <lead>Der Bundesrat begrüsst die geplante Übernahme der Credit Suisse durch die UBS. Um die Finanzmarktstabilität zu stärken, bis die Übernahme vollzogen ist, leistet der Bund die Garantie für eine zusätzliche Liquiditätshilfe der Schweizerischen Nationalbank (SNB) an die Credit Suisse. Diese Unterstützung dient dazu, die Liquidität der Credit Suisse und damit auch eine erfolgreiche Umsetzung der Übernahme zu gewährleisten. Sie erfolgt zum Schutz der Finanzstabilität und der Schweizer Volkswirtschaft.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Heute hat die UBS bekannt gegeben, dass sie bereit ist, die Credit Suisse zu übernehmen. Der Bundesrat begrüsst diesen Schritt als wichtigen Beitrag zur Stabilität des Finanzmarktes. Um die Fortführung der Geschäftstätigkeit der Credit Suisse bis zur Umsetzung der Übernahme sicherzustellen und die Kosten für die Schweizer Volkswirtschaft zu reduzieren, hat der Bundesrat zusätzliche Liquiditätsmassnahmen beschlossen.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Erstens hat der Bundesrat die nötigen rechtlichen Grundlagen geschaffen, damit die SNB der Credit Suisse zusätzliche Liquiditätshilfen gewähren kann. Konkret hat der Bundesrat für diese zusätzlichen Liquiditätshilfen ein Konkursprivileg geschaffen. Die SNB erhält dadurch die notwendige Sicherheit, um der Credit Suisse substanzielle zusätzliche Liquidität zur Verfügung stellen zu können.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Um die Credit Suisse mit jederzeit ausreichend Liquidität zu versorgen, hat der Bundesrat zweitens entschieden, der SNB darüber hinaus eine Ausfallgarantie für Liquiditätsdarlehen zu gewähren. Beide Massnahmen erfolgten gestützt auf die Art. 184 und Art. 185 der Bundesverfassung (Notrecht).&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Diese Massnahmen ergänzen die bereits bestehenden Instrumente der SNB zur Stärkung der Liquidität von Banken; zu diesen bestehenden Instrumenten zählt namentlich die übliche Liquiditätshilfe in Notfällen (ELA, Emergency Liquidity Assistance). Die Massnahmen erachtet der Bundesrat als die geeignetste Lösung, um das Vertrauen der Märkte in die Credit Suisse und den Schweizer Finanzplatz zu stärken. Sowohl in den USA als auch in der EU und im Vereinigten Königreich bestehen vergleichbare Instrumente.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Um allfällige Risiken für die UBS zu reduzieren, spricht der Bund der UBS zudem eine Garantie im Umfang von 9 Milliarden Franken zur Übernahme von potenziellen Verlusten aus bestimmten Aktiven, die die UBS im Rahmen der Transaktion übernimmt, sofern in Zukunft allfällige Verluste eine bestimmte Schwelle überschreiten sollten.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Der Bundesrat hat der Finanzdelegation der Eidgenössischen Räte einen dringlichen Verpflichtungskredit beantragt. Diesem Verpflichtungskredit hat die Finanzdelegation heute Sonntag, 19. März 2023, zugestimmt.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mit den getroffenen Massnahmen wurde sichergestellt, dass die SNB der Credit Suisse im Bedarfsfall umfassend Liquidität zur Verfügung stellen kann. Für den Bezug der Liquiditätshilfen gelten strenge Voraussetzungen. Zudem wird der Bundesrat gemäss Artikel 10a des Bankengesetzes auch Massnahmen im Bereich der Vergütungen anordnen.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Der Bundesrat hat Vorkehrungen getroffen, um die Risiken für den Bund so klein wie möglich zu halten. So muss die Credit Suisse dem Bund und der SNB je eine Risikoprämie, dem Bund für die Bereitstellung der Ausfallgarantie eine Bereitstellungsprämie sowie der SNB einen Zins entrichten. Zusammen mit dem Konkursprivileg resultiert daraus ein geringes Ausfallrisiko für den Bund.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Die bestehenden und neu zur Verfügung stehenden Liquiditätshilfen der Nationalbank genügen, zusammen mit den bei der Credit Suisse vorhandenen Liquiditätsreserven, um die Liquidität der Credit Suisse umfassend zu gewährleisten. Mit diesem Massnahmenpaket bekräftigt der Bundesrat seine Bereitschaft, die notwendigen Massnahmen zu ergreifen, um die Einleger und die Stabilität des Finanzplatzes Schweiz zu schützen.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Kommunikation EFD info@gs-efd.admin.ch +41 58 462 60 33</contact>
      <attachment id="244942">
        <title>Verordnung</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>210</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/76275.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="244943">
        <title>Änderung der Verordnung Liquiditätshilfe</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>256</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/76276.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="244946">
        <title>Erläuternder Bericht</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>350</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/76270.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <link id="244953">
        <title>FAQ</title>
        <uri>https://www.efd.admin.ch/dam/efd/de/finanzplatz/uebernahem-cs-ubs/faq-cs-ubs.pdf.download.pdf/faq-cs-de.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Assurer la stabilité des marchés financiers: le Conseil fédéral approuve et soutient l'acquisition de Credit Suisse par UBS</title>
      <lead>Le Conseil fédéral est favorable à l'acquisition prévue de Credit Suisse par UBS. Afin de renforcer la stabilité des marchés financiers jusqu’à l’exécution de l’acquisition, la Confédération accorde une garantie à la Banque nationale suisse (BNS) en vue de l’octroi à Credit Suisse d’une aide supplémentaire sous forme de liquidités. Cette aide vise à assurer la liquidité de Credit Suisse et, partant, la réalisation de l’acquisition. Le but de la mesure est de préserver la stabilité financière et de protéger l’économie suisse.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Aujourd'hui, UBS a fait savoir qu’elle était prête à acquérir Credit Suisse. Le Conseil fédéral soutient cette décision, qu’il juge importante pour la stabilité des marchés financiers. Il a adopté des mesures d’injection de liquidités supplémentaires afin de garantir la poursuite des activités de Credit Suisse jusqu'à l’exécution de l’acquisition et de réduire les coûts pour l’économie suisse.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Le Conseil fédéral a d’une part créé les bases légales requises pour que la BNS puisse octroyer à Credit Suisse une aide supplémentaire sous forme de liquidités. Concrètement, il a assorti cette aide d’un privilège des créances afin de garantir à la BNS la sécurité nécessaire pour pouvoir fournir à Credit Suisse des liquidités supplémentaires de grande ampleur. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Dans l’intention de garantir en tout temps des liquidités suffisantes à Credit Suisse, le Conseil fédéral a d’autre part décidé d’octroyer à la BNS une garantie contre le risque de défaillance lié à des prêts de liquidités. Ces deux mesures se fondent sur les art. 184 et 185 de la Constitution (droit de nécessité).&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ces mesures prises par le Conseil fédéral viennent compléter les instruments dont la BNS dispose d’ores et déjà pour renforcer les liquidités des banques. Les instruments actuels comprennent notamment la fourniture d’une aide d’urgence ordinaire en cas de crise de liquidités (emergency liquidity assistance, ELA). Le Conseil fédéral considère que ces mesures sont la meilleure solution pour renforcer la confiance des marchés dans Credit Suisse et dans la place financière suisse. Des instruments similaires sont utilisés aussi bien aux États-Unis qu’au sein de l’Union européenne ou du Royaume-Uni.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;La Confédération accorde en outre une garantie de 9 milliards de francs à UBS afin de réduire les risques que cet établissement encourt du fait de l’acquisition de certains actifs pouvant potentiellement subir des pertes, dans la mesure où ces éventuelles pertes devaient dépasser un seuil déterminé.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Le Conseil fédéral a sollicité un crédit d’engagement urgent auprès de la Délégation des finances des Chambres fédérales, qui l’a autorisé ce dimanche 19 mars 2023. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Les mesures adoptées garantissent que la BNS puisse, si nécessaire, mettre des liquidités suffisantes à la disposition de Credit Suisse. Le recours à des aides sous forme de liquidités est assorti de conditions strictes. De plus, le Conseil fédéral ordonnera des mesures en matière de rémunération conformément à l’art. 10a de la loi sur les banques.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Le Conseil fédéral a pris des mesures pour que la Confédération encoure le moins de risques possible. Ainsi, Credit Suisse devra verser deux primes de risque, une à la Confédération et une à la BNS, ainsi qu’une prime de mise à disposition à la Confédération pour la garantie contre le risque de défaillance et un intérêt à la BNS. Associées au privilège des créances, ces mesures assurent la Confédération de courir un faible risque de défaillance.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Avec les réserves de liquidités dont dispose Credit Suisse, les aides sous forme de liquidités existantes ou nouvelles fournies par la BNS suffisent à garantir la liquidité de Credit Suisse. Par ce train de mesures, le Conseil fédéral confirme sa volonté de prendre les mesures qui s’imposent pour protéger les déposants et préserver la stabilité de la place financière suisse.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Communication DFF info@gs-efd.admin.ch +41 58 462 60 33</contact>
      <attachment id="244947">
        <title>Ordonnance</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>209</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/76277.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="244948">
        <title>Modification de l'Ordonnance - Version corrigée concernant l'article 14a. du 20.03.2023</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>305</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/76291.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="244949">
        <title>Rapport explicatif</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>392</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/76272.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <link id="244954">
        <title>Questions et réponses</title>
        <uri>https://www.efd.admin.ch/dam/efd/fr/finanzplatz/uebernahem-cs-ubs/faq-cs-ubs.pdf.download.pdf/faq-cs-fr.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Garanzia della stabilità del mercato finanziario: il Consiglio federale approva e sostiene l’acquisizione di Credit Suisse da parte di UBS</title>
      <lead>Il Consiglio federale approva la prevista acquisizione di Credit Suisse da parte di UBS. Al fine di rafforzare la stabilità del mercato finanziario, fino alla conclusione dell’acquisizione la Confederazione concede una garanzia per un sostegno supplementare di liquidità a Credit Suisse da parte della Banca nazionale svizzera (BNS). Questo sostegno serve a garantire la liquidità di Credit Suisse e un’attuazione riuscita dell’acquisizione. L’intervento mira a tutelare la stabilità finanziaria e l’economia svizzera.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;In data odierna UBS ha reso nota la propria disponibilità ad acquisire Credit Suisse. Il Consiglio federale approva questa decisione e lo considera un importante contributo alla stabilità del mercato finanziario. Al fine di assicurare la continuazione dell’attività operativa di Credit Suisse fino all’attuazione dell’acquisizione e ridurre i costi per l’economia svizzera, l’Esecutivo ha deciso ulteriori misure in materia di liquidità:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;come prima misura il Consiglio federale ha creato le basi giuridiche necessarie per consentire alla BNS di concedere a Credit Suisse sostegni supplementari di liquidità. Concretamente, per questi aiuti l’Esecutivo ha introdotto un privilegio nel fallimento. La BNS ottiene così la sicurezza necessaria per poter mettere a disposizione di Credit Suisse, in caso di necessità, questa sostanziale liquidità supplementare;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;per garantire a Credit Suisse in qualsiasi momento una liquidità sufficiente, come seconda misura il Consiglio federale ha deciso di concedere alla BNS una garanzia in caso di dissesto. Entrambe le misure sono rette dagli articoli 184 e 185 della Costituzione federale (diritto di necessità).&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Queste misure completano gli strumenti già a disposizione della BNS per rafforzare la liquidità delle banche, tra i quali si annovera segnatamente il sostegno alla liquidità ordinario fornito in situazioni di emergenza (ELA, «Emergency Liquidity Assistance»).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Il Consiglio federale ritiene che tali provvedimenti siano la soluzione più adeguata per accrescere la fiducia dei mercati in Credit Suisse e nella piazza finanziaria svizzera. Negli Stati Uniti, nell’UE e nel Regno Unito esistono strumenti analoghi.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Per ridurre eventuali rischi per UBS, la Confederazione accorda a quest’ultima una garanzia dell’ordine di 9 miliardi di franchi per l’assunzione di potenziali perdite derivanti da determinati attivi che UBS riprenderebbe nel quadro della transazione, qualora queste eventuali perdite dovessero superare una certa soglia.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;L’Esecutivo ha chiesto alla Delegazione delle finanze delle Camere federali un credito d’impegno urgente. Quest’ultima ha approvato questo credito d’impegno oggi, domenica 19 marzo 2023.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Le misure decise garantiscono che la BNS possa mettere a disposizione di Credit Suisse, in caso di necessità, la liquidità sufficiente. L’ottenimento del sostegno di liquidità è subordinato a condizioni rigorose. Inoltre, secondo l’articolo 10a della legge sulle banche, il Consiglio federale ordinerà anche misure concernenti le retribuzioni.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;L’Esecutivo ha preso provvedimenti volti a contenere il più possibile i rischi per la Confederazione. Per tale motivo, Credit Suisse dovrà versare un premio di rischio sia alla Confederazione che alla BNS. Dovrà inoltre corrispondere un premio per la messa a disposizione della garanzia in caso di dissesto alla Confederazione e interessi alla BNS. Da questi provvedimenti e dal privilegio nel fallimento, per la Confederazione risulta un rischio di dissesto esiguo.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I sostegni di liquidità della BNS esistenti e quelli nuovi sono sufficienti, insieme alle riserve di liquidità di cui Credit Suisse dispone, per garantire sufficiente liquidità all’istituto. Con questa serie di misure, il Consiglio federale ribadisce la sua disponibilità ad adottare i provvedimenti necessari per tutelare i detentori di depositi e la stabilità della piazza finanziaria svizzera.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Comunicazione DFF info@gs-efd.admin.ch +41 58 462 60 33</contact>
      <attachment id="244950">
        <title>Ordinanza</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>203</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/76278.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="244951">
        <title>Modifica all'Ordinanza</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>248</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/76273.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="244952">
        <title>Spiegazioni</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>329</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/76274.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <link id="244955">
        <title>FAQ</title>
        <uri>https://www.efd.admin.ch/dam/efd/it/finanzplatz/uebernahem-cs-ubs/faq-cs-ubs.pdf.download.pdf/faq-cs-it.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Safeguarding financial market stability: Federal Council welcomes and supports UBS takeover of Credit Suisse</title>
      <lead>The Federal Council welcomes the planned takeover of Credit Suisse by UBS. To strengthen financial market stability until the takeover is complete, the federal government is providing a guarantee for additional liquidity assistance from the Swiss National Bank (SNB) to Credit Suisse. This support is intended to secure the liquidity of Credit Suisse and thus also ensure the successful implementation of the takeover. The Federal Council is taking this measure in order to protect financial stability and the Swiss economy.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;UBS announced today that it stands ready to take over Credit Suisse. The Federal Council welcomes this move as an important contribution to financial market stability. The Federal Council has agreed on additional liquidity measures to ensure business continuity at Credit Suisse until the takeover is complete and to reduce the burden on the Swiss economy.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;First, the Federal Council has created the necessary legal basis for the SNB to be able to provide Credit Suisse with additional liquidity assistance. Specifically, the Federal Council has established bankruptcy privilege rights for this additional liquidity assistance. This gives the SNB the necessary assurance to make available to Credit Suisse substantial additional liquidity.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Second, to ensure that Credit Suisse is provided with sufficient liquidity at all times, the Federal Council has decided to give the SNB a default guarantee for liquidity assistance. Both of these measures were taken on the basis of Articles 184 and 185 of the Federal Constitution (emergency law).&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;These measures supplement SNB's existing instruments for strengthening banks' liquidity, which include standard emergency liquidity assistance (ELA). The Federal Council considers these measures to be the most appropriate solution to strengthen both market confidence in Credit Suisse and the Swiss financial centre. Similar instruments exist in the United States and also in the European Union and the United Kingdom.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In order to reduce any risks for UBS, the federal government is also granting UBS a guarantee in the amount of CHF 9 billion to assume potential losses arising from certain assets that UBS takes over as part of the transaction, should any future losses exceed a certain threshold.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Federal Council submitted a request to the Finance Delegation for an emergency credit committment, and this was approved by the Finance Delegation today, Sunday, 19 March 2023.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;With the measures taken it is ensured that the SNB is able to provide Credit Suisse with sufficient liquidity if necessary. Strict conditions are in place for drawing on this liquidity assistance. The Federal Council will also impose restrictions in regard to remuneration packages, pursuant to Article 10a of the Banking Act.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Federal Council has taken precautions to minimise the risk for the Confederation. Credit Suisse is thus required to pay a risk premium to both the federal government and the SNB, a commitment premium to the federal government for providing the default guarantee, and interest to the SNB. Together with the bankruptcy privilege rights, this means that the Confederation's default risk exposure is low.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The existing and newly available liquidity assistance from the SNB, together with the liquidity reserves available at Credit Suisse, are sufficient to comprehensively secure Credit Suisse's liquidity. With this package of measures, the Federal Council is reaffirming its readiness to take the necessary measures to protect depositors and the stability of the Swiss financial centre.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>FDF Communications info@gs-efd.admin.ch +41 58 462 60 33</contact>
      <attachment id="244944">
        <title>Ordinance</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>190</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/76289.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="244945">
        <title>Ordinance Amendment</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>242</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/76290.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="244946">
        <title>Erläuternder Bericht</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>350</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/76270.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <link id="244956">
        <title>FAQ</title>
        <uri>https://www.efd.admin.ch/dam/efd/en/finanzplatz/uebernahem-cs-ubs/faq-cs-ubs.pdf.download.pdf/faq-cs-en.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <keywords>
      <keyword id="118" org-id="1060">
        <name lang="de">Finanzmarktregulierung und -aufsicht</name>
        <name lang="fr">Réglementation et surveillance des marchés financiers</name>
        <name lang="it">Regolamentazione e vigilanza dei mercati finanziari</name>
        <name lang="en">Financial market regulation and supervision</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="126" org-id="1060">
        <name lang="de">Finanzplatz Schweiz</name>
        <name lang="fr">Place financière suisse</name>
        <name lang="it">Piazza finanziaria svizzera</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland as a financial centre</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="1111" org-id="1060">
        <name lang="de">Too big to fail</name>
        <name lang="fr">Too big to fail</name>
        <name lang="it">Too big to fail</name>
        <name lang="en">Too big to fail</name>
      </keyword>
    </keywords>
    <topics>
      <topic id="35">
        <name lang="de">Finanzplatz</name>
        <name lang="fr">Place financière</name>
        <name lang="it">Piazza finanziaria</name>
        <name lang="en">Financial Centre</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="44">
        <name lang="de">Steuern</name>
        <name lang="fr">Impôts</name>
        <name lang="it">Imposte</name>
        <name lang="en">Taxation</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="47">
        <name lang="de">Wirtschaft</name>
        <name lang="fr">Économie</name>
        <name lang="it">Economia</name>
        <name lang="en">Economic Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
