<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="94021" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2023-03-29</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="1070" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>1070</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Der Bundesrat</name>
      <name lang="fr">Conseil fédéral</name>
      <name lang="it">Il Consiglio federale</name>
      <name lang="en">The Federal Council</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.admin.ch/gov/de/start.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.admin.ch/gov/fr/accueil.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.admin.ch/gov/it/pagina-iniziale.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.admin.ch/gov/en/start.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="101" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>101</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Bundeskanzlei</name>
      <name lang="fr">Chancellerie fédérale</name>
      <name lang="it">Cancelleria federale</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Chancellery</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.bk.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.bk.admin.ch/index.html?lang=fr</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.bk.admin.ch/index.html?lang=it</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.bk.admin.ch/index.html?lang=en</www>
      <email lang="de">infokomm@admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">infokomm@admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">infokomm@admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">infokomm@admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="501" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>501</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Verteidigung, Bevölkerungsschutz und Sport</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de la défense, de la protection de la population et des sports</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale della difesa, della protezione della popolazione e dello sport</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Defence, Civil Protection and Sports DDPS</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.vbs.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.vbs.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.vbs.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.vbs.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@gs-vbs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@gs-vbs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@gs-vbs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@gs-vbs.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="1070">
      <name lang="de">Der Bundesrat</name>
      <name lang="fr">Conseil fédéral</name>
      <name lang="it">Il Consiglio federale</name>
      <name lang="en">The Federal Council</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.admin.ch/gov/de/start.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.admin.ch/gov/fr/accueil.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.admin.ch/gov/it/pagina-iniziale.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.admin.ch/gov/en/start.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <department id="101">
      <name lang="de">Bundeskanzlei</name>
      <name lang="fr">Chancellerie fédérale</name>
      <name lang="it">Cancelleria federale</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Chancellery</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.bk.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.bk.admin.ch/index.html?lang=fr</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.bk.admin.ch/index.html?lang=it</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.bk.admin.ch/index.html?lang=en</www>
      <email lang="de">infokomm@admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">infokomm@admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">infokomm@admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">infokomm@admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <department id="501">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Verteidigung, Bevölkerungsschutz und Sport</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de la défense, de la protection de la population et des sports</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale della difesa, della protezione della popolazione e dello sport</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Defence, Civil Protection and Sports DDPS</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.vbs.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.vbs.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.vbs.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.vbs.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@gs-vbs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@gs-vbs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@gs-vbs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@gs-vbs.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Bundesrat verbessert Organisation des Krisenmanagements</title>
      <lead>Der Bundesrat soll auf Krisen besser vorbereitet und bei deren Bewältigung effizienter unterstützt werden. An seiner Sitzung vom 29. März 2023 hat er, basierend auf den Lehren aus der Corona-Pandemie, entschieden, die Organisation der Bundesverwaltung für künftige Krisen zu stärken. Bei komplexen Krisen kann der Bundesrat den Einsatz eines Krisenstabs auf politisch-strategischer und auf operativer Ebene beschliessen. Oberste leitende Behörde bleibt der Bundesrat. Neu soll ausserdem ein Permanenter Kernstab die Stäbe der Departemente in der Krisenbewältigung unterstützen. Der Bundesrat hat das VBS und die Bundeskanzlei bis Ende 2023 mit der Ausarbeitung von Rechtsgrundlagen für die neue Krisenorganisation beauftragt. </lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Die Auswertungen der Bundeskanzlei, der Konferenz der Kantonsregierungen und der Geschäftsprüfungskommission beider Räte zum Krisenmanagement in der Covid-19-Pandeme haben Verbesserungspotenziale aufgezeigt. Der Bundesrat hat die Schlüsse aus diesen Evaluationen gezogen und beantwortet mit dem Bericht «Verbesserte Krisenorganisation der Bundesverwaltung» die Postulate 21.3205 «Rolle des Bundesstabes für Bevölkerungsschutzes (BSTB) im Rahmen der Covid-19 Pandemie», 21.3449 «Strategisches Krisenmanagement» und 22.3343 «Endlich institutionelle Krisenresistenz des Bundesrates sicherstellen».&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Drei Säulen der künftigen Krisenorganisation&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Der Bundesrat ist der Auffassung, dass die ordentlichen Strukturen und Prozesse der Bundesverwaltung nicht grundsätzlich geändert werden müssen. Hingegen soll die Arbeit der Krisenstäbe in Zukunft methodisch und administrativ besser unterstützt werden. Diese Leistungen sollen von einem Permanenten Kernstab erbracht werden. Dieser wird aus Mitarbeitenden des VBS, der Departemente und der Bundeskanzlei zusammengesetzt, womit das überdepartementale Krisenmanagement unterstützt wird. Der Permanente Kernstab ermöglicht dadurch eine bessere Kontinuität, mehr Einheitlichkeit beim Krisenmanagement des Bundes und einen grösseren Wissenserhalt zwischen Krisen. Die Aufgaben umfassen u.a. den Einbezug relevanter Akteure und die integrale Lagedarstellung.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Zur Bewältigung von komplexen Krisen kann der Bundesrat künftig den Politisch-Strategischen Krisenstab einsetzen. Dieser wird von dem in der jeweiligen Krise federführenden Departement geleitet. Seine Aufgabe besteht darin, Anträge an den Bundesrat politisch vorzubereiten und das Krisenmanagement überdepartemental zu koordinieren, dies unter Einbezug aller relevanten Akteure. Dieser Stab setzt sich aus den Generalsekretärinnen bzw. Generalsekretären der betroffenen Departemente, den beiden Vizekanzlern, der EFV, dem BJ und dem SECO zusammen. Allenfalls nehmen der Bundeskanzler sowie externe Stellen teil. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Zusätzlich bildet das federführende Departement bei Bedarf einen Operativen Krisenstab, der die Koordination auf Ebene der Verwaltungseinheiten sicherstellt und die notwendigen Informationen und Grundlagen für den Politisch-Strategischen Krisenstab erarbeitet. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Die Details dieser drei Säulen der künftigen Krisenorganisation und ihrer Zusammenarbeit untereinander sowie mit externen Partnern werden in der Umsetzung geklärt. Hierzu hat der Bundesrat das VBS beauftragt in Zusammenarbeit mit der BK und unter Einbezug der Departemente die Zusammensetzung, Leistungen, Prozesse und Ressourcen des Permanenten Kernstabs zu definieren, damit der Bundesrat bis Ende 2023 darüber befinden kann. Ebenfalls bis Ende Jahr soll eine neue Verordnung über die Krisenbewältigung erarbeitet werden, die die bisherigen Rechtsgrundlagen ersetzt.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Einbezug der Kantone und der Wissenschaft&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Die Kantone und die Wissenschaft sowie situativ weitere relevante Akteure werden in die Arbeiten des Politisch-Strategischen oder Operativen Krisenstab einbezogen. Die Verantwortung hierfür liegt in einer Krisensituation beim federführenden Departement. Dieses wird dabei durch den Permanenten Kernstab unterstützt. Die Details des Einbezugs werden in der Umsetzung geklärt.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Verstärkte Krisenantizipation&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Durch eine stärkere Verknüpfung von Risikomanagement Bund, Krisenfrüherkennung, kontinuierlicher Lage- und Umfeldanalyse und den Analysen aus den Departementen wird die Frühwarnung bei Krisen verbessert. Mit der verstärkten Krisenantizipation soll der Bundesrat die Möglichkeit erhalten, eine überdepartementale Krisenorganisation rechtzeitig einzusetzen. &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Ursula Eggenberger, Leiterin Kommunikation BK ursula.eggenberger@bk.admin.ch, Tel. 058 462 37 63 Lorenz Frischknecht, Stv. Chef Komm VBS / Sprecher VBS lorenz.frischknecht@gs-vbs.admin.ch, Tel. 058 484 26 17</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Le Conseil fédéral améliore l’organisation de la gestion de crise</title>
      <lead>Le Conseil fédéral doit être mieux préparé aux crises et soutenu plus efficacement dans la gestion de celles-ci. Se fondant sur les enseignements tirés de la pandémie de COVID-19, il a décidé le 29 mars 2023 de renforcer l’organisation de l’administration fédérale pour les crises à venir. En cas de crise complexe, le Conseil fédéral pourra décider de constituer un état-major de crise aux niveaux politico-stratégique et opérationnel. Le Conseil fédéral demeure l’autorité directoriale et exécutive suprême. En outre, un état-major central permanent soutiendra les états-majors des départements dans la gestion de crise. Le Conseil fédéral a chargé le Département fédéral de la défense, de la protection de la population et des sports et la Chancellerie fédérale d’élaborer les bases légales nécessaires à la nouvelle organisation de crise d’ici à la fin 2023.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Les évaluations de la gestion de crise pendant la pandémie de COVID-19, faites par la Chancellerie fédérale, la Conférence des gouvernements cantonaux et les Commissions de gestion des Chambres fédérales, ont révélé un potentiel d’amélioration. Le Conseil fédéral en a tiré les conséquences et donne suite aux postulats 21.3205 « Rôle de l’État-major fédéral Protection de la population dans le contexte de la pandémie de COVID-19 », 21.3449 « Gestion de crise à l’échelon stratégique » et 22.3343 « Garantir enfin la capacité institutionnelle du Conseil fédéral à faire face aux crises » par le rapport « Amélioration de l’organisation de crise de l’administration fédérale ». &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Les trois piliers de la future organisation de crise&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Le Conseil fédéral estime qu’il n’y a pas lieu de revoir de fond en comble les processus et les structures ordinaires de l’administration fédérale. Il faut par contre mieux soutenir, sous l’angle méthodologique et administratif, le travail des états-majors de crise. Les prestations nécessaires à la gestion de crise supradépartementale seront fournies par un état-major central permanent, composé de collaborateurs du Département fédéral de la défense, de la protection de la population et des sports (DDPS), d’autres départements et de la Chancellerie fédérale (ChF). L’état-major central permanent permettra d’assurer la continuité et d’uniformiser la gestion de crise de la confédération, sans perte des connaissances acquises entre les crises. Ses tâches comprendront notamment l’association des acteurs pertinents et la présentation intégrale de la situation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;À l’avenir, le Conseil fédéral pourra engager l’état-major de crise politico-stratégique, qui sera dirigé par le département responsable en l’espèce, pour gérer les crises complexes. Cet état-major aura pour tâche de préparer, au niveau politique, des propositions au Conseil fédéral et de coordonner la gestion de crise au niveau supradépartemental, en associant tous les acteurs pertinents. Il se composera des secrétaires généraux des départements concernés, des deux vice-chanceliers, de représentants de l’Administration fédérale des finances, de l’Office fédéral de la justice et du Secrétariat d’État à l’économie. Le cas échéant, la composition sera élargie au chancelier de la Confédération et à des externes.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Par ailleurs, le département responsable constituera, au besoin, un état-major de crise opérationnel, lequel assurera la coordination au niveau des unités administratives et fournira les informations et les bases nécessaires à l’état-major de crise politico-stratégique. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Les détails concernant les trois piliers de la future organisation de crise et la collaboration entre eux et avec les partenaires externes seront précisés dans le cadre de la mise en œuvre. Dans ce contexte, le Conseil fédéral a chargé le DDPS, en collaboration avec la ChF et avec la participation des départements, de définir la composition, les prestations, les processus et les ressources de l’état-major central permanent, afin qu’il puisse se prononcer à ce sujet d’ici à la fin de 2023. Une nouvelle ordonnance sur la gestion de crise, qui remplacera les bases légales actuelles, devra être élaborée dans le même délai. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Association des cantons et des milieux scientifiques&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Les cantons, les milieux scientifiques et d’autres acteurs pertinents selon la situation seront associés aux travaux de l’état-major de crise politico-stratégique ou de l’état-major de crise opérationnel. En cas de crise, il appartiendra au département responsable de veiller à cette association, avec le soutien de l’état-major central permanent. Les détails seront précisés dans le cadre de la mise en œuvre.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Amélioration de l’anticipation des crises&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;En cas de crise, l’alerte précoce sera améliorée par un renforcement des liens entre la gestion des risques de la Confédération, la détection précoce des crises, l’analyse continue de la situation et du contexte et les analyses provenant des départements. L’amélioration de l’anticipation des crises vise à permettre au Conseil fédéral de mettre en place en temps utile une organisation de crise supradépartementale.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Ursula Eggenberger, responsable de la section Communication ChF ursula.eggenberger@bk.admin.ch, tél. 058 462 37 63 Lorenz Frischknecht, responsable suppl. Communication DDPS / Porte-parole DDPS lorenz.frischknecht@gs-vbs.admin.ch, tél. 058 484 26 17</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Il Consiglio federale migliora l'organizzazione della gestione di crisi</title>
      <lead>Il Consiglio federale deve essere meglio preparato e supportato in modo più efficiente per affrontare le crisi. Nella seduta del 29 marzo 2023, il Consiglio federale ha deciso, sulla base degli insegnamenti tratti dalla pandemia di COVID-19, di rafforzare l’organizzazione dell’Amministrazione federale per le crisi future. Il Consiglio federale può decidere, in presenza di crisi complesse, di istituire uno stato maggiore di crisi a livello politico-strategico e uno a livello operativo. La suprema autorità direttiva resta il Consiglio federale. Uno Stato maggiore centrale permanente sarà inoltre incaricato di supportare gli stati maggiori dei dipartimenti nella gestione di crisi. Il Consiglio federale ha incaricato il Dipartimento federale della difesa, della protezione della popolazione e dello sport (DDPS) e la Cancelleria federale (CaF) di elaborare le basi legali della nuova organizzazione di crisi entro la fine del 2023. </lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Le valutazioni della CaF e della Conferenza dei Governi cantonali nonché il rapporto delle Commissioni della gestione delle Camere federali sulla gestione di crisi durante la pandemia di COVID 19 hanno individuato un certo margine di miglioramento. Il Consiglio federale ha tratto le sue conclusioni sulla base di tali valutazioni e col rapporto «Miglioramento dell’organizzazione di crisi della Confederazione» ha adempiuto ai postulati 21.3205 Ruolo dello Stato maggiore federale Protezione della popolazione nell’ambito della pandemia di Covid-19, 21.3449 Gestione strategica delle crisi e 22.3343 Rafforzare finalmente a livello istituzionale la capacità del Consiglio federale di affrontare le crisi.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;I tre pilastri della futura organizzazione di crisi&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Il Consiglio federale ritiene che le strutture e i processi ordinari dell’Amministrazione federale non debbano essere modificati in modo sostanziale. Cionondimeno, in futuro il lavoro degli stati maggiori di crisi dovrà ricevere un supporto più efficace sul piano metodologico e amministrativo. Tali prestazioni saranno fornite da uno Stato maggiore centrale permanente, composto dai collaboratori del DDPS, dei dipartimenti e della CaF e incaricato di fornire supporto nella gestione di crisi a livello sovradipartimentale. Lo Stato maggiore centrale permanente potrà così favorire una migliore continuità, una procedura uniforme nella gestione di crisi della Confederazione e una conservazione delle conoscenze più duratura tra una crisi e l’altra. Esso avrà in particolare il compito di coinvolgere gli attori rilevanti e di garantire la presentazione integrale della situazione.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Per affrontare crisi complesse, in futuro il Consiglio federale potrà impiegare lo Stato maggiore di crisi politico-strategico (SMCPS), diretto dal dipartimento responsabile per la crisi in questione. Il compito dello SMCPS è quello di preparare sul piano politico le proposte per il Consiglio federale e di coordinare la gestione di crisi a livello sovradipartimentale coinvolgendo tutti gli attori rilevanti. Lo SMCPS è composto dai segretari generali dei dipartimenti interessati, dei vicecancellieri, dell’Amministrazione federale delle finanze, dell’Ufficio federale di giustizia, della SECO. Possono partecipare anche il cancelliere della Confederazione e servizi esterni.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Il dipartimento responsabile potrà inoltre istituire, se necessario, uno Stato maggiore di crisi operativo (SMCOp) il quale garantisce il coordinamento tra le unità amministrative ed elabora le informazioni e la documentazione di base necessaria per lo SMCPS. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I dettagli relativi ai tre pilastri della futura organizzazione di crisi nonché alla collaborazione reciproca e con i partner esterni saranno chiariti nella fase di attuazione. A tal fine, il Consiglio federale ha incaricato il DDPS e la CaF, in collaborazione con gli altri dipartimenti, di definire le prestazioni, i processi e le risorse dello Stato maggiore centrale permanente affinché il Consiglio federale possa decidere in merito entro la fine del 2023. Prima della fine dell’anno sarà inoltre elaborata una nuova ordinanza per la gestione di crisi che sostituirà le attuali basi legali.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Coinvolgimento dei Cantoni e della comunità scientifica&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I Cantoni, la comunità scientifica e, a seconda dei casi, eventuali altri attori rilevanti saranno coinvolti nei lavori dello SMCPS e dello SMCOp. In una situazione di crisi essi saranno coinvolti dal dipartimento responsabile, il quale riceve il supporto dello SMCPS nell’esecuzione di tale compito. I dettagli relativi a tale coinvolgimento saranno chiariti nell’ambito dell’attuazione.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Migliore capacità di anticipare le crisi&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Grazie a una più forte sinergia tra la gestione dei rischi della Confederazione, l’identificazione precoce delle crisi, l’analisi continua della situazione e del contesto e le analisi dei dipartimenti sarà possibile migliorare la capacità di anticipare le crisi. In tal modo, il Consiglio federale avrà la possibilità di impiegare con tempestività un’organizzazione di crisi sovradipartimentale. &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Ursula Eggenberger, capo della sezione Comunicazione CaF ursula.eggenberger@bk.admin.ch, tel. 058 462 37 63 Lorenz Frischknecht, sostituto del capo della Comunicazione / portavoce del DDPS lorenz.frischknecht@gs-vbs.admin.ch, tel. 058 484 26 17</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Federal Council improves crisis management structures</title>
      <lead>The Federal Council aims to be better prepared for crisis situations and have more efficient mechanisms in place for dealing with them. At its meeting on 29 March, it decided, based on the lessons learned from the COVID-19 pandemic, to strengthen the organisation of the Federal Administration so it is better equipped for future crises. In the event of complex crises, the Federal Council will be able to deploy crisis units at both a strategic and operational level. The Federal Council remains the supreme governing authority. In addition, a Standing Core Unit will provide crisis management support to the departmental staff offices. The Federal Council has tasked the Federal Department of Defence, Civil Protection and Sport DDPS and the Federal Chancellery FCh with drawing up core legislation on the new crisis management structure by the end of 2023. </lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Reviews conducted by the Federal Chancellery, the Conference of Cantonal Governments and the parliamentary control committees on crisis management during the COVID-19 pandemic revealed that there is potential for improvement. In its report on improved crisis organisation in the Federal Administration, the Federal Council has responded to the review findings and to postulates 21.3205 ‘Role of the Federal Civil Protection Crisis Management Board CCMB in the COVID-19 pandemic’, 21.3449 ‘Strategic Crisis Management’ and 22.3343 ‘Ensure the Federal Council’s Institutional Crisis Resilience’.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Crisis management with three pillars&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Federal Council is of the opinion that no fundamental change needs to be made to the ordinary structures and processes in the Federal Administration. However, going forward, crisis management units are to receive greater methodological and administrative support from a permanent unit set up for this purpose. This Standing Core Unit will comprise staff from the DDPS, other federal departments and the Federal Chancellery, and so promote interdepartmental crisis management. It will foster continuity, greater uniformity in federal crisis management and better knowledge retention between crisis events. It will include other relevant players and will be required to provide regular situation reports.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In future, the Federal Council can call on the Policy and Strategic Crisis Management Unit in order to manage complex crises. Headed by the lead department dealing with the crisis in question, this unit’s task will be to draw up policy proposals for the Federal Council and to coordinate crisis management on an interdepartmental basis, involving all relevant actors. The unit will comprise the secretaries general of the departments concerned, the two vice chancellors, the Federal Finance Administration, the Federal Office of Justice and the State Secretariat for Economic Affairs. The federal chancellor and external bodies may also be involved. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;If required, the lead department can also form an Operational Crisis Management Unit to ensure coordination between all administrative units and prepare all information required by the Policy and Strategic Crisis Management Unit. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The details of these three pillars of crisis management and the way in which they cooperate with each other and with external partners will be refined going forward. To this end, the Federal Council has instructed the DDPS, in conjunction with the FCh and with the involvement of the departments, to define the composition, services, processes and resources of the Standing Core Unit for its consideration by the end of 2023. A new crisis management ordinance is also to be drawn up by the end of the year to replace the previous statutory basis.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Involvement of the cantons and scientific community&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The cantons and the scientific community, as well as other relevant actors if the situation requires, will be involved in the work of the Policy and Strategic Crisis Management Unit and the Operational Crisis Management Unit. The lead department, aided by the Standing Core Unit, will be responsible for deciding on their composition, the exact details of which will be decided in the given situation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Improved crisis anticipation&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A stronger link between federal risk management, early crisis detection, continuous situational and environment analysis and analyses from the departments will improve early warning in a crisis. With improved crisis anticipation, the Federal Council will be in a position to deploy cross-departmental crisis organisation in good time. &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Ursula Eggenberger, Head of Communications FCh ursula.eggenberger@bk.admin.ch, Tel. 058 462 37 63 Lorenz Frischknecht, Deputy Chief Comm DDPS / DDPS Spokesperson lorenz.frischknecht@gs-vbs.admin.ch, Tel. 058 484 26 17</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="10">
        <name lang="de">Bundesrat</name>
        <name lang="fr">Conseil fédéral</name>
        <name lang="it">Consiglio federale</name>
        <name lang="en">Federal Council</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
