<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="41125" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2011-09-13</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="201" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>201</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="201">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Bundespräsidentin Micheline Calmy-Rey trifft Tessiner Regierung</title>
      <lead>Bundespräsidentin Micheline Calmy-Rey hat am Dienstagabend in Bern die Tessiner Regierung zu einem Arbeitsgespräch empfangen. Im Zentrum der Gespräche standen die Beziehungen mit Italien. Der Bundesrat setze sich seit längerem für die Überwindung der Schwierigkeiten mit Rom in den Steuerfragen ein, betonte die Bundespräsidentin. Seit ihrem Treffen mit dem italienischen Ministerpräsidenten Silvio Berlusconi Anfang Juni haben Gespräche mit der italienischen Seite stattgefunden.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Neben den Steuerfragen waren unter anderem die Auswirkungen der Personenfreizügigkeit, die Verstärkung der flankierenden Massnahmen gegen Lohndumping sowie die Vorbereitungen für den Schweizer Auftritt an der Expo 2015 in Mailand Gegenstand der heutigen Gespräche.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Bundespräsidentin Micheline Calmy-Rey betonte, dass die Wiederaufnahme von Steuer-Verhandlungen mit Italien im Mittelpunkt der Bemühungen des Bundesrats stehe. Diese seien ebenfalls Hauptthema ihrer Gespräche mit Premierminister Berlusconi von Anfang Juni gewesen. Seitdem hat Rom positive Signale ausgesendet. Zudem hat das italienische Parlament eine Reihe von Motionen verabschiedet, welche von der italienischen Regierung die Aufnahme von Steuerverhandlungen mit der Schweiz fordern.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Information EDA Bundeshaus West CH-3003 Bern Tel.: +41 (0)31 322 31 53 Fax: +41 (0)31 324 90 47 E-Mail: info@eda.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Rencontre entre la présidente de la Confédération Micheline Calmy-Rey et le gouvernement tessinois</title>
      <lead>La présidente de la Confédération Micheline Calmy-Rey a reçu le gouvernement tessinois mardi soir à Berne pour un entretien de travail. Les discussions ont principalement porté sur les relations avec l’Italie. Le Conseil fédéral œuvre de longue date pour le règlement des différends fiscaux avec Rome, a souligné la présidente de la Confédération. Depuis sa rencontre avec le premier ministre italien Silvio Berlusconi début juin, des entretiens ont eu lieu avec la partie italienne.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Outre les questions fiscales, les conséquences de la libre circulation des personnes, le renforcement des mesures d’accompagnement destinées à éviter le dumping salarial ainsi que les travaux préparatoires en vue de la participation de la Suisse à l’Expo 2015 à Milan figuraient à l’ordre du jour des entretiens.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;La présidente de la Confédération Micheline Calmy-Rey a relevé que la reprise des négociations fiscales avec l’Italie est au cœur des efforts du Conseil fédéral. Elles étaient également le thème principal des entretiens qu’elle a eus avec le premier ministre Silvio Berlusconi début juin. Rome a envoyé depuis lors des signes positifs. En outre, le Parlement italien a adopté une série de motions demandant au gouvernement italien de relancer les négociations fiscales avec la Suisse.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Information DFAE Palais fédéral ouest CH-3003 Berne Tél.: (+41) 031 322 31 53 Fax: (+41) 031 324 90 47 E-Mail: info@eda.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>La presidente della Confederazione Micheline Calmy-Rey incontra il Governo ticinese</title>
      <lead>Martedì sera la presidente della Confederazione Micheline Calmy-Rey ha ricevuto a Berna il Governo ticinese per un incontro di lavoro. Al centro dei colloqui stavano le relazioni con l'Italia. La presidente della Confederazione ha sottolineato che il Consiglio federale s'impegna già da tempo per superare le difficoltà con Roma nell'ambito delle questioni fiscali. In seguito al suo incontro tenutosi all'inizio di giugno con il presidente del consiglio Silvio Berlusconi si sono svolti colloqui con la parte italiana.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Oltre alle questioni fiscali, oggetto dei colloqui odierni erano tra l'altro le ripercussioni della libera circolazione delle persone, il rafforzamento delle misure di accompagnamento contro il dumping salariale e i preparativi per la partecipazione svizzera all'Expo 2015 a Milano.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Micheline Calmy-Rey ha sottolineato che la ripresa dei negoziati con l'Italia in ambito fiscale è al centro degli sforzi del Consiglio federale e che all'inizio di giugno è già stato il tema principale dei colloqui con il presidente del consiglio Silvio Berlusconi. Successivamente a tale incontro Roma ha dato segnali positivi. Inoltre il parlamento italiano ha adottato una serie di mozioni che chiedono al governo italiano di avviare negoziati con la Svizzera in ambito fiscale.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Informazione DFAE Palazzo federale ovest CH-3003 Berna Tel.: (+41) 031 322 31 53 Fax: (+41) 031 324 90 47 E-Mail: info@eda.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>The President of the Confederation meets the cantonal government of Ticino</title>
      <lead>On Tuesday evening, the President of the Confederation, Micheline Calmy-Rey, received the cantonal government of Ticino in Bern for talks on relations with Italy. Mrs Calmy-Rey made a point of saying that the Federal Council had been actively working on ways to overcome difficulties with Rome on a number of tax issues for some time already. Talks have been taking place with Italy since Mrs Calmy-Rey met the Italian Prime Minister Silvio Berlusconi at the beginning of June this year.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;In addition to tax questions, the discussions in Bern covered other issues including the effects of the free movement of persons, strengthening parallel measures to combat wage dumping, and the preparations under way for Switzerland’s appearance at Expo 2015 Milan.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The President of the Confederation stressed that the resumption of negotiations on tax issues with Italy was a central aspect of the Federal Council’s efforts in this area and that taxation was the main issue of discussion at the meeting with Mr Berlusconi at the beginning of June. Rome has since given some positive signs, and the Italian Parliament has passed a series of motions demanding that the Italian government enter into negotiations with Switzerland on tax issues.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Information FDFA Bundeshaus West CH-3003 Bern Tel.: (+41) 031 322 31 53 Fax: (+41) 031 324 90 47 E-Mail: info@eda.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
