<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="40991" revoked="no">
    <version>3</version>
    <pubdate>2011-09-06</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="815" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>801</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössische Kommunikationskommission ComCom</name>
      <name lang="fr">Commission fédérale de la communication ComCom</name>
      <name lang="it">Commissione federale delle comunicazioni ComCom</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Communications Commission ComCom</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.comcom.admin.ch/</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.comcom.admin.ch/</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.comcom.admin.ch/</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.comcom.admin.ch/</www>
      <email lang="de">comcom@comcom.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">comcom@comcom.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">comcom@comcom.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">comcom@comcom.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="810" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>801</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Bundesamt für Kommunikation</name>
      <name lang="fr">Office fédéral de la communication</name>
      <name lang="it">Ufficio federale delle comunicazioni</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Office of Communications</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.bakom.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.ofcom.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.ufcom.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.ofcom.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">media@bakom.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">media@bakom.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">media@bakom.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">media@bakom.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="801">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Umwelt, Verkehr, Energie und Kommunikation</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'environnement, des transports, de l'énergie et de la communication</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'ambiente, dei trasporti, dell'energia e delle comunicazioni</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of the Environment, Transport, Energy and Communications</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.uvek.admin.ch/uvek/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.uvek.admin.ch/uvek/fr/home.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.uvek.admin.ch/uvek/it/home.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.uvek.admin.ch/uvek/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-uvek.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-uvek.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-uvek.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-uvek.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Runder Tisch zu Glasfasernetzen: die Teilnehmer ziehen Bilanz</title>
      <teaser>An ihrem achten Runden Tisch zu Glasfasernetzen haben sich die Marktakteure darüber ausgetauscht, wie sich der Ausbau von Telekommunikationsnetzen mit sehr hohen Bandbreiten entwickelt und wie sich die Kooperationen beim Glasfaserbau gestalten.</teaser>
      <lead>An ihrem achten Runden Tisch zu Glasfasernetzen haben sich die Marktakteure darüber ausgetauscht, wie sich der Ausbau von Telekommunikationsnetzen mit sehr hohen Bandbreiten entwickelt und wie sich die Kooperationen beim Glasfaserbau gestalten.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Die Teilnehmer am Runden Tisch haben diskutiert, wie sich der Ausbau von Fest- und Mobilfunknetzen mit sehr hohen Bandbreiten (VDSL, Kabelfernsehen, Glasfaser und LTE) entwickelt. Sie begrüssen den Fortschritt bei der Verfügbarkeit von Angeboten für die verschiedenen Dienste-Anbieter, vor allem auch der Ausbau der Glasfasernetze in einigen Städten. Das Bundesamt für Kommunikation (BAKOM) hat die Stossrichtung der Anfang Juli ins Leben gerufenen Arbeitsgruppe vorgestellt, um möglichst viele Gebiete der Schweiz mit modernen Telekommunikationsnetzen zu versorgen.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Darüber hinaus haben die Teilnehmer zur Kenntnis genommen, dass der Betriebsstart der gemeinsamen Plattform für Bestellungen und Kundenmutationen im Glasfaserbereich im Mai erfolgen konnte. Sie unterstützen die laufenden Anstrengungen zur gemeinsamen Weiterentwicklung dieser für eine dynamische Marktentwicklung wichtigen Plattform.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Schliesslich hat der Direktor des WEKO-Sekretariats die gestern veröffentlichte Einschätzung der Kooperationsverträge zwischen Swisscom und Elektrizitätswerken erläutert.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Der nächste Runde Tisch findet im Januar 2012 statt.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;b&gt;Fiber to the Home (FTTH)&lt;/b&gt; &lt;p&gt;Als Fiber to the Home (FTTH) bezeichnet man ein Fernmeldenetz, das bis in jedes Geschäfts-, Mehr- oder Einfamilienhaus über Lichtwellenleiter (Glasfaser) geführt wird. Die Glasfaser ist ein längst erprobtes Übertragungsmedium für hohe Datenraten und wird in der Evolution der Anschlussnetze in den nächsten Jahren notwendig sein, weil die alten Kupferleitungen dem wachsenden Bedarf nach höheren Bandbreiten für Internet-Applikationen, insbesondere für das Fernsehen mit hoher Auflösung, nicht mehr genügen werden.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Die ComCom hat im Herbst 2008 entschieden, mit den Marktakteuren Diskussionen über diese Erschliessungsform zu führen; sie will damit verhindern, dass Monopole entstehen, die den Zugang für andere Telekommunikationsanbieter erschweren und den Wettbewerb behindern. Gleichzeitig soll der Netzaufbau möglichst effizient stattfinden, um volkswirtschaftlich sinnvolle Investitionen zu erlauben.&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Sekretariat der ComCom: Tel. 031 323 52 90</contact>
      <link id="152457">
        <title>Verlegung der Glasfaser in der Schweiz</title>
        <uri>https://www.bakom.admin.ch/bakom/de/home/telekommunikation/technologie/verlegung-der-glasfaser-in-der-schweiz.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions>
        <revision date="2016-06-10 15:45" type="R"/>
      </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Table ronde sur les réseaux de fibre optique: les participants font le point</title>
      <teaser>Conviés à la huitième table ronde sur les réseaux de fibre optique, les acteurs du marché ont parlé de l’aménagement et du développement des réseaux de télécommunication à très haut débit ainsi que des modèles de coopération apparus lors du déploiement de la fibre optique.</teaser>
      <lead>Conviés à la huitième table ronde sur les réseaux de fibre optique, les acteurs du marché ont parlé de l’aménagement et du développement des réseaux de télécommunication à très haut débit ainsi que des modèles de coopération apparus lors du déploiement de la fibre optique.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Les participants à la ronde table ont parlé du développement et de l’aménagement des réseaux fixes et mobiles à très haut débit (VDSL, câble, fibre optique et LTE). Ils ont salué les progrès réalisés en ce qui concerne la disponibilité des offres pour les divers fournisseurs de services, notamment la mise en place de réseaux de fibre optique dans certaines villes. L’Office fédéral de la communication (OFCOM) a présenté dans ses grandes lignes le nouveau groupe de travail constitué début juillet pour raccorder le plus grand nombre possible de régions suisses aux réseaux de télécommunication modernes.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Par ailleurs, les participants ont pris note de la mise en service, en mai 2011, de la plateforme commune pour les commandes et la mutation de clients dans le domaine de la fibre optique. Ils soutiennent les efforts consentis pour développer ensemble cet outil important pour une évolution dynamique du marché.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Enfin, le directeur du secrétariat de la Comco a commenté l’évaluation des contrats de coopération entre Swisscom et les entreprises électriques publiée hier.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; La prochaine table ronde aura lieu en janvier 2012. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Fiber to the Home (FTTH)&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; &lt;/b&gt;Le terme Fiber to the Home (FTTH), en français "fibre optique jusque dans les foyers", désigne un réseau de télécommunication utilisant la fibre optique pour acheminer des données jusqu’à un bâtiment commercial, un immeuble locatif ou une maison individuelle. En tant que technologie de transmission à haut débit, la fibre optique a d’ores et déjà fait ses preuves. Elle devrait s’imposer ces prochaines années, car les anciennes lignes de cuivre ne seront bientôt plus assez performantes pour répondre aux besoins croissants en largeurs de bande. En effet, les applications Internet, en particulier dans le domaine de la télévision à haute définition, sont de plus en plus gourmandes. &lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; En automne 2008, la ComCom a décidé de mener avec les acteurs du marché une série de discussions sur ce type de raccordement. Elle souhaitait en premier lieu éviter l’apparition de monopoles, qui entraveraient l’arrivée sur le marché de fournisseurs de services de télécommunication tiers et nuiraient à la concurrence. L’extension des réseaux de fibres optiques doit s’effectuer le plus efficacement possible pour permettre des investissements judicieux sur le plan économique.&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Secrétariat de la ComCom : tél. 031 323 52 90</contact>
      <link id="152458">
        <title>Déploiement de la fibre optique en Suisse</title>
        <uri>https://www.bakom.admin.ch/bakom/fr/page-daccueil/telecommunication/technologie/deploiement-de-la-fibre-optique-en-suisse.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions>
        <revision date="2016-06-10 15:45" type="R"/>
      </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Tavola rotonda sulla fibra ottica: è tempo di bilanci</title>
      <teaser>In occasione dell’ottava tavola rotonda sul tema della fibra ottica, gli attori di mercato hanno discusso degli ultimi sviluppi in materia di ampliamento delle reti di telecomunicazione ad altissima velocità e dell’avanzamento dei progetti di cooperazione.</teaser>
      <lead>In occasione dell’ottava tavola rotonda sul tema della fibra ottica, gli attori di mercato hanno discusso degli ultimi sviluppi in materia di ampliamento delle reti di telecomunicazione ad altissima velocità e dell’avanzamento dei progetti di cooperazione.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;I partecipanti alla tavola rotonda hanno discusso della recente evoluzione del progetto di estensione delle reti fisse e mobili a banda ultra larga (VDSL, TV via cavo, fibra ottica e LTE). Apprezzano la maggiore disponibilità di offerte per i vari fornitori di servizi, in particolare l’ampliamento della rete in fibra ottica in alcune città. L’Ufficio federale delle comunicazioni (UFCOM) ha dal canto suo colto l’occasione per esporre l’orientamento strategico del gruppo di lavoro istituito a inizio luglio, onde allacciare una vasta fetta del territorio elvetico alle moderne reti di telecomunicazione.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; È stato inoltre comunicato che la piattaforma comune per la gestione degli ordini e dei cambiamenti relativi ai clienti ha potuto essere resa operativa nel mese di maggio. I partecipanti sostengono l’impegno costante teso a uno sviluppo comune di questa piattaforma importante per un’evoluzione dinamica del mercato.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Il Direttore della segreteria della COMCO ha infine commentato la valutazione dei contratti di cooperazione tra Swisscom e aziende elettriche, resa pubblica il giorno prima.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; La prossima tavola rotonda si terrà nel gennaio 2012. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Fiber to the Home (FTTH)&lt;br /&gt; &lt;/b&gt;Il termine "Fiber to the Home" (FTTH) designa una rete di telecomunicazione collegata a stabili commerciali, condomini e abitazioni unifamiliari attraverso conduttori a fibre ottiche. La fibra ottica è un mezzo di trasmissione ampiamente collaudato che garantisce un'elevata velocità di trasmissione dei dati. Nei prossimi anni diventerà sempre più importante per lo sviluppo delle reti locali, poiché i vecchi cavi in rame non basteranno per far fronte al crescente bisogno di larghezza di banda determinato dalle nuove applicazioni Internet, segnatamente dalla televisione ad alta definizione. &lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Nell'autunno 2008 la ComCom ha deciso di discutere su questa forma di collegamento insieme agli attori del mercato; con ciò vuole evitare la nascita di monopoli nel settore che ostacolino l'entrata sul mercato di altri operatori di servizi di telecomunicazione e dunque la libera concorrenza. Inoltre, per la costruzione della nuova rete bisognerà procedere nel modo più efficiente possibile, così da permettere investimenti economicamente sensati.&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Segreteria ComCom: tel. 031 323 52 90</contact>
      <link id="152459">
        <title>Ampliamento della fibra ottica in Svizzera</title>
        <uri>https://www.bakom.admin.ch/bakom/it/home/telecomunicazione/tecnologia/ampliamento-della-fibra-ottica-in-svizzera.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions>
        <revision date="2016-06-10 15:45" type="R"/>
      </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Round Table on fibre networks: the participants take stock</title>
      <teaser>At their eighth Round Table on fibre-optic networks, market players exchanged views on how the deployment of telecommunications networks with very high bandwidth is progressing and how cooperation in constructing optical fibre networks is evolving.</teaser>
      <lead>At their eighth Round Table on fibre-optic networks, market players exchanged views on how the deployment of telecommunications networks with very high bandwidth is progressing and how cooperation in constructing optical fibre networks is evolving.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;The participants at the Round Table discussed how the expansion of fixed and mobile networks providing very high bandwidths (VDSL, cable TV, fibre optics and LTE) is progressing. They welcome the progress in relation to the availability of offers for the various service providers, and in particular the deployment of optical fibre networks in some cities. The Federal Office of Communications (OFCOM) outlined the approach being taken by the NGA working group, set up at the beginning of July, in order to provide as many regions as possible in Switzerland with modern telecommunication networks.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Furthermore, the participants noted that in May the operational start-up of the joint platform for customer orders and customer switching in the fibre sector could take place. The participants support the ongoing efforts in relation to the joint development of this platform which is important for dynamic market development.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Finally, the director of the Competition Commission secretariat explained the assessment, published yesterday, of the cooperation agreements between Swisscom and electricity utility companies.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; The next Round Table will take place in January 2012. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fibre to the Home (FTTH)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt; Fibre to the Home (FTTH) describes a telecommunications network which extends via fibre-optic cable into every business, multiple dwelling or family home. Glass-fibre is a well-proven transmission medium for high data rates and will be necessary in the next few years as access networks evolve, because the old copper cables will no longer be adequate to meet the growing demand for high bandwidths for internet applications, especially high-definition television.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; In autumn 2008, The Federal Communications Commission ComCom decided to conduct discussions with market players about this form of development; in this way it wishes to prevent the creation of monopolies which make access more difficult for other telecommunications providers and obstruct competition. At the same time, network construction must take place as efficiently as possible, to allow economically appropriate investment.&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>ComCom secretariat: tel. 031 323 52 90</contact>
      <link id="152460">
        <title>Deployment of optical fibre in Switzerland</title>
        <uri>https://www.bakom.admin.ch/bakom/en/home/telecommunication/technology/deployment-of-optical-fibre-in-switzerland.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions>
        <revision date="2016-06-10 15:45" type="R"/>
      </revisions>
    </content>
    <offers>
      <offer id="120" org-id="815">
        <name lang="de">Medienmitteilungen</name>
        <name lang="fr">Communiqués de presse</name>
        <name lang="it">Comunicati stampa</name>
        <name lang="en">Press releases</name>
      </offer>
    </offers>
    <keywords>
      <keyword id="140" org-id="815">
        <name lang="de">Bundesamt für Kommunikation (BAKOM)</name>
        <name lang="fr">Office fédéral de la communication (OFCOM)</name>
        <name lang="it">Ufficio federale delle comunicazioni (UFCOM)</name>
        <name lang="en">Federal Office of Communications (OFCOM)</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="630" org-id="815">
        <name lang="de">Kommunikationskommission, Eidg. ComCom</name>
        <name lang="fr">Commission fédérale de la communication ComCom</name>
        <name lang="it">Commissione federale delle comunicazioni ComCom</name>
        <name lang="en">Federal Communications Commission ComCom</name>
      </keyword>
    </keywords>
    <topics>
      <topic id="19">
        <name lang="de">Medien</name>
        <name lang="fr">Médias</name>
        <name lang="it">Media</name>
        <name lang="en">Media</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="28">
        <name lang="de">Telekommunikation</name>
        <name lang="fr">Télécommunications</name>
        <name lang="it">Telecomunicazione</name>
        <name lang="en">Telecommunications</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="36">
        <name lang="de">Informatik und E-Government</name>
        <name lang="fr">Informatique et cyberadministration</name>
        <name lang="it">Informatica ed e-government</name>
        <name lang="en">IT and E-Government</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
