<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="41355" revoked="no">
    <version>2</version>
    <pubdate>2011-09-23</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="201" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>201</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="201">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Staatsbesuch der indischen Staatspräsidentin</title>
      <lead>Auf Einladung des Bundesrats wird die indische Staatspräsidentin Pratibha Devisingh Patil der Schweiz am 3. und 4. Oktober 2011 einen Staatsbesuch abstatten. Indien ist einer der wichtigsten Partner der Schweiz in Asien. Die bilateralen und politischen Kontakte entwickeln sich stetig. Der Handelsaustausch nimmt ebenso zu wie die wissenschaftliche Zusammenarbeit.</lead>
      <text link="no">Nach dem ersten Tag in der Bundeshauptstadt wird Bundespräsidentin Micheline Calmy-Rey die indische Staatspräsidentin in den Kanton Waadt führen. Frau Pratibha Devisingh Patil wird von ihrem Ehemann Devisingh Ramsingh Shekhawat begleitet.</text>
      <contact>Information EDA Bundeshaus West CH-3003 Bern Tel.: +41 (0)31 322 31 53 Fax: +41 (0)31 324 90 47 E-Mail: info@eda.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="88709">
        <title>Spezialseite Staatsbesuch Indien</title>
        <uri>http://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home/dfa/head/event/2011/india.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions>
        <revision date="2011-09-23 13:18" type="R"/>
      </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Visite d’Etat de la Présidente de la République de l’Inde</title>
      <lead>A l’invitation du Conseil fédéral, son Excellence Smt. Pratibha Devisingh Patil, Présidente de la République de l’Inde, effectuera une visite d’Etat en Suisse les 3 et 4 octobre 2011. L’Inde est l’un des principaux partenaires de la Suisse en Asie. Les contacts bilatéraux et politiques entre les deux pays se développent constamment. Les échanges économiques augmentent, tout comme la collaboration scientifique.</lead>
      <text link="no">Après la première journée qui se déroulera dans la capitale fédérale, la Présidente de la Confédération, Mme Micheline Calmy-Rey, mènera &amp;nbsp;la Présidente de la République de l’Inde dans le canton de Vaud. Mme Pratibha Devisingh Patil sera accompagnée par son époux Devisingh Ramsingh Shekhawat.</text>
      <contact>Information DFAE Palais fédéral ouest CH-3003 Berne Tél.: (+41) 031 322 31 53 Fax: (+41) 031 324 90 47 E-Mail: info@eda.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="88710">
        <title>Page spéciale visite d'Etat Inde</title>
        <uri>http://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/home/dfa/head/event/2011/india.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Visita di Stato della presidente della Repubblica dell'India</title>
      <lead>Dal 3 al 4 ottobre 2011 la presidente della Repubblica dell'India Pratibha Devisingh Patil effettuerà, su invito del Consiglio federale, una visita di Stato in Svizzera. L'India è uno dei principali partner della Svizzera in Asia. I contatti bilaterali e politici tra i due Paesi sono in costante sviluppo e gli scambi economici come anche la cooperazione in campo scientifico aumentano continuamente.</lead>
      <text link="no">Dopo la prima giornata che si svolgerà nella capitale federale, la presidente della Confederazione Micheline Calmy-Rey e la presidente della Repubblica dell'India si recheranno nel Cantone di Vaud. Pratibha Devisingh Patil sarà accompagnata da suo marito Devisingh Ramsingh Shekhawat.</text>
      <contact>Informazione DFAE Palazzo federale ovest CH-3003 Berna Tel.: (+41) 031 322 31 53 Fax: (+41) 031 324 90 47 E-Mail: info@eda.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="88711">
        <title>Pagina speciale visita di Stato India</title>
        <uri>http://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/home/dfa/head/event/2011/india.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>State visit of the President of the Republic of India</title>
      <lead>At the invitation of the Federal Council, Her Excellency Smt. Pratibha Devisingh Patil, President of the Republic of India, will carry out a state visit to Switzerland on 3 and 4 October 2011. Today India is one of Switzerland’s most important partners in Asia. Bilateral and political contacts are constantly developing, and trade and scientific cooperation between the two countries are flourishing.</lead>
      <text link="no">The President of India will spend the first day of her official visit in the federal capital before travelling on to the canton of Vaud in the company of the President of the Swiss Confederation, Micheline Calmy-Rey. Her Excellency Smt Pratibha Devisingh Patil will be accompanied by her husband, Dr. Devisingh Ramsingh Shekhawat.</text>
      <contact>Information FDFA Bundeshaus West CH-3003 Bern Tel.: (+41) 031 322 31 53 Fax: (+41) 031 324 90 47 E-Mail: info@eda.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="88712">
        <title>Special page to State visit India</title>
        <uri>http://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home/dfa/head/event/2011/india.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
