<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="60848" revoked="no">
    <version>3</version>
    <pubdate>2016-03-03</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="201" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>201</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="201">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Afrika- und Europareise von Bundesrat Didier Burkhalter</title>
      <lead>Bundesrat Didier Burkhalter startet am Montag, 7. März 2016, zu einer dreitägigen Reise, die ihn in vier Länder führt. Am Montag besucht der EDA-Vorsteher Burkina Faso, ein wichtiges Land der Schweizer Entwicklungszusammenarbeit, und am Dienstag Nigeria, das bevölkerungsreichste Land und die grösste Volkswirtschaft Afrikas. Dort eröffnet er in der Wirtschaftsmetropole Lagos das neue Schweizer Konsulat. Am Mittwoch stattet Bundesrat Burkhalter zuerst Malta, dann der Slowakei einen offiziellen Besuch ab. Die beiden Staaten werden ab der zweiten Jahreshälfte nacheinander den halbjährlich wechselnden Vorsitz der Europäischen Union (EU) übernehmen.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Bundesrat Didier Burkhalter trifft am Montagmorgen in Burkina Faso ein. In diesem Schwerpunktland der Schweizer Entwicklungszusammenarbeit ist die Schweiz seit 1974 tätig. Dort trifft er den nach einem Übergangsjahr kürzlich neu gewählten Präsidenten Roch Marc Christian Kaboré sowie Aussenminister Mamadou Alpha Barry. &lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;Anschliessend reist der Vorsteher des Eidgenössischen Departements für auswärtige Angelegenheiten (EDA) in die nigerianische Hauptstadt Abuja weiter, wo er am Dienstag Präsident Muhammadu Buhari und Aussenminister Geoffrey Onyeama trifft. Zu den Gesprächsthemen gehören die Rückerstattung unrechtmässig erworbener Vermögenswerte, die Wirtschaftsbeziehungen sowie die Sicherheit in der Region und das humanitäre Engagement der Schweiz. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mit 180 Millionen Einwohnerinnen und Einwohnern ist Nigeria der bevölkerungsreichste Staat Afrikas und liegt weltweit auf dem siebten Rang. Vor Kurzem ist das Land, dessen Bruttoinlandprodukt 23% desjenigen des ganzen Kontinents ausmacht, zur grössten Volkswirtschaft Afrikas aufgestiegen. Von Abuja reist der Vorsteher des EDA in die Wirtschaftsmetropole Lagos, wo er am Dienstagnachmittag eintrifft. In Lagos eröffnet er das neue Schweizer Generalkonsulat und trifft den Gouverneur von Lagos, Akinwunmi Ambode. Der Auftrag des Konsulats, das als Colocation mit dem dänischen Konsulat geführt wird, besteht hauptsächlich darin, Handel und Investitionen in einem dynamischen und für Schweizer Unternehmen sehr interessanten Wirtschaftsumfeld zu fördern. &lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;Auf der Rückreise am Mittwoch macht Bundesrat Burkhalter in Malta und in der Slowakei Halt. Diese beiden Länder werden demnächst den halbjährlich wechselnden Vorsitz des Rats der EU übernehmen. &lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;In La Valletta besucht der EDA-Vorsteher die von der Schweiz und Malta gemeinsam gegründete Mediterranean Academy of Diplomatic Studies und hält eine Rede vor den Studierenden. Danach trifft er seinen maltesischen Amtskollegen George W. Vella zu einem Gespräch. Auf der Agenda stehen bilaterale Themen, die Beziehungen der Schweiz zur EU, der maltesische Vorsitz im Rat der EU, die Migrationssituation in der Region und verschiedene andere internationale Themen. Malta wird im ersten Halbjahr 2017 den Vorsitz der EU innehaben.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Auch in Bratislava, wo Bundesrat Burkhalter Aussenminister Miroslav Lajčák trifft, stehen die Beziehungen zwischen der Schweiz und der EU im Zentrum der Gespräche. Die Schweiz und die Slowakei pflegen enge diplomatische Beziehungen und arbeiten im Rahmen der internationalen Organisationen zusammen. In den letzten Jahren hat der Handel zwischen den beiden Ländern stark zugenommen. Ein wichtiger Pfeiler der bilateralen Beziehungen ist das Kooperationsprogramm im Rahmen des Schweizer Erweiterungsbeitrags an die EU. Die Slowakei wird den Vorsitz der EU im zweiten Halbjahr 2016 innehaben.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Kommunikation EDA Bundeshaus West CH-3003 Bern Tel. Kommunikationsservice: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Medienstelle: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <link id="148284">
        <title>Bilaterale Beziehungen Schweiz - Burkina Faso</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/countries/burkina-faso/de/home/bilaterale-beziehungen/in-kuerze.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="148285">
        <title>Bilaterale Beziehungen Schweiz - Nigeria</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/countries/nigeria/de/home/bilaterale-beziehungen/in-kuerze.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="148286">
        <title>Bilaterale Beziehungen Schweiz - Malta</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/countries/malta/de/home/bilaterale-beziehungen/in-kuerze.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="148287">
        <title>Bilaterale Beziehungen Schweiz - Slowakei</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/countries/slovakia/de/home/bilaterale-beziehungen/in-kuerze.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions>
        <revision date="2016-03-03 11:21" type="R"/>
        <revision date="2016-03-03 18:17" type="R"/>
      </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Tournée africaine et européenne pour le conseiller fédéral Didier Burkhalter</title>
      <lead>Le conseiller fédéral Didier Burkhalter entamera le lundi 7 mars 2016 une tournée qui le verra visiter quatre pays en trois jours. Tout d’abord en Afrique, le chef du DFAE se rendra lundi au Burkina Faso, pays important pour la coopération suisse au développement, puis mardi au Nigeria, pays le plus peuplé et plus grande économie d’Afrique, où il ouvrira le nouveau consulat de Suisse dans la capitale économique Lagos. M. Burkhalter effectuera ensuite mercredi une visite officielle à Malte, puis en Slovaquie. Ces deux pays assumeront les présidences successives de l’Union européenne (UE) durant les prochains semestres.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;M. Burkhalter arrivera lundi matin au Burkina Faso, un pays prioritaire de la coopération suisse au développement. La Suisse s’engage au Burkina Faso depuis 1974 avec la coopération au développement. Le conseiller fédéral rencontrera le président Roch Marc Christian Kaboré – élu récemment après une année de transition – et le ministre des affaires étrangères Mamadou Alpha Barry. &lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;Le chef du Département fédéral des affaires étrangères (DFAE) se rendra ensuite à Abuja, capitale du Nigeria. Lors de cette étape qui se déroulera mardi, M. Burkhalter s’entretiendra avec le président Muhammadu Buhari et le ministre des affaires étrangères Geoffrey Onyeama. Les thèmes principaux au menu des discussions seront la restitution d’avoirs illicites, les relations économiques, ainsi que la sécurité dans la région et l’engagement humanitaire suisse. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Avec 180 millions d’habitants le Nigéria est le pays le plus peuplé d’Afrique et le 7e au monde. Il est également devenu récemment la plus grande économie d’Afrique, représentant 23% du PIB du continent. Le chef du DFAE se déplacera à Lagos, poumon économique du Nigeria, où il se trouvera mardi après-midi. M.Burkhalter y inaugurera le nouveau consulat général suisse et il rencontrera le gouverneur de Lagos, Akinwunmi Ambode. Ce consulat, sis en colocation avec le consulat du Danemark, aura comme tâche principale la promotion du commerce et des investissements dans une région économiquement très dynamique et intéressante pour les entreprises suisses. &lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;Sur le chemin du retour, M. Burkhalter fera deux escales mercredi, l'une à Malte et l'autre en Slovaquie. Ces deux pays assureront prochainement la présidence tournante du Conseil de l’UE. &lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;A La Vallette, le chef du DFAE visitera la Mediterranean Academy of Diplomatic Studies fondée par la Suisse et Malte où il prononcera un discours devant les étudiants de l’Académie. Ensuite, M.Burkhalter rencontrera son homologue maltais, le ministre des affaires étrangères George W.Vella. Des thèmes bilatéraux, les relations de la Suisse avec l’UE, la présidence maltaise du Conseil de l’UE, la situation migratoire dans la région et divers autres thèmes internationaux figureront au menu de l’entretien. Malte présidera l’UE au premier semestre 2017.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Les relations entre la Suisse et l’UE figureront également au centre des discussions à Bratislava, où M. Burkhalter rencontrera le ministre des affaires étrangères Miroslav Lajčák. La Suisse et la Slovaquie entretiennent d’étroites relations sur le plan diplomatique, collaborent dans le cadre des organisations internationales, et ont vu leurs échanges commerciaux fortement augmenter au cours des dernières années. Un pilier important des relations bilatérales est le programme de coopération dans le cadre de la contribution de la Suisse à l’élargissement de l’UE. La Slovaquie présidera l’UE au second semestre 2016.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Communication DFAE Palais fédéral ouest CH-3003 Berne Tél. Service de communication: +41 58 462 31 53 Tél. Service de presse: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <link id="148288">
        <title>Relations bilatérales Suisse - Burkina Faso</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/countries/burkina-faso/fr/home/relations-bilaterales/bilaterale.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="148289">
        <title>Relations bilatérales Suisse - Nigéria</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/countries/nigeria/fr/home/relations-bilaterales/bilaterale.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="148290">
        <title>Relations bilatérales Suisse - Malte</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/countries/malta/fr/home/relations-bilaterales/bilaterale.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="148291">
        <title>Relations bilatérales Suisse - Slovaquie</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/countries/slovakia/fr/home/relations-bilaterales/bilaterale.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions>
        <revision date="2016-03-03 11:21" type="R"/>
      </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Tournée africana ed europea per il consigliere federale Didier Burkhalter</title>
      <lead>Il consigliere federale Didier Burkhalter inizierà lunedì 7 marzo 2016 una tournée che toccherà quattro Paesi in tre giorni. Il capo del DFAE si recherà dapprima lunedì in Burkina Faso, Stato importante per la cooperazione svizzera allo sviluppo, per poi spostarsi martedì in Nigeria, il Paese più popoloso e principale economia del continente africano, dove inaugurerà il nuovo consolato di Svizzera nella capitale economica Lagos. Il viaggio continuerà mercoledì con una visita ufficiale a Malta e in Slovacchia, i Paesi che assumeranno la presidenza di turno dell’Unione europea (UE) nei prossimi due semestri.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Didier Burkhalter arriverà lunedì mattina in Burkina Faso, Paese prioritario della cooperazione svizzera allo sviluppo, in cui la Svizzera si impegna dal 1974. Il consigliere federale incontrerà il presidente Roch Marc Christian Kaboré, recentemente eletto dopo un anno di transizione, e il ministro degli affari esteri Mamadou Alpha Barry. &lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;Il capo del Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri (DFAE) proseguirà poi martedì verso Abuja, capitale della Nigeria, dove incontrerà il presidente Muhammadu Buhari e il ministro degli affari esteri Geoffrey Onyeama. I temi principali dei colloqui saranno la restituzione di fondi illeciti, le relazioni economiche, la sicurezza nella regione e l’impegno umanitario svizzero. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Con 180 milioni di abitanti, la Nigeria è il Paese più popoloso dell’Africa e il settimo al mondo. Di recente, è inoltre diventata la maggiore economia del continente africano, del quale rappresenta il 23 per cento del PIL. Martedì pomeriggio, Didier Burkhalter si sposterà poi a Lagos, il cuore economico della Nigeria, per l’inaugurazione del nuovo consolato generale svizzero e un incontro con il governatore della città, Akinwunmi Ambode. Il compito principale di questo consolato, in colocalizzazione con il Consolato di Danimarca, sarà la promozione del commercio e degli investimenti in una regione economicamente molto dinamica e interessante per le aziende svizzere. &lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;Sulla via del ritorno, mercoledì il consigliere federale farà scalo a Malta e in Slovacchia, i due Paesi che assumeranno le prossime presidenze di turno del Consiglio dell’UE. &lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;Alla Valletta, il capo del DFAE visiterà la Mediterranean Academy of Diplomatic Studies, fondata dalla Svizzera e da Malta, dove pronuncerà un discorso davanti agli studenti dell’Accademia. In seguito, Didier Burkhalter incontrerà il suo omologo maltese, il ministro degli affari esteri George W. Vella. I colloqui verteranno su temi bilaterali, sulle relazioni tra la Svizzera e l’UE, sulla presidenza maltese del Consiglio dell’UE, sulla situazione migratoria nella regione e su vari altri argomenti internazionali. Malta assumerà la presidenza dell’UE nel primo semestre 2017.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Le relazioni tra la Svizzera e l’UE saranno al centro dell’attenzione anche a Bratislava, dove il consigliere federale Burkhalter incontrerà il ministro degli affari esteri Miroslav Lajčák. La Svizzera e la Slovacchia intrattengono strette relazioni sul piano diplomatico, collaborano nel quadro delle organizzazioni internazionali e hanno aumentato sensibilmente gli scambi commerciali nel corso degli ultimi anni. Un pilastro fondamentale delle relazioni bilaterali è il programma di cooperazione nell’ambito del contributo della Svizzera all’allargamento dell’UE. La Slovacchia presiederà l’UE nel secondo semestre 2016.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Comunicazione DFAE Palazzo federale ovest CH-3003 Berna Tel. Servizio di comunicazione: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Servizio stampa: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <link id="148292">
        <title>Relazioni bilaterali Svizzera - Burkina Faso</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/countries/burkina-faso/it/home/bilaterale-beziehungen/in-kuerze.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="148293">
        <title>Relazioni bilaterali Svizzera - Nigeria</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/countries/nigeria/it/home/bilaterale-beziehungen/in-kuerze.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="148294">
        <title>Relazioni bilaterali Svizzera - Malta</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/countries/malta/it/home/bilaterale-beziehungen/in-kuerze.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="148295">
        <title>Relazioni bilaterali Svizzera - Slovacchia</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/countries/slovakia/it/home/bilaterale-beziehungen/in-kuerze.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions>
        <revision date="2016-03-03 11:21" type="R"/>
        <revision date="2016-03-03 18:17" type="R"/>
      </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Federal Councillor Didier Burkhalter visits countries in Africa and Europe</title>
      <lead>On Monday 7 March, Federal Councillor Didier Burkhalter will set off on a tour during which he will visit four countries in three days. In Africa on Monday the head of the FDFA will visit Burkina Faso, a priority country for Swiss development cooperation. On Tuesday he will arrive in Nigeria, the country in Africa with the largest population and economy, where he will open the new Swiss consulate in the economic capital Lagos. On Wednesday Mr Burkhalter will make an official visit to Malta, before travelling to Slovakia. Slovakia and Malta are the next two countries to assume the six-month presidency of the European Union.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;On Monday morning Mr Burkhalter will arrive in Burkina Faso, a priority country for Swiss development cooperation. Switzerland has been working in development cooperation with Burkina Faso since 1974. Mr Burkhalter will meet President Roch Marc Christian Kaboré, recently elected following a year of transition, and Foreign Minister Mamadou Alpha Barry. &lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;He will then travel to the Nigerian capital, Abuja. On this stage of his journey, which will take place on Tuesday, Mr Burkhalter will meet with President Muhammadu Buhari and Foreign Minister Geoffrey Onyeama. The main topics on the agenda are the restitution of illicit assets, economic relations, security in the region and Switzerland's humanitarian engagement. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;With a population of 180 million, Nigeria is the most populous country in Africa and the 7th most populous in the world. It is also Africa's biggest economy, making up 23% of the continent's GDP. Mr Burkhalter will visit Lagos, Nigeria's economic hub, on Tuesday afternoon. He will inaugurate the new Swiss consulate general and meet the governor of Lagos, Akinwunmi Ambode. The main task of the representation, which shares its premises with the Danish consulate, will be to promote trade and investment in this region whose dynamic economy presents opportunities for Swiss companies. &lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;On his way home on Wednesday, Mr Burkhalter has scheduled stops in Malta and Slovakia, which will assume the next two terms of the EU's rotating presidency. &lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;In La Vallette, he will visit the Mediterranean Academy of Diplomatic Studies, founded by Switzerland and Malta, where he will give a speech to the students. The Swiss foreign minister will then meet his Maltese counterpart, George W. Vella. Bilateral affairs, relations between Switzerland and the EU, the Maltese presidency of the Council of the European Union, the migration situation in the region and various other international topics are on the discussion agenda. Malta will hold the presidency of the EU in the first half of 2017.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Relations between Switzerland and the EU will also be at the centre of the discussions in Bratislava, where Mr Burkhalter will meet Foreign Minister Miroslav Lajčák. Switzerland and Slovakia maintain close diplomatic relations, work together within international organisations and have seen a strong increase in trade in recent years. A cornerstone of their bilateral relations is the cooperation programme as part of Switzerland's contribution to the enlarged EU. Slovakia will hold the presidency of the EU in the second half of 2016.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>FDFA Communication Federal Palace West Wing CH-3003 Bern, Switzerland Tel. Communication service: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Press service: +41 58 460 55 55 E-mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @SwissMFA</contact>
      <link id="148296">
        <title>Bilateral relations Switzerland - Burkina Faso</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/countries/burkina-faso/en/home/bilaterale-beziehungen/in-kuerze.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="148297">
        <title>Bilateral relations Switzerland - Nigeria</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/countries/nigeria/en/home/bilaterale-beziehungen/in-kuerze.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="148298">
        <title>Bilateral relations Switzerland - Malta</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/countries/malta/en/home/bilaterale-beziehungen/in-kuerze.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="148299">
        <title>Bilateral relations Switzerland - Slovakia</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/countries/slovakia/en/home/bilaterale-beziehungen/in-kuerze.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions>
        <revision date="2016-03-03 11:21" type="R"/>
        <revision date="2016-03-03 18:17" type="R"/>
      </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
