<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="61087" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2016-03-23</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="804" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>801</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Generalsekretariat UVEK</name>
      <name lang="fr">Secrétariat général DETEC</name>
      <name lang="it">Segreteria generale DATEC</name>
      <name lang="en">General Secretariat of the Federal Department of Environment, Transport, Energy and Communications; General Secretariat DETEC</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.uvek.admin.ch/uvek/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.uvek.admin.ch/uvek/fr/home.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.uvek.admin.ch/uvek/it/home.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.uvek.admin.ch/uvek/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-uvek.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-uvek.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-uvek.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-uvek.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="801">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Umwelt, Verkehr, Energie und Kommunikation</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'environnement, des transports, de l'énergie et de la communication</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'ambiente, dei trasporti, dell'energia e delle comunicazioni</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of the Environment, Transport, Energy and Communications</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.uvek.admin.ch/uvek/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.uvek.admin.ch/uvek/fr/home.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.uvek.admin.ch/uvek/it/home.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.uvek.admin.ch/uvek/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-uvek.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-uvek.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-uvek.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-uvek.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Offizieller Arbeitsbesuch von Bundesrätin Doris Leuthard in Indonesien</title>
      <lead>In der kommenden Woche, und zwar vom 30. März bis zum 1. April 2016, reist Bundesrätin Doris Leuthard zu einem Arbeitsbesuch nach Indonesien. Im Mittelpunkt der Gespräche stehen die Energie-, die Klima- und die Umweltpolitik. Auch die Verkehrsproblematik wird thematisiert. In Jakarta wird Bundesrätin Leuthard mehrere Mitglieder der indonesischen Regierung sowie den Generalsekretär des Verbands Südostasiatischer Nationen (ASEAN) treffen. </lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Während ihres Besuchs in Jakarta wird die Vorsteherin des Eidgenössischen Departements für Umwelt, Verkehr, Energie und Kommunikation (UVEK) Unterredungen mit mehreren Mitgliedern der indonesischen Regierung führen. Geplant sind Gespräche mit dem für Energie- und Verkehrsthemen zuständigen Koordinierenden Minister Rizal Ramli, mit Umwelt- und Forstwirtschaftsministerin Siti Nurbaya Bakar, mit dem Minister für nationale Entwicklungsplanung Sofyan Djalil und mit Verkehrsminister Ignasius Jonan. Vorgesehen ist auch ein Treffen mit Le Luong Minh, dem Generalsekretär des Verbands Südostasiatischer Nationen (Association of Southeast Asian Nations, ASEAN). Der ASEAN gehören zehn südostasiatische Staaten mit gesamthaft rund 620 Millionen Einwohnerinnen und Einwohnern an. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Auf dem Programm des Besuchs in Indonesien stehen ferner mehrere Besichtigungen. Am indonesischen Institut der Wissenschaften wird Bundesrätin Doris Leuthard eine Ansprache halten. Auch dem Zentrum für Meteorologie, Klima und Geophysik wird sie einen Besuch abstatten. Auf der Agenda von Doris Leuthard stehen ausserdem eine Präsentation von Projekten auf dem Gebiet der erneuerbaren Energien, die Besichtigung einer Fabrik des ABB-Konzerns und ein Besuch bei der nationalen Fluggesellschaft Garuda. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Die UVEK-Vorsteherin wird von einer Wirtschaftsdelegation aus Vertretern der Cleantech- und der Transportbranche begleitet. &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Dominique Bugnon, Chef des Presse- und Informationsdienstes, GS-UVEK, Tel. +41 58 464 71 60</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>La conseillère fédérale Doris Leuthard en visite officielle de travail en Indonésie</title>
      <lead>La conseillère fédérale Doris Leuthard se rendra la semaine prochaine – du 30 mars au 1er avril 2016 – en Indonésie pour des entretiens de travail consacrés pour l’essentiel à la politique énergétique, climatique et environnementale. La problématique des transports est également à l’agenda de ce déplacement. A Jakarta, plusieurs rencontres sont prévues avec des ministres du gouvernement indonésien ainsi qu’avec le Secrétaire général de l’Association des nations de l’Asie du Sud-Est – ASEAN.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;A Jakarta, Doris Leuthard, cheffe du Département fédéral de l’environnement, des transports, de l’énergie et de la communication DETEC aura l’occasion de s’entretenir avec plusieurs membres du gouvernement indonésien, à savoir Rizal Ramli, ministre responsable de la coordination, notamment dans les domaines de l’énergie et des transports, Siti Nurbaya Bakar, ministre de l’environnement et des forêts, Sofyan Djalil, ministre d’Etat à la planification du développement national et Ignasius Jonan, ministre des transports. Lors de son séjour à Jakarta, la vice-présidente du Conseil fédéral aura également l’opportunité de s’entretenir avec Le Luong Minh, secrétaire général de l’Association des nations de l’Asie du Sud-Est – ASEAN. Cette association regroupe 10 pays d’Asie du Sud-Est, représentant 620 millions d’habitants. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Plusieurs visites sont également au programme de ce déplacement en Indonésie. La conseillère fédérale Doris Leuthard aura l’occasion de tenir un discours devant l’Institut indonésien des Sciences. Elle se rendra également au Centre de Météorologie, du Climat et de la Géophysique. Une présentation de projets en matière d’énergie renouvelable ainsi que la visite d’une usine du groupe ABB et de la compagnie aérienne nationale Garuda figurent aussi à l’agenda de Doris Leuthard.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;La cheffe du DETEC sera accompagnée par une délégation issue de l’économie (cleantech et transports).&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Dominique Bugnon, Chef de l’information du DETEC, tél. +41 58 464 71 60</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>La Consigliera federale in visita di lavoro ufficiale in Indonesia</title>
      <lead>La prossima settimana, dal 30 marzo al 1° aprile 2016, la Consigliera federale Doris Leuthard si recherà in Indonesia per alcuni colloqui di lavoro incentrati sulla politica energetica, climatica e ambientale. Anche i trasporti saranno all'ordine del giorno degli incontri. A Giacarta Doris Leuthard incontrerà alcuni Ministri del Governo indonesiano e il Segretario generale dell'Associazione delle Nazioni del Sud-Est Asiatico ANSEA.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;A Giacarta, il Capo del Dipartimento federale dell'ambiente, dei trasporti, dell'energia e delle comunicazioni (DATEC) avrà l'occasione di discutere con diversi membri del Governo indonesiano, tra cui Rizal Ramli, Ministro responsabile del coordinamento, in particolare nei settori energia e trasporti, Siti Nurbaya Bakar, Ministro dell'ambiente e delle foreste, Sofyan Djalil, Ministro di Stato per la pianificazione dello sviluppo nazionale e Ignasius Jonan, Ministro dei trasporti. Durante il suo soggiorno a Giacarta, la Vicepreseidente del Consiglio federale avrà anche l'opportunità di incontrare Le Luong Minh, Segretario generale dell'Associazione delle Nazioni del Sud-Est Asiatico ANSEA, che raggruppa 10 Paesi cmprendenti 620 milioni di abitanti. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Diverse visite sono previste durante il soggiorno in Indonesia. Doris Leuthard terrà un discorso all'Istituto delle scienze indonesiano. Si recherà inoltre al Centro di meteorologia, del clima e di geofisica. L'agenda degli incontri prevede anche una presentazione di progetti in materia di energie rinnovabili come pure la visita di una fabbrica del gruppo ABB e della compagnia aerea nazionale Garuda. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Il Capo del DATEC sarà accompagnato da una delegazione economica (cleantech e trasporti).&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Dominique Bugnon, Capo dell'informazione del DATEC, tel. +41 58 464 71 60</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Federal Councillor Doris Leuthard to pay an official working visit to Indonesia</title>
      <lead>Federal Councillor Doris Leuthard is to pay a working visit to Indonesia next week (from 30 March to 1 April) for talks focusing on energy, climate and environment policy. Issues relating to transport will also be on the agenda. Several meetings with Indonesian government ministers have been arranged in Jakarta, and Federal Councillor Leuthard will also be holding talks with the Secretary-General of the Association of Southeast Asian Nations (ASEAN).</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;During her visit to Jakarta, the head of the Federal Department of the Environment, Transport, Energy and Communications, Federal Councillor Doris Leuthard, will have an opportunity to hold talks with several representatives of the Indonesian government, namely Rizal Ramli, Minister responsible for coordination in the areas of energy and transport; Siti Nurbaya Bakar, Minister of the Environment and Forests; Sofyan Djalil, Minister of State for National Planning and Development; and Ignasius Jonan, Transport Minister. Federal Councillor Doris Leuthard will also have an opportunity to meet with Le Luong Minh, Secretary-General of the Association of Southeast Asian Nations (ASEAN), which represents a group of ten Southeast Asian countries with a total population of 620 million. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Several other events have been arranged during this trip to Indonesia by Federal Councillor Doris Leuthard, including a speech to be given at the Indonesian Institute of Sciences. She will also be visiting the Centre for Meteorology, Climate and Geophysics. Other items on her agenda include a presentation of projects relating to renewable energy, a visit to the factory of the ABB Group and a visit to Indonesia’s national airline, Garuda. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The head of DETEC will be accompanied on this visit to Indonesia by a business delegation from the cleantech and transport sectors.&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Dominique Bugnon, head of DETEC Information Service. Phone +41 58 464 71 60</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <keywords>
      <keyword id="310" org-id="804">
        <name lang="de">Energiepolitik</name>
        <name lang="fr">Energiepolitik</name>
        <name lang="it">Energiepolitik</name>
        <name lang="en">Energiepolitik</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="121212" org-id="804">
        <name lang="de">Doris Leuthard</name>
        <name lang="fr">Doris Leuthard</name>
        <name lang="it">Doris Leuthard</name>
        <name lang="en">Doris Leuthard</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="300" org-id="804">
        <name lang="de">Energieffizienz</name>
        <name lang="fr">Efficacité énergétique</name>
        <name lang="it">Efficienza energetica</name>
        <name lang="en">Energy Efficiency</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="1610" org-id="804">
        <name lang="de">Grüne Wirtschaft</name>
        <name lang="fr">Économie verte</name>
        <name lang="it">Economia verde</name>
        <name lang="en">Grüne Wirtschaft</name>
      </keyword>
    </keywords>
    <topics>
      <topic id="11">
        <name lang="de">Energie</name>
        <name lang="fr">Énergie</name>
        <name lang="it">Energia</name>
        <name lang="en">Energy</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
