<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="61034" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2016-03-17</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="408" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>408</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Bundesanwaltschaft</name>
      <name lang="fr">Ministère public de la Confédération</name>
      <name lang="it">Ministero pubblico della Confederazione</name>
      <name lang="en">Office of the Attorney General of Switzerland</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.ba.admin.ch/ba/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.ba.admin.ch/ba/fr/home.html</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.ba.admin.ch/ba/it/home.html</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.ba.admin.ch/</www>
      <email lang="de">info@ba.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@ba.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@ba.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@ba.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="408">
      <name lang="de">Bundesanwaltschaft</name>
      <name lang="fr">Ministère public de la Confédération</name>
      <name lang="it">Ministero pubblico della Confederazione</name>
      <name lang="en">Office of the Attorney General of Switzerland</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.ba.admin.ch/ba/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.ba.admin.ch/ba/fr/home.html</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.ba.admin.ch/ba/it/home.html</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.ba.admin.ch/</www>
      <email lang="de">info@ba.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@ba.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@ba.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@ba.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Verfahrenskomplex Petrobras: Weitere Deblockierung von rund 70 Millionen US-Dollar zu Gunsten von Brasilien</title>
      <lead>Die Bundesanwaltschaft (BA) sieht im Rahmen des Verfahrenskomplexes Petrobras eine weitere Deblockierung von circa 70 Millionen US-Dollar zu Gunsten von Brasilien vor. Anlässlich eines Treffens heute in Bern besprachen der brasilianische Generalstaatsanwalt Rodrigo Janot und Bundesanwalt Michael Lauber die Zusammenarbeit der beiden Generalstaatsanwaltschaften rund um den Verfahrenskomplex Petrobras.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Im Rahmen des heutigen Treffens zwischen dem brasilianischen Generalstaatsanwalt Rodrigo Janot und Bundesanwalt Michael Lauber wurde das Vorgehen betreffend der geplanten Deblockierung von weiteren rund 70 Millionen US-Dollar zu Gunsten von Geschädigten in Brasilien besprochen. Diskutiert wurde auch die Schaffung einer gemeinsamen Ermittlungsgruppe (Joint Investigation Team, JIT), mit dem Ziel, die Verfahrensführung der beiden involvierten Strafverfolgungsbehörden beschleunigen zu können. Die Generalstaatsanwälte bekräftigten anlässlich des Treffens ihren Willen, die gute Zusammenarbeit zwischen den beiden Behörden weiterzuführen und insofern zu intensivieren.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Schweizer Strafverfahren&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;/b&gt;Der BA wurden bisher von der Meldestelle für Geldwäscherei (MROS) rund 340 verdächtige Bankbeziehungen im Zusammenhang mit der internationalen Korruptionsaffäre rund um das brasilianische (halb-) staatliche Unternehmen Petrobras gemeldet. Gestützt darauf hat die BA seit April 2014 rund 60 Strafuntersuchungen eröffnet wegen Verdachts der qualifizierten Geldwäscherei (Art. 305bis Ziff. 2 StGB), und in zahlreichen Fällen wegen Verdachts der Bestechung fremder Amtsträger (Art. 322septies StGB). In diesem Zusammenhang forderte die BA die Herausgabe von Unterlagen betreffend insgesamt über 1‘000 Kontoverbindungen bei über 40 Bankinstituten ein. Angesichts des Ausmasses der zu führenden Untersuchungen werden diese von einer Task Force – bestehend aus verschiedenen Fachleuten der BA – und mit Unterstützung von fedpol geführt. Die Weiterführung von zwei von der BA eröffneten Strafuntersuchungen wurde von Brasilien übernommen und hat in Brasilien bereits zu Anklagen geführt. Die BA hat die Absicht, bei den brasilianischen Strafverfolgungsbehörden die Weiterführung von weiteren in der Schweiz eröffneten Strafuntersuchungen zu beantragen.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Im Rahmen dieser rund 60 Strafuntersuchungen wurden in der Schweiz Vermögenswerte in der Höhe von rund 800 Millionen US-Dollar gesperrt. Davon wurden im Einverständnis der Kontoinhaber bereits im Frühling 2015 120 Millionen US-Dollar freigegeben und deren Überweisung zuhanden der Geschädigten veranlasst. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Wirtschaftlich berechtigt an diesen grösstenteils auf Sitzgesellschaften lautenden Kontobeziehungen in der Schweiz sind Kadermitglieder von Petrobras, Kadermitglieder von Zulieferfirmen, Finanzintermediäre, brasilianische Politiker sowie direkt oder indirekt brasilianische oder andere ausländische Unternehmen.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="nsbtextkasten"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Foto&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Bildlegende: Treffen des Bundesanwalts Michael Lauber mit dem Generalstaatsanwalt Brasiliens Rodrigo Janot vom 17. März 2016 in Bern&lt;br /&gt;Foto: Bundesanwaltschaft&lt;br /&gt;Bildrechte: Bundesanwaltschaft&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>André Marty, Informationschef Bundesanwaltschaft; +41 58 464 32 40; info@ba.admin.ch</contact>
      <attachment id="148912">
        <title>Photo: Swiss Attorney General Michael Lauber meets the Brazilian Attorney General Rodrigo Janot in Bern</title>
        <format>jpg</format>
        <size-kb>2375</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/43384.jpg</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="148913">
        <title>Photo: Swiss Attorney General Michael Lauber meets the Brazilian Attorney General Rodrigo Janot in Bern</title>
        <format>gif</format>
        <size-kb>84</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/43385.gif</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </attachment>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Affaire Petrobras: nouvelle libération d’environ 70 millions USD en faveur du Brésil</title>
      <lead>Dans le cadre du complexe d’enquêtes Petrobras, le Ministère public de la Confédération (MPC) va débloquer à nouveau environ 70 millions USD en faveur du Brésil. Lors d’une rencontre aujourd’hui à Berne, le Procureur général du Brésil Rodrigo Janot et le Procureur général de la Confédération Michael Lauber ont discuté de la collaboration entre leurs deux parquets en relation avec le complexe d’enquêtes Petrobras. </lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;b&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;p&gt;Dans le cadre de la rencontre d’aujourd’hui entre le Procureur général du Brésil Rodrigo Janot et le Procureur général de la Confédération Michael Lauber, la manière de procéder pour débloquer, comme envisagé, 70 millions de USD supplémentaires au profit des lésés au Brésil a été discutée. L’échange a également porté sur la création d’un groupe commun d’enquête (Joint Investigation Team, JIT) dans le but d’accélérer la conduite des procédures menées par les deux autorités de poursuite pénale impliquées. A l’occasion de cette rencontre, les procureurs généraux ont réaffirmé leur volonté de poursuivre, respectivement d’intensifier la bonne collaboration qui s’est instaurée entre les deux autorités. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Enquêtes pénales en Suisse &lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A ce jour, le Bureau de communication en matière de blanchiment d’argent (MROS) a annoncé au MPC environ 340 relations bancaires qui faisaient l’objet d’un soupçon dans le contexte du scandale de corruption internationale lié à l’entreprise brésilienne (semi-) étatique Petrobras. Sur cette base, le MPC a ouvert depuis avril 2014 environ 60 enquêtes pénales pour soupçon de blanchiment d’argent aggravé (art. 305bis ch. 2 CP) et dans un grand nombre de cas pour soupçon de corruption d’agents publics étrangers (art. 322septies CP). Dans ce contexte, le MPC a ordonné l’édition de documents concernant au total plus de 1'000 comptes auprès de plus de 40 établissements bancaires. Compte tenu de l’ampleur des investigations devant être menées, une task force menée par des spécialistes du MPC ̶ avec le soutien de fedpol, a été constituée. Le Brésil a accepté la reprise de deux procédures qui avaient été ouvertes par le MPC et qui ont déjà abouti à des mises en accusation dans ce pays. Le MPC a l’intention de solliciter des autorités de poursuite pénale brésiliennes la reprise d’autres enquêtes pénales ouvertes en Suisse.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Dans le cadre des plus de 60 enquêtes pénales ouvertes, des valeurs patrimoniales à hauteur d’environ 800 millions USD ont été bloquées. De ce montant et en accord avec les titulaires des comptes, au printemps 2015 déjà, 120 millions USD ont été libérés et transférés en faveur des lésés.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Les ayants droit économiques de ces relations bancaires établies pour la plupart par des sociétés de domicile en Suisse sont des cadres de Petrobras, des cadres de sociétés de fournisseurs, des intermédiaires financiers, des politiciens brésiliens ainsi que, directement ou indirectement, des entreprises brésiliennes ou étrangères. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class="nsbtextkasten"&gt;Photo&lt;br /&gt;Légende: Rencontre du Procureur général de la Confédération Michael Lauber avec le Procureur général du Brésil Rodrigo Janot du 17 mars 2016 à Berne&lt;br /&gt;Photo: Ministère public de la Confédération&lt;br /&gt;Droits d’image: Ministère public de la Confédération&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>André Marty, Chef de l‘information du Ministère public de la Confédération; +41 58 464 32 40; info@ba.admin.ch</contact>
      <attachment id="148912">
        <title>Photo: Swiss Attorney General Michael Lauber meets the Brazilian Attorney General Rodrigo Janot in Bern</title>
        <format>jpg</format>
        <size-kb>2375</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/43384.jpg</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="148913">
        <title>Photo: Swiss Attorney General Michael Lauber meets the Brazilian Attorney General Rodrigo Janot in Bern</title>
        <format>gif</format>
        <size-kb>84</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/43385.gif</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </attachment>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Vicenda Petrobras: sblocco di un ulteriore importo di circa 70 milioni di USD a favore del Brasile</title>
      <lead>Nell’ambito della vicenda Petrobras il Ministero pubblico della Confederazione (MPC) prospetta lo sblocco di un ulteriore importo di circa 70 milioni di USD a favore del Brasile. In occasione di un incontro tenutosi oggi a Berna, il procuratore generale brasiliano Rodrigo Janot e il procuratore generale della Confederazione Michael Lauber hanno discusso della collaborazione tra le due procure generali nel complesso di casi collegati a questa vicenda.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Nell’ambito dell’incontro odierno, il procuratore generale brasiliano Rodrigo Janot e il procuratore generale della Confederazione Michael Lauber hanno discusso dell’ulteriore procedere per il previsto sblocco di un ulteriore importo di circa 70 milioni di USD a favore dei danneggiati in Brasile. Per accelerare la conduzione dei procedimenti da parte delle autorità di perseguimento penale coinvolte, si è anche discusso della costituzione di un organo investigativo comune (Joint Investigation Team, JIT). Durante l’incontro i procuratori generali hanno ribadito la loro volontà di portare avanti la positiva collaborazione instauratasi tra le due autorità in questa vicenda e di intensificarla ulteriormente.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Procedimenti penali in Svizzera &lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; &lt;/b&gt;Ad oggi L’Ufficio di comunicazione in materia di riciclaggio di denaro (MROS) ha segnalato all’MPC circa 340 relazioni bancarie sospette in rapporto con il caso di corruzione internazionale che ha coinvolto la società (para)statale brasiliana Petrobras. Sulla base di queste segnalazioni, dal mese di aprile 2014 l’MPC ha avviato una sessantina di inchieste penali per sospetto riciclaggio aggravato di denaro (art. 305bis n. 2 CP) e in numerosi casi per sospetta corruzione di pubblici ufficiali stranieri (art. 322septies CP). In tale contesto, ha ordinato la produzione in giudizio di documenti riguardanti complessivamente un migliaio di conti presso oltre 40 istituti bancari. Date le proporzioni della vicenda, le necessarie inchieste sono condotte da una task force formata da diversi specialisti del MPC, con l’appoggio di fedpol. Le autorità brasiliane hanno assunto il perseguimento di due inchieste avviate dall’MPC, già sfociate nella formulazione di atti d’accusa. L’MPC intende chiedere alle autorità di perseguimento brasiliane di assumere altre inchieste penale avviate in Svizzera.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;In Svizzera, la sessantina di inchieste avviate dall’MPC ha portato al sequestro di un importo complessivo di circa 800 milioni di USD, di cui 120 milioni di USD già dissequestrati di comune accordo con i titolari dei conti nella primavera del 2015 e trasferiti in Brasile a favore dei danneggiati. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Tra gli aventi economicamente diritto delle relazioni bancarie in Svizzera interessate dalla vicenda, intestate per la maggior parte a società di sede, vi sono dirigenti di Petrobras, dirigenti di imprese fornitrici, intermediari finanziari, esponenti politici brasiliani e direttamente o indirettamente imprese brasiliane o altre imprese estere.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="nsbtextkasten"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;fotografia&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;br /&gt;Didascalia: incontro a Berna del 17 marzo 2016 tra il procuratore generale della Confederazione Michael Lauber e il suo omonimo brasiliano Rodrigo Janot &lt;br /&gt;Fotografia: Ministero pubblico della Confederazione&lt;br /&gt;Diritti sulle immagini: Ministero pubblico della Confederazione &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>André Marty, capo Informazione del Ministero pubblico della Confederazione; +41 58 464 32 40; info@ba.admin.ch</contact>
      <attachment id="148912">
        <title>Photo: Swiss Attorney General Michael Lauber meets the Brazilian Attorney General Rodrigo Janot in Bern</title>
        <format>jpg</format>
        <size-kb>2375</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/43384.jpg</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="148913">
        <title>Photo: Swiss Attorney General Michael Lauber meets the Brazilian Attorney General Rodrigo Janot in Bern</title>
        <format>gif</format>
        <size-kb>84</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/43385.gif</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </attachment>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Petrobras affair: Further USD 70 million of frozen assets to be unblocked and returned to Brazil</title>
      <lead>The Office of the Attorney General of Switzerland (OAG) is planning to unblock a further USD 70 million of assets and have them returned to Brazil as part of the Petrobras affair. The Brazilian Attorney General Rodrigo Janot and his Swiss counterpart Michael Lauber met today in Bern to discuss cooperation between their respective offices in connection with the Petrobras proceedings.</lead>
      <text link="no">At today’s meeting between the Brazilian Attorney General Rodrigo Janot and the Attorney General of Switzerland Michael Lauber, the action required to unblock a further USD 70 million and return it to the parties who have incurred related losses in Brazil was discussed. Talks also focused on creating a Joint Investigation Team (JIT) with the aim of speeding up the proceedings being conducted by the two prosecution authorities. The two attorneys general expressed satisfaction with their cooperation so far and confirmed their commitment to working even more closely together as the case progresses. &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Swiss criminal proceedings&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;So far the OAG has received reports of around 340 suspicious banking relations from the Money Laundering Reporting Office (MROS) in relation to the international corruption affair involving the semi-state-owned Brazilian company Petrobras. In response, the OAG has since April 2014 opened some 60 investigations on suspicion of aggravated money laundering (Art. 305bis Sec. 2 Swiss Criminal Code (SCC)) and in numerous cases on suspicion of bribery of foreign public officials (Art. 322septies SCC). The OAG has requested the handover of documents relating to over 1,000 banking accounts from over 40 banking institutions. In view of the complexity of the investigations, a task force made up of various specialists from the OAG and supported by fedpol is conducting the proceedings. Two of the investigations opened by the OAG have been taken over by the Brazilian authorities and have already led to charges in Brazil. The OAG plans to request the Brazilian authorities to take over other investigations that have been opened in Switzerland.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;In the course of these 60 investigations, around USD 800 million of assets held in Switzerland have been frozen. In spring 2015, USD 120 million of these assets were unblocked with the consent of the account holders concerned and arrangements made for the assets to be returned to the parties who have incurred related losses. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The beneficial owners of the Swiss accounts, for the most part ostensibly held by domiciliary companies, are senior executives of Petrobras and of its suppliers, financial intermediaries, Brazilian politicians and directly or indirectly Brazilian or other foreign companies.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="nsbtextkasten"&gt;photograph&lt;br /&gt;Caption: Swiss Attorney General Michael Lauber meets the Brazilian Attorney General Rodrigo Janot on 17 March 2016 in Bern&lt;br /&gt;Photograph: Office of the Attorney General of Switzerland&lt;br /&gt;Copyright: Office of the Attorney General of Switzerland &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>André Marty, Head of Information, Office of the Attorney General of Switzerland; +41 58 464 32 40; info@ba.admin.ch</contact>
      <attachment id="148912">
        <title>Photo: Swiss Attorney General Michael Lauber meets the Brazilian Attorney General Rodrigo Janot in Bern</title>
        <format>jpg</format>
        <size-kb>2375</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/43384.jpg</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="148913">
        <title>Photo: Swiss Attorney General Michael Lauber meets the Brazilian Attorney General Rodrigo Janot in Bern</title>
        <format>gif</format>
        <size-kb>84</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/43385.gif</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </attachment>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="17">
        <name lang="de">Kriminalität</name>
        <name lang="fr">Criminalité</name>
        <name lang="it">Criminalità</name>
        <name lang="en">Criminality</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
