<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="60189" revoked="no">
    <version>2</version>
    <pubdate>2016-01-05</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="810" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>801</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Bundesamt für Kommunikation</name>
      <name lang="fr">Office fédéral de la communication</name>
      <name lang="it">Ufficio federale delle comunicazioni</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Office of Communications</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.bakom.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.ofcom.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.ufcom.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.ofcom.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">media@bakom.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">media@bakom.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">media@bakom.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">media@bakom.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="801">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Umwelt, Verkehr, Energie und Kommunikation</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'environnement, des transports, de l'énergie et de la communication</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'ambiente, dei trasporti, dell'energia e delle comunicazioni</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of the Environment, Transport, Energy and Communications</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.uvek.admin.ch/uvek/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.uvek.admin.ch/uvek/fr/home.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.uvek.admin.ch/uvek/it/home.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.uvek.admin.ch/uvek/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-uvek.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-uvek.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-uvek.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-uvek.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Biel/Bienne</city>
      <title>Allgemeine Öffnung der .swiss-Internetadressen</title>
      <lead>Am 11. Januar beginnt die zweite Registrierungsphase für .swiss-Internetadressen. Damit wird die Palette der möglichen Domainnamen vergrössert und der Kreis der potenziellen Kandidaturen erweitert. Ausserdem können Dachorganisationen oder Branchenvertretungen eine Bewerbung für eine generische Adresse wie hotel.swiss oder watch.swiss einreichen, die der gesamten Branche zur Verfügung gestellt wird. In der ersten Phase wurden bereits rund 7000 .swiss-Domainnamen zugeteilt. </lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Am 11. Januar 2016 öffnet sich die Internetdomain .swiss für zahlreiche neue Internetadressen und ist nicht mehr auf Firmennamen und eingetragene Marken beschränkt. Neu können also auch Gesuche für Produktnamen, Slogans, geografische Bezeichnungen oder Fantasienamen gestellt werden. Die Gesuchstellenden müssen weiterhin einen Geschäftssitz und einen physischen Verwaltungssitz in der Schweiz sowie einen klaren Bezug zur beantragten Internetadresse aufweisen. Die in der ersten Phase noch ausgeschlossenen Vereine und Stiftungen ohne Eintrag im Handelsregister können nun ebenfalls einen .swiss-Domainnamen beantragen. Die Öffnung gilt jedoch nicht für Privatpersonen.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Erfüllen die neuen Gesuche die Grundvoraussetzungen, werden sie einmal pro Woche für 20 Tage auf der Website www.nic.swiss veröffentlicht, damit allfällige Kommentare angebracht oder Konkurrenzgesuche eingereicht werden können. Nicht in Frage gestellte Domainnamen werden nach Ablauf dieser Frist zugeteilt. Bei Streitigkeiten entscheidet das BAKOM auf Grundlage der Bestimmungen der Verordnung über Internet-Domains (VID). Priorität haben die öffentlich-rechtlichen Körperschaften gefolgt von Einheiten, die über ein mit der beantragten Bezeichnung verbundenes Recht verfügen. Bei Bewerbungen, die in allen Punkten gleich gestellt sind, kann die Zuteilung per Versteigerung, Losentscheid oder aufgrund der Beurteilung des grösseren Mehrwertes für die Schweizer Gemeinschaft erfolgen.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Generische Adressen&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ab dem 11. Januar können ausserdem generische Adressen, die eine ganze Branche betreffen, beantragt werden. Für ein sogenanntes Namenszuteilungsmandat kann ein Dachverband oder eine Vertretung eines Berufsstandes oder Tätigkeitssektors beim BAKOM eine Bewerbung für einen generischen Domainnamen wie hotel.swiss oder watch.swiss einreichen. Die Bewerbenden müssen die Adresse anschliessend in den Dienst der gesamten betroffenen Gemeinschaft stellen.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Das BAKOM wird sämtliche Bewerbungen für generische Domainnamen einzeln prüfen. Pro Dossier werden eine einmalige Gebühr von 2'900 Franken sowie eine jährliche Gebühr von 360 Franken für die Aufsichtstätigkeiten erhoben. Diese beiden Gebühren sind Teil der Gesamtrechnung, die die Bewerberinnen und Bewerber von ihrem Registrar erhalten.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Bereits 7'000 .swiss-Adressen zugeteilt&lt;/h2&gt;Während der ersten Registrierungsphase, die am 9. November 2015 zu Ende gegangen ist, wurden 9'738 .swiss-Domainnamen beantragt. Nach Ablauf der Veröffentlichungsfrist wurden bereits rund 7'000 Adressen zugeteilt.</text>
      <contact>Bundesamt für Kommunikation BAKOM Medienstelle, +41 58 460 55 50, media@bakom.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="146281">
        <title>Website der Registerbetreiberin www.nic.swiss</title>
        <uri>http://dotswiss.net</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="146285">
        <title>Informationsportal zur .swiss-Domain</title>
        <uri>http://dotswiss.ch</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="146289">
        <title>Verordnung über Internet-Domains (VID)</title>
        <uri>https://www.admin.ch/opc/de/classified-compilation/20141744/index.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions>
        <revision date="2016-01-05 10:16" type="R"/>
      </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Biel/Bienne</city>
      <title>Adresses internet .swiss: ouverture généralisée</title>
      <lead>Le lancement le 11 janvier de la deuxième phase d'enregistrement des adresses internet .swiss élargit l'éventail de noms de domaine possibles ainsi que le cercle des candidats potentiels. Elle ouvre aussi la possibilité pour les organisations faîtières ou représentants de branches de présenter un dossier pour obtenir une adresse générique, comme hotel.swiss ou watch.swiss, mise ensuite à disposition de toute la branche. La première phase a déjà permis d'attribuer quelques 7'000 adresses internet .swiss.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;A partir du 11 janvier 2016, le domaine internet .swiss s'ouvre à de nombreuses nouvelles adresses et n'est plus limité aux raisons sociales et aux marques déposées. Ainsi un requérant pourra déposer des demandes pour des noms de produits, des slogans, des désignations géographiques ou encore des dénominations fantaisistes. Il devra toujours disposer d'un siège social et d'un réel site administratif en Suisse, ainsi que d'un lien clair avec l'adresse internet demandée. Alors qu'elles étaient exclues de la première phase, les associations et fondations qui ne sont pas inscrites au registre du commerce pourront aussi briguer une adresse .swiss. L'ouverture ne concerne toutefois pas les personnes privées.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Pour autant qu'elles remplissent les conditions de base, les nouvelles demandes seront publiées sur le site www.nic.swiss une fois par semaine pour une période de 20 jours afin de permettre le dépôt de commentaires ou de requêtes concurrentes. S'ils ne font pas l'objet de contestations, les noms de domaine seront attribués à l'issue de ce délai. Dans le cas contraire, l'OFCOM arbitrera les litiges sur la base des règles de l'Ordonnance sur les domaines Internet. La priorité sera notamment accordée aux collectivités publiques puis aux entités qui disposent d'un droit lié à la désignation demandée. Selon les cas, des enchères, un tirage au sort ou l'évaluation de la meilleure plus-value apportée à la communauté suisse pourront départager les candidatures en tous points équivalentes. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Adresses génériques &lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Le 11 janvier marque aussi l'ouverture des candidatures pour des adresses génériques qui concernent toute une branche. La procédure dite de mandat de nommage permet à une association faîtière, à une entité qui représente un corps de métier ou un secteur d'activités de déposer un dossier à l'OFCOM pour un nom de domaine comme par exemple hotel.swiss ou watch.swiss. Le requérant devra ensuite mettre ces adresses au service de l'ensemble de la communauté qu'il représente. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;L'OFCOM traitera individuellement chaque candidature pour un nom de domaine générique. Il percevra un émolument unique de 2'900 francs par dossier ainsi que 360 francs par année pour ses activités de surveillance. Le requérant paiera ces montants dans la facture globale que lui adressera son registraire.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;7'000 adresses .swiss déjà attribuées&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Lors de la phase de lancement qui s'est terminée le 9 novembre 2015, 9'738 noms de domaine .swiss ont été demandés. A l'issue de la période de publication des candidatures, quelques 7'000 adresses .swiss ont déjà été attribuées.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Office fédéral de la communication OFCOM Service de presse, +41 58 460 55 50, media@bakom.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="146282">
        <title>Site du registre www.nic.swiss</title>
        <uri>http://www.dotswiss.net</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="146286">
        <title>Portail d'information sur le nouveau domaine .swiss</title>
        <uri>http://dotswiss.ch</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="146290">
        <title>Ordonnance sur les domaines Internet (ODI)</title>
        <uri>https://www.admin.ch/opc/fr/classified-compilation/20141744/index.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Biel/Bienne</city>
      <title>Indirizzi .swiss: apertura generale</title>
      <lead>L'avvio, l'11 gennaio, della seconda fase di registrazione degli indirizzi Internet .swiss amplia il ventaglio dei nomi di dominio possibili e la cerchia dei potenziali candidati. Apre anche la possibilità, per le associazioni di categoria o i rappresentanti dei settori, di presentare un dossier per ottenere un indirizzo generico, come hotel.swiss o watch.swiss, da mettere poi a disposizione di tutto il settore. La prima fase ha già permesso di attribuire circa 7000 indirizzi Internet .swiss.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Dall'11 gennaio 2016, il dominio Internet .swiss si apre a numerosi nuovi indirizzi e non è più limitato alle ragioni sociali e ai marchi depositati. I richiedenti potranno dunque presentare domande per nomi di prodotti, slogan, denominazioni geografiche o denominazioni di fantasia. Dovranno sempre avere una sede sociale e un centro amministrativo effettivo in Svizzera e dimostrare l'esistenza di un legame chiaro con l'indirizzo Internet richiesto. Le associazioni e le fondazioni non iscritte nel registro di commercio, escluse dalla prima fase, potranno d'ora in poi candidarsi anch'esse per un indirizzo .swiss. L'apertura non riguarda però privati. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Se soddisfano le condizioni di base, le nuove domande saranno pubblicate sul sito www.nic.swiss una volta a settimana per un periodo di 20 giorni allo scopo di permettere la presentazione di commenti o richieste concorrenti. Se non sono oggetto di contestazioni, i nomi di dominio saranno attribuiti alla scadenza di tale periodo. In caso contrario, l'UFCOM comporrà le controversie in base alle regole dell'ordinanza sui domini Internet. La priorità sarà data alle collettività pubbliche e agli enti che dispongono di un diritto legato alla denominazione richiesta. In presenza di candidati dai criteri equivalenti, a seconda delle circostanze, i nomi di dominio saranno attribuiti in base a una vendita all'asta, un'estrazione a sorte o alla valutazione del maggior valore aggiunto apportato alla collettività svizzera.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2&gt;&lt;b&gt;Indirizzi generici&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;L'11 gennaio segna anche l'apertura delle candidature per degli indirizzi generici che concernono un intero settore. La procedura, detta mandato di nominazione, permette a un'associazione di categoria, a un ente che rappresenta una categoria professionale o un settore d'attività di inoltrare all'UFCOM un dossier per un nome di dominio come per esempio hotel.swiss ou watch.swiss. Il richiedente dovrà poi mettere questi indirizzi al servizio di tutta la categoria che rappresenta.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;L'UFCOM tratterà individualmente ogni candidatura per un nome di dominio generico. Riscuoterà una tassa unica di 2900 franchi per dossier e 360 franchi all'anno per le sue attività di vigilanza: Il richiedente pagherà questi importi tramite la fattura globale inviatagli dal suo centro di registrazione. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2&gt;&lt;b&gt;7000 indirizzi .swiss già attribuiti&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;Durante la fase di lancio conclusasi il 9 novembre 2015, sono stati richiesti 9738 nomi di dominio .swiss. Al termine del periodo di pubblicazione delle candidature, circa 7000 indirizzi .swiss sono già stati attribuiti.&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Ufficio federale delle comunicazioni UFCOM Servizio stampa, +41 58 460 55 50, media@bakom.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="146283">
        <title>Sito del gestore del registro www.nic.swiss</title>
        <uri>http://www.dotswiss.net</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="146287">
        <title>Portale informativo sul nuovo dominio .swiss</title>
        <uri>http://dotswiss.ch</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="146291">
        <title>Ordinanza sui domini Internet (ODIn)</title>
        <uri>https://www.admin.ch/opc/it/classified-compilation/20141744/index.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Biel/Bienne</city>
      <title>.swiss internet addresses: generalised opening</title>
      <lead>The 11 January launch of the second phase of registration of .swiss internet addresses extends the range of possible domain names and potential candidates. It also opens up the possibility for umbrella organisations or sector representatives to submit a dossier in order to obtain a generic address, such as hotel.swiss or watch.swiss, which will then be put at the disposal of the sector as a whole. The first phase has already enabled some 7000 .swiss internet addresses to be assigned.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;From 11 January 2016, the .swiss internet domain will be opened up to numerous possible new addresses and will no longer be restricted to company names and trademarks. Thus applicants will be able to submit applications for names of products, slogans, geographical designations or made-up names. The applicant will still have to have a registered office and an actual administrative site in Switzerland and a clear connection with the requested internet address. Whereas they were excluded from the first phase, associations and foundations which are not listed in the commercial register will also be able to aspire to a .swiss address. However, the launch does not extend to private individuals. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;In so far as they meet the basic conditions, new applications will be published weekly on the www.nic.swiss site for a period of 20 days in order to allow comments or rival applications to be submitted. If they are not contested, the domain names will be assigned at the end of this period. Otherwise, OFCOM will arbitrate disputes on the basis of the rules of the Ordinance on Internet Domains. In particular, priority will be given to public bodies and then to entities which exercise a right related to the requested name. Depending on the individual cases, auctions, drawing of lots or an evaluation of the best added value brought to the Swiss community will be used to decide between candidatures which are equivalent in every respect. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2&gt;&lt;b&gt;Generic addresses &lt;/b&gt;&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;January 11 also marks the opening of applications for generic addresses which relate to a sector as a whole. The procedure, termed a naming mandate, enables an umbrella association, an entity which represents a trade or an industry sector to submit a dossier to OFCOM for a domain name such as, for example, hotel.swiss or watch.swiss. The applicant will then have to make these addresses available to the entire community which it represents. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;OFCOM will process each application for a generic domain name individually. It will charge a one-off fee of CHF 2900 per dossier, and CHF 360 per annum for its monitoring activities. The applicant will pay these amounts in the total invoice which its registrar will submit to it. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2&gt;&lt;b&gt;7000 .swiss addresses already assigned&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;In the course of the launch phase which ended on 9 November 2015, a total of 9738 .swiss domain names were applied for. At the end of the publication period for applications, some 7000 .swiss addresses had already been assigned. &lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Federal Office of Communications OFCOM Press service, +41 58 460 55 50, media@bakom.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="146284">
        <title>Registry site www.nic.swiss</title>
        <uri>http://dotswiss.net</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="146288">
        <title>Information portal on the new .swiss domain</title>
        <uri>http://dotswiss.ch</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="146292">
        <title>Ordinance on Internet Domains (OID)</title>
        <uri>https://www.admin.ch/opc/en/classified-compilation/20141744/index.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <offers>
      <offer id="67" org-id="810">
        <name lang="de">Medienmitteilungen Telecom</name>
        <name lang="fr">Communiqués de presse télécommunications</name>
        <name lang="it">Comunicati stampa telecomunicazioni</name>
        <name lang="en">Press releases Telecom</name>
      </offer>
    </offers>
    <keywords>
      <keyword id="140" org-id="810">
        <name lang="de">Bundesamt für Kommunikation (BAKOM)</name>
        <name lang="fr">Office fédéral de la communication (OFCOM)</name>
        <name lang="it">Ufficio federale delle comunicazioni (UFCOM)</name>
        <name lang="en">Federal Office of Communications (OFCOM)</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="540" org-id="810">
        <name lang="de">Informationsgesellschaft</name>
        <name lang="fr">Société de l'information</name>
        <name lang="it">Società dell'informazione</name>
        <name lang="en">Information Society</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="570" org-id="810">
        <name lang="de">Internet</name>
        <name lang="fr">Internet</name>
        <name lang="it">Internet</name>
        <name lang="en">Internet</name>
      </keyword>
    </keywords>
    <topics>
      <topic id="28">
        <name lang="de">Telekommunikation</name>
        <name lang="fr">Télécommunications</name>
        <name lang="it">Telecomunicazione</name>
        <name lang="en">Telecommunications</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="36">
        <name lang="de">Informatik und E-Government</name>
        <name lang="fr">Informatique et cyberadministration</name>
        <name lang="it">Informatica ed e-government</name>
        <name lang="en">IT and E-Government</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
