<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="61302" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2016-04-08</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="701" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>701</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Wirtschaft, Bildung und Forschung</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'économie, de la formation et de la recherche</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'economia, della formazione e della ricerca</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Economic Affairs, Education and Research</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="yes" id="703" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>701</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Staatssekretariat für Wirtschaft</name>
      <name lang="fr">Secrétariat d'Etat à l'économie</name>
      <name lang="it">Segreteria di Stato dell'economia</name>
      <name lang="en">State Secretariat for Economic Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.seco.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.seco.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.seco.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.seco.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@seco.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@seco.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@seco.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@seco.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="701">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Wirtschaft, Bildung und Forschung</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'économie, de la formation et de la recherche</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'economia, della formazione e della ricerca</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Economic Affairs, Education and Research</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Bundespräsident Schneider-Ammann trifft Chinas Staatschef Xi Jinping</title>
      <lead>Bundespräsident Johann N. Schneider-Ammann ist im Rahmen der Einladung zum Staatsbesuch am Freitag, 8. April, in Peking mit Chinas Staatschef Xi Jinping zusammengekommen. Die beiden Seiten verständigten sich auf eine „Innovative Strategische Partnerschaft“. Damit erhalten die schweizerisch-chinesischen Beziehungen eine neue Dimension und eine neue Dynamik. Vor dem Treffen am Freitag hatte der Bundespräsident bereits den chinesischen Premierminister Li Keqiang sowie mehrere Fachminister getroffen. Zudem standen die Eröffnung des Sino Swiss Economic Forums und Firmenbesuche auf dem Programm. Der Präsidialbesuch endet am Samstag in Shanghai. </lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Mit der Erklärung zur Errichtung einer „Innovativen Strategischen Partnerschaft“ gehört die Schweiz nun zum Kreis der rund 60 Staaten, mit denen sich China auf eine „strategische Partnerschaft“ verständigt hat. Im Gespräch der Präsidenten am Freitag kamen neben der Vertiefung dieser Partnerschaft vor allem wirtschafts-, finanz-, handels- und wissenschaftspolitische Themen sowie Fragen der Rechtsstaatlichkeit zur Sprache. Auch internationale Angelegenheiten und die Zusammenarbeit beider Länder in multilateralen Organen wie der G20 und der WTO waren Gegenstand des Gesprächs. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Über die Menschenrechte sprachen die Präsidenten ebenfalls; dabei wurde unter anderem festgehalten, dass die nächste Runde des Menschenrechtsdialogs vor Ende Mai stattfinden soll. Bezüglich der Bewilligung neuer Visaannahmestellen und der Eröffnung eines Generalkonsulates in Chengdu, sicherte Präsident Xi Jinping seine Unterstützung zu. An der Zusammenarbeit zwischen China und den osteuropäischen Staaten (16+1) wird die Schweiz künftig als Beobachter beteiligt sein. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Im Rahmen des Präsidialbesuchs wurden in Peking sieben Vereinbarungen und Protokolle unterzeichnet: Zur Zusammenarbeit in Fragen der Arbeitssicherheit und im Bereich der Wissenschaftskooperation, über eine Kooperation zwischen Switzerland Innovation und dem chinesischen TusPark, sowie vier Vereinbarungen zum Projekt Sino-Swiss Low Carbon Cities (SSLCC), dessen Ziel es ist, das Wachstum der chinesischen Städte nachhaltig zu gestalten.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Treffen mit Premierminister Li Keqiang&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/b&gt;Zuvor hatte der Bundespräsident in Peking bereits den chinesischen Premierminister Li Keqiang, den Vorsitzenden des Nationalen Volkskongresses, Zhang Dejiang, sowie mehrere Fachminister getroffen. Thema war dabei im Rahmen des Austausches über wirtschafts- und handelspolitische Fragen auch die Anwendung und Weiterentwicklung des Freihandelsabkommens zwischen der Schweiz und China. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Des Weiteren kam bei den Treffen die Zusammenarbeit in den Bereichen Wissenschaft und Innovation und nachhaltige Entwicklung zur Sprache. Am Freitagmittag hatte der Bundespräsident, der auf seiner China-Reise von Delegationen der Schweizer Wirtschaft und Wissenschaft begleitet wird, das Sino-Swiss Economic Forum eröffnet. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Shanghai als zweite Station des Präsidialbesuchs&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/b&gt;Am Samstag, 9. April, reisen die Schweizer Delegationen weiter nach Shanghai. Auf dem Programm stehen mehrere Treffen zu Wirtschaft und Innovation sowie ein Arbeitsessen mit Han Zheng, dem Sekretär der Kommunistischen Partei der Handelsmetropole. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Der Bundespräsident wird ausserdem neue Lokalitäten des Swiss Center Shanghai (SCS) eröffnen sowie ein örtliches Novartis-Forschungszentrum besichtigen. Den Abschluss des Präsidialbesuchs bildet eine Veranstaltung an der Wirtschaftshochschule China Europe International Business School (CEIBS). Der Bundespräsident wird vor Wirtschaftsvertretern und Absolventen der Hochschule über Wissenschaftskooperation und Innovation sprechen.&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Informationsdienst WBF 058 462 20 07, info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</contact>
      <attachment id="149619">
        <title>Gemeinsame Erklärung zwischen der Volksrepublik China und der Schweizerischen Eidgenossenschaft zur Errichtung einer Innovativen Strategischen Partnerschaft</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>16</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/43590.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <link id="149623">
        <title>Zusätzliche Verweise</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home/laender-reise-information/china/schweiz-china.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Le président Schneider-Ammann rencontre le président chinois Xi Jinping</title>
      <lead>Le président de la Confédération Johann N. Schneider-Ammann s’est entretenu le vendredi 8 avril avec le président chinois Xi Jinping dans le cadre de la visite d’Etat qu’il effectue en Chine. Les deux parties se sont mises d’accord sur un « partenariat stratégique innovateur », qui confère aux relations sino-suisses une dimension et une dynamique nouvelles. Le président Schneider-Ammann avait précédemment rencontré le premier ministre chinois Li Keqiang et plusieurs ministres du gouvernement. Il a par ailleurs ouvert le Forum économique sino-suisse et visité plusieurs entreprises. La visite présidentielle prendra fin samedi à Shanghai.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;La déclaration conjointe détaillée en vue d’établir un « partenariat stratégique innovateur » fait entrer la Suisse dans le cercle de la soixantaine d’Etats qui ont conclu un partenariat stratégique avec la Chine. L’entretien que les deux présidents ont eu vendredi a notamment porté aussi bien sur les possibilités d’approfondir ce partenariat que sur des sujets économiques, financiers, commerciaux ou de politique scientifique, ou encore sur des questions ayant trait à l’état de droit. Ont également été abordées plusieurs affaires internationales et la coopération des deux pays dans des enceintes multilatérales telles que le G20 ou l’OMC.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Les présidents se sont également entretenus des droits de l’homme, les deux parties convenant notamment que le prochain cycle de dialogue en la matière devra intervenir avant la fin mai. Le président Xi Jinping a par ailleurs assuré la Suisse de son soutien s’agissant de l’ouverture et d’un consulat général à Chengdu et de nouveaux services de visas. La Suisse participera enfin en qualité d’observateur aux travaux de coopération entre la Chine et les pays d’Europe orientale (16+1). &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;La visite présidentielle a permis de signer à Pékin sept accords ou protocoles, dont trois concernant la coopération sur les questions de sécurité au travail, la coopération scientifique et la coopération entre Switzerland Innovation et le Tsinghua University Science Park (TusPark), et quatre accords portant sur le projet Sino-Swiss Low Carbon Cities (SSLCC), qui vise à assurer aux villes chinoises une croissance durable.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Rencontre avec le premier ministre Li Keqiang&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/b&gt;Le président de la Confédération avait déjà précédemment rencontré à Pékin le premier ministre chinois Li Keqiang, le président de l’Assemblée nationale populaire Zhang Dejiang, ainsi que plusieurs ministres du gouvernement. L’échange de vues a porté sur différentes questions économiques et commerciales, parmi lesquelles l’application et le développement de l’accord de libre-échange qui unit la Suisse et la Chine.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;A également été abordée la coopération dans les domaines de la science et de l‘innovation et du développement durable. Le président Schneider-Ammann a par ailleurs ouvert vendredi midi le Forum&lt;b&gt; &lt;/b&gt;économique sino-suisse, en présence d’une délégation des entreprises et des institutions scientifiques suisses qui l’accompagnait dans son déplacement.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Shanghai, seconde étape de la visite présidentielle&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/b&gt;Le président Schneider-Ammann se rendra ensuite à Shanghai le samedi 9 avril. Le programme prévoit plusieurs rencontres qui seront consacrées à la science et à l’innovation, ainsi qu’un repas de travail avec Han Zheng, secrétaire du parti communiste pour la municipalité de Shanghai.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Le président de la Confédération inaugurera par ailleurs de nouveaux locaux du Swiss Center Shanghai (SCS) et il visitera un centre de recherche de Novartis. La visite présidentielle s’achèvera sur une manifestation organisée par l’école de commerce China Europe International Business School (CEIBS), à l’occasion de laquelle le président Schneider-Ammann parlera de coopération scientifique et d’innovation devant des représentants des entreprises et des diplômés de l’école.&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Service d’information DEFR 058 / 462 20 07; info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</contact>
      <attachment id="149620">
        <title>Déclaration commune de la République populaire de Chine et de la Confédération suisse concernant la mise en place d’un partenariat stratégique innovateur</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>16</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/43591.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <link id="149624">
        <title>Informations supplémentaires</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/home/laender-reise-information/china/schweiz-china.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Il presidente della Confederazione Schneider-Ammann incontra il capo di Stato cinese Xi Jinping</title>
      <lead>Venerdì 8 aprile, nell’ambito della visita di Stato, il presidente della Confederazione Johann N. Schneider-Ammann ha incontrato a Pechino il capo di Stato cinese Xi Jinping. Le due parti si sono accordate su un «partenariato strategico innovativo», che darà alle relazioni fra la Svizzera e la Cina una nuova dimensione e le renderà più dinamiche. Prima del colloquio di venerdì il presidente della Confederazione aveva incontrato il primo ministro cinese Li Keqiang e diversi altri ministri. Il programma prevedeva anche l’inaugurazione del forum economico cino-elvetico e alcune visite aziendali. La visita presidenziale si concluderà sabato a Shanghai. </lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Grazie alla Dichiarazione per l’istituzione di un «partenariato strategico innovativo» la Svizzera fa parte ora della sessantina di Stati con i quali la Cina ha concluso un partenariato strategico. Oltre ad approfondire questo partenariato, venerdì i presidenti hanno discusso anche di temi economici, finanziari, commerciali e scientifici nonché di questioni legate allo Stato di diritto. Sono state affrontate anche questioni internazionali e la collaborazione dei due Paesi in organi multilaterali come il G20 e l’OMC. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;I presidenti hanno inoltre affrontato la questione dei diritti umani: a questo proposito è stato fra l’altro deciso che la prossima tornata del dialogo sui diritti umani dovrà tenersi entro fine maggio. Il presidente Xi Jinping ha assicurato il suo sostegno per quanto riguarda la concessione di nuovi uffici per il rilascio dei visti e l’apertura di un Consolato generale a Chengdu. In futuro la Svizzera parteciperà come osservatrice nel contesto della cooperazione fra la Cina e gli Stati dell’Europa orientale (16+1). &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Nel quadro della visita presidenziale sono stati firmati a Pechino sette fra convenzioni e protocolli concernenti la cooperazione in materia di sicurezza sul lavoro, la cooperazione scientifica, una cooperazione fra Switzerland Innovation e TusPark, nonché quattro convenzioni concernenti il progetto Sino-Swiss Low Carbon Cities (SSLCC), il cui obiettivo è di impostare la crescita delle città cinesi in modo sostenibile. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Incontro con il primo ministro Li Keqiang&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/b&gt;In precedenza il presidente della Confederazione aveva incontrato il primo ministro cinese Li Keqiang e il presidente dell’Assemblea nazionale del Popolo, Zhang Dejiang, nonché diversi altri ministri. Durante i colloqui sono state trattate questioni economiche e commerciali, con particolare riferimento all’applicazione e allo sviluppo dell’Accordo di libero scambio tra la Svizzera e la Cina. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Inoltre si è discusso anche della cooperazione nei settori dell’economia e dell’innovazione nonché dello sviluppo sostenibile. Venerdì a mezzogiorno il presidente della Confederazione, che nel suo viaggio in Cina è accompagnato da delegazioni di rappresentanti svizzeri dell’economia e delle cerchie scientifiche, ha inaugurato il forum economico cino-elvetico. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Shanghai, seconda tappa del viaggio presidenziale&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/b&gt;Sabato 9 aprile le delegazioni svizzere proseguiranno per Shanghai, dove il programma prevede diversi incontri su economia e innovazione nonché un pranzo di lavoro con Han Zheng, segretario del partito comunista della metropoli commerciale. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Il presidente della Confederazione inaugurerà inoltre nuovi locali allo Swiss Center Shanghai (SCS) e visiterà un centro di ricerca della Novartis. Una manifestazione presso la China Europe International Business School (CEIBS) concluderà la visita. Il presidente della Confederazione parlerà di cooperazione scientifica e di innovazione a rappresentanti dell'economia e a diplomati della scuola universitaria.&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Servizio informazioni del DEFR 058 462 20 07, info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</contact>
      <attachment id="149621">
        <title>Dichiarazione congiunta tra la Repubblica popolare Cinese e la Confederazione Svizzera sull’istituzione di un partenariato strategico innovativo</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>16</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/43592.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <link id="149625">
        <title>Altri rimandi</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/home/laender-reise-information/china/schweiz-china.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>President Schneider-Ammann meets Chinese President Xi Jinping</title>
      <lead>Taking up China’s invitation to pay a state visit to the country, President Johann N. Schneider-Ammann met with President Xi Jinping in Beijing on Friday, 8 April. The two sides agreed on an 'innovative strategic partnership'. This will give an added dimension and fresh impulse to Sino-Swiss bilateral relations. Prior to the meeting on Friday the Swiss president met Chinese Premier Li Keqiang and a number of other ministers. Also on the agenda was the opening of the Sino-Swiss Economic Forum and visits to a number of businesses. On Saturday the president will round off his visit in Shanghai.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;With the Declaration on the establishment of an 'innovative strategic partnership', Switzerland joins the group of some 60 states with which China has entered into a strategic partnership. In addition to ways of consolidating the partnership, the talks between the two presidents on Friday covered economic, financial, trade and science policy issues, as well as the rule of law. International affairs and cooperation between the two countries in multilateral bodies such as the G20 and the WTO were also addressed.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The two presidents also addressed the subject of human rights where it was agreed, among other things, that the next round of the human rights dialogue should take place before the end of May. President Xi Jinping gave assurance of his support regarding the approval of new visa application centres and the opening of a consulate general in Chengdu. In future Switzerland will have observer status in the Cooperation between China and Eastern European Countries (16+1).&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;During the president’s visit to Beijing, seven agreements and protocols have been signed in a range of fields; three concern cooperation on matters of occupational safety, scientific cooperation and cooperation between Switzerland Innovation and Tsinghua University Science Park (TusPark), and four agreements concern the Sino-Swiss Low Carbon Cities (SSLCC) project, which aims to promote the sustainable growth of Chinese cities. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Meeting with Premier Li Keqiang&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/b&gt;Prior to the reception the president met with Chinese Premier Li Keqiang, the Chairman of the National People’s Congress, Zhang Dejiang, and a number of other ministers. The topics covered included economic and trade policy issues as well as the application and development of the free trade agreement between Switzerland and China. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The meeting also provided an opportunity to discuss cooperation in the areas of science and innovation and sustainable development. At midday the president opened the Sino-Swiss Economic Forum in the presence of the economic and science delegations that are accompanying him on his visit. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Shanghai second stop on presidential visit&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/b&gt;On Saturday, 9 April, the Swiss delegations will move on to Shanghai where several business and innovation-themed meetings are on the agenda, as well as a working lunch with Han Zheng, the secretary of the Shanghai Communist Party.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The president will also open the new offices of the Swiss Center Shanghai (SCS) and tour the local Novartis research centre. The trip will be rounded off with an event at the China Europe International Business School (CEIBS), where the president will address business representatives and alumni on the subject of scientific cooperation and innovation.&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>EAER Information Service 058 462 20 07, info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</contact>
      <attachment id="149622">
        <title>Joint declaration between the People's Republic of China and the Swiss Confederation on the establishment of an innovative strategic partnership</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>15</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/43593.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <link id="149626">
        <title>Additional information</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home/laender-reise-information/china/schweiz-china.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <keywords>
      <keyword id="0001" org-id="701">
        <name lang="de">Wirtschaft</name>
        <name lang="fr">Economie</name>
        <name lang="it">Economia</name>
        <name lang="en">Economic Affairs</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="0005" org-id="701">
        <name lang="de">Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Etranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Straniero</name>
        <name lang="en">Foreign</name>
      </keyword>
    </keywords>
    <topics>
      <topic id="47">
        <name lang="de">Wirtschaft</name>
        <name lang="fr">Économie</name>
        <name lang="it">Economia</name>
        <name lang="en">Economic Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
