<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="61883" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2016-05-25</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="1070" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>1070</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Der Bundesrat</name>
      <name lang="fr">Conseil fédéral</name>
      <name lang="it">Il Consiglio federale</name>
      <name lang="en">The Federal Council</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.admin.ch/gov/de/start.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.admin.ch/gov/fr/accueil.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.admin.ch/gov/it/pagina-iniziale.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.admin.ch/gov/en/start.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="yes" id="703" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>701</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Staatssekretariat für Wirtschaft</name>
      <name lang="fr">Secrétariat d'Etat à l'économie</name>
      <name lang="it">Segreteria di Stato dell'economia</name>
      <name lang="en">State Secretariat for Economic Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.seco.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.seco.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.seco.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.seco.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@seco.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@seco.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@seco.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@seco.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="1070">
      <name lang="de">Der Bundesrat</name>
      <name lang="fr">Conseil fédéral</name>
      <name lang="it">Il Consiglio federale</name>
      <name lang="en">The Federal Council</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.admin.ch/gov/de/start.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.admin.ch/gov/fr/accueil.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.admin.ch/gov/it/pagina-iniziale.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.admin.ch/gov/en/start.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <department id="701">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Wirtschaft, Bildung und Forschung</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'économie, de la formation et de la recherche</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'economia, della formazione e della ricerca</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Economic Affairs, Education and Research</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Sanktionen gegenüber Côte d’Ivoire werden aufgehoben</title>
      <lead>Der Bundesrat hat aufgrund der UNO-Sicherheitsratsresolution 2283 (2016) vom 28. April 2016 die Verordnung über Massnahmen gegenüber Côte d’Ivoire aufgehoben. Die Massnahmen umfassten ein Teilembargo für Rüstungsgüter sowie Finanz- und Reisesanktionen. Die Aufhebung der Verordnung tritt am 25. Mai 2016 um 18.00 in Kraft.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Als Reaktion auf einen missglückten Putschversuch gegen die Regierung von Laurent Gbagbo vom 19. September 2002 und dem anschliessenden Ausbruch des Bürgerkrieges erliess der Bundesrat am 19. Januar 2005 die Verordnung über Massnahmen gegenüber Côte d’Ivoire. Damit setzte er die Sanktionen des UNO-Sicherheitsrats um. Die Verordnung und deren Anhang wurden aufgrund der politischen Entwicklungen mehrmals angepasst. So wurden Ende 2014 die Massnahmen betreffend den Handel von Rohdiamanten aus Côte d’Ivoire aufgehoben. Seither sah die Verordnung lediglich noch ein Teilembargo für Rüstungsgüter sowie Reiseverbote und die Sperrung von Geldern vor. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Die politische Entspannung und der ordnungsgemässe Ablauf der Präsidentschaftswahl vom 25. Oktober 2015 haben den UNO-Sicherheitsrat dazu bewogen, die verbleibenden Sanktionen gegen Côte d’Ivoire mit der Resolution 2283 (2016) aufzuheben. Auf dieser Grundlage beschloss der Bundesrat die Aufhebung der Verordnung per 25. Mai 2016. &lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Antje Baertschi, Leiterin Kommunikation, SECO Tel. 058 463 52 75</contact>
      <link id="151610">
        <title>Amtliche Sammlung</title>
        <uri>https://www.admin.ch/opc/de/official-compilation/2016/index_50.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="151613">
        <title>Massnahmen gegenüber Côte d'Ivoire</title>
        <uri>https://www.seco.admin.ch/seco/de/home/Aussenwirtschaftspolitik_Wirtschaftliche_Zusammenarbeit/Wirtschaftsbeziehungen/exportkontrollen-und-sanktionen/sanktionen-embargos/sanktionsmassnahmen/massnahmen-gegenueber-cote-d-ivoire.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Levée des sanctions à l’encontre de la Côte d’Ivoire</title>
      <lead>Conformément à la résolution 2283 (2016) du 28 avril 2016 du Conseil de sécurité des Nations Unies, le Conseil fédéral a abrogé l’ordonnance instituant des mesures à l’encontre de la Côte d’Ivoire. Celle-ci prévoyait un embargo partiel sur les biens d’équipement militaires, ainsi que des sanctions financières et de voyage. L’abrogation de l’ordonnance entre en vigueur le 25 mai 2016 à 18 h 00.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Suite au coup d’Etat manqué contre Laurent Gbagbo le 19 septembre 2002 et à la guerre civile qui s’en est suivie, le Conseil fédéral a édicté, le 19 janvier 2005, l’ordonnance instituant des mesures à l’encontre de la Côte d’Ivoire, reprenant ainsi les sanctions décrétées par les Nations Unies. Au vu des développements politiques subséquents, l’ordonnance et son annexe ont fait l’objet de plusieurs adaptations. Depuis fin 2014, lorsque les mesures concernant le commerce de diamants bruts en provenance de Côte d’Ivoire ont été levées, l’ordonnance ne prévoyait plus qu’un embargo partiel sur les biens d’équipement militaires, une interdiction de voyage ainsi qu’un gel des avoirs. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Les progrès d’ensemble réalisés en Côte d’Ivoire sur la voie d’une paix et d’une stabilité durables et le bon déroulement de l’élection présidentielle du 25 octobre 2015 ont conduit le Conseil de sécurité à lever les sanctions encore en vigueur à l’encontre de la Côte d’Ivoire avec sa résolution 2283 (2016) du 28 avril 2016. Sur cette base, le Conseil fédéral a décidé d’abroger l’ordonnance avec effet au 25 mai 2016. &lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Antje Baertschi, Cheffe de la Communication SECO Tél.: 058 463 52 75</contact>
      <link id="151611">
        <title>Recueil officiel</title>
        <uri>https://www.admin.ch/opc/fr/official-compilation/2016/index_50.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="151614">
        <title>Mesures à l’encontre de la Côte d’Ivoire</title>
        <uri>https://www.seco.admin.ch/seco/fr/home/Aussenwirtschaftspolitik_Wirtschaftliche_Zusammenarbeit/Wirtschaftsbeziehungen/exportkontrollen-und-sanktionen/sanktionen-embargos/sanktionsmassnahmen/massnahmen-gegenueber-cote-d-ivoire.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Revocate le sanzioni contro la Costa d’Avorio</title>
      <lead>In conformità con la risoluzione 2283 (2016) del 28 aprile 2016 del Consiglio di sicurezza delle Nazioni Unite, il Consiglio federale ha abrogato l’ordinanza che istituisce provvedimenti nei confronti della Costa d’Avorio. Le misure comprendevano un embargo parziale sul materiale d’armamento, sanzioni finanziarie e restrizioni di viaggio. L’abrogazione dell’ordinanza entra in vigore il 25 maggio 2016 alle ore 18.00. </lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;In seguito al fallito colpo di Stato del 19 settembre 2002 contro il governo di Laurent Gbagbo, sfociato in una guerra civile, il 19 gennaio 2005 il Consiglio federale aveva emanato l’ordinanza che istituisce provvedimenti nei confronti della Costa d’Avorio, applicando così le sanzioni delle Nazioni Unite. L’ordinanza e il suo allegato sono stati adeguati a più riprese in base agli sviluppi politici. Per esempio, a fine 2014 sono state revocate le misure relative al commercio di diamanti grezzi provenienti dalla Costa d’Avorio. Da allora l’ordinanza contemplava solamente un embargo parziale sul materiale d’armamento, sulle restrizioni di viaggio e sul blocco degli averi. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Il clima politico sereno e il buon svolgimento delle elezioni presidenziali del 25 ottobre 2015 hanno indotto il Consiglio di sicurezza dell’ONU a revocare le sanzioni ancora vigenti nei confronti della Costa d’Avorio con la risoluzione 2283 (2016), in base alla quale il Consiglio federale ha deciso di abrogare l’ordinanza con effetto dal 25 maggio 2016. &lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Antje Baertschi, capo Comunicazione, SECO tel. 058 463 52 75</contact>
      <link id="151612">
        <title>Raccolta ufficiale</title>
        <uri>https://www.admin.ch/opc/it/official-compilation/2016/index_50.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="151615">
        <title>Provvedimenti nei confronti della Costa d'Avorio</title>
        <uri>https://www.seco.admin.ch/seco/it/home/Aussenwirtschaftspolitik_Wirtschaftliche_Zusammenarbeit/Wirtschaftsbeziehungen/exportkontrollen-und-sanktionen/sanktionen-embargos/sanktionsmassnahmen/massnahmen-gegenueber-cote-d-ivoire.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Sanctions against Côte d’Ivoire lifted</title>
      <lead>On the basis of UN Security Council Resolution 2283 (2016) of 28 April 2016, the Federal Council has repealed the Ordinance on Measures against Côte d’Ivoire. The measures involved a partial embargo on armaments, as well as financial and travel sanctions. The Ordinance is repealed as of 6pm on 25 May 2016.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Following the failed putsch against Laurent Gbagbo's government on 19 September 2002 and the subsequent outbreak of civil war in the country, the Federal Council issued the Ordinance on Measures against Côte d’Ivoire, thereby implementing the UN Security Council sanctions. The Ordinance and its annex have been amended several times to take account of political developments. For example, in late 2014 the measures regarding trade in raw diamonds originating in Côte d’Ivoire were repealed. Since then, the Ordinance has covered only a partial embargo on armaments, travel sanctions and the freezing of assets. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As the political situation in the country has become less tense, and with presidential elections correctly conducted on 25 October 2015, the UN Security Council has decided to lift the remaining sanctions against Côte d’Ivoire. On the basis of the corresponding Resolution 2283 (2016), the Federal Council will repeal the Ordinance as of 25 May 2016. &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Antje Baertschi, Head of Communications, SECO Tel. 058 463 52 75</contact>
      <link id="151610">
        <title>Amtliche Sammlung</title>
        <uri>https://www.admin.ch/opc/de/official-compilation/2016/index_50.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="151613">
        <title>Massnahmen gegenüber Côte d'Ivoire</title>
        <uri>https://www.seco.admin.ch/seco/de/home/Aussenwirtschaftspolitik_Wirtschaftliche_Zusammenarbeit/Wirtschaftsbeziehungen/exportkontrollen-und-sanktionen/sanktionen-embargos/sanktionsmassnahmen/massnahmen-gegenueber-cote-d-ivoire.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <offers>
      <offer id="255" org-id="703">
        <name lang="de">Sanktionen / Embargos und Exportkontrollen</name>
        <name lang="fr">sanctions / embargos et contrôles à l‘exportation</name>
        <name lang="it">Sanzioni / embarghi e controlli delle esportazioni</name>
        <name lang="en">sanctions / embargoes and export controls</name>
      </offer>
    </offers>
    <topics>
      <topic id="47">
        <name lang="de">Wirtschaft</name>
        <name lang="fr">Économie</name>
        <name lang="it">Economia</name>
        <name lang="en">Economic Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
