<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="63685" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2016-09-07</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="323" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>701</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidg. Materialprüfungs- und Forschungsanstalt</name>
      <name lang="fr">Laboratoire fédéral d'essai des matériaux et de recherche</name>
      <name lang="it">Laboratorio federale di prova dei materiali e di ricerca</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Laboratory for Materials Testing and Research</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.empa.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.empa.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.empa.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.empa.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">contact@empa.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">contact@empa.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">contact@empa.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">contact@empa.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="701">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Wirtschaft, Bildung und Forschung</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'économie, de la formation et de la recherche</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'economia, della formazione e della ricerca</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Economic Affairs, Education and Research</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Dübendorf, St. Gallen und Thun</city>
      <title>Wenn Boule-Kugeln plötzlich explodieren</title>
      <lead>Ein Quartierfest, eine lauschige Sommernacht, ein geselliges Boule-Spiel – und plötzlich ein ohrenbetäubender Knall. Allerdings waren weder Feuerwerkskörper noch Sprengstoff der Auslöser, sondern eine explodierende Boule-Kugel.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Ein Loch in der Decke des Zeltes und ein Krater im Boden waren Zeuge der unglaublichen Explosion, die sich am letzten Samstag im deutschen Nettetal an der holländischen Grenze zutrug. Verletzt wurde glücklicherweise niemand, die Feiernden kamen mit dem Schrecken davon. Doch wie können Boule-Kugeln so mir nichts, dir nichts explodieren?&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Empa-Experten hatten dies - nach ähnlichen Fällen in der Schweiz im Jahr 2009 - eingehend untersucht. Ihr Fazit: Die preisgünstig hergestellten, dünnwandigen Kugeln waren mit Mörtel gefüllt, um sie schwerer zu machen. Unglücklicherweise war der eingefüllte Mörtel feucht und enthielt zudem Eisenspäne. Diese korrodierten, und es entstand Wasserstoff, der im Inneren der Boule-Kugel einen hohen Druck erzeugte. Schliesslich brach eine schlecht ausgeführte Schweissnaht der Billig-Kugel und führte zur Explosion.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Ob in Nettetal die gleichen Ursachen zur Explosion geführt haben wie seinerzeit in der Schweiz, müssen genauere Untersuchungen vor Ort klären. Die nicht explodierten Kugeln aus dem Boule-Spielset wurden laut Presseberichten jedenfalls inzwischen von Sprengstoffexperten in Gewahrsam genommen.&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Weitere Informationen Dr. Gabor Piskoty Mechanical Systems Engineering Tel. +41 58 765 40 58 gabor.piskoty@empa.ch Redaktion / Medienkontakt Dr. Michael Hagmann Kommunikation Tel. +41 58 765 45 92 michael.hagmann@empa.ch</contact>
      <link id="158557">
        <title>Video</title>
        <uri>https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=a8KXnyk6rJA</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="158558">
        <title>Artikel "Rheinische Post"</title>
        <uri>http://www.rp-online.de/panorama/boule-kugel-explodiert-in-nettetal-lobberich-aid-1.6236413</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Dübendorf, St. Gallen und Thun</city>
      <title>Des boules de pétanque qui explosent soudainement</title>
      <lead>Une fête de quartier, une douce soirée d'été, une joyeuse partie de pétanque – et soudainement une détonation assourdissante. La cause, non pas un engin pyrotechnique ou une bombe, mais l'éclatement d'une boule de pétanque.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Un trou dans le toit de la tente et un cratère dans le sol sont les marques laissées par cette explosion incroyable qui s'est produite samedi dernier dans la ville allemande de Nettetal près de la frontière hollandaise. Par miracle pas de blessés mais seulement une grande frayeur. Mais comment est-ce qu'une boule de pétanque peut exploser ainsi soudainement sans crier gare?&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Après des cas similaires qui s'étaient produits en 2009 en Suisse, des experts de l'Empa avaient procédés à des examens approfondis leurs conclusions: ces boules de pétanque bon marché avec une paroi mince étaient remplies de mortier pour les alourdir. Malheureusement le mortier était humide et renfermait de plus de la limaille de fer. La corrosion de cette limaille avait produit un dégagement d'hydrogène qui avait provoqué une pression élevée à l'intérieur de la boule. Finalement une soudure mal réalisée avait conduit à la rupture de ces boules et à leur explosion.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Des examens approfondis et l'enquête menée à Nettetal doivent cependant éclaircir si cette explosion est due aux mêmes causes que les explosions qui s'étaient déjà produites en Suisse. Selon les articles publiés dans la presse, des experts en explosif ont procédé à l'explosion contrôlée des boules restantes encore intactes.&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Informations Dr. Gabor Piskoty Mechanical Systems Engineering Tél. +41 58 765 40 58 gabor.piskoty@empa.ch Rédaction / Contact médias Dr. Michael Hagmann Communcation Tél. +41 58 765 45 92 michael.hagmann@empa.ch</contact>
      <link id="158557">
        <title>Video</title>
        <uri>https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=a8KXnyk6rJA</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Dübendorf, St. Gallen und Thun</city>
      <title>Exploding boules balls</title>
      <lead>A local festival, a pleasant summer’s evening, a friendly game of boules – and suddenly a deafening bang. Not from a firework or a cracker, but from an exploding boules ball.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;The incredible explosion, which occurred in Nettetal, Germany, on the Dutch border, left a hole in the tent and a crater in the ground. Fortunately, nobody was hurt in the incident; the revelers merely got the shock of their lives. But how can boules balls just blow up like that?&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Following similar cases in Switzerland in 2009, a team of Empa experts carried out an in-depth investigation. Their conclusion: the cheaply produced, thin-walled balls were filled with mortar to make them heavier. Unfortunately, the mortar was damp and contained iron filings, which corroded. This produced hydrogen, which created high pressure inside the boules balls. Eventually, a shoddy weld seam on the cheap ball burst and caused the blast.&lt;/p&gt; More accurate tests are required to ascertain whether or not the same causes led to the explosion in Nettetal as in Switzerland. At any rate, the press reports that the balls in the boules set, which didn’t blow sky high, have since been secured by explosives experts.</text>
      <contact>Information Dr. Gabor Piskoty Mechanical Systems Engineering phone +41 58 765 40 58 gabor.piskoty@empa.ch Editor / Media contact Dr. Michael Hagmann Communcations phone +41 58 765 45 92 michael.hagmann@empa.ch</contact>
      <link id="158557">
        <title>Video</title>
        <uri>https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=a8KXnyk6rJA</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="45">
        <name lang="de">Technologie</name>
        <name lang="fr">Technologie</name>
        <name lang="it">Tecnologia</name>
        <name lang="en">Technology</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
