<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="65052" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2016-12-21</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="710" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>701</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Wettbewerbskommission</name>
      <name lang="fr">Commission de la concurrence</name>
      <name lang="it">Commissione della concorrenza</name>
      <name lang="en">Competition Commission</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.weko.admin.ch/</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.weko.admin.ch/</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.weko.admin.ch/</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.weko.admin.ch/</www>
      <email lang="de">weko@weko.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">weko@weko.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">weko@weko.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">weko@weko.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="701">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Wirtschaft, Bildung und Forschung</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'économie, de la formation et de la recherche</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'economia, della formazione e della ricerca</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Economic Affairs, Education and Research</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>WEKO büsst Banken wegen Teilnahme am EURIBOR-Kartell</title>
      <lead>Die Wettbewerbskommission (WEKO) schliesst die Untersuchung bezüglich Euro-Zinsderivaten mit einer einvernehmlichen Regelung und Bussen von insgesamt rund CHF 45.3 Mio. gegenüber einem Teil der Parteien ab.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Die WEKO gelangte zum Ergebnis, dass zwischen September 2005 und Mai 2008 ein Kartell bezüglich Euro-Zinsderivaten bestand, an dem sich zu unterschiedlichen Zeiträumen mehrere Banken beteiligten. Vier der beteiligten Banken (Barclays, Deutsche Bank, Royal Bank of Scotland [RBS] und Société Générale) haben eine einvernehmliche Regelung unterzeichnet, welche von der WEKO am 5. Dezember 2016 genehmigt wurde. Am vorgenannten Kartell nahmen die Barclays und die Deutsche Bank während 32 Monaten, die Société Générale während 26 Monaten und die RBS während acht Monaten teil. Die WEKO verhängte Sanktionen von insgesamt rund CHF 45.3 Mio. Der Deutschen Bank wurde die Sanktion erlassen, da das Unternehmen die WEKO vom Kartell in Kenntnis gesetzt hatte. Die anderen Banken erhielten aufgrund der Bonusregelung für ihre Zusammenarbeit mit der WEKO während der Untersuchung eine Reduktion ihrer Sanktionen. Die einzelnen Sanktionen betragen CHF 29.772 Mio. für die Barclays, CHF 12.332 Mio. für die RBS und CHF 3.254 Mio. für die Société Générale. Gegen die weiteren Untersuchungsadressatinnen BNP Paribas, Crédit Agricole, HSBC, JPMorgan und Rabobank läuft das Verfahren weiter.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Das Kartell zielte auf die Beeinflussung der normalen Preisfestlegungskomponenten für Euro-Zinsderivate ab. Die Händler der verschiedenen Banken diskutierten gelegentlich die Angebote ihrer Banken für die Berechnung des EURIBOR sowie ihre Handels- und Preisstrategien. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Zinsderivate sind Finanzprodukte (z. B. Forward Rate Agreements, Swaps, Futures, Optionen), die von Banken und Unternehmen für die Handhabung des Risikos von Zinsschwankungen verwendet werden. Ihr Wert richtet sich nach der Höhe eines Referenzzinssatzes wie im konkreten Fall dem EURIBOR (Euro Interbank Offered Rate).&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Der Entscheid der WEKO kann an das Bundesverwaltungsgericht weitergezogen werden.&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Prof. Dr. Vincent Martenet Präsident 021 692 27 46 079 506 73 87 vincent.martenet@weko.admin.ch Dr. Rafael Corazza Direktor 058 462 20 41 079 652 49 57 rafael.corazza@weko.admin.ch Dr. Olivier Schaller Vizedirektor 058 462 21 23 079 703 80 07 olivier.schaller@weko.admin.ch</contact>
      <attachment id="162223">
        <title>WEKO büsst Banken wegen Teilnahme am EURIBOR-Kartell</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>92</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/46704.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="162227">
        <title>Presserohstoff</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>491</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/46708.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>La COMCO sanctionne des banques pour leur participation au cartel EURIBOR</title>
      <lead>La Commission de la concurrence (COMCO) clôt l’enquête portant sur les produits dérivés en euros contre certaines parties à la procédure, avec un accord amiable et des sanctions se montant à environ CHF 45.3 mio.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;La COMCO est arrivée à la conclusion que plusieurs banques ont participé pour des durées différentes à un cartel dans les produits dérivés de taux d’intérêt en euros entre septembre 2005 et mai 2008. Quatre banques participantes (Barclays, Deutsche Bank, Royal Bank of Scotland (RBS) et Société Générale) ont signé un accord amiable, approuvé par la COMCO le 5 décembre 2016. Les durées de participation au cartel ont été de 32 mois pour Barclays et Deutsche Bank, 26 mois pour Société Générale et 8 mois pour RBS. La Comco a infligé des sanctions se montant à environ CHF 45.3 mio. Deutsche Bank a bénéficié d’une remise totale de la sanction pour avoir révélé l’existence de l’entente à la COMCO. Les autres banques ont bénéficié d’une réduction de la sanction pour leur participation au programme de clémence et leur coopération avec la COMCO. Les sanctions individuelles se montent à CHF 29.772 mio pour Barclays, CHF 12.332 mio pour RBS et CHF 3.254 mio pour Société Générale. L’enquête continue à l’encontre de BNP Paribas, Crédit Agricole, HSBC, JPMorgan et Rabobank.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Le cartel avait pour objectif d’influencer l’évolution normale des composants du prix des produits dérivés libellés en euros. Des traders de différentes banques discutaient occasionnellement des soumissions de leur banque pour le calcul de l'EURIBOR ainsi que de leurs stratégies de négociation et de fixation des prix. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Les produits dérivés de taux d’intérêt (p. ex. : contrats à terme, futures, swaps et options) sont des produits financiers qui sont utilisés par les banques et les entreprises pour gérer le risque de fluctuation des taux d’intérêt. Leur valeur résulte du niveau d’un taux d’intérêt de référence, tel que dans le cas concret le taux interbancaire offert européen (EURIBOR).&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;La décision de la COMCO peut être attaquée devant le Tribunal administratif fédéral.&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Prof. Dr Vincent Martenet Président 021 692 27 46 079 506 73 87 vincent.martenet@comco.admin.ch Dr Rafael Corazza Directeur 058 462 20 41 079 652 49 57 rafael.corazza@comco.admin.ch Dr Olivier Schaller Vice-directeur 058 462 21 23 079 703 80 07 olivier.schaller@comco.admin.ch</contact>
      <attachment id="162224">
        <title>La COMCO sanctionne des banques pour leur participation au cartel EURIBOR</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>143</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/46705.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="162228">
        <title>Documentation de presse</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>549</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/46709.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>La COMCO multa delle banche per la partecipazione al cartello EURIBOR</title>
      <lead>La Commissione della concorrenza (COMCO) chiude l’inchiesta sui prodotti derivati in euro contro alcune parti alla procedura, con una conciliazione e delle multe per un totale di circa CHF 45.3 mio.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;La COMCO è arrivata alla conclusione che diverse banche hanno partecipato, per periodi differenti, a un cartello sui prodotti derivati dei tassi di interesse in euro tra settembre 2005 e maggio 2008. Quattro banche partecipanti (Barclays, Deutsche Bank, Royal Bank of Scotland (RBS) e Société Générale) hanno concluso una conciliazione, approvata dalla COMCO il 5 dicembre 2016. La durata della partecipazione al cartello è stata di 32 mesi per Barclay e Deutsche Bank, 26 mesi per Société Générale e 8 mesi per RBS. La COMCO ha inflitto delle multe per un totale di circa CHF 45.3 mio. Deutsche Bank ha beneficiato di una riduzione completa della multa per avere rivelato alla COMCO l’esistenza del cartello. Le altre banche hanno beneficiato di una riduzione della multa per la loro partecipazione al programma di clemenza e la loro cooperazione con la COMCO. Le multe individuali ammontano a CHF 29.772 mio per Barclays, CHF 12.332 mio per RBS e CHF 3.254 mio per Société Générale. L’inchiesta continua contro BNP Paribas, Crédit Agricole, HSBC, JP Morgan e Rabobank.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Il cartello aveva per obiettivo di falsare l’evoluzione normale dei componenti del prezzo dei prodotti derivati in euro. I traders delle differenti banche discutevano occasionalmente delle offerte della loro banca per il calcolo dell’EURIBOR così come delle loro strategie di negoziato e della fissazione dei prezzi.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;I prodotti derivati da tassi di interesse (come per esempio i contratti a termine, i futures, gli swaps e le options) sono dei prodotti finanziari che sono utilizzati dalle banche o da altre imprese per gestire il rischio di fluttuazione dei tassi di interesse. Il loro valore risulta dal livello di un tasso di interesse di riferimento, come nel caso concreto, il tasso interbancario di offerta in euro (EURIBOR).&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;La decisione della COMCO è soggetta a ricorso presso il Tribunale amministrativo federale.&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Prof. Dott. Vincent Martenet Presidente 021 692 27 46 079 506 73 87 vincent.martenet@comco.admin.ch Dr. Rafael Corazza Direttore 058 462 20 41 079 652 49 57 rafael.corazza@comco.admin.ch Dr. Olivier Schaller Vicedirettore 058 462 21 23 079 703 80 olivier.schaller@comco.admin.ch</contact>
      <attachment id="162225">
        <title>La COMCO multa delle banche per la partecipazione al cartello EURIBOR</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>141</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/46716.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>COMCO fines banks for participating in the EURIBOR cartel</title>
      <lead>The Competition Commission (COMCO) has closed its investigation against certain banks related to interest rate derivatives in euro with an amicable settlement and imposes total fines of approximately CHF 45.3 million.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;COMCO reached the conclusion that between September 2005 and May 2008 several banks participated, for different durations, in a cartel in interest rate derivatives in euro. Four of these banks (Barclays, Deutsche Bank, Royal Bank of Scotland [RBS] and Société Générale) signed an amicable settlement, approved by the COMCO on December 5, 2016. Barclays and Deutsche Bank participated in the cartel for 32 months, Société Générale for 26 months and RBS for 8 months. COMCO imposed total fines of approximately CHF 45.3 million. Deutsche Bank received full immunity for revealing the existence of the cartel to the COMCO. The other banks involved received reductions of their respective fines for cooperating with the investigation under the leniency programme. The individual fines amount to CHF 29.772 million for Barclays, CHF 12.332 million for RBS and CHF 3.254 million for Société Générale. The proceeding continues against BNP Paribas, Crédit Agricole, HSBC, JPMorgan and Rabobank.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The cartel aimed at distorting the normal course of pricing components for interest rate&lt;br /&gt; derivatives in euro. Traders of different banks occasionally discussed their bank's submissions for the calculation of the EURIBOR as well as their trading and pricing strategies.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Interest rate derivatives (e.g. forward rate agreements, swaps, futures, options) are financial products used for managing the risk of interest rate fluctuations. They derive their value from the level of a benchmark interest rate, such as the Euro Interbank Offered Rate (EURIBOR).&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;COMCO’s decision can be appealed to the Federal Administrative Court.&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Prof. Dr. Vincent Martenet President 021 692 27 46 079 506 73 87 vincent.martenet@comco.admin.ch Dr. Rafael Corazza Director 058 462 20 41 079 652 49 57 rafael.corazza@comco.admin.ch Dr. Olivier Schaller Vice-Director 058 462 21 23 079 703 80 07 olivier.schaller@comco.admin.ch</contact>
      <attachment id="162226">
        <title>COMCO fines banks for participating in the EURIBOR cartel</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>90</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/46707.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="5">
        <name lang="de">Behörden</name>
        <name lang="fr">Autorités</name>
        <name lang="it">Autorità</name>
        <name lang="en">Authorities</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="26">
        <name lang="de">Recht</name>
        <name lang="fr">Droit</name>
        <name lang="it">Diritto</name>
        <name lang="en">Legal Affairs</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="35">
        <name lang="de">Finanzplatz</name>
        <name lang="fr">Place financière</name>
        <name lang="it">Piazza finanziaria</name>
        <name lang="en">Financial Centre</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="47">
        <name lang="de">Wirtschaft</name>
        <name lang="fr">Économie</name>
        <name lang="it">Economia</name>
        <name lang="en">Economic Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
