<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="15251" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2007-10-23</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="201" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>201</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="201">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Offizieller Arbeitsbesuch des slowenischen Aussenministers, Dimitrij Rupel, bei Bundespräsidentin Micheline Calmy-Rey am 23. Oktober 2007 in Bern</title>
      <lead>Bundespräsidentin Micheline Calmy-Rey, Vorsteherin des Eidgenössischen Departements für auswärtige Angelegenheiten (EDA), hat am 23. Oktober den slowenischen Aussenminister Dimitrij Rupel zu einem offiziellen Arbeitsbesuch in Bern empfangen. Die Gespräche boten die Gelegenheit, sich über die ausgezeichneten bilateralen Beziehungen zwischen den beiden Ländern auszutauschen und sich über die aktuelle internationale Lage, insbesondere die europäische Zusammenarbeit, zu unterhalten. Slowenien wird im ersten Halbjahr 2008 die Präsidentschaft des Rats der Europäischen Union (EU) übernehmen.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Die Vorsteherin des EDA, Micheline Calmy-Rey, hat sich für eine weitere Vertiefung der bilateralen Beziehungen über eine Zusammenarbeit zwischen der Schweiz und Slowenien im Rahmen des Schweizer Beitrags zur Verringerung der wirtschaftlichen und sozialen Ungleichheiten in der erweiterten EU ausgesprochen. Die Grundsätze sowie der Inhalt und die Modalitäten dieser Zusammenarbeit werden in einem Rahmenabkommen zwischen den beiden Ländern geregelt, über dessen baldigen Abschluss Bundespräsidentin Calmy-Rey und ihr Amtskollege ihre Freude zum Ausdruck brachten. Die Schweiz wird mit jedem der zehn Staaten, die 2004 der EU beigetreten sind, ein solches Abkommen abschliessen.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Der slowenische Aussenminister und die Schweizer Aussenministerin sprachen ausserdem über europapolitische Themen von gemeinsamem Interesse, namentlich über die Umsetzung der bilateralen Abkommen zwischen der Schweiz und der EU, deren Präsidentschaft Slowenien Anfang 2008 übernehmen wird. Die Bundespräsidentin konnte bei dieser Gelegenheit betonen, wie wichtig der Schweiz die Umsetzung der schon unterzeichneten Abkommen, insbesondere des Schengen/Dublin-Abkommens, ist. Ausserdem informierte sie Aussenminister Rupel über den Stand der Dinge in Bezug auf die Ausweitung der Personenfreizügigkeit auf Bulgarien und Rumänien.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Im Hinblick auf die aktuelle internationale Lage kamen auch die Situation im Westbalkan sowie die laufenden UNO-Reformen zur Sprache. Aussenminister Rupel und Bundespräsidentin Calmy-Rey befassten sich insbesondere mit der Verbesserung der Arbeitsmethoden im Sicherheitsrat.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Die Vorsteherin des EDA war am 28. November 2005 zu einem offiziellen Arbeitsbesuch in Ljubljana.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Presse- und Informationsdienst Bundeshaus West CH-3003 Bern Tel.: +41 (0)31 322 31 53 Fax: +41 (0)31 324 90 47 E-Mail: info@eda.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Visite officielle de travail de M. Dimitrij Rupel, Ministre slovène des Affaires étrangères auprès de la Présidente de la Confédération Micheline Calmy-Rey à Berne le 23 octobre 2007</title>
      <lead>La Présidente de la Confédération et Cheffe du Département fédéral des Affaires étrangères (DFAE) Micheline Calmy-Rey a reçu le 23 octobre M. Dimitrij Rupel, Ministre slovène des Affaires étrangères, en visite officielle de travail à Berne. Les entretiens ont permis d'aborder les excellentes relations bilatérales entre les deux pays et de faire un tour d'horizon de l'actualité internationale avec un accent particulier sur la coopération européenne. La Slovénie exercera la présidence de l’Union européenne (UE) au premier semestre 2008.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;La Cheffe du DFAE Micheline Calmy-Rey a exprimé sa conviction quant à un nouvel approfondissement des relations bilatérales au travers de la coopération de la Suisse avec la Slovénie dans le cadre de la contribution suisse à la réduction des disparités économiques et sociales dans l'Union européenne élargie. Madame Calmy-Rey et son homologue se sont réjouis de la conclusion prochaine de l’accord-cadre entre les deux pays qui déterminera les principes de cette coopération, et en réglera les thèmes et modalités. Un accord de ce type sera conclu avec chacun des dix Etats qui ont adhéré à l’UE en 2004.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Les deux ministres se sont également entretenus de sujets d'intérêt commun en matière de politique européenne ainsi que de la mise en œuvre des accords bilatéraux entre la Suisse et l'UE, dont la Présidence revient à la Slovénie début 2008. La Présidente de la Confédération a eu l'occasion de rappeler la priorité de la Suisse consistant à mettre en œuvre tous les accords déjà signés, notamment l'accord Schengen/Dublin. Elle a également informé son interlocuteur de l'état des dossiers en matière d'extension de la libre circulation des personnes à la Bulgarie et à la Roumanie.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Au chapitre de l'actualité internationale, les entretiens ont porté sur la situation dans les Balkans occidentaux ainsi que sur les réformes en cours à l'ONU. A ce titre, les deux ministres se sont plus particulièrement penchés sur l'amélioration des méthodes de travail du Conseil de sécurité.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;La Cheffe du DFAE s'était rendue en visite officielle de travail à Ljubljana le 28 novembre 2005.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Service de presse et d'information Palais fédéral ouest CH-3003 Berne Tél.: (+41) 031 322 31 53 Fax: (+41) 031 324 90 47 E-Mail: info@eda.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Visita ufficiale di lavoro del Ministro degli affari esteri sloveno, Dimitrij Rupel, alla Presidente della Confederazione, Micheline Calmy-Rey, a Berna il 23 ottobre 2007</title>
      <lead>La Presidente della Confederazione e capo del Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri (DFAE), Micheline Calmy-Rey, ha ricevuto il 23 ottobre Dimitrij Rupel, Ministro degli affari esteri sloveno, in visita ufficiale di lavoro a Berna. I colloqui hanno permesso di abbordare le ottime relazioni bilaterali tra i due Paesi e di fare un giro d’orizzonte dell’attualità internazionale, con particolare rilievo sulla cooperazione europea. La Slovenia eserciterà la presidenza dell’Unione europea (UE) nel primo semestre 2008.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Il capo del DFAE, Micheline Calmy-Rey, ha espresso la propria convinzione riguardo a un nuovo approfondimento delle relazioni bilaterali attraverso la cooperazione della Svizzera con la Slovenia nell’ambito del contributo svizzero alla riduzione delle disparità economiche e sociali nell’Unione europea allargata. La Ministra Calmy-Rey e il suo omologo si sono rallegrati della prossima conclusione dell’accordo quadro tra i due Paesi che determinerà i principi di questa cooperazione disciplinandone temi e modalità. Un accordo di questo tipo sarà concluso con ciascuno dei dieci Stati che hanno aderito all’UE nel 2004.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;I due ministri hanno inoltre discusso di temi di comune interesse in materia di politica europea, nonché dell’attuazione degli accordi bilaterali tra la Svizzera e l’UE, la cui Presidenza spetterà alla Slovenia all’inizio del 2008. La Presidente della Confederazione ha colto l’occasione di ricordare la priorità della Svizzera, che consiste nell’attuare tutti gli accordi già firmati, segnatamente l’accordo Schengen/Dublino. Ha inoltre informato il suo interlocutore sullo stato dei dossier in materia di estensione della libera circolazione delle persone alla Bulgaria e alla Romania.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt; Per quanto riguarda l’attualità internazionale, i colloqui si sono incentrati sulla situazione nei Balcani occidentali, nonché sulle riforme in atto presso l’ONU. A questo proposito, i due ministri si sono in particolare concentrati sul miglioramento dei metodi di lavoro del Consiglio di Sicurezza.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Il capo del DFAE si era recato in visita ufficiale di lavoro a Ljubljana il 28 novembre 2005.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Servizio stampa e informazione Palazzo federale ovest CH-3003 Berna Tel.: (+41) 031 322 31 53 Fax: (+41) 031 324 90 47 E-Mail: info@eda.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Official working visit to Bern by Mr Dimitrij Rupel, Slovenian Minister of Foreign Affairs, on 23 October 2007</title>
      <lead>President of the Confederation and Head of the Federal Department of Foreign Affairs (DFAE) Micheline Calmy-Rey today received Mr Dimitrij Rupel, Slovenian Minister of Foreign Affairs, who is paying an official working visit to Bern. Their talks focused on the excellent bilateral relations between the two countries and a review of current international events, with special emphasis on European cooperation. Slovenia will hold the presidency of the European Union (EU) in the first half of 2008.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Mrs Calmy-Rey said that bilateral relations with Slovenia would further intensify as a result of Switzerland's cooperation with Slovenia in the framework of the Swiss contribution to the reduction of economic and social disparities in the enlarged European Union. Mrs Calmy-Rey and Mr Rupel were pleased with the forthcoming conclusion of the framework agreement between the two countries which will fix the principles of this cooperation and regulate procedures. An agreement of this type will be made with each of the ten States which joined the EU in 2004.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The two ministers also discussed matters of mutual interest in European policy and the implementation of the bilateral agreements between Switzerland and the EU, in which Slovenia will be president at the beginning of 2008. Mrs Calmy-Rey stressed that Switzerland's priority was to implement all the agreements that have already been signed, particularly the Schengen/Dublin agreement. She also informed Mr Rupel of the current state of dossiers concerning the extension of the free movement of persons to Bulgaria and to Romania.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;On international matters, their discussions covered the Western Balkans and UN reform. In this context, the ministers talked in particular about improvements to the working methods of the Security Council.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Mrs Calmy-Rey paid an official working visit to Ljubljana on 28 November 2005.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Press and Information Service Bundeshaus West CH-3003 Berne Tel.: (+41) 031 322 31 53 Fax: (+41) 031 324 90 47 E-Mail: info@eda.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
