<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="34206" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2010-07-07</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="1060" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>601</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Staatssekretariat für internationale Finanzfragen</name>
      <name lang="fr">Secrétariat d'Etat aux questions financières internationales</name>
      <name lang="it">Segreteria di Stato per le questioni finanziarie internazionali</name>
      <name lang="en">State Secretariat for International Financial Matters</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.sif.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.sif.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.sif.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.sif.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@sif.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@sif.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@sif.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@sif.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="601">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Finanzdepartement</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des finances</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale delle finanze</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Finance</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.efd.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.dff.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.efd.admin.ch/efd/it/home.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.efd.admin.ch/efd/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Arbeitsbesuch von Staatssekretär Michael Ambühl bei der EU-Präsidentschaft</title>
      <lead>Staatssekretär Michael Ambühl, Leiter des Staatssekretariats für internationale Finanzfragen im Eidgenössischen Finanzdepartement (EFD), führte gestern bei der belgischen EU-Präsidentschaft in Brüssel einen Arbeitsbesuch durch.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Staatssekretär Ambühl traf in Brüssel mit Olivier Henin, Kabinettschef des belgischen Finanzministers, Hans D’Hondt, Leiter der Finanzverwaltung sowie dem Gouverneur der belgischen Nationalbank, Guy Quaden, zusammen. Neben einem Meinungsaustausch über die Finanzmarktstrategien drehten sich die Gespräche insbesondere auch um die steuer- und finanzpolitischen Prioritäten der belgischen EU-Präsidentschaft. Belgien hat am 1. Juli für das zweite Halbjahr 2010 die EU-Präsidentschaft übernommen.&lt;/p&gt; Ein weiterer Meinungsaustausch fand mit Alexandre Lamfalussy statt, einem der Vordenker des europäischen Finanzsystems und früheren Generaldirektor der Bank für Internationalen Zahlungsausgleich (BIZ).</text>
      <contact>Mario Tuor, Leiter Kommunikation SIF, Tel. + 41 (0)31 322 46 16</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Le secrétaire d'Etat Michael Ambühl en visite de travail auprès de la présidence de l'UE</title>
      <lead>Michael Ambühl, chef du Secrétariat d'Etat aux questions financières internationales (SFI) au sein du Département fédéral des finances (DFF), a effectué hier une visite de travail à Bruxelles auprès de la présidence belge de l'UE.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;A Bruxelles, le secrétaire d'Etat Michael Ambühl a rencontré Olivier Henin, chef de cabinet du ministre belge des finances, Hans D’Hondt, président du Service public fédéral des finances et Guy Quaden, gouverneur de la Banque nationale de Belgique. Après un échange de vues sur les stratégies en matière de place financière, les discussions ont porté notamment sur les priorités fixées par la présidence belge de l'UE dans les domaines fiscal et financier. Le 1er juillet 2010, la Belgique a pris la tête de la présidence de l'Union européenne pour les six prochains mois.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Un échange de vues a également eu lieu entre Michael Ambühl et Alexandre Lamfalussy, l'un des fondateurs du système financier européen et ancien directeur général de la Banque des règlements internationaux (BRI).&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Mario Tuor, responsable de la communication du SFI, tél.: 031 322 46 16</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Visita di lavoro del segretario di Stato Michael Ambühl presso la presidenza dell'UE</title>
      <lead>Ieri, il segretario di Stato Michael Ambühl, capo della Segreteria di Stato per le questioni finanziarie internazionali in seno al Dipartimento federale delle finanze (DFF), ha effettuato presso la presidenza belga dell’UE a Bruxelles una visita di lavoro.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Il segretario di Stato Ambühl ha incontrato a Bruxelles Olivier Henin, responsabile al Ministero delle finanze belga, Hans D’Hondt, capo dell’amministrazione delle finanze, nonché Guy Quaden, governatore della banca nazionale belga. Oltre a uno scambio di opinioni sulle strategie dei mercati finanziari, i colloqui hanno riguardato in particolare le priorità di politica fiscale e finanziaria fissate dalla presidenza belga dell’UE. Il 1°&amp;nbsp;luglio il Belgio ha assunto la presidenza dell’UE per la seconda metà del 2010.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Un ulteriore scambio di opinioni è avvenuto con Alexandre Lamfalussy, il precursore del sistema finanziario europeo ed ex direttore generale della Banca dei regolamenti internazionali (BRI).&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Mario Tuor, capo della Comunicazione SFI, tel. 031 322 46 16</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Working visit of State Secretary Michael Ambühl to the EU Presidency</title>
      <lead>Yesterday State Secretary Michael Ambühl, Head of the State Secretariat for International Financial Matters in the Federal Department of Finance (FDF), conducted a working visit to the Belgian EU presidency in Brussels.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;In Brussels State Secretary Ambühl met Olivier Henin, the Head of Cabinet of the Belgian Ministry of Finance, Hans D’Hondt, Head of the Finance Administration and the Governor of the National Bank of Belgium, Guy Quaden. Aside from an exchange of ideas on the financial market strategies, the talks also revolved around the tax and financial policy priorities of Belgium’s EU presidency in particular. Belgium took over the EU presidency on 1 July for the second half of 2010. &amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;A further exchange of ideas took place with Alexandre Lamfalussy, a mastermind of the European financial system and former Director-General of the Bank for International Settlements (BIS).&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Mario Tuor, Head of SIF Communications, tel. +41 (0)31 322 46 16</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <keywords>
      <keyword id="235" org-id="1060">
        <name lang="de">Internationale Steuerpolitik</name>
        <name lang="fr">Politique fiscale internationale</name>
        <name lang="it">Politica fiscale internazionale</name>
        <name lang="en">International tax policy</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="118" org-id="1060">
        <name lang="de">Finanzmarktregulierung und -aufsicht</name>
        <name lang="fr">Réglementation et surveillance des marchés financiers</name>
        <name lang="it">Regolamentazione e vigilanza dei mercati finanziari</name>
        <name lang="en">Financial market regulation and supervision</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="126" org-id="1060">
        <name lang="de">Finanzplatz Schweiz</name>
        <name lang="fr">Place financière suisse</name>
        <name lang="it">Piazza finanziaria svizzera</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland as a financial centre</name>
      </keyword>
    </keywords>
    <topics>
      <topic id="34">
        <name lang="de">Europa</name>
        <name lang="fr">Europe</name>
        <name lang="it">Europa</name>
        <name lang="en">Europe</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="35">
        <name lang="de">Finanzplatz</name>
        <name lang="fr">Place financière</name>
        <name lang="it">Piazza finanziaria</name>
        <name lang="en">Financial Centre</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="44">
        <name lang="de">Steuern</name>
        <name lang="fr">Impôts</name>
        <name lang="it">Imposte</name>
        <name lang="en">Taxation</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="47">
        <name lang="de">Wirtschaft</name>
        <name lang="fr">Économie</name>
        <name lang="it">Economia</name>
        <name lang="en">Economic Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
