<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="67009" revoked="no">
    <version>2</version>
    <pubdate>2017-06-09</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="1070" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>1070</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Der Bundesrat</name>
      <name lang="fr">Conseil fédéral</name>
      <name lang="it">Il Consiglio federale</name>
      <name lang="en">The Federal Council</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.admin.ch/gov/de/start.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.admin.ch/gov/fr/accueil.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.admin.ch/gov/it/pagina-iniziale.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.admin.ch/gov/en/start.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="yes" id="605" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>601</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössische Steuerverwaltung</name>
      <name lang="fr">Administration fédérale des contributions</name>
      <name lang="it">Amministrazione federale delle contribuzioni</name>
      <name lang="en">The Federal Tax Administration</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.estv.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.estv.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.estv.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.estv.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de"/>
      <email lang="fr"/>
      <email lang="it"/>
      <email lang="en"/>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="yes" id="603" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>601</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidg. Finanzverwaltung</name>
      <name lang="fr">Administration fédérale des finances</name>
      <name lang="it">Amministrazione federale delle finanze</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Finance Administration</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.efv.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.efv.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.efv.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.efv.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@efv.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@efv.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@efv.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@efv.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="1070">
      <name lang="de">Der Bundesrat</name>
      <name lang="fr">Conseil fédéral</name>
      <name lang="it">Il Consiglio federale</name>
      <name lang="en">The Federal Council</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.admin.ch/gov/de/start.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.admin.ch/gov/fr/accueil.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.admin.ch/gov/it/pagina-iniziale.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.admin.ch/gov/en/start.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <department id="601">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Finanzdepartement</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des finances</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale delle finanze</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Finance</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.efd.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.dff.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.efd.admin.ch/efd/it/home.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.efd.admin.ch/efd/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Bundesrat diskutiert steuerpolitische Agenda und verabschiedet Eckwerte der Steuervorlage 17</title>
      <lead>Der Bundesrat hat an seiner Sitzung vom 9. Juni 2017 eine Diskussion über die steuerpolitische Reformagenda geführt und dabei die Eckwerte der Steuervorlage 17 (SV17) verabschiedet. Er hat das Eidgenössische Finanzdepartement (EFD) beauftragt, ihm bis September eine Vernehmlassungsvorlage zur SV17 zu unterbreiten. Der Bundesrat plant, die Botschaft zur SV17 voraussichtlich im Frühjahr 2018 zusammen mit der Botschaft zur Reform der Ehegattenbesteuerung zu beraten. Zu diesem Zeitpunkt wird er über eine mögliche Etappierung der Vorlagen entscheiden.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Im Februar 2017 lehnte das Schweizer Stimmvolk die Unternehmenssteuerreform III (USR III) an der Urne ab. Mit der Steuervorlage 17 (SV17) wird dem Urnenentscheid Rechnung getragen und der Steuerföderalismus respektiert. Die Attraktivität des Steuerstandortes Schweiz soll gestärkt und die internationale Akzeptanz wieder hergestellt werden. Besonderes Augenmerk legt die SV17 auf die Sicherstellung der Steuereinnahmen von Bund, Kantonen, Städten und Gemeinden.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Der Bundesrat hat bei der Beratung der Eckwerte zur SV17 im Wesentlichen die Empfehlungen des Steuerungsorgans aus Bund und Kantonen übernommen, wie sie am 1. Juni 2017 vorgestellt wurden. Der Kantonsanteil an der direkten Bundessteuer soll auf 20,5 Prozent erhöht werden – statt auf 21,2 Prozent, wie vom Steuerungsorgan empfohlen. Das EFD wird auf der Basis dieser Eckwerte bis im September eine Vernehmlassungsvorlage zur SV17 erarbeiten.&lt;b&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Im Rahmen seiner steuerpolitischen Reformagenda hat die SV17 für den Bundesrat Priorität. Vor dem Hintergrund der aktuellen finanziellen Situation im Bundeshaushalt wird der Bundesrat deshalb zum Zeitpunkt der Beratung der beiden Botschaften deren Finanzierung und den weiteren Fahrplan erörtern.&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Roland Meier, Mediensprecher EFD Tel. +41 (0)79 208 12 87, roland.meier@gs-efd.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Le Conseil fédéral discute le calendrier des réformes fiscales et adopte les lignes directrices du Projet fiscal 17</title>
      <lead>Lors de sa séance du 9 juin 2017, le Conseil fédéral a discuté le calendrier des réformes fiscales et adopté les lignes directrices du Projet fiscal 17 (PF 17). Il a chargé le Département fédéral des finances (DFF) de lui soumettre, d'ici au mois de septembre, un projet destiné à la consultation. Le Conseil fédéral entend traiter le message sur le PF 17 au printemps 2018, en même temps que le message sur la réforme de l'imposition du couple marié. Il décidera à ce moment-là d'un éventuel échelonnement des projets.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;En février 2017, le peuple suisse a rejeté la troisième réforme de l'imposition des entreprises. Le Projet fiscal 17 tient compte de cette décision et respecte les principes du fédéralisme dans le domaine fiscal. Il vise à renforcer l'attrait de la Suisse et à rétablir l'acceptation, sur le plan international, du système fiscal suisse. Une attention particulière est accordée à la garantie des recettes fiscales de la Confédération, des cantons, des villes et des communes.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Lors des délibérations sur les lignes directrices du PF 17, le Conseil fédéral a suivi, pour l'essentiel, les recommandations que l'organe de pilotage formé de représentants de la Confédération et des cantons a présentées le 1er juin 2017. La part des cantons au produit de l'impôt fédéral direct sera relevée à 20,5 % – au lieu de 21,2 % comme le recommandait l'organe de pilotage. Sur la base de ces lignes directrices, le DFF va élaborer, d'ici au mois de septembre, un projet destiné à la consultation.&lt;b&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Le Conseil fédéral a décidé d'accorder la priorité au PF 17 dans le calendrier des réformes fiscales. Vu le contexte budgétaire actuel, il fixera les modalités de financement de ces projets et la suite des travaux quand il traitera les deux messages.&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Roland Meier, porte-parole du DFF Tél. +41 (0)79 208 12 87, roland.meier@gs-efd.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Il Consiglio federale discute l’agenda di politica tributaria e approva i parametri del Progetto fiscale 17</title>
      <lead>Nella sua seduta del 9 giugno 2017 il Consiglio federale ha discusso il calendario della riforma di politica tributaria e approvato i parametri del Progetto fiscale 17. Inoltre ha incaricato il Dipartimento federale delle finanze (DFF) di presentare entro settembre un progetto di PF17 da porre in consultazione. L’Esecutivo intende deliberare sia sul PF17 che sulla riforma dell’imposizione dei coniugi nella primavera del 2018, quando deciderà anche in merito alla possibilità di attuare i due progetti a tappe. </lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Nel mese di febbraio 2017 l’elettorato svizzero ha bocciato la Riforma III dell’imposizione delle imprese (RI imprese III). Con il PF17 si tiene conto dell’esito della votazione e si rispetta il principio del federalismo fiscale. L’obiettivo è rafforzare l’attrattiva della piazza fiscale svizzera e ristabilire il consenso internazionale. Particolare attenzione è posta alla garanzia delle entrate fiscali di Confederazione, Cantoni, città e Comuni.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Nella deliberazione sui parametri del PF17 il Consiglio federale ha sostanzialmente ripreso le raccomandazioni che l’organo di coordinamento, composto da rappresentanti della Confederazione e dei Cantoni, ha presentato il 1° giugno 2017. L’Esecutivo auspica tuttavia che la quota dei Cantoni all’imposta federale diretta venga aumentata al 20,5 per cento e non al 21,2 per cento, raccomandato dall’organo di coordinamento. Sulla base di questi parametri il DFF elaborerà entro settembre un progetto di PF17 da porre in consultazione.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Tra le riforme fiscali in agenda, il Consiglio federale attribuisce la massima priorità al PF17. Data l’attuale situazione delle finanze della Confederazione, il Consiglio federale esaminerà la questione del finanziamento e dei tempi di attuazione quando delibererà sui due messaggi.&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Roland Meier, portavoce DFF Tel. +41 (0)79 208 12 87, roland.meier@gs-efd.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Federal Council discusses tax policy agenda and adopts parameters for tax proposal 17</title>
      <lead>During its meeting on 9 June 2017, the Federal Council discussed the tax policy reform agenda and adopted the parameters for tax proposal 17 (TP17) in the process. It instructed the Federal Department of Finance (FDF) to submit a TP17 consultation draft to it by September. The Federal Council expects to discuss the dispatch on TP17 in spring 2018, together with the dispatch on reforming the taxation of spouses. It will take the decision on a possible staggered schedule for the proposals at that time. </lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Swiss voters rejected the third series of corporate tax reforms (CTR III) in February 2017. Tax proposal 17 takes account of the referendum outcome and respects tax federalism. Switzerland's appeal as a tax location should be boosted and international acceptance should be restored. TP17 pays special attention to safeguarding the tax receipts of the Confederation, the cantons, the cities and the communes.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;When discussing the parameters for TP17, the Federal Council largely took on board the 1 June 2017 recommendations of the steering body comprised of representatives of the Confederation and the cantons. The cantons' share of direct federal tax is to be increased to 20.5% instead of 21.2% as was recommended by the steering body. The FDF will prepare a TP17 consultation draft based on those parameters by September.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Within the framework of its tax policy reform agenda, TP17 is a priority for the Federal Council. Against the backdrop of the federal budget's current financial situation, the Federal Council will thus address their financing and the timetable going forward when the two dispatches are discussed.&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Roland Meier, Media Spokesperson FDF Tel. +41 (0)79 208 12 87, roland.meier@gs-efd.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <offers>
      <offer id="6" org-id="605">
        <name lang="de">Direkte Bundessteuer</name>
        <name lang="fr">Impôt fédéral direct</name>
        <name lang="it">Imposta federale diretta</name>
        <name lang="en">Direct Federal Tax</name>
      </offer>
    </offers>
    <keywords>
      <keyword id="110" org-id="603">
        <name lang="de">Finanzen von Bund, Kantonen und Gemeinden</name>
        <name lang="fr">Finances de la Confédération / cantons / communes</name>
        <name lang="it">Finanze di Confederazione, Cantoni e Comuni</name>
        <name lang="en">Finances of the Confederation / cantons / communes</name>
      </keyword>
    </keywords>
    <topics>
      <topic id="10">
        <name lang="de">Bundesrat</name>
        <name lang="fr">Conseil fédéral</name>
        <name lang="it">Consiglio federale</name>
        <name lang="en">Federal Council</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="13">
        <name lang="de">Öffentliche Finanzen</name>
        <name lang="fr">Finances publiques</name>
        <name lang="it">Finanze pubbliche</name>
        <name lang="en">Public Finances</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="44">
        <name lang="de">Steuern</name>
        <name lang="fr">Impôts</name>
        <name lang="it">Imposte</name>
        <name lang="en">Taxation</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
