<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="86550" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2021-12-21</pubdate>
    <blocking-period>2021-12-21</blocking-period>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="318" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>301</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Bundesamt für Statistik</name>
      <name lang="fr">Office fédéral de la statistique</name>
      <name lang="it">Ufficio federale di statistica</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Statistical Office</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.statistik.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.statistique.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.statistica.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.statistics.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@bfs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@bfs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@bfs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@bfs.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="301">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement des Innern</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'intérieur</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'interno</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Home Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Neuchâtel</city>
      <title>Trotz Covid-19 bleibt die Sozialhilfequote im Jahr 2020 unverändert bei 3,2%</title>
      <lead>Im Jahr 2020 haben in der Schweiz 272 100 Personen mindestens einmal eine finanzielle Leistung der wirtschaftlichen Sozialhilfe erhalten. Die Auswirkungen der Covid-19-Pandemie auf die Sozialhilfe sind bisher gering; die Sozialhilfequote bleibt unverändert bei 3,2%. Jedoch ging 2020 die Zahl der Abgänge aus der wirtschaftlichen Sozialhilfe zurück. Dies sind einige Ergebnisse aus der Sozialhilfestatistik des Bundesamtes für Statistik (BFS).</lead>
      <text link="no">Diese Medienmitteilung und weitere Informationen zum Thema finden Sie auf der Website des BFS (siehe Link unten).</text>
      <contact>Marc Dubach, BFS, Sektion Sozialhilfe, Tel.: +41 58 463 65 78, E-Mail: marc.dubach@bfs.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="225498">
        <title>Kompletter Text und Mediendossier</title>
        <uri>https://www.bfs.admin.ch/news/de/2021-0349</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Neuchâtel</city>
      <title>Le taux d’aide sociale s’est maintenu à 3,2% en 2020 malgré le COVID-19</title>
      <lead>En 2020, 272 100 personnes ont reçu au moins une prestation financière de l’aide sociale économique en Suisse. Les répercussions de la pandémie de COVID-19 sur l’aide sociale sont faibles jusqu’ici; le taux d’aide sociale est resté stable à 3,2%. Le nombre de dossiers d’aide sociale économique ayant pu être clos a toutefois diminué en 2020. Ce sont-là quelques-uns des derniers résultats de la statistique suisse de l’aide sociale, établie par l’Office fédéral de la statistique (OFS).</lead>
      <text link="no">Vous trouverez ce communiqué de presse et d'autres informations sur ce thème sur le site web de l'OFS (cf. lien ci-dessous).</text>
      <contact>Marc Dubach, OFS, Section Aide sociale, tél.: +41 58 463 65 78, e-mail: marc.dubach@bfs.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="225499">
        <title>Texte intégral et dossier de presse</title>
        <uri>https://www.bfs.admin.ch/news/fr/2021-0349</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Neuchâtel</city>
      <title>Nonostante la pandemia di COVID-19, nel 2020 la quota di aiuto sociale è rimasta invariata al 3,2%</title>
      <lead>Nel 2020 le persone che hanno percepito almeno una volta una prestazione dell'aiuto sociale finanziario in Svizzera sono state 272 100. Finora le ripercussioni della pandemia di COVID-19 sull’aiuto sociale sono state minime e la quota di aiuto sociale è rimasta invariata al 3,2%. Tuttavia, si è registrato un calo del numero delle uscite dall’aiuto sociale finanziario. Questi sono alcuni dei risultati della statistica svizzera dell’aiuto sociale realizzata dall’Ufficio federale di statistica (UST).</lead>
      <text link="no">Il presente comunicato stampa e ulteriori informazioni sul tema sono reperibili sulla pagina Internet dell'UST (link sotto).</text>
      <contact>Marc Dubach, UST, sezione Aiuto sociale, tel.: +41 58 463 65 78, e-mail: marc.dubach@bfs.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="225500">
        <title>Testo integrale e dossier per i media</title>
        <uri>https://www.bfs.admin.ch/news/it/2021-0349</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Neuchâtel</city>
      <title>Despite COVID-19, the social assistance rate in 2020 remained unchanged at 3.2%</title>
      <lead>In 2020, 272 100 persons in Switzerland received financial benefits from social assistance on at least one occasion. The effects of the COVID-19 pandemic on social assistance to date have been minor; the social assistance rate has remained unchanged at 3.2%. However, the number of people leaving the economic social assistance system in 2020 decreased. These are some of the findings of the Swiss Social Assistance Statistics from the Federal Statistical Office (FSO).</lead>
      <text link="no">This press release and further information on this topic can be found on the FSO website (see link below).</text>
      <contact>Marc Dubach, FSO, Social Welfare section, tel.: +41 58 463 65 78, email: marc.dubach@bfs.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="225502">
        <title>Complete text and press kit - Please note that the English version only includes the release's lead</title>
        <uri>https://www.bfs.admin.ch/news/en/2021-0349</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <keywords>
      <keyword id="317.21" org-id="318">
        <name lang="de">Wirtschaftliche und soziale Situation der Bevölkerung</name>
        <name lang="fr">Situation économique et sociale de la population</name>
        <name lang="it">Reddito e qualità di vita della popolazione</name>
        <name lang="en">Economic and social data</name>
      </keyword>
    </keywords>
    <topics>
      <topic id="41">
        <name lang="de">Soziales</name>
        <name lang="fr">Social</name>
        <name lang="it">Opere sociali</name>
        <name lang="en">Social Affairs</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="43">
        <name lang="de">Statistik</name>
        <name lang="fr">Statistiques</name>
        <name lang="it">Statistica</name>
        <name lang="en">Statistics</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
