<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="86260" revoked="no">
    <version>6</version>
    <pubdate>2021-12-03</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="1070" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>1070</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Der Bundesrat</name>
      <name lang="fr">Conseil fédéral</name>
      <name lang="it">Il Consiglio federale</name>
      <name lang="en">The Federal Council</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.admin.ch/gov/de/start.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.admin.ch/gov/fr/accueil.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.admin.ch/gov/it/pagina-iniziale.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.admin.ch/gov/en/start.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="302" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>301</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Generalsekretariat EDI</name>
      <name lang="fr">Secrétariat général DFI</name>
      <name lang="it">Segreteria generale DFI</name>
      <name lang="en">General Secretariat FDHA</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="317" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>301</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Bundesamt für Gesundheit</name>
      <name lang="fr">Office fédéral de la santé publique</name>
      <name lang="it">Ufficio federale della sanità pubblica</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Office of Public Health</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.bag.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.bag.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.bag.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.bag.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">media@bag.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">media@bag.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">media@bag.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">media@bag.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="401" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>401</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Justiz- und Polizeidepartement</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de justice et police</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale di giustizia e polizia</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Justice and Police</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.ejpd.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.ejpd.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.ejpd.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.ejpd.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-ejpd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">Info@gs-ejpd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-ejpd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-ejpd.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="405" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>401</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Staatssekretariat für Migration</name>
      <name lang="fr">Secrétariat d’Etat aux migrations</name>
      <name lang="it">Segreteria di Stato della migrazione</name>
      <name lang="en">State Secretariat for Migration</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.sem.admin.ch/sem/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.sem.admin.ch/sem/fr/home.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.sem.admin.ch/sem/it/home.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.sem.admin.ch/sem/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@sem.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@sem.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@sem.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@sem.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="606" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>601</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössische Zollverwaltung</name>
      <name lang="fr">Administration fédérale des douanes</name>
      <name lang="it">Amministrazione federale delle dogane</name>
      <name lang="en">The Federal Customs Administration</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.ezv.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.ezv.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.ezv.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.ezv.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">ozd.zentrale@ezv.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">ozd.zentrale@ezv.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">ozd.zentrale@ezv.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">ozd.zentrale@ezv.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="1070">
      <name lang="de">Der Bundesrat</name>
      <name lang="fr">Conseil fédéral</name>
      <name lang="it">Il Consiglio federale</name>
      <name lang="en">The Federal Council</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.admin.ch/gov/de/start.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.admin.ch/gov/fr/accueil.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.admin.ch/gov/it/pagina-iniziale.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.admin.ch/gov/en/start.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <department id="301">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement des Innern</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'intérieur</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'interno</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Home Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <department id="401">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Justiz- und Polizeidepartement</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de justice et police</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale di giustizia e polizia</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Justice and Police</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.ejpd.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.ejpd.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.ejpd.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.ejpd.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-ejpd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">Info@gs-ejpd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-ejpd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-ejpd.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <department id="601">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Finanzdepartement</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des finances</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale delle finanze</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Finance</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.efd.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.dff.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.efd.admin.ch/efd/it/home.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.efd.admin.ch/efd/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Coronavirus: Bundesrat verstärkt die Massnahmen gegen die Pandemie</title>
      <lead>Ab Montag, 6. Dezember 2021, wird in der Schweiz die Zertifikats- und Maskenpflicht ausgeweitet, die Home-Office-Empfehlung verstärkt sowie die Gültigkeit von Antigen-Schnelltests verkürzt. Ausserdem erhalten zertifikatspflichtige Veranstaltungen und Einrichtungen die Möglichkeit, den Zutritt auf geimpfte und genesene Personen zu beschränken und damit auf die Maskenpflicht zu verzichten. Dies hat der Bundesrat nach Konsultation der Kantone, der Sozialpartner und der zuständigen Parlamentskommissionen an seiner Sitzung vom 3. Dezember 2021 entschieden. Er reagiert damit auf die starke Zunahme von Covid-19-Patientinnen und -Patienten in den Spitälern und auf das Auftreten der neuen Omikron-Virusvariante. Die neuen Massnahmen sind bis am 24. Januar 2022 befristet. Zudem gilt bei der Einreise eine verschärfte Testpflicht. Dafür werden ab morgen 4. Dezember 2021 alle Länder von der aktuellen Quarantäneliste gestrichen.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Die Infektionen nehmen seit einigen Wochen stark zu. Neben lokalen Ausbrüchen hauptsächlich in Schulen sowie in Alters- und Pflegeheimen breitet sich das Virus auch wieder in der breiten Bevölkerung aus. In den letzten Wochen ist auch die Zahl der schweren Erkrankungen und damit der Druck auf den Intensivstationen wieder stark gestiegen. Bei Geimpften und Genesenen ist der Verlauf der Infektion in der Regel milde. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Der Bundesrat beurteilt die Situation derzeit als sehr kritisch. Das Auftreten der Omikron-Variante stellt zudem neue Anforderungen an die Pandemiebekämpfung. Die Variante wurde am 26. November 2021 von der WHO als besorgniserregend eingestuft. Es ist davon auszugehen, dass sie hoch ansteckend ist, und es ist möglich, dass auch Personen angesteckt werden können, die gegen die Delta-Variante immun sind. Unklar ist auch, wie gut die Impfung vor schweren Verläufen schützt und wie gefährlich die neue Variante ist.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ziel: Spitäler entlasten&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;Mit den verstärkten Massnahmen will der Bundesrat die Ansteckungen mit der Delta-Variante reduzieren, damit die Spitalstrukturen so gut wie möglich entlastet werden. Die Massnahmen sind vorerst bis am 24. Januar 2022 befristet. Um die Spitäler zu entlasten, bleibt die Impfung das beste Mittel. Wichtig ist zudem die rasche Auffrischimpfung. Der Bundesrat hat folgende Massnahmen beschlossen:&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ausweitung der Zertifikatspflicht &lt;br /&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;Das Zertifikat belegt, dass jemand geimpft, genesen oder negativ getestet ist (3G). Es reduziert das Übertragungsrisiko stark. Die Zertifikatsplicht gilt neu in Innenräumen für alle öffentlichen Veranstaltungen sowie für alle sportlichen und kulturellen Aktivitäten von Laien. Die bestehende Ausnahme für beständige Gruppen unter 30 Personen wird aufgehoben. Zudem gilt neu bei Veranstaltungen im Freien bereits ab 300 Teilnehmenden eine Zertifikatspflicht. Bisher lag die Grenze bei 1000 Teilnehmenden. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Erfahrungen zeigen, dass das Risiko einer Ansteckung im privaten Rahmen beträchtlich ist. Bei Treffen im Familien- und Freundeskreis in Innenbereichen gilt künftig ab 11 Personen die dringliche Empfehlung, das Zertifikat einzusetzen. Für den Bundesrat ist es wichtig, dass die Bevölkerung im privaten Bereich, insbesondere an Familienanlässen, besonders vorsichtig ist.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ausweitung der Maskenpflicht&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;Die Maske hat sich als einfaches und kostengünstiges Mittel bewährt, um die Übertragung des Virus zu verhindern. Eine Maskenpflicht gilt drinnen neu überall dort, wo eine Zertifikatspflicht gilt - ausser bei privaten Treffen.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Möglichkeit zur Beschränkung auf 2G &lt;br /&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;Wo Maskentragen nicht möglich ist, ist besondere Vorsicht geboten. Es gelten deshalb Ersatzmassnahmen: eine Sitzpflicht für die Konsumation im Restaurant oder das Erheben der Kontaktdaten bei Kultur- und Sportaktivitäten wie Chorproben oder Hallentrainings.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Alle öffentlichen Einrichtungen mit Zertifikatspflicht sowie alle Veranstaltungen innen und aussen haben zudem die Möglichkeit, den Zutritt auf geimpfte und genesene Personen (2G) zu beschränken und auf eine Maskenpflicht zu verzichten Geimpfte und genesene Personen sind deutlich weniger ansteckend und nach einer Ansteckung mit einer sehr hohen Wahrscheinlichkeit von einem schweren Verlauf oder einer Hospitalisation geschützt. Zu diesem Zweck muss die Prüf-App für die Covid-Zertifikate erweitert werden. Diese Anpassung wird erst per 13. Dezember 2021 zur Verfügung stehen. Bis dann müssen die Betreiber der Einrichtungen oder die Veranstalter manuell prüfen, ob die entsprechende Person geimpft oder genesenen ist. Ein freiwilliger Einsatz der 2G-Regel wurde in der Konsultation gewünscht, unter anderem weil etwa in Discos ein Betrieb mit Sitzpflicht bei Konsumation nicht wirtschaftlich sei.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dringliche Home-Office-Empfehlung&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;Um die Kontakte am Arbeitsplatz zu reduzieren, gilt eine dringliche Home-Office-Empfehlung. Zudem müssen alle Mitarbeitende in Innenräumen eine Maske tragen, in denen sich mehrere Personen aufhalten. Die grosse Mehrheit der Kantone und der Sozialpartner hat sich gegen eine Home-Office-Pflicht ausgesprochen. Eine verbindliche Regelung hätte epidemiologisch den stärkeren Effekt als die Empfehlung.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Beschränkung der Gültigkeitsdauer der Testzertifikate&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;Die Gültigkeitsdauer der Antigen-Schnelltests wird von 48 Stunden auf 24 Stunden reduziert - ab dem Zeitpunkt der Probeentnahme. Die kürzere Gültigkeit erhöht die Aussagekraft der Testresultate; die Zeitdauer, in welcher Personen mit gültigem Testzertifikat infektiös werden können, wird dadurch stark reduziert. PCR-Tests sind nach wie vor 72 Stunden gültig.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Aufhebung der Kapazitätsbeschränkungen&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;Gemäss einer Vorgabe des Covid-19-Gesetzes sind Kapazitätsbeschränkungen für öffentlich zugängliche Einrichtungen und Betriebe sowie Veranstaltungen und private Zusammenkünfte aufzuheben, sobald der impfwillige erwachsene Teil der Bevölkerung «ausreichend geimpft» ist. Diese Bestimmung hat das Parlament im Rahmen der Beratungen in der Sommersession 2021 beschlossen. Nach den Anstrengungen der Kantone und des Bundes im Zusammenhang mit der Impfwoche, muss davon ausgegangen werden, dass die impfwilligen Personen ab 12 Jahren in der Schweiz geimpft sind. Dem Bundesrat ist es aufgrund der Vorgabe des Covid-19-Gesetzes nicht mehr möglich, aus epidemischer Sicht wünschenswerte Kapazitätsbeschränkungen anzuordnen, namentlich in Innenräumen. Deshalb werden die verbleibenden Kapazitätsbeschränkungen aufgehoben, etwa für religiöse Zusammenkünfte, im Bildungsbereich und für Veranstaltungen draussen. Die Kantone können weiterhin Kapazitätsbeschränkungen vorsehen. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Verzicht Testpflicht an Schulen &lt;br /&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;Der Bundesrat verzichtet nach der Konsultation darauf, alle Schulen der obligatorischen Schulen und der Sekundarstufe II zu verpflichten, repetitive Tests anzubieten. 17 von 26 Kantonen lehnten eine solche Verpflichtung ab. Der Bundesrat ist von der Wirksamkeit repetitiver Tests überzeugt. Mit diesen können Ansteckungen früh entdeckt und Übertragungsketten unterbrochen werden. Damit wird auch die Gefahr reduziert, dass Schulen geschlossen oder ganze Klassen in den Fernunterricht geschickt werden müssen.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Zusammenarbeit von Bund und Kantonen bestätigt&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;Fast alle Kantone sind mit den strategischen Grundsätzen der Zusammenarbeit von Bund und Kantonen, die im Oktober 2020 vereinbart wurden, weiterhin einverstanden. Eine grosse Mehrheit ist zudem bereit, weitergehende Massnahmen zu ergreifen, falls die Massnahmen auf Bundeseben aufgrund von regional ausgeprägten Veränderungen nicht ausreichen sollten.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Einreise: Quarantäne aufgehoben , Testpflicht verstärkt&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;Der Bundesrat hat an seiner Sitzung auch die Einreisebestimmungen geändert. Ab morgen Samstag, 4. Dezember 2021, werden sämtliche Länder von der Quarantäneliste gestrichen. Um die Einschleppung der neuen Omikron-Variante weiterhin möglichst zu verhindern, gilt bei sämtlichen Einreisen in die Schweiz neu ein verschärftes Testregime. Diese Testpflicht gilt auch für geimpfte und genesene Personen. Neben einem PCR-Test vor der Einreise ist ein zweiter Test (PCR-Test oder Antigenschnelltest) zwischen dem vierten und dem siebten Tag nach der Einreisedurchzuführen. Mit diesem Test wird sichergestellt, dass infizierte Personen, die sich kurz vor oder während der Reise mit dem Virus&lt;br /&gt;angesteckt haben, erkannt werden. Die Testkosten müssen von den Einreisenden selber getragen werden.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Nicht geimpften Drittstaatsangehörigen, die aus Risikoländern oder -regionen in den Schengen-Raum einreisen wollen, wird die Einreise in die Schweiz für vorübergehende Aufenthalte ohne Erwerbstätigkeit bis zu 90 Tagen innerhalb eines Zeitraums von 180 Tagen - abgesehen von gewissen Ausnahmen (Härtefälle) - verweigert. Betroffen sind insbesondere Tourismus- und Besuchsaufenthalte. Die Liste der Risikoländer und Regionen ist im Anhang 1 der Covid-19-Verordnung 3 aufgeführt. Sie wird unter Berücksichtigung der Empfehlungen der EU-Kommission für die Schengen-Staaten laufend aktualisiert. &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Bundesamt für Gesundheit BAG www.bag.admin.ch media@bag.admin.ch Infoline Coronavirus +41 58 463 00 00 Infoline Covid-19-Impfung +41 58 377 88 92</contact>
      <attachment id="224545">
        <title>Grafik</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>388</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/69384.pdf</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="224549">
        <title>FAQ – Massnahmen</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>139</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/69408.pdf</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="224553">
        <title>FAQ - Neue Regeln bei der Einreise in die Schweiz</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>136</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/69389.pdf</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="224557">
        <title>Covid-19-Verordnung besondere Lage</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>491</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/69396.pdf</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="224561">
        <title>Covid-19-Verordnung internationaler Personenverkehr</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>423</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/69400.pdf</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </attachment>
      <revisions>
        <revision date="2021-12-03 14:50" type="R"/>
      </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Coronavirus : le Conseil fédéral renforce les mesures de lutte contre la pandémie</title>
      <lead>Dès lundi 6 décembre 2021, l’utilisation du certificat et l’obligation du port du masque seront étendues, la recommandation de travail à domicile renforcée et la durée de validité des tests rapides réduite. Par ailleurs, les manifestations et les établissements soumis à l’obligation de certificat pourront restreindre l’accès aux seules personnes vaccinées et guéries, et renoncer ainsi au port du masque. C’est ce qu’a décidé le Conseil fédéral lors de sa séance du 3 décembre 2021 après avoir pris connaissance des résultats de la consultation des cantons, des partenaires sociaux et des commissions parlementaires compétentes. Il réagit ainsi à la forte hausse de patients atteints du COVID-19 dans les hôpitaux et à l’apparition du nouveau variant Omicron. Les nouvelles mesures seront valables jusqu’au 24 janvier 2022. En outre, dès samedi 4 décembre 2021, l’obligation de test sera renforcée pour entrer sur le territoire suisse. En revanche, plus aucun pays ne figure sur la liste des pays concernés par une quarantaine.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Depuis quelques semaines, les infections augmentent fortement. Outre des foyers apparus localement, surtout dans les écoles et les EMS, le virus recommence à circuler dans la population. Ces dernières semaines, le nombre de cas graves a également de nouveau augmenté et, avec lui, la pression sur les soins intensifs. Chez les personnes vaccinées ou guéries, la maladie est généralement bénigne. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Le Conseil fédéral estime que la situation actuelle est très critique. L'apparition du variant Omicron pose par ailleurs de nouveaux défis. Celui-ci a été considéré comme préoccupant par l'Organisation mondiale de la santé (OMS) le 26 novembre. Il faut s'attendre à ce qu'il soit hautement contagieux et qu'il soit susceptible d'infecter des personnes immunisées contre le variant Delta. On ignore encore dans quelle mesure le vaccin protège contre les formes graves de la maladie et quelle est la dangerosité du nouveau variant.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Objectif : décharger les hôpitaux&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;Avec les nouvelles mesures, le Conseil fédéral souhaite réduire la circulation du variant Delta afin de préserver autant que possible les structures hospitalières. Dans un premier temps, ces mesures seront valables jusqu'au 24 janvier 2022. La vaccination reste le meilleur moyen de décharger les hôpitaux. Il est aussi important de procéder rapidement aux doses de rappel.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Le Conseil fédéral a pris les mesures suivantes :&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Extension du certificat COVID &lt;br /&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;Le certificat permet d'attester qu'une personne est vaccinée, guérie ou testée négative. Il réduit fortement le risque de contamination. Il sera désormais obligatoire pour accéder aux espaces intérieurs de toutes les manifestations publiques et pour participer à toutes les activités sportives et culturelles d'amateurs en intérieur. L'exception en vigueur aujourd'hui pour les groupes fixes jusqu'à 30 personnes est supprimée. Par ailleurs, le certificat devient obligatoire pour les événements en plein air dès 300 personnes. Jusqu'à présent, la limite était fixée à 1000 personnes. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;L'expérience montre que le risque d'infection dans le cadre privé est considérable. Il est vivement recommandé d'utiliser le certificat pour les rencontres privées en famille et entre amis se tenant à l'intérieur et réunissant plus de dix personnes. Pour le Conseil fédéral, il est important que la population soit très prudente dans le cadre privé, en particulier lors de fêtes de famille. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Extension de l'obligation du port du masque&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;Le masque s'est révélé un moyen simple et peu coûteux d'empêcher la transmission du virus. Il sera désormais obligatoire à l'intérieur partout où le certificat l'est aussi, à l'exception des rencontres privées.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Possibilité de restreindre l'accès aux manifestations et aux établissements aux seules personnes vaccinées et guéries&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;Une prudence particulière s'impose dans les endroits où le port du masque n'est pas possible. C'est pourquoi, en lieu et place du port du masque, les clients des restaurants auront l'obligation de consommer assis et il faudra collecter les coordonnées des personnes participant à des activités culturelles ou sportives telles que répétitions de chorales ou entraînements en salle.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Par ailleurs, tous les établissements publics et tous les événements se déroulant à l'intérieur ou en plein air auront désormais la possibilité de restreindre l'accès aux seules personnes vaccinées et guéries, et pourront ainsi renoncer à l'obligation de porter un masque. Les personnes vaccinées ou guéries sont nettement moins contagieuses et, en cas d'infection, elles ont beaucoup moins de risque de subir une forme grave ou d'être hospitalisées. Pour pouvoir appliquer cette mesure, il faudra adapter l'application de vérification du certificat COVID. Cette adaptation ne sera pas disponible avant le 13 décembre 2021. Jusque là, les exploitants d'établissements ou les organisateurs d'événements devront vérifier manuellement si les personnes sont vaccinées ou guéries. Cette mesure émane de la consultation : l'obligation de consommer assis ne serait pas viable économiquement pour certains acteurs, par exemple pour les discothèques.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Recommandation de réintroduire le travail à domicile&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;Pour limiter les contacts sur le lieu de travail, le Conseil fédéral recommande instamment de réintroduire le travail à domicile. Par ailleurs, tous les collaborateurs doivent porter un masque dans les locaux qui sont partagés par plusieurs personnes. La grande majorité des cantons et des partenaires sociaux se sont opposés à l'introduction d'une obligation de travailler à domicile. Du point de vue épidémiologique, une réglementation contraignante aurait de meilleurs effets qu'une recommandation.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Réduction de la durée de validité des certificats obtenus à la suite d'un test&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;La durée de validité des tests rapides antigéniques passe de 48 à 24 heures à compter du prélèvement de l'échantillon. Cette mesure permet d'accroître la pertinence des résultats des tests et de réduire fortement le laps de temps durant lequel les personnes munies d'un certificat de test valide peuvent être infectieuses. Les tests PCR restent valables 72 heures.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Suppression des restrictions de capacités&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;Conformément à la loi COVID-19, les restrictions de capacité applicables aux établissements et aux entreprises accessibles au public ainsi qu'aux manifestations et aux rassemblements privés doivent être levées si la population adulte souhaitant être vaccinée a reçu une dose suffisante de vaccin. Cette disposition a été adoptée par le Parlement lors de la session d'été 2021. Au vu des efforts entrepris par les cantons et la Confédération lors de la semaine de vaccination, on peut partir du principe que toutes les personnes de plus de 12 ans vivant en Suisse qui le souhaitent ont été vaccinées. Dès lors, le Conseil fédéral n'est légalement plus en mesure de décréter les restrictions de capacité qui s'imposeraient d'un point de vue épidémiologique, notamment pour les lieux clos. Les restrictions restantes, qui concernent par exemple les rassemblements religieux, le domaine de la formation, les manifestations extérieures, sont donc supprimées. Les cantons, eux, peuvent continuer à prévoir des restrictions de capacité.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pas d'obligation de dépistage dans les écoles&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;À la suite de la consultation, le Conseil fédéral renonce à imposer les dépistages répétés à l'école obligatoire et au secondaire II. Si 17 des 26 cantons se sont opposés à une telle obligation, le Conseil fédéral reste quant à lui convaincu de l'efficacité de ces tests qui permettent de&lt;br /&gt;détecter plus tôt les infections et de casser les chaînes de contamination, limitant par conséquent aussi le risque de devoir fermer des écoles et faire passer des classes entières à l'enseignement à distance.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Collaboration entre la Confédération et les cantons confirmée&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;Presque tous les cantons continuent d'approuver les principes stratégiques de la collaboration Confédération - cantons tels que définis en octobre 2020. Une large majorité d'entre eux est par ailleurs prête à prendre des mesures supplémentaires si les mesures de la Confédération devaient ne pas suffire en raison de fortes disparités régionales.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Entrée sur le territoire : suppression des quarantaines, renforcement des obligations de dépistage&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;Lors de sa séance, le Conseil fédéral a aussi modifié les conditions d'entrée sur le territoire. Demain, samedi 4 décembre 2021, plus aucun pays ne figurera sur la liste des pays concernés par une quarantaine. Mais pour prévenir autant que possible l'importation du variant, les exigences de dépistage qui s'appliquent à l'entrée en Suisse sont durcies. Toutes les personnes entrant sur le territoire, y compris les vaccinées et les guéries, doivent se faire tester. Outre un test PCR avant leur entrée, elles devront procéder à un deuxième test, PCR ou antigénique, entre le quatrième et le septième jour après leur arrivée. Ce deuxième test vise à garantir la détection des personnes qui se seraient infectées juste avant de partir ou pendant leur voyage. Ces dépistages sont à la charge des personnes concernées&lt;strong&gt;.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Les ressortissants d'États tiers non vaccinés qui souhaitent entrer en Suisse depuis un pays à risque ou une région de l'espace Schengen pour des séjours temporaires sans activité lucrative de 90 jours au plus au cours d'une période de 180 jours ne pourront pas le faire, sauf exception (cas de rigueur). Cette interdiction concerne les voyages touristiques et les visites à des proches. La liste des pays et des régions à risque figure à l'annexe 1 de l'ordonnance 3 COVID-19. Elle est actualisée régulièrement en fonction des recommandations de la Commission européenne pour les États de l'espace Schengen.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Office fédéral de la santé publique OFSP www.ofsp.admin.ch media@bag.admin.ch Infoline coronavirus +41 58 463 00 00 Infoline sur la vaccination COVID-19 +41 58 377 88 92</contact>
      <attachment id="224546">
        <title>Graphique</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>379</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/69385.pdf</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="224550">
        <title>FAQ - Mesures</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>135</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/69409.pdf</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="224554">
        <title>FAQ - Nouvelles règles d'entrée en Suisse</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>134</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/69390.pdf</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="224558">
        <title>Ordonnance COVID-19 situation particulière</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>545</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/69397.pdf</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="224562">
        <title>Ordonnance COVID-19 transport international de voyageurs</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>422</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/69401.pdf</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </attachment>
      <revisions>
        <revision date="2021-12-03 15:42" type="R"/>
        <revision date="2021-12-03 14:50" type="R"/>
      </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Coronavirus: il Consiglio federale rafforza i provvedimenti contro la pandemia</title>
      <lead>Da lunedì 6 dicembre 2021 saranno estesi l’obbligo del certificato e l’obbligo della mascherina, rafforzata la raccomandazione del telelavoro e ridotta la durata di validità dei test antigenici rapidi. Inoltre, le manifestazioni e le strutture soggette all’obbligo del certificato avranno la possibilità di limitare l’accesso alle persone vaccinate o guarite e quindi di rinunciare all’obbligo della mascherina. È quanto ha deciso il Consiglio federale nella seduta del 3 dicembre 2021, dopo aver consultato i Cantoni, le parti sociali e le commissioni parlamentari competenti. Con queste contromisure intende reagire al forte aumento dei pazienti COVID-19 ricoverati negli ospedali e alla comparsa della variante Omicron. I nuovi provvedimenti resteranno in vigore fino al 24 gennaio 2022. Sarà inoltre inasprito il regime dei test per chi entra in Svizzera. In compenso, da domani, 4 dicembre 2021, saranno stralciati tutti i Paesi dall’elenco degli Stati e delle regioni per i quali vige l’obbligo della quarantena.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Da qualche settimana i contagi stanno aumentando rapidamente. Oltre a causare focolai circoscritti, soprattutto nelle scuole e nelle case per anziani o di cura, il virus ha ripreso a diffondersi in tutta la popolazione. Nelle ultime settimane è fortemente aumentato anche il numero di casi gravi e con esso la pressione sui reparti di terapia intensiva. Tra le persone vaccinate o guarite il decorso della malattia è generalmente blando. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Il Consiglio federale giudica molto critica l'attuale situazione. La comparsa della variante Omicron ha inoltre complicato la lotta alla pandemia. Scoperta il 26 novembre, la nuova variante è stata classificata come preoccupante dall'Organizzazione mondiale della sanità. Si deve ritenere&lt;br /&gt;che sia molto contagiosa ed è possibile che anche persone immunizzate contro la variante Delta possano esserne infettate. Non è inoltre chiaro quanto sia pericolosa e in che misura il vaccino protegga da decorsi gravi.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;b&gt;Obiettivo: sgravare gli ospedali&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/b&gt;Con il rafforzamento dei provvedimenti, il Consiglio federale intende ridurre i contagi con la variante Delta per sgravare il più possibile le strutture ospedaliere. La validità dei nuovi provvedimenti è per ora limitata al 24 gennaio 2022. Il miglior modo per sgravare gli ospedali resta comunque la vaccinazione ed è importante procedere rapidamente al richiamo. Il Consiglio federale ha deciso i seguenti provvedimenti:&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Estensione dell'obbligo del certificato &lt;br /&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;Il certificato documenta che una persona è vaccinata, guarita o risultata negativa al test. Riduce dunque considerevolmente il rischio di contagio. Dal 6 dicembre sarà obbligatorio per tutte le manifestazioni pubbliche e le attività sportive o culturali amatoriali al chiuso. La deroga vigente per i gruppi a composizione stabile di meno di 30 persone è abrogata. Inoltre, per le manifestazioni all'aperto il certificato sarà obbligatorio già a partire da 300 participanti e non più a partire da 1000. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Le esperienze maturate dall'inizio della pandemia dimostrano che nella sfera privata il rischio di contagio è alto. A partire da 11 persone è pertanto raccomandato di richiedere il certificato anche per gli incontri in famiglia o tra amici al chiuso. Per il Consiglio federale è importante che la popolazione sia particolarmente prudente in ambito privato, soprattutto in occasione di eventi familiari.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;b&gt;Estensione dell'obbligo della mascherina&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/b&gt;Strumento semplice e poco costoso, la mascherina si è dimostrata un mezzo efficace nel contenimento della diffusione del virus. Al chiuso sarà obbligatoria dovunque viga l'obbligo del certificato, ad eccezione degli incontri privati.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Possibilità di limitare l'accesso alle persone vaccinate o guarite&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;Dove non è possibile indossare la mascherina è necessaria molta prudenza. Sono pertanto introdotti provvedimenti alternativi: l'obbligo di stare seduti durante la consumazione nei ristoranti o la rilevazione dei dati di contatto dei partecipanti ad attività culturali o sportive come prove di cori o allenamenti al chiuso.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Per tutte le strutture pubbliche soggette all'obbligo del certificato e tutte le manifestazioni al chiuso e all'aperto è inoltre prevista la possibilità di limitare l'accesso alle persone vaccinate o guarite e di rinunciare quindi all'obbligo della mascherina. Le persone vaccinate o guarite sono molto meno contagiose e, se contagiate, hanno un'alta probabilità di non ammalarsi gravemente e di non essere dunque ricoverate in ospedale. Per agevolare la limitazione dell'accesso alle persone vaccinate o guarite dovrà essere estesa l'app di controllo del certificato COVID. L'adeguamento sarà disponibile soltanto il 13 dicembre. Fino ad allora i gestori delle strutture e gli organizzatori di manifestazioni dovranno verificare manualmente se i presenti sono vaccinati o guariti. La limitazione facoltativa dell'accesso alle persone vaccinate o guarite è stata auspicata in sede di consultazione, tra l'altro perché l'obbligo di stare seduti durante la consumazione danneggerebbe economicamente, per esempio, le discoteche.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fortemente raccomandato il telelavoro&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;Per ridurre i contatti sul posto di lavoro è fortemente raccomandato il telelavoro. Inoltre, tutti i dipendenti devono indossare la mascherina negli spazi chiusi in cui sono presenti più persone. I Cantoni e le parti sociali si sono espressi a larga maggioranza contro l'obbligo del telelavoro. Dal punto di vista epidemiologico una regola vincolante sarebbe più efficace della raccomandazione.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Riduzione della durata di validità dei certificati di test negativo&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;La validità dei test antigenici rapidi è ridotta da 48 a 24 ore a partire dal prelievo del campione. Questo provvedimento aumenta l'attendibilità dei risultati, poiché il periodo di tempo in cui una persona con un certificato di test valido potrebbe diventare contagiosa è ora fortemente ridotto. I test PCR continuano ad essere validi per 72 ore.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Revocate le limitazioni della capienza&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;Conformemente a una prescrizione della legge COVID-19, se la popolazione adulta che lo desidera è stata «debitamente vaccinata», le limitazioni della capienza previste per strutture e aziende aperte al pubblico, manifestazioni e incontri privati devono essere revocate. Questa disposizione è stata adottata dal Parlamento durante le deliberazioni della sessione estiva 2021. Dopo gli sforzi dei Cantoni e della Confederazione durante la settimana di vaccinazione, si deve partire dal presupposto che le persone di età superiore ai 12 anni che lo desideravano siano state vaccinate. A causa della prescrizione della legge COVID-19, il Consiglio federale non può più disporre le limitazioni della capienza opportune dal punto di vista epidemiologico, soprattutto nei luoghi al chiuso. Per questo motivo le limitazioni della capienza ancora vigenti, per esempio per gli incontri religiosi, l'ambito della formazione e le manifestazioni all'aperto, saranno revocate. I Cantoni possono però continuare a prevedere limitazioni della capienza.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rinuncia all'obbligo del test nelle scuole&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;Poiché 17 Cantoni su 26 hanno respinto la proposta, il Consiglio federale rinuncia a richiedere alle scuole dell'obbligo e del livello secondario II di offrire test ripetuti. Resta però convinto dell'efficacia dei test ripetuti per identificare precocemente i contagi e interrompere le catene di trasmissione. Grazie ai test si ridurrebbe anche il rischio di dover chiudere le scuole o ricorrere nuovamente all'insegnamento a distanza.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Confermata la collaborazione tra Confederazione e Cantoni&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;Quasi tutti i Cantoni continuano ad essere d'accordo con i principi strategici di cooperazione tra la Confederazione e i Cantoni concordati nell'ottobre del 2020. Una grande maggioranza è inoltre disposta ad adottare provvedimenti più restrittivi, nel caso in cui quelli presi a livello federale non fossero sufficienti a causa degli sviluppi epidemiologici regionali.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Entrata in Svizzera: abrogata la quarantena, rafforzato l'obbligo del test&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;Nella seduta il Consiglio federale ha modificato anche le disposizioni per l'entrata in Svizzera. Da domani, sabato 4 dicembre, saranno stralciati tutti i Paesi dall'elenco degli Stati e delle regioni per i quali vige l'obbligo della quarantena .&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Per continuare a contenere il più possibile la diffusione della variante Omicron nel nostro Paese, il regime dei test per l'entrata in Svizzera è stato inasprito. L'obbligo del test vige ora anche per le persone vaccinate o guarite. Oltre a doversi sottoporre a un test PCR prima dell'entrata in Svizzera, occorre eseguire un secondo test (PCR o antigenico rapido) anche tra il quarto e il settimo giorno dopo l'arrivo. In questo modo si può garantire che le persone che sono state contagiate poco prima o durante il viaggio siano identificate. I costi del test sono a carico dei viaggiatori.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ai cittadini di Stati terzi non vaccinati che desiderano entrare nello spazio Schengen da Paesi o regioni considerati a rischio è vietata l'entrata in Svizzera per soggiorni temporanei senza attività lavorativa fino a 90 giorni in un periodo di 180 giorni, ad eccezione di determinate deroghe (casi di rigore). Questo vale in particolare per il turismo e i soggiorni di visita. L'elenco dei Paesi e delle regioni a rischio è riportato nell'allegato 1 dell'ordinanza 3 COVID-19 ed è continuamento aggiornato in base alle raccomandazioni della Commissione europea per gli Stati Schengen.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Ufficio federale della sanità pubblica UFSP www.ufsp.admin.ch media@bag.admin.ch Infoline coronavirus +41 58 463 00 00 Infoline vaccinazione COVID-19 +41 58 377 88 92</contact>
      <attachment id="224547">
        <title>Grafico</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>374</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/69386.pdf</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="224551">
        <title>FAQ - provvedimenti</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>133</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/69410.pdf</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="224555">
        <title>FAQ - Nuove regole per l’entrata in Svizzera</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>132</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/69391.pdf</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="224559">
        <title>Ordinanza COVID-19 situazione particolare</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>715</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/69398.pdf</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="224563">
        <title>Ordinanza COVID-19 traffico internazionale viaggiatori</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>419</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/69403.pdf</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </attachment>
      <revisions>
        <revision date="2021-12-03 14:50" type="R"/>
      </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Coronavirus: Federal Council tightens measures against the pandemic</title>
      <lead>From Monday, 6 December, COVID certificates will be required and face masks will have to be worn in a wider range of situations; people will be urged to work from home and the validity of rapid antigen tests will be reduced. Furthermore, at events and venues subject to a certificate requirement, it will be permitted to restrict access to people who have been vaccinated or who have recovered from COVID; guests and customers would then not have to wear masks. These are the decisions taken by the Federal Council at its meeting on 3 December after consulting the cantons, social partners and the relevant parliamentary committees. These measures reflect the sharp rise in the number of COVID-19 patients admitted to hospital and the emergence of the new Omicron variant. The new measures will remain in place until 24 January 2022. In addition, stricter rules on testing will come into force for persons entering the country. In return, all countries will be removed from the current quarantine list.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Infection rates have been rising rapidly for several weeks now. In addition to local outbreaks, mainly in schools and in old people's and nursing homes, the virus is also spreading again among the general population. In recent weeks, the number of severe cases, and consequently the&lt;br /&gt;pressure on intensive care units, has also risen sharply again. The illness is usually mild for those who have been vaccinated and who have already had COVID.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Federal Council considers the current situation to be of great concern. The emergence of the Omicron variant requires an additional pandemic response. The WHO classified Omicron as a variant of concern on 26 November. It is believed to be highly transmissible, and it is possible that people who are immune to the Delta variant could also become infected. It is also unclear how well the vaccination protects against severe cases of the disease and how dangerous the new variant is.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Aim is to relieve pressure on hospitals&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;In tightening the measures, the Federal Council wants to reduce infections with the Delta variant so as to relieve pressure on hospitals as much as possible. The measures are initially limited until 24 January 2022. If these fail to have the desired effect, the Federal Council will decide on further measures. Vaccination remains the best way to relieve the pressure on hospitals. It is also important to get a booster jab as quickly as possible. The Federal Council has decided on the following measures:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Extension of certificate requirement&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;The certificate provides proof that a person has been vaccinated, has recovered from the disease or has tested negative for COVID. It plays a significant part in reducing the risk of transmission. The certificate requirement now applies to all indoor spaces at all public events, as well as&lt;br /&gt;for all amateur sporting and cultural activities. The current exemption for fixed groups of fewer than 30 people is rescinded. A certificate requirement will now apply to outdoor events with over 300 people. The limit until now had been 1,000 people. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Experience has shown that private gatherings pose a significant risk of infection. Indoor gatherings of friends and family attended by 11 or more people will be subject to a certificate requirement. For the Federal Council it is important that the public are particularly careful, especially at private events such as family gatherings.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;b&gt;Extension of requirement to wear masks&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Masks have proven to be a simple and cost-effective means of preventing the transmission of the virus. The requirement to wear a mask now applies in all situations where a certificate requirement applies - except at private gatherings.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Option of limiting access to those vaccinated or recovered &lt;br /&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;Particular care needs to be taken in situations where it is not possible to wear a mask, which is why alternative measures will apply: a seating requirement when consuming food and drink in restaurants or recording the contact details of those attending cultural and sporting activities such as choir practice and indoor training.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;At all public venues and events, whether indoors or outdoors, where a requirement to wear masks and be seated is impracticable or undesirable, it will be permitted to restrict access to people who have been vaccinated or who have recovered from COVID. These people are considered to be far less infectious and are very unlikely to experience a serious case of the disease or need to be admitted to hospital should they become infected. The COVID Certificate Check app will need to be updated to take account of this and the new version will only become available on 13 December. Until then, business owners and event organisers will have to check manually whether or not individuals are vaccinated or have recovered. The option to allow businesses or venues to restrict access to those who are vaccinated or recovered was requested during the consultation on the grounds that operating clubs and discos with a seating requirement is not commercially viable.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;b&gt;Urgent recommendation to work from home&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;To reduce contacts in the workplace, the Federal Council is issuing an urgent recommendation to work from home. In addition, all employees must wear a mask in indoor areas where several people are working. The vast majority of the cantons and the social partners were opposed to a requirement to work from home. A binding rule would have a greater epidemiological impact than a recommendation.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Validity of test certificates shortened&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The validity of rapid antigen tests will be reduced from 48 hours to 24 hours from the time the sample is taken. The reduced validity increases the evidentiary value of the test result; the period in which people with a valid test certificate could be contagious is thereby significantly reduced. PCR tests continue to be valid for 72 hours.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Lifting of capacity restrictions&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;According to a provision of the COVID-19 Act, capacity restrictions for publicly accessible venues and businesses, as well as events and private gatherings, must be lifted as soon as a 'sufficient proportion' of the adult population willing to be vaccinated has been vaccinated. Parliament adopted this provision as part of its deliberations in the summer session. Following the efforts undertaken by the cantons and the federal government as part of its Vaccination Week campaign, it must be assumed that all those over the age of 12 who wish to be vaccinated have done so. Due to the requirement set out in the COVID-19 Act, it is no longer possible for the Federal Council to order capacity restrictions that are desirable from an epidemiological point of view, particularly indoors. Therefore, the remaining capacity restrictions for religious gatherings, in the education sector and for outdoor events will be lifted. The cantons may continue to impose capacity restrictions as they see fit.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Decision to forgo testing requirement at schools&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;Following the consultation, the Federal Council has decided not to require all schools at compulsory and upper secondary level to offer routine tests. 17 out of 26 cantons rejected this requirement. The Federal Council is convinced of the effectiveness of routine testing as it allows infections to be detected at an early stage, thereby interrupting chains of transmission. It also reduces the risk that schools will have to close or that entire classes will be forced to switch to distance learning.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cooperation between federal government and cantons confirmed&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;Almost all of the cantons continue to accept the strategic principles of cooperation between the federal government and the cantons agreed in October 2020. A large majority is also prepared to take further steps if the measures at federal level are not sufficient to address the situation in specific regions.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Entry into Switzerland: Quarantine rule lifted, stricter testing requirement&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;At its meeting, the Federal Council also amended the rules on entry. With effect from Saturday, 4 December, there will be no countries on the quarantine list. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;In order to continue to prevent the new Omicron variant from entering the country as far as possible, a stricter testing regime will now apply for all arrivals into Switzerland. This testing requirement also applies to those who have been vaccinated or have recovered from the disease. In addition to taking a PCR test before travelling, a second test (PCR test or rapid antigen test) must be carried out between the fourth and seventh day after arrival. This test ensures that infected persons who have contracted the virus shortly before or during travel are detected.&lt;br /&gt;Test costs must be borne by the traveller.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Non-vaccinated third-country nationals wishing to enter the Schengen area from countries or regions at risk will be refused entry to Switzerland for short-term stays without gainful employment of up to 90 days within a period of 180 days - apart from certain exceptions (hardship cases). This primarily affects tourism and social visits. The list of high-risk countries and regions is set out in Annex 1 of COVID-19 Ordinance 3. It is updated on an ongoing basis, taking into account the recommendations for the Schengen states issued by the European Commission.</text>
      <contact>Federal Office of Public Health www.bag.admin.ch media@bag.admin.ch COVID-19 Infoline +41 58 463 00 00 COVID-19 Vaccination Infoline +41 58 377 88 92</contact>
      <attachment id="224548">
        <title>Grafic</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>377</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/69392.pdf</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="224552">
        <title>FAQ - Measures</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>158</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/69411.pdf</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="224556">
        <title>FAQ - New rules for entry into Switzerland</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>122</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/69393.pdf</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="224560">
        <title>Ordonnance COVID-19 situation particulière (French)</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>545</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/69399.pdf</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="224564">
        <title>Ordonnance COVID-19 transport international de voyageurs (French)</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>422</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/69402.pdf</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </attachment>
      <revisions>
        <revision date="2021-12-03 14:50" type="R"/>
      </revisions>
    </content>
    <keywords>
      <keyword id="129" org-id="405">
        <name lang="de">Pandemie</name>
        <name lang="fr">Pandémie</name>
        <name lang="it">Pandemia</name>
        <name lang="en">Pandemic</name>
      </keyword>
    </keywords>
    <topics>
      <topic id="5">
        <name lang="de">Behörden</name>
        <name lang="fr">Autorités</name>
        <name lang="it">Autorità</name>
        <name lang="en">Authorities</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="10">
        <name lang="de">Bundesrat</name>
        <name lang="fr">Conseil fédéral</name>
        <name lang="it">Consiglio federale</name>
        <name lang="en">Federal Council</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
