<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="86516" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2021-12-17</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="1070" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>1070</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Der Bundesrat</name>
      <name lang="fr">Conseil fédéral</name>
      <name lang="it">Il Consiglio federale</name>
      <name lang="en">The Federal Council</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.admin.ch/gov/de/start.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.admin.ch/gov/fr/accueil.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.admin.ch/gov/it/pagina-iniziale.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.admin.ch/gov/en/start.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="yes" id="1080" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>701</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Staatssekretariat für Bildung, Forschung und Innovation</name>
      <name lang="fr">Secrétariat d'Etat à la formation, à la recherche et à l'innovation</name>
      <name lang="it">Segreteria di Stato per la formazione, la ricerca e l'innovazione</name>
      <name lang="en">State Secretariat for Education, Research and Innovation</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.sbfi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.sbfi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.sbfi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.sbfi.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@sbfi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@sbfi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@sbfi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@sbfi.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="1070">
      <name lang="de">Der Bundesrat</name>
      <name lang="fr">Conseil fédéral</name>
      <name lang="it">Il Consiglio federale</name>
      <name lang="en">The Federal Council</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.admin.ch/gov/de/start.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.admin.ch/gov/fr/accueil.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.admin.ch/gov/it/pagina-iniziale.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.admin.ch/gov/en/start.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <department id="701">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Wirtschaft, Bildung und Forschung</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'économie, de la formation et de la recherche</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'economia, della formazione e della ricerca</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Economic Affairs, Education and Research</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Grundlage für die nationalen Aktivitäten im Bereich der Raumfahrt präzisiert</title>
      <lead>Der Bundesrat hat am 17. Dezember 2021 die neue Verordnung über die Förderung von nationalen Aktivitäten im Bereich der Raumfahrt (NARV) verabschiedet. Sie wird auf den 1. Februar 2022 in Kraft gesetzt. </lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Die nationalen Aktivitäten von Schweizer Akteuren an Hochschulen und öffentlichen Forschungsinstitutionen im Bereich der Raumfahrt werden seit 2008 vom Bund gefördert. Ziel dieser Aktivitäten ist es, die Position der Schweiz in der Weltraumforschung zu stärken, die Teilnahme der Schweiz an Programmen der Europäischen Weltraumorganisation (ESA) zu optimieren und den wissenschaftlichen, technologischen und finanziellen Rückfluss aus der ESA in die Schweiz zu verbessern. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Das Staatssekretariat für Bildung, Forschung und Innovation unterstützt diese nationalen Aktivitäten. Dabei geht es einerseits darum, Schweizer Akteure durch Beiträge an Forschungs- und Innovationsprojekte im internationalen Wettbewerb langfristig zu positionieren. Andererseits werden die aus Weltraummissionen gewonnenen Daten für die Nutzerinnen und Nutzer in der Schweiz verfügbar gemacht.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Mit der NARV wird die heute erfolgreiche Praxis weitergeführt. Einzig die Rechtsgrundlage wird mit dem Erlass der NARV präzisiert. &lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Kommunikationsdienst GS-WBF info@gs-wbf.admin.ch +41 58 462 20 07</contact>
      <link id="225352">
        <title>Verordnung über die Förderung von nationalen Aktivitäten im Bereich der Raumfahrt (NARV)</title>
        <uri>https://www.sbfi.admin.ch/dam/sbfi/de/dokumente/2021/12/20211217_narv.pdf.download.pdf/20211217_narv_de.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>La base légale relative aux activités nationales dans le domaine spatial a été précisée</title>
      <lead>Le Conseil fédéral a approuvé le 17 décembre 2021 la nouvelle ordonnance sur l’encouragement des activités nationales dans le domaine spatial (OANS). Elle entrera en vigueur le 1er février 2022. </lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;La Confédération encourage depuis 2008 les activités nationales menées par des acteurs suisses dans le domaine spatial au sein des hautes écoles et des institutions de recherche publiques. Ces activités ont pour objectif de renforcer la position de la Suisse dans la recherche spatiale, d’optimiser la participation de la Suisse aux programmes de l’Agence spatiale européenne (ESA) et d’améliorer pour la Suisse les retours scientifique, technologique et financier de l’ESA. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Le Secrétariat d’État à la formation, à la recherche et à l’innovation encourage ces activités nationales. Il s’agit, d’une part, de positionner durablement les acteurs suisses à l’international par le biais de contributions à des projets de recherche et d’innovation et, d’autre part, de mettre les données issues des missions spatiales à la disposition des utilisatrices et des utilisateurs suisses.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;La pratique actuelle, qui a porté ses fruits, peut se poursuivre grâce à l’approbation de l’OANS, qui donne lieu à une base légale précise.&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Service de la communication SG-DEFR info@gs-wbf.admin.ch +41 58 462 20 07</contact>
      <link id="225353">
        <title>Ordonnance sur l’encouragement des activités nationales dans le domaine spatial (OANS)</title>
        <uri>https://www.sbfi.admin.ch/dam/sbfi/fr/dokumente/2021/12/20211217_narv.pdf.download.pdf/20211217_narv_fr.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Le attività nazionali nel settore spaziale riprendono slancio</title>
      <lead>Il 17 dicembre 2021 il Consiglio federale ha approvato la nuova ordinanza sulla promozione delle attività nazionali nel settore spaziale (OPANS), che entrerà in vigore il 1° febbraio 2022. </lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Dal 2008 la Confederazione promuove le attività nazionali nel settore spaziale degli attori svizzeri presso le scuole universitarie e gli istituti di ricerca pubblici. Queste attività puntano a rafforzare la posizione della Svizzera nella ricerca spaziale, a ottimizzare la sua partecipazione ai programmi dell’Agenzia spaziale europea (ESA) e a migliorare il rendimento scientifico, tecnologico e finanziario di cui beneficia in quanto membro dell’ESA.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;La Segreteria di Stato per la formazione, la ricerca e l’innovazione sostiene le attività nazionali nel settore spaziale con un duplice obiettivo: permettere agli attori svizzeri di ottenere, sul lungo periodo, un buon piazzamento nei concorsi scientifici internazionali – grazie ai sussidi per progetti di ricerca e innovazione – e rendere accessibili i dati ricavati dalle missioni spaziali agli utenti in Svizzera.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Con l’emanazione dell’OPANS si intende portare avanti queste pratiche virtuose creando una base legale più specifica. &lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Comunicazione SG-DEFR info@gs-wbf.admin.ch +41 58 462 20 07</contact>
      <link id="225354">
        <title>Ordinanza sulla promozione delle attività nazionali nel settore spaziale (OPANS)</title>
        <uri>https://www.sbfi.admin.ch/dam/sbfi/it/dokumente/2021/12/20211217_narv.pdf.download.pdf/20211217_narv_it.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Clear basis established for national space activities</title>
      <lead>On 17 December, the Federal Council adopted a new ordinance on the promotion of national space activities. This will enter into force on 1 February 2022. </lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;The Confederation has supported national activities in the space field by Swiss players at universities and public research institutions since 2008. The aim of these activities is to strengthen Switzerland's position in space research, optimise the country's participation in European Space Agency (ESA) programmes and improve the scientific, technological and financial return flow from ESA to Switzerland. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The State Secretariat for Education, Research and Innovation supports these national activities. The aim is both to position Swiss players in international competition long term by contributing to research and innovation projects, and to ensure that data obtained from space missions is made available to users in Switzerland.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The new ordinance provides a clearer legal basis on which the established successful practice can be pursued. &lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Communications Service GS-EAER info@gs-wbf.admin.ch +41 58 462 20 07</contact>
      <link id="225352">
        <title>Verordnung über die Förderung von nationalen Aktivitäten im Bereich der Raumfahrt (NARV)</title>
        <uri>https://www.sbfi.admin.ch/dam/sbfi/de/dokumente/2021/12/20211217_narv.pdf.download.pdf/20211217_narv_de.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="225353">
        <title>Ordonnance sur l’encouragement des activités nationales dans le domaine spatial (OANS)</title>
        <uri>https://www.sbfi.admin.ch/dam/sbfi/fr/dokumente/2021/12/20211217_narv.pdf.download.pdf/20211217_narv_fr.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="8">
        <name lang="de">Bildung und Forschung</name>
        <name lang="fr">Formation et recherche</name>
        <name lang="it">Formazione e ricerca</name>
        <name lang="en">Education and Research</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="10">
        <name lang="de">Bundesrat</name>
        <name lang="fr">Conseil fédéral</name>
        <name lang="it">Consiglio federale</name>
        <name lang="en">Federal Council</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="28">
        <name lang="de">Telekommunikation</name>
        <name lang="fr">Télécommunications</name>
        <name lang="it">Telecomunicazione</name>
        <name lang="en">Telecommunications</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="45">
        <name lang="de">Technologie</name>
        <name lang="fr">Technologie</name>
        <name lang="it">Tecnologia</name>
        <name lang="en">Technology</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="47">
        <name lang="de">Wirtschaft</name>
        <name lang="fr">Économie</name>
        <name lang="it">Economia</name>
        <name lang="en">Economic Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
