<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="86499" revoked="no">
    <version>2</version>
    <pubdate>2021-12-16</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="1080" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>701</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Staatssekretariat für Bildung, Forschung und Innovation</name>
      <name lang="fr">Secrétariat d'Etat à la formation, à la recherche et à l'innovation</name>
      <name lang="it">Segreteria di Stato per la formazione, la ricerca e l'innovazione</name>
      <name lang="en">State Secretariat for Education, Research and Innovation</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.sbfi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.sbfi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.sbfi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.sbfi.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@sbfi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@sbfi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@sbfi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@sbfi.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="701">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Wirtschaft, Bildung und Forschung</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'économie, de la formation et de la recherche</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'economia, della formazione e della ricerca</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Economic Affairs, Education and Research</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Teilnahme der Schweiz am 8. Treffen der Fachminister für Bildung der ASEM-Staaten</title>
      <lead>Die Schweiz ist Mitglied des Asia-Europe Meeting ASEM, ein Gesprächsforum, das seit 1996 dem Austausch zwischen Europa und Asien zu den Themen Wirtschaft, Politik, Bildung, Kultur sowie Umwelt- und Klimaschutz dient. Bildung steht seit 2006 als ein Schwerpunktbereich auf der Agenda und wird seit 2008 im Rahmen regelmässiger Fachministertreffen inhaltlich vertieft. Am 15. Dezember 2021 fand das 8. Treffen der Bildungsminister der ASEM-Staaten (sog. ASEMME; Asia-Europe Meeting of Ministers for Education) online statt. Gastgeber war Thailand.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;ASEM ist als informelle Plattform für den Dialog europäischer und asiatischer Staaten konzipiert. Ziel der ministeriellen Gespräche und zweijährlichen Gipfeltreffen der Staats- und Regierungschefs ist ein Austausch über Herausforderungen und Probleme, die sich für beide Kontinente stellen. ASEM umfasst derzeit die EU-Staaten, Norwegen, das Vereinigte Königreich, die Schweiz, die Europäische Union sowie 21 asiatische Staaten und das ASEAN-Sekretariat. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Das 8. Treffen der für Bildung zuständigen Fachminister fand am 15. Dezember 2021 online statt und wurde vom thailändischen Bildungsminister, Treenuch Thienthong eröffnet. Die Schweiz war durch Silvia Studinger, Vizedirektorin des SBFI, vertreten. Das Treffen stand unter dem Leitthema «ASEM Bildung 2030: auf dem Weg zu einer resilienten, prosperierenden und nachhaltigen Zukunft». Ziel war es, sich über bestehende und neue Initiativen und Projekte auszutauschen sowie die ASEM-Bildungsstrategie 2030 und den Aktionsplan zu unterstützen.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Die vier strategischen Ziele der ASEM-Bildungsstrategie 2030 bilden die Grundlage für die Zusammenarbeit im nächsten Jahrzehnt: Dazu gehören die Förderung einer inklusiven und ausgewogenen Mobilität und des Austauschs zwischen Asien und Europa, die Förderung des lebenslangen Lernens, einschliesslich der berufsbezogenen Aus- und Weiterbildung, die Förderung der Entwicklung von Fähigkeiten und Kompetenzen sowie die Schaffung von mehr Transparenz und gegenseitigem Verständnis in Bezug auf Anerkennung, Validierung und Qualitätssicherung. Die Teilnehmenden unterstrichen auch die Bedeutung der Ziele für nachhaltige Entwicklung sowie der Digitalisierung zur Förderung des Austausches und der Zusammenarbeit zwischen Asien und Europa.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Staatssekretariat für Bildung, Forschung und Innovation SBFI Kommunikation medien@sbfi.admin.ch T +41 58 462 96 90</contact>
      <revisions>
        <revision date="2021-12-16 17:27" type="I"/>
      </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>La Suisse participe à la 8e réunion des ministres en charge de l’éducation des pays de l’ASEM</title>
      <lead>La Suisse est membre de l’Asia-Europe Meeting ASEM, un forum de dialogue créé en 1996 entre l’Europe et l’Asie sur les thèmes de l’économie, de la politique, de l’éducation, de la culture, de la protection de l’environnement et de la préservation du climat. L’éducation figure depuis 2006 en bonne place sur l’agenda et fait l’objet depuis 2008 de réunions régulières des ministres en charge de ces dossiers. La 8e réunion des ministres en charge de l’éducation des pays membres de l’Asia-Europe Meeting ASEM (Asia-Europe Meeting of Ministers for Education ASEMME) a été organisée en ligne par la Thaïlande le 15 décembre 2021.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;L’ASEM est une plateforme informelle de dialogue entre pays européens et asiatiques. Les discussions ministérielles et les rencontres bisannuelles des chefs d’État et de gouvernement ont pour but d’échanger sur les défis et les problèmes auxquels font face les deux continents. L’ASEM réunit actuellement les 28 États membres de l’UE, la Norvège, le Royaume-Uni, la Suisse, l’Union européenne, 21 pays d’Asie ainsi que le secrétariat de l’Association des nations d’Asie du Sud-Est (ASEAN). &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;La 8e réunion des ministres de l’éducation, qui a eu lieu par vidéoconférence le 15 décembre 2021, a été ouverte par le ministre thaïlandais de l’Éducation, Treenuch Thienthong. La Suisse était représentée par Silvia Studinger, vice-directrice du Secrétariat d’État à la formation, à la recherche et à l’innovation (SEFRI). La rencontre avait pour thème « ASEM Éducation 2030 : vers un avenir résilient, prospère et durable ». L’objectif était d’échanger sur les initiatives et les projets en cours et à venir ainsi que de soutenir la stratégie 2030 et le plan d’action de l’ASEM en matière d’éducation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Les quatre objectifs de la stratégie Éducation 2030 de l’ASEM sous-tendent la coopération pour la décennie à venir et visent notamment à promouvoir une mobilité et des échanges inclusifs et équilibrés entre l’Asie et l’Europe, à favoriser l’apprentissage tout au long de la vie, y compris la formation et la formation continue dans le domaine professionnel, à encourager le développement des aptitudes et des compétences et à instaurer une plus grande transparence et une compréhension mutuelle en matière de reconnaissance, de validation et d’assurance qualité. Les participants à l’ASEM ont également souligné l’importance des objectifs de développement durable et de la numérisation pour promouvoir les échanges et la coopération entre l’Asie et l’Europe.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Secrétariat d’État à la formation, à la recherche et à l’innovation SEFRI Communication medien@sbfi.admin.ch Tél. : +41 58 462 96 90</contact>
      <revisions>
        <revision date="2021-12-16 17:27" type="I"/>
      </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Switzerland attends 8th ASEM Education Ministers’ Meeting</title>
      <lead>Switzerland is a member of the Asia-Europe Meeting (ASEM), which has served since 1996 as a forum for exchange between Europe and Asia to address economic, political, educational, cultural, environmental and climate issues. Education and training has been one of the priority areas on the agenda since 2006 and has been discussed in detail at regular ministerial meetings since 2008. On 15 December, the 8th Asia-Europe Meeting of Ministers for Education (ASEMME) was held online. The host was Thailand.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;ASEM is designed to serve as an informal platform to foster dialogue between European and Asian states. The aim of the ministerial talks and biennial summits is to exchange views on the challenges and problems facing both continents. ASEM currently comprises the EU Member States, Norway, the United Kingdom, Switzerland, representatives of the European Union as well as 21 Asian states and the ASEAN Secretariat. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The 8th meeting of education ministers was held online on 15 December and was opened by the Thai Minister of Education, Treenuch Thienthong. Switzerland was represented by the Vice Director of SERI, Silvia Studinger. The theme of the meeting was 'ASEM Education 2030: On our way to a resilient, prosperous and sustainable future'. The aim was to exchange views on existing and future initiatives and projects, as well as to support the ASEM Education 2030 Strategy and the corresponding Action Plan.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The four strategic objectives of the ASEM Education 2030 Strategy form the basis for cooperation in this decade. They include promoting inclusive and balanced mobility and exchanges between Asia and Europe, promoting lifelong learning (including vocational education and training), promoting skills development, and increasing transparency and mutual understanding in the areas of recognition, validation and quality assurance. Participants also underlined the importance of these strategic objectives to ensure sustainable development, and of digitalisation to promote exchanges and cooperation between Asia and Europe.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>State Secretariat for Education, Research and Innovation SERI Communication medien@sbfi.admin.ch T+41 58 462 96 90</contact>
      <revisions>
        <revision date="2021-12-16 17:27" type="I"/>
      </revisions>
    </content>
    <keywords>
      <keyword id="325.18" org-id="1080">
        <name lang="de">Akademie der Naturwissenschaften Schweiz</name>
        <name lang="fr">Académie suisse des sciences naturelles</name>
        <name lang="it">Accademia svizzera di scienze naturali</name>
        <name lang="en">Swiss Academy of Sciences</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="325.6" org-id="1080">
        <name lang="de">Bildungsprogramme</name>
        <name lang="fr">Programmes d'éducation</name>
        <name lang="it">Programmi di educazione</name>
        <name lang="en">Educational programmes</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="325.11" org-id="1080">
        <name lang="de">Eidgenössische Technische Hochschule ETH</name>
        <name lang="fr">Ecole polytechnique fédérale EPF</name>
        <name lang="it">Politecnico federale</name>
        <name lang="en">Federal Institutes of Technology</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="325.25" org-id="1080">
        <name lang="de">Euresearch</name>
        <name lang="fr">Euresearch</name>
        <name lang="it">Euresearch</name>
        <name lang="en">Euresearch</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="325.20" org-id="1080">
        <name lang="de">Forschungsförderung</name>
        <name lang="fr">Encouragement de la recherche</name>
        <name lang="it">Promozione della ricerca</name>
        <name lang="en">Research promotion</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="325.9" org-id="1080">
        <name lang="de">Forschungsrahmenprogramme</name>
        <name lang="fr">Programmes-cadre de recherche</name>
        <name lang="it">Programmi quadro di ricerca</name>
        <name lang="en">Research framework programmes</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="325.4" org-id="1080">
        <name lang="de">Hochschullandschaft</name>
        <name lang="fr">Paysage des hautes écoles</name>
        <name lang="it">Panorama universitario</name>
        <name lang="en">University landscape</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="325.26" org-id="1080">
        <name lang="de">OECD</name>
        <name lang="fr">OCDE</name>
        <name lang="it">OCSE</name>
        <name lang="en">OECD</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="325.22" org-id="1080">
        <name lang="de">Raumfahrt</name>
        <name lang="fr">Affaires spatiales</name>
        <name lang="it">Questioni spaziali</name>
        <name lang="en">Space affairs</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="325.16" org-id="1080">
        <name lang="de">Schweizerische Akademie der Geistes- und Sozialwissenschaften</name>
        <name lang="fr">Académie suisse des sciences humaines et sociales</name>
        <name lang="it">Accademia svizzera di scienze morali e sociali</name>
        <name lang="en">Swiss Academy of Humanities and Social Sciences</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="325.17" org-id="1080">
        <name lang="de">Schweizerische Akademie der medizinischen Wissenschaften</name>
        <name lang="fr">Académie suisse des sciences médicales</name>
        <name lang="it">Accademia svizzera delle scienze mediche</name>
        <name lang="en">Swiss Academy of Medical Sciences</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="325.19" org-id="1080">
        <name lang="de">Schweizerische Akademie der technischen Wissenschaften</name>
        <name lang="fr">Académie suisse des sciences techniques</name>
        <name lang="it">Accademia svizzera delle scienze tecniche</name>
        <name lang="en">Swiss Academy of Engineering Sciences</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="325.15" org-id="1080">
        <name lang="de">Schweizerischer Nationalfonds</name>
        <name lang="fr">Fonds national suisse</name>
        <name lang="it">Fondo nazionale Svizzero</name>
        <name lang="en">Swiss National Science Foundation</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="325.12" org-id="1080">
        <name lang="de">Stipendien</name>
        <name lang="fr">Bourses</name>
        <name lang="it">Borse di studio</name>
        <name lang="en">Scholarships</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="325.8" org-id="1080">
        <name lang="de">Technologie</name>
        <name lang="fr">Technologie</name>
        <name lang="it">Tecnologia</name>
        <name lang="en">Technology</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="325.1" org-id="1080">
        <name lang="de">Universitäten</name>
        <name lang="fr">Universités</name>
        <name lang="it">Università</name>
        <name lang="en">Universities</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="325.23" org-id="1080">
        <name lang="de">Weltraum</name>
        <name lang="fr">Espace</name>
        <name lang="it">Spazio</name>
        <name lang="en">Space</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="325.10" org-id="1080">
        <name lang="de">Wissenschaft</name>
        <name lang="fr">Science</name>
        <name lang="it">Scienza</name>
        <name lang="en">Science</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="325.21" org-id="1080">
        <name lang="de">Wissenschaftsaussenpolitik</name>
        <name lang="fr">Politique scientifique extérieure</name>
        <name lang="it">Politica scientifica dell'esterno</name>
        <name lang="en">Foreign scientific policy</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="325.30" org-id="1080">
        <name lang="de">Bildung</name>
        <name lang="fr">Education</name>
        <name lang="it">Educazione</name>
        <name lang="en">Education</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="325.31" org-id="1080">
        <name lang="de">Berufsbildung</name>
        <name lang="fr">Formation professionnelle</name>
        <name lang="it">Formazione professionale</name>
        <name lang="en">Vocational and Professional Education and Training</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="325.33" org-id="1080">
        <name lang="de">Höhere Berufsbildung</name>
        <name lang="fr">Formation professionnelle supérieure</name>
        <name lang="it">Formazione professionale superiore</name>
        <name lang="en">Professional Education and Training</name>
      </keyword>
    </keywords>
    <topics>
      <topic id="8">
        <name lang="de">Bildung und Forschung</name>
        <name lang="fr">Formation et recherche</name>
        <name lang="it">Formazione e ricerca</name>
        <name lang="en">Education and Research</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="29">
        <name lang="de">Umwelt und Natur</name>
        <name lang="fr">Environnement et nature</name>
        <name lang="it">Ambiente e natura</name>
        <name lang="en">Environment and Nature</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="34">
        <name lang="de">Europa</name>
        <name lang="fr">Europe</name>
        <name lang="it">Europa</name>
        <name lang="en">Europe</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="45">
        <name lang="de">Technologie</name>
        <name lang="fr">Technologie</name>
        <name lang="it">Tecnologia</name>
        <name lang="en">Technology</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="47">
        <name lang="de">Wirtschaft</name>
        <name lang="fr">Économie</name>
        <name lang="it">Economia</name>
        <name lang="en">Economic Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
