<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="80743" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2020-10-15</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="1079" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>301</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Bundesamt für Lebensmittelsicherheit und Veterinärwesen</name>
      <name lang="fr">Office fédéral de la sécurité alimentaire et des affaires vétérinaires</name>
      <name lang="it">Ufficio federale della sicurezza alimentare e di veterinaria</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Food Safety and Veterinary Office</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.blv.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.blv.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.blv.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.blv.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">media@blv.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@blv.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@blv.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@blv.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="302" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>301</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Generalsekretariat EDI</name>
      <name lang="fr">Secrétariat général DFI</name>
      <name lang="it">Segreteria generale DFI</name>
      <name lang="en">General Secretariat FDHA</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="301">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement des Innern</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'intérieur</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'interno</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Home Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Die Pelzdeklaration muss verbessert werden</title>
      <lead>Der Bericht zu den Pelzdeklarationskontrollen 2019/2020 zeigt, dass in der Branche immer noch erhebliche Wissenslücken bestehen. Bei Kontrollen durch das Bundesamt für Lebensmittelsicherheit und Veterinärwesen (BLV) wurden 79 % der Verkaufsstellen beanstandet. Aufgrund der gewonnen Erkenntnisse wird das BLV den Vollzug verschärfen, aber auch die Geschäftsstellen verstärkt informieren.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Wie bereits in den Vorjahren führte das BLV in der Periode 2019/2020 seine Kontrollen sowohl bei kleinen Unternehmen und Internetanbietern als auch bei grossen Geschäftsketten durch. Von den durchgeführten 180 Kontrollen führten 142 (79 %) zu Beanstandungen. Bei diesen Beanstandungen wurden in 110 Fällen die Mängel fristgerecht behoben. In 32 Fällen wurde eine Verfügung erlassen und in 4 Fällen ein Strafverfahren eingeleitet. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Pelzjackenkrägen sind am problematischsten&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Insgesamt 6 950 Pelzprodukte wurden in der Periode 2019/20 kontrolliert. Von diesen waren 63 % korrekt deklariert. Die restlichen Pelzprodukte wurden beanstandet, weil sie entweder gar nicht (15 %) oder fehlerhaft deklariert (22 %) waren. Bei den meisten Produkten handelte es sich um Pelzjackenkrägen, die 55 % aller beanstandeten Produkte ausmachten. Die meisten beanstandeten Produkte stammten vom Marderhund, gefolgt von Polarfuchs- und Nerzprodukten.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Kontrollen werden verstärkt&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Seit dem Jahr 2013 führt das BLV Kontrollen durch. Die hohe Zahl an Beanstandungen zeigt, dass viele Verkaufsstellen die Pelzdeklaration noch immer nicht korrekt umsetzen und in der Branche weiterhin beträchtliche Wissenslücken bestehen. Das BLV wird deshalb die Aufklärungsarbeit intensivieren und vor allem den Vollzug verschärfen. So wird etwa die Frist zur Korrektur von mangelhaften Deklarationen verkürzt. Und wenn die Deklaration nach Ablauf der Frist nicht korrekt ist, leitet das BLV rechtliche Schritte ein.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Bessere Information der Kundschaft&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Die Pelzdeklarationsverordnung wurde am 1. April 2020 revidiert. Neue Bestimmungen wurden eingeführt, etwa die Verpflichtung, Produkte eindeutig als «Echtpelz» zu kennzeichnen, wenn sie von Tieren stammen. Das soll es der Kundschaft ermöglichen, 2/2 sofort zu erkennen, ob es sich um Kunst- oder Echtpelz handelt. Die Etikette muss neu fünf Informationen enthalten: die Deklaration «Echtpelz», die zoologische sowie die wissenschaftliche Bezeichnung der Tierart, das Herkunftsland und die Gewinnungsart (d. h. die Methode der Aufzucht oder des Fangens des Tieres, von dem das Fell stammt). Dadurch können die Kundinnen und Kunden ihren Kaufentscheid in voller Kenntnis der Sachlage fällen.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Bundesamt für Lebensmittelsicherheit und Veterinärwesen (BLV) Medienstelle Tel. 058 463 78 98 media@blv.admin.ch</contact>
      <attachment id="206230">
        <title>Etikette Pelzdeklaration</title>
        <format>jpg</format>
        <size-kb>133</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/63262.jpg</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <link id="206238">
        <title>Webseite BLV</title>
        <uri>https://www.blv.admin.ch/blv/de/home/das-blv/auftrag/vollzug/pelzdeklaration.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>La déclaration des fourrures doit être améliorée</title>
      <lead>Les contrôles réalisés sur la déclaration des fourrures en 2019/2020 indiquent que les connaissances des professionnels restent très lacunaires. 79 % des contrôles faits auprès de points de vente ont donné lieu à des contestations de l’Office fédéral de lasécurité alimentaire et des affaires vétérinaires (OSAV). Au vu de ce constat, l’OSAV entend renforcer les mesures d’application de la loi, mais aussi mieux informer les professionnels de la vente.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;A l’instar des années précédentes, l’OSAV a effectué durant la période 2019/20 des contrôles dans tous les types de commerces : petits magasins, ventes en ligne, grandes chaînes. Sur les 180 contrôles effectués, 142 (79 %) n’étaient pas concluants. Dans 110 cas, les manquements ont pu être corrigés dans le délai imparti. 32 cas ont fait l’objet d’une décision administrative et dans 4 cas une procédure pénale a été ouverte.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Cols de fourrure problématiques&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Sur les 6950 produits de pelleterie contrôlés, 63 % étaient déclarés correctement. Les autres produits ont fait l’objet de contestations, soit parce qu’ils ne portaient aucune déclaration (15 %), soit parce que celle-ci était erronée (22 %). Au niveau des types de produits, ce sont les cols de veste qui affichaient le plus souvent des manquements (55 % des problèmes constatés). Concernant l’espèce animale, les produits issus de chien viverrin ont été les plus contestés, suivi par les produits issus de renard polaire et de vison.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Les contrôles seront renforcés&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;L’OSAV effectue des contrôles depuis 2013. Les taux élevés et répétés de contestations indiquent que les fourrures ne sont toujours pas déclarées correctement dans de nombreux points de vente et que les connaissances continuent d’être lacunaires dans la profession. En conséquence, l’OSAV va intensifier le travail d’information et surtout renforcer les mesures d’application du droit. Le délai pour corriger les manquements en matière de déclarations sera par exemple raccourci. Si la déclaration n'est toujours pas correcte dans le délai imparti, l’OSAV engagera des actions judiciaires.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Mieux informer le client&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;L’ordonnance sur la déclaration des fourrures a été révisée le 1er avril 2020. De nouvelles dispositions ont été introduites, par exemple l’obligation d’étiqueter clairement les produits comme « fourrure véritable » s’ils sont issus d’animaux. Celle-ci doit permettre à la clientèle de faire immédiatement la distinction entre fourrure véritable et fourrure synthétique. 2/2 L’étiquette doit par ailleurs désormais contenir cinq informations obligatoires : la mention « fourrure véritable », les désignations zoologique et scientifique de l’espèce animale, le pays de provenance et l’origine (à savoir le mode d’élevage ou de capture de l’animal dont la fourrure est issue). Ces éléments doivent permettre aux clients de prendre une décision en toute connaissance de cause.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Office fédéral de la sécurité alimentaire et des affaires vétérinaires (OSAV) Service médias Tél. 058 463 78 98 media@blv.admin.ch</contact>
      <attachment id="206231">
        <title>Étiquette déclaration de fourrure</title>
        <format>jpg</format>
        <size-kb>120</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/63263.jpg</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <link id="206239">
        <title>Site web OSAV</title>
        <uri>https://www.blv.admin.ch/blv/fr/home/das-blv/auftrag/vollzug/pelzdeklaration.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>La dichiarazione sulle pellicce deve essere migliorata</title>
      <lead>Il rapporto 2019/2020 sui controlli sulle dichiarazioni delle pellicce indica che le conoscenze del settore presentano ancora notevoli lacune. Nei controlli eseguiti dall’Ufficio federale della sicurezza alimentare e di veterinaria (USAV) il 79 % dei punti di vendita è stato oggetto di contestazione. Alla luce di quanto appreso dal rapporto, l’Ufficio federale della sicurezza alimentare e di veterinaria (USAV) intende rendere più rigorosa l’applicazione della legge e fornire maggiori informazioni ai negozi.</lead>
      <text link="no"> Anche nel periodo 2019/2020, come negli anni precedenti, l’USAV ha svolto i propri controlli non solo presso le piccole imprese e i fornitori di servizi Internet, ma anche presso le grandi catene commerciali. Dei 180 controlli effettuati, 142 (79 %) hanno dato luogo a contestazioni. In 110 di questi casi le irregolarità sono state eliminate entro il termine stabilito, mentre in 32 casi è stata emanata una decisione e in 4 casi è stato avviato un procedimento penale. &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;I colli delle giacche sono il prodotto più problematico&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Nel periodo 2019/20 sono stati esaminati complessivamente 6 950 prodotti di pellicceria, il 63 % dei quali è risultato correttamente dichiarato. I restanti prodotti di pellicceria sono stati oggetto di contestazioni perché non recavano alcuna dichiarazione (15 %) o quest’ultima non era corretta (22 %). La contestazione più frequente ha riguardato i colli delle giacche (55 % di tutti i prodotti oggetto di contestazione). I prodotti di pellicceria di gran lunga più contestati sono stati quelli di cane procione, seguiti dalla volpe polare e dai prodotti in visone.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;I controlli saranno intensificati&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/b&gt;L’USAV effettua controlli sulle pellicce dal 2013. Il tasso di contestazioni elevato dimostra che la dichiarazione delle pellicce continua ancora a non essere effettuata correttamente in molti punti di vendita e che le conoscenze degli addetti del settore presentano ancora notevoli lacune. Da qui la decisione dell’USAV di intensificare la sua attività di sensibilizzazione e soprattutto di rendere più rigorosa l’applicazione della legge. In concreto, il termine per la correzione delle dichiarazioni irregolari sarà ridotto e se la dichiarazione non risulterà corretta alla scadenza del termine, l’USAV procederà per vie legali. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Migliori informazioni per la clientela&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;La versione rivista dell’ordinanza sulla dichiarazione delle pellicce e dei prodotti di pellicceria è in vigore dal 1° aprile 2020. Sono state introdotte nuove disposizioni, come l’obbligo di contrassegnare chiaramente il prodotto come «vera pelliccia» se è derivato da animali. Ciò dovrebbe consentire ai clienti di riconoscere immediatamente se si tratta di una pelliccia vera o sintetica. L’etichetta deve contenere ora cinque informazioni: la dichiarazione «vera pelliccia», il nome zoologico e scientifico della specie animale, il Paese di origine e il metodo di ottenimento, cioè il metodo di allevamento o di cattura dell’animale da cui proviene la pelliccia). Con queste informazioni i clienti possono decidere se acquistare il prodotto di pellicceria con piena cognizione di causa.&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Ufficio federale della sicurezza alimentare e di veterinaria USAV Servizio stampa Tel. 058 463 78 98 media@blv.admin.ch</contact>
      <attachment id="206234">
        <title>Etichetta per la dichiarazione della pelliccia</title>
        <format>jpg</format>
        <size-kb>133</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/63264.jpg</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <link id="206240">
        <title>Sito web USAV</title>
        <uri>https://www.blv.admin.ch/blv/it/home/das-blv/auftrag/vollzug/pelzdeklaration.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>The declaring of furs needs to be improved</title>
      <lead>The 2019/2020 report on fur declaration inspections shows that significant knowledge gaps remain in the sector. Inspections by the Federal Food Safety and Veterinary Office (FSVO) found deficiencies at 79% of sales outlets. Based on the knowledge gained, the FSVO will provide more information to points of sale but also tighten up on enforcement.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;As in previous years, in 2019/20 the FSVO carried out its inspections in small shops, online outlets and large retail chains alike. Of the 180 inspections carried out, 142 (79%) led to rejections. In 110 of these cases, the shortcomings were rectified within the time limit. Orders were issued in 32 cases and criminal proceedings were instituted in four cases. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Jacket collars are the most problematic fur product&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;In the 2019/20 period, a total of 6,950 fur products were inspected; 63% of these were correctly declared. The remaining products were rejected because they were either not declared at all (15%) or were incorrectly declared (22%). The most problematic fur products were jacket collars, which accounted for 55% of all rejected products. The majority of rejected products were made from raccoon dog fur, followed by arctic fox and mink products.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Inspections to be intensified&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The FSVO has been carrying out inspections since 2013. The high rejection rate shows that fur declarations are still not being implemented correctly at many points of sale and that significant knowledge gaps remain in the sector. The FSVO will therefore intensify its educational work and, above all, tighten up on enforcement. For example, the time limit for correcting defective declarations will be shortened. And if the declaration is still incorrect after the time limit expires, the FSVO will take legal action. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Better information for customers&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The Fur Declaration Ordinance was revised on 1 April 2020. New provisions were introduced, such as the requirement to label products clearly as “real fur” if they are derived from animals. This should enable customers to tell immediately whether the fur is real or artificial. Labels must now contain five items of information: the declaration “real fur”, the zoological name and scientific name of the species, the country of origin and the method of production (i.e. the method of rearing or catching the animal from which the fur is derived). This will enable customers to make purchasing decisions with full knowledge of the facts.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Federal Food Safety and Veterinary Office (FSVO) Media Unit Tel. +41 58 463 78 98 media@blv.admin.ch</contact>
      <attachment id="206237">
        <title>Label for declarating fur</title>
        <format>jpg</format>
        <size-kb>167</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/63265.jpg</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <link id="206241">
        <title>Website FSVO</title>
        <uri>https://www.blv.admin.ch/blv/en/home/das-blv/auftrag/vollzug/pelzdeklaration.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <keywords>
      <keyword id="0001" org-id="1079">
        <name lang="de">Artenschutz</name>
        <name lang="fr">Conservation des espèces</name>
        <name lang="it">Conservazione delle specie</name>
        <name lang="en">Conservation of endangered species</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="0002" org-id="1079">
        <name lang="de">Handel</name>
        <name lang="fr">Commerce</name>
        <name lang="it">Commercio</name>
        <name lang="en">Trade</name>
      </keyword>
    </keywords>
    <topics>
      <topic id="5">
        <name lang="de">Behörden</name>
        <name lang="fr">Autorités</name>
        <name lang="it">Autorità</name>
        <name lang="en">Authorities</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="10">
        <name lang="de">Bundesrat</name>
        <name lang="fr">Conseil fédéral</name>
        <name lang="it">Consiglio federale</name>
        <name lang="en">Federal Council</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
