<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="80721" revoked="no">
    <version>2</version>
    <pubdate>2020-10-14</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="1070" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>1070</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Der Bundesrat</name>
      <name lang="fr">Conseil fédéral</name>
      <name lang="it">Il Consiglio federale</name>
      <name lang="en">The Federal Council</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.admin.ch/gov/de/start.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.admin.ch/gov/fr/accueil.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.admin.ch/gov/it/pagina-iniziale.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.admin.ch/gov/en/start.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="201" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>201</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="1070">
      <name lang="de">Der Bundesrat</name>
      <name lang="fr">Conseil fédéral</name>
      <name lang="it">Il Consiglio federale</name>
      <name lang="en">The Federal Council</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.admin.ch/gov/de/start.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.admin.ch/gov/fr/accueil.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.admin.ch/gov/it/pagina-iniziale.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.admin.ch/gov/en/start.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <department id="201">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Der Bundesrat ernennt Livia Leu zur neuen Staatssekretärin und verabschiedet strukturelle Anpassungen im EDA</title>
      <lead>Livia Leu, derzeit Botschafterin in Paris, übernimmt ab sofort die Direktion für europäische Angelegenheiten (DEA) und wird Chefunterhändlerin für die Verhandlungen mit der EU. Sie erhält dazu den Titel einer Staatssekretärin. Dies hat der Bundesrat an seiner Sitzung vom 14. Oktober 2020 beschlossen. Zudem hat er einer strukturellen Anpassung im Eidgenössischen Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten (EDA) zugestimmt. Auf den 1. Januar 2021 hin werden die DEA und die Politische Direktion in einem Staatssekretariat zusammengeführt. Livia Leu wird dieses als Staatssekretärin EDA von diesem Zeitpunkt an leiten.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Mit diesen Entscheidungen schafft der Bundesrat die strukturellen und personellen Voraussetzungen, um die aussenpolitische Strategie 2020-2023 und die nächste Phase der Verhandlungen mit der EU optimal umsetzen zu können. Der Bundesrat hat angekündigt, dass die Gespräche über das Institutionelle Abkommen nach der BGI-Abstimmung wiederaufgenommen werden. Er wird in den nächsten Wochen die Position der Schweiz festlegen und mit der EU die Diskussion über die Lösung der noch offenen Punkte aufnehmen.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fähigkeiten für eine entschlossene Umsetzung der aussenpolitischen Strategie&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Die Ernennung von Livia Leu erfolgte im Rahmen eines öffentlichen Ausschreibungsverfahrens. Die neue Staatssekretärin hat vertiefte Erfahrungen in den thematischen Schwerpunkten der aussenpolitischen Strategie 2020-2023, namentlich Frieden, Sicherheit, Wohlstand, Nachhaltigkeit und Digitalisierung.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Nach Abschluss ihrer Studien in Zürich und teilweise Lausanne mit dem Lizentiat der Rechte und dem Rechtsanwaltspatent des Kantons Zürich, trat Livia Leu 1989 in den Dienst des EDA ein. Nach verschiedenen Funktionen in der Zentrale in Bern und im Ausland – unter anderem als Missionschefin in Iran – ist Livia Leu seit zwei Jahren Botschafterin in Frankreich und Monaco. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Livia Leu wird die Direktion für europäische Angelegenheiten bis zu dessen Integration in das neu strukturierte Staatssekretariat leiten. Sie bleibt danach Chefunterhändlerin für die Verhandlungen mit der EU und ab dem 1. Januar 2021 Chefin des Staatssekretariats.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Der bisherige Direktor der DEA, Staatssekretär Roberto Balzaretti, wird demnächst neu Botschafter in Paris. Er übernimmt zudem von Livia Leu das Amt des Präsidenten der Zulassungskommission für neue Diplomatinnen und Diplomaten. Der Bundesrat dankt ihm für seine kompetente Arbeit als EU-Chefunterhändler. Roberto Balzaretti handelte 2018 den nun vorliegenden Entwurf für das Institutionelle Abkommen aus, der es ermöglichte, auf einer konkreten Basis eine innenpolitische Diskussion zu führen.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Der Bundesrat dankt auch Krystyna Marty. Sie übernahm Anfang 2020 interimistisch das Staatssekretariat EDA und führte dieses umsichtig und im Sinne der bundesrätlichen Aussenpolitik. Sie wird wie vorgesehen Anfang 2021 Botschafterin in Moskau.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Stärkung der Kohärenz der Aussenpolitik&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Im neu strukturierten Staatssekretariat sollen im Gegensatz zu heute alle europäischen Länder und Institutionen unter einem Dach zusammengefasst werden. Die grössere Nähe an die anderen geographischen Abteilungen und eine direkte Anbindung an die thematischen Abteilungen schafft eine bessere Kohärenz der Schweizer Aussenpolitik.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Im Staatssekretariat sollen zudem alle sechs geographischen Abteilungen vereint werden. Es sind dies neben «Europa» die Abteilungen «Eurasien», «Amerikas», «Asien», «Afrika», sowie «Mittlerer und naher Osten» (MENA).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Weiter werden fünf thematische Abteilungen geschaffen: «Frieden und Menschenrechte», «Internationale Sicherheit», «Digitalisierung», «Sektorielle Angelegenheiten», sowie «UNO». Dies entspricht den Schwerpunkten, die der Bundesrat in der Aussenpolitischen Strategie 2020-2023 gesetzt hat.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Zunehmende Bedeutung der Digitalisierung&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Mit der Aussenpolitischen Strategie 2020-2023 hat der Bundesrat die Digitalisierung zu einer der Schwerpunkten der Schweizer Aussenpolitik erklärt. Mit der Schaffung einer neuen Abteilung «Digitalisierung» trägt das EDA der zunehmenden Bedeutung dieses Themas für die Aussenpolitik Rechnung. Im Fokus soll unter anderem die Positionierung des multilateralen Genf als Hub für die digitale Gouvernanz sowie als Zentrum für die globale Digital- und Technologiepolitik stehen. Weiter will das EDA die digitale Aussenpolitik vorantreiben.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>für weitere Informationen: Kommunikation EDA Tel. +41 58 462 31 53 kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Le Conseil fédéral nomme Livia Leu au poste de secrétaire d’État et approuve les ajustements structurels du DFAE</title>
      <lead>Livia Leu, actuellement ambassadrice de Suisse à Paris, reprend dès à présent les rênes de la Direction des affaires européennes (DAE) et devient négociatrice en chef pour les négociations avec l’UE. Elle se voit décerner à cet effet le titre de secrétaire d’État. Le Conseil fédéral a pris cette décision lors de sa séance du 14 octobre 2020. À cette occasion, il a également approuvé les ajustements structurels du Département fédéral des affaires étrangères (DFAE). La DAE et la Direction politique seront regroupées au sein d’un secrétariat d’État au 1er janvier 2021, date à partir de laquelle Livia Leu dirigera ce dernier en qualité de secrétaire d’État.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Par ces décisions, le Conseil fédéral crée les conditions nécessaires en termes de structures et de personnel pour mettre en œuvre au mieux la stratégie de politique extérieure 2020-2023 et la prochaine phase des négociations avec l’UE. Le Conseil fédéral a annoncé la reprise, après la votation sur l’initiative de limitation, des discussions sur l’accord institutionnel. Dans les semaines qui viennent, il définira la position de la Suisse et engagera les discussions avec l’UE sur le règlement des points encore en suspens.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Des capacités pour une mise en œuvre résolue de la stratégie de politique extérieure&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;La nomination de Livia Leu a eu lieu dans le cadre d’une mise au concours publique. La nouvelle secrétaire d’État possède une expérience approfondie en ce qui concerne les différentes priorités thématiques de la stratégie de politique extérieure 2020-2023, à savoir en matière de paix, de sécurité, de prospérité, de durabilité et de numérisation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Après avoir obtenu une licence en droit et un brevet d’avocat du canton de Zurich au terme de ses études effectuées à Zurich et en partie à Lausanne, Livia Leu a rejoint le DFAE en 1989. Elle a exercé diverses fonctions à la centrale à Berne ainsi qu’à l’étranger – notamment celle de cheffe de mission en Iran – et, depuis deux ans, elle est ambassadrice de Suisse en France et à Monaco. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Livia Leu sera à la tête de la Direction des affaires européennes jusqu’à l’intégration de cette dernière dans le Secrétariat d’État restructuré. Elle continuera ensuite à exercer les fonctions de négociatrice en chef pour les négociations avec l’UE et assumera, à partir du 1er janvier 2021, celles de cheffe du Secrétariat d’État.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Le directeur actuel de la DAE, le secrétaire d’État Roberto Balzaretti, deviendra prochainement le nouvel ambassadeur de Suisse à Paris. Il succédera en outre à Livia Leu à la présidence de la Commission d’admission des nouveaux diplomates. Le Conseil fédéral le remercie pour le travail qu’il a accompli avec grande compétence en qualité de négociateur en chef pour l’UE. En 2018, Roberto Balzaretti a négocié le projet actuel d’accord institutionnel, qui a permis de mener un débat de politique intérieure sur des bases concrètes.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Le Conseil fédéral exprime aussi ses remerciements à Krystyna Marty. Début 2020, elle a pris la direction ad interim du Secrétariat d’État du DFAE, fonction qu’elle a exercée de manière avisée, dans l’esprit de la politique extérieure du Conseil fédéral. Elle sera comme prévu ambassadrice de Suisse à Moscou à partir du début de l’année 2021.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Renforcement de la cohérence de la politique extérieure&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;À la différence de la situation actuelle, tous les pays et institutions européens relèveront des attributions du Secrétariat d’État restructuré. Une plus grande proximité avec les autres divisions géographiques et une connexion directe aux divisions thématiques assurera une meilleure cohérence de la politique extérieure suisse.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Les six divisions géographiques seront réunies au sein du Secrétariat d’État. Ce dernier regroupera donc en son sein, outre la Division «Europe», les Divisions «Eurasie», «Amériques», «Asie», «Afrique» ainsi que «Proche et Moyen-Orient (MENA).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Par ailleurs, cinq divisions thématiques seront créées dans le Secrétariat d’État restructuré: «Paix et droits de l’homme», « Sécurité internationale», «Numérisation», «Affaires sectorielles» et «ONU». Cette structure correspond aux priorités que le Conseil fédéral a fixées dans la stratégie de politique extérieure 2020-2023.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Importance croissante de la numérisation&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Avec sa stratégie de politique extérieure 2020-2023, le Conseil fédéral a fait de la numérisation l’une des priorités thématiques de la politique extérieure suisse. Par la création d’une nouvelle Division «Numérisation», le DFAE tient compte de l’importance croissante de cette question pour la politique extérieure. L’accent est mis notamment sur le positionnement de la Genève multilatérale comme pôle de la gouvernance numérique et comme centre de la politique mondiale en matière de numérisation et de technologies. Le DFAE entend par ailleurs promouvoir sa politique extérieure en matière de numérisation.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Pour plus d'informations: Communication DFAE Tél. +41 58 462 31 53 kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions>
        <revision date="2020-10-14 16:12" type="R"/>
      </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Il Consiglio federale nomina Livia Leu nuova segretaria di Stato e approva adeguamenti strutturali al DFAE</title>
      <lead>Livia Leu, attualmente ambasciatrice a Parigi, assume con decorrenza immediata la guida della Direzione degli affari europei (DAE) e diventa caponegoziatrice per i negoziati con l’UE, ottenendo a tale scopo il titolo di segretaria di Stato. È quanto deciso dal Consiglio federale nella sua seduta del 14 ottobre 2020. Il Governo ha inoltre approvato un adeguamento strutturale all’interno del Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri (DFAE): dal 1° gennaio 2021 la DAE e la Direzione politica saranno fuse in un’unica Segreteria di Stato e Livia Leu ne assumerà la direzione in veste di segretaria di Stato del DFAE.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Con queste decisioni il Consiglio federale crea i presupposti necessari, a livello di strutture e di personale, per garantire un’attuazione ottimale della Strategia di politica estera 2020–2023 e della prossima fase dei negoziati con l’UE. Il Governo ha annunciato la ripresa dei colloqui sull’Accordo istituzionale dopo la votazione sull’Iniziativa per la limitazione. Nelle prossime settimane definirà la posizione della Svizzera e avvierà i colloqui con l’UE per risolvere le questioni ancora in sospeso.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Capacità di attuare con determinazione la strategia di politica estera&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Livia Leu è stata nominata tramite un concorso pubblico. La nuova segretaria di Stato vanta una grande esperienza in tutti gli ambiti tematici prioritari della Strategia di politica estera 2020–2023, ossia pace e sicurezza, prosperità, sostenibilità e digitalizzazione.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Dopo aver concluso gli studi a Zurigo e a Losanna, conseguendo la licenza in diritto e il brevetto di avvocato nel Cantone di Zurigo, nel 1989 Livia Leu è entrata al DFAE. Ha ricoperto diverse funzioni sia alla Centrale a Berna che all’estero – per esempio come capomissione in Iran – e da due anni è ambasciatrice di Svizzera in Francia e nel Principato di Monaco. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Livia Leu guiderà la Direzione degli affari europei fino all’integrazione di quest’ultima nella nuova e ristrutturata Segreteria di Stato, dopodiché rimarrà caponegoziatrice per i negoziati con l’UE e, dal 1° gennaio 2021, sarà a capo della Segreteria di Stato.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;L’attuale direttore della DAE, il segretario di Stato Roberto Balzaretti, assumerà prossimamente la funzione di ambasciatore di Svizzera a Parigi. Prenderà inoltre il posto di Livia Leu quale presidente della Commissione di ammissione alla carriera diplomatica. Il Consiglio federale gli ha espresso il proprio ringraziamento per la competenza con cui ha svolto il lavoro di caponegoziatore con l’UE. Nel 2018 Roberto Balzaretti ha infatti negoziato la bozza dell’Accordo istituzionale, ora disponibile, che ha permesso di condurre su una base concreta la discussione a livello di politica interna.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Il Consiglio federale ringrazia anche Krystyna Marty, che all’inizio del 2020 ha assunto la funzione di segretaria di Stato ad interim assicurando una gestione avveduta e in linea con la politica estera del Governo. Come previsto, dall’inizio del 2021 sarà la nuova ambasciatrice di Svizzera a Mosca.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Politica estera più coerente&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;La nuova struttura della Segreteria di Stato riunirà sotto lo stesso tetto tutte le istituzioni e tutti i Paesi europei. La maggiore vicinanza alle altre divisioni geografiche e il collegamento diretto con le divisioni tematiche renderanno più coerente la politica estera della Svizzera.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;La Segreteria di Stato raggrupperà le sei divisioni geografiche, cioè – oltre alla Divisione Europa – anche le divisioni Eurasia, Americhe, Asia, Africa, e Medio Oriente e Africa del Nord (MOAN).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Comprenderà inoltre cinque divisioni tematiche: «Pace e diritti umani», «Sicurezza internazionale», «Digitalizzazione», «Affari settoriali» e «ONU», conformemente agli ambiti tematici fissati dal Consiglio federale nella Strategia di politica estera 2020–2023.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Crescente importanza della digitalizzazione&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Con la Strategia di politica estera 2020–2023 il Consiglio federale ha inserito la digitalizzazione tra gli ambiti tematici della politica estera svizzera. Creando una nuova divisione «Digitalizzazione», il DFAE tiene conto della crescente importanza di questo tema per la politica estera. L’attenzione si concentrerà, tra le altre cose, sul posizionamento della Ginevra internazionale come polo della governance digitale e come centro per la politica digitale e tecnologica globale. Il DFAE intende anche promuovere la politica estera digitale.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Informazioni: Comunicazione DFAE Tel. +41 58 462 31 53 kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Federal Council appoints Livia Leu as new State Secretary and approves adjustments to the structure of the FDFA</title>
      <lead>Livia Leu, who is currently Switzerland's ambassador in Paris, will assume the leadership of the Directorate for European Affairs (DEA) with immediate effect and will take up the post of chief negotiator for negotiations with the EU. She will receive the title of State Secretary. The Federal Council took this decision at its meeting on 14 October 2020. It also agreed to adjustments to the structure of the Federal Department of Foreign Affairs (FDFA). From 1 January, the European Affairs and Political Affairs directorates will be merged under a single State Secretariat headed by Livia Leu as the FDFA State Secretary.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;The Federal Council decision creates the structural and staffing conditions needed to effectively implement the Foreign Policy Strategy 2020–23 and the next phase of the negotiations with the EU. The Federal Council announced that talks on the institutional agreement would resume following the vote on the Limitation Initiative. In the weeks to come, it will set out Switzerland's position and launch discussions with the EU on how to resolve the remaining issues.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Capacities for determined implementation of the Foreign Policy Strategy&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Livia Leu was appointed through a competitive application process. The new State Secretary has in-depth experience with regard to the themes of peace and security, prosperity, sustainability and digitalisation, which are focuses of the Foreign Policy Strategy 2020–23.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Livia Leu studied law in Zurich and Lausanne and was admitted to the bar in the canton of Zurich before joining the FDFA in 1989. She has held various posts at the FDFA's head office in Bern and abroad – including that of head of mission in Iran – and for the last two years has been the ambassador to France and Monaco. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Livia Leu will head the Directorate of European Affairs until it is integrated into the restructured State Secretariat. She will remain the chief negotiator for negotiations with the EU when she assumes leadership of the State Secretariat on 1 January 2021.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The current head of the DEA, State Secretary Roberto Balzaretti, will shortly take up his new appointment as the ambassador in Paris. He will also take over the chairmanship of the Diplomatic Service Admissions Committee from Livia Leu. The Federal Council thanks him for his capable efforts as EU chief negotiator. In 2018, Roberto Balzaretti negotiated the draft of the Institutional Agreement, enabling discussions inside Switzerland to take place on the basis of a concrete document.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Federal Council also expresses its thanks to Krystyna Marty for her judicious interim leadership of the State Secretariat in pursuit of the Federal Council's foreign policy objectives since the start of 2020. She will assume the post of ambassador in Moscow in early 2021 as planned.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;More coherence in foreign policy matters&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;All European countries and institutions are now covered by a single division of the new State Secretariat. This division's closer proximity with those responsible for the other regions and direct liaison with the thematic divisions will result in more coherence on matters of importance for Switzerland's foreign policy.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, the State Secretariat will bring together all six geographical divisions. In addition to Europe, it will comprise the divisions responsible for Eurasia, the Americas, Asia, Africa and the Middle East (MENA).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Five thematic divisions will also be created: Peace and Human Rights, International Security, Digitalisation, Sectoral Affairs and UN. This reflects the priorities set by the Federal Council in its Foreign Policy Strategy 2020–23.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Increasing importance of digitisation&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;In its Foreign Policy Strategy 2020–23, the Federal Council selected digitalisation as one of Switzerland's priorities in terms of foreign policy. The creation of a new division in charge of Digitalisation takes account of the growing importance of this topic in Switzerland's foreign policy. Among this division's main tasks will be to position multilateral Geneva as a hub for digital governance and centre for global digital and technology policy. The FDFA also intends to advance its digital foreign policy.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>For further information: FDFA Communication Tel. +41 58 462 31 53 kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
