<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="78190" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2020-02-21</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="1080" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>701</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Staatssekretariat für Bildung, Forschung und Innovation</name>
      <name lang="fr">Secrétariat d'Etat à la formation, à la recherche et à l'innovation</name>
      <name lang="it">Segreteria di Stato per la formazione, la ricerca e l'innovazione</name>
      <name lang="en">State Secretariat for Education, Research and Innovation</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.sbfi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.sbfi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.sbfi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.sbfi.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@sbfi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@sbfi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@sbfi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@sbfi.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="701">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Wirtschaft, Bildung und Forschung</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'économie, de la formation et de la recherche</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'economia, della formazione e della ricerca</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Economic Affairs, Education and Research</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Evaluation bestätigt hohen Mehrwert des swissnex Netzwerks für Schweizer Bildungs-, Forschungs- und Innovationsakteure</title>
      <lead>Im Auftrag des Staatssekretariats für Bildung, Forschung und Innovation (SBFI) hat «Oxford Research» das swissnex Netzwerk evaluiert. Die Evaluation beschreibt swissnex als eine kundenorientierte, flexible und dynamische Organisation, die ihren öffentlich finanzierten wie privaten Partnern einen signifikanten Mehrwert bietet. Ohne die Unterstützung von swissnex hätten die meisten Hochschulen, Forschenden oder Start-ups ihre Internationalisierungsziele nicht im gleichen Ausmass erreichen können. Für die Zukunft empfiehlt die Evaluation unter anderem eine verbesserte Präsenz in der Schweiz, eine stärkere Ausrichtung auf langfristige Projekte und einen gezielteren Austausch zwischen den einzelnen swissnex Standorten.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Knapp zwanzig Jahre nach der Gründung von swissnex Boston – dem in dieser Form weltweit ersten Wissenschaftskonsulat – bescheinigt «Oxford Research» dem swissnex Netzwerk eine hohe Relevanz für die Internationalisierungsaktivitäten der Schweizer Akteure im Bildungs-, Forschungs- und Innovationsbereich. Die Evaluation hält fest, dass die fünf swissnex Standorte in Bangalore, Boston, Rio de Janeiro, San Francisco und Shanghai im jeweiligen örtlichen Bildungs-, Forschungs- und Innovationsystem stark verankert sind. Sie sind über die neusten Trends bestens informiert, was allen Partnern unmittelbar zugutekommt. Dank ihres dezentralen Organisationmodells bündeln die swissnex Standorte ein hohes Mass an Flexibilität und interdisziplinärer Kreativität. Sie passen ihre strategischen Prioritäten ihren Standorten an und können so ihren Partnern relevante und massgeschneiderte Dienstleistungen für ihre jeweiligen Internationalisierungsziele anbieten. Gepaart mit einer sichtbaren und zugänglichen Präsenz vor Ort ist dieses Organisationsmodell besonders im Vergleich zu ähnlichen Instrumenten anderer Länder eine bedeutende Stärke von swissnex.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Über 80% der swissnex Partner im BFI-Bereich, die eine von der Evaluationsfirma ausgeführte Umfrage beantwortet haben, sind entweder sehr zufrieden oder zufrieden mit den erhaltenen Dienstleistungen. 70% der Partner hätten ihre Ziele ohne die Unterstützung von einem swissnex nicht im gleichen Ausmass erreichen können und 75% planen auch in Zukunft eine Zusammenarbeit, respektive wollen diese vertiefen.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Dank der Partnerschaft mit swissnex erhielten Hochschulen, individuelle Forschende und Jungunternehmende unmittelbar Zugang zu einem breiten Netzwerk vor Ort und Wissen über dessen Funktionsweise und Opportunitäten. Langfristig konnten mit der Unterstützung von swissnex 30% der Schweizer Hochschulen Kooperationsabkommen mit Partnerinstitutionen abschliessen, 24% der Start-ups konnten kommerzielle Aktivitäten im jeweiligen Land entwickeln und 16% der individuellen Forschenden lancierten Forschungsaktivitäten mit Akteuren vor Ort. Durch die physische Präsenz und teils öffentlichen Aktivitäten in diesen BFI-Hotspots wird die Schweiz als führender Standort für Bildung, Forschung und Innovation wahrgenommen.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Die Evaluation identifiziert demgegenüber Verbesserungspotenzial im Aufbau einer gemeinsamen Internet-Infrastruktur. Diese würde die Sichtbarkeit des swissnex Netzwerks in der Schweiz wie auch im Ausland verstärken. Insbesondere in der Schweiz bestehe noch viel Potenzial bezüglich der Verbreitung von Wissen über die Dienstleistungen des swissnex Netzwerks. Ausserdem sollten die swissnex Standorte vermehrt bewährte Praktiken und Formate austauschen, um Synergien zu schaffen. Die Evaluation schlägt zudem vor, dass die swissnex Standorte ihren Fokus verstärkt auf langfristige Projekte mit entsprechendem Impact richten.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;swissnex ist das weltweite Schweizer Aussennetz für Bildung, Forschung und Innovation. Das Netzwerk unterstützt seine Partner bei der internationalen Vernetzung und ihrem Engagement im globalen Austausch von Wissen, Ideen und Talenten. Die fünf swissnex Standorte und ihre Aussenstellen befinden sich in den innovativsten Zentren der Welt. Gemeinsam mit rund 20 Wissenschaftsrätinnen und -räten an Schweizer Botschaften stärken sie die weltweite Ausstrahlung der Schweiz als Innovations-Hotspot.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Das swissnex Netzwerk ist eine Initiative des Staatssekretariats für Bildung, Forschung und Innovation und ist Teil des Aussennetzes des Bundes unter der Federführung des Eidgenössischen Departements für auswärtige Angelegenheiten. Die Tätigkeiten des swissnex Netzwerks gründen in einem kooperativen Ansatz sowie auf öffentliche und private Partnerschaften und Finanzierung.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Mauro Moruzzi, Botschafter, Leiter der Abteilung Internationale Beziehungen mauro.moruzzi@sbfi.admin.ch T +41 58 462 68 36</contact>
      <attachment id="198340">
        <title>Evaluation of the swissnex Network, Evaluation report by Oxford Research for the Swiss State Secretariat for Education, Research and Innovation</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>1057</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/60363.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Une évaluation confirme la plus-value élevée offerte par le réseau swissnex aux acteurs suisses de la formation, de la recherche et de l’innovation</title>
      <lead>«Oxford Research» a évalué le réseau swissnex sur mandat du Secrétariat d'État à la formation, à la recherche et à l'innovation (SEFRI). Cette évaluation décrit swissnex comme étant une organisation dynamique, flexible et orientée vers ses clients, offrant une plus-value significative à ses partenaires privés ou financés par des fonds publics. Sans le soutien de swissnex, la plupart des hautes écoles, des chercheurs ou des start-up n’auraient pas pu atteindre leurs objectifs d’internationalisation dans la même mesure. À l’avenir, l’évaluation recommande entre autres une présence renforcée en Suisse, une orientation accrue vers des projets à long terme ainsi qu’un échange plus ciblé entre les différents sites de swissnex.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Près de vingt ans après la création de swissnex Boston – premier consulat scientifique au monde revêtant cette forme –, « Oxford Research » atteste une pertinence élevée au réseau swissnex pour les activités d’internationalisation des acteurs suisses dans les domaines de la formation, de la recherche et de l’innovation. L’évaluation relève que les cinq sites swissnex basés à Bangalore, Boston, Rio de Janeiro, San Francisco et Shanghai sont fortement ancrés dans le système local de formation, de recherche et d’innovation (FRI). Ils sont parfaitement informés des dernières tendances, ce qui est au bénéfice direct de tous les partenaires. Grâce à leur modèle organisationnel décentralisé, les sites de swissnex mettent en commun un haut degré de flexibilité et de créativité interdisciplinaire. Ils adaptent leurs priorités stratégiques à leurs sites et peuvent ainsi proposer à leurs partenaires des prestations de services pertinentes et taillées sur mesure pour leurs objectifs en matière d’internationalisation. Couplé à une présence visible et accessible au niveau local, ce modèle organisationnel représente un atout significatif de swissnex, notamment en comparaison avec les instruments similaires d’autres pays.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Plus de 80% des partenaires de swissnex dans le domaine FRI ayant répondu à une enquête menée par l’entreprise d’évaluation «Oxford Research» sont soit très contents ou contents des prestations de services obtenues. Sans le soutien de swissnex, 70% des partenaires n’auraient pas pu atteindre leurs objectifs dans une même mesure et 75% envisagent également une collaboration à venir, ou souhaitent approfondir celle-ci.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Grâce au partenariat avec swissnex, les hautes écoles, les chercheurs individuels ainsi que les jeunes entreprises ont obtenu un accès direct à un large réseau local et ont pu en connaître le fonctionnement et les opportunités. À long terme, avec le soutien de swissnex, 30% des hautes écoles suisses ont pu conclure des accords de coopération avec des institutions partenaires; 24% des start-up ont pu développer des activités commerciales dans le pays en question et 16% des chercheurs individuels ont lancé des activités de recherche en collaboration avec des acteurs locaux. Par sa présence physique et en partie grâce à des activités publiques en ces hauts lieux FRI, la Suisse est perçue comme site de premier plan pour la formation, la recherche et l’innovation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;En revanche, l’évaluation identifie un potentiel d’amélioration dans la mise en place d’une infrastructure Internet commune. Cette dernière renforcerait la visibilité du réseau swissnex en Suisse ainsi qu’à l’étranger. En Suisse notamment, il subsiste une importante marge de progression en ce qui concerne la diffusion des connaissances par le biais des prestations de services du réseau swissnex. Par ailleurs, les sites swissnex devraient échanger un nombre accru de bonnes pratiques et de formats éprouvés afin de créer des synergies. De plus, l’évaluation propose que les sites swissnex accordent une plus grande attention aux projets à long terme présentant un impact en conséquence.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;swissnex est le réseau extérieur de la Suisse pour la formation, la recherche et l’innovation. Le réseau soutient ses partenaires lors de la mise en réseau internationale et de leur engagement dans l’échange mondial de connaissances, d’idées et de talents. Les cinq sites swissnex et leurs antennes sont implantés dans les centres les plus innovants au monde. Avec près de 20 conseillers et conseillères scientifiques répartis dans les ambassades suisses, ils renforcent le rayonnement de la Suisse sur le plan mondial en tant que pôle d’innovation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Le réseau swissnex est une initiative du Secrétariat d’État à la formation, à la recherche et à l'innovation; il fait partie du réseau extérieur de la Confédération sous la direction du Département fédéral des affaires étrangères. Les activités du réseau swissnex se basent sur une approche coopérative ainsi que sur des partenariats et sur un financement publics et privés.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Mauro Moruzzi, ambassadeur, chef de la division Relations internationales mauro.moruzzi@sbfi.admin.ch T +41 58 462 68 36</contact>
      <attachment id="198340">
        <title>Evaluation of the swissnex Network, Evaluation report by Oxford Research for the Swiss State Secretariat for Education, Research and Innovation</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>1057</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/60363.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Uno studio conferma l’importanza della rete swissnex per il settore della formazione, della ricerca e dell’innovazione</title>
      <lead>Su incarico della Segreteria di Stato per la formazione, la ricerca e l’innovazione (SEFRI), l’agenzia «Oxford Research» ha valutato la rete swissnex definendola un’organizzazione orientata al cliente, flessibile e dinamica, in grado di offrire un vantaggio competitivo ai partner pubblici e privati. Senza l’appoggio di swissnex, la maggior parte delle università, dei ricercatori e delle start-up non sarebbero riusciti a raggiungere tutti i loro obiettivi di internazionalizzazione. In futuro si dovrà lavorare per garantire una maggiore presenza di swissnex in Svizzera, investire di più nei progetti a lungo termine e promuovere in maniera mirata l’interazione tra le varie sedi.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Quasi vent’anni dopo la fondazione di swissnex Boston - il primo consolato scientifico al mondo organizzato in questa forma - Oxford Research ha confermato che la rete swissnex riveste un’importanza fondamentale per le attività di internazionalizzazione degli enti svizzeri che si occupano di formazione, ricerca e innovazione. Secondo lo studio, le cinque sedi swissnex di Bangalore, Boston, Rio de Janeiro, San Francisco e Shanghai sono fortemente radicate nei rispettivi sistemi ERI. Il loro alto livello di aggiornamento rappresenta un vantaggio per tutti i partner. Grazie a un modello organizzativo decentrato, le sedi swissnex sono in grado di combinare elevata flessibilità e creatività interdisciplinare, di adattare le loro priorità strategiche alle diverse sedi e di offrire ai partner servizi su misura per aiutarli a realizzare gli obiettivi di internazionalizzazione. La presenza fisica sul territorio, unita all’accessibilità dei servizi, rende questo modello organizzativo un particolare punto di forza di swissnex, soprattutto se confrontato con la situazione di altri Paesi.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Oltre l’80% dei partner ERI di swissnex che hanno preso parte a un sondaggio realizzato dall’agenzia incaricata di condurre lo studio si sono detti soddisfatti o molto soddisfatti dei servizi di cui hanno beneficiato. Senza l’appoggio di swissnex, il 70% non sarebbe stato in grado di raggiungere tutti gli obiettivi prefissati, mentre il 75% ha dichiarato che sta pianificando di avviare una collaborazione o di intensificare quella già in corso.&lt;br /&gt;Essere partner di swissnex permette alle università, ai singoli ricercatori e ai giovani imprenditori di accedere direttamente a un’ampia rete locale e di conoscerne il funzionamento e le opportunità. Sul lungo periodo swissnex ha consentito al 30% delle università svizzere di concludere accordi di cooperazione con istituzioni partner, mentre il 24% delle start-up è riuscita a sviluppare attività commerciali nei rispettivi Paesi e il 16% dei ricercatori ha avviato attività di ricerca in collaborazione con le istituzioni locali. Grazie alla presenza fisica sul territorio e alle attività, alcune anche pubbliche, organizzate dagli hotspot ERI, la Svizzera viene considerata un polo di riferimento per la formazione, la ricerca e l’innovazione.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ciò nonostante, lo studio individua dei margini di miglioramento per quanto riguarda lo sviluppo di un’infrastruttura informatica comune che potrebbe contribuire ad aumentare la visibilità di swissnex a livello nazionale e internazionale. La Svizzera può ancora lavorare molto per far conoscere i servizi offerti dalla rete swissnex. Inoltre, le sedi dovrebbero interagire più spesso e confrontarsi su pratiche e modelli ormai consolidati per creare sinergie, oltre a concentrarsi maggiormente sui progetti a lungo termine e sul relativo impatto.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;swissnex è la rete esterna svizzera per la formazione, la ricerca e l’innovazione attiva in tutto il mondo che aiuta i partner a stringere contatti internazionali e sostiene il loro impegno per favorire la circolazione del sapere, delle idee e dei talenti. Le cinque sedi di swissnex e le loro antenne si trovano nelle zone più all’avanguardia del mondo e, insieme a una ventina di consiglieri scientifici impiegati presso le ambasciate svizzere, rafforzano l’immagine della Svizzera come polo mondiale dell’innovazione.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;swissnex è un’iniziativa della Segreteria di Stato per la formazione, la ricerca e l’innovazione e fa parte della rete esterna della Confederazione, gestita dal Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri. Le attività di swissnex si basano su un approccio cooperativo; i partenariati e i finanziamenti sono sia pubblici che privati.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Mauro Moruzzi, Ambasciatore, capodivisione Relazioni internazionali mauro.moruzzi@sbfi.admin.ch T +41 58 462 68 36</contact>
      <attachment id="198340">
        <title>Evaluation of the swissnex Network, Evaluation report by Oxford Research for the Swiss State Secretariat for Education, Research and Innovation</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>1057</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/60363.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Evaluation confirms value of swissnex network for Swiss education, research and innovation players</title>
      <lead>The specialised knowledge company Oxford Research has evaluated the swissnex network at the request of the State Secretariat for Education, Research and Innovation SERI. The evaluation describes swissnex as a customer-oriented, flexible and dynamic organisation that offers significant added value to its publicly funded and private partners. Without the support of swissnex, most universities, researchers or start-ups would not be able to achieve their internationalisation goals to the same extent. Among the recommendations made by the evaluation are a greater swissnex presence in Switzerland, a stronger focus on long-term projects and a more targeted exchange between the individual swissnex locations.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Almost twenty years after swissnex was founded in Boston, USA – the first science consulate in the world in such a form – Oxford Research attests that the swissnex network plays an extremely valuable role in the internationalisation activities of Swiss players in education, research and innovation (ERI). Their evaluation concludes that the five swissnex locations in Bangalore, Boston, Rio de Janeiro, San Francisco and Shanghai are strongly anchored in their respective local ERI systems. They are well informed about the latest trends, and this brings direct benefit to all partners. Thanks to their decentralised organisational model, the swissnex locations combine a high degree of flexibility and interdisciplinary creativity. They adapt their strategic priorities to the given location and can thus offer partners appropriate and tailor-made services to help them achieve their internationalisation goals. Coupled with a visible and accessible local presence, this organisational model is one of swissnex’s strong points, especially compared to similar instruments that other countries have.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Over 80% of the swissnex ERI partners who responded to the survey conducted by Oxford Research are either satisfied or very satisfied with the services they receive. 70% would not have been able to achieve their goals to the same extent without the support of swissnex, and 75% intend to continue working with the network or to work more closely with it.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The partnership with swissnex gives higher education institutions, individual researchers and young entrepreneurs direct access to a broad local network and insight into how this operates and the opportunities it presents. 30% of Swiss higher education institutions have concluded long-term cooperation agreements with partner institutions thanks to support from swissnex, 24% of start-ups have developed commercial activities locally and 16% of individual researchers have launched research activities with local players. Thanks to the physical presence and the events held by swissnex in these ERI hotspots – some of which are open to the general public – Switzerland is seen as a leading location for education, research and innovation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The evaluation also identifies improvements that could be made to the network, namely the creation of a joint internet infrastructure. This would allow swissnex to raise its visibility both in Switzerland and abroad. In Switzerland in particular, it can still do a lot to market its services. Furthermore, the swissnex locations could do more to exchange information on useful practices and formats and so create synergies. The evaluation also suggests that the swissnex locations should focus to a greater extent on long-term projects with greater impact.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;swissnex is the Swiss international network for education, research and innovation. It helps its partners to form international networks for the exchange of knowledge, ideas and talent. The five swissnex locations and their branch offices can be found in some of the world’s most lively innovation hubs. Along with around 20 science councillors based at Swiss embassies, swissnex promotes Switzerland’s influence as a global innovation hotspot.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The swissnex network is an initiative of the State Secretariat for Education, Research and Innovation and forms part of the Confederation’s network abroad under the management of the Federal Department of Foreign Affairs. Based on a cooperative approach, the swissnex network activities involve both public and private partnerships and funding.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Mauro Moruzzi, Ambassador, Head of International Relations mauro.moruzzi@sbfi.admin.ch T +41 58 462 68 36</contact>
      <attachment id="198340">
        <title>Evaluation of the swissnex Network, Evaluation report by Oxford Research for the Swiss State Secretariat for Education, Research and Innovation</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>1057</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/60363.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <keywords>
      <keyword id="325.18" org-id="1080">
        <name lang="de">Akademie der Naturwissenschaften Schweiz</name>
        <name lang="fr">Académie suisse des sciences naturelles</name>
        <name lang="it">Accademia svizzera di scienze naturali</name>
        <name lang="en">Swiss Academy of Sciences</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="325.11" org-id="1080">
        <name lang="de">Eidgenössische Technische Hochschule ETH</name>
        <name lang="fr">Ecole polytechnique fédérale EPF</name>
        <name lang="it">Politecnico federale</name>
        <name lang="en">Federal Institutes of Technology</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="325.20" org-id="1080">
        <name lang="de">Forschungsförderung</name>
        <name lang="fr">Encouragement de la recherche</name>
        <name lang="it">Promozione della ricerca</name>
        <name lang="en">Research promotion</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="325.27" org-id="1080">
        <name lang="de">Institution</name>
        <name lang="fr">Institution</name>
        <name lang="it">Istituzione</name>
        <name lang="en">Institution</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="325.22" org-id="1080">
        <name lang="de">Raumfahrt</name>
        <name lang="fr">Affaires spatiales</name>
        <name lang="it">Questioni spaziali</name>
        <name lang="en">Space affairs</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="325.16" org-id="1080">
        <name lang="de">Schweizerische Akademie der Geistes- und Sozialwissenschaften</name>
        <name lang="fr">Académie suisse des sciences humaines et sociales</name>
        <name lang="it">Accademia svizzera di scienze morali e sociali</name>
        <name lang="en">Swiss Academy of Humanities and Social Sciences</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="325.17" org-id="1080">
        <name lang="de">Schweizerische Akademie der medizinischen Wissenschaften</name>
        <name lang="fr">Académie suisse des sciences médicales</name>
        <name lang="it">Accademia svizzera delle scienze mediche</name>
        <name lang="en">Swiss Academy of Medical Sciences</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="325.19" org-id="1080">
        <name lang="de">Schweizerische Akademie der technischen Wissenschaften</name>
        <name lang="fr">Académie suisse des sciences techniques</name>
        <name lang="it">Accademia svizzera delle scienze tecniche</name>
        <name lang="en">Swiss Academy of Engineering Sciences</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="325.8" org-id="1080">
        <name lang="de">Technologie</name>
        <name lang="fr">Technologie</name>
        <name lang="it">Tecnologia</name>
        <name lang="en">Technology</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="325.1" org-id="1080">
        <name lang="de">Universitäten</name>
        <name lang="fr">Universités</name>
        <name lang="it">Università</name>
        <name lang="en">Universities</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="325.23" org-id="1080">
        <name lang="de">Weltraum</name>
        <name lang="fr">Espace</name>
        <name lang="it">Spazio</name>
        <name lang="en">Space</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="325.10" org-id="1080">
        <name lang="de">Wissenschaft</name>
        <name lang="fr">Science</name>
        <name lang="it">Scienza</name>
        <name lang="en">Science</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="325.21" org-id="1080">
        <name lang="de">Wissenschaftsaussenpolitik</name>
        <name lang="fr">Politique scientifique extérieure</name>
        <name lang="it">Politica scientifica dell'esterno</name>
        <name lang="en">Foreign scientific policy</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="325.30" org-id="1080">
        <name lang="de">Bildung</name>
        <name lang="fr">Education</name>
        <name lang="it">Educazione</name>
        <name lang="en">Education</name>
      </keyword>
    </keywords>
    <topics>
      <topic id="8">
        <name lang="de">Bildung und Forschung</name>
        <name lang="fr">Formation et recherche</name>
        <name lang="it">Formazione e ricerca</name>
        <name lang="en">Education and Research</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="45">
        <name lang="de">Technologie</name>
        <name lang="fr">Technologie</name>
        <name lang="it">Tecnologia</name>
        <name lang="en">Technology</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
