<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="78214" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2020-02-27</pubdate>
    <blocking-period>2020-02-27</blocking-period>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="318" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>301</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Bundesamt für Statistik</name>
      <name lang="fr">Office fédéral de la statistique</name>
      <name lang="it">Ufficio federale di statistica</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Statistical Office</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.statistik.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.statistique.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.statistica.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.statistics.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@bfs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@bfs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@bfs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@bfs.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="301">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement des Innern</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'intérieur</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'interno</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Home Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Neuchâtel</city>
      <title>Die Schweizer Hotellerie verbucht 2019 erneut einen Logiernächterekord</title>
      <lead>2019 verzeichnete die Schweizer Hotellerie 39,6 Millionen Logiernächte. Dies entspricht einem Anstieg von 1,9% (+755 000) gegenüber 2018 und einem neuen Höchstwert. Damit setzt sich der seit 2017 anhaltende Aufwärtstrend fort. Die ausländische Nachfrage stieg um 1,1% (+246 000) auf einen Rekordwert von 21,6 Millionen Logiernächten. Auch die Zahl der Schweizer Logiernächte war mit 17,9 Millionen (+2,9% / +509 000) so hoch wie noch nie. Soweit einige der definitiven Ergebnisse des Bundesamtes für Statistik (BFS).</lead>
      <text link="no">Diese Medienmitteilung und weitere Informationen zum Thema finden Sie auf der Website des BFS (siehe Link unten)</text>
      <contact>Vincenzo Carelli, BFS, Sektion Tourismus, Tel.: +41 58 463 62 80, E-Mail: Info-Tour@bfs.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="198378">
        <title>Kompletter Text und Mediendossier</title>
        <uri>https://www.bfs.admin.ch/news/de/2020-0302</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Neuchâtel</city>
      <title>Nouveau record de nuitées pour l’hôtellerie suisse en 2019</title>
      <lead>En 2019, l’hôtellerie en Suisse a comptabilisé 39,6 millions de nuitées. Ceci représente une hausse de 1,9% (+755 000) par rapport à 2018 et constitue un nouveau record. Ce résultat confirme la tendance à la hausse initiée en 2017. La demande étrangère a totalisé 21,6 millions de nuitées, ce qui représente une hausse de 1,1% (+246 000), soit un niveau de nuitées jamais atteint jusqu’à présent. De son côté, la demande suisse a progressé de 2,9% (+509 000) et atteint un nouveau seuil historique de 17,9 millions de nuitées. Tels sont les résultats définitifs de l’Office fédéral de la statistique (OFS).</lead>
      <text link="no">Vous trouverez ce communiqué de presse et d'autres informations sur ce thème sur le site web de l'OFS (voir le lien ci-dessous)</text>
      <contact>Vincenzo Carelli, OFS, Section Tourisme, tél.: +41 58 463 62 80, e-mail: Info-Tour@bfs.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="198379">
        <title>Texte intégral et dossier de presse</title>
        <uri>https://www.bfs.admin.ch/news/fr/2020-0302</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Neuchâtel</city>
      <title>Nuovo record di pernottamenti per il settore alberghiero svizzero nel 2019</title>
      <lead>Nel 2019 il settore alberghiero svizzero ha contabilizzato 39,6 milioni di pernottamenti. Tale risultato, che rappresenta un aumento dell’1,9% (+755 000) rispetto al 2018 e costituisce un nuovo record, conferma la tendenza al rialzo iniziata nel 2017. La domanda degli ospiti stranieri ha totalizzato 21,6 milioni di pernottamenti, il che corrisponde a un aumento dell’1,1% (+246 000), un numero mai raggiunto prima d’ora. Dal canto suo, la domanda degli ospiti svizzeri è aumentata del 2,9% (+509 000) mettendo a segno il risultato storico di 17,9 milioni di pernottamenti. Ecco quanto emerge dai risultati definitivi dell’Ufficio federale di statistica (UST).</lead>
      <text link="no">Il presente comunicato stampa e ulteriori informazioni sul tema sono reperibili sulla pagina Internet dell'UST (link sotto)</text>
      <contact>Vincenzo Carelli, UST, Sezione Turismo, tel.: +41 58 463 62 80, e-mail: Info-Tour@bfs.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="198380">
        <title>Testo integrale e dossier per i media</title>
        <uri>https://www.bfs.admin.ch/news/it/2020-0302</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Neuchâtel</city>
      <title>New record for overnight stays for the Swiss hotel sector in 2019</title>
      <lead>In 2019, the Swiss hotel sector registered 39.6 million overnight stays. This represented growth of 1.9% (+755 000) compared with 2018 and constitutes a new record. This result confirms the upward trend started in 2017. Foreign demand totalled 21.6 million overnight stays which represents an increase of 1.1% (+246 000), i.e. a level of overnight stays never seen before. Swiss demand increased by 2.9% (+509 000), reaching the record value of 17.9 million overnight stays. These are the final results from the Federal Statistical Office (FSO).</lead>
      <text link="no">This press release and further information on this topic can be found on the FSO website (see link below)</text>
      <contact>Vincenzo Carelli, FSO, Tourism section, tel.: +41 58 463 62 80, email: Info-Tour@bfs.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="198381">
        <title>Complete text and press kit</title>
        <uri>https://www.bfs.admin.ch/news/en/2020-0302</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <keywords>
      <keyword id="317.11" org-id="318">
        <name lang="de">Tourismus</name>
        <name lang="fr">Tourisme</name>
        <name lang="it">Turismo</name>
        <name lang="en">Tourism</name>
      </keyword>
    </keywords>
    <topics>
      <topic id="27">
        <name lang="de">Reisen und Tourismus</name>
        <name lang="fr">Voyages et tourisme</name>
        <name lang="it">Viaggi e turismo</name>
        <name lang="en">Travel and Tourism</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="43">
        <name lang="de">Statistik</name>
        <name lang="fr">Statistiques</name>
        <name lang="it">Statistica</name>
        <name lang="en">Statistics</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
