<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="78637" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2020-03-31</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="323" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>701</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidg. Materialprüfungs- und Forschungsanstalt</name>
      <name lang="fr">Laboratoire fédéral d'essai des matériaux et de recherche</name>
      <name lang="it">Laboratorio federale di prova dei materiali e di ricerca</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Laboratory for Materials Testing and Research</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.empa.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.empa.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.empa.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.empa.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">contact@empa.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">contact@empa.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">contact@empa.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">contact@empa.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="701">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Wirtschaft, Bildung und Forschung</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'économie, de la formation et de la recherche</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'economia, della formazione e della ricerca</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Economic Affairs, Education and Research</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Dübendorf, St. Gallen und Thun</city>
      <title>Effiziente Lösungen für ein sauberes Wirtschaftswachstum</title>
      <lead>Das Empa-Spinoff TwingTec ist nun Teil der #1000solutions der Solar Impulse Foundation von Bertrand Picard.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Nach dem ersten erfolgreichen Solarflug um die Welt haben Bertrand Piccard und die Stiftung Solar Impulse die zweite Phase ihrer Aktion gestartet: die Auswahl von 1000 Lösungen (#1000solutions), die die Umwelt auf profitable Weise schützen können. Diese Lösungen will die Stiftung an Entscheidungsträger in Politik und Wirtschaft weitervermitteln, damit diese ehrgeizigere Umweltziele und Energiespar-Massnahmen umsetzen können.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Bislang haben fünf Lösungen aus der Schweiz das Label erhalten, darunter zwei, die nach der jüngsten Auswahl im März nominiert wurden. Wir sind stolz darauf, dass das Empa-Spin-off Twingtec ab jetzt ebenfalls Teil der 1000solutions-Liste der Stiftung Solar Impulse ist. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;h3&gt;Windenergie 2.0 von TwingTec&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Zur Förderung der Windenergie 2.0 entwickelte TwingTec eine innovative und nachhaltige Energiequelle, die die volle Kraft des Windes nutzt. Nach einem Bericht der internationalen Agentur für erneuerbare Energien werden bis 2050 6 Terawatt (TW) elektrische Energie aus Windkraft benötigt, um die Klimaziele zu erreichen. Die Wachstumsprognosen der gegenwärtigen Windturbinentechnologie weisen auf ein ungenutztes Volumen von 3 TW bis 2050 hin, was eine Lücke von mehreren Terawatt bedeutet. Herkömmliche Windturbinen sind jedoch in ihren Möglichkeiten begrenzt, was sowohl wirtschaftlich als auch technisch ihr Verbreitungspotential einschränkt. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;TwingTec füllt diese Lücke, indem es eine neue Windenergietechnologie anbietet, die gegenüber Windkraftanlagen entscheidende Vorteile bietet. TwingPower setzt auf einen minimalen Materialeinsatz (es wird kein Turm und kein Fundament benötigt), die kompakten und mobilen Einheiten können schnell und einfach aufgestellt werden, es können größere Höhen und stärkere Winde erreicht werden, ebenso wie die starken Offshore-Winde über grösseren Wassertiefen, bei denen das Potenzial für Europa allein auf 4 TW geschätzt wird. TwingPower ermöglicht neue Standorte für die Windenergie, höhere Auslastungsfaktoren von bis zu 60% und mehr, die den Bedarf an Speicherung reduzieren und die Möglichkeit, die Kosten der Windenergie auf weniger als die Hälfte zu senken.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Das Ziel von TwingTec ist es, den Übergang zu nachhaltiger Energie zu beschleunigen, indem die volle Kraft des Windes genutzt wird, ein Schlüsselelement einer zu 100 Prozent erneuerbaren Welt. &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Dr. Rolf Luchsinger Center for Synergetic Structures Tel. +41 58 765 40 90 Rolf.Luchsinger@empa.ch http://twingtec.ch/</contact>
      <attachment id="199677">
        <title>TwingTec T100 landing automatically at sunset.</title>
        <format>jpg</format>
        <size-kb>386</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/60787.jpg</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <link id="199678">
        <title>Empa Medienmitteilung</title>
        <uri>https://www.empa.ch/web/s604/twingtec_solarimpulse_foundation</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Dübendorf, St. Gallen und Thun</city>
      <title>Des solutions efficaces pour une croissance économique proper</title>
      <lead>La spin-off TwingTec de l'Empa fait désormais partie des #1000solutions de la Fondation Solar Impulse de Bertrand Picard.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Après le succès du premier vol solaire autour du monde, Bertrand Piccard et la Fondation Solar Impulse ont lancé la deuxième phase de leur action : sélectionner des solutions milliaires qui peuvent protéger l'environnement de manière rentable, et les présenter aux décideurs pour les aider à adopter des objectifs environnementaux et des politiques énergétiques plus ambitieux.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Jusqu'à présent, cinq solutions suisses ont reçu le label, dont deux ont été nominées à la suite de la récente sélection du mois de mars. Nous sommes fiers d'annoncer que la spin-off Twingtec de l'Empa fait désormais partie de la gamme des 1000 solutions de la Fondation Solar Impulse. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;L'énergie éolienne 2.0 par TwingTec&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;En promouvant l'énergie éolienne 2.0, Twingtech a mis au point une solution énergétique innovante et durable qui exploite toute la puissance du vent. Selon un rapport de l'agence internationale pour les énergies renouvelables, 6 TW de production d'énergie éolienne sont nécessaires d'ici 2050 pour atteindre les objectifs climatiques. Les projections de croissance de la technologie actuelle des turbines éoliennes indiquent un volume installé de 3 TW d'ici 2050, ce qui laisse un écart de plusieurs térawatts. Les éoliennes à axe horizontal ont des limites qui limitent leur potentiel de pénétration tant sur le plan économique que technique. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;TwingTec comble cette lacune en proposant une nouvelle technologie éolienne qui offre des avantages essentiels par rapport aux éoliennes. TwingPower repose sur une utilisation minimale de matériaux (aucune tour ni fondation n'est nécessaire), les unités compactes et mobiles peuvent être déployées rapidement et facilement, il est possible d'accéder à des altitudes plus élevées et à des vents plus forts, ainsi qu'à des vents off-shore forts en eaux profondes, où le potentiel pour l'Europe seulement est estimé à 4 TW. TwingPower permet de trouver de nouveaux sites pour l'énergie éolienne, d'augmenter les facteurs de capacité jusqu'à 60 % et plus, de réduire le besoin de stockage et de réduire d'au moins un facteur deux les coûts nivelés de l'énergie éolienne. L'objectif de TwingTec est d'accélérer la transition vers une énergie durable en exploitant toute la puissance du vent, élément clé d'un monde 100 % renouvelable.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Dr. Rolf Luchsinger Center for Synergetic Structures Tél +41 58 765 40 90 Rolf.Luchsinger@empa.ch http://twingtec.ch/</contact>
      <attachment id="199677">
        <title>TwingTec T100 landing automatically at sunset.</title>
        <format>jpg</format>
        <size-kb>386</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/60787.jpg</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <link id="199678">
        <title>Empa Medienmitteilung</title>
        <uri>https://www.empa.ch/web/s604/twingtec_solarimpulse_foundation</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Dübendorf, St. Gallen und Thun</city>
      <title>Efficient solutions for a clean economic growth</title>
      <lead>Empa spinoff TwingTec is now part of Bertrand Picard's #1000solutions of the Solar Impulse Foundation.</lead>
      <text link="no"> Following the success of the first solar flight around the world, Bertrand Piccard and the Solar Impulse Foundation has launched the second phase of their action: selecting #1000solutions that can protect the environment in a profitable way, and bringing them to decision makers to help them adopt more ambitious environmental tar-gets and energy policies. So far, five solutions from Switzerland have received the Label including two that were nominated following the recent selection in March. We are proud to announce that the Empa spinoff Twingtec is now part of the #1000solutions lineup of the Solar Impulse Foundation. Wind Energy 2.0 by TwingTec Promoting Wind Energy 2.0, Twingtech developed an innovative and sustainable en-ergy solution that unlocks the full power of the wind. According to a report from the international renewable energy agency, 6 TW of wind power generation is needed by 2050 to reach the climate targets. The growth projections of current wind turbine technology indicate an installed volume of 3 TW by 2050 leaving a gap of several terawatts. Horizontal axis wind turbines have limitations which restrain both economically and technically their penetration potential. TwingTec fills this gap by offering a new wind energy technology which provides key benefits over wind turbines. TwingPower builds on minimal material usage (no tower and no foundation are needed), the compact and mobile units can be fast and easily deployed, higher altitudes and stronger winds can be accessed as well as the strong off-shore winds in deep water, where the potential for Europe only is estimated to be 4 TW. TwingPower enables new sites for wind energy, higher capacity factors up to 60% and more reducing the need for storage and opportunity to reduce the levelised costs of energy of wind by at least a factor two. TwingTec's goal is to speed up the transition to sustainable energy by unlocking the full power of wind, a key element of a 100 % renewable world. </text>
      <contact>Dr. Rolf Luchsinger Center for Synergetic Structures Phone +41 58 765 40 90 Rolf.Luchsinger@empa.ch http://twingtec.ch/</contact>
      <attachment id="199677">
        <title>TwingTec T100 landing automatically at sunset.</title>
        <format>jpg</format>
        <size-kb>386</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/60787.jpg</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <link id="199678">
        <title>Empa Medienmitteilung</title>
        <uri>https://www.empa.ch/web/s604/twingtec_solarimpulse_foundation</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="8">
        <name lang="de">Bildung und Forschung</name>
        <name lang="fr">Formation et recherche</name>
        <name lang="it">Formazione e ricerca</name>
        <name lang="en">Education and Research</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="11">
        <name lang="de">Energie</name>
        <name lang="fr">Énergie</name>
        <name lang="it">Energia</name>
        <name lang="en">Energy</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="45">
        <name lang="de">Technologie</name>
        <name lang="fr">Technologie</name>
        <name lang="it">Tecnologia</name>
        <name lang="en">Technology</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
