<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="78772" revoked="no">
    <version>2</version>
    <pubdate>2020-04-09</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="201" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>201</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="201">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Zuweisung der Verantwortung für den Einsatz chemischer Waffen in Syrien – Stellungnahme der Schweiz</title>
      <lead>Die Schweiz nimmt Kenntnis vom ersten Bericht des Untersuchungsausschusses der Organisation für das Verbot Chemischer Waffen (OPCW), der die Urheberschaft von drei Chemiewaffeneinsätzen im Kontext des Syrien-Konflikts untersuchte. Die Schweiz verurteilt den Einsatz chemischer Waffen in aller Schärfe und fordert, dass die Verantwortlichen aller Verstösse gegen das Völkerrecht in Syrien zur Rechenschaft gezogen werden.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Der Untersuchungsausschuss der OPCW («Investigation and Identification Team», IIT) hat im Rahmen seiner ersten Ermittlung zu Syrien drei Chemiewaffeneinsätze in Ltamenah untersucht. In seinem am 8. April 2020 veröffentlichten Bericht kommt er zum Schluss, dass berechtigte Gründe zur Annahme bestehen, dass es sich bei den Tätern des Einsatzes von Sarin am 24. und 30. März 2017 sowie von Chlor am 25. März 2017 um Personen handelt, die zum Zeitpunkt der Tat der Luftwaffe der Arabischen Republik Syrien angehörten . Der Ausschuss der OPCW wird seine Ermittlungen fortsetzen und weitere Vorfälle in Syrien untersuchen.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Die Schweiz verurteilt den Einsatz chemischer Waffen in Syrien in aller Schärfe. Dieser ist allen Konfliktparteien jederzeit und unter allen Umständen untersagt. Die Schweiz fordert von allen Kriegsparteien in Syrien, das Völkerrecht zu respektieren. Es obliegt nun den politischen Organen der OPCW und dem UNO-Sicherheitsrat, Konsequenzen zu ergreifen, die sie für notwendig erachten. Die Schweiz ruft den Sicherheitsrat auf, die Situation in Syrien dem Internationalen Strafgerichtshof zu überweisen und weitere Massnahmen zu ergreifen, um das grassierende Klima der Straflosigkeit für schwerste Verbrechen einzudämmen und den Schutz der Zivilbevölkerung und anderer Kriegsopfer sicherzustellen.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Um zukünftige Übergriffe zu verhindern und solch schwere Verbrechen nicht ungeahndet zu lassen, ist die Ermittlung der Tatsachen von zentraler Bedeutung. Der Ausschuss der OPCW wird von vielen Mitgliedsländern politisch und finanziell unterstützt, darunter die Schweiz. Sie unterstützt auch weitere internationale Bemühungen, welche zum Ziel haben, derartige und andere Verstösse gegen das Völkerrecht aller Parteien zu dokumentieren und Verantwortliche zur Rechenschaft zu ziehen. Dazu gehören UNO-Mechanismen wie der «International, Impartial and Independent Mechanism for Syria» (IIIM) und Bemühungen syrischer NGOs. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Die Schweiz wird ihr humanitäres Engagement für die vom Konflikt betroffene Bevölkerung in Syrien und den Nachbarländern, welche die Mehrheit der Flüchtlinge aufgenommen haben, weiterführen. Zudem wird sie auch weiterhin ihre guten Dienste anbieten, um einen Beitrag zu einem nachhaltigen Frieden in Syrien zu leisten. Dazu unterstützt sie insbesondere den UNO-Friedensprozess in Genf.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Kommunikation EDA Bundeshaus West CH-3003 Bern Tel. Kommunikationsservice: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Medienstelle: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Établissement des responsabilités dans l’emploi d’armes chimiques en Syrie – la Suisse prend position</title>
      <lead>La Suisse prend connaissance du premier rapport rédigé par l’organe d’investigation de l’Organisation pour l’interdiction des armes chimiques (OIAC), qui a enquêté sur trois cas d’utilisation d’armes chimiques dans le contexte du conflit en Syrie pour en déterminer les auteurs. La Suisse condamne l’utilisation d’armes chimiques avec la plus grande fermeté et exige que les responsables de toutes les violations du droit international en Syrie aient à répondre de leurs actes.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;L’équipe d’investigation et d’identification (IIT) de l’OIAC a enquêté sur trois cas d’emploi d’armes chimiques à Latamné dans le cadre de sa première investigation en Syrie. Dans son rapport publié le 8 avril 2020, elle conclut qu’il existe de bonnes raisons de penser que les auteurs de l’utilisation de sarin les 24 et 30 mars 2017 et de chlore le 25 mars 2017 faisaient partie de l’armée de l’air de la République arabe syrienne au moment des faits. La commission d’enquête de l’OIAC va poursuivre ses investigations et enquêter sur d’autres incidents en Syrie.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;La Suisse condamne avec la plus grande fermeté le recours aux armes chimiques en Syrie. L’utilisation de telles armes est interdite à toutes les parties au conflit, en tout temps et en toutes circonstances. La Suisse exige de tous les belligérants en Syrie qu’ils respectent le droit international. Il appartient désormais aux organes politiques de l’OIAC et au Conseil de sécurité de l’ONU de prendre les mesures qu’ils jugent nécessaires. La Suisse appelle le Conseil de sécurité à renvoyer la situation en Syrie devant la Cour pénale internationale et à prendre toute mesure complémentaire visant à apaiser le climat d’impunité qui prévaut actuellement pour les crimes les plus graves et à assurer la protection de la population civile et des autres victimes de guerre.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Pour éviter de futures attaques et empêcher que de tels crimes ne restent impunis, l’établissement des faits revêt une importance capitale. L’équipe d’investigation et d’identification de l’OIAC bénéficie du soutien politique et financier de nombreux pays membres, dont la Suisse. La Confédération soutient également d’autres efforts internationaux visant à documenter ces violations et d’autres atteintes au droit international par toutes les parties et à amener les responsables à répondre de leurs actes, notamment le Mécanisme international, impartial et indépendant pour la Syrie ainsi que les efforts déployés par les ONG syriennes. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;La Suisse entend maintenir son engagement humanitaire en faveur des populations touchées par le conflit en Syrie et dans les pays voisins, lesquels ont accueilli la majeure partie des personnes fuyant le conflit. En outre, elle continuera à offrir ses bons offices afin de contribuer à une paix durable en Syrie. À cette fin, elle soutient en particulier le processus de paix de l’ONU à Genève.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Communication DFAE Palais fédéral ouest CH-3003 Berne Tél. Service de communication: +41 58 462 31 53 Tél. Service de presse: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <revisions>
        <revision date="2020-04-15 12:49" type="R"/>
      </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Attribuzione di responsabilità per l’uso di armi chimiche in Siria: presa di posizione della Svizzera</title>
      <lead>La Svizzera prende atto del primo rapporto della commissione d’inchiesta dell’Organizzazione per la proibizione delle armi chimiche (OPAC), che ha indagato sulla responsabilità dell’utilizzo di armi chimiche in tre episodi nel contesto del conflitto siriano. La Svizzera condanna severamente l’impiego di queste armi e chiede che i responsabili di qualsiasi violazione del diritto internazionale pubblico in Siria siano chiamati a rendere conto del loro operato.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Nell’ambito della sua prima indagine relativa alla Siria, la commissione d’inchiesta dell’OPAC (Investigation and Identification Team, IIT) si è concentrata su tre episodi in cui sono state utilizzate armi chimiche a Ltamenah. Nel rapporto pubblicato l’8 aprile 2020, giunge alla conclusione che vi sono motivi fondati per ritenere che le persone responsabili dell’uso di sarin il 24 e il 30 marzo 2017 e di cloro il 25 marzo 2017 erano, al momento dei fatti, membri delle forze aeree della Repubblica araba siriana. La commissione dell’OPAC proseguirà le indagini e analizzerà altri episodi verificatisi in Siria.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;La Svizzera condanna severamente l’utilizzo di armi chimiche in Siria, il cui impiego è vietato a tutte le parti in conflitto in ogni momento e in qualsiasi circostanza, ed esorta tutti i belligeranti nel Paese a rispettare il diritto internazionale pubblico. Spetta ora agli organi politici dell’OPAC e al Consiglio di sicurezza dell’ONU trarre le conseguenze che ritengono necessarie. La Svizzera chiede al Consiglio di sicurezza di deferire la situazione in Siria alla Corte penale internazionale, di adottare ulteriori misure per arginare il dilagante clima di impunità per i crimini più gravi e di garantire la protezione della popolazione civile e di altre vittime del conflitto.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Per impedire nuovi attacchi ed evitare che tali gravi crimini rimangano impuniti, le indagini volte ad accertare i fatti sono di fondamentale importanza. La commissione dell’OPAC viene sostenuta politicamente e finanziariamente da molti Paesi membri, tra cui la Svizzera, che appoggia anche altre iniziative internazionali volte a documentare violazioni simili o di altro genere del diritto internazionale pubblico commesse da tutte le parti, e a rinviare a giudizio i responsabili. Tra queste iniziative rientrano meccanismi dell’ONU come l’«International, Impartial and Independent Mechanism for Syria» (IIIM) e gli sforzi di ONG siriane. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;La Svizzera è decisa a portare avanti il proprio impegno umanitario a favore della popolazione colpita dal conflitto, in Siria e nei Paesi confinanti, che hanno accolto la maggior parte dei profughi. Inoltre, continuerà a offrire i propri buoni uffici per contribuire a una pace duratura in Siria. A tal fine, sostiene in particolare il processo di pace dell’ONU a Ginevra.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Comunicazione DFAE Palazzo federale ovest CH-3003 Berna Tel. Servizio di comunicazione: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Servizio stampa: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <revisions>
        <revision date="2020-04-15 12:49" type="R"/>
      </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Attribution of responsibility for the use of chemical weapons in Syria – Switzerland's position</title>
      <lead>Switzerland has taken note of the first report of the Investigation and Identification Team (IIT) of the Organisation for the Prohibition of Chemical Weapons (OPCW), which is responsible for identifying the perpetrators in three instances where chemical weapons were used in the Syrian conflict. Switzerland strongly condemns the use of chemical weapons and demands that those responsible for all violations of international law in Syria be held to account.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;In its first report, the IIT presents its findings on the investigation of three incidents where chemical weapons were used in the town of Ltamenah. The report, published on 8 April 2020, concludes that there are reasonable grounds to believe that the perpetrators of the use of sarin in Ltamenah on 24 and 30 March 2017, and the use of chlorine on 25 March 2017 were individuals belonging to the Syrian Arab Air Force. The IIT will continue its investigations and look into other incidents in Syria.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Switzerland condemns in the strongest possible terms the use of chemical weapons in Syria. All parties to the conflict are prohibited from using such weapons at all times and under all circumstances. Switzerland therefore calls on all warring parties in Syria to respect international law. It is now up to the OPCW's political organs and the UN Security Council to take such steps as they deem necessary. Switzerland calls on the Security Council to refer the situation in Syria to the International Criminal Court and to take further action to curb the pervasive climate of impunity for the most serious crimes and ensure the civilian population and other victims of war are protected.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Establishing the facts is of crucial importance to prevent future attacks and ensure that serious crimes of this nature do not go unpunished. The IIT receives political and financial support from many OPCW member states, including Switzerland. Switzerland also supports other international efforts aimed at documenting these and other violations of international law by all parties involved and bringing those responsible to account. These include UN mechanisms such as the 'International, Impartial and Independent Mechanism for Syria' and activities undertaken by Syrian NGOs.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Switzerland will continue to provide humanitarian assistance to the people affected by the conflict in Syria as well as to neighbouring countries which have taken in the majority of those displaced. In addition, it will continue to offer its good offices to facilitate a lasting peace in Syria. A key element of this is its support for the UN peace process in Geneva.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>FDFA Communication Federal Palace West Wing CH-3003 Bern, Switzerland Tel. Communication service: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Press service: +41 58 460 55 55 E-mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @SwissMFA</contact>
      <revisions>
        <revision date="2020-04-15 12:49" type="R"/>
      </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
