<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="78794" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2020-04-16</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="408" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>408</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Bundesanwaltschaft</name>
      <name lang="fr">Ministère public de la Confédération</name>
      <name lang="it">Ministero pubblico della Confederazione</name>
      <name lang="en">Office of the Attorney General of Switzerland</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.ba.admin.ch/ba/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.ba.admin.ch/ba/fr/home.html</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.ba.admin.ch/ba/it/home.html</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.ba.admin.ch/</www>
      <email lang="de">info@ba.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@ba.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@ba.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@ba.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="408">
      <name lang="de">Bundesanwaltschaft</name>
      <name lang="fr">Ministère public de la Confédération</name>
      <name lang="it">Ministero pubblico della Confederazione</name>
      <name lang="en">Office of the Attorney General of Switzerland</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.ba.admin.ch/ba/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.ba.admin.ch/ba/fr/home.html</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.ba.admin.ch/ba/it/home.html</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.ba.admin.ch/</www>
      <email lang="de">info@ba.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@ba.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@ba.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@ba.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Bundesanwaltschaft: Tätigkeitsbericht 2019</title>
      <lead>Wie aus ihrem Tätigkeitsbericht 2019 hervorgeht, gewinnt die Zusammenarbeit der Bundesanwaltschaft (BA) mit nationalen und internationalen Partnern zunehmend an Bedeutung. Eine starke Vernetzung ist unabdingbar für eine wirksame Bekämpfung moderner Kriminalitätsformen.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Per Ende 2019 waren bei der BA insgesamt 395 (Vorjahr: 407) Strafuntersuchungen hängig und 501 (456) Vorabklärungen. Im Berichtsjahr überwies die BA dem Bundesstrafgericht 17 (10) Anklagen, 7 (1) Anklagen im abgekürzten Verfahren sowie 23 (13) Strafbefehle als Anklage im ordentlichen Verfahren und stellte 228 (170) Strafbefehle aus. Zudem wurden 2019 von der BA und dem Bundesstrafgericht Vermögenseinziehungen / Ersatzforderungen in der Gesamthöhe von CHF 324 (791) Millionen verfügt. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Weil im Zeitalter grenzüberschreitender Geschäftstätigkeiten und Geldflüsse fast alle Verfahren eine internationale Dimension aufweisen, nimmt die Bearbeitung von internationalen Rechtshilfeersuchen kontinuierlich zu: Per Ende 2019 waren insgesamt 317 (313) Rechtshilfeverfahren hängig. 248 (223) Rechtshilfeersuchen wurden abgeschlossen und 244 (233) neue Rechtshilfeersuchen wurden angenommen.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fälle im Interesse der Öffentlichkeit&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Bei der BA waren per Ende 2019 insgesamt mehr als 700 Strafuntersuchungen und Rechtshilfeverfahren hängig. Die umfangreichsten, aufwändigsten und öffentlichkeitswirksamsten Fallkomplexe waren auch im Berichtsjahr erneut die Untersuchungen im Zusammenhang mit Petrobras-Odebrecht, 1MDB und Fussball. In den Komplexen Petrobras-Odebrecht und Fussball konnten 2019 erste Anklagen erhoben werden, ebenso in den Bereichen Völkerstrafrecht und Cyberkriminalität. Wichtige Anklagen wurden auch im Bereich der Terrorismusbekämpfung erhoben. Zudem hat die BA die Einziehung namhafter Deliktsbeträge erwirkt, insbesondere zur Restitution an geschädigte natürliche oder juristische Personen. So wurden beispielsweise im Komplex Petrobras-Odebrecht bis Ende 2019 insgesamt mehr als CHF 400 Millionen an Brasilien zurückerstattet. Und 2019 wurden im Rahmen von Geldwäscherei-Ermittlungen im Zusammenhang mit Usbekistan CHF 130 Millionen zur Restitution eingezogen. &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Kommunikationsdienst der Bundesanwaltschaft; T +41 58 464 32 40; info@ba.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Ministère public de la Confédération : Rapport de gestion 2019</title>
      <lead>Comme le montre le rapport de gestion 2019, la coopération entre le Ministère public de la Confédération (MPC) et ses partenaires nationaux et internationaux est de plus en plus importante. Un réseau solide est indispensable pour lutter efficacement contre les formes modernes de criminalité.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;A fin 2019, un total de 395 enquêtes pénales étaient pendantes au MPC (année précédente : 407) ainsi que 501 (456) recherches préliminaires. Au cours de l'année sous revue, le MPC a déposé 17 (10) actes d'accusation, 7 (1) actes d’accusation en procédure simplifiée et 23 (13) ordonnances pénales tenant lieu d’acte d’accusation au Tribunal pénal fédéral (TPF) et il a prononcé 228 (170) ordonnances pénales. En outre, le MPC et le TPF ont prononcé des confiscations /créances compensatrices pour un montant total de CHF 324 (791) millions en 2019. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Parce qu'à l'ère des activités commerciales et des flux monétaires transfrontaliers, presque toutes les procédures ont une dimension internationale, le traitement des demandes d'entraide judiciaire internationales est en constante augmentation : A fin 2019, un total de 317 (313) procédures d’entraide judiciaire étaient pendantes. 248 (223) demandes d’entraide judiciaire ont été clôturées et 244 (233) nouvelles demandes d’entraide judiciaire ont été acceptées.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cas d'intérêt public&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;br /&gt;Au MPC, plus de 700 enquêtes pénales et procédures d'entraide judiciaire étaient en cours à la fin de 2019. Les complexes d’affaires les plus vastes, les plus complexes et les plus médiatisés de l'année sous revue ont été une fois de plus les enquêtes relatives à Petrobras-Odebrecht, 1MDB et au football. En 2019, les premiers actes d’accusation ont été transmis dans les complexes de Petrobras-Odebrecht et du football, ainsi que dans les domaines du droit pénal international et de la cybercriminalité. Il a également été procédé à d'importantes mises en accusation dans le domaine de la lutte contre le terrorisme. Le MPC a également confisqué des sommes considérables provenant d’infractions, notamment pour les restituer aux personnes physiques ou morales lésées. Dans le complexe Petrobras-Odebrecht, par exemple, un total de plus de CHF 400 millions a été restitué au Brésil jusqu’à la fin de 2019. CHF 130 millions ont été confisqués, en 2019 toujours, pour restitution dans le cadre d'enquêtes sur le blanchiment d'argent en Ouzbékistan. &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Service de communication du Ministère public de la Confédération; T +41 58 464 32 40; info@ba.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Ministero pubblico della Confederazione: Rapporto di gestione 2019</title>
      <lead>Dal Rapporto di gestione 2019 del Ministero pubblico della Confederazione (MPC) si evince che la collaborazione con partner svizzeri e internazionali acquista un'importanza sempre maggiore. Una rete solida è indispensabile per una lotta efficiente alle forme moderne di criminalità.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Alla fine del 2019, il MPC registrava complessivamente 395 (2018: 407) inchieste penali pendenti e 501 (456) accertamenti preliminari. Nell’anno in rassegna il MPC ha depositato al Tribunale penale federale (TPF) 17 (10) atti d’accusa, 7 (1) atti d’accusa in rito abbreviato e 23 (13) decreti d’accusa come atti d’accusa nel procedimento ordinario ed emesso 228 (170) decreti d’accusa. Nel 2019, il MPC e il TPF hanno ordinato confische di patrimoni e dei risarcimenti per un importo totale di CHF 324 (791) milioni. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Nell'era degli affari e dei flussi finanziari che oltrepassano i confini, quasi tutti i procedimenti hanno una dimensione internazionale. Di conseguenza, il trattamento delle domande di assistenza giudiziaria internazionali continua ad aumentare: alla fine del 2019, il MPC registrava complessivamente 317 (313) procedure di assistenza giudiziaria pendenti. Le domande di assistenza giudiziaria evase erano 248 (223), mentre quelle accolte 244 (233).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Casi d’interesse pubblico&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Alla fine del 2019, il MPC registrava oltre 700 inchieste penali e procedure di assistenza giudiziaria pendenti. Anche nell’anno in rassegna le inchieste più vaste, dispendiose e d'interesse pubblico sono state quelle riguardanti i complessi Petrobras-Odebrecht, 1MDB e al calcio. Nel 2019, nell'insieme di casi relativi a Petrobras-Odebrecht e al calcio, come pure negli ambiti del diritto penale internazionale, della cybercriminalità, è stato possibile promuovere i primi atti d’accusa. Importanti accuse sono state mosse anche nell’ambito della lotta contro il terrorismo. Inoltre, il MPC ha ottenuto la confisca di notevoli proventi di reato, in particolare per la loro restituzione alle persone fisiche o giuridiche danneggiate. Nel corso del 2019, per esempio, nei casi Petrobras-Odebrecht sono stati rimborsati complessivamente oltre CHF 400 milioni al Brasile. E sempre nel 2019 sono stati confiscati, per restituzione, CHF 130 milioni nel quadro delle inchieste condotte per riciclaggio di denaro in relazione all'Uzbekistan.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Servizio Comunicazione del Ministero pubblico della Confederazione; tel. +41 58 464 32 40, info@ba.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Office of the Attorney General of Switzerland: Annual Report 2019</title>
      <lead>As its annual report for 2019 shows, cooperation between the Office of the Attorney General of Switzerland (OAG) and its national and international partners is becoming increasingly important. A strong network is essential for combating modern forms of crime effectively. </lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;At the end of 2019, the OAG had a total of 395 (previous year: 407) ongoing criminal investigations and 501 (456) ongoing preliminary clarifications. In the report year, the OAG filed in the Federal Criminal Court (FCC) 17 (10) indictments, 7 (1) indictments in accelerated proceedings and 23 (13) summary penalty orders as indictments in ordinary proceedings; it also issued a further 228 (170) summary penalty orders. In addition, in 2019 the OAG and the FCC issued orders in respect of forfeitures of assets / compensation claims amounting to CHF 324 (791) million. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In this era of cross-border business activities and money transfers, almost all OAG cases have an international dimension; as a result, the number of international requests for mutual assistance that have to be processed is steadily increasing. As of the end of 2019, a total of 317 (313) mutual assistance cases were ongoing. In 2019, 248 (223) requests for mutual assistance were executed and 244 (233) new requests for mutual assistance were accepted.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cases of public interest&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;At the end of 2019, the OAG had more than 700 ongoing criminal investigations and mutual assistance proceedings. The most complex and extensive cases, and those that generated the greatest public interest in the report year were once again the investigations relating to Petrobras-Odebrecht, 1MDB and football. 2019 saw the first indictments filed in the Petrobras-Odebrecht and football-related cases, and also in the fields of international criminal law and cybercrime. Important indictments were also filed in relation to combating terrorism. In addition, the OAG secured the forfeiture of substantial sums of money made from crime, in particular for restitution to persons or legal entities that had fallen victim to criminal offences. For example, in the series of cases relating to Petrobras-Odebrecht, more than CHF 400 million had been returned to Brazil by the end of 2019. And in 2019, CHF 130 million was forfeited for the purpose of restitution as part of the money laundering investigations connected with Uzbekistan. &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Communication Service of the Office of the Attorney General of Switzerland; T +41 58 464 32 40; info@ba.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="17">
        <name lang="de">Kriminalität</name>
        <name lang="fr">Criminalité</name>
        <name lang="it">Criminalità</name>
        <name lang="en">Criminality</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
