<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="78998" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2020-05-04</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="505" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>501</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Gruppe Verteidigung</name>
      <name lang="fr">Groupement de la Défense</name>
      <name lang="it">Aggruppamento Difesa</name>
      <name lang="en">Defence</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.vtg.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.vtg.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.vtg.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.vtg.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@vtg.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@vtg.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@vtg.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@vtg.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="502" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>501</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Generalsekretariat VBS</name>
      <name lang="fr">Secrétariat général du DDPS</name>
      <name lang="it">Segreteria generale del DDPS</name>
      <name lang="en">General Secretariat DDPS</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.vbs.admin.ch/</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.vbs.admin.ch/</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.vbs.admin.ch/</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.vbs.admin.ch/</www>
      <email lang="de">postmaster.vbs@gs-vbs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">postmaster.vbs@gs-vbs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">postmaster.vbs@gs-vbs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">postmaster.vbs@gs-vbs.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="501">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Verteidigung, Bevölkerungsschutz und Sport</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de la défense, de la protection de la population et des sports</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale della difesa, della protezione della popolazione e dello sport</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Defence, Civil Protection and Sports DDPS</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.vbs.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.vbs.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.vbs.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.vbs.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@gs-vbs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@gs-vbs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@gs-vbs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@gs-vbs.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>RUAG AG baut Service für die Luftwaffe in Payerne aus</title>
      <lead>In Zusammenarbeit mit der Schweizer Luftwaffe hat die RUAG AG mit den Arbeiten für den Aufbau eines neuen Standplatzes für den Flugzeugunterhalt auf dem Militärflugplatz Payerne begonnen. Die RUAG AG schafft dadurch in der Region zwölf neue Arbeitsplätze.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Mit der Errichtung eines neuen Standplatzes auf dem Militärflugplatz Payerne stellt die RUAG AG neu auch in der Westschweiz die Vor-Ort-Maintenance zu Gunsten der Schweizer Luftwaffe sicher. Zusätzlich zu den sechs Mitarbeitenden, die schon heute in Payerne stationiert sind, werden in der Region zwölf neue Arbeitsplätze geschaffen. Die Aufnahme des operativen Betriebes ist gegen Ende des ersten Quartals 2021 geplant. Ab dann führen die Mitarbeitenden der RUAG AG am Standort Payerne beim F/A-18 bis zu fünf grosse Kontrollen pro Jahr durch sowie Unterstützung bei kleinen Kontrollen. Der Endausbau des zweischichtigen Betriebs wird bis zum Ende des dritten Quartals 2021 erfolgen. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mit diesem Schritt werden die Mitarbeitenden des Flugzeugunterhalts der RUAG AG in Emmen noch fokussierter am Struktursanierungs-Programm beim F/A-18 arbeiten können. Durch den Ausbauschritt in Payerne wird die über 30-jährige erfolgreiche Zusammenarbeit zwischen der RUAG und dem VBS noch intensiver und enger. Durch die geographische Annäherung von Flugzeugunterhalt und Operationen können die Effizienz und die Effektivität der Leistungserbringung zugunsten der Luftwaffe verbessert werden und beide Partner können aus den Synergien gleichermassen Vorteile ziehen.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Obwohl sich der Bedarf an grossen Kontrollen am Hauptstandort Emmen ab der Betriebsaufnahme in Payerne etwas reduzieren wird, werden die Gesamtleistungen zu Gunsten der Luftwaffe auch in Zukunft im gleichen Ausmass erbracht. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mit ungefähr 7000 F/A-18 Bewegungen pro Jahr ist der Flugplatz Payerne der Hauptstandort für die Kampfflugzeuge der Luftwaffe und hauptverantwortlich für den Luftpolizeidienst. Das vom Bundesrat gesteckte Ziel, die Interventionsfähigkeit im Luftpolizeidienst rund um die Uhr und an 365 Tagen im Jahr leisten zu können, wird Anfang nächsten Jahres umgesetzt. &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Kirsten Hammerich Mediensprecherin RUAG AG +41 58 467 05 11 Delphine Allemand Armeesprecherin +41 58 463 22 58</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>RUAG AG aménage une infrastructure de service à Payerne</title>
      <lead>En collaboration avec les Forces aériennes, RUAG AG a entamé la construction d’une place de stationnement destinée à l’entretien des avions sur la base aérienne de Payerne. L’entreprise crée ainsi douze nouveaux emplois dans la région. </lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Grâce à la construction d’une nouvelle place de stationnement sur la base aérienne de Payerne, RUAG AG assure désormais, en faveur des Forces aériennes, la présence d’un service de maintenance sur place en Suisse romande. En plus des six postes actuellement occupés à Payerne, douze autres seront créés dans la région. L’exploitation opérationnelle doit débuter vers la fin du premier trimestre 2021. Dès lors, à Payerne, les collaborateurs de RUAG AG conduiront jusqu’à cinq contrôles majeurs par an sur les F/A-18 et fourniront leur assistance pour les contrôles secondaires. L’aménagement de cette infrastructure accueillant deux équipes sera terminé d’ici la fin du troisième trimestre 2021. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Cette étape franchie, les agents de maintenance de RUAG AG engagés à Emmen pourront davantage concentrer leur travail sur le programme d’assainissement des F/A-18. La réalisation des travaux d’assainissement à Payerne permettra de renforcer la collaboration déjà étroite entre RUAG et le DDPS, un succès qui dure depuis plus de 30 ans. Grâce au rapprochement géographique des sites de maintenance des avions et des opérations, l’efficience et l’efficacité des prestations fournies en faveur des Forces aériennes seront accrues et les deux partenaires pourront, dans une même mesure, tirer profit des synergies.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Bien qu’une réduction des besoins en contrôles majeurs soit prévue sur le site d’Emmen dès le lancement de l’exploitation à Payerne, l’ensemble des prestations en faveur des Forces aériennes seront, à l’avenir, toujours fournies dans la même ampleur. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Avec environ 7 000 mouvements de F/A-18 par an, la base aérienne de Payerne est le premier site pour les avions de combat des Forces aériennes et le principal site responsable du service de police aérienne. Concernant ce dernier, l’objectif fixé par le Conseil fédéral consistant à en assurer la permanence se concrétisera au début de l’année prochaine.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Kirsten Hammerich Porte-parole RUAG AG +41 58 467 05 11 Delphine Allemand Porte-parole de l’armée +41 58 463 22 58</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>La RUAG AG amplia i servizi per le Forze aeree a Payerne</title>
      <lead>In collaborazione con le Forze aeree svizzere, la RUAG AG ha intrapreso i lavori di costruzione di un nuovo luogo di stazionamento per la manutenzione degli aerei sull’aerodromo militare di Payerne. In tal modo la RUAG AG crea dodici nuovi posti di lavoro nella regione.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Con la creazione di un nuovo luogo di stazionamento sull’aerodromo militare di Payerne, la RUAG AG garantirà la manutenzione sul posto a favore delle Forze aeree svizzere anche nella Svizzera romanda. Oltre ai sei collaboratori che già oggi operano a Payerne, nella regione saranno creati dodici nuovi posti di lavoro. L’entrata in funzione è prevista verso la fine del primo trimestre 2021. A partire da quel momento, i collaboratori della RUAG AG presso l’ubicazione di Payerne effettueranno fino a cinque grandi revisioni all’anno per gli F/A-18 e forniranno appoggio nelle piccole revisioni. L’esercizio in due turni di lavoro acquisirà la sua forma finale entro la fine del terzo trimestre 2021. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In questo modo i collaboratori della manutenzione degli aerei della RUAG AG a Emmen potranno concentrarsi ancora di più sul programma di risanamento della struttura degli F/A-18. Con l’ampliamento a Payerne, la proficua collaborazione più che trentennale tra la RUAG e il DDPS viene ulteriormente intensificata. Lo svolgimento della manutenzione degli aerei in prossimità del luogo delle operazioni permetterà di migliorare l’efficienza e l’efficacia della fornitura di prestazioni a favore delle Forze aeree ed entrambi i partner potranno trarre vantaggio in ugual misura dalle sinergie. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Anche se, con l’inizio dell’attività a Payerne, in parte diminuirà il fabbisogno di grandi revisioni nell’ubicazione principale di Emmen, le prestazioni complessive a favore delle Forze aeree saranno fornite nella stessa misura anche in futuro. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Con circa 7000 movimenti aerei di F/A-18 all’anno, l’aerodromo di Payerne è l’ubicazione principale per gli aerei da combattimento e detiene la responsabilità principale del servizio di polizia aerea. L’obiettivo fissato dal Consiglio federale di garantire la capacità d’intervento del servizio di polizia aerea 24 ore su 24, 365 giorni all’anno, sarà realizzato all’inizio del prossimo anno. &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Kirsten Hammerich Portavoce RUAG AG +41 58 467 05 11 Delphine Allemand Portavoce dell’esercito +41 58 463 22 58</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>RUAG Ltd expands its service for the Air Force in Payerne</title>
      <lead>In collaboration with the Swiss Air Force, RUAG Ltd has begun working on the construction of a new location on Payerne’s military airfield. In doing so, RUAG Ltd creates 12 new jobs in the region.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;With the construction of a new location at Payerne’s military airfield, RUAG Ltd also ensures new on-site maintenance in Romandy for the benefit of the Swiss Air Force. In addition to the six employees who are already stationed in Payerne, 12 new jobs will be created. The commencement of operations is planned for around the end of Q1 2021. From then on, RUAG Ltd employees at the Payerne location will provide up to five large heavy maintenance checks annually on the F/A-18 as well support through small heavy maintenance checks. The final expansion of the two-shift operation will proceed through the end of Q3 2021. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;With this step, RUAG Ltd’s aircraft maintenance employees in Emmen can focus even more on the restructuring program when working on the F/A-18. Due to the expansion stage in Payerne, the more than 30-year successful collaboration between RUAG and VBS will become closer and more intensive. Through the geographical convergence of aircraft maintenance and operations, the efficiency and effectiveness of the provision of services can be improved to the benefit of the Air Force, and both partners can in equal measure extract advantages from the synergies.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Although the need for large heavy maintenance checks at the Emmen headquarters will be somewhat reduced once operations commence in Payerne, comprehensive services will also be rendered for the benefit of the Air Force going forward. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;With approximately 7,000 F/A-18 movements per year, Payerne's airfield is the headquarters for the Air Force’s fighter aircraft and is mainly responsible for the air police. The Federal Council's goal of being able to provide air police with the ability to intervene around the clock and every day of the year will be implemented at the beginning of next year. &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Kirsten Hammerich Media Spokesperson, RUAG Ltd +41 58 467 05 11 Delphine Allemand Army Spokesperson +41 58 463 22 58</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <keywords>
      <keyword id="530" org-id="502">
        <name lang="de">Luftraumsicherung</name>
        <name lang="fr">Sécurité de l'espace aérien</name>
        <name lang="it">Sicurezza dello spazio aereo</name>
        <name lang="en">Air Policing</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="5160" org-id="502">
        <name lang="de">Verteidigung</name>
        <name lang="fr">Défense</name>
        <name lang="it">Difesa</name>
        <name lang="en">defence</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="5180" org-id="502">
        <name lang="de">Armee</name>
        <name lang="fr">Armée</name>
        <name lang="it">Esercito</name>
        <name lang="en">armed forces</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="5850" org-id="502">
        <name lang="de">Unterhalt / Instandhaltung</name>
        <name lang="fr">Entretien / Maintenance</name>
        <name lang="it">Manutenzione</name>
        <name lang="en">maintenance / upkeep</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="5900" org-id="502">
        <name lang="de">Flugbetrieb</name>
        <name lang="fr">Service de vol</name>
        <name lang="it">Esercizio di volo</name>
        <name lang="en">flight operations</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="5920" org-id="502">
        <name lang="de">Flugsicherung</name>
        <name lang="fr">Sécurité aérienne</name>
        <name lang="it">Sicurezza aerea</name>
        <name lang="en">air traffic control</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="5017" org-id="502">
        <name lang="de">Dossier RUAG</name>
        <name lang="fr">Dossier RUAG</name>
        <name lang="it">Dossier RUAG</name>
        <name lang="en">Dossier RUAG</name>
      </keyword>
    </keywords>
    <topics>
      <topic id="3">
        <name lang="de">Armee</name>
        <name lang="fr">Armée</name>
        <name lang="it">Esercito</name>
        <name lang="en">Armed Forces</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
