<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="79575" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2020-06-24</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="1070" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>1070</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Der Bundesrat</name>
      <name lang="fr">Conseil fédéral</name>
      <name lang="it">Il Consiglio federale</name>
      <name lang="en">The Federal Council</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.admin.ch/gov/de/start.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.admin.ch/gov/fr/accueil.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.admin.ch/gov/it/pagina-iniziale.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.admin.ch/gov/en/start.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="yes" id="703" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>701</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Staatssekretariat für Wirtschaft</name>
      <name lang="fr">Secrétariat d'Etat à l'économie</name>
      <name lang="it">Segreteria di Stato dell'economia</name>
      <name lang="en">State Secretariat for Economic Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.seco.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.seco.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.seco.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.seco.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@seco.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@seco.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@seco.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@seco.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="1070">
      <name lang="de">Der Bundesrat</name>
      <name lang="fr">Conseil fédéral</name>
      <name lang="it">Il Consiglio federale</name>
      <name lang="en">The Federal Council</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.admin.ch/gov/de/start.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.admin.ch/gov/fr/accueil.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.admin.ch/gov/it/pagina-iniziale.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.admin.ch/gov/en/start.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <department id="701">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Wirtschaft, Bildung und Forschung</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'économie, de la formation et de la recherche</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'economia, della formazione e della ricerca</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Economic Affairs, Education and Research</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Menschenrechtsverletzungen in Nicaragua: Bundesrat erlässt gezielte Sanktionen</title>
      <lead>Der Bundesrat hat am 24. Juni 2020 Zwangsmassnahmen im Zusammenhang mit der Situation in Nicaragua erlassen. Damit schliesst sich die Schweiz Sanktionen an, welche die EU aufgrund der anhaltenden Beeinträchtigung der Menschenrechte, der Demokratie und der Rechtsstaatlichkeit in Nicaragua erlassen hat. Die Verordnung über Massnahmen gegenüber Nicaragua tritt am 24. Juni 2020 in Kraft.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Der Bundesrat hat am 24. Juni 2020 Finanz- und Reisesanktionen gegenüber sechs Personen aus dem Umfeld von Präsident Daniel Ortega beschlossen. Mit den verabschiedeten Massnahmen werden deren Vermögenswerte gesperrt. Diesen Personen wird zusätzlich die Einreise bzw. die Durchreise durch die Schweiz verboten. Die Massnahmen richten sich aktuell gegen zwei persönliche Berater von Präsident Daniel Ortega sowie vier hochrangige Vertreter des Justiz- und Polizeiapparats, denen schwerwiegende Menschenrechtsverletzungen vorgeworfen werden. Vermögenswerte, die unter die Sperrung fallen, müssen dem SECO unverzüglich gemeldet werden. Die Sanktionen richten sich nicht gegen die nicaraguanische Bevölkerung.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Der Bundesrat ist sehr besorgt über die zunehmende Untergrabung der Demokratie, der Rechtsstaatlichkeit und der Menschenrechte in Nicaragua. Er fordert die nicaraguanischen Behörden auf, die Menschenrechte gemäss nationalem und internationalem Recht zu respektieren und zu schützen, insbesondere die Meinungsäusserungs- und Versammlungsfreiheit. Der Bundesrat fordert die nicaraguanischen Behörden auf, die Grundrechte der Bürgerinnen und Bürger, wie sie in den beiden Abkommen mit der Opposition von Ende März 2019 festgelegt sind, zu respektieren und eine echte Wahlreform durchzuführen. In Fortsetzung ihres 40-jährigen Engagements für die Entwicklung Nicaraguas ist die Schweiz bereit, die Bemühungen zur friedlichen Lösung des soziopolitischen Konflikts zu unterstützen.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Mit der Verordnung vom 24. Juni 2020 schliesst sich die Schweiz den Sanktionen der EU angesichts der Lage in Nicaragua an. Die beschriebenen Massnahmen treten am 24. Juni 2020 um 18.00 Uhr in Kraft.&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Kommunikationsdienst WBF, info@gs-wbf.admin.ch, 058 462 20 07</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Violations des droits de l’homme au Nicaragua : le Conseil fédéral édicte des sanctions ciblées</title>
      <lead>Le 24 juin 2020, le Conseil fédéral a arrêté des mesures de coercition en lien avec la situation au Nicaragua. La Suisse s’associe ainsi aux sanctions prises par l’UE en raison de la détérioration persistante des droits de l’homme, de la démocratie et de l’état de droit au Nicaragua. L’ordonnance instituant des mesures à l’encontre du Nicaragua entre en vigueur le 24 juin 2020.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Le Conseil fédéral a, le 24 juin 2020, arrêté des sanctions financières et des restrictions de déplacement à l’encontre de six personnes faisant partie de l’entourage du président Daniel Ortega. Les mesures décidées consistent en un gel des avoirs de ces personnes et une interdiction d’entrée en Suisse ou de transit par notre pays. Elles visent actuellement deux conseillers personnels du président Daniel Ortega et quatre représentants de haut rang de l’appareil judiciaire et policier, accusés de violations graves des droits de l’homme. Les avoirs faisant l’objet des sanctions financières doivent être déclarés sans délai au SECO. Les sanctions ne s’appliquent pas à la population du Nicaragua.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Le Conseil fédéral est très préoccupé par la multiplication des atteintes à la démocratie, à l’état de droit et aux droits de l’homme au Nicaragua. Il appelle les autorités nicaraguayennes à respecter et à défendre les droits de l’homme inscrits dans le droit interne et le droit international public, en particulier la liberté d’expression et la liberté de réunion. Le Conseil fédéral enjoint aux autorités du pays de respecter les droits fondamentaux des citoyens, tels que définis dans les deux accords conclus avec l’opposition à la fin de mars 2019, et de mener à bien une véritable réforme électorale. En considération de ses quarante années d’engagement en faveur du développement du Nicaragua, la Suisse est prête à soutenir les efforts visant une résolution pacifique du conflit sociopolitique.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Par l’ordonnance du 24 juin 2020, la Suisse s’associe aux sanctions prises par l’UE face à la situation au Nicaragua. Les mesures de coercition susmentionnées entrent en vigueur le 24 juin 2020, à 18 heures.&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Communication DEFR, info@gs-wbf.admin.ch, 058 462 20 07</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Violazioni dei diritti umani in Nicaragua: il Consiglio federale emana sanzioni mirate</title>
      <lead>Il 24 giugno 2020 il Consiglio federale ha emanato misure coercitive in relazione alla situazione osservata in Nicaragua. La Svizzera si allinea così alle sanzioni disposte dall’UE in seguito alle persistenti violazioni dei diritti umani, della democrazia e dello Stato di diritto in Nicaragua. L’ordinanza che istituisce provvedimenti nei confronti del Nicaragua entra in vigore il 24 giugno 2020.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Il 24 giugno 2020 il Consiglio federale ha deciso di adottare sanzioni finanziarie e restrizioni di viaggio nei confronti di sei persone vicine al presidente Daniel Ortega. Tali provvedimenti determinano il blocco dei valori patrimoniali e il divieto di ingresso e transito in Svizzera di queste persone. Attualmente riguardano due consulenti personali del presidente nicaraguense e quattro esponenti di alto rango dell’apparato di giustizia e polizia, accusati di gravi violazioni dei diritti umani. I valori patrimoniali soggetti al blocco devono essere notificati senza indugio alla SECO. Le sanzioni non vanno a colpire la popolazione nicaraguense.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Il Consiglio federale è seriamente preoccupato per il crescente indebolimento della democrazia, dello Stato di diritto e dei diritti umani in Nicaragua. Esso esorta le autorità del Paese a rispettare e a tutelare i diritti umani, e in particolare la libertà di espressione e di riunione, conformemente alle disposizioni del diritto nazionale e internazionale. Esorta inoltre le autorità nicaraguensi a rispettare i diritti fondamentali dei cittadini, come stabilito nei due accordi stipulati con le forze di opposizione a fine marzo 2019, e ad attuare una vera riforma elettorale. In linea con il suo impegno quarantennale per lo sviluppo del Nicaragua, la Svizzera è pronta a sostenere gli sforzi a favore di una soluzione pacifica del conflitto sociopolitico.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Con l’ordinanza del 24 giugno 2020 la Svizzera si associa alle sanzioni dell’UE nei confronti del Nicaragua. I provvedimenti descritti entrano in vigore il 24 giugno 2020 alle ore 18.00.&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Comunicazione DEFR, info@gs-wbf.admin.ch, 058 462 20 07</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Human rights violations in Nicaragua: Federal Council to impose targeted sanctions</title>
      <lead>On 24 June, the Federal Council decided to impose coercive measures in response to the current situation in Nicaragua. Switzerland is therefore joining the European Union in imposing sanctions on Nicaragua due to ongoing violations against human rights, democracy and the rule of law. The corresponding ordinance will come into force on 24 June.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;On 24 June, the Federal Council will impose financial and travel sanctions against six persons with ties to Nicaraguan president Daniel Ortega: their assets will be frozen and they will be banned from entering or travelling through Switzerland. The measures are currently aimed at two personal advisors to President Ortega, and four high-ranking representatives of Nicaragua’s judicial system and police force who are accused of serious human rights violations. Assets affected by the freeze must be reported to SECO immediately. These sanctions are not directed against the people of Nicaragua.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt; The Federal Council is very concerned by the increasing undermining of democracy, the rule of law and human rights in Nicaragua, and is urging the country’s authorities to respect and protect national and international laws on human rights, in particular those on freedom of expression and assembly. The Federal Council is also urging the Nicaraguan government to respect its citizens’ fundamental rights as defined in two agreements made with the opposition in March 2019, and to implement genuine electoral reform. Continuing on its 40-year commitment to the development of Nicaragua, Switzerland is prepared to support efforts to find a peaceful solution to this socio-political conflict.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;With its Ordinance of 24 June 2020, Switzerland is joining the EU in imposing sanctions in response to the situation in Nicaragua. The measures will come into force at 6pm on 24 June 2020.&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Communication Service EAER, info@gs-wbf.admin.ch, +41 58 462 20 07</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <offers>
      <offer id="255" org-id="703">
        <name lang="de">Sanktionen / Embargos und Exportkontrollen</name>
        <name lang="fr">sanctions / embargos et contrôles à l‘exportation</name>
        <name lang="it">Sanzioni / embarghi e controlli delle esportazioni</name>
        <name lang="en">sanctions / embargoes and export controls</name>
      </offer>
    </offers>
    <topics>
      <topic id="47">
        <name lang="de">Wirtschaft</name>
        <name lang="fr">Économie</name>
        <name lang="it">Economia</name>
        <name lang="en">Economic Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
