<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="79678" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2020-06-30</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="601" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>601</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Finanzdepartement</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des finances</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale delle finanze</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Finance</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.efd.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.dff.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.efd.admin.ch/efd/it/home.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.efd.admin.ch/efd/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="1060" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>601</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Staatssekretariat für internationale Finanzfragen</name>
      <name lang="fr">Secrétariat d'Etat aux questions financières internationales</name>
      <name lang="it">Segreteria di Stato per le questioni finanziarie internazionali</name>
      <name lang="en">State Secretariat for International Financial Matters</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.sif.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.sif.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.sif.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.sif.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@sif.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@sif.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@sif.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@sif.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="601">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Finanzdepartement</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des finances</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale delle finanze</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Finance</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.efd.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.dff.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.efd.admin.ch/efd/it/home.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.efd.admin.ch/efd/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Die Schweiz und das Vereinigte Königreich streben eine engere Zusammenarbeit für Finanzdienstleistungen an</title>
      <lead>Die Finanzminister der Schweiz und des Vereinigten Königreichs, Bundesrat Ueli Maurer und Schatzkanzler Rishi Sunak, haben heute an einem digitalen Treffen eine Erklärung über die künftige vertiefte Zusammenarbeit für Finanzdienstleistungen zwischen den beiden Ländern unterzeichnet. Sie tauschten sich zudem über die Auswirkungen der Corona-Pandemie auf die Wirtschaftslage und die Finanzmärkte sowie die nationalen Überbrückungshilfen für die Wirtschaft aus.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Die von Bundesrat Ueli Maurer und dem britischen Schatzkanzler Rishi Sunak unterzeichnete Erklärung (Joint Statement) unterstreicht die gemeinsame Absicht für ein Abkommen der beiden Länder. Dieses soll den grenzüberschreitenden Marktzugang für eine breite Palette an Finanzdienstleistungen im Versicherungs-, Banken-, Asset Management- sowie Kapitalmarktinfrastrukturbereich ermöglichen. Mit einem solchen Abkommen wollen die Schweiz und das Vereinigte Königreich ihr Bekenntnis zur Bedeutung offener Finanzmärkte und zur internationalen Finanzstabilität bekräftigen sowie ihre Stellung als weltweit führende internationale Finanzzentren in Europa festigen. Zusätzlich wollen die Schweiz und das Vereinigte Königreich ihre bereits etablierte Zusammenarbeit in internationalen Finanzgremien wie den Bretton-Woods-Institutionen künftig vertiefen.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Das von der Schweiz und dem Vereinigten Königreich angestrebte Abkommen soll auf dem Prinzip der gegenseitigen Anerkennung der jeweils anwendbaren Finanzmarktregulierung sowie des Aufsichtsrahmens basieren. Beide Seiten sind dabei dem Schutz von Investoren und Konsumenten sowie integren Märkten und Finanzstabilität unter Einhaltung höchster Regulierungsstandards verpflichtet. Das künftige Abkommen könnte darüber hinaus als Beispiel für eine mögliche Form der internationalen Zusammenarbeit im Bereich der Finanzdienstleistungen dienen. Die Schweiz sieht diese Arbeiten im Rahmen der Mind the gap-Strategie, mit der sie das bisherige Verhältnis zum Vereinigten Königreich über dessen EU-Austritt hinaus sichern und ausbauen will.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Die beiden Finanzminister tauschten sich weiter über die Situation rund um die Börsenäquivalenz sowie die Massnahme zum Schutz der Schweizer Börseninfrastruktur aus. Sie stellten in Aussicht, dass der gegenseitige Zugang zu den schweizerischen und britischen Börsen mittels gegenseitiger Anerkennungen ermöglicht werden soll, sobald beide Seiten nach dem Ende der Übergangsperiode für das UK gegenüber der EU die hierfür notwendigen Schritte umgesetzt haben.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Am nächsten Finanzdialog zwischen der Schweiz und dem Vereinigten Königreich im Herbst 2020 soll die Umsetzung der in der gemeinsamen Erklärung festgehaltenen Ambitionen diskutiert werden. Ende 2020 soll eine Zwischenbilanz gezogen werden.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Das Treffen der beiden Minister fand wegen der nach wie vor bestehenden Pandemie-Schutzvorkehrungen per Videokonferenz in Bern und London statt. Weitere Themen waren die Auswirkungen der Corona-Pandemie auf die Wirtschaftslage und die Finanzmärkte sowie die nationalen Überbrückungshilfen für die Wirtschaft.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Peter Minder, Leiter Kommunikation EFD +41 (0)58 462 63 01 peter.minder@gs-efd.admin.ch</contact>
      <attachment id="202906">
        <title>Joint Statement between the Federal Department of Finance and Her Majesty’s Treasury on deepening cooperation in financial services</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>336</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/61959.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>La Suisse et le Royaume-Uni entendent approfondir la collaboration dans le domaine des services financiers</title>
      <lead>Lors d'une rencontre virtuelle, le conseiller fédéral Ueli Maurer, chef du Département fédéral des finances, et Rishi Sunak, chancelier de l'Échiquier britannique, ont signé aujourd'hui une déclaration portant sur l'approfondissement de la collaboration des deux pays dans le domaine des services financiers. Ils ont également discuté des conséquences de la pandémie de coronavirus sur l'économie et les marchés financiers ainsi que des aides transitoires nationales en faveur de l'économie.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;La déclaration commune signée par le conseiller fédéral Ueli Maurer et Rishi Sunak, chancelier de l'Échiquier britannique, souligne que les deux pays ont l'intention de parvenir à un accord. Celui-ci devra faciliter l'accès transfrontalier au marché pour un large éventail de services financiers dans les secteurs de l'assurance, de la banque, de la gestion d'actifs et des infrastructures du marché des capitaux. En concluant un tel accord, la Suisse et le Royaume-Uni entendent réaffirmer leur engagement en faveur de marchés financiers ouverts et de la stabilité financière internationale ainsi que consolider leur position de centres financiers européens incontournables au niveau mondial. En outre, la Suisse et le Royaume-Uni souhaitent approfondir à l'avenir leur coopération déjà bien établie au sein d'organismes financiers internationaux tels que les institutions dites de Bretton Woods.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;L'accord visé par la Suisse et le Royaume-Uni sera fondé sur le principe de la reconnaissance mutuelle des cadres respectifs de réglementation et de surveillance des marchés financiers. Les deux parties s'engagent à protéger les investisseurs et les consommateurs, ainsi qu'à favoriser l'intégrité et la stabilité financière des marchés, en appliquant les normes de réglementation les plus exigeantes. Le futur accord pourrait également servir de modèle pour la coopération internationale dans le domaine des services financiers. Pour la Suisse, ces travaux sont en ligne avec sa stratégie «Mind the gap», qui a pour objectif de poursuivre et développer les relations avec le Royaume-Uni au-delà du retrait de ce dernier de l'UE.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Les deux ministres des finances ont par ailleurs échangé leurs points de vue sur la situation concernant l'équivalence boursière et la mesure visant à protéger l'infrastructure boursière suisse. Ils ont laissé entendre que l'accès réciproque aux bourses suisse et britannique sera possible grâce à la reconnaissance mutuelle dès que les deux parties auront mis en œuvre les mesures requises à cette fin, une fois que la période de transition du Royaume-Uni à l'égard de l'UE sera arrivée à terme.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Le prochain dialogue sur les questions financières entre la Suisse et le Royaume-Uni, à l'automne 2020, portera sur la mise en œuvre des objectifs énoncés dans la déclaration commune. Une évaluation intermédiaire sera effectuée à la fin de 2020.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Les mesures de protection contre la pandémie étant encore en vigueur, la réunion des deux ministres s'est tenue par vidéoconférence à Berne et à Londres. Par ailleurs, les conséquences de la pandémie de coronavirus sur la situation économique et les marchés financiers ainsi que les aides transitoires nationales en faveur de l'économie ont également été abordées.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Peter Minder, responsable de la communication du DFF n° tél. +41 (0)58 462 63 01, peter.minder@gs-efd.admin.ch</contact>
      <attachment id="202906">
        <title>Joint Statement between the Federal Department of Finance and Her Majesty’s Treasury on deepening cooperation in financial services</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>336</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/61959.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>La Svizzera e il Regno Unito auspicano una più stretta collaborazione in materia di servizi finanziari</title>
      <lead>In data odierna il ministro delle finanze svizzero Ueli Maurer e il suo omologo britannico, il cancelliere dello Scacchiere Rishi Sunak, si sono riuniti in videoconferenza per firmare una dichiarazione congiunta volta ad approfondire la futura collaborazione tra i due Paesi in materia di servizi finanziari. Inoltre, i due ministri hanno scambiato opinioni sugli effetti della pandemia da coronavirus per la situazione economica e i mercati finanziari nonché sulla concessione di aiuti transitori nazionali a favore dell’economia.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Con la dichiarazione congiunta firmata dal consigliere federale Ueli Maurer e dal cancelliere dello Scacchiere britannico Rishi Sunak i due Paesi sottolineano l’intenzione comune di stipulare un accordo per consentire l’accesso al mercato transfrontaliero per un’ampia gamma di servizi finanziari nei settori delle assicurazioni, delle banche, dell’«asset management» e dell’infrastruttura del mercato dei capitali. Questo accordo permetterebbe alla Svizzera e al Regno Unito di ribadire il loro impegno a favore dell’apertura dei mercati finanziari e della stabilità finanziaria internazionale nonché di consolidare la loro posizione in Europa come principali centri finanziari a livello globale. Inoltre i due Paesi intendono approfondire in futuro la loro già affermata collaborazione negli organismi finanziari internazionali come le istituzioni di Bretton Woods.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;L’accordo auspicato tra la Svizzera e il Regno Unito si fonderà sul principio del mutuo riconoscimento sia del quadro di vigilanza sia della regolamentazione applicabile in materia di mercati finanziari. A tal fine entrambe le Parti si impegnano a tutelare investitori e consumatori nonché a garantire l’integrità dei mercati e la stabilità finanziaria nel rispetto dei più elevati standard di regolamentazione. Il futuro accordo potrebbe, tra l’altro, servire da modello per una possibile forma di collaborazione internazionale nell’ambito della fornitura di servizi finanziari. Questi lavori si inseriscono nella strategia «Mind the gap», con la quale la Svizzera intende salvaguardare e intensificare l’attuale rapporto con il Regno Unito anche dopo la sua uscita dall’UE.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Inoltre, i due ministri delle finanze hanno scambiato opinioni sulla situazione concernente l’equivalenza borsistica e sulla misura di protezione dell’infrastruttura delle borse svizzere, avanzando la possibilità di consentire l’accesso reciproco alle borse svizzere e britanniche in base al principio del mutuo riconoscimento non appena, scaduto il periodo transitorio tra Regno Unito e UE, i due Paesi avranno attuato le misure necessarie a tale scopo.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In occasione del prossimo dialogo finanziario tra la Svizzera e il Regno Unito, previsto nell’autunno 2020, le Parti discuteranno dell’attuazione degli obiettivi fissati nella dichiarazione congiunta. Alla fine del 2020 sarà stilato un bilancio intermedio.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A causa delle disposizioni di sicurezza ancora in vigore dovute all’emergenza sanitaria, l’incontro tra i due ministri si è svolto in videoconferenza a Berna e Londra. Gli altri temi trattati riguardavano le ripercussioni della pandemia sulla situazione economica e sui mercati finanziari nonché la concessione di aiuti transitori nazionali a favore dell’economia.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Peter Minder, capo Comunicazione DFF Tel. +41 (0)58 462 63 01, peter.minder@gs-efd.admin.ch</contact>
      <attachment id="202906">
        <title>Joint Statement between the Federal Department of Finance and Her Majesty’s Treasury on deepening cooperation in financial services</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>336</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/61959.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Switzerland and United Kingdom seek closer cooperation on financial services</title>
      <lead>The Swiss and UK finance ministers, Federal Councillor Ueli Maurer and Chancellor of the Exchequer Rishi Sunak, today signed a joint statement on deepening cooperation between the two countries in the area of financial services during a virtual meeting. They also exchanged views on the impact of the COVID-19 pandemic on the economic situation and financial markets, as well as on national bridging aid schemes for the economy.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;The joint statement signed by Federal Councillor Ueli Maurer and the Chancellor of the Exchequer, Rishi Sunak, underscores the shared ambition for an agreement between the two countries that would enable cross-border market access for a wide range of financial services relating to insurance, banking, asset management and capital market infrastructure. With such an agreement, Switzerland and the United Kingdom intend to reaffirm their commitment to the importance of open financial markets and international financial stability, as well as to consolidate their position as the world's leading international financial centres in Europe. Furthermore, Switzerland and the United Kingdom intend to deepen their already established cooperation in international financial bodies such as the Bretton Woods institutions in the future.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The agreement pursued by Switzerland and the United Kingdom is to be based on the principle of mutual recognition of the respective financial market regulations and the supervisory framework. Thereby, both sides are committed to investor and consumer protection, financial market integrity and stability, while maintaining the highest regulatory standards. Moreover, the future agreement could serve as a possible template for international cooperation in the area of financial services. Switzerland sees this work as a continuation of the "mind the gap" strategy, with which it intends to secure and expand the existing relationship with the UK beyond its withdrawal from the EU.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The two finance ministers also exchanged views on the situation regarding stock market equivalence and the measure to protect the Swiss stock exchange infrastructure. They are holding out the prospect that reciprocal access to the Swiss and UK stock exchanges should be facilitated based on mutual recognition once both sides have implemented the necessary steps after the end of the United Kingdom's transition period vis-à-vis the EU.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The implementation of the ambitions set out in the joint statement will be discussed in the next financial dialogue between Switzerland and the United Kingdom in autumn 2020. An interim assessment will be carried out at the end of 2020.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The meeting of the two ministers took place via videoconference in Bern and London due to the continuing pandemic protection measures. Other topics discussed included the impact of the COVID-19 pandemic on the economic situation and financial markets, as well as national bridging aid schemes for the economy.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Peter Minder, Head of FDF Communications +41 (0)58 462 63 01 peter.minder@gs-efd.admin.ch</contact>
      <attachment id="202906">
        <title>Joint Statement between the Federal Department of Finance and Her Majesty’s Treasury on deepening cooperation in financial services</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>336</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/61959.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <offers>
      <offer id="291" org-id="1060">
        <name lang="de">Wirtschaft, Währung, Finanzplatz</name>
        <name lang="fr">Economie, monnaie, place financière</name>
        <name lang="it">Economia, Moneta, Piazza finanziaria</name>
        <name lang="en">Economic, Monetary and Financial Affairs</name>
      </offer>
    </offers>
    <keywords>
      <keyword id="126" org-id="1060">
        <name lang="de">Finanzplatz Schweiz</name>
        <name lang="fr">Place financière suisse</name>
        <name lang="it">Piazza finanziaria svizzera</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland as a financial centre</name>
      </keyword>
    </keywords>
    <topics>
      <topic id="35">
        <name lang="de">Finanzplatz</name>
        <name lang="fr">Place financière</name>
        <name lang="it">Piazza finanziaria</name>
        <name lang="en">Financial Centre</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="44">
        <name lang="de">Steuern</name>
        <name lang="fr">Impôts</name>
        <name lang="it">Imposte</name>
        <name lang="en">Taxation</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="47">
        <name lang="de">Wirtschaft</name>
        <name lang="fr">Économie</name>
        <name lang="it">Economia</name>
        <name lang="en">Economic Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
