<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="79913" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2020-07-23</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="804" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>801</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Generalsekretariat UVEK</name>
      <name lang="fr">Secrétariat général DETEC</name>
      <name lang="it">Segreteria generale DATEC</name>
      <name lang="en">General Secretariat of the Federal Department of Environment, Transport, Energy and Communications; General Secretariat DETEC</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.uvek.admin.ch/uvek/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.uvek.admin.ch/uvek/fr/home.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.uvek.admin.ch/uvek/it/home.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.uvek.admin.ch/uvek/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-uvek.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-uvek.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-uvek.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-uvek.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="201" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>201</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="801">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Umwelt, Verkehr, Energie und Kommunikation</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'environnement, des transports, de l'énergie et de la communication</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'ambiente, dei trasporti, dell'energia e delle comunicazioni</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of the Environment, Transport, Energy and Communications</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.uvek.admin.ch/uvek/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.uvek.admin.ch/uvek/fr/home.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.uvek.admin.ch/uvek/it/home.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.uvek.admin.ch/uvek/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-uvek.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-uvek.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-uvek.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-uvek.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <department id="201">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Bundespräsidentin Sommaruga besucht mit Präsident Zelenskyy die Ostukraine</title>
      <lead>Bundespräsidentin Simonetta Sommaruga ist am Donnerstag, 23. Juli 2020, gemeinsam mit Präsident Volodymyr Zelenskyy in den Osten der Ukraine gereist. Die Erarbeitung einer friedlichen Lösung für den Konflikt in dieser Region ist ein Schwerpunkt der Schweizer Friedenspolitik. Als fünftwichtigste Gebernation leistet die Schweiz Entwicklungszusammenarbeit und humanitäre Hilfe in der Ukraine und ist insbesondere auch mit der Organisation für Sicherheit und Zusammenarbeit in Europa (OSZE) am Friedensprozess beteiligt.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;In Stanyzja Luhanska besichtigten die Bundepräsidentin und der ukrainische Präsident am Nachmittag die Arbeiten zur Wiederinstandstellung einer Strasse und besuchten einen Übergang über die Kontaktlinie zwischen den Konfliktseiten. Die Bundespräsidentin betonte, dass die sogenannte Kontaktlinie Familien und Freunde teile und trenne, was zusammengehöre. Die fünf Übergänge, die jeden Monat eine Million Übertritte verzeichnen, seien aber hoffnungsvolle Orte. Sie betonte das Schweizer Engagement bei der Suche nach einer friedlichen Lösung des Konfliktes und verwies darauf, dass die von der Schweiz unterstützte OSZE-Mission auch zum Wiederaufbau der zivilen Infrastruktur beitrage. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Am Vormittag hatten Bundespräsidentin Sommaruga und Präsident Zelenskyy die aktuelle Situation in Slowjansk mit lokalen Behörden sowie Fachleuten der humanitären Hilfe und Entwicklungspolitik besprochen. Vor Ort wurde ausserdem ein Schweizer Hilfstransport empfangen, der Material zur Trinkwasser-Aufbereitung angeliefert hatte. Das Wasserwerk «Voda Donbasu» zählt in Europa zu den grössten seiner Art und versorgt fast vier Millionen Menschen auf beiden Seiten der Kontaktlinien mit Trinkwasser. Die Schweiz unterstützt dies seit 2015. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Die Reise in den Osten der Ukraine beschliesst den ersten bilateralen Präsidialbesuch aus der Schweiz in dem Land. Ziel war es, die bereits sehr gute Zusammenarbeit zwischen der Schweiz und der Ukraine zu würdigen und zugleich das grosse Potential für einen noch engeren Austausch in politischer, wirtschaftlicher, wissenschaftlicher und kultureller Hinsicht zu betonen. &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Informationsdienst UVEK: Géraldine Eicher, 079 211 30 52</contact>
      <link id="203617">
        <title>Schweiz und die Ukraine: Bilaterale Beziehungen</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/countries/ukraine/de/home/bilaterale-beziehungen/in-kuerze.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="203618">
        <title>Dossier UVEK</title>
        <uri>https://www.uvek.admin.ch/uvek/de/home/uvek/bundesraetin-simonetta-sommaruga/anlaesse/praesidialbesuch-in-der-ukraine.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>La présidente de la Confédération en visite dans l’Est de l’Ukraine avec le président ukrainien</title>
      <lead>La présidente de la Confédération Simonetta Sommaruga s’est rendue jeudi 23 juillet 2020, en compagnie du président ukrainien Volodymyr Zelenskyy, dans l’Est de l’Ukraine. Trouver une solution pacifique au conflit qui déchire cette région est une priorité de la politique de paix de la Suisse. Comptant parmi les cinq plus importants donateurs en Ukraine, notre pays mène des projets de coopération au développement et d’aide humanitaire et participe au processus de paix avec l’Organisation pour la sécurité et la coopération en Europe (OSCE) notamment.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Dans l’après-midi, la présidente de la Confédération et le président ukrainien ont assisté aux travaux de remise en état d’une rue dans la ville de Stanytsya Louhanska et ont visité un point de passage sur la ligne de contact entre les deux parties au conflit. La présidente de la Confédération a souligné que la ligne dite « de contact » divise des familles et des amis et sépare ce qui va de pair, mais que les cinq points de passage empruntés tous les mois par un million de personnes sont des lieux d’espoir. Elle a rappelé l’engagement de la Suisse dans la recherche d’une solution pacifique au conflit et précisé que la mission de l’OSCE, qui est soutenue par la Suisse, contribue également à la reconstruction de l’infrastructure civile.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Dans la matinée, la présidente de la Confédération et son homologue ukrainien ont discuté de la situation dans la région de Sloviansk avec des autorités locales et des spécialistes de l’aide humanitaire et de la politique de développement. Ils ont également reçu sur place un convoi suisse d’aide humanitaire qui avait livré du matériel pour le traitement de l’eau potable. La station hydraulique Voda Donbassa est l’une des plus grandes stations de ce type en Europe. Approvisionnant en eau potable près de 4 millions de personnes des deux côtés de la ligne de contact, elle est soutenue depuis 2015 par la Suisse.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Le voyage dans l’Est de l’Ukraine marque la fin de la première visite présidentielle bilatérale de la Suisse en Ukraine. L’objectif était de saluer la très bonne collaboration entre nos deux pays et de relever le grand potentiel de développement de relations encore plus étroites dans les domaines politique, économique, scientifique et culturel.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Service d’information du DETEC, Géraldine Eicher, 079 211 30 52</contact>
      <link id="203619">
        <title>La Suisse et l’Ukraine: Relations bilatérales</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/countries/ukraine/fr/home/relations-bilaterales/bilaterale.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="203620">
        <title>Dossier DETEC</title>
        <uri>https://www.uvek.admin.ch/uvek/fr/home/uvek/bundesraetin-simonetta-sommaruga/anlaesse/praesidialbesuch-in-der-ukraine.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>La presidente della Confederazione visita l’Ucraina orientale con il presidente Zelenskyy</title>
      <lead>Giovedì 23 luglio 2020, la presidente della Confederazione Simonetta Sommaruga si è recata in Ucraina orientale insieme al presidente della Repubblica ucraina Volodymyr Zelenskyy. Una soluzione pacifica del conflitto in questa regione è una priorità della politica di pace della Svizzera. In qualità di quinta più importante nazione donatrice, la Svizzera fornisce cooperazione allo sviluppo e aiuto umanitario in Ucraina e partecipa al processo di pace, in particolare con l’Organizzazione per la sicurezza e la cooperazione in Europa (OSCE).</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;A Stanytsia Luhanska, nel pomeriggio la presidente della Confederazione Svizzera e il presidente della Repubblica ucraina hanno assistito ai lavori di ripristino di una strada e visitato un punto di attraversamento sulla linea di contatto tra le due parti al conflitto. La presidente della Confederazione ha rilevato che la linea cosiddetta «di contatto» divide famiglie e amici e separa ciò che si appartiene; tuttavia i cinque punti di attraversamento, utilizzati ogni mese da un milione di persone, rappresentano luoghi di speranza. Simonetta Sommaruga ha sottolineato l’impegno della Svizzera nella ricerca di una soluzione pacifica del conflitto e rammentato che la missione dell’OCSE sostenuta dalla Svizzera contribuisce anche alla ricostruzione delle infrastrutture civili. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In mattinata, la presidente della Confederazione e il suo omologo ucraino hanno discusso, con le autorità locali e gli esperti dell’aiuto umanitario e della politica di sviluppo, della situazione attuale a Slowjansk. Sul posto è stato inoltre ricevuto un trasporto umanitario svizzero con materiale per il trattamento dell’acqua potabile. L’acquedotto «Voda Donbasu» è uno dei più grandi nel suo genere in Europa e fornisce acqua potabile a quasi quattro milioni di persone sui due lati della linea di contatto. La Svizzera sostiene questo progetto dal 2015. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Con il viaggio nell’Ucraina orientale si conclude la prima visita bilaterale di una presidente della Confederazione Svizzera nel Paese. L’obiettivo era di rendere omaggio alla già ottima cooperazione esistente tra la Svizzera e l’Ucraina e al tempo stesso di ribadire il grande potenziale per relazioni ancora più strette sotto il profilo politico, economico, scientifico e culturale. &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Servizio informazioni del DATEC, Géraldine Eicher, 079 211 30 52</contact>
      <link id="203621">
        <title>La Svizzera e l’Ucraina: Relazioni bilaterali</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/countries/ukraine/it/home/la-svizzera-e/relazioni-bilaterali.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="203622">
        <title>Dossier DATEC</title>
        <uri>https://www.uvek.admin.ch/uvek/it/home/uvek/bundesraetin-simonetta-sommaruga/anlaesse/praesidialbesuch-in-der-ukraine.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>President Sommaruga visits Eastern Ukraine with President Zelenskyy</title>
      <lead>On Thursday, 23 July, President Simonetta Sommaruga travelled with President Volodymyr Zelenskyy to Eastern Ukraine. Finding a peaceful solution to the conflict in this region is one of Switzerland’s peace policy priorities. Switzerland is Ukraine’s fifth most important donor nation, providing development cooperation and humanitarian aid, and is also involved in the peace process, primarily through the Organization for Security and Cooperation in Europe (OSCE).</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;In Stanytsia Luhanska, Ms Sommaruga and the Ukrainian president visited the site of road refurbishment work in the afternoon and inspected a crossing point on the contact line between the two sides in the conflict. Ms Sommaruga expressed her regret that the contact line divides families and friends and separates those who belong together. However, the five crossing points, through which one million people pass every month, remain places of hope, she said. She stressed Switzerland’s commitment to finding a peaceful solution to the conflict and cited the contribution that the OSCE mission, supported by Switzerland, has made to rebuilding civilian infrastructure.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In the morning, the two presidents discussed the current situation in Sloviansk with local officials and specialists in humanitarian aid and development policy. They were also present as a Swiss humanitarian aid convoy delivered a consignment of drinking water treatment equipment. The Voda Donbasu water facility is among the largest of its kind in Europe and supplies almost four million people on both sides of the contact line with drinking water; it has received financial support from Switzerland since 2015. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The trip to Eastern Ukraine concluded the first bilateral presidential visit to the country by Switzerland. Its purpose was to acknowledge the extremely good cooperation between Switzerland and Ukraine, and to stress the enormous potential for even closer political, economic, scientific and cultural ties between the two countries. &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>DETEC Information Service: Géraldine Eicher, 079 211 30 52</contact>
      <link id="203623">
        <title>Switzerland and Ukraine: Bilateral relations</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/countries/ukraine/en/home/switzerland-and/bilateral-relations.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="203624">
        <title>Dossier DETEC (in German)</title>
        <uri>https://www.uvek.admin.ch/uvek/de/home/uvek/bundesraetin-simonetta-sommaruga/anlaesse/praesidialbesuch-in-der-ukraine.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <keywords>
      <keyword id="560" org-id="804">
        <name lang="de">Internationales</name>
        <name lang="fr">Affaires internationales</name>
        <name lang="it">Affari Internazionali</name>
        <name lang="en">International Affairs</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="200" org-id="804">
        <name lang="de">Bundespräsident</name>
        <name lang="fr">Président de la Confédération</name>
        <name lang="it">Presidente della Confederazione</name>
        <name lang="en">President of the Confederation</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="1700" org-id="804">
        <name lang="de">Wirtschaft</name>
        <name lang="fr">Economie</name>
        <name lang="it">Economia</name>
        <name lang="en">Economy</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="1600" org-id="804">
        <name lang="de">Umweltpolitik</name>
        <name lang="fr">Umweltpolitik</name>
        <name lang="it">Umweltpolitik</name>
        <name lang="en">Umweltpolitik</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="310" org-id="804">
        <name lang="de">Energiepolitik</name>
        <name lang="fr">Energiepolitik</name>
        <name lang="it">Energiepolitik</name>
        <name lang="en">Energiepolitik</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="620" org-id="804">
        <name lang="de">Klima</name>
        <name lang="fr">Climat</name>
        <name lang="it">Clima</name>
        <name lang="en">Climate</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="1390" org-id="804">
        <name lang="de">Wasser</name>
        <name lang="fr">Eau</name>
        <name lang="it">Acqua</name>
        <name lang="en">Wasser</name>
      </keyword>
    </keywords>
    <topics>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
