<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="79918" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2020-07-27</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="1089" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>701</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Innosuisse – Schweizerische Agentur für Innovationsförderung</name>
      <name lang="fr">Innosuisse – Agence suisse pour l’encouragement de l’innovation</name>
      <name lang="it">Innosuisse – Agenzia svizzera per la promozione dell’innovazione</name>
      <name lang="en">Innosuisse – Swiss Innovation Promotion Agency</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.innosuisse.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.innosuisse.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.innosuisse.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.innosuisse.ch</www>
      <email lang="de"/>
      <email lang="fr"/>
      <email lang="it"/>
      <email lang="en"/>
    </originator>
    <department id="701">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Wirtschaft, Bildung und Forschung</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'économie, de la formation et de la recherche</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'economia, della formazione e della ricerca</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Economic Affairs, Education and Research</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Innosuisse bewilligt zwölf NTN – Innovation Booster</title>
      <lead>Innosuisse, die Schweizerische Agentur für Innovationsförderung, baut nächstes Jahr ihr Förderportfolio mit dem Instrument NTN - Innovation Booster aus. Diese bringen die wichtigsten Akteure aus Wissenschaft, Industrie und Gesellschaft in der Schweiz in zukunftsträchtigen Innovationsbereichen zusammen und ermöglichen es, in einer offenen Innovationskultur gemeinsam entwickelte, konkrete Innovationsideen zu testen. Im Rahmen der ersten Ausschreibung gingen 64 Gesuche ein, zwölf hat Innosuisse bewilligt.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Die eingegangenen Gesuche decken ein breites Spektrum ab, insbesondere in den Bereichen Gesundheit, Digitalisierung und Nachhaltigkeit. Für die Förderperiode 2021–2024 hat Innosuisse in einem ersten zweistufigen Verfahren zwölf NTN – Innovation Booster mit folgenden thematischen Ausrichtungen bewilligt:&lt;/p&gt; &lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Additive Manufacturing&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Applied Circular Economy&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Blockchain Nation Switzerland&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Databooster&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Energy Lab&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Futur de la Microtechnique&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Living Labs for Decarbonisation&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Next Generation of Food Ecosystems&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Photonics&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Sport et Activité Physique&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Technology and Special Needs&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;User-Centred Innovation in Medtech&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt; &lt;p&gt;Innosuisse rechnet damit, dass mithilfe der NTN – Innovation Booster in den nächsten vier Jahren rund 1000 radikale Innovationsideen entstehen, wovon rund ein Drittel zu konkreten Lösungen weiterentwickelt werden soll.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h3&gt;Nachhaltige Wettbewerbsvorteile für KMU&lt;/h3&gt; &lt;p&gt;Die Teilnahme an den Aktivitäten der NTN – Innovation Booster steht allen interessierten Schweizer Akteuren offen. Dank der Zusammenarbeit mit Partnern entlang der gesamten Wertschöpfungskette und dem Wissenstransfer zwischen Hochschulen, Wirtschaft und Gesellschaft sollen die NTN – Innovation Booster Schweizer KMU nachhaltige Wettbewerbsvorteile verschaffen und massgeblich zur Lösung gesellschaftlicher Herausforderungen beitragen. Wissenschaftliche Erkenntnisse geben dabei wichtige Impulse und führen zur Einführung von innovativen Prozessen, Produkten, Dienstleistungen und Geschäftsmodellen.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Die NTN – Innovation Booster nehmen ihre Arbeit Anfang 2021 auf. Die Ausschreibungen für weitere NTN - Innovation Booster finden alljährlich im November statt. Der nächste Eingabeschluss ist Ende Februar 2021. Das Förderbudget über vier Jahre beträgt 21,3 Millionen Schweizer Franken.&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Lukas Krienbühl und Eliane Kersten, Co-Leitung Kommunikation media@innosuisse.ch +41 58 481 84 73 / +41 58 464 19 95</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Innosuisse approuve douze NTN – Innovation Boosters</title>
      <lead>Innosuisse, l’Agence suisse pour l’encouragement de l’innovation, va étoffer l’année prochaine son portefeuille d’encouragement avec l’instrument appelé NTN – Innovation Booster. Il s’agit de rassembler les principaux acteurs du monde scientifique, industriel et de la société en Suisse autour de domaines d’innovation prometteurs et de stimuler, dans une culture d’innovation ouverte, l’expérimentation d’idées novatrices, concrètes et développées en commun. Dans le cadre du premier appel d’offres, Innosuisse a reçu 64 demandes, parmi lesquelles elle en a approuvé douze.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Les demandes reçues couvrent un large éventail de sujets, notamment dans les domaines de la santé, de la numérisation et de la durabilité. À l’issue d’un premier processus en deux étapes, Innosuisse a approuvé pour la période d’encouragement 2021-2024 douze NTN – Innovation Boosters s’articulant autour des thèmes suivants:&lt;/p&gt; &lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Additive Manufacturing&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Applied Circular Economy&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Blockchain Nation Switzerland&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Databooster&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Energy Lab&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Futur de la Microtechnique&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Living Labs for Decarbonisation&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Next Generation of Food Ecosystems&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Photonics&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Sport et Activité Physique&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Technology and Special Needs&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;User-Centred Innovation in Medtech&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt; &lt;p&gt;Durant les quatre prochaines années, Innosuisse escompte que les NTN – Innovation Boosters généreront près d’un millier d’idées innovantes radicales, dont un tiers environ débouchera sur des solutions concrètes.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h3&gt;Des avantages concurrentiels durables pour les PME&lt;/h3&gt; &lt;p&gt;La participation aux activités des NTN – Innovation Boosters est ouverte à tous les acteurs suisses intéressés. Grâce à la coopération avec des partenaires tout au long de la chaîne de valeur et au transfert de savoirs entre les hautes écoles, les entreprises et la société, les NTN – Innovation Boosters devraient fournir aux PME suisses des avantages concurrentiels durables et contribuer à la résolution de défis sociétaux qui se posent. Les connaissances scientifiques devront donner des impulsions importantes et aboutir à la mise en place de procédés, de produits, de services et de modèles d’affaires novateurs.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Les NTN – Innovation Boosters seront opérationnels dès le début de l’année 2021. Les appels à candidatures pour d’autres NTN – Innovation Boosters auront lieu chaque année en novembre. La prochaine date limite de soumission est fixée à fin février 2021. Le budget d’encouragement sur quatre ans est de 21,3 millions de francs suisses.&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Lukas Krienbuehl et Eliane Kersten, co-responsables de la communication media@innosuisse.ch +41 58 481 84 73 / +41 58 464 19 95</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Innosuisse approva 12 NTN – Innovation Booster</title>
      <lead>Innosuisse, l’Agenzia svizzera per la promozione dell’innovazione, amplierà il prossimo anno il suo portafoglio di promozione con gli NTN – Innovation Booster. Questi ultimi riuniscono i più importanti attori del mondo scientifico e industriale nonché della società civile in Svizzera in settori promettenti dell’innovazione, stimolando la sperimentazione di idee innovative concrete, sviluppate congiuntamente, nell’ambito di una cultura dell’open innovation. In occasione del primo bando di concorso sono pervenute 64 domande, 12 delle quali sono state approvate da Innosuisse.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Le domande presentate coprono un’ampia gamma di argomenti, in particolare nei settori della salute, della digitalizzazione e della sostenibilità. Nel corso di una procedura articolata in due fasi, per il periodo di promozione 2021–2024 Innosuisse ha approvato 12 NTN – Innovation Booster incentrati sulle seguenti tematiche:&lt;/p&gt; &lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Additive Manufacturing&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Applied Circular Economy&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Blockchain Nation Switzerland&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Databooster&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Energy Lab&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Futur de la Microtechnique&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Living Labs for Decarbonisation&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Next Generation of Food Ecosystems&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Photonics&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Sport et Activité Physique&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Technology and Special Needs&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;User-Centred Innovation in Medtech &lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt; &lt;p&gt;Innosuisse prevede che, nei prossimi quattro anni, dagli NTN - Innovation Booster scaturiranno circa 1000 idee innovative radicali, di cui circa un terzo sarà sviluppato fino a sfociare in soluzioni concrete.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h3&gt;Vantaggi competitivi sostenibili per le PMI&lt;/h3&gt; &lt;p&gt;La partecipazione alle attività degli NTN – Innovation Booster è aperta a tutti gli attori svizzeri interessati. Grazie alla collaborazione con i partner lungo l’intera catena del valore e al trasferimento di sapere tra il mondo accademico, l’economia e la società, gli NTN – Innovation Booster procureranno alle PMI svizzere vantaggi competitivi sostenibili e contribuiranno in modo significativo alla risoluzione di sfide sociali. I risultati scientifici forniranno importanti impulsi e favoriranno l’introduzione di processi, prodotti, servizi e modelli di business innovativi.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Gli NTN – Innovation Booster avvieranno le proprie attività all’inizio del 2021. I bandi di concorso per ulteriori NTN – Innovation Booster saranno indetti ogni anno a novembre. Il prossimo termine per la presentazione delle domande è febbraio 2021. Il supporto di Innosuisse sui 4 anni si eleva a 21.3 milioni di Franchi.&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Lukas Krienbühl e Eliane Kersten, coresponsabili comunicazione media@innosuisse.ch +41 58 481 84 73 / +41 58 464 19 95</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Innosuisse approves twelve NTN – Innovation Boosters</title>
      <lead>Innosuisse, the Swiss Innovation Agency, will next year expand its funding portfolio with the instrument NTN – Innovation Boosters. These bring together the most important players from science, industry and society in Switzerland in promising fields of innovation and stimulate the testing of jointly developed, concrete innovation ideas in an open innovation culture. In the first call for proposals, 64 applications were received and twelve were approved by Innosuisse.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;The applications received cover a wide range of topics, particularly in the areas of health, digitalisation and sustainability. In a first two-stage process, Innosuisse has approved twelve NTN – Innovation Boosters for the funding period 2021-2024 on the following topics:&lt;/p&gt; &lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Additive Manufacturing&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Applied Circular Economy&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Blockchain Nation Switzerland&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Databooster&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Energy Lab&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Futur de la Microtechnique&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Living Labs for Decarbonisation&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Next Generation of Food Ecosystems&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Photonics&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Sport et Activité Physique&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Technology and Special Needs&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;User-Centred Innovation in Medtech &lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt; &lt;p&gt;Innosuisse expects the NTN – Innovation Boosters to generate around 1,000 radical innovation ideas over the next four years, around a third of which should be developed further into concrete solutions.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h3&gt;Sustainable competitive advantages for SMEs&lt;/h3&gt; &lt;p&gt;Participation in the activities of NTN – Innovation Boosters is open to all interested Swiss stakeholders. Thanks to the collaboration with partners along the entire value chain and a transfer of knowledge between universities, business and society, the NTN – Innovation Boosters are set to provide Swiss SMEs with sustainable competitive advantages and make a significant contribution to solving societal challenges. Scientific findings should provide important impetus and lead to the introduction of innovative processes, products, services and business models.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The NTN – Innovation Boosters will start their work at the beginning of 2021. Calls for proposals for further NTN – Innovation Boosters will take place annually in November. The next deadline for submissions is end of February 2021. The funding budget over four years is 21.3 million Swiss francs.&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Lukas Krienbuehl and Eliane Kersten, co-heads of communications media@innosuisse.ch +41 58 481 84 73 / +41 58 464 19 95</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="8">
        <name lang="de">Bildung und Forschung</name>
        <name lang="fr">Formation et recherche</name>
        <name lang="it">Formazione e ricerca</name>
        <name lang="en">Education and Research</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
