<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="80237" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2020-09-01</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="703" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>701</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Staatssekretariat für Wirtschaft</name>
      <name lang="fr">Secrétariat d'Etat à l'économie</name>
      <name lang="it">Segreteria di Stato dell'economia</name>
      <name lang="en">State Secretariat for Economic Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.seco.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.seco.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.seco.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.seco.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@seco.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@seco.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@seco.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@seco.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="701">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Wirtschaft, Bildung und Forschung</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'économie, de la formation et de la recherche</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'economia, della formazione e della ricerca</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Economic Affairs, Education and Research</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>EasyGov.swiss lanciert neues Update mit SHAB-Meldungen und Markenanmeldungen</title>
      <lead>Das Staatssekretariat für Wirtschaft (SECO) hat per 1. September 2020 den Online-Schalter für Unternehmen EasyGov.swiss erneut ausgebaut. Mit dem Release 1.6 lassen sich auf der Plattform neu gewisse Meldungen des Schweizerischen Handelsamtsblatts (SHAB) erfassen und publizieren sowie beim Institut für Geistiges Eigentum (IGE) elektronische Markenanmeldungen via «e-trademark» vornehmen. </lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Neu wurde der Publikationsprozess für die Veröffentlichung von amtlichen SHAB-Meldungen auf EasyGov integriert. So können gewisse amtliche Meldungen via EasyGov erfasst und an das SHAB übermittelt werden. Diese Meldungen, können direkt im EasyGov-Cockpit eingesehen, mittels intuitiven Filtermöglichkeiten durchsucht und als PDF heruntergeladen werden.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Die elektronische Markenanmeldung «e-trademark» wird als Teilintegration über EasyGov angeboten. Neben der Anmeldung von Marken lassen sich für bestehende Marken auch Adressänderungen im Register durchführen. Ziel ist, dass Unternehmen in Zukunft Schutztitel für Marken, Patente und Designs beim IGE beantragen können.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Schrittweiser Ausbau als Umsetzungsziel von E-Government Schweiz&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;EasyGov ist Teil der Strategie von E-Government Schweiz, der Organisation von Bund, Kantonen und Gemeinden für die Ausbreitung elektronischer Behördenleistungen. Zudem ist der Ausbau von EasyGov in der aktuellen Strategie «Digitale Schweiz» des Bundesrats verankert. Ziel ist es, die Geschäftsprozesse zu vereinfachen, konsequent auf die Nutzerbedürfnisse auszurichten und laufend zu optimieren. Behördenleistungen sollen so bereitgestellt werden, dass sie ohne besondere Kenntnisse über behördliche Zuständigkeiten aus einer Hand und ohne technisches Spezialwissen nutzbar sind.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Der One-Stop-Shop EasyGov wird schrittweise ausgebaut, auf welchem Unternehmen alle angebotenen Behördenleistungen über einen einzigen Account mit einheitlicher Benutzerführung abwickeln können. So müssen regelmässig benötigte Firmendaten wie zum Beispiel die Adressdaten, die Handelsregisternummer oder neu auch die Bankverbindung nur einmal erfasst werden (Once-Only-Prinzip). &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Seit der Lancierung im November 2017 hat EasyGov bereits mehrere grosse Updates erfahren. Zu Beginn wurde die Plattform insbesondere von Gründerinnen und Gründern genutzt. Sie können von der Anmeldung beim Handelsregister bis zur Mehrwertsteuer, den Sozial- und Unfallversicherungen, sämtliche nötigen Behördengänge für die Firmengründung online erledigen. In der Legislaturperiode 2020–2023 soll das Angebot an Behördenleistungen stark ausgebaut und die Plattform laufend optimiert werden.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Die Covid19-Krise hat die Digitalisierung vieler KMU beschleunigt. Dies hat sich auf die Anzahl registrierter Firmen positiv ausgewirkt. Seit Februar 2020 durfte EasyGov einen starken Zuwachs von über 10'000 neuen Firmen verzeichnen. Unterdessen wird das Angebot bereits von über 30'000 Unternehmen genutzt.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Staatssekretariat für Wirtschaft SECO Holzikofenweg 36 CH-3003 Bern Tel. +41 58 462 56 56 Fax +41 58 462 56 00</contact>
      <link id="204629">
        <title>Leistungsumfang von EasyGov.swiss Version 1.6 - https://aktuell.easygov.swiss</title>
        <uri>https://bit.ly/2EGegwh</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="204633">
        <title>www.EasyGov.swiss</title>
        <uri>http://www.easygov.ch/easygov</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>EasyGov.swiss lance une nouvelle mise à jour avec les publications de la FOSC et les dépôts de marque</title>
      <lead>Le Secrétariat d’État à l’économie (SECO) a encore étoffé Easygov.swiss, le guichet en ligne pour les entreprises, le 1er septembre 2020. Dans la version 1.6, il sera désormais possible de saisir et de publier des annonces de la Feuille officielle suisse du commerce (FOSC), mais aussi de procéder au dépôt de marque en ligne auprès de l’Institut Fédéral de la Propriété Intellectuelle (IPI) par le biais d’« e-trademark ». </lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;La procédure permettant de publier des informations officielles dans la FOSC a été nouvellement intégrée à EasyGov. Ainsi, certaines publications officielles peuvent être saisies par l’intermédiaire d’EasyGov et transmises à la FOSC. Elles peuvent être consultées directement dans le cockpit EasyGov, faire l’objet de recherches au moyen d’options de filtre intuitives et être téléchargées au format PDF.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Le dépôt de marque électronique « e-trademark » est proposé sous forme d’intégration partielle dans EasyGov. Les marques existantes peuvent également procéder à des changements d’adresse dans le registre. L’objectif est de permettre à l’avenir aux entreprises de demander des titres de protection pour leurs marques, brevets et designs auprès de l’Institut Fédéral de la Propriété Intellectuelle (IPI).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Un développement progressif : un objectif de mise en œuvre de cyberadministration suisse&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;br /&gt;EasyGov fait partie de la stratégie de cyberadministration suisse, l’organisation commune de la Confédération, des cantons et des communes visant à développer l’offre de prestations électroniques des autorités. L’extension d’EasyGov est en outre inscrite dans la Stratégie actuelle « Suisse numérique » du Conseil fédéral, dont l’objectif est de simplifier les procédures, de les orienter de manière systématique vers les besoins des utilisateurs et de les optimiser en permanence. Les prestations électroniques des autorités doivent être fournies de manière centralisée, sans qu’il soit nécessaire de connaître les compétences spécifiques à chaque autorité ou de disposer de connaissances techniques particulières.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Guichet unique, EasyGov fait l’objet de développements continus et permet aux entreprises d’utiliser un seul compte, avec une interface standardisée pour toutes les démarches administratives proposées. De cette manière, il suffit de saisir une fois pour toutes les données d’entreprise régulièrement demandées telles que les coordonnées, le numéro du registre du commerce ou, – une nouveauté – les coordonnées bancaires (principe du « once only »). &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Depuis son lancement en novembre 2017, EasyGov a connu plusieurs mises à jour d’envergure. À ses débuts, la plateforme était principalement utilisée par les fondateurs d’entreprise, qui peuvent accomplir en ligne toutes les démarches administratives nécessaires à la création de leur structure, de l’inscription au registre du commerce à la TVA en passant par les assurances sociales et l’assurance-accidents. Au cours de la législature 2020–2023, l’offre de prestations doit être sensiblement étendue, tandis que la plateforme sera optimisée en continu.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;La crise du coronavirus a accéléré le passage au numérique de nombreuses PME, comme en témoigne le nombre de raisons sociales enregistrées. Depuis février 2020, EasyGov a connu une forte hausse, avec l’entrée de plus de 10 000 nouvelles entreprises. Entretemps, l’offre est utilisée par plus de 30 000 entreprises.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Secrétariat d'Etat à l'économie SECO Holzikofenweg 36 CH-3003 Berne tél. +41 58 462 56 56 fax +41 58 462 56 00</contact>
      <link id="204630">
        <title>Étendue des prestations de la version 1.6 d’EasyGov.swiss - https://actuel.easygov.swiss/</title>
        <uri>https://bit.ly/32EXTIm</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="204633">
        <title>www.EasyGov.swiss</title>
        <uri>http://www.easygov.ch/easygov</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>EasyGov.swiss lancia un nuovo aggiornamento con comunicazioni FUSC e depositi di marchi</title>
      <lead>Dal 1° settembre 2020, la Segreteria di Stato dell’economia (SECO) offre una versione ulteriormente ampliata del proprio sportello online per le imprese EasyGov.swiss. La release 1.6 è infatti arricchita di nuove funzioni: la possibilità di redigere e pubblicare sulla piattaforma determinate comunicazioni per il Foglio ufficiale svizzero di commercio (FUSC) e quella di depositare marchi per via elettronica, tramite «e-trademark», presso l’Istituto Federale della Proprietà Intellettuale (IPI). </lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Il processo di pubblicazione delle comunicazioni nel FUSC è stato integrato in EasyGov, pertanto ora è possibile redigere determinate comunicazioni ufficiali tramite EasyGov e trasmetterle al FUSC. Tali comunicazioni possono essere consultate direttamente nel cockpit Easy-Gov, sfogliate mediante funzioni di filtro intuitive e scaricate in formato PDF.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Il sistema elettronico di deposito dei marchi «e-trademark» viene offerto tramite EasyGov come integrazione parziale e permette non solo di depositare nuovi marchi, ma anche di effettuare variazioni di indirizzo per marchi già registrati. L’obiettivo è consentire alle imprese, in futuro, &lt;strong&gt;di utilizzare questo canale per richiedere all’IPI titoli di protezione per marchi, brevetti e design.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ampliamento graduale come obiettivo di attuazione di e-government Svizzera&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;EasyGov è parte integrante della Strategia di e-government Svizzera, l’organizzazione della Confederazione, dei Cantoni e dei Comuni che promuove la diffusione delle prestazioni elettroniche fornite dalle autorità. Inoltre, l’ampliamento di EasyGov è ancorato nell’attuale Strategia «Svizzera digitale» del Consiglio federale. L’obiettivo è quello di semplificare i processi operativi, calibrarli in maniera coerente sulle esigenze degli utenti e ottimizzarli continuamente. Le prestazioni fornite dalle autorità dovrebbero essere strutturate in modo tale da essere fruibili attraverso un’unica interfaccia, senza che l’utente debba disporre di particolari conoscenze riguardo alle competenze delle varie istituzioni o di nozioni tecniche specifiche. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;L’one-stop-shop EasyGov verrà gradualmente ampliato fino a consentire alle imprese di accedere a tutte le prestazioni fornite dalle autorità attraverso un unico account e una gestione dell’utente unitaria. I dati aziendali richiesti frequentemente, come ad es. quelli relativi all’indirizzo, il numero del registro di commercio o – ulteriore novità – anche le coordinate bancarie devono poter essere immessi una sola volta (principio «once only»). &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Da quando è stato lanciato, nel novembre del 2017, EasyGov è già stato oggetto di numerosi e sostanziali aggiornamenti. Inizialmente, la piattaforma veniva utilizzata in particolare da chi fondava un’impresa, che poteva servirsene per sbrigare online tutte le procedure amministrative necessarie per la costituzione – dall’iscrizione nel registro di commercio all’imposta sul valore aggiunto, dalle assicurazioni sociali a quelle contro gli infortuni. Nel periodo legislativo 2020–2023 si prevedono un forte ampliamento dell’offerta di prestazioni fornite dalle autorità e una continua ottimizzazione della piattaforma.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;La crisi provocata dalla Covid-19 ha impresso un’accelerazione al processo di digitalizzazione di molte PMI, e ciò si è tradotto in un incremento del numero di imprese registrate: da febbraio 2020, il sistema conta oltre 10 000 nuovi utenti. Al momento, più di 30 000 aziende utilizzano il sistema.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Segreteria di Stato dell'economia SECO Holzikofenweg 36 CH-3003 Berna tel. +41 58 462 56 56 fax +41 58 462 56 00</contact>
      <link id="204631">
        <title>Gamma di servizi di EasyGov.swiss versione 1.6 - https://attualita.easygov.swiss</title>
        <uri>https://bit.ly/3hJ5jAt</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="204633">
        <title>www.EasyGov.swiss</title>
        <uri>http://www.easygov.ch/easygov</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>EasyGov.swiss launches new update with SOGC publications and trade mark registra-tions</title>
      <lead>With effect from 1 September 2020, the Swiss State Secretariat for Economic Affairs (SECO) has once again expanded EasyGov.swiss, its online service desk for companies. The 1.6 release now allows certain publications of the Swiss Official Gazette of Commerce (SOGC) to be filed and published on the platform and electronic trade mark applications to be submitted to the Swiss Institute of Intellectual Property (IGE) via “e-trademark”. </lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;The process for publishing official SOGC reports has now been integrated into EasyGov, meaning that certain official publications can be filed via EasyGov and transmitted to the SOGC. Users can view these publications directly in the EasyGov cockpit, search through them using intuitive filter options and download them as PDFs.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;“e-trademark”, the electronic trade mark application process, is offered as a partial integration via EasyGov. In addition to trade mark applications, changes of address for existing trademarks can also be made in the register. The aim is for companies to be able to apply to the IGE for protective titles for trade marks, patents and designs.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Gradual expansion as an implementation goal of E-Government Switzerland&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;EasyGov is part of the E-Government Switzerland strategy, the organisation of the federal government, cantons and municipalities for the expansion of electronic government services. The expansion of EasyGov is also anchored in the current “Digital Switzerland” strategy of the Federal Council. The aim is to simplify business processes, rigorously align them to user needs and continuously optimise them. Government services are to be provided in such a way that they can be used from a single source with no particular knowledge of official responsibilities and no specialist knowledge of technical issues.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The one-stop-shop EasyGov is being gradually expanded to become a website on which companies can process all available government services via a single account with uniform user guidance. For example, company data that is regularly required, such as address data, commercial register number or now also bank details, only has to be entered once (once-only principle). &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Since its launch in November 2017, EasyGov has already undergone several major updates. Originally, the platform was used by company founders in particular. They can take care of all the necessary formalities for setting up a company online, from registering with the commercial register and handling VAT to sorting out social security and accident insurance, etc. In the legislative period from 2020 to 2023, the range of government services is to be significantly broadened and the platform continuously enhanced.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The COVID-19 crisis has accelerated the digitalisation of many SMEs, which has had a positive effect on the number of registered companies. Since February 2020, EasyGov has posted strong growth of over 10,000 new companies. The facility is already used by over 30,000 companies.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>State Secretariat for Economic Affairs SECO Holzikofenweg 36 CH-3003 Bern Tel. +41 58 462 56 56 Fax +41 58 462 56 00</contact>
      <link id="204632">
        <title>Service scope of EasyGov.swiss Version 1.6 - https://news.easygov.swiss</title>
        <uri>https://bit.ly/3jxozS1</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="204633">
        <title>www.EasyGov.swiss</title>
        <uri>http://www.easygov.ch/easygov</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="47">
        <name lang="de">Wirtschaft</name>
        <name lang="fr">Économie</name>
        <name lang="it">Economia</name>
        <name lang="en">Economic Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
