<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="80532" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2020-09-28</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="703" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>701</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Staatssekretariat für Wirtschaft</name>
      <name lang="fr">Secrétariat d'Etat à l'économie</name>
      <name lang="it">Segreteria di Stato dell'economia</name>
      <name lang="en">State Secretariat for Economic Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.seco.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.seco.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.seco.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.seco.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@seco.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@seco.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@seco.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@seco.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="701">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Wirtschaft, Bildung und Forschung</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'économie, de la formation et de la recherche</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'economia, della formazione e della ricerca</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Economic Affairs, Education and Research</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Vierteljährliches Bruttoinlandprodukt: Revidierte Daten bis zum 2. Quartal 2020</title>
      <lead>Das Staatssekretariat für Wirtschaft SECO und das Bundesamt für Statistik BFS haben im Einklang mit den internationalen Empfehlungen eine « Benchmark-Revision » der BIP-Daten durchgeführt. Neu publiziert das SECO detailliertere Quartalsdaten für die Wertschöpfung der Industrie und des Handels. Die konjunkturelle Interpretation bleibt im Wesentlichen unverändert.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Die revidierten BIP-Daten bestätigen: Im 2. Quartal 2020 ging das BIP der Schweiz so stark zurück wie noch nie seit Beginn der vierteljährlichen Daten 1980 (–7,3 %, vor der Revision: –8,2 %). &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Neben der vergleichsweise frühen Lockerung der gesundheitspolitischen Einschränkungen trug die Branchenstruktur der Schweizer Wirtschaft dazu bei, einen noch stärkeren Einbruch des BIP zu verhindern. Dies wird an den neu vom SECO veröffentlichten Quartalsdaten zur Wertschöpfung einzelner bedeutender Branchen deutlich. So steigerte die chemisch-pharmazeutische Industrie ihre Wertschöpfung im 2. Quartal immerhin um 0,3 % und stabilisierte damit das Ergebnis des gesamten verarbeitenden Gewerbes (–10,3%, vor der Revision: –9,0 %), ohne jedoch die Einbussen der konjunktursensitiveren Industriebranchen zu kompensieren.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Die Nachfrage ging im 2. Quartal auf breiter Basis zurück. Die privaten Konsumausgaben (–8,1 %, vor der Revision: –8,6 %) brachen im Zuge der Pandemie und der Eindämmungsmassnahmen ein; die Ausrüstungsinvestitionen waren stark rückläufig (–10,0 %, vor der Revision:–11,7 %). Vor dem Hintergrund abrupter Nachfragerückgänge im Ausland waren schliesslich auch die Exporte von Waren (–6,5 %, vor der Revision: –9,4 %) und Diensten (–15,3 %, vor der Revision: –15,9 %) rückläufig.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Die Arbeitnehmerentgelte* reduzierten sich stark (–4,9 %). Unter Berücksichtigung der Kurzarbeitsentschädigung, die breit eingesetzt wurde, fielen die Einkommenseinbussen der Arbeitnehmenden unter dem Strich aber wesentlich geringer aus (–0,3 %).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Die diesen Zahlen zugrunde liegende « Benchmark-Revision » wird in einer technischen Notiz erläutert.** In einzelnen Fällen wurden die historischen Daten erheblich revidiert, insbesondere deren absolute Niveaus, weniger jedoch deren Entwicklung über die Zeit. Die konjunkturelle Interpretation der Daten bleibt nach den Revisionsarbeiten unverändert.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class="nsbtextkasten"&gt;Mediengespräch 28. September 2020 – 9.30 Uhr, Medienzentrum in Bern: Ist die Krise überstanden?&lt;br /&gt;Eric Scheidegger, Leiter der Direktion für Wirtschaftspolitik des SECO, und Philippe Küttel, Leiter der Sektion Volkswirtschaftliche Gesamtrechnung des BFS, erläutern die aktuellen BIP-Zahlen und die Konjunkturlage.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Telefonische Medienanfragen werden nach dem Mediengespräch ab ca. 11 Uhr beantwortet.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;* Entgelte für geleistete Arbeit. Transfers (z. B. Kurzarbeitsentschädigung) sind nicht darin enthalten.&lt;br /&gt;** «Revision 2020 der Volkswirtschaftlichen Gesamtrechnung: Wichtigste Änderungen sowie strukturelle und konjunkturelle Auswirkungen», erhältlich unter www.seco.admin.ch/bip .&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Staatssekretariat für Wirtschaft SECO Holzikofenweg 36 CH-3003 Bern Tel. +41 58 462 56 56 Fax +41 58 462 56 00</contact>
      <attachment id="205696">
        <title>Wirtschaftslage Schweiz</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>1018</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/63065.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="205700">
        <title>Medienmitteilung und Tabellen - Vierteljährliches Bruttoinlandprodukt: Revidierte Daten bis zum 2. Quartal 2020</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>318</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/63069.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>PIB trimestriel : séries révisées jusqu’au 2e trimestre 2020</title>
      <lead>Suivant les recommandations internationales, le Secrétariat d’État à l’économie SECO et l’Office fédéral de la statistique OFS ont procédé à une révision « benchmark » des séries du PIB. Le SECO publiera désormais des données trimestrielles détaillées relatives à la valeur ajoutée dans l’industrie et le commerce. L’interprétation conjoncturelle demeure pratiquement inchangée.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;La révision des séries du PIB confirme qu’au 2e trimestre 2020, le PIB de la Suisse a reculé comme jamais auparavant depuis le début des données trimestrielles en 1980, enregistrant un repli de 7,3 % (avant la révision : –8,2 %).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Deux principaux facteurs ont néanmoins contribué à empêcher une chute encore plus marquée du PIB : le fait que les restrictions sanitaires ont été levées relativement tôt, mais aussi la structure sectorielle de l’économie suisse, ce que montrent clairement les données trimestrielles sur la valeur ajoutée nouvellement publiées par le SECO pour certaines branches. Dans le secteur chimique et pharmaceutique, notamment, la valeur ajoutée a en effet augmenté de 0,3 % au 2e trimestre, ce qui a permis de stabiliser le résultat global de l’industrie manufacturière (–10,3 % , contre –9,0 % avant révision), sans pour autant compenser les pertes des branches plus sensibles à la conjoncture.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;La contraction de la demande a été quasi généralisée au 2e trimestre. Les dépenses de consommation privée ont dégringolé (–8,1 % , contre –8,6 % avant révision) dans le sillage de la pandémie et des mesures prises pour l’endiguer, et les investissements en biens d’équipement se sont également inscrits en fort recul (–10,0 % , contre –11,7 % avant révision). Enfin, le net repli de la demande à l’étranger a entraîné un tassement des exportations de marchandises (–6,5 % , contre –9,4 % avant révision) et de services (–15,3 % contre –15,9 % avant révision).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;La rémunération des salariés* a fortement baissé (–4,9 %). En prenant en compte l’indemnité en cas de réduction de l’horaire de travail, qui a été utilisée à large échelle, la perte de revenu des salariés a toutefois été bien moins importante (−0,3 %).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;La révision « benchmark » sous-tendant ces chiffres est explicitée dans une note technique.** Dans certains cas, les données historiques ont été considérablement révisées, en particulier en ce qui concerne leurs niveaux absolus. L’évolution dans le temps, elle, est beaucoup moins touchée par la révision. L’interprétation conjoncturelle des données reste inchangée à l’issue des travaux de révision.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class="nsbtextkasten"&gt;Point de presse du 28 septembre 2020, 9 h 30, au Centre de presse du Palais fédéral, à Berne : La crise est-elle surmontée ? &lt;br /&gt;Eric Scheidegger, chef de la Direction de la politique économique du SECO, et Philippe Küttel, chef de la section Comptes nationaux de l’OFS, commenteront les séries du PIB ainsi que la situation conjoncturelle.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Les questions par téléphone pourront être reçues à l’issue du point de presse, à partir de 11 h environ.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;* Rémunération pour le travail effectué. Les transferts (par exemple, l’indemnité en cas de réduction de l’horaire de travail) ne sont pas inclus.&lt;br /&gt;** « Révision 2020 des comptes nationaux : Principaux changements et impacts », v. www.seco.admin.ch/pib.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Secrétariat d'Etat à l'économie SECO Holzikofenweg 36 CH-3003 Berne tél. +41 58 462 56 56 fax +41 58 462 56 00</contact>
      <attachment id="205697">
        <title>Situation de l’économie suisse (en allemand)</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>1018</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/63066.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="205701">
        <title>Communiqué de presse et tableaux - PIB trimestriel : séries révisées jusqu’au 2e trimestre 2020</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>375</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/63070.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>PIL trimestrale: dati rivisti fino al 2° trimestre 2020</title>
      <lead>In linea con le raccomandazioni internazionali, la Segreteria di Stato dell’economia (SECO) e l’Ufficio federale di statistica (UST) hanno effettuato una revisione «benchmark» dei dati sul prodotto interno lordo (PIL). La SECO pubblica ora dati trimestrali più dettagliati sulla creazione di valore dell’industria e del commercio; in termini congiunturali l’interpretazione resta sonstanzialmente invariata.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Come confermano i dati revisionati, nel 2° trimestre 2020 il PIL svizzero ha registrato il più forte calo dall’inizio del rilevamento dei dati trimestrali nel 1980 (−7,3 %; prima della revisione: −8,2 %).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;L’allentamento delle restrizioni sanitarie avvenuto relativamente presto e la struttura settoriale dell’economia svizzera hanno contribuito a evitare un crollo del PIL ancora più marcato, come dimostrano i nuovi dati trimestrali sulla creazione di valore in singoli settori importanti, pubblicati dalla SECO. In particolare, nel 2° semestre l’industria chimica e farmaceutica ha pur sempre registato un aumento dello 0,3 per cento del valore aggiunto, stabilizzando i risultati dell’intera industria manifatturiera (−10,3 %, prima della revisione: −9,0 %), anche se non è stata in grado di compensare le perdite dei rami industriali più sensibili alle variazioni congiunturali.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;Nel corso del 2° trimestre la domanda è fortemente diminuita. Il consumo privato (−8,1 %, prima della revisione: −8,6 %) è crollato per via della pandemia e dei provvedimenti di contenimento; gli investimenti in beni di equipaggiamento sono fortemente regrediti (−10,0 %, prima della revisione: −11,7 %). Infine, dato il brusco calo della domanda estera, si sono ridotte anche le esportazioni di beni (−6,5 %, prima delle revisione: −9,4 %) e di servizi (−15,3 %, prima della revisione: −15,9 %).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I redditi da lavoro dipendente* sono notevolmente diminuiti (−4,9 %). Tuttavia, tendendo conto del ricorso su vasta scala all’indennità per lavoro ridotto, il reddito dei lavoratori dipendenti è calato solo dello 0,3 per cento.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;La revisione «benchmark» su cui si basano queste cifre viene illustrata in un documento tecnico**. In singoli casi i dati storici sono stati rivisti in modo significativo, soprattutto in termini di livello assoluto, mentre hanno subito poche modifiche per quanto riguarda l’evoluzione nel tempo. In termini congiunturali l’interpretazione è invece rimasta invariata.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class="nsbtextkasten"&gt;Incontro con i media: 28 settembre 2020, ore 9.30, Centro media di Palazzo federale, Berna: La crisi è stata superata?&lt;br /&gt;Eric Scheidegger, capo della Direzione politica economica della SECO, e Philipp Küttel, capo della Sezione Conti economici nazionali dell’UST, illustrano le cifre attuali del PIL e la situazione congiunturale.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Alle domande telefoniche dei giornalisti si risponderà dopo l’incontro a partire dalle 11.00 ca.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;* Corrispettivo per il lavoro svolto; non comprende importi aggiuntivi (ad es. indennità per lavoro ridotto)&lt;br /&gt;** «Revisione 2020 dei conti nazionali: principali cambiamenti e conseguenze a livello strutturale e congiunturale » ottenibile sul sito www.seco.admin.ch/pil.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Segreteria di Stato dell'economia SECO Holzikofenweg 36 CH-3003 Berna tel. +41 58 462 56 56 fax +41 58 462 56 00</contact>
      <attachment id="205698">
        <title>Situazione dell’economia svizzera (in tedesco)</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>1018</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/63067.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="205702">
        <title>Comunicato stampa e tabelle - PIL trimestrale: dati rivisti fino al 2° trimestre 2020</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>305</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/63078.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Quarterly GDP: revised data up to Q2 2020</title>
      <lead>In line with international recommendations, the State Secretariat for Economic Affairs (SECO) and the Federal Statistical Office (FSO) have undertaken a “benchmark revision” of gross domestic product (GDP) data. SECO is now publishing more detailed quarterly data on value added in trade and industry. The interpretation of this data from an economic perspective is remaining largely unchanged.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;As the revised GDP data confirms, in the second quarter of 2020 Swiss GDP experienced its sharpest decline since the quarterly figures were first calculated in 1980 (–7.3%, pre-revision: –8.2%).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As well as the decision to ease public health restrictions relatively early, the industry mix in the Swiss economy also helped to prevent an even more drastic slump in GDP. This is highlighted in the quarterly data that SECO has recently published on value added in a number of important sectors. In particular, the chemical and pharmaceutical industry increased its value added by 0.3% in the second quarter despite the prevailing situation, thus stabilising the result for the manufacturing industry as a whole (revised from –9.0% to –10.3%). However, this was not enough to offset the losses sustained by the industrial sectors more sensitive to the economic cycle.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Demand fell across the board in the second quarter. Private consumption (revised from –8.6% to –8.1%) slumped in the wake of the pandemic and the measures taken to contain it, while investment in equipment also contracted sharply (revised from –11.7% to –10.0%). Finally, exports of goods (revised from –9.4% to –6.5%) and services (revised from –15.9% to –15.3%) also dropped due to abrupt falls in demand from abroad.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The compensation of the employees* fell significantly (–4.9%). Taking into account the short-time work compensation, which was widely used, the income losses for employees were much lower (–0.3%).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The «benchmark revision» underpinning these figures is explained in more detail in the accompanying technical note.** In a few cases, the historical data has been revised significantly – primarily in terms of absolute levels rather than trends over time. The revision has not changed the interpretation of the data from a business cycle perspective.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class="nsbtextkasten"&gt;Press conference 28 September 2020 – 9.30 a.m. Media Centre in Bern: “Has the crisis been overcome?”&lt;br /&gt;Eric Scheidegger, Head of SECO’s Economic Policy Directorate, and Philippe Küttel, Head of the FSO’s National Accounts Section, explain the current GDP figures and the economic situation.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Phoned-in questions from the press will be answered after the press conference from around 11 a.m.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;* Compensation for work. Transfers such short-time working compensation are not included. &lt;br /&gt;** «2020 revision of the National Accounts: main changes and structural and economic effects», available at www.seco.admin.ch/gdp.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>State Secretariat for Economic Affairs SECO Holzikofenweg 36 CH-3003 Bern Tel. +41 58 462 56 56 Fax +41 58 462 56 00</contact>
      <attachment id="205699">
        <title>Economic situation in Switzerland (in German)</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>1018</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/63068.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="205703">
        <title>Press release and tables - Quarterly GDP: revised data up to Q2 2020</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>317</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/63072.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <offers>
      <offer id="156" org-id="703">
        <name lang="de">BIP-Quartalsdaten und Konjunkturtendenzen</name>
        <name lang="fr">Données trimestrielles PIB et tendances conjoncturelles</name>
        <name lang="it">Tendenze congiunturali</name>
        <name lang="en">Quarterly data on GDP and economic trends</name>
      </offer>
    </offers>
    <topics>
      <topic id="43">
        <name lang="de">Statistik</name>
        <name lang="fr">Statistiques</name>
        <name lang="it">Statistica</name>
        <name lang="en">Statistics</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="47">
        <name lang="de">Wirtschaft</name>
        <name lang="fr">Économie</name>
        <name lang="it">Economia</name>
        <name lang="en">Economic Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
