<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="81663" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2020-12-21</pubdate>
    <blocking-period>2020-12-21</blocking-period>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="318" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>301</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Bundesamt für Statistik</name>
      <name lang="fr">Office fédéral de la statistique</name>
      <name lang="it">Ufficio federale di statistica</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Statistical Office</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.statistik.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.statistique.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.statistica.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.statistics.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@bfs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@bfs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@bfs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@bfs.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="301">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement des Innern</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'intérieur</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'interno</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Home Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Neuchâtel</city>
      <title>Höhere Berufsbildung: Arbeitgeber übernehmen zwischen 23% und 41% der Ausbildungskosten</title>
      <lead>2018 finanzierten die Kandidatinnen und Kandidaten der höheren Berufsbildung (HBB) ihre Ausbildung etwa zur Hälfte selbst. Als wichtigste externe Finanzierungsquelle wird der Arbeitgeber genannt; er übernimmt zwischen 23% (Diplom der höheren Fachschule) und 41% (eidgenössisches Diplom) der Ausbildungskosten. Daneben spielen für die eidgenössischen Prüfungen erstmals die 2018 eingeführten Bundesbeiträge eine Rolle. Wurden Bundesbeiträge bezogen, so deckten diese etwa ein Drittel der angefallenen Kosten. Das zeigen die Ergebnisse der zweiten Erhebung zur höheren Berufsbildung des Bundesamtes für Statistik (BFS).</lead>
      <text link="no">Diese Medienmitteilung und weitere Informationen zum Thema finden Sie auf der Website des BFS (siehe Link unten)</text>
      <contact>Info eHBB, BFS, Sektion Bildungssystem, Tel.: +41 58 483 93 70, E-Mail: ehbb@bfs.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="209872">
        <title>Kompletter Text und Mediendossier</title>
        <uri>https://www.bfs.admin.ch/news/de/2020-0029</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Neuchâtel</city>
      <title>Formation professionnelle supérieure: les employeurs assument de 23% à 41% des coûts de formation</title>
      <lead>En 2018, les candidats de la formation professionnelle supérieure (FPS) ont financé eux-mêmes près de la moitié de leur formation. Les candidats citent l’employeur comme la plus importante source de financement externe. Celui-ci prend en charge entre 23% (diplôme des écoles supérieures) et 41% (diplôme fédéral) des coûts de formation. En outre, le régime de subventions fédérales introduit en 2018 joue pour la première fois un rôle pour les examens fédéraux. Si les candidats ont perçu des contributions fédérales, celles-ci couvraient environ un tiers des coûts. C’est ce qui ressort des résultats de la deuxième enquête sur la formation professionnelle supérieure réalisée par l’Office fédéral de la statistique (OFS).</lead>
      <text link="no">Vous trouverez ce communiqué de presse et d'autres informations sur ce thème sur le site web de l'OFS (voir le lien ci-dessous)</text>
      <contact>Info eHBB, OFS, Section Système de formation, tél.: +41 58 483 93 70, e-mail: ehbb@bfs.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="209873">
        <title>Texte intégral et dossier de presse</title>
        <uri>https://www.bfs.admin.ch/news/fr/2020-0029</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Neuchâtel</city>
      <title>Formazione professionale superiore: i datori di lavoro si assumono tra il 23 e il 41% dei costi di formazione</title>
      <lead>Nel 2018 le candidate e i candidati alla formazione professionale superiore (FPS) hanno finanziato di tasca propria circa metà della formazione. La più importante fonte di finanziamento esterna indicata è il datore di lavoro, che sostiene tra il 23% (diploma di scuola specializzata superiore) e il 41% (diploma federale) dei costi di formazione. Inoltre, per la prima volta entrano in gioco anche i contributi federali per gli esami federali, introdotti nel 2018. Laddove vi si è fatto ricorso, questi contributi hanno coperto circa un terzo dei costi. Questo è quanto emerge dai risultati della seconda indagine sulla formazione professionale superiore realizzata dall’Ufficio federale di statistica (UST).</lead>
      <text link="no">Il presente comunicato stampa e ulteriori informazioni sul tema sono reperibili sulla pagina Internet dell'UST (link sotto)</text>
      <contact>Info eHBB, UST, Sezione Sistema di formazione, tel.: +41 58 483 93 70, e-mail: ehbb@bfs.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="209874">
        <title>Testo integrale e dossier per i media</title>
        <uri>https://www.bfs.admin.ch/news/it/2020-0029</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Neuchâtel</city>
      <title>Professional education: Employers assume between 23% and 41% of professional education costs</title>
      <lead>In 2018, candidates financed around half of their professional education themselves. The employer was cited as the main external source of funding, assuming between 23% (in the case of a federal diploma awarded by a professional education institution) and 41% (in the case of a federal diploma awarded by means of a federal examination) of professional education costs. The federal contributions introduced in 2018 also played a part for the first time in the funding of federal examinations. Where contributions were obtained, they covered roughly a third of the costs incurred. These are the results of the second survey on professional education from the Federal Statistical Office (FSO).</lead>
      <text link="no">This press release and further information on this topic can be found on the FSO website (see link below)</text>
      <contact>Info eHBB, FSO, Education System section, tel.: +41 58 483 93 70, email: ehbb@bfs.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="209875">
        <title>Please note that the English version only includes the release's lead</title>
        <uri>https://www.bfs.admin.ch/news/en/2020-0029</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <keywords>
      <keyword id="317.16" org-id="318">
        <name lang="de">Bildung und Wissenschaft</name>
        <name lang="fr">Education et science</name>
        <name lang="it">Formazione e scienza</name>
        <name lang="en">Education and science</name>
      </keyword>
    </keywords>
    <topics>
      <topic id="8">
        <name lang="de">Bildung und Forschung</name>
        <name lang="fr">Formation et recherche</name>
        <name lang="it">Formazione e ricerca</name>
        <name lang="en">Education and Research</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="43">
        <name lang="de">Statistik</name>
        <name lang="fr">Statistiques</name>
        <name lang="it">Statistica</name>
        <name lang="en">Statistics</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
