<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="22622" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2000-06-27</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="404" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>401</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Bundesamt für Polizei</name>
      <name lang="fr">Office fédéral de la police</name>
      <name lang="it">Ufficio federale di polizia</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Office of Police</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.fedpol.admin.ch/fedpol/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.fedpol.admin.ch/fedpol/fr/home.html</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.fedpol.admin.ch/fedpol/it/home.html</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.fedpol.admin.ch/fedpol/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@fedpol.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@fedpol.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@fedpol.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@fedpol.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="401">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Justiz- und Polizeidepartement</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de justice et police</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale di giustizia e polizia</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Justice and Police</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.ejpd.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.ejpd.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.ejpd.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.ejpd.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-ejpd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">Info@gs-ejpd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-ejpd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-ejpd.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>370 Meldungen wegen Geldwäschereiverdacht - 1,5 Milliarden Franken gesperrt - Zweiter Rechenschaftsbericht der Meldestelle für Geldwäscherei</title>
      <lead>Die Meldestelle für Geldwäscherei im Bundesamt für Polizei (BAP) hat im zweiten Jahr ihrer Tätigkeit eine massive Zunahme von Meldungen und davon betroffener Vermögenswerte verzeichnet: Insgesamt gingen 370 Meldungen über geldwäschereiverdächtige Vorgänge (Vorjahr: 160) bei der Meldestelle ein, die Vermögenswerte von über 1,5 Milliarden Franken (Vorjahr: über 330 Millionen Franken) betrafen.</lead>
      <text link="no">Die Zunahme der Meldungen bedeutet nicht, dass im Zeitraum des zweiten Rechenschaftsberichtes (1. April 1999 bis 31. März 2000) in der Schweiz mehr Geld gewaschen worden ist. Diese positiv zu bewertende Zunahme zeigt vielmehr, dass Geldwäscher nicht mehr damit rechnen können, gefahrlos ihre Tätigkeit auszuüben und unerkannt zu bleiben. Die gesetzlichen Bestimmungen werden von vielen Akteuren auf dem Finanzplatz Schweiz ernst genommen. Die Meldungen stammen überwiegend von Banken (85%); die Beteiligung des Nichtbankensektors liegt noch unter den Erwartungen. &lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Die Meldestelle leitete rund zwei Drittel der Meldungen an Strafverfolgungsbehörden weiter. Betroffen waren hauptsächlich die Finanzzentren Genf und Zürich. Den häufigsten Hintergrund der Meldungen bildeten Vorgänge im Bereich Wirtschaftskriminalität. Bei den Vertragspartnern sticht die Stellung der Offshore-Gesellschaften (British Virgin Islands, Cayman Islands, Isle of Man, Bahamas) hervor, während bei den wirtschaftlich Berechtigten der höhere Anteil von Personen russischer Nationalität bemerkenswert ist. Zahlreiche Meldungen lösten die Vorgänge bei der Bank of New York sowie das nigerianische Rechtshilfeersuchen im Fall Abacha aus. &lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; &lt;strong&gt;Abschreckende Wirkung von Strafverfahren&lt;br /&gt; &lt;/strong&gt;63% der insgesamt 107 Meldungen, welche die Meldestelle im ersten Jahr ihrer Tätigkeit an die Strafverfolgungsbehörden weitergeleitet hat, führten zur Eröffnung von Strafverfahren, die noch offen sind. Diese Quote ist – auch im internationalen Vergleich – erfreulich hoch. Die meisten Verfahren müssen rechtshilfeweise in Zusammenarbeit mit ausländischen Justizbehörden geführt werden, was viel Zeit benötigt. Daher liegen noch keine rechtskräftigen Verurteilungen oder Einziehungsverfügungen vor. Bereits die Eröffnung eines Strafverfahrens hat aber eine abschreckende Wirkung und dient so dem guten Ruf des Finanzplatzes Schweiz. &lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Die internationale Zusammenarbeit spielt bei der Bekämpfung der Geldwäscherei eine entscheidende Rolle. Die Meldestelle für Geldwäscherei arbeitet deshalb in den Gremien der FATF (Financial Action Task Force on Money Laundering) und in der Egmont Gruppe der FIU's (weltweiter Verbund der Geldwäscherei-Meldestellen Financial Intelligence Units) mit. Zudem hat sie letztes Jahr mit der belgischen Meldestelle eine Absichtserklärung unterzeichnet, welche die Zusammenarbeit regelt. Weitere Absichtserklärungen werden in nächster Zeit mit den Meldestellen Frankreichs, Finnlands und Tschechiens unterzeichnet.</text>
      <contact>Mediendienst fedpol, T +41 31 324 13 91</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>370 communications de présomption de blanchiment d'argent – 1,5 milliard de francs bloqué - Deuxième bilan des activités du Bureau de communication en matière de blanchiment d'argent.</title>
      <lead>Le Bureau de communication en matière de blanchiment d'argent de l'Office fédéral de la police (OFP) a enregistré au cours de sa deuxième année d'activité une augmentation substantielle du nombre des communications et des sommes d'argent impliquées. En effet, 370 communications de présomption de blanchiment lui ont été adressées en 1999 (1998: 160). Les sommes d'argent concernées se montent à plus de 1,5 milliard de francs (1998: plus de 300 millions de francs).</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;La nette progression du nombre des communications ne signifie pas qu'il y ait eu davantage d'argent blanchi en Suisse durant la période considérée par le rapport (1er avril 1999 – 31 mars 2000). Elle doit être considérée comme positive, car elle démontre que les responsables du blanchiment d'argent ne peuvent plus espérer effectuer impunément leurs opérations en restant dans l'ombre. Les dispositions légales ne sont donc pas restées lettre morte et de nombreux acteurs de la place financière suisse les prennent au sérieux. Les communications ont été en majorité le fait des banques (85%) ; la participation du secteur non bancaire reste en revanche en-dessous des attentes.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Le Bureau de communication a transmis près des deux tiers des communications aux autorités de poursuite pénale, principalement des places financières de Genève et de Zurich. Le motif le plus fréquent de toutes ces communications avait trait à la criminalité économique. Alors que, pour les cocontractants, les sociétés offshore (Iles Vierges Britanniques, Iles Caïman, Ile de Man, Bahamas, etc) prédominent, les ayants droit économiques sont surtout des ressortissants russes. De nombreuses communications ont été faites en relation avec les enquêtes sur la "Bank of New York" et l'affaire Abacha, qui a fait l'objet d'une demande d'entraide judiciaire de la part du Nigéria.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; &lt;strong&gt;Effet dissuasif des procédures pénales&lt;br /&gt; &lt;/strong&gt;63% des 107 communications transmises aux autorités de poursuite pénale par le Bureau de communication durant sa première année d'existence ont conduit à l'ouverture de procédures pénales. Celles-ci suivent leur cours. Ce pourcentage est hautement satisfaisant et soutient largement la comparaison au plan international. La plupart des procédures doivent être menées par voie d'entraide judiciaire en collaboration avec les autorités judiciaires étrangères, ce qui nécessite beaucoup de temps. C'est la raison pour laquelle il n'y a pas encore eu de jugement définitif ni de décision de confiscation. Mais l'ouverture d'une procédure pénale a déjà un effet dissuasif et contribue à la bonne réputation de la place financière helvétique.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; La collaboration internationale joue un rôle déterminant en matière de lutte contre le blanchiment d'argent. Le Bureau de communication participe donc activement aux réunions du GAFI (Groupe d'Action Financière sur le Blanchiment d'Argent) du Groupe Egmont des FIU (Financial Intelligence Units – Bureaux de communication en matière de blanchiment d'argent). De plus, une déclaration d'intention a été signée avec le Bureau belge de communication en matière de blanchiment d'argent. D'autres déclarations d'intention devraient être signées prochainement avec les organes similaires de France, Finlande et de la République tchèque.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Service de presse fedpol, T +41 31 323 13 10</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>370 comunicazioni per sospetto riciclaggio di denaro. Un miliardo e mezzo di franchi bloccati - Secondo rapporto d'attività dell'Ufficio di comunicazione in materia di riciclaggio di denaro</title>
      <lead>L'Ufficio di comunicazione in materia di riciclaggio di denaro presso l'Ufficio federale di polizia (UFP) ha registrato nel corso del secondo anno della sua attività un'impennata nel numero delle comunicazioni e nell'entità dei valori patrimoniali interessati. In tutto sono 370 le comunicazioni concernenti operazioni sospette nel settore del riciclaggio di denaro pervenute all'Ufficio di comunicazione (l'anno scorso ve ne sono state 160), mentre i valori patrimoniali indagati hanno superato il miliardo e mezzo di franchi (l'anno scorso la cifra superava i 330 milioni di franchi).</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;L'aumento delle comunicazioni non significa che durante il periodo, oggetto del secondo rapporto d'attività (dal 1° aprile 1999 al 31 marzo 2000), sia stato riciclato in Svizzera più denaro di prima. Da questo aumento, che va valutato in senso positivo, traspare anzi che il riciclatore ormai non può più contare di poter esercitare i propri traffici senza pericolo e nell'anonimato. Le disposizioni legislative sono state prese seriamente da molti attori della piazza finanziaria svizzera ed è infatti proprio dalle banche (85%) che è partito il maggior numero di comunicazioni, mentre l'apporto dei settori non bancari rimane ancora al di sotto delle aspettative.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; L'Ufficio di comunicazione ha trasmesso alle autorità di perseguimento penale circa i due terzi delle comunicazioni. Ginevra e Zurigo sono stati finora i centri finanziari principalmente coinvolti. Le comunicazioni sono state motivate soprattutto da operazioni del settore della criminalità economica. Nel caso di contraenti risalta la posizione occupata dalle società offshore (British Virgin Islands, Cayman Islands, Isle of Man, Bahamas), mentre nel caso degli aventi economicamente diritto è interessante notare il ragguardevole numero di persone di nazionalità russa. Le numerose comunicazioni hanno fatto scattare i procedimenti relativi alla Bank of New York e la domanda di assistenza giudiziaria nigeriana nel caso Abacha.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; &lt;strong&gt;Effetto inibitorio del procedimento penale&lt;br /&gt; &lt;/strong&gt;Il 63% delle 107 comunicazioni trasmesse in totale dall'Ufficio di comunicazione alle autorità di perseguimento penale durante il primo anno di attività, ha provocato l'apertura di procedimenti penali ancor oggi pendenti. Questa quota, anche in paragone a quelle estere, è soddisfacentemente alta. Se non ci sono state ancora sentenze passate in giudicato o provvedimenti di sequestro, dipende dal dispendio di tempo che comporta, nella maggior parte dei procedimenti, la cooperazione con le autorità di giustizia straniere nel quadro dell'assistenza giudiziaria. Tuttavia la stessa apertura di un procedimento penale ha l'effetto di scoraggiare il crimine e di contribuire alla buona nomea della piazza finanziaria svizzera.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; La cooperazione internazionale svolge un ruolo decisivo nella lotta contro il riciclaggio di denaro. Per tale motivo l'Ufficio di comunicazione in materia di riciclaggio di denaro collabora nelle commissioni del FATF (Financial Action Task Force on Money Laundering) e del Egmont Gruppe del FIU (Unione mondiale degli Uffici di comunicazione in materia di riciclaggio di denaro Financial Intelligence Units). L'anno scorso tra l'altro è stata sottoscritta, assieme all'Ufficio di comunicazione belga, una dichiarazione d'intenti per regolare la cooperazione, mentre altre dichiarazioni d'intenti verranno presto firmate con gli Uffici di comunicazione di Francia, Finlandia e Repubblica Ceca.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Servizio stampa fedpol, T +41 31 323 13 10</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>370 reports of suspected money laundering – assets totalling 1.5 billion Swiss francs blocked - Money Laundering Reporting Office’s second report of activities</title>
      <lead>In its second year of operation, the Money Laundering Reporting Office in the Federal Office of Police (FOP) has recorded a massive increase in the number of reports received and the volume of assets involved: the Reporting Office received a total of 370 reports of suspected money laundering transactions (compared to 160 the previous year) involving assets of over 1.5 billion Swiss francs (up from just over 330 million francs).</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;This increase in the number of reports does not mean that there was more money laundering activity in Switzerland during the reference period of the second report of activities (1 April 1999 to 31 March 2000). The increase is in fact a positive development and shows that money launderers are no longer able to carry on their activity without risk of detection. The statutory provisions have been taken very seriously by many players in the Swiss financial industry. The great majority of the reports were filed by banks (85%); the response of the non-banking sector is still lagging behind expectations.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Approximately two thirds of the reports received by the Money Laundering Reporting Office were passed on to the prosecution authorities. The bulk of these related to the major financial centres of Geneva and Zurich. Economic crime was the most common backdrop to cases reported. The most frequent customers involved in reported cases were offshore companies (based in the British Virgin Islands, Cayman Islands, Isle of Man or Bahamas), while among the beneficial owners the high proportion of Russian nationals is striking. A large number of reports were triggered by the events surrounding the Bank of New York case and by the Nigerian request for judicial assistance in the Abacha case.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; &lt;strong&gt;Deterrent effect of criminal prosecutions&lt;br /&gt; &lt;/strong&gt;63% of the total of 107 reports which the Reporting Office passed on to the prosecution authorities in its first year of operation resulted in the bringing of criminal proceedings, all of which are still pending. This represents a gratifyingly high proportion – by Swiss or by international standards. Most criminal prosecutions of this type entail the use of procedures for judicial cooperation with foreign judicial authorities. This is a very time-consuming process. As a result no final convictions or asset seizures have yet been secured. But even the institution of criminal proceedings has a deterrent effect in itself, which helps to enhance Switzerland’s reputation as a financial centre.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; International cooperation plays a crucial role in the fight against money laundering. The Money Laundering Reporting Office therefore participates in the working groups of the FATF (Financial Action Task Force on Money Laundering) and in the Egmont Group of FIUs (this is the international association of money laundering reporting agencies or Financial Intelligence Units) . Last year it also signed a declaration of intent with the Belgian Reporting Office to regulate cooperation between them. In the near future similar declarations of intent are to be signed with the French, Finnish and Czech Reporting Offices.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Press service fedpol, T +41 31 323 13 10</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="35">
        <name lang="de">Finanzplatz</name>
        <name lang="fr">Place financière</name>
        <name lang="it">Piazza finanziaria</name>
        <name lang="en">Financial Centre</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
