<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="2314" revoked="no">
    <version>4</version>
    <pubdate>2000-03-22</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="815" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>801</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössische Kommunikationskommission ComCom</name>
      <name lang="fr">Commission fédérale de la communication ComCom</name>
      <name lang="it">Commissione federale delle comunicazioni ComCom</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Communications Commission ComCom</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.comcom.admin.ch/</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.comcom.admin.ch/</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.comcom.admin.ch/</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.comcom.admin.ch/</www>
      <email lang="de">comcom@comcom.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">comcom@comcom.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">comcom@comcom.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">comcom@comcom.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="801">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Umwelt, Verkehr, Energie und Kommunikation</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'environnement, des transports, de l'énergie et de la communication</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'ambiente, dei trasporti, dell'energia e delle comunicazioni</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of the Environment, Transport, Energy and Communications</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.uvek.admin.ch/uvek/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.uvek.admin.ch/uvek/fr/home.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.uvek.admin.ch/uvek/it/home.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.uvek.admin.ch/uvek/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-uvek.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-uvek.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-uvek.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-uvek.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Neuer Nummerierungsplan für den 29. März 2002: Die ComCom ändert den Nummerierungsplan, hält aber am Umstellungstermin fest</title>
      <teaser>Die Eidg. Kommunikationskommission (ComCom) genehmigt einen neuen Nummerierungsplan.</teaser>
      <lead>Die Eidg. Kommunikationskommission (ComCom) genehmigt einen neuen Nummerierungsplan.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Dieser ist einfacher und verursacht weniger Kosten als der im Dezember 1997 gutgeheissene Plan. Der Termin der Umstellung auf die neuen Telefonnummern - der 29. März 2002 - hingegen wird nicht geändert.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Hauptmerkmal des von der ComCom genehmigten neuen Plans ist seine Einfachheit: Bei den meisten Nummern wird einzig die Vorwahl (022, 031 usw.) hinzugefügt. Diese ist somit auch im Lokalbereich zu wählen. Bei den meisten Anschlüssen ist es jedoch bereits heute möglich, die Vorwahl im Nahbereich einzustellen. Für Anrufe in andere Netzgruppen der Schweiz oder aus dem Ausland ändert sich gegenüber heute nichts. Dank dieser Lösung wird die Zuweisung von neuen Vorwahlnummern für 9 Regionen hinfällig, die im von der Kommission im Dezember 1997 genehmigten Plan vorgesehen war. Da für die Teilnehmerinnen und Teilnehmer, aber auch für die Betreiberinnen im Vergleich zum ursprünglichen Plan viel weniger Änderungen nötig sind, fallen auch die Realisierungskosten für die Volkswirtschaft bedeutend geringer aus.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Die ComCom ist allerdings der Ansicht, dass es aufgrund der möglichen zukünftigen Entwicklung der Nummerierungssysteme nicht wünschenswert ist, in der Region Zürich (9 Ziffern) langfristig eine andere Nummernlänge als in der übrigen Schweiz (10 Ziffern) beizubehalten. Aus diesem Grund hat sie beschlossen, dass die 01-Nummern innerhalb von maximal 5 Jahren ab dem 29. März 2002 auf das in den anderen Landesteilen verwendete Nummernformat zu migrieren sind (z.B. von 01 auf 044). Das für die Umsetzung des neuen Plans zuständige Bundesamt für Kommunikation (BAKOM) wurde von der Kommission beauftragt, zusammen mit den Betreiberinnen die Modalitäten für die Realisierung dieser zweiten Etappe festzulegen.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Der Entscheid der ComCom wurde einerseits durch die einfache Umsetzung und andererseits durch die geringeren Kosten motiviert. Mit dem neuen geschlossenen Nummerierungsplan kann das oberste Ziel eines Nummerierungsplans - die Gewährleistung einer ausreichenden Zahl von Adressierungselementen (Nummern) - erreicht werden. Dieser geschlossene Nummerierungsplan (gleiches Wählformat für lokale und nationale Anrufe) erlaubt eine grosse Flexibilität bei der Zuweisung von Nummernblöcken und bildet die Grundlage für die Einführung der geografischen Nummernportabilität. Das einerseits durch die Liberalisierung und andererseits durch die Entwicklung der Technologien (z.B. Internet-Telefonie) bedingte Wachstum im Telekommunikationsmarkt erhöht die Nachfrage nach Nummern.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Zur Erinnerung: Im Dezember 1997 hatte die ComCom einen Nummerierungsplan genehmigt, der am 12. April 2001 eingeführt werden sollte. Dieser Plan sah die Vereinheitlichung der Nummernlänge auf 9 Ziffern für die gesamte Schweiz vor. Dabei wären die Vorwahl-Nummern in 9 Regionen, darunter auch die Netzgruppe Zürich, geändert worden. Seine klare Struktur hätte auch erlaubt, die verschiedenen Dienste anhand der führenden Ziffer zu erkennen (z.B. 7 für Mobiltelefone, 8 für Gratisnummern und 9 für Dienstenummern). Im September 1999 beschloss die Kommission - aufgrund der Klagen aus verschiedenen Wirtschaftskreisen, welche mit der knappen Vorbereitungszeit und den bevorstehenden Arbeiten für den Milleniums-Wechsel argumentierten - die Einführung des neuen Nummerierungsplans um ein Jahr zu verschieben.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Die ComCom weist darauf hin, dass trotz der Proteste aus verschiedenen Kreisen und der bereits im Dezember 1997 erfolgten Bekanntgabe des neuen Plans bis im November 1999 von keiner Seite Alternativlösungen für die Nummerierung vorgeschlagen worden waren.Im Spätherbst 1999 stellte die Swisscom ein Projekt eines neuen Nummerierungsplans vor, das den interessierten Kreisen anfangs 2000 zusammen mit anderen Lösungen zur Konsultation unterbreitet wurde. Die heutige Entscheidung der ComCom stützt sich zu einem grossen Teil auf diesen Vorschlag der Swisscom, der bei der Konsultation auf ein positives Echo gestossen war. Der genehmigte Plan unterscheidet sich gegenüber diesem Vorschlag hauptsächlich darin, dass er in einem zweiten Schritt die Vereinheitlichung der Nummernlänge für die gesamte Schweiz vorsieht.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact/>
      <revisions>
        <revision date="2006-01-24 17:26" type="R"/>
      </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Nouveau plan de numérotation au 29 mars 2002: La ComCom modifie le plan et maintient sa date d'introduction</title>
      <teaser>La Commission fédérale de la communication (ComCom) approuve un nouveau plan de numérotation qui se distingue principalement de celui qu'elle avait adopté en décembre 1997 par sa plus grande simplicité et par ses coûts moindres. Elle maintient cependant la date d'introduction de la nouvelle numérotation au 29 mars 2002.</teaser>
      <lead>La Commission fédérale de la communication (ComCom) approuve un nouveau plan de numérotation qui se distingue principalement de celui qu'elle avait adopté en décembre 1997 par sa plus grande simplicité et par ses coûts moindres. Elle maintient cependant la date d'introduction de la nouvelle numérotation au 29 mars 2002.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Le nouveau plan de numérotation qui vient d'être approuvé par la ComCom se caractérise par sa simplicité: la grande majorité des raccordements garderont leur numéro actuel, à la différence près que le préfixe interurbain (022, 031, etc.) sera intégré au numéro actuel et devra être composé également dans le domaine local. Il faut relever ici que cette opération de sélectionner l'indicatif interurbain dans le domaine local est déjà possible actuellement pour la plupart des raccordements. Pour les appels d'une autre région de Suisse ou de l'étranger, rien ne sera modifié par rapport au système actuel. Cette solution évite de devoir attribuer de nouveaux indicatifs à neuf régions ainsi que le prévoyait le plan initialement adopté par la commission en décembre 1997. Comme les changements pour les abonnés et les opérateurs sont beaucoup moins importants qu'avec le plan original, cela a pour conséquence une réduction massive des coûts d'implémentation pour l'économie en général.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Toutefois, la ComCom juge que le maintien à long terme d'une longueur de numéros différente pour la région de Zurich (9 chiffres) et pour le reste de la Suisse (10 chiffres), n'est pas souhaitable en vue de l'évolution possible des systèmes de numérotation. Pour cette raison, elle a décidé que les numéros 01 devront migrer vers un format identique à celui du reste du pays (p. ex de 01 à 044) dans un laps de temps de 5 ans maximum à partir du 29 mars 2002. L'Office fédéral de la communication (OFCOM), qui est chargé de l'application du nouveau plan, a été mandaté par la commission, pour définir, en collaboration avec les opérateurs, les modalités de réalisation de la deuxième étape.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Ces deux motifs - simplicité d'application et coûts d'implémentation réduits - expliquent la décision de la commission. Le but premier d'un nouveau plan de numérotation, à savoir garantir un nombre suffisant de ressources d'adressage (numéros), est assuré avec le nouveau plan de numérotation fermé; la fermeture du plan de numérotation (même format de sélection pour les appels locaux et nationaux) garantit une grande flexibilité dans l'attribution des blocs de numéros et offre la base pour l'introduction de la portabilité géographique des numéros. La croissance du marché des télécommunications, induite par la libéralisation, d'une part, et l'évolution des technologies dans ce secteur (p. ex. téléphonie par internet), d'autre part, engendre une demande accrue de numéros.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Pour rappel, la commission avait approuvé un plan de numérotation en décembre 1997, dont l'introduction était fixée au 12 avril 2001. Ce plan unifiait la longueur des numéros à 9 chiffres pour toute la Suisse et obligeait 9 régions à changer d'indicatif interurbain, dont la région de Zurich. Sa structure claire permettait en outre l'identification des services au moyen du premier chiffre (p. ex. 7 pour le réseau mobile, 8 pour les numéros gratuits et 9 pour les numéros de services). En septembre 1999, la commission, suite aux cris d'alarme de certains milieux de l'économie devant leur manque de préparation au changement et à la proximité des travaux consécutifs au passage à l'an 2000, avait décidé de reporter l'introduction du plan de numérotation d'un an.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;La commission relève que, jusqu'en novembre 1999, en dépit de protestations provenant de différents milieux et alors que le nouveau plan était connu depuis décembre 1997, aucune proposition alternative de numérotation n'a été avancée.Au cours de la fin de l'automne 1999, Swisscom a présenté un projet de nouveau plan de numérotation qui a été soumis, avec d'autres variantes, à consultation des milieux intéressés au début de cette année. La décision de ce jour de la ComCom se base pour une grande part sur cette proposition de Swisscom, qui a rencontré un écho favorable lors de la consultation. La différence principale avec cette proposition réside dans la deuxième étape qui verra l'homogénéisation des longueurs de numéros pour l'ensemble de la Suisse.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact/>
      <revisions>
        <revision date="2006-01-24 17:26" type="R"/>
      </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Nuovo piano di numerazione per il 29 marzo 2002: La ComCom modifica il piano ma mantiene la data per la sua introduzione</title>
      <teaser>La Commissione federale delle comunicazioni (ComCom) approva un nuovo piano di numerazione. A differenza di quello che aveva adottato nel dicembre 1997, il nuovo piano è caratterizzato da una maggiore semplicità e da costi ridotti. È invece rimasta invariata la data per l'introduzione della nuova numerazione che avverrà il 29 marzo 2002.</teaser>
      <lead>La Commissione federale delle comunicazioni (ComCom) approva un nuovo piano di numerazione. A differenza di quello che aveva adottato nel dicembre 1997, il nuovo piano è caratterizzato da una maggiore semplicità e da costi ridotti. È invece rimasta invariata la data per l'introduzione della nuova numerazione che avverrà il 29 marzo 2002.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Il nuovo piano di numerazione recentemente approvato dalla ComCom si distingue per la sua semplicità: la maggior parte dei collegamenti manterranno il loro attuale numero, con l'unica differenza che il prefisso interurbano (022, 031, ecc.) sarà integrato nel numero attuale e dovrà essere composto anche per i collegamenti locali. Occorre notare che per la maggior parte dei collegamenti è già ora possibile selezionare il prefisso interurbano nella zona locale. Nulla cambierà invece rispetto all'attuale sistema per quanto riguarda le chiamate provenienti da un'altra regione della Svizzera o dall'estero. Questa soluzione permette di evitare l'attribuzione di nuovi prefissi a nove regioni, così come previsto dal piano inizialmente adottato dalla commissione nel dicembre 1997. Poiché i cambiamenti per gli abbonati e gli operatori risultano meno importanti rispetto a quelli necessari per la realizzazione del piano originale, si riducono in modo massiccio i costi di realizzazione per l'intera economia.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Tuttavia, in vista dei possibili sviluppi dei sistemi di numerazione, la ComCom ritiene che non sia auspicabile mantenere a lungo termine una lunghezza dei numeri diversa tra la regione di Zurigo (9 cifre) e il resto della Svizzera (10 cifre). Per questo motivo, ha deciso che, al massimo entro 5 anni a partire dal 29 marzo 2002, i numeri con prefisso 01 dovranno essere uniformati al resto del Paese (ad es. sostituendo lo 01 con 044). La commissione ha affidato all'Ufficio federale delle comunicazioni (UFCOM), autorità incaricata dell'applicazione del nuovo piano, il compito di definire, in collaborazione con gli operatori, le modalità di realizzazione della seconda tappa.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;La decisione della commissione poggia sulla semplicità d'applicazione e sui costi di realizzazione ridotti. Con il nuovo piano di numerazione chiuso viene raggiunto lo scopo principale della realizzazione di un nuovo piano, ossia garantire un numero sufficiente di elementi d'indirizzo (numeri); la chiusura del piano di numerazione (stesso formato di selezione per le chiamate locali e nazionali) garantisce una grande flessibilità nell'attribuzione di serie di numeri e offre le basi per l'introduzione della portabilità geografica dei numeri. La crescita del mercato delle telecomunicazioni, indotta dalla liberalizzazione e dallo sviluppo delle tecnologie del settore (ad es. telefonia via Internet), provoca una domanda maggiore di numeri.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Ricordiamo che, nel dicembre 1997, la commissione aveva approvato un piano di numerazione la cui introduzione era prevista per il 12 aprile 2001. Questo piano uniformava la lunghezza dei numeri a 9 cifre per tutta la Svizzera e obbligava 9 regioni a cambiare il prefisso interurbano, tra cui la regione di Zurigo. La sua struttura chiara permetteva inoltre d'identificare i servizi mediante la prima cifra (ad es. 7 per la rete mobile, 8 per i numeri gratuiti e 9 per i numeri di servizio). Nel settembre 1999, a seguito di gridi d'allarme lanciati da alcuni settori dell'economia a motivo della loro mancanza di preparazione al cambiamento e alla vicinanza dei lavori necessari per il passaggio al 2000, la ComCom aveva deciso di posticipare di un anno l'introduzione del piano di numerazione.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;La Commissione rileva che, fino al novembre 1999, nonostante le proteste provenienti da più parti e malgrado che il nuovo piano fosse conosciuto fin dal dicembre 1997, non è stata avanzata alcuna proposta alternativa di numerazione.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;A fine autunno 1999, la Swisscom ha presentato un progetto per un nuovo piano di numerazione che, con altre varianti, è stato inviato in consultazione alle cerchie interessate all'inizio di quest'anno. La soluzione adottata dalla ComCom si basa in gran parte sulla proposta della Swisscom, che durante la consultazione ha raccolto i favori degli interessati. La principale differenza con questa proposta risiede nella seconda tappa, durante la quale verrà omogeneizzata la lunghezza dei numeri per l'insieme del Paese.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact/>
      <revisions>
        <revision date="2006-01-24 17:26" type="R"/>
      </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>New numbering plan for 29 March 2002: ComCom amends the plan and maintains the date for its introduction</title>
      <teaser>The Federal Communications Commission (ComCom) has approved a new numbering plan which differs in the main from the one it had adopted in December 1997 by its greater simplicity and lower costs. However, it is maintaining the date for introduction of the new numbers, 29 March 2002.</teaser>
      <lead>The Federal Communications Commission (ComCom) has approved a new numbering plan which differs in the main from the one it had adopted in December 1997 by its greater simplicity and lower costs. However, it is maintaining the date for introduction of the new numbers, 29 March 2002.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;The new numbering plan which has just been approved by ComCom is characterised by its simplicity: the great majority of lines will keep their current number, the only difference being that the dialling code (022, 031, etc.) will be integrated into the current number and will have to be dialled even within the local area. It should be noted here that this operation of dialling the trunk dialling code within the local area is currently already possible for most connections. For calls from another region of Switzerland or from abroad, nothing in the current system will be changed. This solution avoids having to allocate new codes to nine regions as was envisaged by the plan initially adopted by the Commission in December 1997. Since the changes for subscribers and operators are much less drastic than with the original plan, the result is a massive reduction in the implementation costs for the economy in general.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;However, ComCom considers that long-term retention of a different length for numbers for the Zurich region (9 digits) and for the rest of Switzerland (10 digits) is not desirable in view of the possible evolution of the numbering systems. For this reason, it has decided that 01 numbers will have to migrate to a format identical to the rest of the country (e.g. from 01 to 044) within a maximum of 5 years from 29 March 2002. The Federal Office of Communications (OFCOM), which is responsible for the application of the new plan, has been mandated by the Commission to define the terms of implementation of the second stage with the operators.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;These two factors - simplicity of application and lower implementation costs - explain the Commission’s decision. The primary aim of the new numbering plan, i.e. to guarantee a sufficient number of addressing resources (numbers) is achieved with the new closed numbering plan; the closure of the numbering plan (same dialling format for local and national calls) guarantees a high degree of flexibility in the allocation of blocks of numbers and provides a basis for the introduction of geographical number portability. The growth in the telecoms market, as a result of both liberalisation and the development of technology (e.g. Internet telephony), is generating greater demand for numbers.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;As background information, the Commission had approved a numbering plan in December 1997, and its introduction was fixed for 12 April 2001. This plan unified the length of numbers at 9 digits for all of Switzerland and obliged 9 regions, including the Zurich region, to change their trunk code. Its clear structure also permitted service identification by means of the first digit (e.g. 7 for the mobile network, 8 for freephone numbers and 9 for services numbers). In September 1999, the Commission, in response to the alarm expressed by certain sectors of the economy due to the short preparation time for the change and its proximity to work related to the Y2K changeover, had decided to postpone the introduction of the numbering plan for one year.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The Commission notes that up to November 1999, despite protests from various sides and despite the fact that the new plan had been known about since December 1997, no alternative numbering proposal had been put forward.In late autumn 1999, Swisscom submitted a new numbering plan which was put out for consultation, along with other variants, to the interested parties at the beginning of this year. ComCom’s decision today is largely based on this proposal from Swisscom, which was favourably received in the course of the consultation. The main difference with this proposal lies in the second stage in which number lengths will be homogenized for Switzerland as a whole.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact/>
      <revisions>
        <revision date="2006-01-24 17:26" type="R"/>
      </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="28">
        <name lang="de">Telekommunikation</name>
        <name lang="fr">Télécommunications</name>
        <name lang="it">Telecomunicazione</name>
        <name lang="en">Telecommunications</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
