<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="88271" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2022-04-28</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="201" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>201</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="201">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Delegation des Kongresses der Gemeinden und Regionen des Europarates zu Besuch in Glarus, Bern und Freiburg</title>
      <lead>Vom 30. April bis 3. Mai 2022 weilt eine Delegation des Kongresses der Gemeinden und Regionen des Europarates in der Schweiz. Ziel des Besuchs von Kongresspräsident Leendert Verbeek ist es, der Strassburger Institution den Schweizer Föderalismus «im Feld» vorzustellen. David Eray, Regierungspräsident des Kantons Jura und Leiter der Schweizer Delegation im Kongress sowie verschiedene Vertreterinnen und Vertreter des EDA werden die Delegation begleiten. Neben der Teilnahme an der Landsgemeinde im Glarus stehen Treffen mit der Staatssekretärin Livia Leu, dem Berner Stadtpräsidenten Alec von Graffenried sowie der Konferenz der Kantonsregierungen (KdK), Städte- und Gemeindeverband auf dem Programm. </lead>
      <text link="no">Der Besuch von Präsident Leendert Verbeek (Niederlande) dient dazu, dem Kongress verschiedene Aspekte der Schweizer Demokratie auf lokaler und regionaler Ebene vor Ort aufzuzeigen. Der Kongress hatte den Schweizer Föderalismus in seinem letzten Bericht von 2017 als «besonders positiv» bezeichnet. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;b&gt;Der jurassische Regierungspräsident als Teil der Delegation&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Der Besuch wird vom Eidgenössischen Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten (EDA) in enger Absprache mit dem Kanton Jura organisiert, dessen Regierungspräsident David Eray auch Leiter der Schweizer Delegation im Kongress ist. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Am 1. Mai weilt die Delegation in Glarus. Mit der Teilnahme an der dortigen Landsgemeinde lernt sie damit ein gutes Beispiel der direkten Demokratie in der Schweiz kennen. Am nächsten Tag trifft der Kongress Staatssekretärin des EDA Livia Leu. Sie werden dabei auf die Konsequenzen des kürzlich erfolgten Ausschlusses Russlands aus dem Europarat eingehen, der auch die Mitgliedschaft im Kongress betrifft. Weitere Treffen finden mit dem Berner Stadtpräsidenten Alec von Graffenried und Vertreterinnen und Vertreter der Konferenz der Kantonsregierungen, des Städte- und des Gemeindeverbands statt. Die Delegation wird in Bern auch das Museum für Kommunikation besichtigen, welches 2019 mit dem Museumspreis des Europarats ausgezeichnet wurde. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Am 3. Mai besucht die Delegation das Institut für Föderalismus in Freiburg und lässt sich dort über laufende Forschungsarbeiten sowie das Gemeindefusionsprojekt Grossfreiburg informieren.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;b&gt;Der Kongress fördert den Austausch demokratischer Erfahrungen auf lokaler und regionaler Ebene&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Der Kongress der Gemeinden und Regionen ist ein 1994 gegründetes, beratendes Organ des Europarates. Als Sprachrohr der Städte, Gemeinden und Regionen ist er für die Förderung der lokalen und regionalen Demokratie in den 46 Mitgliedstaaten zuständig. Er wacht über die Einhaltung der Europäischen Charta der kommunalen Selbstverwaltung, beobachtet Lokal- und Regionalwahlen und führt verschiedene thematische Aktivitäten durch, darunter ein umfangreiches Jugendprogramm.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Zwölf Regierungsrätinnen und Regierungsräte, Vertreterinnen und Vertreter von Gemeinden und Städten sowie ein Jugenddelegierter vertreten die Schweiz im Kongress. Bundespräsident Ignazio Cassis, Vorsteher des EDA, hatte die Delegation im Januar 2021 ernannt. Das EDA führt auch das Delegationssekretariat. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Die Schweiz ist seit 1963 Mitglied des Europarats. Sie hat die Charta der kommunalen Selbstverwaltung am 17. Februar 2005 ratifiziert. &lt;br /&gt;</text>
      <contact>Kommunikation EDA Bundeshaus West CH-3003 Bern Tel. Kommunikationsservice: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Medienstelle: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <attachment id="230374">
        <title>Factsheet: Kongress der Gemeinden und Regionen des Europarats</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>226</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/71281.pdf</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </attachment>
      <link id="230376">
        <title>Newsartikel EDA, 12.02.2021</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home/das-eda/aktuell/newsuebersicht/2021/02/kongress-europarat.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="230377">
        <title>Kongress der Gemeinden und Regionen des Europarats (fr)</title>
        <uri>https://www.coe.int/fr/web/congress/home</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="230378">
        <title>Schweizer Delegation, Kongress der Gemeinden und Regionen, Europarat (fr)</title>
        <uri>https://www.coe.int/fr/web/congress/country?id=11</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="230379">
        <title>Schweiz – Monitoringbericht vom 20. Oktober 2017 (fr)</title>
        <uri>https://www.congress-monitoring.eu/fr/17-pays.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="230380">
        <title>Europarat</title>
        <uri>https://www.coe.int/de/web/portal/home</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="230381">
        <title>Europarat, EDA</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home/aussenpolitik/internationale-organisationen/europarat.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Une délégation du Congrès des pouvoirs locaux et régionaux du Conseil de l’Europe en visite à Glaris, à Berne et à Fribourg</title>
      <lead>Du 30 avril au 3 mai 2022, une délégation du Congrès des pouvoirs locaux et régionaux (CPLRE) du Conseil de l’Europe sera présente en Suisse. Le but de la visite du président du Congrès Leendert Verbeek est de présenter à l'institution strasbourgeoise le fédéralisme suisse «sur le terrain». David Eray, président du gouvernement du canton du Jura, qui dirige la délégation suisse au Congrès, ainsi que plusieurs représentants et représentantes du DFAE accompagneront la délégation du CPLRE. Le programme prévoit, outre la participation à la Landsgemeinde de Glaris, des rencontres avec la secrétaire d’État Livia Leu, le président de la Ville de Berne Alec von Graffenried et des représentants et représentantes de la Conférence des gouvernements cantonaux, de l’Union des villes suisses et de l’Association des communes suisses. </lead>
      <text link="no">La visite du président Leendert Verbeek (Pays-Bas) permet de présenter sur place au Congrès divers aspects de la démocratie suisse aux niveaux local et régional. Dans son dernier rapport publié en 2017, le Congrès avait qualifié le fédéralisme suisse de «particulièrement positif». &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;b&gt;Le président du gouvernement jurassien fait partie de la délégation&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Cette visite est organisée par le Département fédéral des affaires étrangères (DFAE) en étroite concertation avec le canton du Jura, dont le président du gouvernement David Eray dirige la délégation suisse au Congrès. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;La délégation du CPLRE sera présente à Glaris le 1er mai. La participation à la Landsgemeinde lui offrira une bonne illustration de la démocratie directe en Suisse. Le lendemain, le Congrès rencontrera la secrétaire d’État du DFAE Livia Leu. Ils évoqueront les conséquences de l’exclusion récente de la Russie du Conseil de l’Europe, qui affecte également la composition du Congrès. D’autres rencontres sont prévues avec le président de la Ville de Berne Alec von Graffenried et des représentants et représentantes de la Conférence des gouvernements cantonaux, de l’Union des villes suisses et de l’Association des communes suisses. La délégation visitera à Berne le Musée de la communication, qui a remporté le Prix du Musée 2019 du Conseil de l’Europe. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Le 3 mai, la délégation se rendra à l’Institut du Fédéralisme à Fribourg, où elle se renseignera sur les travaux de recherche qui y sont menés et sur le projet de fusion du Grand Fribourg.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;b&gt;Le Congrès favorise les échanges d’expériences démocratiques aux niveaux local et régional&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Le Congrès des pouvoirs locaux et régionaux, organe consultatif du Conseil de l’Europe, a été fondé en 1994. Porte-parole des villes, des communes et des régions, il est chargé de renforcer la démocratie locale et régionale dans les 46 États membres du Conseil de l’Europe. Il veille au respect de la Charte européenne de l’autonomie locale, observe des élections locales et régionales et mène diverses activités thématiques, dont un vaste programme pour la jeunesse.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Six conseillères et conseillers d’État, six représentants et représentantes de communes et de villes ainsi qu’un jeune délégué représentent la Suisse au sein du Congrès. Le président de la Confédération Ignazio Cassis, chef du DFAE, avait nommé la délégation en janvier 2021. Le DFAE assure le secrétariat de la délégation. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;La Suisse est membre du Conseil de l’Europe depuis 1963. Elle a ratifié la Charte européenne de l’autonomie locale le 17 février 2005. &lt;br /&gt;</text>
      <contact>Communication DFAE Palais fédéral ouest CH-3003 Berne Tél. Service de communication: +41 58 462 31 53 Tél. Service de presse: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <attachment id="230373">
        <title>Fiche d'information: Congrès des pouvoirs locaux et régionaux du Conseil de l’Europe</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>292</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/71280.pdf</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </attachment>
      <link id="230382">
        <title>Conseil de l’Europe, DFAE</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae/politique-exterieure/organisations-internationales/conseil-europe.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="230390">
        <title>Article du DFAE, 12.02.2021</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae/dfae/aktuell/newsuebersicht/2021/02/kongress-europarat.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="230391">
        <title>Congrès des pouvoirs locaux et régionaux, Conseil de l’Europe</title>
        <uri>https://www.coe.int/fr/web/congress/home</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="230392">
        <title>Délégation suisse, Congrès des pouvoirs locaux et régionaux, Conseil de l’Europe</title>
        <uri>https://www.coe.int/fr/web/congress/country?id=11</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="230393">
        <title>Suisse – Rapport de monitoring du 20 octobre 2017.</title>
        <uri>https://www.congress-monitoring.eu/fr/17-pays.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="230394">
        <title>Conseil de l’Europe</title>
        <uri>https://www.coe.int/fr/web/portal/home</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Una delegazione del Congresso dei poteri locali e regionali del Consiglio d’Europa visita Glarona, Berna e Friburgo</title>
      <lead>Dal 30 aprile al 3 maggio 2022 sarà in Svizzera una delegazione del Congresso dei poteri locali e regionali del Consiglio d’Europa. Obiettivo della visita del presidente del Congresso, Leendert Verbeek, è presentare il federalismo svizzero «sul campo» all’istituzione di Strasburgo. David Eray, presidente del Governo del Cantone del Giura e capo della delegazione svizzera al Congresso, nonché diversi rappresentanti del DFAE accompagneranno la delegazione. Oltre alla partecipazione alla Landsgemeinde di Glarona, il programma prevede incontri con la segretaria di Stato Livia Leu, il sindaco di Berna, Alec von Graffenried, la Conferenza dei Governi cantonali e l’Associazione delle città e dei Comuni. </lead>
      <text link="no">La visita del presidente Leendert Verbeek (Paesi Bassi) servirà a mostrare al Congresso vari aspetti della democrazia svizzera a livello locale e regionale. Nel suo ultimo rapporto del 2017 il Congresso ha descritto il federalismo svizzero come «particolarmente positivo». &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;b&gt;Il presidente del Governo del Giura membro della delegazione&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;La visita è organizzata dal Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri (DFAE) in stretta collaborazione con il Cantone del Giura, il cui presidente del Governo, David Eray, è anche capo della delegazione svizzera al Congresso dei poteri locali e regionali del Consiglio d’Europa. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;La delegazione sarà a Glarona il 1° maggio. Partecipando alla Landsgemeinde potrà scoprire un buon esempio di democrazia diretta in Svizzera. Il giorno dopo incontrerà Livia Leu, segretaria di Stato del DFAE, con cui discuterà delle conseguenze della recente esclusione della Russia dal Consiglio, che si ripercuote anche sulla sua appartenenza al Congresso. Altri incontri si terranno con il sindaco di Berna, Alec von Graffenried, e con rappresentanti della Conferenza dei Governi cantonali e dell’Associazione delle città e dei Comuni. La delegazione visiterà inoltre il Museo della comunicazione di Berna, che nel 2019 è stato insignito del Premio per i musei del Consiglio d’Europa. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Il 3 maggio la delegazione si recherà all’Istituto del federalismo, che ha sede a Friburgo, dove avrà modo di conoscere le ricerche in corso e il progetto di fusione comunale Grande Friburgo.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;b&gt;Il Congresso promuove lo scambio di esperienze democratiche a livello locale e regionale&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Il Congresso dei poteri locali e regionali è un organo consultivo del Consiglio d’Europa istituito nel 1994. Come portavoce di città, comuni e regioni, è responsabile della promozione della democrazia a livello locale e regionale nei 46 Stati membri. Verifica il rispetto della Carta europea dell’autonomia locale, segue come osservatore le elezioni locali e regionali e svolge molte attività su vari temi, compreso un ampio programma rivolto ai giovani.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Dodici consigliere e consiglieri cantonali, rappresentanti di comuni e città e un delegato dei giovani rappresentano la Svizzera al Congresso. Il presidente della Confederazione Ignazio Cassis, capo del DFAE, ha nominato la delegazione nel gennaio del 2021. Il DFAE gestisce il suo segretariato. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;La Svizzera è membro del Consiglio d’Europa dal 1963. Ha ratificato la Carta europea dell’autonomia locale il 17 febbraio 2005. &lt;br /&gt;</text>
      <contact>Comunicazione DFAE Palazzo federale ovest CH-3003 Berna Tel. Servizio di comunicazione: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Servizio stampa: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <attachment id="230372">
        <title>Scheda informativa : Congresso dei poteri locali e regionali del Consiglio d’Europa</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>231</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/71279.pdf</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </attachment>
      <link id="230383">
        <title>Consiglio d’Europa, DFAE</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae/politica-estera/organizzazioni-internazionali/consiglio-europa.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="230395">
        <title>News DFAE, 12.2.2021</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae/dfae/aktuell/newsuebersicht/2021/02/kongress-europarat.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="230396">
        <title>Congresso dei poteri locali e regionali del Consiglio d’Europa (fr, en)</title>
        <uri>https://www.coe.int/fr/web/congress/home</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="230397">
        <title>Delegazione Svizzera, Congresso dei poteri locali e regionali del Consiglio d’Europa (fr, en)</title>
        <uri>https://www.coe.int/fr/web/congress/country?id=11</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="230398">
        <title>Svizzera – rapporto di monitoraggio del 20 ottobre 2017 (fr, en)</title>
        <uri>https://www.congress-monitoring.eu/fr/17-pays.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="230399">
        <title>Consiglio d’Europa</title>
        <uri>https://www.coe.int/it/web/portal/home</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Delegation of the Congress of Local and Regional Authorities of the Council of Europe visits Glarus, Bern and Fribourg</title>
      <lead>A delegation from the Congress of Local and Regional Authorities of the Council of Europe will be in Switzerland from 30 April to 3 May 2022. The aim of the visit by Congress President Leendert Verbeek is to present Swiss federalism in situ to the Strasbourg institution. David Eray, the president of the Cantonal Council of Jura and head of the Swiss delegation to the Congress, along with various representatives of the FDFA, will accompany the delegation. In addition to attending the Landsgemeinde in Glarus, the programme will include meetings with FDFA State Secretary Livia Leu, the mayor of Bern, Alec von Graffenried, the Conference of Cantonal Governments, the Swiss Union of Cities and the Association of Swiss Communes. </lead>
      <text link="no">The visit by Mr Verbeek (Netherlands) will serve to show the Congress various aspects of Swiss democracy on the ground at local and regional level. The Congress described Swiss federalism as "particularly positive" in its last report of 2017. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;b&gt;President of the Cantonal Council of Jura to join the delegation&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The visit is being organised by the FDFA in close consultation with the Canton of Jura, whose president, David Eray, is also head of the Swiss delegation to the Congress. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The delegation will be in Glarus on 1 May, where it will obtain first-hand experience of Swiss direct democracy by participating in the Landsgemeinde. The next day, the delegation will meet Livia Leu, the state secretary of the FDFA. They will discuss the consequences of Russia's recent exclusion from the Council of Europe, which also affects its membership of the Congress. Further meetings will be held with the mayor of Bern, Alec von Graffenried, and representatives of the Conference of Cantonal Governments, the Swiss Union of Cities and the Association of Swiss Communes. The delegation will also visit the Museum of Communication in Bern, which was awarded the 2019 Council of Europe Museum Prize. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;On 3 May, the delegation will visit the Institute of Federalism in Fribourg to learn about ongoing research and the Greater Fribourg communal merger project.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;b&gt;The Congress promotes the exchange of democratic experiences at local and regional level&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The Congress of Local and Regional Authorities is a consultative body of the Council of Europe which was established in 1994. As the voice of cities, municipalities and regions, it is responsible for promoting local and regional democracy in the 46 member states. It monitors compliance with the European Charter of Local Self-Government, observes local and regional elections and carries out various thematic activities, including an extensive youth programme.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Twelve cantonal councillors, representatives of communes and cities, and a youth delegate represent Switzerland at the Congress. President of the Swiss Confederation and head of the FDFA, Ignazio Cassis, appointed the delegation in January 2021. The FDFA also runs the delegation's secretariat. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Switzerland has been a member of the Council of Europe since 1963. It ratified the European Charter of Local Self-Government on 17 February 2005. &lt;br /&gt;</text>
      <contact>FDFA Communication Federal Palace West Wing CH-3003 Bern, Switzerland Tel. Communication service: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Press service: +41 58 460 55 55 E-mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @SwissMFA</contact>
      <attachment id="230375">
        <title>Factsheet: Congress of Local and Regional Authorities of the Council of Europe (de)</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>226</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/71282.pdf</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </attachment>
      <link id="230384">
        <title>Council of Europe, FDFA</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/fdfa/foreign-policy/international-organizations/council-europe.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="230385">
        <title>FDFA news article, 12.02.2021</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/fdfa/fdfa/aktuell/newsuebersicht/2021/02/kongress-europarat.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="230386">
        <title>Congress of Local and Regional Authorities</title>
        <uri>https://www.coe.int/en/web/congress/home</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="230387">
        <title>National delegation to the congress: Switzerland</title>
        <uri>https://www.coe.int/en/web/congress/country?id=11</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="230388">
        <title>Switzerland – Monitoring Report of 20 October 2017</title>
        <uri>https://www.congress-monitoring.eu/en/17-pays.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="230389">
        <title>Council of Europe</title>
        <uri>https://www.coe.int/en/web/portal/home</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
