<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="96680" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2023-07-13</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="323" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>701</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidg. Materialprüfungs- und Forschungsanstalt</name>
      <name lang="fr">Laboratoire fédéral d'essai des matériaux et de recherche</name>
      <name lang="it">Laboratorio federale di prova dei materiali e di ricerca</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Laboratory for Materials Testing and Research</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.empa.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.empa.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.empa.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.empa.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">contact@empa.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">contact@empa.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">contact@empa.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">contact@empa.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="1032" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>701</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eawag: Wasserforschungsinstitut des ETH-Bereichs</name>
      <name lang="fr">Eawag: L'Institut de Recherche de l'Eau du Domaine des EPF</name>
      <name lang="it">Eawag: L'Istituto per la Ricerca sulle Acque nel Settore dei Politecnici Federali</name>
      <name lang="en">Eawag: Swiss Federal Institute of Aquatic Science and Technology</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.eawag.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.eawag.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.eawag.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.eawag.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@eawag.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@eawag.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@eawag.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@eawag.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="701">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Wirtschaft, Bildung und Forschung</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'économie, de la formation et de la recherche</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'economia, della formazione e della ricerca</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Economic Affairs, Education and Research</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Dübendorf, St. Gallen und Thun</city>
      <title>«co-operate»: Modell für klimagerechtes Bauen</title>
      <lead>Der zukünftige Campus von Empa und Eawag steht kurz vor der Fertigstellung; er soll ein inspirierender Raum für neue Ideen und Innovationen werden, auch mit Blick auf umwelt- und klimafreundliches Bauen der Zukunft. Die Gebäude und Anlagen stecken voller Ideen, mit denen sich Energie sparen oder gewinnen lässt und Rohstoffe für spätere Nutzung gewonnen werden – von den Tiefen des Baugrundes bis auf die Dächer.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Was den schonenden Umgang mit Ressourcen und die Reduzierung des CO2-Ausstosses betrifft, soll der Campus, der auf dem Empa-Areal in Dübendorf Gestalt annimmt, durchaus ein Musterschüler werden – vom Scheitel bis zur Sohle, von den Dächern bis in 100 Meter Tiefe, wo die Erdsonden eines einzigartigen experimentellen saisonalen Energiespeichers enden. Im Sommer wird in diesen «Röhren» die Abwärme etwa von den Kältemaschinen, Lüftungen und Laborgeräten gespeichert, um sie dann im Winter zum Heizen oder für die Produktion von Warmwasser zu nutzen. Das Ziel: den CO2-Ausstoss der Gebäude auf dem gesamten Campus auf ein Minimum senken und zugleich diese innovative Technologie für eine nachhaltige Energiezukunft erkunden.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Den Ausstoss von Treibhausgasen minimieren: Dieser Anspruch prägt auch die Konstruktionen des neuen Campus. Das dreistöckige Gebäude rechter Hand der Einfahrt ist ein einzigartiges «Holz-Beton-Parkhaus», dessen Decken eine anspruchsvolle Konstruktion aus Fichtenträgern und -platten mit Betonüberzug sind. Durch diese Hybridbauweise liess sich die Dicke der Betonschichten laut dem Bauunternehmen Implenia auf rund ein Drittel reduzieren. Eine deutliche Einsparung also beim «Klimasünder» Zement: Rund 9'300 Quadratmeter Betonrippendecken wurden mit Holzbalkendecken ersetzt – auch ein Beitrag zum aktuellen Trend, Beton, wo möglich und sinnvoll, zum grossen Teil mit Konstruktionen aus Holz zu ersetzen.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Anspruchsvoll bei diesem Vorhaben war laut Kevin Olas, Leiter «Immobilien» der Empa, unter anderem die geschickt unauffällig integrierte Installation von Beleuchtung, Elektrotrassen und Abwasserleitungen, um die Ästhetik dieser raffinierten Hybridkonstruktionsweise nicht zu beeinträchtigen. Zudem musste die Planung auch künftige Aspekte berücksichtigen: Das Parkhaus wurde mit Blick auf den Klimawandel in Modulbauweise aus demontierbaren Fertigteilen geplant – mit Blick in eine fernere Zukunft, in der die individuelle Mobilität womöglich eine geringe Rolle spielt als heute. Dann liessen sich Teile des Bauwerks auch zu Werkstätten oder für andere Zwecke umwidmen.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Urin als Rohstoff für Dünger&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;In dieser Zukunft wird auch umweltfreundliche Kreislaufwirtschaft das Bauen bestimmen: Nicht nur Stahl, Beton oder Holzelemente lassen sich klimaschonend wiederverwerten, sondern auch menschliche «Rohstoffe». Beispiel Urin: Im grossen Laborgebäude im Zentrum von «co-operate» sind «NoMix»-WCs installiert, die Fachleute des Wasserforschungsinstituts Eawag in den vergangenen Jahren entwickelt haben. Ohne die gewohnte Benutzung zu verändern, trennen sie den menschlichen Urin vom so genannten Schwarzwasser aus Fäkalien, Spülwasser und Toilettenpapier.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Weil der Urin wertvolle Nährstoffe wie Stickstoff, Phosphor und Kalium enthält, lässt er sich nutzen, um Dünger für die Landwirtschaft herzustellen. In einem eigens entwickelten Verfahren der Eawag wird das Rohmaterial im Kellergeschoss des NEST-Gebäudes zunächst mit einem biologischen Prozess stabilisiert und verliert so den strengen Geruch. Ein Aktivkohle-Filter entfernt sämtliche Medikamentenrückstände, bevor die Flüssigkeit schliesslich eingedampft wird – zu einem hochwertigen Dünger namens «Aurin», den der Eawag-Spin-Off Vuna GmbH vermarktet. Aus 1000 Litern Urin entstehen 100 Liter von diesem Dünger, der seit 2018 vom Bundesamt für Landwirtschaft auch für den Einsatz bei essbaren Pflanzen zugelassen ist.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Viele Mosaiksteine für eine gute Klimabilanz&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Neben dem unauffälligen Urin-Sammelsystem dokumentieren viele offensichtliche Details den Anspruch des Campus als Wegweiser für umweltfreundliches Bauen. Photovoltaik-Installationen werden die Eigenstrom-Produktionen massiv erhöhen. Und auf mehr als 14'000 Quadratmetern Fläche bewegen sich die Menschen auf Recycling-Asphalt mit einem hohen Anteil von 80 Prozent wiederverwertetem Material in der Tragschicht und 20 Prozent in der dünnen Deckschicht.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Zugleich haben die Landschaftsarchitekten freilich auf Asphalt verzichtet, um naturnah zu gestalten: Bislang versiegelte Flächen werden «befreit», wie die Ludwig-Tetmajer-Strasse auf dem Empa-Areal. «Aus dieser ‹Parkplatz-Asphalt-Wüste› wird eine begrünte und schattige Zone», erklärt Kevin Olas. Und auch hinter den grossen Neubauten wird die Biodiversität mit vielfältigen Pflanzen und Bäumen gefördert – dank ausgewählter hitzeresistenter Arten, die sich auch bei künftigen Klimabedingungen wohlfühlen werden.&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Kevin Olas Immobilien, Empa Tel. +41 58 765 41 64 kevin.olas@empa.ch Vlatko Biljaka Immobilien, Empa Tel. +41 58 765 60 16 vlatko.biljaka@empa.ch Prof. Dr. Kai Udert Eawag, Verfahrenstechnik Tel. +41 58 765 53 60 kai.udert@eawag.ch</contact>
      <attachment id="258039">
        <title>Bauen mit Blick in die Zukunft: Zufahrt von der Überlandstrasse auf den künftigen Campus mit dem neuen Parkhaus auf der rechten Seite. Illustration: SAM Architekten / Filippo Bolognese Images</title>
        <format>jpg</format>
        <size-kb>3025</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/80956.jpg</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="258040">
        <title>Viel Holz hilft Beton sparen: Die Balken und Platten aus Fichtenholz für die Holz-Beton-Decke des neuen Parkhauses während der Montage. Bild: Empa</title>
        <format>jpg</format>
        <size-kb>2428</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/80957.jpg</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="258041">
        <title>Konstruktive Ästhetik: Die Verwendung von zwei Baustoffen mit unterschiedlichen Fertigungstoleranzen machten Planung und Montage zu einer Herausforderung. Bild: Empa</title>
        <format>jpg</format>
        <size-kb>1842</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/80958.jpg</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="258042">
        <title>Urin als Rohstoff: Das «NoMix»-WC trennt dank des sogenannten Teekanneneffekts den Urin ab, um ihn der Verwertung zuzuführen. Bild: Eawag</title>
        <format>jpg</format>
        <size-kb>133</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/80959.jpg</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="258043">
        <title>Dünger für Garten und Äcker: Das Produkt «Aurin» wird bereits vermarktet und vertrieben. Bild: Eawag</title>
        <format>jpg</format>
        <size-kb>4120</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/80960.jpg</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <link id="258046">
        <title>«co-operate»: Modell für klimagerechtes Bauen</title>
        <uri>https://www.empa.ch/web/s604/klimagerechtes-bauen-co-operate</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="258045">
        <title>Smarter Bauen: Wärmedepot im Erdreich</title>
        <uri>https://www.empa.ch/web/s604/eq73-waermedepot</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="258044">
        <title>Aurin Recycling-Dünger</title>
        <uri>https://vuna.ch/aurin/</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Dübendorf, St. Gallen und Thun</city>
      <title>"co-operate": modèle de construction adaptée au climat</title>
      <lead>Le futur campus de l'Empa et de l'Eawag est sur le point d'être achevé; il devrait devenir un espace inspirant pour de nouvelles idées et innovations, notamment dans l'optique d'une construction future respectueuse de l'environnement et du climat. Les bâtiments et les installations regorgent d'idées qui permettent d'économiser ou de gagner de l'énergie et de récupérer des matières premières pour une utilisation ultérieure – des profondeurs du sol de construction jusqu'aux toits.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;En ce qui concerne la préservation des ressources et la réduction des émissions de CO2, le campus qui prend forme sur le site de l'Empa à Dübendorf est appelé à devenir un élève modèle – du sommet à la base, des toits jusqu'à 100 mètres de profondeur, où aboutissent les sondes géothermiques d'un accumulateur d'énergie saisonnier expérimental unique en son genre. En été, ces "tubes" permettent de stocker la chaleur dégagée par exemple par les machines frigorifiques, les systèmes de ventilation et les appareils de laboratoire, pour l'utiliser ensuite en hiver pour le chauffage ou la production d'eau chaude. L'objectif : réduire au maximum les émissions de CO2 des bâtiments de l'ensemble du campus tout en explorant cette technologie innovante pour un avenir énergétique durable.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Minimiser les émissions de gaz à effet de serre : Cette exigence caractérise également les constructions du nouveau campus. Le bâtiment de trois étages situé à droite de l'entrée est un "parking bois-béton" unique en son genre, dont les plafonds sont une construction sophistiquée de poutres et de dalles en épicéa recouvertes de béton. Grâce à cette construction hybride, l'épaisseur des couches de béton a pu être réduite d'environ un tiers, selon l'entreprise de construction Implenia. Une économie considérable pour le ciment, "nuisible au climat" : environ 9300 mètres carrés de plafonds nervurés en béton ont été remplacés par des plafonds à poutres en bois – une contribution à la tendance actuelle qui consiste à remplacer le béton par des constructions en bois lorsque cela est possible et judicieux.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Selon Kevin Olas, responsable de l'immobilier à l'Empa, l'un des défis de ce projet consistait à intégrer de manière habilement discrète l'éclairage, les lignes électriques et les conduites d'eaux usées afin de ne pas nuire à l'esthétique de ce mode de construction hybride raffiné. En outre, la planification devait également tenir compte des aspects futurs : Dans la perspective du changement climatique, le parking a été conçu en construction modulaire à partir d'éléments préfabriqués démontables – dans l'optique d'un avenir lointain où la mobilité individuelle jouera peut-être un rôle moins important qu'aujourd'hui. Il serait alors possible de transformer certaines parties de l'ouvrage en ateliers ou de les utiliser à d'autres fins.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;L'urine, matière première pour les engrais&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Dans cet avenir, l'économie circulaire respectueuse de l'environnement déterminera également la construction : Non seulement l'acier, le béton ou les éléments en bois peuvent être recyclés en préservant le climat, mais aussi les "matières premières" humaines. Prenons l'exemple de l'urine : des WC "NoMix", développés ces dernières années par des spécialistes de l'Institut de recherche sur l'eau Eawag, ont été installés dans le grand bâtiment de laboratoire au centre de "co-operate". Sans modifier l'utilisation habituelle, ils séparent l'urine humaine de ce que l'on appelle les eaux noires, composées de matières fécales, d'eau de rinçage et de papier toilette.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Comme l'urine contient des nutriments précieux tels que l'azote, le phosphore et le potassium, elle peut être utilisée pour produire des engrais pour l'agriculture. Grâce à un procédé spécialement développé par l'Eawag, la matière première est d'abord stabilisée par un processus biologique dans le sous-sol du bâtiment NEST et perd ainsi son odeur forte. Un filtre à charbon actif élimine tous les résidus de médicaments avant que le liquide ne soit finalement évaporé – pour devenir un engrais de haute qualité appelé "Aurin", commercialisé par la société spin-off de l'Eawag Vuna GmbH. A partir de 1000 litres d'urine, on obtient 100 litres de cet engrais qui, depuis 2018, est également autorisé par l'Office fédéral de l'agriculture pour l'utilisation pour les plantes comestibles.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;De nombreuses pièces de la mosaïque pour un bon bilan climatique&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Outre le système discret de collecte des urines, de nombreux détails évidents témoignent de la volonté du campus de montrer la voie d'une construction respectueuse de l'environnement. Des installations photovoltaïques permettront d'augmenter massivement la production d'électricité propre. Et sur une surface de plus de 14 000 mètres carrés, les gens se déplacent sur de l'asphalte recyclé avec un pourcentage élevé de 80 pour cent de matériaux recyclés dans la couche de base et 20 pour cent dans la fine couche de roulement.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Parallèlement, les architectes paysagistes ont renoncé à l'asphalte afin de créer un aménagement proche de la nature : Les surfaces jusqu'ici imperméabilisées sont "libérées", comme la Ludwig-Tetmajer-Strasse sur le site de l'Empa. "Ce 'désert de parking et d'asphalte' devient une zone verdoyante et ombragée", explique Kevin Olas. Et la biodiversité sera également favorisée derrière les grands nouveaux bâtiments avec des plantes et des arbres variés – grâce à des espèces sélectionnées résistantes à la chaleur, qui se sentiront également bien dans les conditions climatiques rudes.&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Kevin Olas Immobilien, Empa Tél. +41 58 765 41 64 kevin.olas@empa.ch Vlatko Biljaka Immobilien, Empa Tél. +41 58 765 60 16 vlatko.biljaka@empa.ch Prof. Dr. Kai Udert Département Technologie des procédés, Eawag Tél. +41 58 765 53 60 kai.udert@eawag.ch</contact>
      <attachment id="258047">
        <title>Construire en regardant vers l'avenir : accès au futur campus depuis la Überlandstrasse avec le nouveau parking sur la droite. Illustration : SAM Architectes / Filippo Bolognese Images</title>
        <format>jpg</format>
        <size-kb>3025</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/80961.jpg</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="258048">
        <title>Beaucoup de bois permet d'économiser du béton : Les poutres et les panneaux en épicéa pour le plancher bois-béton du nouveau parking pendant le montage. Image : Empa</title>
        <format>jpg</format>
        <size-kb>2428</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/80962.jpg</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="258049">
        <title>Esthétique constructive : l'utilisation de deux matériaux de construction avec des tolérances de fabrication différentes a fait de la planification et du montage un défi. Image : Empa</title>
        <format>jpg</format>
        <size-kb>1842</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/80963.jpg</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="258062">
        <title>L'urine comme matière première : grâce à ce qu'on appelle l'effet "théière", les WC "NoMix" séparent l'urine pour la recycler. Image : Eawag</title>
        <format>jpg</format>
        <size-kb>137</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/80970.jpg</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="258050">
        <title>Engrais pour le jardin et les champs : le produit "Aurin" est déjà commercialisé et distribué. Image : Eawag</title>
        <format>jpg</format>
        <size-kb>4120</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/80964.jpg</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <link id="258053">
        <title>"co-operate" : modèle de construction adaptée au climat</title>
        <uri>https://www.empa.ch/web/s604/klimagerechtes-bauen-co-operate</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="258051">
        <title>Bâtir plus intelligemment: Dépôt de chaleur dans le sol</title>
        <uri>https://www.empa.ch/web/s604/eq73-waermedepot</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="258052">
        <title>Engrais de recyclage Aurin</title>
        <uri>https://vuna.ch/fr/aurin-recycling-dunger/</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Dübendorf, St. Gallen und Thun</city>
      <title>co-operate: model for climate-friendly construction</title>
      <lead>The future Empa and Eawag campus is nearing completion; it is set to become an inspiring space for new ideas and innovation, also with a view to environmentally and climate-friendly construction of the future. The buildings and facilities are full of ideas for saving or generating energy and recovering raw materials for later use – from the depths of the subsoil to the rooftops.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;When it comes to saving resources and reducing CO2 emissions, the campus taking shape on the Empa site in Dübendorf is set to be quite a role model – from top to bottom, from the rooftops down to a depth of 100 meters below ground, where the geothermal probes of a unique experimental seasonal energy storage system end. In summer, these "tubes" will store waste heat from, for example, the chillers, ventilation systems and laboratory equipment, and then use it in winter for heating or producing hot water. The goal: to minimize CO2 emissions from buildings across the campus while exploring this innovative technology for a sustainable energy future.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Minimize greenhouse gas emissions: This aspiration also shapes the designs of the new campus. The three-story building to the right of the entrance is a unique wood-concrete parking garage, the ceilings of which are a sophisticated construction of spruce beams and slabs overlaid with concrete. This hybrid construction method allowed the thickness of the concrete layers to be reduced to around one-third, according to construction company Implenia. Around 9,300 square meters of concrete ribbed ceilings were replaced with wooden beam ceilings – also a contribution to the current trend to replace concrete, whenever possible and sensible, to a large extent with constructions made of wood.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;According to Kevin Olas, Head of "Immobilien" at Empa, one of the challenging aspects of this project was the cleverly unobtrusive installation of lighting, electrical lines and wastewater pipes, so as not to detract from the aesthetics of this sophisticated hybrid construction. In addition, the planning also had to take future aspects into account: With a view to climate change, the parking garage was planned as a modular structure made of demountable prefabricated parts – with a view to a more distant future, in which individual mobility may play a lesser role than it does today. In that case, parts of the structure could also be converted into workshops or for other purposes.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Urine as raw material for fertilizer&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;In this future, environmentally friendly circular economy will also determine construction: Not only steel, concrete or wooden elements can be recycled in a climate-friendly way, but also human "raw materials". Take urine, for example: In the large laboratory building at the heart of co-operate, NoMix toilets have been installed, developed in recent years by experts from Eawag, the water research institute of the ETH Domain. Without changing the way they are normally used, they separate human urine from the so-called black water consisting of feces, flushing water and toilet paper.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Because urine contains valuable nutrients such as nitrogen, phosphorus and potassium, it can be used to produce fertilizer for agriculture. In a process specially developed by Eawag, the raw material is first stabilized by a biological process in the basement of the NEST building, thus losing its strong odor. An activated carbon filter removes all drug residues before the liquid is finally evaporated – to produce a high-quality fertilizer called Aurin, which is marketed by the Eawag spin-off Vuna GmbH. 1000 liters of urine produce 100 liters of fertilizer, which since 2018 has also been approved by the Swiss Federal Office for Agriculture for use on edible plants.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Many pieces of the puzzle for a good climate footprint&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;In addition to the inconspicuous urine collection system, many obvious details document the campus' claim to be a beacon for environmentally friendly construction. Photovoltaic installations will massively increase the campus' own electricity production. And on more than 14,000 square meters, people will move on recycled asphalt with a high proportion of 80 percent recycled material in the base course and 20 percent in the thinner surface course.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;At the same time, the landscape architects have freely dispensed with asphalt in order to design close to nature: Previously sealed areas are "liberated," such as Ludwig Tetmajer Street on the Empa site. "This 'asphalt desert' that had served as a parking lot will become a green and shady zone," explains Kevin Olas. And behind the large new buildings, biodiversity is also being promoted with diverse plants and trees – thanks to selected heat-resistant species that will also thrive in future climate conditions.&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Kevin Olas Immobilien, Empa Phone: +41 58 765 41 64 kevin.olas@empa.ch Vlatko Biljaka Immobilien, Empa Phone: +41 58 765 60 16 vlatko.biljaka@empa.ch Prof. Dr. Kai Udert Department Process Engineering, Eawag Phone: +41 58 765 53 60 kai.udert@eawag.ch</contact>
      <attachment id="258054">
        <title>Building with a view to the future: access to the future campus with the new parking garage on the right. Illustration: SAM Architects / Filippo Bolognese Images</title>
        <format>jpg</format>
        <size-kb>3025</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/80965.jpg</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="258055">
        <title>A lot of wood helps save concrete: The beams and slabs of spruce wood for the wood-concrete ceiling of the new parking garage during assembly. Image: Empa</title>
        <format>jpg</format>
        <size-kb>2428</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/80966.jpg</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="258056">
        <title>Structural aesthetics: The use of two building materials with different manufacturing tolerances made planning and assembly a challenge. Image: Empa</title>
        <format>jpg</format>
        <size-kb>1842</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/80967.jpg</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="258057">
        <title>Urine as a raw material: Thanks to the so-called teapot effect, the NoMix toilet separates urine for recycling. Image: Eawag</title>
        <format>jpg</format>
        <size-kb>138</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/80968.jpg</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="258058">
        <title>Fertilizer for gardens and fields: Aurin is already being marketed and distributed. Image: Eawag</title>
        <format>jpg</format>
        <size-kb>4120</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/80969.jpg</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <link id="258061">
        <title>"co-operate": model for climate-friendly construction</title>
        <uri>https://www.empa.ch/web/s604/klimagerechtes-bauen-co-operate</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="258059">
        <title>Building smarter: Heat storage in the deep</title>
        <uri>https://www.empa.ch/web/s604/eq73-waermedepot</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="258060">
        <title>Aurin recycled fertiliser</title>
        <uri>https://vuna.ch/aurin/</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="8">
        <name lang="de">Bildung und Forschung</name>
        <name lang="fr">Formation et recherche</name>
        <name lang="it">Formazione e ricerca</name>
        <name lang="en">Education and Research</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="11">
        <name lang="de">Energie</name>
        <name lang="fr">Énergie</name>
        <name lang="it">Energia</name>
        <name lang="en">Energy</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="29">
        <name lang="de">Umwelt und Natur</name>
        <name lang="fr">Environnement et nature</name>
        <name lang="it">Ambiente e natura</name>
        <name lang="en">Environment and Nature</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="45">
        <name lang="de">Technologie</name>
        <name lang="fr">Technologie</name>
        <name lang="it">Tecnologia</name>
        <name lang="en">Technology</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
