<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="100270" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2024-03-01</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="yes" id="703" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>701</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Staatssekretariat für Wirtschaft</name>
      <name lang="fr">Secrétariat d'Etat à l'économie</name>
      <name lang="it">Segreteria di Stato dell'economia</name>
      <name lang="en">State Secretariat for Economic Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.seco.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.seco.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.seco.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.seco.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@seco.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@seco.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@seco.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@seco.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="701">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Wirtschaft, Bildung und Forschung</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'économie, de la formation et de la recherche</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'economia, della formazione e della ricerca</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Economic Affairs, Education and Research</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Ukraine: Die Schweiz setzt das 13. Sanktionspaket der EU um</title>
      <lead>Das für Sanktionen zuständige Departement für Wirtschaft, Bildung und Forschung (WBF) hat am 29. Februar 2024 weitere Sanktionsmassnahmen gegen Russland beschlossen. Die Schweiz schliesst sich somit dem 13. Sanktionspaket der Europäischen Union (EU) an, das als Reaktion auf die nun zweijährige militärische Aggression Russlands gegen die Ukraine erlassen wurde. Die Massnahmen treten am 1. März 2024 um 18:00 Uhr in Kraft. </lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Als Reaktion auf die mittlerweile seit zwei Jahren anhaltende militärische Aggression Russlands gegen die Ukraine hat die EU am 23. Februar 2024 im Rahmen ihres 13. Sanktionspakets neue Sanktionen gegen Russland erlassen. Das WBF hat die in seiner Kompetenz stehende Sanktionierung von weiteren 106 natürlichen Personen und 88 Unternehmen und Organisationen durch die Schweiz am 29. Februar 2024 vorgenommen. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Bei den neu sanktionierten natürlichen Personen sowie Unternehmen und Organisationen handelt es sich vorwiegend um solche, die im russischen militärisch-industriellen Komplex tätig sind und somit namentlich an der Herstellung von Raketen, Drohnen, Flugabwehrraketensystemen und anderer militärischer Ausrüstung beteiligt sind. Neu wurden zudem russische Unternehmen und Personen sanktioniert, die an der Lieferung von Rüstungsgütern der Demokratischen Volksrepublik Korea nach Russland beteiligt sind. Ebenso wurden Richter und Beamte aus den besetzten Gebieten der Ukraine sowie Personen und Einrichtungen, die an der Zwangsverschleppung ukrainischer Kinder beteiligt sind, Sanktionen unterstellt. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Um Russland weiter daran zu hindern, sensible Güter und Technologien für das russische Militär zu erwerben, wurden zudem weitere Massnahmen im Handelsbereich eingeführt. Diese Massnahmen&lt;b&gt; &lt;/b&gt;umfassen ein Exportverbot von &lt;i&gt;dual-use&lt;/i&gt; Gütern und Gütern zur militärischen und technologischen Stärkung Russlands an 27 zusätzliche Unternehmen. Ebenso wurde die Liste der einem Exportverbot unterliegenden Güter erweitert. Neu ist beispielsweise der Verkauf und die Ausfuhr nach Russland von Komponenten verboten, die für die Entwicklung und Herstellung von Drohnen verwendet werden. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Sämtliche Massnahmen treten am 1. März 2024 um 18:00 Uhr in Kraft.&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Rückfragen Medien: Kommunikation WBF info@gs-wbf.admin.ch 058 462 20 07 Rückfragen Unternehmen: sanctions@seco.admin.ch 058 464 08 12</contact>
      <link id="271391">
        <title>Massnahmen im Zusammenhang mit der Situation in der Ukraine</title>
        <uri>http://www.seco.admin.ch/situation-ukraine</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="271394">
        <title>Verordnung über Massnahmen im Zusammenhang mit der Situation in der Ukraine</title>
        <uri>https://www.fedlex.admin.ch/eli/oc/2024/94/de</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Ukraine : la Suisse met en œuvre le 13e paquet de sanctions de l’UE</title>
      <lead>Le 29 février 2024, le Département fédéral de l’économie, de la formation et de la recherche, compétent en matière de sanctions, a arrêté de nouvelles mesures à l’encontre de la Russie. La Suisse s’associe ainsi au 13e paquet de sanctions de l’Union européenne, adopté en réaction à l’agression militaire russe en Ukraine, qui dure maintenant depuis deux ans. Les mesures entrent en vigueur le 1er mars 2024 à 18 heures.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;En réponse à l'agression militaire russe en Ukraine, qui perdure depuis deux ans, l'Union européenne (UE) a arrêté, le 23 février 2024, de nouvelles mesures à l'encontre de la Russie sous la forme d'un 13e paquet de sanctions. Le 29 février 2024, le Département fédéral de l'économie, de la formation et de la recherche (DEFR) a étendu, eu égard à sa compétence, le régime de sanctions de la Suisse à 106 personnes et à 88 entreprises et entités supplémentaires.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;La plupart des personnes, entreprises et entités nouvellement sanctionnées sont actives dans le complexe militaro-industriel de la Russie et participent donc notamment à la fabrication de missiles, de drones, de systèmes de missiles antiaériens et d'autres équipements militaires. Des entreprises et personnes russes impliquées dans la livraison de biens d'équipement militaires de la Corée du Nord vers la Russie sont dorénavant également visées par des sanctions, tout comme des juges et des fonctionnaires dans les territoires occupés de l'Ukraine ainsi que des personnes et des établissements participant à la déportation forcée d'enfants ukrainiens.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;De nouvelles mesures commerciales ont en outre été arrêtées pour entraver davantage la Russie dans l'acquisition de biens et de technologies sensibles pour son armée. Elles prévoient, entre autres, l'interdiction d'exporter à 27 nouvelles entreprises des biens à double usage et des biens susceptibles de contribuer au renforcement militaire et technologique de la Russie. De plus, la liste des biens dont l'exportation est interdite a été allongée. À titre d'exemple, la vente et l'exportation à destination de la Russie de composants utilisés pour développer et fabriquer des drones sont désormais interdites.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Les nouvelles mesures entrent en vigueur le 1er mars 2024 à 18 heures.&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Renseignements (pour les médias) : Communication DEFR info@gs-wbf.admin.ch 058 462 20 07 Renseignements (pour les entreprises) : sanctions@seco.admin.ch 058 464 08 12</contact>
      <link id="271392">
        <title>Mesures en lien avec la situation en Ukraine (admin.ch)</title>
        <uri>http://www.seco.admin.ch/situation-en-ukraine</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="271395">
        <title>Ordonnance instituant des mesures en lien avec la situation en Ukraine</title>
        <uri>https://www.fedlex.admin.ch/eli/oc/2024/94/fr</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Ucraina: la Svizzera attua il 13° pacchetto di sanzioni dell’UE</title>
      <lead>Il 29 febbraio 2024 il Dipartimento federale dell’economia, della formazione e della ricerca (DEFR) ha deciso ulteriori sanzioni nei confronti della Russia. La Svizzera aderisce così al 13° pacchetto di sanzioni dell’Unione europea (UE) emanato in risposta all’aggressione militare della Russia in Ucraina, che si protrae ormai da due anni. Le misure entrano in vigore il 1° marzo 2024 alle ore 18:00. </lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;In risposta all'aggressione militare della Russia contro l'Ucraina, che si protrae ormai da due anni, il 23 febbraio 2024 l'UE ha imposto nuove sanzioni nei confronti della Russia (13° pacchetto). Il 29 febbraio il DEFR ha esteso le sanzioni di sua competenza ad altre 106 persone fisiche e 88 imprese e organizzazioni. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Le persone fisiche, le imprese e le organizzazioni sanzionate sono principalmente quelle che operano nell'apparato militare-industriale russo e sono quindi coinvolte nella produzione di missili, droni, sistemi missilistici antiaerei e altre attrezzature militari. Le sanzioni colpiscono ora anche imprese e individui russi coinvolti nella fornitura di beni d'armamento dalla Repubblica popolare democratica di Corea alla Russia. Nella nuova lista figurano anche i giudici e i funzionari dei territori occupati dell'Ucraina, così come gli individui e gli organismi coinvolti nel trasferimento forzato di bambini ucraini. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Al fine di impedire ulteriormente alla Russia di acquisire beni e tecnologie sensibili per le sue forze armate, sono state introdotte altre misure commerciali, che includono il divieto di esportazione di beni a duplice impiego (&lt;i&gt;dual use&lt;/i&gt;) e di beni per il rafforzamento militare e tecnologico della Russia ad altre 27 imprese. È stata inoltre ampliata la lista dei beni soggetti al divieto di esportazione. Ad esempio, la vendita e l'esportazione in Russia di componenti utilizzati per lo sviluppo e la produzione di droni sono adesso vietate.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Le nuove misure entrano in vigore il 1° marzo 2024 alle ore 18:00.&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Per maggiori informazioni (media): Comunicazione DEFR info@gs-wbf.admin.ch 058 462 20 07 Per maggiori informazioni (imprese): sanctions@seco.admin.ch 058 464 08 12</contact>
      <link id="271393">
        <title>Provvedimenti in relazione alla situazione in Ucraina (admin.ch)</title>
        <uri>http://www.seco.admin.ch/situazione-ucraina</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="271396">
        <title>Ordinanza che istituisce provvedimenti in relazione alla situazione in Ucraina</title>
        <uri>https://www.fedlex.admin.ch/eli/oc/2024/94/it</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Ukraine: Switzerland implements the EU’s 13th package of sanctions</title>
      <lead>The Federal Department of Economic Affairs, Education and Research (EAER), which is responsible for sanctions, decided on 29 February to impose further sanctions against Russia. Switzerland is thus joining the 13th sanctions package of the European Union (EU), adopted in response to Russia's ongoing military aggression against Ukraine over the past two years. The measures will enter into force at 6pm on 1 March.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;As part of a 13th package of sanctions adopted on 23 February, the EU imposed new sanctions in response to Russia's ongoing military aggression against Ukraine, which has continued for more than two years. The EAER followed suit on 29 February by expanding the Swiss sanctions lists under its jurisdiction to include a further 106 individuals and 88 entities and organisations. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The individuals, entities and organisations newly placed under sanction are primarily those operating in Russia's military-industrial complex and involved in the manufacture of missiles, drones, anti-aircraft missile systems and other military equipment. The new listings also target Russian companies and individuals involved in supplying Russia with defence equipment from the Democratic People's Republic of Korea. Sanctions have also been placed on judges and officials from the occupied territories of Ukraine and on individuals and organisations involved in the forced transfer of Ukrainian children. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Additional trade sanctions have been introduced to further prevent Russia from acquiring sensitive goods and technologies for the Russian military. These measures add 27 entities to the export ban on dual-use goods and on goods that may contribute to Russia's military and technological enhancement. The list of goods included in the export ban has also been expanded: for example, the sale and export to Russia of components used in the design and manufacture of drones is now prohibited. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;All measures enter into force at 6pm on 1 March 2024.&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Enquiries from the media: EAER Communications info@gs-wbf.admin.ch 058 462 20 07 Enquiries from businesses: sanctions@seco.admin.ch 058 464 08 12</contact>
      <link id="271391">
        <title>Massnahmen im Zusammenhang mit der Situation in der Ukraine</title>
        <uri>http://www.seco.admin.ch/situation-ukraine</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="271392">
        <title>Mesures en lien avec la situation en Ukraine (admin.ch)</title>
        <uri>http://www.seco.admin.ch/situation-en-ukraine</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="271394">
        <title>Verordnung über Massnahmen im Zusammenhang mit der Situation in der Ukraine</title>
        <uri>https://www.fedlex.admin.ch/eli/oc/2024/94/de</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="271395">
        <title>Ordonnance instituant des mesures en lien avec la situation en Ukraine</title>
        <uri>https://www.fedlex.admin.ch/eli/oc/2024/94/fr</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <offers>
      <offer id="255" org-id="703">
        <name lang="de">Sanktionen / Embargos und Exportkontrollen</name>
        <name lang="fr">sanctions / embargos et contrôles à l‘exportation</name>
        <name lang="it">Sanzioni / embarghi e controlli delle esportazioni</name>
        <name lang="en">sanctions / embargoes and export controls</name>
      </offer>
    </offers>
    <topics>
      <topic id="1">
        <name lang="de">Amtliche Veröffentlichungen (wird nicht mehr angeboten)</name>
        <name lang="fr">Publications officielles (n’est plus proposé)</name>
        <name lang="it">Pubblicazioni ufficiali (non è più offerto)</name>
        <name lang="en">Official Publications (is no longer offered)</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="17">
        <name lang="de">Kriminalität</name>
        <name lang="fr">Criminalité</name>
        <name lang="it">Criminalità</name>
        <name lang="en">Criminality</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="35">
        <name lang="de">Finanzplatz</name>
        <name lang="fr">Place financière</name>
        <name lang="it">Piazza finanziaria</name>
        <name lang="en">Financial Centre</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="47">
        <name lang="de">Wirtschaft</name>
        <name lang="fr">Économie</name>
        <name lang="it">Economia</name>
        <name lang="en">Economic Affairs</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="48">
        <name lang="de">Zoll</name>
        <name lang="fr">Douanes</name>
        <name lang="it">Dogane</name>
        <name lang="en">Customs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
