<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="64480" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2016-11-11</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="201" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>201</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="201">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Bilaterale Themen, Situation in Europa, Sicherheit: Bundesrat Didier Burkhalter reist zu bilateralen Gespräche nach Slowenien</title>
      <lead>Am 15. November 2016 trifft Bundesrat Didier Burkhalter in Ljubljana mit Vertretern der slowenischen Regierung und des Parlaments zusammen. Im Zentrum der Gespräche stehen bilaterale, die Situation in Europa, die Politik der Schweiz gegenüber der EU sowie regionale Sicherheitsfragen. </lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Bei seinem Aufenthalt in der slowenischen Hauptstadt Ljubljana am 15. November 2016 wird Bundesrat Didier Burkhalter mit Premierminister Miro Cerar, Aussenminister Karl Erjavec und Parlamentspräsident Milan Brglez bilaterale Gespräche führen. Im Zentrum der Treffen stehen bilaterale Aspekte, darunter aktuelle Fragen zu Europa, der Stand der Umsetzung des neuen Verfassungsartikels zur Zuwanderung sowie Aspekte der Sicherheit wie die Lage in der Region und im Mittleren Osten. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Die Beziehungen der Schweiz zu Slowenien sind eng. So hat die Schweiz in Slowenien im Rahmen des Erweiterungsbeitrags zur Verminderung der wirtschaftlichen und sozialen Ungleichheiten in Europa mehrere Projekte unterstützt, beide Staaten vertreten sich in verschiedenen Ländern im konsularischen Bereich. Auch die bilateralen Kontakte zwischen Vertreterinnen und Vertretern beider Staaten sind intensiv. So weilte unter anderem im vergangenen Jahr die damalige Bundespräsidentin Simonetta Sommaruga in Slowenien, 2012 empfing Bundesrat Burkhalter den slowenischen Aussenminister Erjavec zum Gespräch in Bern. &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Kommunikation EDA Bundeshaus West CH-3003 Bern Tel. Kommunikationsservice: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Medienstelle: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <link id="160720">
        <title>Bilaterale Beziehungen Schweiz–Slowenien</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home/vertretungen-und-reisehinweise/slowenien/bilatereale-beziehungenschweizslowenien.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="160721">
        <title>Schweizer Erweiterungsbeitrag für Slowenien</title>
        <uri>https://www.erweiterungsbeitrag.admin.ch/erweiterungsbeitrag/de/home/laender/slowenien.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Thèmes bilatéraux, situation en Europe et sécurité: le conseiller fédéral Didier Burkhalter se rendra en Slovénie pour divers entretiens bilatéraux</title>
      <lead>Le 15 novembre 2016, le conseiller fédéral Didier Burkhalter rencontrera à Ljubljana des représentants du gouvernement et du parlement slovènes. Les relations bilatérales, la situation en Europe, la politique de la Suisse à l’égard de l’UE et les questions liées à la sécurité régionale seront au menu des discussions.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Durant sa visite dans la capitale slovène Ljubljana, le 15 novembre 2016, le conseiller fédéral Didier Burkhalter rencontrera le premier ministre Miro Cerar, le ministre des affaires étrangères Karl Erjavec et le président du Parlement Milan Brglez pour des entretiens bilatéraux. Les discussions porteront notamment sur des questions bilatérales, notamment en lien avec l'actualité européenne, sur la mise en œuvre du nouvel article constitutionnel relatif à l’immigration ainsi que sur des aspects sécuritaires, en particulier dans la région et au Moyen-Orient. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;La Suisse entretient des relations étroites avec la Slovénie. En témoignent notamment les nombreux projets qu'elle a soutenus dans ce pays dans le cadre de la contribution suisse à la réduction des disparités économiques et sociales au sein de l’UE, ainsi que la représentation réciproque que les deux États ont instaurée en matière consulaire dans plusieurs pays. Les échanges bilatéraux entre représentants des deux États sont également intenses. Ainsi, Simonetta Sommaruga s'est rendue l'an dernier en Slovénie alors qu'elle était présidente de la Confédération et le conseiller fédéral Didier Burkhalter a reçu son homologue slovène Karl Erjavec à Berne en 2012, à l'occasion d'une visite officielle de travail.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Communication DFAE Palais fédéral ouest CH-3003 Berne Tél. Service de communication: +41 58 462 31 53 Tél. Service de presse: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <link id="160722">
        <title>Relations bilatérales Suisse–Slovénie</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae/representations-et-conseils-aux-voyageurs/slovenie/suisse-slovenie.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="160723">
        <title>Contribution de la Suisse à l’élargissement en faveur de la Slovénie</title>
        <uri>https://www.erweiterungsbeitrag.admin.ch/erweiterungsbeitrag/fr/home/laender/slowenien.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Temi bilaterali, situazione in Europa e sicurezza al centro dei colloqui bilaterali del consigliere federale Didier Burkhalter in visita in Slovenia</title>
      <lead>Il 15 novembre 2016 il consigliere federale Didier Burkhalter incontrerà a Lubiana rappresentanti del Governo e del Parlamento sloveni. Al centro dei colloqui, questioni bilaterali e di sicurezza regionale, la situazione in Europa e la politica della Svizzera nei confronti dell’UE.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;In occasione del suo soggiorno nella capitale slovena Lubiana il 15 novembre 2016, il consigliere federale Didier Burkhalter svolgerà colloqui bilaterali con il premier Miro Cerar, il ministro degli esteri Karl Erjavec e il presidente del Parlamento Milan Brglez. La discussione sarà incentrata su questioni bilaterali, in particolare quelle relative all’Europa, allo stato di attuazione del nuovo articolo costituzionale sull’immigrazione e agli aspetti di sicurezza come la situazione nella regione e nel Medio Oriente. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Le relazioni tra la Svizzera e la Slovenia sono strette. In Slovenia, nel quadro del contributo all’allargamento, la Svizzera ha infatti sostenuto numerosi progetti per la lotta contro le disparità sociali ed economiche ed entrambi gli Stati si rappresentano vicendevolmente in ambito consolare in vari Paesi. Anche i contatti bilaterali tra le rappresentanti dei due Stati sono fitti. Lo scorso anno, ad esempio, l’allora presidente della Confederazione Simonetta Sommaruga si è recata in visita in Slovenia e nel 2012 il consigliere federale Didier Burkhalter ha accolto il ministro degli esteri sloveno Kalr Erjavec, giunto a Berna per colloqui. &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Comunicazione DFAE Palazzo federale ovest CH-3003 Berna Tel. Servizio di comunicazione: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Servizio stampa: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <link id="160724">
        <title>Relazioni bilaterali Svizzera–Slovenia</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae/rappresentanze-e-consigli-di-viaggio/slovenia/svizzera-slovenia.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="160725">
        <title>Contribuito della Svizzera all'allargamento a favore della Slovenia</title>
        <uri>https://www.erweiterungsbeitrag.admin.ch/erweiterungsbeitrag/it/home/laender/slowenien.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Bilateral matters, the situation in Europe and security: Federal Councillor Didier Burkhalter to travel to Slovenia for bilateral talks</title>
      <lead>On 15 November 2016, Federal Councillor Didier Burkhalter will travel to Ljubljana to meet representatives of the Slovenian parliament and government. The talks will focus on bilateral matters, the situation in Europe, Swiss policy on the EU and regional security issues.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;During his visit to the Slovenian capital Ljubljana on 15 November 2016, Federal Councillor Didier Burkhalter will have talks with the Prime Minister, Miro Cerar, the Foreign Minister, Karl Erjavec, and the President of the National Assembly, Milan Brglez. The talks will focus on bilateral matters, including current issues concerning Europe, the status of implementation of the new article in the Swiss constitution on immigration, and aspects of security including the situation in the region and in the Middle East. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Switzerland and Slovenia have close ties. Switzerland has supported several projects in Slovenia in the context of Switzerland's contribution to the enlarged EU, which aims to help reduce economic and social disparities in Europe. The two countries represent each other in consular matters in a number of countries. Bilateral contacts between representatives of the two countries are close and frequent. Visiting Swiss officials to Slovenia last year included Simonetta Sommaruga, the then President of the Confederation, and in 2012 Federal Councillor Didier Burkhalter received his Slovenian counterpart Karl Erjavec for talks in Bern. &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>FDFA Communication Federal Palace West Wing CH-3003 Bern, Switzerland Tel. Communication service: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Press service: +41 58 460 55 55 E-mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @SwissMFA</contact>
      <link id="160726">
        <title>Bilateral relations Switzerland-Slovenia</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home/representations-and-travel-advice/slovenia/switzerland-slovenia.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="160727">
        <title>Switzerland’s enlargement contribution for Slovenia</title>
        <uri>https://www.erweiterungsbeitrag.admin.ch/erweiterungsbeitrag/en/home/laender/slowenien.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <offers>
      <offer id="313" org-id="201">
        <name lang="de">Schweizerische Europapolitik</name>
        <name lang="fr">Politique européenne de la Suisse</name>
        <name lang="it">Politica europea della Svizzera</name>
        <name lang="en">Swiss policy on the EU</name>
      </offer>
    </offers>
    <topics>
      <topic id="34">
        <name lang="de">Europa</name>
        <name lang="fr">Europe</name>
        <name lang="it">Europa</name>
        <name lang="en">Europe</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
