<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="64697" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2016-11-28</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="1070" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>1070</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Der Bundesrat</name>
      <name lang="fr">Conseil fédéral</name>
      <name lang="it">Il Consiglio federale</name>
      <name lang="en">The Federal Council</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.admin.ch/gov/de/start.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.admin.ch/gov/fr/accueil.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.admin.ch/gov/it/pagina-iniziale.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.admin.ch/gov/en/start.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="201" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>201</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="1070">
      <name lang="de">Der Bundesrat</name>
      <name lang="fr">Conseil fédéral</name>
      <name lang="it">Il Consiglio federale</name>
      <name lang="en">The Federal Council</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.admin.ch/gov/de/start.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.admin.ch/gov/fr/accueil.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.admin.ch/gov/it/pagina-iniziale.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.admin.ch/gov/en/start.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <department id="201">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Internationale Tunesien-Konferenz: Samuel Schmid vertritt die Schweiz</title>
      <lead>Die Schweiz wird am 29. und 30. November 2016 an einer internationalen Konferenz zur Förderung der wirtschaftlichen Entwicklung und der Investitionen in Tunesien teilnehmen. Sie wird dabei von alt Bundesrat Samuel Schmid vertreten. </lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Am 29. und 30. November 2016 findet in Tunis die internationale Konferenz «Tunisia 2020» zur Förderung der wirtschaftlichen Entwicklung und der Investitionen in Tunesien statt. Der Bundesrat hat alt Bundesrat Samuel Schmid ernannt, die Schweiz an der Konferenz zu vertreten. Samuel Schmid ist Präsident der Freundschaftsgruppe Schweiz-Tunesien. Er wird als ehemaliger Bundespräsident sprechen. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Die Schweiz unterstützt Tunesien seit 2011 im Rahmen eines Programms zur Transitionshilfe. Samuel Schmid wird in seiner Rede die Fortschritte begrüssen, die Tunesien in den letzten Jahren erzielt hat, und die tunesischen Behörden ermutigen, die Reformen weiterzuführen, die zur Förderung ausländischer Investitionen, darunter jener der Schweiz, erforderlich sind. Er wird Tunesien auch die Unterstützung der Schweiz bei der Umsetzung dieser Reformen zusichern, namentlich im Rahmen ihrer Strategie zur internationalen Zusammenarbeit 2017–2020 für Nordafrika, die demnächst verabschiedet werden soll. &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Information EDA Tel.: +41 58 462 31 53 info@eda.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Conférence internationale pour la Tunisie – La Suisse représentée par Samuel Schmid</title>
      <lead>La Suisse participera à la conférence internationale d’appui à l’économie et de promotion de l’investissement en Tunisie les 29 et 30 novembre 2016. Elle sera représentée à cette occasion par l’ancien conseiller fédéral Samuel Schmid.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;La Tunisie organise les 29 et 30 novembre prochains à Tunis une Conférence internationale d’appui à l’économie et de promotion de l’investissement en Tunisie (« Tunisie 2020 »). Le Conseil fédéral a nommé l’ancien conseiller fédéral Samuel Schmid pour représenter la Suisse à cette occasion. Il s’exprimera en tant qu’ancien président de la Confédération. Pour rappel, M. Schmid préside le Groupe d’amitié Suisse-Tunisie. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;La Suisse soutient la Tunisie depuis 2011 dans le cadre d’un programme d’aide à la transition. Dans son intervention, Samuel Schmid va saluer les avancées réalisées par la Tunisie au cours des dernières années et encourager les autorités tunisiennes à poursuivre les réformes nécessaires pour promouvoir les investissements étrangers dans ce pays, y compris ceux de la Suisse. Il va aussi assurer la Tunisie du soutien de la Suisse dans la mise en œuvre de ces réformes, notamment au travers de sa stratégie de coopération internationale 2017-2020 pour l’Afrique du Nord sur le point d’être adoptée. &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Information DFAE Tél. +41 58 462 31 53 info@eda.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Conferenza internazionale per la Tunisia – Samuel Schmid rappresenta la Svizzera</title>
      <lead>Il 29 e il 30 novembre 2016, la Svizzera parteciperà alla conferenza internazionale di sostegno allo sviluppo economico e di promozione degli investimenti in Tunisia. In questa occasione, sarà rappresentata dall’ex consigliere federale Samuel Schmid.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Il 29 e il 30 novembre, la Tunisia organizza a Tunisi una Conferenza internazionale di sostegno allo sviluppo economico e di promozione degli investimenti in Tunisia («Tunisia 2020»). Per rappresentare la Svizzera, il Consiglio federale ha nominato l’ex consigliere federale Samuel Schmid, che terrà un discorso nelle veci di ex presidente della Confederazione. Non si deve dimenticare che Samuel Schmid presiede il Gruppo di amicizia Svizzera-Tunisia. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;La Svizzera sostiene la Tunisia dal 2011 nell’ambito di un programma di aiuto alla transizione. Nel suo intervento, Samuel Schmid parlerà dei progressi realizzati dalla Tunisia nel corso degli ultimi anni e incoraggerà le autorità tunisine a proseguire le riforme necessarie per promuovere gli investimenti stranieri nel Paese, compresi quelli svizzeri. Garantirà inoltre alla Tunisia il sostegno della Svizzera nell’attuazione di queste riforme, in particolare attraverso la sua strategia di cooperazione internazionale 2017-2020 per il Nord Africa, che sta per essere adottata. &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Informazione DFAE Tel. +41 58 462 31 53 info@eda.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>International Conference for Tunisia – Switzerland represented by Samuel Schmid</title>
      <lead>Switzerland is to take part in the international conference on economic support and investment promotion in Tunisia on 29 and 30 November 2016. It will be represented by former Federal Councillor Samuel Schmid.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;On 29 and 30 November, Tunisia will organise an international conference in Tunis on economic support and investment promotion in Tunisia (TUNISIA 2020). The Federal Council has appointed former Federal Councillor Samuel Schmid to represent Switzerland at the event. He will speak in his capacity as a former President of the Swiss Confederation. Mr Schmid currently chairs the Tunisian-Swiss friendship group. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Since 2011, Switzerland has supported Tunisia within the framework of a programme of transition assistance. In his speech, Mr Schmid will commend the progress Tunisia has made in recent years and encourage the Tunisian authorities to pursue the reforms needed to promote foreign investment in the country, including Swiss investment. He will also assure Tunisia of Switzerland's support in the implementation of these reforms, notably through its international cooperation strategy 2017–2020 for North Africa, which it is about to adopt. &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>FDFA Information Tel. +41 31 322 31 53 info@eda.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
