<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="55987" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2015-01-23</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="201" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>201</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="201">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Unterzeichnung eines Abkommens mit dem WEF</title>
      <lead>Am Rande des Weltwirtschaftsforums 2015 in Davos traf sich EDA-Vorsteher Didier Burkhalter mit dem Präsidenten des WEF-Stiftungsrates Klaus Schwab. Bei dieser Gelegenheit wurde ein Abkommen über den Status des WEF in der Schweiz unterschrieben.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Am 23. Januar 2015 fand am Rande des World Economic Forum (WEF) in Davos ein Treffen zwischen dem Vorsteher des Eidgenössischen Departements für auswärtige Angelegenheiten (EDA), Bundesrat Didier Burkhalter, und dem Präsidenten des WEF-Stiftungsrates, Klaus Schwab, statt. Bei dieser Gelegenheit wurde ein Abkommen unterzeichnet, das den Status der Stiftung World Economic Forum in der Schweiz im Sinne des Gaststaatgesetzes vom 22. Juni 2007 (GSG, SR 192.12) bestätigt.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;An seiner Sitzung vom 17. Dezember 2014 hat der Bundesrat das WEF als „anderes internationales Organ“ im Sinne des Gaststaatgesetzes anerkannt und das Abkommen genehmigt. Das Abkommen bestätigt den Status, den die Stiftung World Economic Forum in der Schweiz geniesst. Es beruht auf der bedeutenden Rolle des WEF für die Schweiz und sieht eine Stärkung der Zusammenarbeit zwischen dem Bund und dem WEF in dessen Tätigkeitsgebiet vor. Inhaltlich orientiert sich das Abkommen an jenen, die der Bundesrat bereits mit vergleichbaren Organisationen abgeschlossen hat, und sieht beispielsweise Erleichterungen bei der Anstellung von Personal vor. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Seit seiner Gründung im Jahr 1971 hat das WEF seine Tätigkeiten beträchtlich weiterentwickelt. Insbesondere mit Blick auf das jährliche Treffen in Davos hat das WEF eine globale Dimension erreicht und geniesst seitens der Staatengemeinschaft und der internationalen Organisationen hohes Ansehen.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Kommunikation EDA Bundeshaus West CH-3003 Bern Tel. Kommunikationsservice: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Medienstelle: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <attachment id="132382">
        <title>Abkommen (Dieser Text ist ein Vorabdruck. Verbindlich ist die Version, welche im Bundesblatt veröffentlicht wird.)</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>20</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/38056.pdf</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </attachment>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Conclusion d'un accord avec le WEF</title>
      <lead>En marge de la rencontre annuelle du WEF à Davos a eu lieu une rencontre entre le chef du DFAE, Didier Burkhalter, et le président du Conseil de fondation du WEF Klaus Schwab. Un accord sur le statut du WEF en Suisse a été signé à cette occasion. </lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Le 23 janvier 2015, une rencontre a eu lieu entre le chef du Département fédéral des affaires étrangères (DFAE), le conseiller fédéral Didier Burkhalter, et le président du Conseil de fondation du WEF, Klaus Schwab, en marge de la rencontre annuelle du WEF à Davos. Un accord a été signé à cette occasion, qui confirme le statut de la Fondation World Economic Forum en Suisse conformément à la loi sur l'Etat hôte du 22 juin 2007 (LEH, RS 192.12). &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Lors de sa séance du 17 décembre 2014, le Conseil fédéral a reconnu le WEF en tant que «autre organisme international» au sens de la loi sur l’Etat hôte et a approuvé cet accord. L'accord a pour objet de confirmer le statut dont la Fondation du World Economic Forum bénéficie en Suisse. Il se fonde sur le rôle important du WEF pour la Suisse et prévoit un renforcement de la coopération entre la Confédération et le WEF dans son champ d'activités. Le contenu de cet accord entre dans le cadre de ceux qui ont été conclus par le Conseil fédéral avec d'autres organisations du même type et prévoit par exemple des facilitations au niveau du recrutement du personnel. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Depuis sa fondation en 1971, le WEF a considérablement développé ses activités et, au travers notamment de sa réunion annuelle à Davos, a atteint une dimension mondiale et une large reconnaissance au sein des Etats et des organisations internationales.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Communication DFAE Palais fédéral ouest CH-3003 Berne Tél. Service de communication: +41 58 462 31 53 Tél. Service de presse: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <attachment id="132383">
        <title>Accord (Ce texte est une version provisoire. Seule la version qui sera publiée dans la Feuille fédérale fait foi.)</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>19</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/38057.pdf</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </attachment>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Conclusione di un accordo con il WEF</title>
      <lead>Il capo del DFAE Didier Burkhalter ha incontrato il presidente del consiglio di fondazione del WEF Klaus Schwab a margine del vertice annuale del Forum economico mondiale (World Economic Forum, WEF) a Davos. Durante l’incontro è stato firmato un accordo sullo statuto del WEF in Svizzera. </lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Il 23 gennaio 2015 si è svolto un incontro tra il capo del Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri (DFAE), consigliere federale Didier Burkhalter, e il presidente del consiglio di fondazione del WEF, Klaus Schwab, a margine del vertice annuale del Forum a Davos. In quest’occasione è stato sottoscritto un accordo che conferma lo statuto della Fondazione World Economic Forum in Svizzera conformemente alla legge del 22 giugno 2007 sullo Stato ospite (LSO, RS 192.12). &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Nella sua seduta del 17 dicembre 2014, il Consiglio federale ha riconosciuto il WEF come «altro organismo internazionale» ai sensi della legge sullo Stato ospite e ha approvato questo accordo, che conferma lo statuto di cui la Fondazione World Economic Forum gode in Svizzera. L’accordo si basa sull’importante ruolo del WEF per la Svizzera e prevede un rafforzamento della cooperazione tra la Confederazione e il WEF nel suo ambito di attività. Il contenuto dell’accordo si inserisce nel quadro di quelli conclusi dal Consiglio federale con altre organizzazioni dello stesso tipo e prevede, per esempio, facilitazioni a livello di reclutamento del personale. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Dalla sua fondazione nel 1971 il WEF ha notevolmente sviluppato le proprie attività e ha assunto, soprattutto grazie alla sua riunione annuale a Davos, una dimensione mondiale, ottenendo un ampio riconoscimento tra gli Stati e le organizzazioni internazionali. &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Comunicazione DFAE Palazzo federale ovest CH-3003 Berna Tel. Servizio di comunicazione: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Servizio stampa: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <attachment id="132384">
        <title>Accordo (Questo testo è una versione provvisoria. Fa stato la versione pubblicata nel Foglio federale.)</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>18</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/38058.pdf</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </attachment>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Agreement signed with the WEF</title>
      <lead>A meeting took place on the margins of the annual meeting of the World Economic Forum (WEF) in Davos between the head of the Federal Department of Foreign Affairs (FDFA), Didier Burkhalter, and the executive chairman of the WEF, Klaus Schwab, at which an agreement was signed on the status of the WEF in Switzerland. </lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;On 23 January 2015, a meeting took place between the head of the FDFA, Didier Burkhalter, and the executive chairman of the WEF, Klaus Schwab, on the margins of the annual meeting of the WEF in Davos at which an agreement was signed confirming the status of the WEF in Switzerland in compliance with the Host State Act of 22 June 2007 (HSA, SR 192.12). &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;At its meeting on 17 December 2014, the Federal Council recognised the WEF as an "other international body" as defined in the Host State Act and approved the agreement, the purpose of which is to confirm the status of foundation that the World Economic Forum enjoys in Switzerland. This status is based on the WEF's important role for Switzerland, and provides for closer cooperation between the Swiss Confederation and the WEF in its field of activity. The substance of the agreement corresponds to agreements that the Federal Council has already concluded with other organisations of this kind and provides, for example, for facilities in the recruitment of personnel. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Since its foundation in 1971, the WEF has considerably developed its activities and, in particular through its annual meeting in Davos, has attained a global dimension and gained wide recognition among states and international organisations. &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>FDFA Communication Federal Palace West Wing CH-3003 Bern, Switzerland Tel. Communication service: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Press service: +41 58 460 55 55 E-mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @SwissMFA</contact>
      <attachment id="132385">
        <title>Agreement (This text is provisional. Only the version published in the Federal Gazette is binding.) (de)</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>20</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/38059.pdf</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </attachment>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
