<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="33653" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2010-06-11</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="201" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>201</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="yes" id="702" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>701</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Generalsekretariat WBF</name>
      <name lang="fr">Secrétariat général DEFR</name>
      <name lang="it">Segreteria generale DEFR</name>
      <name lang="en">Secretariat-General EAER</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="201">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <department id="701">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Wirtschaft, Bildung und Forschung</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'économie, de la formation et de la recherche</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'economia, della formazione e della ricerca</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Economic Affairs, Education and Research</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Joseph Deiss ist Präsident der 65. Session der UNO-Generalversammlung</title>
      <lead>Die UNO-Generalversammlung hat am Freitag in New York Joseph Deiss per Akklamation zum Präsidenten der 65. Session der UNO-Generalversammlung gewählt. Bundespräsidentin Doris Leuthard gratulierte Joseph Deiss schriftlich im Namen des Bundesrats und bezeichnete die Wahl als grosse Ehre für die Schweiz. Bundesrätin Micheline Calmy-Rey sprach in New York von einem wichtigen Zeichen internationaler Anerkennung für das schweizerische Engagement in der UNO.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;„Im Namen des Bundesrats gratuliere ich herzlich zur erfolgreichen Wahl“ erklärte Bundespräsidentin Doris Leuthard in ihrem Schreiben an Alt-Bundesrat Joseph Deiss. „Diese Wahl stellt für die Schweiz eine grosse Ehre dar und bedeutet auch eine Wertschätzung Ihres persönlichen Engagements, das zum UNO-Beitritt unseres Landes im Jahr 2002 geführt hat.“&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Micheline Calmy-Rey, die Vorsteherin des Eidgenössischen Departements für auswärtige Angelegenheiten EDA, betonte ihrerseits in New York: „Diese Wahl nur acht Jahre nach dem UNO-Beitritt der Schweiz 2002 ist eine internationale Anerkennung für den aktiven Einsatz der Schweiz bei der Förderung von Sicherheit und Frieden im Rahmen der internationalen Gemeinschaft“.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Bei der Präsidentschaft der UNO-Generalversammlung, dem wichtigsten Gremium der UNO neben dem Sicherheitsrat, handelt es sich um ein anspruchsvolles und prestigeträchtiges Amt. Die westliche Regionalgruppe (WEOG) stellt turnusgemäss den Präsidenten der 65. Session der UNO-Generalversammlung und hatte im vergangenen Dezember in New York Joseph Deiss zu ihrem offiziellen Kandidaten bestimmt. Joseph Deiss hatte sich in der WEOG-internen Ausscheidung gegen den ehemaligen belgischen Aussenminister und ehemaligen EU-Kommissar Louis Michel durchgesetzt.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Joseph Deiss tritt sein Amt am 14. September 2010 an. Ein erster Höhepunkt seiner einjährigen Amtszeit ist die Leitung eines hochrangigen Treffens der Generalversammlung zu den Millenniums-Entwicklungszielen vom 20.-22. September. Am 23. September wird Joseph Deiss auch die jährliche Generaldebatte eröffnen. Zahlreiche Staats- und Regierungschefs werden an diesen Anlässen teilnehmen.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Die Aufgabe des Präsidenten der Generalversammlung besteht darin, für einen korrekten und geordneten Ablauf der Sitzungen dieses Organs zu sorgen. Er kann zudem Einfluss auf die Agenda nehmen. Zudem kommt ihm die Rolle eines Fazilitators zu, welcher bei unterschiedlichen Positionen unter den UNO-Mitgliedstaaten einen Konsens herbeizuführen sucht.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Joseph Deiss war 2004 Bundespräsident. Als Vorsteher des EDA von 1999 bis 2002 war er federführend am Beitritt der Schweiz zur UNO beteiligt. 2003 übernahm er das Eidgenössische Volkswirtschaftsdepartement, welches er bis zu seinem Rücktritt 2006 leitete.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Für weitere Auskünfte:&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Adrian Sollberger, Mediensprecher EDA, +41 79 301 62 84&lt;br /&gt; Johann Aeschlimann, Botschaftsrat, Mission der Schweiz bei der UNO, +1 917 757 33 89&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Information EDA Bundeshaus West CH-3003 Bern Tel.: +41 (0)31 322 31 53 Fax: +41 (0)31 324 90 47 E-Mail: info@eda.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="70704">
        <title>Die Schweiz und die Vereinten Nationen</title>
        <uri>http://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home/topics/intorg/un.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Election de Joseph Deiss à la présidence de la 65e session de l’Assemblée générale de l’ONU</title>
      <lead>Vendredi, à New York, l’Assemblée générale des Nations Unies a élu par acclamation Joseph Deiss à la présidence de sa 65e session. La Présidente de la Confédération Doris Leuthard a félicité dans une lettre M. Deiss au nom du Conseil fédéral et qualifié son élection de grand honneur pour la Suisse. Présente à New York à cette occasion, la Conseillère fédérale Micheline Calmy-Rey a déclaré que l’élection de Joseph Deiss était un signe important de la reconnaissance internationale de l’engagement de la Suisse à l’ONU.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;«Je tiens, au nom du Conseil fédéral, à vous féliciter chaleureusement de votre brillante élection», a déclaré la Présidente de la Confédération Doris Leuthard dans une lettre adressée à l’ancien conseiller fédéral Joseph Deiss. Et d’ajouter&amp;nbsp;: «Cette élection est pour la Suisse un grand honneur et témoigne de l’estime portée à votre engagement personnel, qui fut déterminant dans le processus d’adhésion de la Suisse à l’ONU en 2002».&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Présente à New York, la Cheffe du Département fédéral des affaires étrangères (DFAE) Micheline Calmy-Rey a déclaré que cette élection, huit ans seulement après l’adhésion de la Suisse à l’ONU, traduisait la reconnaissance internationale de l’engagement actif de notre pays en faveur de la promotion de la sécurité et de la paix dans la communauté internationale.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;La fonction de président de l’Assemblée générale de l’ONU, organe majeur des Nations Unies au même titre que le Conseil de sécurité, est une fonction à la fois exigeante et prestigieuse. En décembre dernier, à New York, le groupe des Etats d’Europe occidentale et autres (GEOA), à qui revient cette année la présidence de la 65e session de l’Assemblée générale des Nations Unies, avait choisi comme candidat officiel l’ancien conseiller fédéral Joseph Deiss. Lors de la procédure de sélection au sein du GEOA, Joseph Deiss avait réussi à s’imposer face à l’autre candidat, Louis Michel, ancien ministre des affaires étrangères belge et ancien commissaire européen.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Joseph Deiss prendra ses fonctions le 14 septembre 2010 et occupera ce poste pendant un an. Premier moment fort de son mandat, M.&amp;nbsp;Deiss dirigera, du 20 au 22 septembre, une réunion plénière de haut niveau de l’Assemblée générale consacrée aux objectifs du Millénaire pour le développement. Le 23 septembre, Joseph Deiss ouvrira le débat général annuel. De nombreux chefs d’Etat et de gouvernement participeront à ces événements.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Le président de l’Assemblée générale a pour tâche de veiller au déroulement correct et efficace des réunions de l’Assemblée générale et peut exercer une influence sur la définition de l’agenda. Appelé en outre à jouer un rôle de facilitateur, le président doit s’efforcer de trouver un consensus entre les pays membres ayant des vues divergentes.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Joseph Deiss a été président de la Confédération en 2004. Chef du DFAE de 1999 à fin 2002, il a conduit le processus d’adhésion de la Suisse à l’ONU. Il a repris le Département fédéral de l’économie en 2003 avant de se retirer en 2006.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Pour d’autres informations&amp;nbsp;:&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Adrian Sollberger, porte-parole DFAE, +41 79 301 62 84&lt;br /&gt; Johann Aeschlimann,&amp;nbsp;Conseiller d’ambassade, Mission permanente de la Suisse auprès de l’ONU, +1 917 757 33 89&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Information DFAE Palais fédéral ouest CH-3003 Berne Tél.: (+41) 031 322 31 53 Fax: (+41) 031 324 90 47 E-Mail: info@eda.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="70705">
        <title>La Suisse et les Nations Unies</title>
        <uri>http://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/home/topics/intorg/un.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Joseph Deiss è presidente della 65a sessione dell’Assemblea generale dell’ONU</title>
      <lead>Venerdì a New York l’Assemblea generale dell’ONU ha eletto per acclamazione il già consigliere federale Joseph Deiss a presidente della 65a sessione dell’Assemblea generale dell’ONU. La presidente della Confederazione Doris Leuthard ha inviato a Joseph Deiss le sue congratulazioni scritte a nome del Consiglio federale e ha definito l’elezione “un grande onore per la Svizzera”. La consigliera federale Micheline Calmy-Rey, attualmente a New York, ha parlato di un segno di riconoscimento importante a livello internazionale dell’impegno profuso dalla Svizzera in seno all’ONU.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;“A nome del Consiglio federale porgo le mie più vive congratulazioni per la brillante elezione”, ha dichiarato la presidente della Confederazione Doris Leuthard nella sua lettera al già consigliere federale Joseph Deiss. “Questa elezione è un grande onore per la Svizzera e testimonia l’alta considerazione riservata al Suo impegno personale che ha portato all’adesione del nostro Paese all’ONU nel 2002”.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Micheline Calmy-Rey, capo del Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri DFAE, attualmente a New York, ha sottolineato da parte sua che “l’elezione a soli otto anni dall’entrata della Svizzera nell’ONU nel 2002 rappresenta un riconoscimento internazionale dell’impegno profuso dalla Svizzera per la promozione della sicurezza e della pace nella comunità internazionale.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;La presidenza dell’Assemblea generale dell’ONU, l’organo più importante delle Nazioni Unite accanto al Consiglio di sicurezza, è un incarico prestigioso e impegnativo. Il gruppo regionale occidentale (WEOG), incaricato per turno di nominare il presidente della 65a sessione dell’Assemblea generale della Nazioni Unite, ha designato lo scorso dicembre a New York il già consigliere federale Joseph Deiss quale proprio candidato ufficiale. Nella votazione interna al WEOG Joseph Deiss ha prevalso sul già ministro degli esteri belga e commissario europeo Louis Michel.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Joseph Deiss entrerà in carica il 14 settembre 2010. Uno dei primi compiti del suo mandato annuale sarà di presiedere, dal 20 al 22 settembre, l’importante incontro dell’Assemblea generale sugli obiettivi di sviluppo del Millennio. Il 23 settembre darà inoltre il via all’annuale dibattito generale. Numerosi capi di Stato e di governo parteciperanno ai suddetti eventi.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Il presidente dell’Assemblea generale ha il compito di garantire uno svolgimento corretto e ordinato delle sedute. Egli può inoltre proporre punti da trattare e svolge il ruolo di facilitatore, provvedendo, in caso di posizioni divergenti, a creare un consenso tra gli Stati membri dell’Assemblea.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Joseph Deiss è stato presidente della Confederazione nel 2004. In qualità di capo del Dipartimento degli affari esteri dal 1999 al 2002 ha partecipato attivamente, come responsabile in carica, all’adesione della Svizzera all’ONU. Nel 2003 ha assunto la direzione del DFE, funzione che ha mantenuto fino al suo ritiro nel 2006.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Per ulteriori informazioni:&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Adrian Sollberger, portavoce DFAE, +41 79 301 62 84&lt;br /&gt; Johann Aeschlimann, Consigliere d'Ambasciata, Missione permanente della Svizzera presso le Nazioni Unite, +1 917 757 33 89&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Informazione DFAE Palazzo federale ovest CH-3003 Berna Tel.: (+41) 031 322 31 53 Fax: (+41) 031 324 90 47 E-Mail: info@eda.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="70706">
        <title>La Svizzera e le Nazioni Unite</title>
        <uri>http://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/home/topics/intorg/un.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Joseph Deiss elected President of the 65th Session of the UN General Assembly</title>
      <lead>Today in New York, the United Nations General Assembly has elected by acclamation Joseph Deiss to the office of President of the 65th Session of the General Assembly. The President of the Swiss Confederation, Doris Leuthard, has congratulated Joseph Deiss in writing on behalf of the Federal Council, welcoming the election as a great honour for Switzerland. Federal Councillor Micheline Calmy-Rey, speaking in New York, regards the election as a strong signal of the international community’s recognition of Switzerland’s commitment to the United Nations.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;“On behalf of the Federal Council I congratulate you most sincerely on your election to the presidency of the 65th session of the UN General Assembly,” wrote the President of the Confederation, Doris Leuthard, in her letter to former Federal Councillor Joseph Deiss. She went on to say: “Your election is a great honour for Switzerland and an expression of appreciation of the personal commitment you showed by leading our country to UN membership&amp;nbsp; in 2002.” &amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The head of the Federal Department of Foreign Affairs, Micheline Calmy-Rey, speaking in New York, declared: “This election, coming only eight years after Switzerland joined the UN in 2002, is recognition by the international community of Switzerland’s active commitment to the promotion of peace and security in the international community”. &amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The presidency of the General Assembly, which together with the Security Council are the two most important bodies of the United Nations, is a demanding and prestigious office. Within the General Assembly it was the turn of the Western European and Others Group (WEOG) to occupy the post of president of the 65th Session of the General Assembly. It elected Joseph Deiss as its official candidate last December in New York. Joseph Deiss was competing for the nomination against the former Belgian foreign minister and EU commissioner, Louis Michel, in the WEOG internal election process.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Mr Deiss will take up his functions on 14 September 2010. One of the first highlights of his one-year term in office will be to chair the Summit on the Millennium Development Goals which takes place on 20-22 September 2010. On 23 September, he will open the Annual General Debate. Many heads of state and government will take part in these events.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The president of the General Assembly is responsible for ensuring that its meetings run correctly and in an orderly fashion. He can exercise an influence on the General Assembly’s agenda. In addition, in the event of diverging views among the member states, he assumes the role of facilitator in the search for a consensus position.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Joseph Deiss was President of the Swiss Confederation in 2004. As head of the Federal Department of Foreign Affairs, he led the campaign for Switzerland’s membership of the United Nations. He subsequently went on to head the Federal Department of Economic Affairs from 2003 until his retirement in 2006.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;For further information:&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Adrian Sollberger, media spokesman FDFA, +41 79 301 62 84&lt;br /&gt; Johann Aeschlimann, Counsellor, Permanent Mission of Switzerland to the United Nations, +1 917 757 33 89&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Information FDFA Bundeshaus West CH-3003 Bern Tel.: (+41) 031 322 31 53 Fax: (+41) 031 324 90 47 E-Mail: info@eda.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="70707">
        <title>Switzerland and the United Nations</title>
        <uri>http://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home/topics/intorg/un.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
