<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="100193" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2024-02-26</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="201" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>201</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="201">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Bundesrat Ignazio Cassis empfängt den Aussenminister von Laos</title>
      <lead>Bundesrat Ignazio Cassis hat am 26. Februar 2024 in Bern den Vizepremierminister und Aussenminister der Demokratischen Volksrepublik Laos, Saleumxay Kommasith, zu einem offiziellen Arbeitsbesuch empfangen. Bei den Gesprächen ging es vor allem um die Weiterentwicklung der bilateralen Beziehungen, die Partnerschaft der Schweiz mit dem Verband Südostasiatischer Nationen (ASEAN) und die geopolitische Lage. </lead>
      <text link="no">Die politischen, wirtschaftlichen und konsularischen Beziehungen zwischen der Schweiz und der Demokratischen Volksrepublik Laos wurden in den letzten Jahren intensiviert. 2021 wurde in Vientiane eine Konsularagentur und 2022 in Luang Prabang ein Honorarkonsulat eröffnet. Bei ihrem Treffen in Bern begrüssten Ignazio Cassis und Saleumxay Kommasith diese Entwicklungen. Sie stehen in Einklang mit der Südostasien-Strategie 2023–2026 des Bundesrats, welche vorsieht, dass die Schweiz ihre Beziehungen zu den Ländern dieser Region weiter festigt und vertieft. Diese Dynamik wurde bereits bei den Feierlichkeiten zum 60-jährigen Bestehen der diplomatischen Beziehungen zwischen den beiden Ländern im Jahr 2023 in Vientiane hervorgehoben.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Die Teilnahme der Schweiz an verschiedenen hochrangigen Treffen der ASEAN, deren Vorsitz Laos in diesem Jahr innehat, war ebenfalls Gegenstand der Gespräche. Die Schweiz und die ASEAN, die als wichtigste internationale Organisation im asiatisch-pazifischen Raum gilt, pflegen seit 2016 eine sektorielle Dialogpartnerschaft, dank der die Schweiz ihre Interessen in Südostasien vermehrt auch auf multilateraler Ebene einbringen kann.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;b&gt;Internationale Zusammenarbeit: die Schweiz engagiert sich seit fast 30 Jahren in Laos &lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Die beiden Aussenminister sprachen auch über die Entwicklungszusammenarbeit. Die Schweiz unterstützt Laos seit 1995 im Rahmen ihres Regionalprogramms für die Mekong-Region. Die drei Hauptbereiche des Programms sind: Klimawandel und Bewirtschaftung der natürlichen Ressourcen, inklusive Wirtschaftsentwicklung sowie Gouvernanz und Bürgerbeteiligung. Konkret unterstützt die Schweiz beispielsweise Initiativen in den Bereichen grenzüberschreitendes Wassermanagement, Staudammsicherheit oder Berufsbildung im Tourismussektor. Im Zeitraum 2022–2025 unterstützt die Schweiz die Mekong-Region mit rund 140 Millionen Franken, wovon 60 Millionen für Laos vorgesehen sind. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Ignazio Cassis und Saleumxay Kommasith tauschten sich ausserdem über die aktuelle geopolitische Lage aus, insbesondere in Myanmar und im Nahen Osten. Auch mögliche Ansätze für einen dauerhaften Frieden in der Ukraine wurden erörtert. Nach seinem Besuch in Bern wird der laotische Vizepremierminister an der 55. Sitzung des UNO-Menschenrechtsrats in Genf teilnehmen, die Bundesrat Ignazio Cassis heute eröffnet hat. &lt;br /&gt;</text>
      <contact>Kommunikation EDA Bundeshaus West CH-3003 Bern Tel. Medienstelle: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <link id="271017">
        <title>Bilaterale Beziehungen Schweiz–Laos</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/countries/laos/de/home/bilaterale-beziehungen/in-kuerze.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="271021">
        <title>Südostasien Strategie 2023–2026</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/publikationen/de/eda/schweizer-aussenpolitik/suedostasien-strategie-2023-2026.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Le conseiller fédéral Ignazio Cassis rencontre le ministre laotien des affaires étrangères</title>
      <lead>Le conseiller fédéral Ignazio Cassis a reçu le 26 février à Berne le vice-premier ministre et ministre des affaires étrangères de la République démocratique populaire lao Saleumxay Kommasith pour une visite officielle de travail. Les discussions ont principalement porté sur le développement des relations bilatérales, le partenariat de la Suisse avec l’Association des Nations d’Asie du Sud-Est (ASEAN) et la situation géopolitique. </lead>
      <text link="no">Les liens politiques, économiques et consulaires entre la Suisse et la République démocratique populaire lao se sont renforcés ces dernières années, à l’image notamment de l’ouverture d’une agence consulaire à Vientiane en 2021 et d’un consulat honoraire à Luang Prabang en 2022. Lors de leur rencontre à Berne, Ignazio Cassis et Saleumxay Kommasith ont salué ces développements. Cette dynamique s’inscrit également dans les objectifs de la stratégie 2023-2026 du Conseil fédéral pour l’Asie du Sud-Est qui vise à consolider et à approfondir les relations de la Suisse avec les pays de cette région. Elle avait par ailleurs été mise en exergue lors des célébrations des 60 ans des relations diplomatiques entre les deux pays en 2023, à Vientiane.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;La participation de la Suisse à diverses rencontres de haut-niveau organisées par l’ASEAN, dont le Laos assure cette année la présidence, a également été au centre des échanges. La Suisse et l’ASEAN, considérée comme l’organisation internationale la plus importante de la région Asie-Pacifique, entretiennent depuis 2016 un partenariat de dialogue sectoriel. Ce dernier permet à la Suisse de faire davantage valoir ses intérêts en Asie du Sud-Est au niveau multilatéral.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;b&gt;Coopération internationale: la Suisse engagée au Laos depuis près de 30 ans &lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Les discussions ont aussi porté sur la coopération au développement. La Suisse est engagée au Laos depuis 1995 à travers son programme régional consacré à la région du Mékong. Et ce dans trois domaines principaux: changement climatique et gestion des ressources naturelles, développement économique inclusif ainsi que gouvernance et participation citoyenne. Concrètement, la Suisse soutient par exemple des initiatives dans le domaine de la gestion des eaux transfrontalières, de la sécurité des barrages hydroélectriques ou encore de la formation professionnelle dans le secteur du tourisme. Le soutien suisse pour la région du Mékong s’élève à environ 140 millions de CHF, dont 60 millions alloués au Laos, pour la période 2022-2025. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Ignazio Cassis et Saleumxay Kommasith ont en outre échangé sur la situation géopolitique actuelle, notamment au Myanmar et au Proche-Orient. Les voies possibles d’une paix durable en Ukraine ont également été évoquées. Après sa visite à Berne, le vice-premier ministre participera à la 55ème session du Conseil des droits de l’homme à Genève, ouverte aujourd’hui par le conseiller fédéral Ignazio Cassis. </text>
      <contact>Communication DFAE Palais fédéral ouest CH-3003 Berne Tél. Service de presse: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <link id="271018">
        <title>Relations bilatérales Suisse–Laos</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/countries/laos/fr/home/relations-bilaterales/bilaterale.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="271022">
        <title>Stratégie Asie du Sud-Est 2023-2026</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/publikationen/fr/eda/schweizer-aussenpolitik/suedostasien-strategie-2023-2026.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Il consigliere federale Ignazio Cassis incontra il ministro degli esteri del Laos</title>
      <lead>Il 26 febbraio il consigliere federale Ignazio Cassis ha ricevuto a Berna il vice primo ministro e ministro degli esteri della Repubblica democratica popolare del Laos Saleumxay Kommasith per una visita ufficiale di lavoro. Le discussioni si sono concentrate sullo sviluppo delle relazioni bilaterali, sul partenariato della Svizzera con l’Associazione delle Nazioni del Sud-Est asiatico (ASEAN) e sulla situazione geopolitica. </lead>
      <text link="no">I legami politici, economici e consolari tra la Svizzera e la Repubblica democratica popolare del Laos si sono rafforzati negli ultimi anni, in particolare con l’apertura di un’agenzia consolare a Vientiane nel 2021 e di un consolato onorario a Luang Prabang nel 2022. Durante l’incontro a Berna, Ignazio Cassis e Saleumxay Kommasith hanno sottolineato questi sviluppi positivi, messi in evidenza anche durante i festeggiamenti per i 60 anni di relazioni diplomatiche tra i due Paesi nel 2023 a Vientiane. Questa dinamica è anche in linea con gli obiettivi della Strategia Sud-Est asiatico 2023–2026 del Consiglio federale, che mira a consolidare e approfondire le relazioni della Svizzera con i Paesi di questa regione. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;I colloqui si sono concentrati anche sulla partecipazione della Svizzera a diversi incontri di alto livello organizzati dall’ASEAN, di cui quest’anno il Laos detiene la presidenza. La Svizzera e l’ASEAN, considerata la più importante organizzazione internazionale della regione Asia-Pacifico, intrattengono dal 2016 un partenariato di dialogo settoriale che consente alla Svizzera di far valere maggiormente i propri interessi nel Sud-Est asiatico a livello multilaterale.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;b&gt;Cooperazione internazionale: impegno svizzero in Laos da quasi 30 anni &lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;I colloqui si sono concentrati anche sulla cooperazione allo sviluppo. La Svizzera è presente in Laos dal 1995 con il suo programma regionale dedicato alla regione del Mekong, in particolare in tre settori principali: cambiamento climatico e gestione delle risorse naturali, sviluppo economico inclusivo nonché buongoverno e partecipazione dei cittadini. Concretamente, la Svizzera sostiene per esempio iniziative nell’ambito della gestione delle acque transfrontaliere, della sicurezza delle dighe delle centrali idroelettriche e della formazione professionale nel settore del turismo. Il sostegno svizzero alla regione del Mekong ammonta per il periodo 2022-2025 a circa 140 milioni di franchi, di cui 60 milioni destinati al Laos. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Ignazio Cassis e Saleumxay Kommasith hanno inoltre parlato della situazione geopolitica attuale, in particolare in Myanmar e in Medio Oriente. Sono state menzionate anche le possibili vie da seguire per giungere a una pace duratura in Ucraina. Dopo la visita a Berna, il vice primo ministro parteciperà alla 55a sessione del Consiglio dei diritti umani a Ginevra, aperta oggi dal consigliere federale Ignazio Cassis. </text>
      <contact>Comunicazione DFAE Palazzo federale ovest CH-3003 Berna Tel. Servizio stampa: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <link id="271019">
        <title>Relazioni bilaterali Svizzera–Laos</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/countries/laos/it/home/la-svizzera-e/relazioni-bilaterali.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="271023">
        <title>Strategia Sud-Est asiatico 2023-2026</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/publikationen/it/eda/schweizer-aussenpolitik/suedostasien-strategie-2023-2026.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Federal Councillor Ignazio Cassis meets Laotian Foreign Minister</title>
      <lead>On 26 February, Federal Councillor Ignazio Cassis received the Deputy Prime Minister and Minister of Foreign Affairs of the Lao People's Democratic Republic, Mr Saleumxay Kommasith, in Bern for an official working visit. Discussions focused on the development of bilateral relations, Switzerland's partnership with the Association of Southeast Asian Nations (ASEAN) and the geopolitical situation. </lead>
      <text link="no">Political, economic and consular ties between Switzerland and the Lao People’s Democratic Republic have been strengthened in recent years, with the opening of a consular agency in Vientiane in 2021 and an honorary consulate in Luang Prabang in 2022. At their meeting in Bern, Mr Cassis and Mr Kommasith welcomed these developments. This dynamic is in keeping with the objectives of the Federal Council's South East Asia Strategy 2023–26, which aims to consolidate and deepen Switzerland's relations with the countries in this region. It was also highlighted during the celebrations to mark 60 years of diplomatic relations between the two countries in 2023, in Vientiane. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Switzerland's participation in various high-level meetings organised by ASEAN, of which Laos holds the chairmanship this year, was also at the heart of discussions. Switzerland and ASEAN, considered to be the most important international organisation in the Asia–Pacific region, have maintained a sectoral dialogue partnership since 2016. This enables Switzerland to assert its interests in South East Asia more effectively at the multilateral level. &lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;b&gt;International cooperation: Switzerland active in Laos for almost 30 years &lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Discussions also focused on development cooperation. Switzerland has been present in Laos since 1995 as part of its regional programme devoted to the Mekong. It has been active in three main areas: climate change and natural resource management, inclusive economic development, and governance and civic engagement. In concrete terms, Switzerland supports initiatives in cross-border water management, hydroelectric dam safety, and vocational training in the tourism sector. Swiss support for the Mekong region amounts to around CHF 140 million, including CHF 60 million allocated to Laos, for the 2022–25 period. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Mr Cassis and Mr Kommasith touched upon the current geopolitical situation, particularly in Myanmar and the Middle East. Possible avenues for lasting peace in Ukraine were also discussed. Following his visit to Bern, Mr Kommasith will take part in the 55th session of the Human Rights Council in Geneva, which was opened today by Mr Cassis. &lt;br /&gt;</text>
      <contact>FDFA Communication Federal Palace West Wing CH-3003 Bern, Switzerland Tel. Press service: +41 58 460 55 55 E-mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @SwissMFA</contact>
      <link id="271020">
        <title>Bilateral relations Switzerland–Laos</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/countries/laos/en/home/switzerland-and/bilateral-relations.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="271024">
        <title>South East Asia Strategy 2023-2026</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/publikationen/en/eda/schweizer-aussenpolitik/suedostasien-strategie-2023-2026.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
