<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="99957" revoked="no">
    <version>2</version>
    <pubdate>2024-02-06</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="yes" id="502" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>501</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Generalsekretariat VBS</name>
      <name lang="fr">Secrétariat général du DDPS</name>
      <name lang="it">Segreteria generale del DDPS</name>
      <name lang="en">General Secretariat DDPS</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.vbs.admin.ch/</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.vbs.admin.ch/</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.vbs.admin.ch/</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.vbs.admin.ch/</www>
      <email lang="de">postmaster.vbs@gs-vbs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">postmaster.vbs@gs-vbs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">postmaster.vbs@gs-vbs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">postmaster.vbs@gs-vbs.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="505" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>501</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Gruppe Verteidigung</name>
      <name lang="fr">Groupement de la Défense</name>
      <name lang="it">Aggruppamento Difesa</name>
      <name lang="en">Defence</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.vtg.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.vtg.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.vtg.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.vtg.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@vtg.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@vtg.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@vtg.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@vtg.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="501">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Verteidigung, Bevölkerungsschutz und Sport</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de la défense, de la protection de la population et des sports</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale della difesa, della protezione della popolazione e dello sport</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Defence, Civil Protection and Sports DDPS</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.vbs.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.vbs.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.vbs.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.vbs.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@gs-vbs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@gs-vbs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@gs-vbs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@gs-vbs.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Bundespräsidentin trifft Präsidenten und Premierministerin von Estland</title>
      <lead>Bundespräsidentin Viola Amherd ist am Dienstag, 6. Februar 2024, in der estnischen Hauptstadt Tallinn mit Präsident Alar Karis, Premierministerin Kaja Kallas und Verteidigungsminister Hanno Pevkur zusammengekommen. Zentrale Gesprächsthemen waren die Europapolitik und die Sicherheitslage. Mit Blick auf die Zusammenarbeit in Fragen der Cyberabwehr stand auch ein Besuch des Cyberverteidigungszentrums auf dem Programm.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Beide Seiten würdigten die ausgezeichneten bilateralen Beziehungen und besprachen das Programm zur Umsetzung des zweiten Schweizer Beitrags an ausgewählte EU-Staaten. In Estland werden mit 26 Millionen Franken Projekte in den Bereichen Migration/Integration und Biodiversität unterstützt. Die Kooperation in diesem Rahmen bietet die Möglichkeit, die bilateralen Kontakte weiter zu vertiefen. Der zweite Schweizer Beitrag ist Ausdruck der Rolle der Schweiz als verlässliche Partnerin für Frieden, Sicherheit, Stabilität und Wohlstand in Europa. Die Bundespräsidentin erläuterte in den Gesprächen die nächsten europapolitischen Schritte der Schweiz nach dem Entscheid des Bundesrates vom 15. Dezember 2023, den Entwurf eines Mandats für Verhandlungen mit der Europäischen Union (EU) zu verabschieden und in die Konsultation zu schicken. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Zentrale Themen waren am Dienstag die Sicherheitslage auf dem Kontinent und insbesondere der russische Angriffskrieg gegen die Ukraine. Die Bundespräsidentin bekräftigte die Solidarität der Schweiz mit der Ukraine und informierte über die laufenden Abklärungen auf dem Weg zur hochrangigen Konferenz zur Friedensformel von Präsident Selenskyi. Bundespräsidentin Amherd betonte, dass ein grosses Engagement der Weltgemeinschaft erforderlich sei, um die Grundlagen für einen umfassenden, gerechten und dauerhaften Frieden in der Ukraine zu erarbeiten. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Ebenfalls zur Sprache kamen die Lage im Nahen Osten, der Multilateralismus und dabei insbesondere die internationale Zusammenarbeit im Kampf gegen Cyberverbrechen und in der Cyberabwehr. Als weiteren Programmpunkt in Tallinn besuchte die Bundespräsidentin das «NATO Cooperative Cyber Defence Centre of Excellence». Das Cyberverteidigungszentrum unterstützt NATO-Mitglieder wie Estland und weitere Länder, zu denen auch die Schweiz gehört, mit Ausbildung, Forschung und Erfahrungsaustausch in Fragen der Cyberabwehr. Das Zentrum wurde 2008 gegründet, seit 2020 nimmt auch die Schweiz an seinen Aktivitäten teil.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Von Estland aus reist die Bundespräsidentin nach Norwegen, wo sie am Mittwoch, 7. Februar, mit Premierminister Jonas Gahr Støre zusammenkommen wird. Am Donnerstag, 8. Februar, ist in Oslo ein Treffen mit König Harald V. geplant. &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Kommunikation VBS kommunikation@gs-vbs.admin.ch +41 58 464 50 58</contact>
      <link id="270628">
        <title>Bilaterale Beziehungen Schweiz–Estland</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home/vertretungen-und-reisehinweise/estland/bilatereale-beziehungenschweizestland.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions>
        <revision date="2024-02-16 16:09" type="R"/>
      </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>La présidente de la Confédération rencontre le président et la première ministre d'Estonie</title>
      <lead>La présidente de la Confédération Viola Amherd s'est rendue le mardi 6 février 2024 à Tallinn, la capitale de l'Estonie, pour y rencontrer le président Alar Karis, la première ministre Kaja Kallas et le ministre de la défense Hanno Pevkur. La politique européenne et la situation sécuritaire ont été au cœur des discussions. Dans le cadre de la coopération en matière de cybersécurité, la présidente a également visité le centre de cyberdéfense.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Les deux parties se sont félicitées des excellentes relations bilatérales qu'elles entretiennent et ont discuté du programme de mise en œuvre de la deuxième contribution de la Suisse en faveur de certains États membres de l'Union européenne (UE). La Suisse soutient à hauteur de 26 millions de francs des projets en Estonie dans les domaines de la migration, de l'intégration et de la biodiversité. Dans ce cadre, la coopération offre l'opportunité de renforcer encore les relations bilatérales qui unissent les deux pays. La deuxième contribution de la Suisse met en évidence son rôle en tant que partenaire fiable pour la paix, la sécurité, la stabilité et la prospérité en Europe. Lors des entretiens, la présidente de la Confédération a présenté les prochaines étapes de la politique européenne de la Suisse, qui feront suite à la décision prise par le Conseil fédéral le 15 décembre 2023 d'adopter un projet de mandat de négociation avec l'UE et le mettre en consultation. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;La situation sécuritaire en Europe, et plus particulièrement la guerre d'agression de la Russie contre l'Ukraine, a constitué le thème principal de la réunion de mardi. La présidente de la Confédération a réaffirmé la solidarité de la Suisse avec l'Ukraine et a donné des informations sur les clarifications en cours concernant la préparation de la conférence au sommet sur la formule de paix du président ukrainien Volodymyr Zelensky. Viola Amherd a affirmé que la communauté internationale devait faire preuve d'un engagement fort pour jeter les bases d'une paix globale, juste et durable en Ukraine. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Les discussions ont également abordé la situation au Proche-Orient, le multilatéralisme, notamment la coopération internationale dans la lutte contre la cybercriminalité, et la cyberdéfense. À Tallinn, la présidente de la Confédération s'est également rendue au Centre d’excellence de cyberdéfense coopérative de l’OTAN. Ce centre, fondé en 2008, assiste les États membres de l’OTAN comme l’Estonie, mais aussi d’autres États dont la Suisse, en matière de formation, de recherche et de partage d'expérience sur les questions de cyberdéfense. La Suisse participe aussi à ses activités depuis 2020.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;En quittant l'Estonie, la présidente de la Confédération se rendra en Norvège pour y rencontrer le premier ministre Jonas Gahr Støre le mercredi 7 février. Le jeudi 8 février, une réunion est prévue à Oslo avec le roi Harald V.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Communication DDPS kommunikation@gs-vbs.admin.ch +41 58 464 50 58</contact>
      <link id="270629">
        <title>Relations bilatérales Suisse–Estonie</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae/representations-et-conseils-pour-les-voyages/estonie/suisse-estonie.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>La presidente della Confederazione incontra il presidente e la prima ministra dell’Estonia</title>
      <lead>Martedì 6 febbraio 2024 la presidente della Confederazione Viola Amherd ha incontrato a Tallinn il presidente estone Alar Karis, la prima ministra Kaja Kallas e il ministro della difesa Hanno Pevkur. Tra i principali temi di discussione vi erano la politica europea e questioni in materia di sicurezza. Data la collaborazione tra i due Paesi nel settore della ciberdifesa, è stata organizzata una visita al centro di eccellenza per la ciberdifesa cooperativa.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Dopo aver espresso reciproco apprezzamento per le eccellenti relazioni bilaterali, le due parti hanno discusso del piano di attuazione per il secondo contributo svizzero destinato ad alcuni Stati membri dell’UE, nell’ambito del quale la Svizzera sostiene l’Estonia con 26 milioni di franchi investiti in progetti nei settori della migrazione, dell’integrazione e della biodiversità. La cooperazione in questo ambito permette di rafforzare ulteriormente i contatti bilaterali. Con l’erogazione del secondo contributo la Svizzera intende rimarcare la sua affidabilità in qualità di partner impegnato a promuovere la pace, la sicurezza, la stabilità e la prosperità in Europa. In tema di politica europea la presidente della Confederazione ha illustrato i prossimi passi da compiere dopo la decisione adottata il 15 dicembre 2023 dal Consiglio federale di approvare e porre in consultazione il progetto di mandato negoziale con l’UE. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;I colloqui si sono concentrati anche sulla sicurezza in Europa e, in particolare, sull’attacco della Russia contro l’Ucraina. La presidente della Confederazione ha ribadito la solidarietà della Svizzera nei confronti dell’Ucraina e ha informato sui chiarimenti in corso finalizzati all’organizzazione del vertice di alto livello sul piano di pace proposto dal presidente ucraino Volodymyr Zelenskyi. Viola Amherd ha inoltre sottolineato come, per giungere a una pace giusta, durevole e globale in Ucraina, sia necessario un profondo impegno da parte dell’intera comunità internazionale. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Durante le discussioni si è anche parlato della situazione in Medio Oriente e del multilateralismo, mettendo in particolare l’accento sull’importanza della cooperazione internazionale in materia di cibercrimini e ciberdifesa. Come previsto dal programma, la presidente della Confederazione ha visitato a Tallinn il «Cooperative Cyber Defence Centre of Excellence». Fondato nel 2008, questo centro di eccellenza per la ciberdifesa cooperativa fornisce sostegno ai membri della NATO come l’Estonia e ad altri Paesi, tra cui la Svizzera, sul fronte della formazione, della ricerca e dello scambio di conoscenze in materia di ciberdifesa. Dal 2020 anche la Svizzera partecipa alle sue attività. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Al termine della sua visita in Estonia, mercoledì 7 febbraio la presidente della Confederazione si recherà in Norvegia, dove incontrerà il primo ministro Jonas Gahr Støre e l’indomani, a Oslo, Sua Maestà il Re Harald V.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Comunicazione DDPS kommunikation@gs-vbs.admin.ch +41 58 464 50 58</contact>
      <link id="270630">
        <title>Relazioni bilaterali Svizzera–Estonia</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae/rappresentanze-e-consigli-di-viaggio/estonia/svizzera-estonia.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions>
        <revision date="2024-02-16 16:09" type="R"/>
      </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>President Amherd meets President and Prime Minister of Estonia</title>
      <lead>On 6 February, President Viola Amherd met with President Alar Karis, Prime Minister Kaja Kallas and Defence Minister Hanno Pevkur in the Estonian capital of Tallinn. The main topics of discussion were European policy and the security situation. A visit to the Cyber Defence Centre was also on the agenda, with a view to cooperation on cyber defence issues.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Both sides acknowledged the excellent bilateral relations and discussed the programme to implement the second Swiss contribution to selected EU member states. In Estonia, CHF 26 million of the Swiss contribution will be used to support projects in the areas of migration/integration and biodiversity. Cooperation under this programme provides an opportunity to further intensify bilateral contacts. Switzerland’s second contribution reflects its role as a reliable partner for peace, security, stability and prosperity in Europe. During the talks, Ms Amherd outlined Switzerland’s next steps in European policy following the Federal Council’s decision on 15 December 2023 to adopt and submit for consultation a draft negotiating mandate with the European Union.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Tuesday’s main topics were the security situation on the continent and, in particular, Russia's war of aggression against Ukraine. Ms Amherd reaffirmed Switzerland’s solidarity with Ukraine and provided information on the ongoing preparations for the upcoming summit on President Zelenskyy’s peace formula. President Amherd stressed the need for a strong commitment from the international community to lay the foundations for a comprehensive, just and lasting peace in Ukraine.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The situation in the Middle East, multilateralism and, in particular, international cooperation in the fight against cyber crime and in cyber defence were also discussed. A visit to the NATO Cooperative Cyber Defence Centre of Excellence was also on Ms Amherd’s agenda in Tallinn. The Cyber Defence Centre provides training, research and knowledge sharing on cyber defence issues to NATO members such as Estonia and certain non-NATO countries, including Switzerland. The centre was founded in 2008 and Switzerland has been a contributing participant since 2020.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;From Estonia, Ms Amherd will travel to Norway, where she will meet Prime Minister Jonas Gahr Støre on 7 February. A meeting with King Harald V is scheduled for 8 February in Oslo.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>DDPS Communications kommunikation@gs-vbs.admin.ch +41 58 464 50 58</contact>
      <link id="270631">
        <title>Bilateral relations Switzerland–Estonia</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/fdfa/representations-and-travel-advice/estonia/switzerland-estonia.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <keywords>
      <keyword id="5180" org-id="502">
        <name lang="de">Armee</name>
        <name lang="fr">Armée</name>
        <name lang="it">Esercito</name>
        <name lang="en">armed forces</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="5930" org-id="502">
        <name lang="de">Internationale Beziehungen</name>
        <name lang="fr">Relations internationales</name>
        <name lang="it">Relazioni internazionali</name>
        <name lang="en">international relations</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="1011" org-id="502">
        <name lang="de">Dossier Ukraine</name>
        <name lang="fr">Dossier Ukraine</name>
        <name lang="it">Dossier Ucraina</name>
        <name lang="en">Dossier Ukraine</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="5981" org-id="502">
        <name lang="de">Departementschef</name>
        <name lang="fr">Departementschef</name>
        <name lang="it">Departementschef</name>
        <name lang="en">Departementschef</name>
      </keyword>
    </keywords>
    <topics>
      <topic id="3">
        <name lang="de">Armee</name>
        <name lang="fr">Armée</name>
        <name lang="it">Esercito</name>
        <name lang="en">Armed Forces</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="33">
        <name lang="de">Bundespräsident/-in</name>
        <name lang="fr">Président/e de la Confédération</name>
        <name lang="it">Presidente della Confederazione</name>
        <name lang="en">President of the Swiss Confederation</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="40">
        <name lang="de">Sicherheit</name>
        <name lang="fr">Sécurité</name>
        <name lang="it">Sicurezza</name>
        <name lang="en">Security</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
