<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="91557" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2022-11-15</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="201" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>201</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="201">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Bundespräsident Ignazio Cassis reist nach Malta und zum Frankophoniegipfel in Djerba</title>
      <lead>Bundespräsident Ignazio Cassis wird am 19. und 20. November 2022 am 18. Frankophoniegipfel in Djerba, Tunesien, teilnehmen. Das Thema des Gipfels lautet: «Connectivité dans la diversité: le numérique, vecteur de développement et de solidarité dans l’espace francophone» (Vernetzung in der Vielfalt: Digitalisierung als Instrument für Entwicklung und Solidarität im französischsprachigen Raum). Bundespräsident Cassis wird die Gelegenheit nutzen, um auf die zentrale Rolle des internationalen Genf im Bereich der digitalen Gouvernanz hinzuweisen. Am Vortag wird Ignazio Cassis in Malta Halt machen, wo bilaterale Gespräche und die Teilnahme an einem Gipfeltreffen zur digitalen Gouvernanz auf dem Programm stehen. </lead>
      <text link="no">In Djerba stehen die Themen Digitalisierung und Vielfalt auf der Traktandenliste der 88 Mitgliedstaaten und -regierungen der Internationalen Organisation der Frankophonie (OIF). Dieser thematische Rahmen wird es der Schweiz erlauben, auf ihre Stärken und ihr Engagement im Bereich der digitalen Gouvernanz, vor allem durch das internationale Genf, aufmerksam zu machen. Die Digitalisierung ist auch einer der vier Schwerpunkte der Aussenpolitischen Strategie 2020–2023 der Schweiz. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Im «Village de la Francophonie», am Rande des Gipfels, wird die Schweiz vier Institutionen des internationalen Genf näher vorstellen. Diese sind in den Bereichen digitale Gouvernanz und Kapazitätsaufbau (DiploFoundation), Wissenschaft und Innovation (GESDA), Gesundheit und Digitalisierung (I-DAIR) sowie Bildung und Konnektivität (GIGA) tätig. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Nachdem der Gipfel der Staats- und Regierungschefinnen und -chefs der französischsprachigen Länder, die höchste Instanz der Frankophonie, aufgrund der Covid-19-Pandemie zweimal verschoben wurde, ist er nun zurück auf der Agenda der internationalen Gemeinschaft. Der Gipfel findet alle zwei Jahre statt und hat zum Ziel, die strategische Ausrichtung der Frankophonie festzulegen und ihre Ausstrahlung in der Welt zu gewährleisten. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;b&gt;Halt in Malta: Zweiter Schweizer Beitrag und Gipfel zur digitalen Gouvernanz &lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Bevor Bundespräsident Ignazio Cassis nach Djerba reist, wird er am 18. November 2022 in Malta Halt machen, wo ein Treffen mit Aussenminister Ian Borg geplant ist. Anlässlich dieses Besuchs wird er das Abkommen über die Umsetzung des zweiten Schweizer Beitrags unterzeichnen. Mit dem zweiten Schweizer Beitrag an ausgewählte EU-Mitgliedstaaten investiert die Schweiz in Sicherheit, Stabilität und Wohlstand in Europa. In Malta wird Bundespräsident Cassis zudem am «Summit on Digital Diplomacy and Governance» teilnehmen. Der Gipfel findet aus Anlass des 20-jährigen Bestehens der DiploFoundation statt, einer schweizerisch-maltesischen Nichtregierungsorganisation, die auf den Kapazitätsaufbau im Bereich der digitalen Gouvernanz spezialisiert ist. </text>
      <contact>Kommunikation EDA Bundeshaus West CH-3003 Bern Tel. Kommunikationsservice: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Medienstelle: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <link id="238379">
        <title>Aussenpolitische Strategie 2020-2023</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home/aussenpolitik/strategien/aussenpolitischestrategie.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="238382">
        <title>Strategie Digitalaussenpolitik 2021-2024</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home/das-eda/aktuell/newsuebersicht/2020/11/digitalaussenpolitik-strategie.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="238383">
        <title>Die Schweiz in der Internationalen Organisation der Frankophonie</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home/das-eda/aktuell/newsuebersicht/2020/11/digitalaussenpolitik-strategie.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="238384">
        <title>Sommet de la Francophonie de Djerba (fr)</title>
        <uri>https://www.francophoniedjerba2022.tn/fr/lile-de-djerba-accueillera-les-19-et-20-novembre-2022-le-xviiieme-sommet-de-la-francophonie</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="238385">
        <title>Bilaterale Beziehungen Schweiz - Malta</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home/vertretungen-und-reisehinweise/malta/bilatereale-beziehungenschweizmalta.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="238386">
        <title>Schweizer Beitrag an ausgewählte EU-Mitgliedstaaten</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/schweizerbeitrag/de/home.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="238387">
        <title>DiploFoundation (eng)</title>
        <uri>https://www.diplomacy.edu/</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Le président de la Confédération Ignazio Cassis se rend à Malte et au Sommet de la Francophonie de Djerba</title>
      <lead>Le président de la Confédération Ignazio Cassis participera les 19 et 20 novembre 2022 au XVIIIe Sommet de la Francophonie, qui se tiendra à Djerba, en Tunisie. Placé sous le thème « Connectivité dans la diversité : le numérique, vecteur de développement et de solidarité dans l’espace francophone », le Sommet sera l’occasion pour le président Cassis de mettre en exergue le rôle central de la Genève internationale dans la gouvernance numérique. La veille, Ignazio Cassis fera une halte à Malte où des entretiens bilatéraux et une participation à un sommet sur la gouvernance numérique sont au programme. </lead>
      <text link="no">A Djerba, le numérique et la diversité seront au cœur des discussions des 88 Etats et gouvernements membres de l’Organisation internationale de la Francophonie (OIF). Ces thématiques permettront à la Suisse de valoriser ses atouts et son engagement en faveur de la gouvernance numérique, notamment au travers de la Genève internationale. La Suisse fait par ailleurs de la numérisation l’une des quatre priorités thématiques de sa stratégie de politique extérieure 2020–2023. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Au Village de la Francophonie, en marge du Sommet, la Suisse mettra en lumière les activités de quatre entités de la Genève internationale. Ces dernières sont actives dans le domaine de la gouvernance du numérique et du renforcement des capacités (DiploFoundation), de la science et de l’innovation (GESDA), de la santé et du numérique (I-DAIR) et de l’éducation et de la connectivité (GIGA).&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Après deux reports consécutifs dus à la pandémie de Covid-19, le Sommet des chefs d’Etats et de gouvernement, organe suprême de la Francophonie, retrouve sa place dans le calendrier des événements de la communauté internationale. Se tenant tous les deux ans, il a pour but de définir les orientations stratégiques de la Francophonie et assurer son rayonnement dans le monde. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;b&gt;Halte à Malte : 2ème contribution suisse et sommet sur la gouvernance numérique&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Avant de rejoindre Djerba, le président de la Confédération Ignazio Cassis fera escale à Malte le 18 novembre 2022 où une rencontre avec le ministre des affaires étrangères Ian Borg est prévue. A cette occasion, il signera l’accord sur la mise en œuvre de la deuxième contribution suisse. La deuxième contribution en faveur de certains États membres de l’UE permet à la Suisse de réaliser un investissement dans la sécurité, la stabilité et la prospérité en Europe. A Malte, le président Cassis participera également au Summit on Digital Diplomacy and Governance. Ce sommet marquera les 20 ans de la DiploFoundation, une organisation non gouvernementale helvético-maltaise spécialisée dans le développement des capacités dans le domaine de la gouvernance numérique. </text>
      <contact>Communication DFAE Palais fédéral ouest CH-3003 Berne Tél. Service de communication: +41 58 462 31 53 Tél. Service de presse: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <link id="238384">
        <title>Sommet de la Francophonie de Djerba (fr)</title>
        <uri>https://www.francophoniedjerba2022.tn/fr/lile-de-djerba-accueillera-les-19-et-20-novembre-2022-le-xviiieme-sommet-de-la-francophonie</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="238387">
        <title>DiploFoundation (eng)</title>
        <uri>https://www.diplomacy.edu/</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="238388">
        <title>Stratégie de politique extérieure 2020-2023</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae/politique-exterieure/mise-oeuvre-politique-exterieure/aussenpolitischestrategie.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="238389">
        <title>Stratégie de politique extérieure numérique 2021-2024</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae/dfae/aktuell/newsuebersicht/2020/11/digitalaussenpolitik-strategie.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="238390">
        <title>La Suisse au sein de l'organisation internationale de la Francophonie</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae/politique-exterieure/organisations-internationales/oif/suisse-oif.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="238391">
        <title>Relations bilatérales Suisse - Malte</title>
        <uri>https://www.dfae.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae/representations-et-conseils-pour-les-voyages/malte/suisse-malte.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="238392">
        <title>Contribution de la Suisse en faveur de certains États membres de l'UE</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/schweizerbeitrag/fr/home.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Il presidente della Confederazione Ignazio Cassis si reca a Malta e al Vertice della Francofonia di Djerba</title>
      <lead>Il 19 e il 20 novembre 2022 il presidente della Confederazione Ignazio Cassis parteciperà al 18° Vertice della Francofonia, che si terrà a Djerba, in Tunisia. All’insegna del tema «Connettività nella diversità: la digitalizzazione, vettore di sviluppo e di solidarietà nello spazio francofono», il vertice sarà l’occasione per il presidente Cassis di evidenziare il ruolo di primo piano della Ginevra internazionale nella governance digitale. Il giorno prima, Ignazio Cassis farà tappa a Malta, dove ha in programma colloqui bilaterali e la partecipazione a un summit sulla governance digitale. </lead>
      <text link="no">A Djerba, la digitalizzazione e la diversità saranno al centro delle discussioni degli 88 Stati e Governi membri dell’Organizzazione internazionale della Francofonia (OIF). Questi temi permetteranno alla Svizzera di promuovere i suoi punti di forza e il suo impegno a favore della governance digitale, soprattutto attraverso la Ginevra internazionale. Il nostro Paese ha del resto inserito la digitalizzazione tra le quattro priorità tematiche della sua Strategia di politica estera 2020–2023. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Nel Villaggio della Francofonia, ai margini del vertice, la Svizzera metterà in luce le attività di quattro entità della Ginevra internazionale attive nei seguenti ambiti: governance digitale e rafforzamento delle capacità (DiploFoundation), scienza e innovazione (GESDA), salute e digitalizzazione (I-DAIR) e formazione e connettività (GIGA).&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Dopo due rinvii consecutivi a causa della pandemia di COVID-19, il vertice dei capi di Stato e di Governo, organo supremo della Francofonia, ritorna nel calendario degli eventi della comunità internazionale. Questo appuntamento biennale ha lo scopo di definire gli orientamenti strategici della Francofonia e di darne risonanza a livello internazionale. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Sosta a Malta: secondo contributo svizzero e vertice sulla governance digitale&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Prima di raggiungere Djerba, il 18 novembre il presidente della Confederazione Ignazio Cassis farà tappa a Malta, dove è previsto un incontro con il ministro degli affari esteri Ian Borg. In tale occasione firmerà l’accordo sull’attuazione del secondo contributo svizzero a favore di alcuni Stati membri dell’UE, che permette alla Svizzera di realizzare un investimento nella sicurezza, nella stabilità e nella prosperità in Europa. A Malta il presidente Cassis parteciperà anche al «Summit on Digital Diplomacy and Governance», che segnerà il 20° anniversario della DiploFoundation, un’organizzazione svizzero-maltese specializzata nello sviluppo di capacità nel campo della governance digitale. </text>
      <contact>Comunicazione DFAE Palazzo federale ovest CH-3003 Berna Tel. Servizio di comunicazione: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Servizio stampa: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <link id="238384">
        <title>Sommet de la Francophonie de Djerba (fr)</title>
        <uri>https://www.francophoniedjerba2022.tn/fr/lile-de-djerba-accueillera-les-19-et-20-novembre-2022-le-xviiieme-sommet-de-la-francophonie</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="238387">
        <title>DiploFoundation (eng)</title>
        <uri>https://www.diplomacy.edu/</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="238393">
        <title>Strategia di politica estera 2020-2023</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae/politica-estera/attuazione-politica-estera/aussenpolitischestrategie.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="238394">
        <title>Strategia di politica estera digitale 2021–2024</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae/dfae/aktuell/newsuebersicht/2020/11/digitalaussenpolitik-strategie.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="238395">
        <title>La Svizzera nell’Organizzazione internazionale della Francofonia</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae/politica-estera/organizzazioni-internazionali/oif/la-svizzera-nell-oif.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="238396">
        <title>Relazioni bilaterali Svizzera - Malta</title>
        <uri>https://www.dfae.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae/rappresentanze-e-consigli-di-viaggio/malta/svizzera-malta.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="238397">
        <title>Contributo svizzero ad alcuni Stati membri dell’UE</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/schweizerbeitrag/it/home.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>President of Swiss Confederation Ignazio Cassis travels to Malta and Francophonie Summit in Djerba</title>
      <lead>President of the Swiss Confederation Ignazio Cassis will attend the 18th Francophonie Summit in Djerba, Tunisia, on 19–20 November 2022. The summit, to be held under the theme "Connectivity in diversity: digital technology as a vector of development and solidarity in the Francophone space", will be an opportunity for Mr Cassis to highlight International Geneva's pivotal role in digital governance. On 18 November, Mr Cassis will make a stopover in Malta to hold bilateral talks and participate in the Summit on Digital Diplomacy and Governance.</lead>
      <text link="no">Digital technology and diversity will be the main topics on the agenda of the 88 member states and governments of the International Organisation of la Francophonie (OIF) in Djerba. These topics will allow Switzerland to highlight its strengths and commitment to digital governance, particularly through International Geneva. Switzerland has also made digitalisation one of the four thematic focus areas of its Foreign Policy Strategy 2020–23. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;At the Village de la Francophonie on the margins of the summit, Switzerland will showcase the activities of four Geneva-based organisations that are active in the fields of digital governance and capacity building (DiploFoundation), science and innovation (GESDA), health and digital technology (I-DAIR), and education and connectivity (GIGA). &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Having twice been postponed because of the COVID-19 pandemic, the Summit of Heads of State and Government – the highest forum of La Francophonie – is back on the international community's events calendar. The summit, held every other year, sets the strategic direction of the Francophonie and aims to ensure its continued global influence. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;b&gt;Stopover in Malta: second Swiss contribution and Summit on Digital Diplomacy and Governance &lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;On the way to Djerba, Mr Cassis will make a stopover in Malta on 18 November 2022 to meet with Foreign Minister Ian Borg. He will also sign the agreement on the implementation of the second Swiss contribution to selected EU member states, through which Switzerland is investing in European security, stability and prosperity. In Malta, Mr Cassis will also participate in the Summit on Digital Diplomacy and Governance, marking the 20th anniversary of the DiploFoundation, a Swiss-Maltese NGO specialising in capacity development in the field of digital governance. </text>
      <contact>FDFA Communication Federal Palace West Wing CH-3003 Bern, Switzerland Tel. Communication service: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Press service: +41 58 460 55 55 E-mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @SwissMFA</contact>
      <link id="238384">
        <title>Sommet de la Francophonie de Djerba (fr)</title>
        <uri>https://www.francophoniedjerba2022.tn/fr/lile-de-djerba-accueillera-les-19-et-20-novembre-2022-le-xviiieme-sommet-de-la-francophonie</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="238387">
        <title>DiploFoundation (eng)</title>
        <uri>https://www.diplomacy.edu/</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="238398">
        <title>Foreign policy strategy 2020-2023</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/fdfa/foreign-policy/implementing-foreign-policy/aussenpolitischestrategie.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="238403">
        <title>Digital Foreign Policy Strategy 2021–2024</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/fdfa/fdfa/aktuell/newsuebersicht/2020/11/digitalaussenpolitik-strategie.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="238404">
        <title>Switzerland in the International Organization of La Francophonie</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/fdfa/foreign-policy/international-organizations/iof/switzerland-in-the-iof.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="238405">
        <title>Bilateral relations Switzerland - Malta</title>
        <uri>https://www.dfae.admin.ch/eda/en/fdfa/representations-and-travel-advice/malta/switzerland-malta.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="238406">
        <title>Swiss contribution to selected EU member states</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/schweizerbeitrag/en/home.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="8">
        <name lang="de">Bildung und Forschung</name>
        <name lang="fr">Formation et recherche</name>
        <name lang="it">Formazione e ricerca</name>
        <name lang="en">Education and Research</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="33">
        <name lang="de">Bundespräsident/-in</name>
        <name lang="fr">Président/e de la Confédération</name>
        <name lang="it">Presidente della Confederazione</name>
        <name lang="en">President of the Swiss Confederation</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="34">
        <name lang="de">Europa</name>
        <name lang="fr">Europe</name>
        <name lang="it">Europa</name>
        <name lang="en">Europe</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="45">
        <name lang="de">Technologie</name>
        <name lang="fr">Technologie</name>
        <name lang="it">Tecnologia</name>
        <name lang="en">Technology</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="47">
        <name lang="de">Wirtschaft</name>
        <name lang="fr">Économie</name>
        <name lang="it">Economia</name>
        <name lang="en">Economic Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
