<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="13326" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2007-06-27</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="608" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>601</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Bundesamt für Privatversicherungen</name>
      <name lang="fr">Office fédéral des assurances privées</name>
      <name lang="it">Ufficio federale delle assicurazioni private</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Office of Private Insurance</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.bpv.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.bpv.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.bpv.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.bpv.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@bpv.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@bpv.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@bpv.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@bpv.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="601">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Finanzdepartement</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des finances</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale delle finanze</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Finance</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.efd.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.dff.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.efd.admin.ch/efd/it/home.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.efd.admin.ch/efd/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>BPV-Entscheid zum weiteren Beteiligungserwerb der SCOR an Converium</title>
      <lead/>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Das BPV knüpft die beabsichtigte Beteiligung der französischen SCOR Gruppe an Converium Holding AG, welche zu einer indirekten Kapitalbeteiligung von mehr als 33% bzw. mehr als 50% an der Converium AG führt, an folgende Bedingungen:&lt;/p&gt; &lt;ul&gt; &lt;li&gt;Sofern die Converium Transaktionen durchzuführen beabsichtigt, welche eine Unterschreitung der Solvabilität I unter 200% zur Folge hätte, sind diese dem BPV vorzulegen.&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;Gleichzeitig sind gruppeninterne sowie auf die Kapitalausstattung bezogene Transaktionen, welche einzeln ca. 5% respektive aggregiert pro Kalenderjahr ca. 10% des Eigenkapitals ausmachen, dem BPV vorgängig zur Genehmigung zu unterbreiten.&lt;/li&gt; &lt;/ul&gt; &lt;p&gt;Das BPV anerkennt, dass die Converium AG heute über eine gute Kapitalausstattung nach Solvabilität I verfügt. Mit diesem Entscheid wird sichergestellt, dass die Substanz der Converium AG auch in Zukunft nicht geschmälert und der Versichertenschutz nicht beeinträchtigt werden.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Gemäss Artikel 21 des Versicherungsaufsichtsgesetz (VAG) sind direkte oder indirekte Beteiligungsabsichten an einem Versicherungsunternehmen mit Sitz in der Schweiz dann der Aufsichtsbehörde mitzuteilen, wenn die Beteiligung 10, 20, 33 oder 50 Prozent des Kapitals oder der Stimmrechte des anderen Unternehmens erreicht oder überschreitet. Die Aufsichtsbehörde kann eine Beteiligung untersagen oder an Bedingungen knüpfen, wenn diese nach Art und Umfang das Versicherungsunternehmen oder die Interessen der Versicherten gefährdet.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Kommunikationsdienst BPV, Tel. 031 325 01 65</contact>
      <link id="28592">
        <title>Verfügung</title>
        <uri>http://www.bpv.admin.ch/dokumentation/00548/00767/index.html?lang=de</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Décision de l'OFAP relative à l'acquisition par SCOR de nouvelles participations dans Converium</title>
      <lead/>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;L'OFAP lie la participation prévue du groupe français SCOR dans Converium Holding AG, et qui aurait pour conséquence une participation indirecte au capital de Converium AG de plus de 33%, resp. plus de 50%, aux conditions ci-dessous :&lt;/p&gt; &lt;ul&gt; &lt;li&gt;dans le cas où Converium envisage de procéder à des transactions qui amèneraient le ratio de solvabilité I au-dessous du seuil de 200%, celles-ci devront être soumises à l'OFAP;&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;dans le même temps, chaque transaction interne au groupe ou se rapportant à la dotation en capital doit être soumise à l'approbation préalable de l'OFAP si elle représente individuellement environ 5% ou, de manière agrégée, environ 10% des fonds propres par année civile.&lt;/li&gt; &lt;/ul&gt; &lt;p&gt;L'OFAP reconnaît que Converium AG dispose actuellement d'une bonne dotation en capital selon Solvabilité I. Cette décision garantit qu'à l'avenir également la substance de Converium AG ne sera pas amoindrie et que la protection des assurés ne sera pas compromise.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Selon l'article 21 de la loi sur la surveillance des assurances (LSA), les intentions de participations directes ou indirectes dans une entreprise d'assurance ayant son siège en Suisse doivent être annoncées à l'autorité de surveillance lorsque ces participations atteignent ou dépassent 10, 20, 33 ou 50% du capital ou des droits de vote de l'entreprise d'assurance. L'autorité de surveillance peut interdire une participation ou la subordonner à des conditions, lorsqu'elle risque, en raison de sa nature ou de son importance, d'être préjudiciable à l'entreprise d'assurance ou de porter atteinte aux intérêts des assurés.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Service de communication de l’OFAP, tél. 031 325 01 65</contact>
      <link id="28593">
        <title>Décision</title>
        <uri>http://www.bpv.admin.ch/dokumentation/00548/00767/index.html?lang=fr</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Decisione dell'UFAP concernente l'ulteriore acquisizione di partecipazioni di Converium da parte della SCOR</title>
      <lead/>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;L'UFAP vincola alle seguenti condizioni la prevista partecipazione del gruppo francese SCOR alla Converium Holding SA, che comporterebbe una partecipazione indiretta al capitale di Converium SA superiore al 33 per cento rispettivamente al 50 per cento:&lt;/p&gt; &lt;ul&gt; &lt;li&gt;se Converium SA intende condurre transazioni che provocano un calo della solvibilità I al di sotto del 200 per cento, le stesse devono essere sottoposte all'UFAP;&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;allo stesso tempo, le transazioni interne al gruppo e quelle riguardanti la dotazione in capitale, che singolarmente ammontano a circa il 5 per cento e, aggregate per anno civile, a circa il 10 per cento del capitale proprio, devono essere previamente sottoposte per approvazione all'UFAP.&lt;/li&gt; &lt;/ul&gt; &lt;p&gt;L'UFAP riconosce che attualmente Converium SA dispone di una buona dotazione in capitale secondo il metodo della solvibilità I. Con questa decisione si garantisce che in futuro la sostanza di Converium SA non venga erosa e che la tutela degli assicurati non ne sia pregiudicata.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Secondo l'articolo 21 della legge sulla sorveglianza degli assicuratori (LSA) chiunque intende partecipare direttamente o indirettamente a un'impresa di assicurazione con sede in Svizzera deve notificarlo all'autorità di sorveglianza se la partecipazione raggiunge o supera il 10, 20, 33 o 50 per cento del capitale o dei diritti di voto dell'impresa di assicurazione. L'autorità di sorveglianza può proibire o subordinare a condizioni una partecipazione suscettibile di pregiudicare, per il suo genere e la sua entità, l'impresa di assicurazione o gli interessi degli assicurati.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Comunicazione UFAP, tel. 031 325 01 65</contact>
      <link id="28597">
        <title>Decisione</title>
        <uri>http://www.bpv.admin.ch/dokumentation/00548/00767/index.html?lang=it</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>FOPI decision on the additional acquisition of shareholdings in Converium by SCOR</title>
      <lead/>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;FOPI has no further comments in respect of the planned holdings by the French SCOR Group in Converium Holding AG, which will lead to indirect capital holdings in Converium AG of more than 33%/50%, but is requiring the following conditions:&lt;/p&gt; &lt;ul&gt; &lt;li&gt;Should Converium plan to perform transactions that result in Solvency I dropping below 200%, such transactions must be submitted to FOPI.&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;At the same time, group-internal transactions and transactions relating to capital resources that individually account for approx. 5% or in aggregate per calendar year approx. 10% of equity capital must be submitted to FOPI for approval in advance.&lt;/li&gt; &lt;/ul&gt; &lt;p&gt;As of today FOPI recognizes that Converium AG is solidly capitalised in accordance with Solvency I requirements. With this decision, it is ensured that Converium's resources will be maintained and therefore the&amp;nbsp; insured parties interests' should remain adequately protected .&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;In accordance with Art. 21 of the Insurance Supervision Act (ISA), planned direct or indirect holdings in an insurance undertaking domiciled in Switzerland must be communicated to the supervisory authority if the holdings reach or exceed 10%, 20%, 33%, or 50% of the capital or voting rights of the other undertaking. The supervisory authority may prohibit the holdings or impose conditions, if the type and scope of the holdings endanger the insurance undertaking or the interests of insured parties.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>FOPI Communications Office, tel. 031 325 01 65</contact>
      <link id="28598">
        <title>Decree</title>
        <uri>http://www.bpv.admin.ch/dokumentation/00548/00767/index.html?lang=en</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <keywords>
      <keyword id="214" org-id="608">
        <name lang="de">Versicherungsaufsicht</name>
        <name lang="fr">Surveillance des assurances</name>
        <name lang="it">Sorveglianza delle assicurazioni</name>
        <name lang="en">Insurance supervision</name>
      </keyword>
    </keywords>
    <topics>
      <topic id="47">
        <name lang="de">Wirtschaft</name>
        <name lang="fr">Économie</name>
        <name lang="it">Economia</name>
        <name lang="en">Economic Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
