<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="52853" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2014-05-02</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="201" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>201</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="402" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>401</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Generalsekretariat EJPD</name>
      <name lang="fr">Secrétariat général DFJP</name>
      <name lang="it">Segreteria generale DFGP</name>
      <name lang="en">General Secretariat FDJP</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.ejpd.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.dfjp.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.dfgp.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.ejpd.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-ejpd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">Info@gs-ejpd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-ejpd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-ejpd.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="201">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <department id="401">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Justiz- und Polizeidepartement</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de justice et police</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale di giustizia e polizia</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Justice and Police</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.ejpd.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.ejpd.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.ejpd.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.ejpd.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-ejpd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">Info@gs-ejpd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-ejpd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-ejpd.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Offizieller Besuch des griechischen Präsidenten Karolos Papoulias in Bern</title>
      <lead>Auf Einladung der Schweiz besuchte am 2. Mai zum ersten Mal seit Aufnahme der diplomatischen Beziehungen vor 119 Jahren ein Präsident der hellenischen Republik die Schweiz. Im Zentrum der Gespräche zwischen Bundespräsident Didier Burkhalter und Präsident Karolos Papoulias standen die bilateralen Beziehungen sowie europapolitische Themen. Griechenland hat seit Anfang Jahr und noch bis Ende Juni die rotierende EU-Ratspräsidentschaft inne. Vor diesem Hintergrund erläuterte der Bundespräsident seinem Amtskollegen die vom Bundesrat geplanten nächsten Schritte in den Beziehungen Schweiz-EU. Am Treffen nahmen auch die Vizepräsidentin des Bundesrates Simonetta Sommaruga (EJPD) und der griechische Vize-Aussenminister Dimitris Kourkoulas sowie die Tourismusministerin Olga Kefalogianni teil.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Staatspräsident Karolos Papoulias wurde von Bundespräsident Didier Burkhalter, dem Vorsteher des Eidgenössischen Departements für auswärtige Angelegenheiten (EDA), auf dem Landgut Lohn bei Kehrsatz mit militärischen Ehren empfangen. Die anschliessenden Gespräche unter Teilnahme von Bundesrätin Simonetta Sommaruga, der Vorsteherin des Eidgenössischen Justiz- und Polizeidepartements (EJPD), boten Gelegenheit zur Würdigung der freundschaftlichen und traditionsreichen bilateralen Beziehungen. Die beiden Delegationen erörterten die Möglichkeiten für eine Vertiefung der Beziehungen im Bereich der Bildung und Forschung, wobei auch das 50-Jahr-Jubiläum des Beginns der Ausgrabungen in Eretria, der Schweizerischen Archäologischen Schule in Griechenland (ESAG), ein Thema war.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ebenfalls Teil der Gespräche war die Schweizerische Europapolitik. Bundespräsident Burkhalter nahm Bezug auf die aktuellen Diskussionen im Bundesrat rund um die Weiterentwicklung der bilateralen Beziehungen Schweiz-EU. Er informierte seinen Gesprächspartner über den Entscheid des Bundesrates vom 30. April 2014 bezüglich der Lösung für die kontingentierte Zulassung von kroatischen Staatsangehörigen zum Schweizer Arbeitsmarkt. Er unterstrich ausserdem, dass die verschiedenen europapolitischen Dossiers in ihrer Gesamtheit vorangetrieben und aufeinander abgestimmt werden, um das beste Ergebnis für alle Parteien zu erzielen. Griechenland hat seit Anfang Jahr während sechs Monaten die rotierende EU-Ratspräsidentschaft inne.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Daneben fanden die Finanzkrise und die Zusammenarbeit in Migrationsfragen sowie energiepolitische Aspekte wie das Erdgaspipelineprojekt Trans Adriatic Pipeline (TAP) in Griechenland Erwähnung. Ferner tauschte sich Bundespräsident Burkhalter mit seinem Gesprächspartner über das Engagement der Schweiz in den Westbalkanländern sowie über die internationale Rolle und Verantwortung Europas insbesondere vor dem Hintergrund der aktuellen Krise in der Ukraine aus. Dabei kam auch die Rolle der Organisation für Sicherheit und Zusammenarbeit in Europa (OSZE) zur Sprache, deren Vorsitz die Schweiz im laufenden Jahr innehat. Nebst den allgemeinen Prioritäten des Schweizer Vorsitzes erläuterte Bundespräsident Burkhalter seinem Amtskollegen die bezüglich der Ukraine-Krise getroffenen Massnahmen wie namentlich die Lancierung einer Beobachtermission.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Kontakte:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Information EDA&lt;br /&gt;info@eda.admin.ch&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;EJPD&lt;br /&gt;info@gs-ejpd.admin.ch &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Kommunikation EDA Bundeshaus West CH-3003 Bern Tel. Kommunikationsservice: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Medienstelle: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <link id="122025">
        <title>Anlassseite: Besuch des griechischen Präsidenten</title>
        <uri>http://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home/dfa/head/hoeven/karolo.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="122027">
        <title>Bilaterale Beziehungen Schweiz - Griechenland</title>
        <uri>http://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home/reps/eur/vgrc/bilgri.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="122029">
        <title>Schweizer OSZE-Vorsitz</title>
        <uri>http://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home/recent/osce.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="122030">
        <title>Engagement der Schweiz im Westbalkan</title>
        <uri>https://www.deza.admin.ch/de/Home/Laender/Westbalkan</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="122031">
        <title>Direktion für europäische Angelegenheiten DEA: Schweizerische Europapolitik</title>
        <uri>http://www.europa.admin.ch/</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="122032">
        <title>Feierlichkeiten 50 Jahre Schweizerische Archäologische Schule in Griechenland (en)</title>
        <uri>http://www.unil.ch/Jahia/site/esag/cache/off/pid/19190;jsessionid=45B59412D5628099FCC1EDBA7714324A.jvm1?showActu=1397548348602.xml&amp;actunilParam=news</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Visite officielle du président grec Karolos Papoulias à Berne</title>
      <lead>Le président de la République hellénique a effectué une visite officielle en Suisse le 2 mai, à l’invitation de la Suisse. Aucun président grec n’était venu en Suisse depuis l’établissement de relations diplomatiques entre les deux pays, il y a 119 ans. Les discussions entre le président de la Confédération Didier Burkhalter et le président Karolos Papoulias ont porté sur les relations bilatérales ainsi que sur des thèmes de politique européenne. La Grèce assume la présidence tournante du Conseil de l’UE depuis le début de cette année, jusqu’à fin juin. Dans ce contexte, le président de la Confédération a expliqué à son homologue les prochaines étapes prévues par le Conseil fédéral en ce qui concerne les relations Suisse-UE. La vice-présidente de la Confédération Simonetta Sommaruga (DFJP) ainsi que le vice-ministre des affaires étrangères grec Dimitris Kourkoulas et la ministre du tourisme grecque Olga Kefalogianni ont également participé aux discussions.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Le président de la Confédération Didier Burkhalter, chef du Département fédéral des affaires étrangères (DFAE), a reçu le président Karolos Papoulias au Manoir du Lohn, à Kehrsatz, avec les honneurs militaires. Les entretiens qui ont suivi, auxquels a pris part la conseillère fédérale Simonetta Sommaruga, cheffe du Département fédéral de justice et police (DFJP), ont offert l’occasion de célébrer des relations bilatérales amicales inscrites dans une longue tradition. Les deux délégations ont évoqué les possibilités d’approfondir les relations dans les domaines de l’éducation et de la recherche. Dans ce cadre, il a été question du 50e anniversaire du début des fouilles archéologiques suisses à Erétrie, qui coïncide avec le cinquantenaire de l’Ecole suisse d’archéologie en Grèce (ESAG).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;La politique européenne menée par la Suisse a également été au menu des échanges. Faisant référence aux discussions en cours au Conseil fédéral sur la poursuite des relations bilatérales entre la Suisse et l’UE, le président Burkhalter a informé son interlocuteur de la décision prise par le Conseil fédéral, le 30 avril dernier relative à l'admission de contingents de ressortissants croates sur le marché suisse de l'emploi. Il a en outre souligné la progression des négociations sur l’ensemble des dossiers de politique européenne et la coordination entre chacun d’eux dans l’optique d’un résultat optimal pour toutes les parties. La Grèce occupe depuis début 2014 la présidence tournante du Conseil de l’UE pour une durée de six mois.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;D’autres questions telles que la crise financière, la collaboration sur les questions migratoires et des éléments de la politique énergétique tels que le projet de gazoduc transadriatique (Trans Adriatic Pipeline, TAP), qui doit passer par la Grèce, ont également été abordées. Le président Burkhalter a ensuite échangé avec son homologue au sujet de l’engagement de la Suisse dans les Balkans occidentaux ainsi que du rôle international et de la responsabilité de l’Europe, en particulier dans le contexte de la crise qui touche actuellement l’Ukraine. A cette occasion, le rôle de l’Organisation pour la sécurité et la coopération en Europe (OSCE), dont la Suisse assure la présidence cette année, a été évoqué. Outre les priorités générales définies par la présidence suisse, Didier Burkhalter a exposé à son homologue grec les mesures prises au sujet de la crise en Ukraine, parmi lesquelles l’envoi d’une mission d’observation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contacts :&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Information DFAE&lt;br /&gt;info@eda.admin.ch &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;DFJP&lt;br /&gt;info@gs-ejpd.admin.ch&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Communication DFAE Palais fédéral ouest CH-3003 Berne Tél. Service de communication: +41 58 462 31 53 Tél. Service de presse: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <link id="122034">
        <title>Page Evènement: Visite du président de la République hellénique</title>
        <uri>http://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/home/dfa/head/hoeven/karolo.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="122035">
        <title>Relations bilatérales Suisse-Grèce</title>
        <uri>http://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/home/reps/eur/vgrc/bilgri.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="122036">
        <title>Présidence suisse de l’OSCE</title>
        <uri>http://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/home/recent/osce.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="122038">
        <title>Engagement de la Suisse dans les Balkans occidentaux</title>
        <uri>https://www.deza.admin.ch/fr/Accueil/Pays/Balkans_occidentaux</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="122039">
        <title>Direction des affaires européennes DAE : politique européenne de la Suisse</title>
        <uri>http://www.europa.admin.ch/index.html?lang=fr</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="122040">
        <title>Cinquantenaire de l’Ecole suisse d’archéologie en Grèce (en anglais)</title>
        <uri>http://www.unil.ch/Jahia/site/esag/cache/off/pid/19190;jsessionid=45B59412D5628099FCC1EDBA7714324A.jvm1?showActu=1397548348602.xml&amp;actunilParam=news</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Visita ufficiale del presidente greco Karolos Papoulias a Berna</title>
      <lead>Su invito della Svizzera, il 2 maggio un presidente della Repubblica ellenica ha visitato la Svizzera per la prima volta dall'inizio, 119 anni fa, delle relazioni diplomatiche. I colloqui tra il presidente della Confederazione Didier Burkhalter e il presidente Karolos Papoulias sono stati improntati alle relazioni bilaterali e ai temi europei. Dall'inizio dell'anno e fino alla fine di giugno, la Grecia detiene la presidenza del Consiglio dell'UE. Il presidente della Confederazione ha quindi colto l'occasione per illustrare al suo omologo i prossimi passi previsti dal Consiglio federale nell'ambito delle relazioni Svizzera-UE. All'incontro hanno partecipato anche la vicepresidente del Consiglio federale Simonetta Sommaruga (DFGP), il viceministro degli esteri greco Dimitris Kourkoulas e la ministra del turismo Olga Kefalogianni.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Il presidente Karolos Papoulias è stato ricevuto con gli onori militari dal presidente della Confederazione e capo del Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri DFAE Didier Burkhalter, nella Residenza del Lohn a Kehrsatz. I successivi colloqui, cui ha partecipato anche la consigliera federale Simonetta Sommaruga, capo del Dipartimento federale di giustizia e polizia (DFGP), hanno permesso di sottolineare le relazioni bilaterali amichevoli e di lunga tradizione tra i due Stati. Le due delegazioni hanno discusso la possibilità di approfondire le relazioni nell'ambito della formazione e della ricerca, ricordando, tra l'altro, il 50° anniversario dell'inizio degli scavi a Eretria della Scuola svizzera di archeologia in Grecia (ESAG).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I colloqui hanno riguardato anche la politica europea. Il presidente della Confederazione Didier Burkhalter ha fatto riferimento all'attuale dibattito del Consiglio federale sullo sviluppo delle relazioni bilaterali Svizzera-UE e ha informato il suo partner sulla decisione del Consiglio federale del 30 aprile 2014 concernente la soluzione per l’ammissione contingentata di cittadini croati al mercato del lavoro svizzero. Ha inoltre sottolineato che i dossier sulla politica europea vengono promossi e armonizzati nella loro globalità, al fine di ottenere il risultato migliore per tutte le parti. Dall'inizio dell'anno, la Grecia detiene per sei mesi la presidenza del Consiglio dell'UE.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Tra gli altri temi sul tappeto, anche la crisi finanziaria e la cooperazione in materia di migrazione, nonché aspetti della politica energetica, come il progetto del gasdotto Trans Adriatic Pipeline (TAP), di cui una tratta è prevista in Grecia. Il presidente della Confederazione Didier Burkhalter ha inoltre discusso con il presidente greco dell'impegno della Svizzera nei Balcani occidentali e del ruolo e della responsabilità internazionale dell'Europa, in particolare sullo sfondo dell'attuale crisi in Ucraina. Entrambi si sono poi soffermati sul ruolo dell'Organizzazione per la sicurezza e la cooperazione in Europa (OSCE), di cui la Svizzera detiene quest'anno la presidenza. Accanto alle priorità generali della presidenza svizzera, il presidente della Confederazione Didier Burkhalter ha illustrato all'omologo greco le misure adottate sulla crisi ucraina, tra cui il lancio di una missione di osservazione.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contatto:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Informazione DFAE&lt;br /&gt;info@eda.admin.ch &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;DFGP&lt;br /&gt;info@gs-ejpd.admin.ch&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Comunicazione DFAE Palazzo federale ovest CH-3003 Berna Tel. Servizio di comunicazione: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Servizio stampa: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <link id="122041">
        <title>Pagina dell’evento: Visita del presidente greco</title>
        <uri>http://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/home/dfa/head/hoeven/karolo.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="122043">
        <title>Relazioni bilaterali Svizzera - Grecia</title>
        <uri>http://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/home/reps/eur/vgrc/bilgri.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="122045">
        <title>Presidenza svizzera dell'OSCE</title>
        <uri>http://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/home/recent/osce.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="122048">
        <title>L'impegno della Svizzera nei Balcani occidentali</title>
        <uri>https://www.deza.admin.ch/it/Pagina_iniziale/Paesi/Balcani_occidentali</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="122051">
        <title>Direzione degli affari europei DAE: politica europea della Svizzera</title>
        <uri>http://www.europa.admin.ch/index.html?lang=it</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="122054">
        <title>Celebrazioni per i 50 anni della Scuola svizzera di archeologia in Grecia (en)</title>
        <uri>http://www.unil.ch/Jahia/site/esag/cache/off/pid/19190;jsessionid=45B59412D5628099FCC1EDBA7714324A.jvm1?showActu=1397548348602.xml&amp;actunilParam=news</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Greek president Karolos Papoulias in Bern on official visit</title>
      <lead>On Switzerland's invitation, the president of the Hellenic Republic visited the country on 2 May for the first time since diplomatic relations between Switzerland and Greece began 119 years ago. President of the Swiss Confederation, Mr Didier Burkhalter, and President Karolos Papoulias primarily discussed bilateral relations between the two countries and topics concerning European policy. Greece has held the rotating presidency of the Council of the European Union since the beginning of the year which will last until the end of June. Against this backdrop, Mr Burkhalter talked about the Federal Council's intended next steps regarding relations between Switzerland and the EU. The vice-president of the Federal Council, Simonetta Sommaruga (FDJP), the Greek deputy foreign minister, Dimitris Kourkoulas, and the Greek minister of tourism, Olga Kefalogianni, also took part in the meeting.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;President Papoulias was received with military honours by the Swiss president and head of the Federal Department of Foreign Affairs (FDFA), Didier Burkhalter, at the Lohn Manor in Kehrsatz. The ensuing talks – which were attended by Federal Councillor Simonetta Sommaruga, head of the Federal Department of Justice and Police (FDJP) – provided an opportunity to give due recognition to the two countries' friendly and long-standing bilateral relations. Both delegations discussed possibilities for strengthening ties between the two countries in the field of education and research, including the 50th anniversary of the excavations in Eretria carried out by the Swiss School of Archaeology in Greece.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Switzerland's policy on Europe was also discussed. Mr Burkhalter referred to current discussions in the Federal Council regarding the ongoing development of bilateral relations between Switzerland and the EU. During the meeting with President Papoulias, he talked about the Federal Council decision of 30 April 2014 on how to solve the issue of quotas to allow Croatian citizens access to the job market in Switzerland. President Burkhalter also underlined that Switzerland advances all its various EU-policy dossiers in their entirety and in a concerted manner, in order to obtain the best possible outcome for all the parties involved. Greece has held the six-month rotating presidency of the Council of the European Union since the beginning of the year.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Other issues including the financial crisis, and cooperation on migration issues and energy policy – such as the natural gas pipeline project, the Trans Adriatic Pipeline (TAP) in Greece, were also discussed. Mr Burkhalter and Mr Papoulias further conferred on Switzerland's engagement in the Western Balkans and Europe's international role and responsibility, in particular against the backdrop of the current crisis in Ukraine. The role of the Organization for Security and Co-operation in Europe (OSCE), which Switzerland is chairing this year, was another point of discussion. Besides the overall priorities of the Swiss Chairmanship, Mr Burkhalter also briefed Mr Papoulias on the measures taken to respond to the crisis in Ukraine, in particular the launch of a special monitoring mission.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contacts:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;FDFA Information&lt;br /&gt;info@eda.admin.ch &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;FDJP&lt;br /&gt;info@gs-ejpd.admin.ch&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>FDFA Communication Federal Palace West Wing CH-3003 Bern, Switzerland Tel. Communication service: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Press service: +41 58 460 55 55 E-mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @SwissMFA</contact>
      <link id="122056">
        <title>Event page: Visit of Greek President</title>
        <uri>http://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home/dfa/head/hoeven/karolo.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="122059">
        <title>Bilateral relations between Switzerland and Greece</title>
        <uri>http://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home/reps/eur/vgrc/bilgri.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="122061">
        <title>Swiss OSCE Chairmanship</title>
        <uri>http://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home/recent/osce.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="122063">
        <title>Switzerland's engagement in the Western Balkans</title>
        <uri>https://www.deza.admin.ch/en/Home/Countries/Western_Balkans</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="122065">
        <title>Directorate for European Affairs DEA: Switzerland's policy on Europe</title>
        <uri>http://www.europa.admin.ch/index.html?lang=en</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="122066">
        <title>Celebrating 50 years of the Swiss School of Archaeology in Greece</title>
        <uri>http://www.unil.ch/Jahia/site/esag/cache/off/pid/19190;jsessionid=45B59412D5628099FCC1EDBA7714324A.jvm1?showActu=1397548348602.xml&amp;actunilParam=news</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
