<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="52905" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2014-05-08</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="201" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>201</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="601" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>601</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Finanzdepartement</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des finances</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale delle finanze</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Finance</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.efd.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.dff.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.efd.admin.ch/efd/it/home.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.efd.admin.ch/efd/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="701" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>701</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Wirtschaft, Bildung und Forschung</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'économie, de la formation et de la recherche</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'economia, della formazione e della ricerca</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Economic Affairs, Education and Research</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="201">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <department id="601">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Finanzdepartement</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des finances</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale delle finanze</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Finance</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.efd.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.dff.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.efd.admin.ch/efd/it/home.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.efd.admin.ch/efd/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <department id="701">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Wirtschaft, Bildung und Forschung</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'économie, de la formation et de la recherche</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'economia, della formazione e della ricerca</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Economic Affairs, Education and Research</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Offizieller Besuch des Präsidenten der Republik Singapur, Tony TAN Keng Yam, in Bern</title>
      <lead>Bundespräsident Didier Burkhalter hat am 8. Mai 2014 den Präsidenten der Republik Singapur, Tony TAN Keng Yam, zu einem offiziellen Besuch empfangen. Die beiden Präsidenten haben ihren Willen bekräftigt, die Beziehungen zwischen der Schweiz und dem südostasiatischen Stadtstaat zu verstärken. Diese Beziehungen sind schon heute bedeutend, namentlich in den Bereichen Wirtschaft, Finanzen und Wissenschaft.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Der Bundespräsident hat seinen Amtskollegen aus Singapur auf dem Landsitz Lohn in Kehrsatz mit militärischen Ehren empfangen. Die anschliessenden Gespräche, an denen auch Bundesrätin Eveline Widmer-Schlumpf, Vorsteherin des Eidgenössischen Finanz­departements (EFD), und Bundesrat Johann N. Schneider-Ammann, Vorsteher des Eidgenössischen Departements für Wirtschaft, Bildung und Forschung (WBF), teilnahmen, boten den beiden Delegationen Gelegenheit, die ausgezeichneten Beziehungen zwischen der Schweiz und Singapur hervorzuheben. Die beiden Länder unterhalten seit 1967 diplomatische Beziehungen.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;In der Absicht, diese Beziehungen zu verstärken, haben die Delegationen der Schweiz und Singapurs am heutigen Donnerstag eine Erklärung über eine verstärkte Partnerschaft («Decla­ration of Enhanced Partnership») unterzeichnet. Mit diesem Dokument wird ein regel­mässiger politischer Dialog eingerichtet und ein Weg zu einer verstärkten Zusam­men­arbeit zwischen der Schweiz und Singapur eröffnet, hauptsächlich in den Be­reichen Wirtschaft und Finanzen sowie in der Forschung und Innovation. Überdies soll mit diesem Dokument die gegenseitige Verständigung zwischen den beiden Ländern gefördert werden, indem insbesondere die wissenschaftliche Zusammen­arbeit unterstützt und der Austausch junger Berufsfachleuten erleichtert werden sollen.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Der asiatisch-pazifische Raum sei die Weltregion mit der grössten Dynamik, hat Bundespräsident Burkhalter bei den Gesprächen betont, und Singapur sei einer der Motoren in diesem Raum und der wichtigste Handelspartner der Schweiz in Südostasien. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Seit der Unterzeichnung des Freihandelsabkommens zwischen der Europäischen Freihandelsassoziation EFTA und Singapur im Jahr 2003 hat der Handel zwischen den beiden Ländern beträchtlich zugenommen. Dieses Freihandelsabkommen war das erste dieser Art zwischen der EFTA und einem asiatischen Land. 2012 beliefen sich die schweizerischen Direktinvestitionen in Singapur auf 19,7 Milliarden Franken. Die Schweiz ist damit der fünftwichtigste Investor in Singapur. Im November 2012 statteten Bundesrat Johann N. Schneider-Ammann, Vorsteher des WBF, und eine Delegation von Vertreterinnen und Vertretern der Privatwirtschaft Singapur einen Besuch ab, der eine Reihe von Treffen mit hochrangigen Regierungsvertretern Singapurs umfasste. Es ging darum, die schon lange bestehenden Beziehungen zwischen den beiden Ländern zu festigen.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Die Zusammenarbeit im Bereich Forschung und Bildung stand heute Donnerstag ebenfalls auf der Traktandenliste. Seit zehn Jahren unterstützt «Swissnex Singapur» die schweize­rischen Hochschulen und Forschungsstätten sowie schweizerische Technologie­unternehmen, die im Stadtstaat Singapur Niederlassungen haben, und fördert damit den wissenschaftlichen und technologischen Austausch. Ziel dieser Einrich­tung ist es, die Schweizer Institutionen zu fördern und durch Austausch zwischen den Hochschulen, durch wissenschaftliche Zusammenkünfte und durch Zusammenarbeit im Forschungsbereich Netzwerke aufzubauen. Hauptakteure sind die Universität St. Gallen, die Eidgenössischen Technischen Hochschulen in Zürich und Lausanne und die «National Research Foundation» von Singapur. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt; Auf multilateraler Ebene haben die Delegationen der Schweiz und Singapurs verschiedene Themen angesprochen, darunter die Fortsetzung der guten Zusammenarbeit im Rahmen der UNO. Bundespräsident Burkhalter, zurzeit Präsident der Organisation für Sicherheit und Zusammenarbeit in Europa (OSZE), hat überdies seinen Amtskollegen über die Prioritäten der Schweiz für die OSZE-Präsidentschaft ins Bild gesetzt und ihm die Bemühungen der OSZE im Zusammenhang mit der Krise in der Ukraine erläutert.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;b&gt;Weitere Auskünfte: &lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; Information EDA&lt;br /&gt;Tel. +41 (0)31 322 31 53, &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; Information EFD&lt;br /&gt;Tel. +41 (0)31 322 60 33&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; Information WBF&lt;br /&gt;Tel. +41 (0)58 462 20 07&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Kommunikation EDA Bundeshaus West CH-3003 Bern Tel. Kommunikationsservice: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Medienstelle: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <link id="122205">
        <title>Bilaterale Beziehungen Schweiz – Singapur</title>
        <uri>http://www.eda.ch/eda/de/home/reps/asia/vsgp/bilsin.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="122206">
        <title>Anlass-Seite: Besuch des Präsidenten Singapurs</title>
        <uri>http://www.eda.ch/eda/de/home/dfa/head/hoeven/sing.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Visite officielle à Berne du président de Singapour Tony TAN Keng Yam</title>
      <lead>Le président de la Confédération Didier Burkhalter a reçu le président de Singapour Tony TAN Keng Yam le jeudi 8 mai 2014 à l’occasion d’une visite officielle. Les deux responsables ont affirmé leur volonté de renforcer les relations entre la Suisse et la Cité-Etat du Sud-Est asiatique qui sont déjà importantes notamment dans les domaines économique, financier et scientifique. </lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Le président de la Confédération a accueilli son homologue singapourien à la résidence du Lohn, à Kehrsatz, avec les honneurs militaires. Les entretiens qui ont suivi, auxquels ont pris part la conseillère fédérale Eveline Widmer-Schlumpf, cheffe du Département fédéral des finances (DFF), et le conseiller fédéral Johann N. Schneider-Ammann, chef du Département fédéral de l’économie, de la formation et de la recherche (DEFR), ont offert l’occasion aux délégations de souligner les excellentes relations entre la Suisse et Singapour. Les deux pays cultivent des relations diplomatiques depuis 1967.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;En vue de renforcer ces liens, les délégations suisse et singapourienne ont signé ce jeudi une Déclaration de partenariat renforcé (« Declaration of Enhanced Partnership »). Ce document établit un dialogue politique régulier et ouvre la voie au renforcement de la coopération entre la Suisse et Singapour, principalement dans le domaine économique et financier ainsi qu’en matière de recherche et d’innovation. Il doit également permettre de promouvoir la compréhension entre les deux pays, notamment en encourageant les collaborations au niveau scientifique, ainsi qu’en facilitant les échanges de jeunes professionnels. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;La région Asie-Pacifique est la région la plus dynamique du monde, a relevé le président de la Confédération au cours des entretiens, soulignant que Singapour est l’un des moteurs de cet espace et est le principal partenaire commercial de la Suisse en Asie du Sud-Est.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Le commerce entre les deux pays a connu un essor considérable depuis la signature de l’accord de libre-échange entre l’Association européenne de libre-échange (AELE) et Singapour en 2003. Cet accord est le premier du genre conclu par l’AELE avec un pays asiatique. En 2012, les investissements directs helvétiques se montaient à 19,7 milliards CHF, faisant de la Suisse le 5e investisseur à Singapour. En novembre 2012, le conseiller fédéral Johann N. Schneider-Ammann, chef du DEFR, et une délégation d’acteurs du secteur privé se sont rendus sur place pour une série de réunions de haut niveau avec des représentants du gouvernement singapourien, dans le but de renforcer les relations de longue date entre les deux pays.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;La coopération dans le domaine de la recherche et de l’éducation a également figuré au menu des discussions de ce jeudi. Depuis 10 ans, le Swissnex Singapour soutient les hautes écoles et les instituts de recherche suisses ainsi que les entreprises technologiques helvétiques installés dans la Cité-Etat et favorise ainsi les échanges scientifiques et technologiques. L’objectif de cette structure est de promouvoir les institutions suisses et de créer des réseaux grâce aux échanges universitaires, aux rencontres scientifiques et à la coopération en matière de recherche. Les principaux acteurs sont l’Université de Saint-Gall (UniSG), les hautes écoles polytechniques fédérales de Zurich et de Lausanne (EPFZ et EPFL) et la National Research Foundation de Singapour.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Au niveau multilatéral, les délégations suisse et singapourienne ont évoqué différents thèmes dont la poursuite de la bonne coopération au sein de l’ONU. M. Burkhalter, en tant que président en exercice de l’Organisation pour la sécurité et la coopération en Europe (OSCE), a également informé son homologue des priorités de la Suisse durant son année de présidence et présenté les efforts de l’organisation dans le contexte de la crise en Ukraine.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Pour plus d’information: &lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Information DFAE&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Tel. +41 (0)31 322 31 53 &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Information DFF&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Tel. +41 (0)31 322 60 33&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Information DEFR&lt;/p&gt; Tel. +41 (0)58 462 20 07</text>
      <contact>Communication DFAE Palais fédéral ouest CH-3003 Berne Tél. Service de communication: +41 58 462 31 53 Tél. Service de presse: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <link id="122207">
        <title>Relations bilatérales Suisse - Singapour</title>
        <uri>http://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/home/reps/asia/vsgp/bilsin.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="122208">
        <title>Page Evénement: Visite du président de la République de Singapour</title>
        <uri>http://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/home/dfa/head/hoeven/sing.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Visita ufficiale a Berna del presidente di Singapore Tony TAN Keng Yam</title>
      <lead>Giovedì 8 maggio 2014 il presidente della Confederazione Didier Burkhalter ha ricevuto il presidente di Singapore Tony TAN Keng Yam per una visita ufficiale. I due presidenti hanno affermato la loro volontà di rafforzare le relazioni tra la Svizzera e la Città-Stato del Sud-Est asiatico, già importanti soprattutto in ambito economico, finanziario e scientifico. </lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Il presidente della Confederazione ha accolto il suo omologo singaporiano alla residenza governativa del Lohn, a Kehrsatz, con gli onori militari. I colloqui, a cui hanno partecipato anche la consigliera federale Eveline Widmer-Schlumpf, capo del Dipartimento federale delle finanze (DFF), e il consigliere federale Johann N. Schneider-Ammann, capo del Dipartimento federale dell'economia, della formazione e della ricerca (DEFR), hanno offerto alle delegazioni l'occasione di sottolineare le eccellenti relazioni tra la Svizzera e Singapore. I due Paesi intrattengono relazioni diplomatiche dal 1967.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Al fine di rafforzare questi legami, le delegazioni svizzera e singaporiana hanno firmato giovedì una Dichiarazione di partenariato rafforzato (« Declaration of Enhanced Partnership »). Questo documento istituisce un dialogo politico regolare e dà avvio al potenziamento della cooperazione tra la Svizzera e Singapore, soprattutto nel settore economico e finanziario e in materia di ricerca e innovazione. Esso permetterà pure di promuovere la comprensione tra i due Paesi, in particolare incoraggiando la collaborazione a livello scientifico e agevolando lo scambio di giovani professionisti.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Il presidente della Confederazione ha affermato che la regione Asia-Pacifico è la più dinamica a livello mondiale e che Singapore, uno dei motori di questo dinamismo, rappresenta il principale partner commerciale della Svizzera nell'Asia sud-orientale.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Il commercio tra i due Paesi ha conosciuto un incremento considerevole dopo la firma dell'Accordo di libero scambio tra l'Associazione europea di libero scambio (AELS) e Singapore nel 2003. Tale Accordo è il primo del suo genere concluso dall’AELS con un Paese asiatico. Nel 2012, gli investimenti diretti svizzeri a Singapore ammontavano a 19,7 miliardi di franchi, facendo della Svizzera il quinto investitore. Nel novembre 2012, il consigliere federale Johann N. Schneider-Ammann, capo del DEFR, e una delegazione di esponenti del settore privato si sono recati sul posto per una serie di riunioni d'alto livello con rappresentanti del Governo singaporiano, allo scopo di rafforzare le relazioni di lunga data tra i due Paesi.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;La cooperazione nel settore della ricerca e dell'educazione è pure stata oggetto dei colloqui di oggi Da dieci anni, Swissnex Singapore sostiene le scuole universitarie e gli istituti di ricerca svizzeri, come pure le imprese tecnologiche svizzere ubicate nella Città-Stato, favorendo così gli scambi a livello scientifico e tecnologico. L’obiettivo di questa struttura è di promuovere le istituzioni svizzere e di costruire reti grazie agli scambi universitari, agli incontri scientifici e alla cooperazione in materia di ricerca. I principali attori sono l’Università di San Gallo (UniSG), i Politecnici federali di Zurigo e di Losanna (PFZ e PFL) e la National Research Foundation di Singapore.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;A livello multilaterale, le delegazioni svizzera e singaporiana hanno abbordato diversi argomenti, tra cui il prosequio di una buona cooperazione in seno alle Nazioni Unite. Il consigliere federale Burkhalter, nella sua qualità di presidente in carica dell'Organizzazione per la sicurezza e la cooperazione in Europa (OSCE), ha pure informato il presidente di Singapore in merito alle priorità della Svizzera durante il suo anno di presidenza, illustrando gli sforzi profusi dall'OSCE nel contesto della crisi in Ucraina.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Per ulteriori informazioni: &lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Informazione DFAE&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Tel. +41 (0)31 322 31 53 &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Informazione DFF&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Tel. +41 (0)31 322 60 33&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Informazione DEFR&lt;/p&gt; Tel. +41 (0)58 462 20 07</text>
      <contact>Comunicazione DFAE Palazzo federale ovest CH-3003 Berna Tel. Servizio di comunicazione: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Servizio stampa: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <link id="122209">
        <title>Relazioni bilaterali Svizzera - Singapore</title>
        <uri>http://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/home/reps/asia/vsgp/bilsin.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="122210">
        <title>Pagina Eventi: Visita del presidente della Repubblica di Singapore</title>
        <uri>http://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/home/dfa/head/hoeven/sing.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>President of the Republic of Singapore, Tony TAN Keng Yam, pays official visit to Bern</title>
      <lead>On Thursday, 8 May, President Didier Burkhalter received the President of the Republic of Singapore, Tony TAN Keng Yam, on an official visit . The two presidents affirmed their desire to strengthen and enhance relations between Switzerland and the South-East Asian city state. Relations are already extensive, particularly in the fields of business, finance and science. </lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;The President of the Swiss Confederation welcomed his Singaporean counterpart at the Lohn country residence in Kehrsatz with military honours. The meetings that followed, which were also attended by Federal Councillor Eveline Widmer-Schlumpf, head of the Federal Department of Finances (FDF), and Federal Councillor Johann N. Schneider-Ammann, head of the Federal Department of Economic Affairs, Education and Research (EAER), provided an opportunity for the delegations to emphasise the excellent relations between Switzerland and Singapore. The two countries have maintained diplomatic relations since 1967.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;In order to reinforce these ties, the Swiss and Singaporean delegations signed a Declaration of Enhanced Partnership. The document establishes a regular political dialogue and paves the way for the strengthening of cooperation between Switzerland and Singapore, primarily in terms of business and finance, as well as in the fields of research and innovation. It should also promote understanding between the two countries, in particular by encouraging cooperation at scientific level, as well as by facilitating exchanges among young professionals. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The Asia-Pacific region is the world's most dynamic region, stated President Burkhalter during the discussions, stressing that Singapore is one of the region's economic drivers and Switzerland's leading trade partner in South-East Asia.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Trade between the two countries increased considerably following the signing of a free trade agreement between the European Free Trade Association (EFTA) and Singapore in 2003. This agreement was the first of its kind to be concluded by EFTA with an Asian country. In 2012, Switzerland's direct investment amounted to CHF 19.7 billion, making Switzerland the fifth largest investor in Singapore. In November 2012, Federal Councillor Johann N. Schneider-Ammann, the head of the EAER, and a delegation of representatives from the private sector travelled to Singapore for a series of high-level meetings with government representatives, with the aim of strengthening long-standing relations between the two countries.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Cooperation in the field of research and education also formed part of today’s discussions. For ten years Swissnex Singapore has been supporting Swiss universities, research institutes and high-tech companies in Singapore and has been facilitating scientific and technological exchanges. The aim is to promote Swiss institutions and establish networks through university exchanges, scientific contacts and research cooperation. The main actors involved are the University of St. Gallen (UniSG), the Federal Institutes of Technology in Zurich and Lausanne (ETH and EPFL) and the National Research Foundation of Singapore.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;At the multilateral level, the Swiss and Singaporean delegations raised a number of issues including the continuation of the good collaboration at the United Nations. Mr Burkhalter, in his capacity as Chairperson-in-Office of the Organisation for Security and Cooperation in Europe (OSCE), also informed his counterpart of Switzerland's priorities during the year-long chairmanship and briefed him about the OSCE's efforts in connection with the crisis in Ukraine.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Further information: &lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Information FDFA&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Tel. +41 (0)31 322 31 53 &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Information FDF&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Tel. +41 (0)31 322 60 33&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Information EAER&lt;/p&gt; Tel. +41 (0)58 462 20 07</text>
      <contact>FDFA Communication Federal Palace West Wing CH-3003 Bern, Switzerland Tel. Communication service: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Press service: +41 58 460 55 55 E-mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @SwissMFA</contact>
      <link id="122211">
        <title>Bilateral relations between Switzerland - Singapore</title>
        <uri>http://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home/reps/asia/vsgp/bilsin.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="122212">
        <title>Events: Official visit of the President of the Republic of Singapore</title>
        <uri>http://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home/dfa/head/hoeven/sing.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <keywords>
      <keyword id="128" org-id="601">
        <name lang="de">Wirtschaftspolitik und Finanzmärkte</name>
        <name lang="fr">Politique économique et marchés financiers</name>
        <name lang="it">Politica economica e mercati finanziari</name>
        <name lang="en">Economic policy and financial markets</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="235" org-id="601">
        <name lang="de">Internationale Steuerpolitik</name>
        <name lang="fr">Politique fiscale internationale</name>
        <name lang="it">Politica fiscale internazionale</name>
        <name lang="en">International tax policy</name>
      </keyword>
    </keywords>
    <topics>
      <topic id="47">
        <name lang="de">Wirtschaft</name>
        <name lang="fr">Économie</name>
        <name lang="it">Economia</name>
        <name lang="en">Economic Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
