<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="44373" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2012-05-01</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="322" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>301</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Staatssekretariat für Bildung und Forschung (SBF) - ab 1.1.2013 SBFI</name>
      <name lang="fr">Secrétariat d'Etat à l'éducation et à la recherche (SER) - dès le 1.1.2013 SEFRI</name>
      <name lang="it">Segreteria di Stato per l'educazione e la ricerca (SER) - a partire dal 1.1.2013 SEFRI</name>
      <name lang="en">State Secretariat for Education and Research (SER) - as of 1.1.2013 SERI</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.sbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.sbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.sbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.sbf.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@sbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@sbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@sbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@sbf.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="301">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement des Innern</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'intérieur</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'interno</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Home Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Weitere Verstärkung der Forschungszusammenarbeit zwischen der Schweiz und Südafrika</title>
      <lead>Eine hochrangige Schweizer Delegation unter der Leitung des Staatssekretariats für Bildung und Forschung (SBF) traf letzte Woche in Südafrika mit den Ansprechpartnern des Ministeriums für Wissenschaft und Technologie zusammen, um die Ausrichtung der zweiten Phase der Zusammenarbeit im Rahmen des 2007 unterzeichneten bilateralen Abkommens festzulegen.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Am Treffen des Gemeinsamen Ausschusses Schweiz-Südafrika, das in Kapstadt stattfand, zogen beide Seiten eine äusserst positive Bilanz der ersten Programmphase (2008-2012), in welche die Schweiz rund 7,8 Mio. Franken investierte. Mit diesem Beitrag konnten nach dem Grundsatz des &lt;i&gt;matched funding&lt;/i&gt; 16 gemeinsame Forschungsprojekte von ausgezeichneter wissenschaftlicher Qualität in den Bereichen Gesundheit und Biomedizin, Bio- und Nanotechnologien sowie Geistes- und Sozialwissenschaften mitfinanziert werden. Diese Projekte, an denen 67 junge Forschende beider Länder beteiligt waren, führten zu 35 wissenschaftlichen Publikationen. 80 junge Forschende aus der Schweiz und Südafrika erhielten ein Austauschstipendium.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Besonderes Augenmerk galt dem Übergang zur Anwendung durch ein Programm für Jungunternehmer im Biotechnologiebereich. Neun Forschungsprojekte mit mindestens einem Industriepartner erhielten ein Startkapital (Seed Money).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Für die Jahre 2013-2016 einigten sich beide Seiten, vorbehältlich der Budgetentscheidungen des Parlaments, auf eine Fortführung der Finanzierung auf gleichem Niveau und auf eine Ausdehnung der Schwerpunktthemen auf den Bereich der erneuerbaren Energien (Greentech und Cleantech). Eine Projektausschreibung soll im Herbst 2012 unter der gemeinsamen Verantwortung des Schweizerischen Nationalfonds und der südafrikanischen &lt;i&gt;National Research Foundation&lt;/i&gt; mit Unterstützung der KTI und der südafrikanischen Innovationsförderagentur TIA erfolgen. Der direkte Dialog zwischen den Organen der Forschungsförderung beider Länder soll in den kommenden Jahren allgemein verstärkt werden im Hinblick auf eine geteilte Nutzung von Expertise und Fachkompetenz. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Die Schweizer Delegation umfasste Professor Antonio Loprieno, Präsident der Rektorenkonferenz der Schweizer Universitäten (CRUS) und Rektor der Universität Basel, die als &lt;i&gt;Leading House&lt;/i&gt; des bilateralen Programms fungiert, Prof. Marcel Tanner, Direktor des Schweizerischen Tropen- und Public Health-Instituts, &lt;i&gt;Associated Leading House&lt;/i&gt; des Programms, Klara Sekanina, Direktorin der Kommission für Technologie und Innovation (KTI), sowie Vertretungen des Schweizerischen Nationalfonds (SNF), des EDA, des SECO und der Direktion für Entwicklung und Zusammenarbeit (DEZA).&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Staatssekretariat für Bildung und Forschung SBF Kommunikation Hallwylstrasse 4 3003 Bern</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>La Suisse et l’Afrique du Sud renforcent leur coopération scientifique</title>
      <lead>Une délégation suisse de haut niveau, conduite par le Secrétariat d’Etat à l’éducation et la recherche (SER), s’est rendue la semaine dernière en Afrique du Sud pour rencontre ses partenaires du Département de la Science et de la Technologie et discuter les grandes lignes de la deuxième phase de la coopération dans le cadre de l’accord bilatéral signé en 2007.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Au cours du comité conjoint helvético-sud-africain qui s'est tenu au Cap, les parties ont tiré un bilan extrêmement positif de la première phase du programme (2008-2012), dans laquelle la Suisse a investi environ CHF 7,8 millions. Cette somme a permis de cofinancer, selon le principe du &lt;i&gt;matching funding&lt;/i&gt;, 16 projets de recherche conjoints d'excellent niveau scientifique dans les domaines de la santé publique et de la biomédecine, des bio- et nanotechnologies ainsi que des sciences humaines et sociales, impliquant notamment 67 jeunes chercheurs des deux pays et conduisant à 35 publications scientifiques. 80 jeunes chercheurs suisses et sud-africains ont par ailleurs bénéficié de bourses pour des échanges.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Un accent particulier a été également mis pour favoriser le passage vers l'application dans le cadre d'un programme pour jeunes entrepreneurs dans le domaine des biotechnologies. Enfin, 9 projets de recherche impliquant au moins un partenaire industriel ont reçu un financement de lancement (seed money).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Concernant la phase 2013-2016, les parties se sont entendues pour maintenir un engagement financier équivalent à celui de la période écoulée, sous réserve des décisions du Parlement, et à élargir le champ des thèmes prioritaires au domaine des énergies renouvelables (greentech et cleantech). Un appel à projets sera lancé en automne 2012, sous la responsabilité conjointe du FNS et de &lt;i&gt;National Research Foundation&lt;/i&gt; sudafricaine, soutenues par la CTI et l'organisation de soutien à l'innovation sudafricaine TIA. En outre, le dialogue direct entre les agences suisses et sudafricaines de financement de la recherche sera également intensifié dans les années à venir, dans le but notamment de partager leur expertise et leurs compétences respectives.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;La délégation comptait dans ses rangs le Professeur Antonio Loprieno, président de la Conférence des recteurs des universités suisse et recteur de l'université de Bâle, &lt;i&gt;leading house&lt;/i&gt; du programme bilatéral; le professeur Marcel Tanner, directeur de l'Institut tropical et de santé publique suisse, &lt;i&gt;leading house&lt;/i&gt; associé du programme; Klara Sekanina, directrice de la Commission pour la technologie et l'innovation (CTI), ainsi que des représentants du Fonds national suisse pour la recherche scientifique (FNS), du DFAE, du SECO et de la Direction pour le développement et la coopération (DDC).&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Secrétariat d’Etat à l’éducation et à la recherche SER Communication Hallwylstrasse 4 3003 Berne</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Rafforzata la cooperazione scientifica fra Svizzera e Sudafrica</title>
      <lead>La scorsa settimana una delegazione svizzera di alto livello, guidata dalla Segreteria di Stato per l’educazione e la ricerca SER, si è recata a Città del Capo per incontrare esponenti del Ministero sudafricano della scienza e della tecnologia e discutere le linee essenziali della seconda fase della cooperazione scientifica istituita in virtù dell’accordo bilaterale stipulato dai due Paesi nel 2007.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Nel quadro dell'incontro del comitato congiunto Svizzera-Sudafrica, le parti hanno fatto un bilancio estremamente positivo della prima fase del programma bilaterale di ricerca 2008-2012, nella quale la Svizzera ha investito circa 7,8 milioni di franchi. Questi fondi hanno permesso di cofinanziare - secondo il principio del &lt;i&gt;matching fund&lt;/i&gt; - 16 progetti comuni di eccellente livello scientifico nei settori sanità pubblica e biomedicina, biotecnologie e nanotecnologie e scienze sociali e umane. I progetti hanno coinvolto 67 giovani ricercatori e sono sfociati in 35 pubblicazioni scientifiche; un'ottantina di nuove leve della ricerca svizzere e sudafricane ha inoltre beneficiato di borse di scambio. Un accento particolare è stato posto anche sulla necessità di favorire il passaggio dalla ricerca fondamentale all'applicazione dei suoi risultati, nel quadro per esempio di un programma per giovani imprenditori attivi nel settore delle biotecnologie. Infine, il comitato congiunto Svizzera-Sudafrica ha deciso di concedere un finanziamento iniziale (&lt;i&gt;seed money&lt;/i&gt;) a nove progetti di ricerca con almeno un partner industriale.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Per quanto riguarda la fase 2013-2016, le parti si sono accordate sul rinnovo di un impegno finanziario equivalente a quello del periodo appena trascorso (su riserva delle decisioni dei rispettivi Parlamenti) e a estendere il campo dei temi prioritari al settore delle energie rinnovabili (&lt;i&gt;greentech&lt;/i&gt; e &lt;i&gt;cleantech&lt;/i&gt;). Un bando per progetti di ricerca sarà indetto nell'autunno 2012, sotto la responsabilità congiunta del Fondo nazionale svizzero per la ricerca scientifica FNS e della fondazione nazionale sudafricana per la ricerca (&lt;i&gt;National Research Foundation&lt;/i&gt;), due istituzioni sostenute rispettivamente dalla Commissione per la tecnologia e l'innovazione CTI e dall'agenzia per la promozione dell'innovazione tecnologica in Sudafrica (&lt;i&gt;Technology Innovation Agency&lt;/i&gt;). Allo scopo di condividere know-how e competenze, nei prossimi anni sarà intensificato anche il dialogo fra gli organi svizzeri e sudafricani preposti al finanziamento della ricerca.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Hanno fatto parte della delegazione svizzera il professor Antonio Loprieno (presidente della Conferenza dei rettori delle università svizzere e rettore dell'Università di Basilea, &lt;i&gt;leading house&lt;/i&gt; del programma bilaterale), il professor Marcel Tanner (direttore dell'Istituto tropicale e di salute pubblica svizzero, &lt;i&gt;leading house&lt;/i&gt; associata del programma), Klara Sekanina (direttrice della CTI), nonché rappresentanti del FNS, del Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri, della Segreteria di Stato dell'economia e della Direzione dello sviluppo e della cooperazione.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Segreteria di Stato per l'educazione e la ricerca SER Communicazione Hallwylstrasse 4 3003 Berna</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Switzerland and South Africa step up cooperation on science</title>
      <lead>A high-level Swiss delegation led by the State Secretariat for Education and Research (SER) arrived in South Africa last week and met their counterparts from the South African Department of Science and Technology to discuss the main points of the second phase of cooperation under the bilateral agreement signed in 2007. </lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;At the joint Swiss-South African committee meeting held in Cape Town, the two parties gave a highly positive assessment of the first phase of the programme (2008-2012), in which Switzerland has invested around CHF 7.8 million. This investment, made on a match-funding basis, has been used for 16 joint research projects of an excellent scientific standard in the fields of public health and biomedicine, bio- and nanotechnology, and humanities and social sciences. This has involved 67 young researchers from the two countries, and 35 scientific papers have been published. 80 young researchers from Switzerland and South Africa have also benefited from exchange grants. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Special emphasis was also placed on facilitating the path to application, through a programme for young entrepreneurs in the field of biotechnology. Nine research projects involving at least one partner from industry were granted seed money.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As far as the 2013-2016 phase is concerned, the two parties agreed to maintain the same financial commitment as for the previous period, subject to parliamentary approval, and to include renewable energy (greentech and cleantech) as a priority research field. A call for project proposals will be launched in autumn 2012 under the joint authority of the Swiss National Science Foundation (SNSF) and the South African National Research Foundation (NRF), with the support of the Swiss Commission for Technology and Innovation (CTI) and the South African Technology Innovation Agency (TIA). Furthermore, direct dialogue between Swiss and South African research funding agencies will be intensified over the coming years, with the aim of sharing expertise and competences.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The delegation included Professor Antonio Loprieno, President of the Rectors' Conference of the Swiss Universities (CRUS) and Rector of the University of Basel, which is the leading house for the bilateral programme; Professor Marcel Tanner, Director of the Swiss Tropical and Public Health Institute (Swiss TPH), the associated leading house for the programme; Klara Sekanina, Director of the CTI; and representatives from the SNSF, the Federal Department of Foreign Affairs (FDFA), the State Secretariat for Economic Affairs (SECO) and the Swiss Agency for Development and Cooperation (SDC).&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>State Secretariat for Education and Research SER Communication Hallwylstrasse 4 3003 Berne</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <keywords>
      <keyword id="325.1" org-id="322">
        <name lang="de">Universitäten</name>
        <name lang="fr">Universités</name>
        <name lang="it">Università</name>
        <name lang="en">Universities</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="325.4" org-id="322">
        <name lang="de">Hochschullandschaft</name>
        <name lang="fr">Paysage des hautes écoles</name>
        <name lang="it">Panorama universitario</name>
        <name lang="en">University landscape</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="325.8" org-id="322">
        <name lang="de">Technologie</name>
        <name lang="fr">Technologie</name>
        <name lang="it">Tecnologia</name>
        <name lang="en">Technology</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="325.10" org-id="322">
        <name lang="de">Wissenschaft</name>
        <name lang="fr">Science</name>
        <name lang="it">Scienza</name>
        <name lang="en">Science</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="325.11" org-id="322">
        <name lang="de">Eidgenössische Technische Hochschule ETH</name>
        <name lang="fr">Ecole polytechnique fédérale EPF</name>
        <name lang="it">Politecnico federale</name>
        <name lang="en">Federal Institutes of Technology</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="325.13" org-id="322">
        <name lang="de">Ressortforschung</name>
        <name lang="fr">Recherche de l'administration publique fédérale</name>
        <name lang="it">Ricerca dell'Amministrazione federale</name>
        <name lang="en">Research in government departments</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="325.15" org-id="322">
        <name lang="de">Schweizerischer Nationalfonds</name>
        <name lang="fr">Fonds national suisse</name>
        <name lang="it">Fondo nazionale Svizzero</name>
        <name lang="en">Swiss National Science Foundation</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="325.16" org-id="322">
        <name lang="de">Schweizerische Akademie der Geistes- und Sozialwissenschaften</name>
        <name lang="fr">Académie suisse des sciences humaines et sociales</name>
        <name lang="it">Accademia svizzera di scienze morali e sociali</name>
        <name lang="en">Swiss Academy of Humanities and Social Sciences</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="325.17" org-id="322">
        <name lang="de">Schweizerische Akademie der medizinischen Wissenschaften</name>
        <name lang="fr">Académie suisse des sciences médicales</name>
        <name lang="it">Accademia svizzera delle scienze mediche</name>
        <name lang="en">Swiss Academy of Medical Sciences</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="325.18" org-id="322">
        <name lang="de">Akademie der Naturwissenschaften Schweiz</name>
        <name lang="fr">Académie suisse des sciences naturelles</name>
        <name lang="it">Accademia svizzera di scienze naturali</name>
        <name lang="en">Swiss Academy of Sciences</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="325.19" org-id="322">
        <name lang="de">Schweizerische Akademie der technischen Wissenschaften</name>
        <name lang="fr">Académie suisse des sciences techniques</name>
        <name lang="it">Accademia svizzera delle scienze tecniche</name>
        <name lang="en">Swiss Academy of Engineering Sciences</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="325.20" org-id="322">
        <name lang="de">Forschungsförderung</name>
        <name lang="fr">Encouragement de la recherche</name>
        <name lang="it">Promozione della ricerca</name>
        <name lang="en">Research promotion</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="325.21" org-id="322">
        <name lang="de">Wissenschaftsaussenpolitik</name>
        <name lang="fr">Politique scientifique extérieure</name>
        <name lang="it">Politica scientifica dell'esterno</name>
        <name lang="en">Foreign scientific policy</name>
      </keyword>
    </keywords>
    <topics>
      <topic id="8">
        <name lang="de">Bildung und Forschung</name>
        <name lang="fr">Formation et recherche</name>
        <name lang="it">Formazione e ricerca</name>
        <name lang="en">Education and Research</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="11">
        <name lang="de">Energie</name>
        <name lang="fr">Énergie</name>
        <name lang="it">Energia</name>
        <name lang="en">Energy</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="45">
        <name lang="de">Technologie</name>
        <name lang="fr">Technologie</name>
        <name lang="it">Tecnologia</name>
        <name lang="en">Technology</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
