<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="74413" revoked="no">
    <version>2</version>
    <pubdate>2019-03-22</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="1070" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>1070</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Der Bundesrat</name>
      <name lang="fr">Conseil fédéral</name>
      <name lang="it">Il Consiglio federale</name>
      <name lang="en">The Federal Council</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.admin.ch/gov/de/start.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.admin.ch/gov/fr/accueil.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.admin.ch/gov/it/pagina-iniziale.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.admin.ch/gov/en/start.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="804" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>801</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Generalsekretariat UVEK</name>
      <name lang="fr">Secrétariat général DETEC</name>
      <name lang="it">Segreteria generale DATEC</name>
      <name lang="en">General Secretariat of the Federal Department of Environment, Transport, Energy and Communications; General Secretariat DETEC</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.uvek.admin.ch/uvek/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.uvek.admin.ch/uvek/fr/home.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.uvek.admin.ch/uvek/it/home.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.uvek.admin.ch/uvek/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-uvek.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-uvek.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-uvek.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-uvek.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="201" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>201</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="812" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>801</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Bundesamt für Raumentwicklung</name>
      <name lang="fr">Office fédéral du développement territorial</name>
      <name lang="it">Ufficio federale dello sviluppo territoriale</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Office for Spatial Development</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.are.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.are.admin.ch/are/fr/home.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.are.admin.ch/are/it/home.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.are.admin.ch/are/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@are.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@are.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@are.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@are.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="1070">
      <name lang="de">Der Bundesrat</name>
      <name lang="fr">Conseil fédéral</name>
      <name lang="it">Il Consiglio federale</name>
      <name lang="en">The Federal Council</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.admin.ch/gov/de/start.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.admin.ch/gov/fr/accueil.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.admin.ch/gov/it/pagina-iniziale.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.admin.ch/gov/en/start.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <department id="801">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Umwelt, Verkehr, Energie und Kommunikation</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'environnement, des transports, de l'énergie et de la communication</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'ambiente, dei trasporti, dell'energia e delle comunicazioni</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of the Environment, Transport, Energy and Communications</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.uvek.admin.ch/uvek/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.uvek.admin.ch/uvek/fr/home.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.uvek.admin.ch/uvek/it/home.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.uvek.admin.ch/uvek/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-uvek.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-uvek.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-uvek.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-uvek.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <department id="201">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Der Bund stärkt die Umsetzung der Agenda 2030 für nachhaltige Entwicklung</title>
      <lead>Der Bundesrat hat an seiner Sitzung vom 22. März 2019 zwei Delegierte für die Agenda 2030 gewählt. Die Agenda 2030 ist der globale Referenzrahmen für nachhaltige Entwicklung und der Bezugspunkt für die Nachhaltigkeitspolitik der Schweiz. Der Bundesrat misst ihr eine hohe Bedeutung bei und stärkt ihre Umsetzung durch eine neue bundesinterne Organisationsstruktur. Kernelemente sind die Schaffung eines interdepartementalen Direktionskomitees und die Wahl von zwei Delegierten. Die neue Struktur ermöglicht die vollständige Verankerung der Agenda 2030 in der Verwaltung. Umgesetzt wird die Agenda 2030 weiterhin im Rahmen der Sektoralpolitiken der Bundesstellen und Departemente.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Die Agenda 2030 bündelt die nationalen und internationalen Anstrengungen für gemeinsame Lösungen bei grossen Herausforderungen wie etwa dem Ressourcenverbrauch oder dem Klimawandel. Kernbestandteil sind die 17 Ziele für nachhaltige Entwicklung (Sustainable Development Goals, SDGs). Eine umfassende Bestandsaufnahme zeigt, wie sich die Schweiz in Bezug auf die Ziele verhält, und wo innen- und aussenpolitisch noch Handlungsbedarf besteht. Die Ergebnisse dieser Bestandsaufnahme wurden 2018 in einem Länderbericht der UNO präsentiert. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Direktionskomitee zur strategischen Steuerung der Umsetzung&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Um die identifizierten Herausforderungen und Chancen wirkungsvoll anzugehen, hat der Bundesrat am 14. Dezember 2018 ein «Direktionskomitee Agenda 2030» eingesetzt. In diesem Komitee sind die hauptsächlich betroffenen Ämter auf Direktionsstufe vertreten. Ihm obliegt die Steuerung und Koordination der Umsetzungsarbeiten. Namentlich umfasst dies das Monitoring der SDGs in der Schweiz, die Erstellung des Länderberichts an die UNO, die Priorisierung der wichtigsten Herausforderungen und Chancen für die Schweiz, das Festlegen nationaler Ziele, die Abstimmung von entsprechenden Massnahmen sowie die Zusammenarbeit mit Kantonen, Gemeinden und nichtstaatlichen Akteuren. Das Direktionskomitee ersetzt den bisher bestehenden Interdepartementalen Ausschuss für Nachhaltige Entwicklung (IDANE). &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Zwei Delegierte für die Agenda 2030 übernehmen die operative Leitung&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Am 14. Dezember 2018 legte der Bundesrat fest, dass die operative Leitung der Umsetzungsarbeiten durch zwei Delegierte für die Agenda 2030 erfolgen soll. An seiner Sitzung vom 22. März 2019 hat der Bundesrat Herrn Daniel Dubas (41) aus dem Departement für Umwelt, Verkehr, Energie und Kommunikation (UVEK) und Herrn Jacques Ducrest (52) aus dem Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten (EDA) zu seinen Delegierten für die Agenda 2030 ernannt.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Herr Daniel Dubas ist studierter Politikwissenschaftler mit einem Diplom in nachhaltiger Stadtentwicklung. Er leitet seit 2013 die Sektion Nachhaltige Entwicklung im Bundesamt für Raumentwicklung ARE.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Herr Jacques Ducrest ist Diplomat mit einer juristischen Ausbildung (Rechtsanwalt und LL.M.). Seit September 2017 ist er stellvertretender Leiter der Abteilung Sektorielle Aussenpolitiken im EDA.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Neben den koordinierenden Tätigkeiten erstatten die Delegierten dem Bundesrat jährlich Bericht zur Umsetzung der Agenda 2030; dies wird erstmals im Januar 2020 der Fall sein.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Kernelemente des Politikzyklus für nachhaltige Entwicklung&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Die Agenda 2030 wird künftig hauptsächlich über die Strategie Nachhaltige Entwicklung (SNE) auf nationaler Ebene umgesetzt. Diese wird neu auf den Zeitraum von 2020 bis 2030 ausgerichtet; dies gewährleistet eine längerfristige Planungssicherheit und Kontinuität. Der Aktionsplan der SNE wird indes weiterhin zusammen mit der Legislaturplanung im Vierjahresrhythmus aktualisiert. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Die Koordination dieser Arbeiten wird durch das oben erwähnte Direktionskomitee unter der Leitung des Delegierten aus dem UVEK sichergestellt. Die Bestandsaufnahme und der Länderbericht zuhanden der UNO werden jeweils in der Mitte der Legislaturperiode erstellt. Die Koordination dieser Arbeiten wird durch das Direktionskomitee unter der Leitung des Delegierten aus dem EDA sichergestellt. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Dieser jeweils um zwei Jahre versetzte Politikzyklus erlaubt es, auf der Grundlage des Länderberichts eine Zwischenbilanz der Wirksamkeit der beschlossenen Massnahmen zu ziehen und neue Schwerpunkte für den darauffolgenden Aktionsplan der SNE zu setzen. Bis spätestens Ende 2022 werden die Wirksamkeit und Effizienz dieser neuen Organisationsstruktur sowie ihrer Aufgaben überprüft und falls nötig angepasst. &lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Stephan Scheidegger, stellvertretender Direktor, Bundesamt für Raumentwicklung ARE, Tel. +41 58 466 18 00 (Kommunikation), stephan.scheidegger@are.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="188474">
        <title>EDA: Agenda 2030 für nachhaltige Entwicklung</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/agenda2030/de/home.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="188475">
        <title>ARE: Agenda 2030 für nachhaltige Entwicklung</title>
        <uri>https://www.are.admin.ch/are/de/home/nachhaltige-entwicklung/internationale-zusammenarbeit/agenda-2030-fuer-nachhaltige-entwicklung.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>La Confédération renforce la mise en œuvre de l’Agenda 2030 pour le développement durable</title>
      <lead>Lors de sa séance du 22 mars 2019, le Conseil fédéral a nommé deux délégués à l’Agenda 2030. Ce dernier est le cadre de référence mondial pour le développement durable et sert de repère à la politique suisse en la matière. Le Conseil fédéral lui accorde une grande importance et renforce sa mise en œuvre en le dotant de sa propre structure administrative fédérale. Les éléments centraux sont la création d’un comité directeur interdépartemental et la nomination de deux délégués. La nouvelle structure permet un ancrage plein et entier de l’Agenda 2030 dans l’administration. L’Agenda 2030 continuera à être mis en œuvre dans le cadre des politiques sectorielles des services fédéraux et des départements. </lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;L’Agenda 2030 réunit les efforts nationaux et internationaux visant à trouver des solutions communes aux grands défis tels que la consommation des ressources ou le changement climatique. Il est essentiellement constitué des 17 objectifs de développement durable (ODD). Un état des lieux complet montre comment la Suisse agit pour atteindre ces objectifs et dans quels domaines de politique intérieure et extérieure une action reste nécessaire. Les résultats de cet état des lieux ont été présentés à l’ONU en 2018 sous la forme d’un rapport national. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Un comité directeur chargé du pilotage stratégique de la mise en œuvre &lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Pour traiter efficacement les défis et les chances identifiés, le Conseil fédéral a institué le 14 décembre 2018 un comité directeur pour l’Agenda 2030, où les offices principalement concernés sont représentés au niveau de la direction. Ce comité est chargé de piloter et de coordonner les travaux de mise en œuvre. Précisément, cela inclut le suivi des ODD en Suisse, l’élaboration du rapport national à remettre à l’ONU, l’attribution de priorités entre les principaux défis et chances qui se présentent à la Suisse, la fixation d’objectifs nationaux, la définition de mesures appropriées et la collaboration avec les cantons, les communes et les acteurs non étatiques. Le comité directeur remplace le Comité interdépartemental pour le développement durable (CIDD) actif jusqu’à présent. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Deux délégués à l’Agenda 2030 assureront la direction opérationnelle &lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Le 14 décembre 2018, le Conseil fédéral a décidé que la direction opérationnelle des travaux de mise en œuvre devait être confiée à deux délégués à l’Agenda 2030. Lors de sa séance du 22 mars 2019, il a nommé M. Daniel Dubas (41 ans), du Département fédéral de l’environnement, des transports, de l’énergie et de la communication (DETEC), et M. Jacques Ducrest (52 ans), du Département fédéral des affaires étrangères (DFAE), délégués du Conseil fédéral à l’Agenda 2030. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;M. Daniel Dubas a étudié les sciences politiques et obtenu un diplôme en développement urbain durable. Il dirige depuis 2013 la section Développement durable de l’Office fédéral du développement territorial (ARE). &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;M. Jacques Ducrest est diplomate et a suivi une formation juridique (avocat, LL.M.). Depuis septembre 2017, il dirige la division Politiques extérieures sectorielles du DFAE.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Outre leurs activités de coordination, les délégués remettront chaque année au Conseil fédéral un rapport sur la mise en œuvre de l’Agenda 2030 ; ils le feront pour la première fois en janvier 2020. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Les éléments-clés du cycle politique du développement durable&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;À l’avenir, l’Agenda 2030 sera principalement mis en œuvre à l’échelon national via la Stratégie pour le développement durable (SDD). Celle-ci connaîtra une nouvelle orientation pour la période 2020 à 2030, ce qui est garant d’une sécurité de planification à plus long terme, et de continuité. Le plan d’action de la SDD continuera toutefois à être actualisé tous les quatre ans, parallèlement au programme de la législature. Ces travaux seront coordonnés par le comité directeur mentionné plus haut et dirigés par le délégué du DETEC. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;L’état des lieux et le rapport national à remettre à l’ONU seront établis en milieu de législature. Ces travaux seront coordonnés par le comité directeur et dirigés par le délégué du DFAE. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ce cycle politique décalé de deux ans à chaque fois permet, sur la base du rapport national, de tirer un bilan intermédiaire de l’efficacité des mesures prises et de fixer de nouvelles priorités pour le plan d’action suivant de la SDD. L’efficacité et l’efficience de la nouvelle structure administrative, ainsi que ses tâches, feront l’objet d’une vérification puis d’une adaptation si nécessaire, au plus tard avant la fin 2022. &lt;b&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Stephan Scheidegger, directeur suppléant, Office fédéral du développement territorial (ARE), tél. +41 58 462 44 50 (Communication), stephan.scheidegger@are.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="188476">
        <title>DFAE: Agenda 2030 pour le développement durable</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/agenda2030/fr/home.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="188477">
        <title>ARE: Agenda 2030 pour le développement durable</title>
        <uri>https://www.are.admin.ch/are/fr/home/developpement-durable/cooperation-internationale/agenda-2030-pour-le-developpement-durable.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>La Confederazione rafforza l'attuazione dell'Agenda 2030 per uno sviluppo sostenibile</title>
      <lead>Nella sua seduta del 22 marzo 2019 il Consiglio federale ha nominato due delegati per l’Agenda 2030. L'Agenda 2030 è il quadro di riferimento internazionale per lo sviluppo sostenibile e un punto di riferimento per la politica svizzera in materia di sostenibilità. Il Consiglio federale vi attribuisce grande importanza e intende rafforzarne l'attuazione creando una nuova struttura organizzativa interna all'Amministrazione federale. Gli elementi chiave sono l'istituzione di un Consiglio direttivo interdipartimentale e la nomina di due delegati allo sviluppo sostenibile. La nuova struttura permette di radicare nell'Amministrazione i principi dell'Agenda 2030 che sarà attuata nel quadro della politica settoriale dei servizi federali e Dipartimenti.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;L'Agenda 2030 è l’interfaccia fra gli impegni nazionali e internazionali volti a trovare soluzioni congiunte per affrontare grandi sfide come il consumo di risorse e i cambiamenti climatici. Il fulcro è costituito dai 17 obiettivi di sviluppo sostenibile (OSS; Sustainable Devlopment Goals, SDG). Da un’ampia analisi sono emersi il comportamento della Svizzera nei confronti degli obiettivi e i settori dove tuttora sono necessari interventi di politica interna ed estera. I risultati dell’indagine sono stati presentati nel quadro del rapporto nazionale della Svizzera, presentato all'ONU nel 2018. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Consiglio direttivo per la gestione strategica dell'attuazione&lt;/b&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Per affrontare in modo efficace le sfide e le opportunità, il 14 dicembre 2018 il Consiglio federale ha istituito un «Consiglio direttivo Agenda 2030», nel quale tutti gli Uffici interessati sono rappresentati a livello di direzione. I suoi compiti principali sono la gestione e il coordinamento dei lavori di attuazione, come ad esempio il monitoraggio degli OSS in Svizzera, la redazione del rapporto nazionale per l'ONU, la priorizzazione delle principali sfide e opportunità per la Svizzera, la definizione di obiettivi nazionali, il coordinamento delle relative misure nonché la collaborazione con i Cantoni, i Comuni e gli attori non statali. Il Consiglio direttivo sostituisce l'attuale Comitato interdipartimentale sullo sviluppo sostenibile (CISvS). &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Due delegati allo sviluppo sostenibile assumeranno la direzione operativa&lt;/b&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Il 14 dicembre 2018, il Consiglio federale ha deciso di affidare la direzione operativa a due delegati allo sviluppo sostenibile. Nella sua seduta del 22 marzo 2019, il Consiglio federale ha nominato Daniel Dubas (41) collaboratore del Dipartimento dell'ambiente, dei trasporti, dell'energia e delle comunicazioni (DATEC) e Jacques Ducrest (52) collaboratore del Dipartimento degli affari esteri (DFAE) quali delegati per l'Agenda 2030.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Daniel Dubas ha studiato scienze politiche e conseguito un diploma in sviluppo urbano sostenibile; dal 2013 dirige la Sezione Sviluppo sostenibile dell'Ufficio federale dello sviluppo territoriale ARE.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Jacques Ducrest è un diplomatico con formazione giuridica (brevetto di avvocato e LL.M.) che, dal 2017, è capo supplente della Divisione Politiche estere settoriali del DFAE.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Oltre alle attività di coordinamento, i delegati sono tenuti a redigere un rapporto annuale all'attenzione del Consiglio federale sull'attuazione dell'Agenda 2030. La prima edizione è prevista per il gennaio 2020.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Elementi chiave del ciclo politico per uno sviluppo sostenibile&lt;/b&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In futuro, a livello nazionale l'Agenda 2030 sarà attuata principalmente attraverso la Strategia per uno sviluppo sostenibile (SSS), con orizzonte temporale 2020 - 2030, allo scopo di garantire la continuità e la sicurezza di pianificazione a lungo termine. Il piano d'azione della SSS continuerà invece ad essere aggiornato ogni quattro anni, in concomitanza con il programma di legislatura. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Questi lavori saranno coordinati dal Consiglio direttivo di cui sopra, sotto la direzione del delegato del DATEC. L’analisi della situazione e il rapporto nazionale all'attenzione dell'ONU saranno eseguiti ogni quattro anni a metà del periodo di legislatura. Il coordinamento dei lavori è affidato al Consiglio direttivo, sotto la direzione del delegato del DFAE. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sulla base del rapporto nazionale, questo ciclo politico biennale permette di tirare un bilancio intermedio dell'efficacia delle misure e di definire nuovi temi chiave per il successivo piano d'azione della SSS. Al più tardi entro fine 2020 saranno verificate l'efficacia e l'efficienza della nuova struttura organizzativa e dei relativi compiti che, se del caso, verranno adeguati.&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Stephan Scheidegger, Direttore supplente, Ufficio federale dello sviluppo territoriale (ARE), tel. +41 58 462 44 50 (comunicazione), stephan.scheidegger@are.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="188478">
        <title>DFAE: LʼAgenda 2030 per uno sviluppo sostenibile</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/agenda2030/it/home.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="188479">
        <title>ARE: LʼAgenda 2030 per uno sviluppo sostenibile</title>
        <uri>https://www.are.admin.ch/are/it/home/sviluppo-sostenibile/cooperazione-internazionale/l_agenda-2030-per-uno-sviluppo-sostenibile.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Federal government takes steps to advance implementation of 2030 Agenda for Sustainable Development</title>
      <lead>At its meeting on 22 March 2019, the Federal Council appointed two delegates for the 2030 Agenda. The 2030 Agenda constitutes a global framework for sustainable development and is the point of reference for Switzerland's sustainability policy. The Federal Council attaches great importance to the 2030 Agenda and is putting in place a new federal government structure to advance its implementation. The creation of an interdepartmental steering committee and the appointment of two delegates are core elements. The new structure will fully anchor the 2030 Agenda in Switzerland's federal administration. The 2030 Agenda will continue to be implemented within the framework of the sectoral policies of the federal offices and departments. </lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;The 2030 Agenda brings together national and international efforts to find collective solutions to major challenges such as the consumption of limited resources and climate change. At its heart are 17 Sustainable Development Goals (SDGs). A comprehensive baseline study has shown Switzerland's progress towards achieving the goals and where domestic and foreign policy action still needs to be taken. The results of this stocktaking were presented in Switzerland's national report to the UN in 2018. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;An interdepartmental committee to coordinate implementation&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;To effectively address the challenges and opportunities, the Federal Council set up a 2030 Agenda steering committee on 14 December 2018. The federal agencies which bear the main responsibility are represented at senior management level in this committee. The committee steers and coordinates the efforts to achieve the 2030 Agenda. This includes monitoring the SDGs in Switzerland, preparing the national report to the UN, setting priorities to reflect the biggest challenges and opportunities for Switzerland, setting national targets, coordinating appropriate measures and cooperating with the cantons, communes and non-state actors. The steering committee replaces the existing Interdepartmental Sustainable Development Committee (ISDC). &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Two 2030 Agenda delegates take over operational management&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;On 14 December 2018, the Federal Council decided to task two delegates to coordinate the operational aspects of the efforts to implement the 2030 Agenda. At its meeting on 22 March 2019, the Federal Council appointed Daniel Dubas from the Federal Department of the Environment, Transport, Energy and Communications (DETEC) and Jacques Ducrest from the Federal Department of Foreign Affairs as its 2030 Agenda delegates.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Daniel Dubas is a political scientist with a degree in sustainable urban development. He has headed the Sustainable Development Section of the Federal Office for Spatial Development (ARE) since 2013.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Jacques Ducrest is a diplomat with a legal background (LL.M and qualified lawyer). Since September 2017 he has been deputy head of the Sectoral Foreign Policies Division at the FDFA.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;In addition to their coordinating activities, the delegates must report annually to the Federal Council on the implementation of the 2030 Agenda. Their first report is due in January 2020.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Key elements of the policy cycle for sustainable development&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;At the national level, the 2030 Agenda will in future be implemented primarily through Switzerland's Sustainable Development Strategy (SDS). This will be realigned to cover the period 2020–2030 to ensure longer-term planning security and continuity. The SDS Action Plan will continue to be updated along with the new legislative programme every four years. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The steering committee will coordinate the updating of the Action Plan under the leadership of the DETEC delegate. The baseline study and national reports to the UN will be drawn up in the middle of each legislative period. The steering committee will coordinate this work under the leadership of the FDFA delegate. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;This policy cycle in two-year intervals makes it possible to use the national report as a basis to take stock of the effectiveness of the measures adopted and to set new priorities for the subsequent SDS Action Plan. By the end of 2022 at the latest, the effectiveness and efficiency of this new organisational structure and its tasks will be reviewed and, if necessary, adapted. &lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Stephan Scheidegger, Deputy Director, Federal Office for Spatial Development ARE, Tel. +41 58 466 18 00 (Communication), stephan.scheidegger@are.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="188480">
        <title>FDFA: 2030 Agenda for Sustainable Development</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/agenda2030/en/home.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="188481">
        <title>ARE: 2030 Agenda for Sustainable Development</title>
        <uri>https://www.are.admin.ch/are/en/home/sustainable-development/international-cooperation/2030agenda.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <offers>
      <offer id="46" org-id="812">
        <name lang="de">Nachhaltige Entwicklung</name>
        <name lang="fr">Développement durable</name>
        <name lang="it">Sviluppo sostenibile</name>
        <name lang="en">Sustainable spatial development</name>
      </offer>
    </offers>
    <keywords>
      <keyword id="820" org-id="812">
        <name lang="de">Nachhaltige Entwicklung</name>
        <name lang="fr">Développement durable</name>
        <name lang="it">Sviluppo sostenibile</name>
        <name lang="en">Sustainable development</name>
      </keyword>
    </keywords>
    <topics>
      <topic id="25">
        <name lang="de">Raumplanung</name>
        <name lang="fr">Aménagement du territoire</name>
        <name lang="it">Pianificazione del territorio</name>
        <name lang="en">Spatial Planning</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
