<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="9143" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2003-07-10</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="703" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>701</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Staatssekretariat für Wirtschaft</name>
      <name lang="fr">Secrétariat d'Etat à l'économie</name>
      <name lang="it">Segreteria di Stato dell'economia</name>
      <name lang="en">State Secretariat for Economic Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.seco.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.seco.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.seco.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.seco.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@seco.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@seco.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@seco.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@seco.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="701">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Wirtschaft, Bildung und Forschung</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'économie, de la formation et de la recherche</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'economia, della formazione e della ricerca</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Economic Affairs, Education and Research</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Die internationale Zusammenarbeit der Schweiz : Jahresbericht 2002</title>
      <teaser>Auf 1,46 Milliarden Franken belief sich im Jahr 2002 die öffentliche Entwicklungshilfe (APD – Aide publique au développement) der Schweiz. Das sind 0,32 Prozent des Bruttosozialproduktes (BSP), wie aus dem Jahresbericht der internationalen Zusammenarbeit der Schweiz hervorgeht.Der neu gestaltete und in eine einheitliche Broschüre gefasste Jahresbericht wurde am 10.07.2003 von der Direktion für Entwicklung und Zusammenarbeit DEZA und dem Staatssekretariat für Wirtschaft seco veröffentlicht.</teaser>
      <lead>Zusammenarbeit seit UNO-Beitritt noch wirkungsvollerAuf 1,46 Milliarden Franken belief sich im Jahr 2002 die öffentliche Entwicklungshilfe (APD – Aide publique au développement) der Schweiz. Das sind 0,32 Prozent des Bruttosozialproduktes (BSP), wie aus dem Jahresbericht der internationalen Zusammenarbeit der Schweiz hervorgeht. Der neu gestaltete und in eine einheitliche Broschüre gefasste Jahresbericht wurde am 10.07.2003 von der Direktion für Entwicklung und Zusammenarbeit DEZA und dem Staatssekretariat für Wirtschaft seco veröffentlicht.</lead>
      <text link="no">«Die Verbesserung der Lebensbedingungen der armen Menschen dieser Welt ist traditionell das wichtigste Ziel der Entwicklungszusammenarbeit der Schweiz», schreiben DEZA-Direktor Walter Fust und seco-Direktor David Syz im Editorial zum «Jahresbericht der Internationalen Zusammenarbeit der Schweiz 2002». Um dieses Ziel zu erreichen, war im Berichtsjahr die DEZA weltweit mit rund 1000 Projekten aktiv. Die Entwicklungszusammenarbeit der DEZA konzentrierte sich vor allem auf 17 Schwerpunktländer und 4 Sonderprogramme, während sich für die – ebenfalls bei der DEZA angesiedelte – Humanitäre Hilfe des Bundes in ihrer globalen Tätigkeit 16 Schwerpunktgebiete herauskristallisierten. Die handels- und wirtschaftspolitischen Massnahmen des seco richteten sich auf 16 Entwicklungsländer und 12 Transitionsländer. Wurde die internationale Zusammenarbeit früher schon sowohl in bilateralem als auch multilateralem Rahmen umgesetzt, so gestaltet sich seit dem UNO-Beitritt der Schweiz die Zusammenarbeit mit der Staatengemeinschaft noch wirkungsvoller.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Die öffentliche Entwicklungshilfe (APD - Aide publique au développement) der Schweiz belief sich 2002 auf 1,46 Milliarden Franken, was 0,32 Prozent des Brutto-Volkseinkommens entspricht. Im Vergleich zu 2001 ist ein temporärer Rückgang zu verzeichnen (2001: 0.34 %), der hauptsächlich auf eine Verzögerung beim Abschluss der 13. Wiederauffüllung der Internationalen Entwicklungsagentur (IDA) der Weltbank zurückzuführen ist. Die Schweiz bleibt somit immer noch weit entfernt von dem durch den Bundesrat bezeichneten Ziel von 0,4 Prozent des Bruttosozialprodukts.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Die schweizerische APD umfasst im Wesentlichen die Ausgaben der DEZA und des seco (knapp 90 %), schliesst aber auch die Beiträge anderer Bundesämter sowie der Kantone und Gemeinden mit ein. Die bilateralen Aufwendungen 2002 haben im Vergleich zu 2001 um rund 100 Mio. zugenommen. 50 Mio. Franken betreffen den vom Bundesrat gesprochenen Zusatzkredit für die humanitäre Hilfe zur Bewältigung von Flutschäden in Europa und Asien.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Während der DEZA-seco-Jahresbericht früher jeweils in drei Hefte gegliedert war, erfolgt jetzt die Präsentation zugunsten der Übersichtlichkeit in einer einzigen Broschüre. «Multilaterale Zusammenarbeit», «Bilaterale Entwicklungszusammenarbeit», «Wirtschaftliche Zusammenarbeit mit Entwicklungs- und Transitionsländern», «Humanitäre Hilfe» heissen die Hauptkapitel des Berichts, welchem ein statistischer Anhang folgt.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Der Jahresbericht ist in Deutsch, Französisch, Italienisch und Englisch erhältlich. Weitere Exemplare können bestellt werden bei:&amp;nbsp; &lt;u&gt;info@deza.admin.ch&lt;/u&gt;&amp;nbsp;oder via Telefon 031 – 322 44 12. Auch im Internet ist der Bericht abrufbar unter &lt;u&gt;www.deza.admin.ch&lt;/u&gt;&amp;nbsp;oder &lt;u&gt;www.seco.admin.ch&lt;/u&gt;&amp;nbsp;.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; DIREKTION FÜR ENTWICKLUNG&amp;nbsp;UND ZUSAMMENARBEIT (DEZA)&lt;br /&gt; Medien und Kommunikation&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; STAATSSEKRETARIAT FÜR WIRTSCHAFT (seco)&lt;br /&gt; Kommunikation/Information&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Weiterführende Informationen:&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Joachim Ahrens, Sprecher der DEZA&amp;nbsp;&lt;br /&gt; Tel. 031 322 35 59&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Christian Hofer, seco Information&lt;br /&gt; Tel. 079 328 74 72</text>
      <contact/>
      <attachment id="25554">
        <title>Jahresbericht der Internationalen Zusammenarbeit der Schweiz 2002</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>880</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/8081.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <link id="17593">
        <title>&lt;u&gt;www.deza.admin.ch&lt;/u&gt;</title>
        <uri>http://www.deza.admin.ch</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Rapport annuel de la coopération internationale de la Suisse 2002</title>
      <teaser>En 2002, l’aide publique au développement (APD) de la Suisse s’est montée à 1,46 milliard de francs. Cette somme équivaut à 0,32 % du produit national brut (PNB), comme l’indique le rapport annuel sur la coopération internationale de la Suisse, que la Direction du développement et de la coopération (DDC) et le Secrétariat d’Etat à l’économie (seco) viennent de rendre public. Ce rapport a d’ailleurs fait peau neuve: il se présentait le 10.07.2003 sous la forme d’une brochure qui regroupe les différents domaines d'activité de la coopération suisse.</teaser>
      <lead>Une coopération encore plus efficace depuis l’adhésion à l’ONUEn 2002, l’aide publique au développement (APD) de la Suisse s’est montée à 1,46 milliard de francs. Cette somme équivaut à 0,32 % du produit national brut (PNB), comme l’indique le rapport annuel sur la coopération internationale de la Suisse, que la Direction du développement et de la coopération (DDC) et le Secrétariat d’Etat à l’économie (seco) viennent de rendre public. Ce rapport a d’ailleurs fait peau neuve: il se présentait le 10.07.2003 sous la forme d’une brochure qui regroupe les différents domaines d'activité de la coopération suisse.</lead>
      <text link="no">«L’objectif premier des efforts de la coopération internationale de la Suisse est depuis toujours d’améliorer les conditions d’existence des pauvres de la planète.» C’est en ces termes que le directeur de la DDC, Walter Fust, et le directeur du seco, David Syz, ouvrent le Rapport annuel de la coopération internationale de la Suisse 2002. Pour atteindre cet objectif, la DDC a mené quelque 1000 projets de par le monde. Elle a concentré son aide sur dix-sept pays prioritaires et quatre programmes spéciaux, tandis que l’aide humanitaire de la Confédération – qui fait également partie de la DDC – a été active dans seize régions prioritaires. Quant aux mesures de politique économique et commerciale, mises en œuvre par le seco, elles ont bénéficié à seize pays en développement et à douze pays en transition. Si la Suisse déployait, par le passé déjà, ses efforts en faveur du développement tant au niveau bilatéral qu’au niveau multilatéral, son adhésion à l’ONU lui a permis d’accroître encore l’efficacité de sa coopération avec la communauté internationale.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; En 2002, l’aide publique au développement (APD) de la Suisse s’est montée à 1,46 milliard de francs, soit l’équivalent de 0,32% du produit national brut. En comparaison avec 2001 (0,34 %), ce pourcentage représente un léger recul. Celui-ci n’est toutefois que temporaire et surtout dû au retard pris par la 13e reconstitution des ressources de l’Association internationale de développement (AID). Quoi qu’il en soit, la Suisse est encore loin de l’objectif fixé par le Conseil fédéral visant à consacrer 0,4 % du produit national brut à l’APD.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; L’aide publique suisse au développement comprend les dépenses de la DDC et du seco (près de 90 % du total), mais aussi les contributions d’autres services fédéraux ainsi que celles des cantons et des communes. Comparées à celles de 2001, les dépenses bilatérales ont augmenté de 100 millions de francs environ en 2002. Sur ce total, 50 millions correspondent au crédit complémentaire accordé par le Conseil fédéral pour participer à la réparation des dégâts causés par les inondations en Europe et en Asie.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Alors que le rapport annuel de la DDC et du seco paraissait autrefois en trois cahiers distincts, il revêt à présent la forme d’une brochure unique, ce qui simplifie sa lecture. Les principaux chapitres ont pour titre «coopération multilatérale», «coopération bilatérale au développement», «coopération économique avec des pays en développement et des pays en transition» et «aide humanitaire». Ils sont complétés par une annexe statistique.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Le rapport annuel est publié en allemand, en français, en italien et en anglais. Il peut être commandé par courrier électronique (&lt;u&gt;info@deza.admin.ch&lt;/u&gt;) ou par téléphone (031 322 44 12). On peut également le consulter sur Internet aux adresses suivantes: &lt;u&gt;www.deza.admin.ch&lt;/u&gt;&amp;nbsp;ou&amp;nbsp; &lt;u&gt;www.seco.admin.ch&lt;/u&gt;.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; DIRECTION DU DÉVELOPPEMENT ET DE LA COOPÉRATION (DDC)&amp;nbsp;&lt;br /&gt; Médias et communication&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; SECRÉTARIAT D’ÉTAT À L’ÉCONOMIE (seco)&lt;br /&gt; Communication/Information&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Pour de plus amples informations:&lt;br /&gt; Joachim Ahrens, porte-parole de la DDC&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;br /&gt; Tél. 031 322 35 59&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Christian Hofer, Information seco&lt;br /&gt; Tél. 079 328 74 72</text>
      <contact/>
      <attachment id="25555">
        <title>Rapport annuel de la coopération internationale de la Suisse 2002</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>876</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/8082.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <link id="17593">
        <title>&lt;u&gt;www.deza.admin.ch&lt;/u&gt;</title>
        <uri>http://www.deza.admin.ch</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>La cooperazione internazionale della Svizzera: Rapporto annuale 2002</title>
      <teaser>Nel 2002 il contributo degli enti statali svizzeri allo sviluppo (APD «Aide publique au développement») è stato di 1,46 miliardi di franchi, pari allo 0,32 percento del prodotto nazionale lordo (PNL). Ciò emerge dal «Rapporto annuale della Cooperazione internazionale della Svizzera», pubblicato il 10.07.2003 dalla Direzione dello Sviluppo e della Cooperazione DSC e dal Segretariato di Stato dell’Economia seco in una veste rinnovata ed in un unico opuscolo.</teaser>
      <lead>Dopo l'adesione alle Nazioni Unite: cooperazione ancora più efficace Nel 2002 il contributo degli enti statali svizzeri allo sviluppo (APD «Aide publique au développement») è stato di 1,46 miliardi di franchi, pari allo 0,32 percento del prodotto nazionale lordo (PNL). Ciò emerge dal «Rapporto annuale della Cooperazione internazionale della Svizzera», pubblicato il 10.07.2003 dalla Direzione dello Sviluppo e della Cooperazione DSC e dal Segretariato di Stato dell’Economia seco in una veste rinnovata ed in un unico opuscolo.</lead>
      <text link="no">«L’obiettivo primario della cooperazione elvetica è, tradizionalmente, quello di migliorare le condizioni di vita delle persone più povere al mondo», scrivono il Direttore della DSC Walter Fust ed il Direttore del seco David Syz nell’introduzione al «Rapporto annuale della Cooperazione internazionale della Svizzera 2002». Per conseguire quest’obiettivo, nell’anno in questione la DSC è stata attiva, a livello mondiale, con un migliaio di progetti. La cooperazione allo sviluppo della DSC si è concentrata soprattutto su 17 paesi prioritari e 4 programmi speciali, mentre le attività globali dell’Aiuto Umanitario della Confederazione – ugualmente facente parte della DSC – sono confluite in 16 regioni prioritarie. Le misure commerciali e politico-economiche del seco hanno interessato 16 paesi in via di sviluppo e 12 paesi in transizione. Se già nel passato la cooperazione internazionale è stata realizzata sia in un quadro bilaterale che in un quadro multilaterale, dall’adesione della Svizzera alle Nazioni Unite in poi la cooperazione con la comunità degli Stati risulta ancora più efficace.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Nel 2002 l’aiuto pubblico allo sviluppo della Svizzera&amp;nbsp; ammontò a 1,46 miliardi di franchi, pari allo 0,32 percento del reddito nazionale lordo. Rispetto al 2001 si è registrata una flessione temporanea (2001: 0,34 %), dovuta in primo luogo al ritardo della decisione riguardo alla 13a ricostituzione del capitale dell’ Agenzia per lo Sviluppo Internazionale (IDA) della Banca Mondiale. La Svizzera è ancora lungi dal realizzare l'obiettivo dello 0,4 % del prodotto nazionale lordo stabilito dal Consiglio Federale.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; L’APS comprende in gran linea gli sborsi della DSC e del seco (che rappresentano all’incirca il 90 %), ma include anche i contributi di altri uffici federali e di cantoni e comuni. Rispetto al 2001, la spesa bilaterale per il 2002 è cresciuta di 100 milioni. 50 milioni di franchi concernono il credito supplementare accordato dal Consiglio Federale per l'aiuto umanitario a seguito delle alluvioni che hanno investito l’Europa e l’Asia.&lt;br /&gt; In passato il rapporto annuale della DSC e del seco era strutturato in tre fascicoli separati; oggi esso viene presentato in un unico opuscolo, più chiaro. «Cooperazione multilaterale», «Cooperazione allo sviluppo bilaterale», «Cooperazione economica con i paesi in via di&amp;nbsp;sviluppo e in transizione» ed «Aiuto umanitario» sono i principali capitoli del rapporto, seguito da un’appendice statistica.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Il rapporto annuale è disponibile in lingua italiana, francese, tedesca ed inglese. Ulteriori esemplari possono essere ordinati all’indirizzo &lt;u&gt;info@deza.admin.ch&lt;/u&gt;&amp;nbsp;o telefonicamente al numero 031 322 44 12. Il rapporto è disponibile anche nell' Internet al sito &lt;u&gt;www.dsc.admin.ch&lt;/u&gt;&amp;nbsp;o&amp;nbsp;&lt;u&gt;www.seco.admin.ch&lt;/u&gt;.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; DIREZIONE DELLO SVILUPPO E DELLA COOPERAZIONE (DSC)&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;br /&gt; Media e Comunicazione&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; SEGRETARIATO DI STATO DELL’ECONOMIA (seco)&lt;br /&gt; Comunicazione / Informazione&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Per ulteriori informazioni rivolgersi a:&lt;br /&gt; Joachim Ahrens, portavoce della DSC&lt;br /&gt; Tel. 031 322 35 59&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Christian Hofer, Informazione seco&lt;br /&gt; Tel. 079 328 74 72</text>
      <contact/>
      <attachment id="25556">
        <title>Rapporto annuale della coperazione internazionale della Svizzera 2002</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>824</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/8083.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <link id="17593">
        <title>&lt;u&gt;www.deza.admin.ch&lt;/u&gt;</title>
        <uri>http://www.deza.admin.ch</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Switzerland's international cooperation: Annual Report 2002</title>
      <teaser>Switzerland's new-look annual report on its international cooperation activities says official development assistance (ODA) amounted to SFr. 1.46 billion in 2002, or 0.32 % of the country's gross national product (GNP). The newly-designed single-volume annual report was released on 10.07.2003 by the Swiss Agency for Development and Cooperation, SDC, and the State Secretariat for Economic Affairs, seco.</teaser>
      <lead>Cooperation even more effective with UN membershipSwitzerland's new-look annual report on its international cooperation activities says official development assistance (ODA) amounted to SFr. 1.46 billion in 2002, or 0.32 % of the country's gross national product (GNP). The newly-designed single-volume annual report was released on 10.07.2003 by the Swiss Agency for Development and Cooperation, SDC, and the State Secretariat for Economic Affairs, seco.</lead>
      <text link="no">In a joint editorial in the «Annual Report on Swiss International Cooperation 2002», SDC Director-General Walter Fust and seco Director David Syz say that «traditionally, the most important goal of Switzerland's development cooperation is the improvement of the living conditions of the world's poverty-stricken populations». In pursuit of this goal, the SDC was actively involved in some 1,000 projects around the world during the reporting year. The SDC's development cooperation concentrated primarily on 17 priority countries and on four special programs. While humanitarian aid - also under SDC responsibility - was globally active, 16 countries required particular attention. Seco’s trade and economic policy measures were aimed at 16 developing countries and 12 countries with transition economies. The report says that although in the past, Swiss international cooperation was implemented within both bilateral and multilateral frameworks, ever since Switzerland joined the United Nations, its cooperation with the international community has become even more effective.&amp;nbsp;&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; In 2002, Swiss official development assistance (ODA) reached SFr. 1.46 billion, or 0.32 % of gross national product, a temporary decline from the 2001 figure of 0.34 %, says the report.&amp;nbsp; This is attributable mainly to the protracted concluding negotiations on the 13th replenishment of the World Bank’s International Development Association (IDA). Switzerland is still far from reaching the goal of 0.4 % of GNP set by the Federal Council.&amp;nbsp;&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; While Switzerland's ODA is essentially composed of spending by the SDC and seco (nearly 90%), it does however also include the contributions of other federal offices as well as those of the Swiss cantons and municipalities. When compared with 2001, bilateral expenditures rose by some SFr. 100 million. A supplementary credit of SFr. 50 million was allocated by the Federal Council for humanitarian aid to flood-ravaged areas in Europe and in Asia.&amp;nbsp;&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Until this year the SDC-seco annual report was printed in three separate booklets. The 2002 edition consists of a single brochure for the sake of enhanced clarity.&amp;nbsp; The principal chapters are Multilateral Cooperation, Bilateral Development Cooperation, Economic Cooperation with Developing and Transition Countries, and Humanitarian Aid. The report is rounded off with a statistical annex.&amp;nbsp;&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; The annual report is available in German, French, Italian, and English. Copies can be ordered at &lt;u&gt;info@deza.admin.ch&lt;/u&gt;&amp;nbsp;or by phone: 031 322 44 12. The report can also be found at&amp;nbsp; &lt;u&gt;www.deza.admin.ch&lt;/u&gt;&amp;nbsp;or&amp;nbsp;&lt;u&gt;www.seco.admin.ch&lt;/u&gt;.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; SWISS AGENCY FOR DEVELOPMENT&amp;nbsp;AND COOPERATION, SDC&lt;br /&gt; Media and Communications&amp;nbsp;&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; STATE SECRETARIAT FOR ECONOMIC AFFAIRS (seco)&lt;br /&gt; Communication/Information&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; For further information, contact:&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Joachim Ahrens, SDC spokesperson&amp;nbsp;&lt;br /&gt; Tel. 031 322 35 59&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Christian Hofer, seco Information&lt;br /&gt; Tel. 079 328 74 72</text>
      <contact/>
      <attachment id="25557">
        <title>Switzerland's international cooperation annual report 2002</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>876</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/8084.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <link id="17593">
        <title>&lt;u&gt;www.deza.admin.ch&lt;/u&gt;</title>
        <uri>http://www.deza.admin.ch</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="47">
        <name lang="de">Wirtschaft</name>
        <name lang="fr">Économie</name>
        <name lang="it">Economia</name>
        <name lang="en">Economic Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
