<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="83920" revoked="no">
    <version>2</version>
    <pubdate>2021-06-11</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="701" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>701</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Wirtschaft, Bildung und Forschung</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'économie, de la formation et de la recherche</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'economia, della formazione e della ricerca</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Economic Affairs, Education and Research</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="701">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Wirtschaft, Bildung und Forschung</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'économie, de la formation et de la recherche</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'economia, della formazione e della ricerca</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Economic Affairs, Education and Research</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Treffen mit König und Premierminister bei Präsidialbesuch in Schweden</title>
      <lead>Bundespräsident Guy Parmelin reist am Montag, 14. Juni 2021, nach Schweden; anlässlich des Präsidialbesuchs wird er von König Carl XVI. Gustaf empfangen. Auf dem Programm stehen zudem Gespräche mit Premierminister Stefan Löfven, Unternehmens-, Industrie- und Innovationsminister Ibrahim Baylan, Bildungs- und Forschungsministerin Matilda Ernkrans und mit Parlamentspräsident Andreas Norlén. </lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;In den Gespräche sollen die gemeinsamen Ziele auf internationaler Ebene erörtert werden, die Europapolitik sowie die politische, wirtschaftliche und wissenschaftliche Zusammenarbeit. Vorgesehen ist zudem ein Austausch über die wirtschaftspolitischen Massnahmen zur Bewältigung der Pandemie. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Unterzeichnet werden soll in Anwesenheit des Bundespräsidenten und von Premierminister Löfven eine Absichtserklärung zwischen den Innovationsagenturen Innosuisse und Vinnova zur Vertiefung der Kooperation, die in diesem Bereich seit 2013 besteht. Innosuisse-Direktorin Annalise Eggimann und Staatssekretärin Martina Hirayama, Direktorin des Staatssekretariats für Bildung, Forschung und Innovation (SBFI), zählen zur Schweizer Delegation, die in Stockholm auch mit Vertreterinnen und Vertretern der schwedischen Wissenschaft und Forschung zusammenkommen wird. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Der bis anhin letzte Besuch eines schweizerischen Bundespräsidenten in Schweden fand 2009 statt. Die beiden Länder verbinden weitgehend identische Werte und Ziele. Die Zusammenarbeit in multilateralen Gremien, vor allem in der UNO und der OSZE, ist von besonderer Bedeutung. Schweden ist zudem der wichtigste Handels- und Investitionspartner der Schweiz im nordischen Raum.&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Kommunikation GS-WBF Tel. +41 58 462 20 07 info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="217344">
        <title>Zusätzliche Verweise</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home/vertretungen-und-reisehinweise/schweden/bilatereale-beziehungenschweizschweden.html#:~:text=Geschichte%20der%20bilateralen%20Beziehungen&amp;text=Schweden%20anerkannte%20die%20Schweizer%20Neutralit%C3%A4t,eine%20st%C3</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Visite présidentielle en Suède : rencontre avec le roi et le premier ministre</title>
      <lead>Lundi 14 juin 2021, le président de la Confédération, Guy Parmelin, se rendra en Suède, où il sera reçu par le roi, Carl XVI Gustaf. Il s’entretiendra de plus avec le premier ministre, Stefan Löfven, le ministre des entreprises, de l’industrie et de l’innovation, Ibrahim Baylan, la ministre de l’enseignement supérieur et de la recherche, Matilda Ernkrans, et le président du Parlement, Andreas Norlén.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Les entretiens porteront sur les objectifs communs au niveau international, la politique européenne et la coopération politique, économique et scientifique. Un échange sur les mesures de politique économique de lutte contre la pandémie est également prévu.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Une déclaration d’intention entre les agences pour l’encouragement de l’innovation Innosuisse et Vinnova visant à approfondir la coopération lancée dans ce domaine en 2013 devrait en outre être signée, en présence du président de la Confédération et du premier ministre suédois. La directrice d’Innosuisse, Annalise Eggimann, et la secrétaire d’État à la formation, à la recherche et à l’innovation (SEFRI), Martina Hirayama, feront partie de la délégation suisse, qui, à Stockholm, rencontrera aussi des représentants suédois de la science et de la recherche.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;La dernière visite d’un président de la Confédération en Suède remonte à 2009. Les deux pays partagent de nombreux valeurs et objectifs. La coopération au sein d’organisations multilatérales, notamment l’ONU et l’OSCE, est d’une importance toute particulière. La Suède est par ailleurs le premier partenaire de commerce et d’investissement de la Suisse dans la région nordique.&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Communication SG DEFR tél. +41 58 462 20 07 info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="217343">
        <title>Informations complémentaires</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae/representations-et-conseils-aux-voyageurs/suede/suisse-suede.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions>
        <revision date="2021-06-11 09:34" type="R"/>
      </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Incontro con Sua Maestà il Re e con il Primo ministro in occasione di una visita presidenziale in Svezia</title>
      <lead>Il Presidente della Confederazione Guy Parmelin si recherà in Svezia lunedì 14 giugno 2021; durante la visita presidenziale sarà ricevuto da Sua Maestà Re Carlo XVI Gustavo. Sono in programma anche colloqui con il Primo ministro Stefan Löfven, con il Ministro delle imprese, dell’industria e dell’innovazione Ibrahim Baylan, con la Ministra della formazione e della ricerca Matilda Ernkrans e con il Presidente del Parlamento Andreas Norlén. </lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;L’obiettivo dei colloqui è discutere degli obiettivi comuni a livello internazionale, della politica europea nonché della collaborazione politica, economica e scientifica.&lt;b&gt; &lt;/b&gt;È inoltre previsto uno scambio di vedute sui provvedimenti politico-economici adottati per fronteggiare la pandemia. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Alla presenza del Presidente della Confederazione e del Primo ministro Löfven verrà firmata una dichiarazione d’intenti fra le agenzie per la promozione dell’innovazione Innosuisse e Vinnova, volta a intensificare la cooperazione esistente in questo settore dal 2013. La direttrice di Innosuisse, Annalise Eggimann, e la Segretaria di Stato Martina Hirayama, direttrice della Segreteria di Stato per la formazione, la ricerca e l’innovazione (SEFRI), faranno parte della delegazione svizzera che a Stoccolma incontrerà anche rappresentanti svedesi della scienza e della ricerca. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;L’ultima visita di un presidente svizzero in Svezia risale al 2009. I due Paesi sono accomunati da valori e obiettivi praticamente identici. La collaborazione all’interno di organismi multilaterali, soprattutto dell’ONU e dell’OSCE, riveste un’importanza particolare. La Svezia è inoltre il principale partner della Svizzera per quanto concerne gli scambi commerciali e gli investimenti nel Nord. &lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Comunicazione SG-DEFR tel. +41 58 462 20 07 info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="217342">
        <title>Maggiori approfondimenti</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae/rappresentanze-e-consigli-di-viaggio/svezia/svizzera-svezia.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>President Parmelin to meet with king and prime minister during presidential visit to Sweden</title>
      <lead>President Guy Parmelin will travel to Sweden on 14 June. During his presidential visit he will be received by King Carl XVI Gustaf. Separate talks are also scheduled to take place with Prime Minister Stefan Löfven, Minister of Enterprise, Industry and Innovation Ibrahim Baylan, Minister for Higher Education and Research Matilda Ernkrans and Speaker of Parliament Andreas Norlén.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;The purpose of the talks is to discuss common goals at the international level, European policy and political, economic and scientific cooperation. The visit will also include talks on economic policy measures to address the pandemic. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;In addition, a declaration of intent will be signed in the presence of the Swiss president and the Swedish prime minister between Innosuisse and Vinnova on strengthening the cooperation that has existed between the two innovation agencies since 2013. The Swiss delegation, which includes Innosuisse Director Annalise Eggimann and State Secretary Martina Hirayama, Director of the State Secretariat for Education, Research and Innovation (SERI), will also meet with representatives of the Swedish science and research community in Stockholm.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The last visit by a Swiss president to Sweden took place in 2009. The two countries largely share the same values and objectives. Cooperation in multilateral bodies, particularly the UN and the OSCE, is very important. Sweden is also Switzerland’s largest trading and investment partner in the Nordic region.&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>GS-EAER Communications Tel. +41 58 462 20 07 info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="217341">
        <title>Further information</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home/vertretungen-und-reisehinweise/schweden/bilatereale-beziehungenschweizschweden.html#:~:text=Geschichte%20der%20bilateralen%20Beziehungen&amp;text=Schweden%20anerkannte%20die%20Schweizer%20Neutralit%C3%A4t,eine%20st%C3</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="8">
        <name lang="de">Bildung und Forschung</name>
        <name lang="fr">Formation et recherche</name>
        <name lang="it">Formazione e ricerca</name>
        <name lang="en">Education and Research</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="33">
        <name lang="de">Bundespräsident/-in</name>
        <name lang="fr">Président/e de la Confédération</name>
        <name lang="it">Presidente della Confederazione</name>
        <name lang="en">President of the Swiss Confederation</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="45">
        <name lang="de">Technologie</name>
        <name lang="fr">Technologie</name>
        <name lang="it">Tecnologia</name>
        <name lang="en">Technology</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="47">
        <name lang="de">Wirtschaft</name>
        <name lang="fr">Économie</name>
        <name lang="it">Economia</name>
        <name lang="en">Economic Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
