<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="83917" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2021-06-11</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="804" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>801</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Generalsekretariat UVEK</name>
      <name lang="fr">Secrétariat général DETEC</name>
      <name lang="it">Segreteria generale DATEC</name>
      <name lang="en">General Secretariat of the Federal Department of Environment, Transport, Energy and Communications; General Secretariat DETEC</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.uvek.admin.ch/uvek/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.uvek.admin.ch/uvek/fr/home.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.uvek.admin.ch/uvek/it/home.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.uvek.admin.ch/uvek/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-uvek.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-uvek.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-uvek.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-uvek.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="810" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>801</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Bundesamt für Kommunikation</name>
      <name lang="fr">Office fédéral de la communication</name>
      <name lang="it">Ufficio federale delle comunicazioni</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Office of Communications</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.bakom.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.ofcom.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.ufcom.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.ofcom.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">media@bakom.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">media@bakom.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">media@bakom.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">media@bakom.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="801">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Umwelt, Verkehr, Energie und Kommunikation</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'environnement, des transports, de l'énergie et de la communication</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'ambiente, dei trasporti, dell'energia e delle comunicazioni</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of the Environment, Transport, Energy and Communications</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.uvek.admin.ch/uvek/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.uvek.admin.ch/uvek/fr/home.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.uvek.admin.ch/uvek/it/home.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.uvek.admin.ch/uvek/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-uvek.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-uvek.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-uvek.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-uvek.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Ministerkonferenz des Europarats: Schweiz setzt sich für den Schutz von Medienschaffenden ein</title>
      <lead>Bundesrätin Simonetta Sommaruga ist beunruhigt über die zunehmende Verschlechterung der Arbeitsbedingungen für Journalistinnen und Journalisten. An der virtuellen Ministerkonferenz des Europarats zu Medien und Informationsgesellschaft vom 11. Juni 2021 unterstrich sie die Bereitschaft der Schweiz, dieser Entwicklung Einhalt zu gebieten und die Massnahmen zur Stärkung der Meinungs- und Medienfreiheit in Europa zu unterstützen.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;«Angriffe auf Medienschaffende und die Straflosigkeit bei solchen Verbrechen sind als Angriffe auf die Demokratie selbst zu betrachten», erklärte Bundesrätin Simonetta Sommaruga in ihrer Rede. Sie betonte die zentrale Rolle von Journalistinnen und Journalisten für eine funktionierende Demokratie und kritisierte die Verschlechterung der Situation für Medienschaffende während der Pandemie in Europa. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Im Einklang mit den Empfehlungen des Europarats kündigte Bundesrätin Sommaruga die Absicht der Schweiz an, einen nationalen Aktionsplan zum Schutz von Medienschaffenden zu erarbeiten. Sie würdigte auch die wichtige Arbeit des Europarats beim Schutz der Meinungs- und Medienfreiheit im digitalen Zeitalter.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Unter dem Titel «Künstliche Intelligenz - Intelligente Politik» diskutierten die Ministerinnen und Minister der 47 Mitgliedstaaten des Europarats die Veränderungen in der Medienlandschaft durch die Digitalisierung. Im Anschluss verabschiedeten sie eine Erklärung und vier Resolutionen zur Nutzung künstlicher Intelligenz und zur Schlüsselfunktion der Internet-Intermediäre im Medienbereich, zur Sicherheit von Medienschaffenden sowie den Auswirkungen der Covid-19 Pandemie auf die Meinungsfreiheit. Die Ministerkonferenz wurde vom Lenkungsausschuss für Medien und Informationsgesellschaft (CDMSI) des Europarates organisiert, in dem das Bundesamt für Kommunikation die Schweiz vertritt. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Die Schweiz trat dem Europarat 1963 bei, 14 Jahre nach seiner Gründung. Der Europarat ist eine paneuropäische Organisation mit 47 Mitgliedstaaten.&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Bundesamt für Kommunikation BAKOM Medienstelle +41 58 460 55 50, media@bakom.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="217303">
        <title>Rede von Simonetta Sommaruga (auf Französisch)</title>
        <uri>https://www.uvek.admin.ch/uvek/fr/home/detec/medias/discours.msg-id-83916.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Conférence ministérielle du Conseil de l’Europe : la Suisse s’engage en faveur de la protection des professionnels des médias</title>
      <lead>La conseillère fédérale Simonetta Sommaruga s’inquiète de la détérioration croissante des conditions de travail des journalistes. Lors de la Conférence ministérielle virtuelle du Conseil de l’Europe sur les médias et la société de l’information du 11 juin 2021, elle a souligné la volonté de la Suisse de mettre un terme à cette évolution et de soutenir les mesures visant à renforcer la liberté d’expression et la liberté des médias en Europe.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;« Les attaques contre des représentants des médias, et l’impunité pour de tels crimes, doivent être considérées comme des attaques contre la démocratie elle-même », a déclaré la conseillère fédérale Simonetta Sommaruga dans son discours. Elle a souligné le rôle central des journalistes pour le bon fonctionnement d’une démocratie et a critiqué l’aggravation de leur situation en Europe, une tendance qui s’est encore accentuée durant la pandémie. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Conformément aux recommandations du Conseil de l’Europe, la conseillère fédérale Simonetta Sommaruga a annoncé l’intention de la Suisse d’élaborer un plan d’action national pour la protection des représentants des médias. Elle a également salué le travail important réalisé par le Conseil de l’Europe pour protéger la liberté d’expression et la liberté des médias à l’ère numérique.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;À l’occasion de cette conférence intitulée « Intelligence artificielle – Politique intelligente », les ministres des 47 États membres du Conseil de l’Europe ont discuté des changements dans le paysage médiatique liés à la numérisation. Ils ont ensuite adopté une déclaration et quatre résolutions sur l’utilisation de l’intelligence artificielle, le rôle clé des intermédiaires Internet dans le secteur des médias, la sécurité des journalistes et l’impact de la pandémie de COVID-19 sur la liberté d’expression. La conférence ministérielle était organisée par le Comité directeur sur les médias et la société de l’information (CDMSI) du Conseil de l’Europe, au sein duquel l’Office fédéral de la communication représente la Suisse. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;La Suisse a rejoint le Conseil de l’Europe en 1963, quatorze ans après sa fondation. Le Conseil de l’Europe est une organisation paneuropéenne qui compte 47 États membres.&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Office fédéral de la communication OFCOM Service de presse +41 58 460 55 50, media@bakom.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="217304">
        <title>Discours de Simonetta Sommaruga</title>
        <uri>https://www.uvek.admin.ch/uvek/fr/home/detec/medias/discours.msg-id-83916.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Conferenza ministeriale del Consiglio d'Europa: la Svizzera si adopera per la protezione dei giornalisti</title>
      <lead>La consigliera federale Simonetta Sommaruga è preoccupata per il peggioramento delle condizioni di lavoro dei giornalisti. In occasione della Conferenza ministeriale virtuale del Consiglio d'Europa sui media e la società dell'informazione dell'11 giugno 2021, la consigliera federale ha sottolineato la volontà della Svizzera di porre fine a questa evoluzione e di sostenere le misure volte a rafforzare la libertà di espressione e dei media in Europa.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;"Gli attacchi ai professionisti dei media e l'impunità di tali crimini vanno considerati come attacchi alla democrazia stessa", ha detto la consigliera federale nella sua allocuzione. Simonetta Sommaruga ha sottolineato il ruolo centrale svolto dai giornalisti in una vera società democratica, criticando il peggioramento della loro situazione durante la pandemia in Europa. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In linea con le raccomandazioni del Consiglio d'Europa, la consigliera federale Sommaruga ha annunciato l'intenzione della Svizzera di elaborare un piano d'azione nazionale per la protezione dei giornalisti. Inoltre ha reso omaggio all'importante lavoro del Consiglio d'Europa a favore della libertà di espressione e dei media nell'era digitale.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Durante la conferenza, intitolata «Intelligenza artificiale - Politica intelligente», i ministri dei 47 Stati membri del Consiglio d'Europa hanno discusso dei cambiamenti nel paesaggio mediatico dovuti alla digitalizzazione. A chiusura dei lavori, i ministri hanno adottato una dichiarazione e quattro risoluzioni sull'uso dell'intelligenza artificiale e sul ruolo chiave degli intermediari Internet nel settore dei media, sulla sicurezza dei giornalisti e sull'impatto della pandemia di COVID-19 sulla libertà di espressione. La conferenza ministeriale è stata organizzata dal Comitato direttivo del Consiglio d'Europa sui media e la società dell'informazione (CDMSI), nel quale la Svizzera è rappresentata dall'Ufficio federale delle comunicazioni. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;La Svizzera ha aderito al Consiglio d'Europa nel 1963, 14 anni dopo la sua istituzione. Il Consiglio d'Europa è un'organizzazione paneuropea di cui fanno parte 47 Stati.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Ufficio federale delle comunicazioni UFCOM Servizio stampa Tel. +41 58 460 55 50, media@bakom.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="217305">
        <title>Allocuzione di Simonetta Sommaruga (in francese)</title>
        <uri>https://www.uvek.admin.ch/uvek/fr/home/detec/medias/discours.msg-id-83916.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Council of Europe Ministerial Conference: Switzerland advocates for the protection of journalists</title>
      <lead>Federal Councillor Simonetta Sommaruga is concerned by the continued deterioration of working conditions experienced by journalists and media professionals. At the Council of Europe’s virtual Ministerial Conference on Media and Information Society on 11 June, she stressed Switzerland’s willingness to reverse this trend and support measures to strengthen freedom of expression and freedom of the media in Europe.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;“Attacks on journalists and media professionals, and the impunity with which such crimes are committed, should be deemed as attacks on democracy itself,” stated Federal Councillor Simonetta Sommaruga in her speech. She stressed the key role played by journalists and media professionals in a functioning democracy and criticised the deterioration with regard to the safety of media professionals in Europe during the pandemic.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In line with the Council of Europe’s recommendations, Federal Councillor Sommaruga announced Switzerland’s intention to develop a national action plan to protect media professionals. She also acknowledged the important work of the Council of Europe in protecting freedom of expression and the freedom of the media in the digital age.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Under the heading of ‘Artificial Intelligence – Intelligent Politics’, ministers from the 47 member states of the Council of Europe discussed the changes to the media landscape brought about by digitalisation, and subsequently adopted a political declaration and four resolutions addressing issues such as the impact of AI products and services on freedom of expression, the key role played by online media intermediaries, the safety of media professionals, and the impact of the COVID-19 pandemic on freedom of expression. The Ministerial Conference was organised by the Council of Europe’s Steering Committee on Media and Information Society (CDMSI), in which Switzerland is represented by the Federal Office of Communications.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Switzerland became a member of the Council of Europe in 1963, 14 years after the organisation was founded. The Council of Europe is pan-European organisation with 47 member states. &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Federal Office of Communications OFCOM Press service, tel. +41 58 460 55 50 media@bakom.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="217306">
        <title>Speech given by Federal Councillor Sommaruga (in French)</title>
        <uri>https://www.uvek.admin.ch/uvek/fr/home/detec/medias/discours.msg-id-83916.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <keywords>
      <keyword id="210" org-id="804">
        <name lang="de">Bundesrat</name>
        <name lang="fr">Conseil fédéral</name>
        <name lang="it">Consiglio federale</name>
        <name lang="en">Federal Council</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="560" org-id="804">
        <name lang="de">Internationales</name>
        <name lang="fr">Affaires internationales</name>
        <name lang="it">Affari Internazionali</name>
        <name lang="en">International Affairs</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="5050" org-id="804">
        <name lang="de">Medien</name>
        <name lang="fr">Medien</name>
        <name lang="it">Medien</name>
        <name lang="en">Medien</name>
      </keyword>
    </keywords>
    <topics>
      <topic id="19">
        <name lang="de">Medien</name>
        <name lang="fr">Médias</name>
        <name lang="it">Media</name>
        <name lang="en">Media</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="28">
        <name lang="de">Telekommunikation</name>
        <name lang="fr">Télécommunications</name>
        <name lang="it">Telecomunicazione</name>
        <name lang="en">Telecommunications</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="36">
        <name lang="de">Informatik und E-Government</name>
        <name lang="fr">Informatique et cyberadministration</name>
        <name lang="it">Informatica ed e-government</name>
        <name lang="en">IT and E-Government</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
