<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="84160" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2021-06-24</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="317" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>301</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Bundesamt für Gesundheit</name>
      <name lang="fr">Office fédéral de la santé publique</name>
      <name lang="it">Ufficio federale della sanità pubblica</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Office of Public Health</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.bag.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.bag.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.bag.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.bag.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">media@bag.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">media@bag.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">media@bag.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">media@bag.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="301">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement des Innern</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'intérieur</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'interno</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Home Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Die SwissCovid App ist seit einem Jahr für Nutzerinnen und Nutzer verfügbar</title>
      <lead>Vor einem Jahr, am 25. Juni 2020, hat die Schweiz als eines der ersten Länder eine Proximity-Tracing-App eingeführt, die SwissCovid App. Nach einem Jahr zieht das BAG ein Zwischenfazit. Bis zu rund zwei Millionen Menschen nutzen die SwissCovid App aktiv, helfen so bei der Unterbrechung von Infektionsketten und können schneller über ein Ansteckungsrisiko gewarnt werden. Nutzerinnen und Nutzer leisten dadurch einen wesentlichen Beitrag zur Bekämpfung der Pandemie. </lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Die SwissCovid App verzeichnete am 27. Juni 2020 (zwei Tage nach ihrem Release) den 1.19 Millionsten Download – aktuell haben 3.18 Millionen Menschen die App installiert. Sie war 2020 die am häufigsten heruntergeladene App in der Schweiz. Ebenfalls einen raschen Anstieg konnte bei den Nutzerzahlen beobachtet werden. Bis zu zwei Millionen Menschen nutzen die SwissCovid App aktiv – zurzeit sind es 1.7 Millionen. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Effektivität von Proximity-Tracing-Apps&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Aus epidemiologischer Sicht war es in der ersten Phase wichtig herauszufinden, ob die Anzahl Anrufe, die nach Warnungen durch die App bei der Infoline eintrafen, mit den Fallzahlen korrelieren, ob also genug Menschen durch die App gewarnt werden. Aufgrund dieser Untersuchungen wurden die Schwellenwerte, welche für die Abschätzung der Distanz verwendet werden, angepasst und somit die Effektivität gesteigert.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Bereits im Herbst 2020 konnte aufgrund der Auswertung von ärztlichen Meldeformularen gezeigt werden, dass sich symptomfreie Personen nach einer App-Warnung haben testen lassen und ein positives Ergebnis erhielten. Durch die Isolierung dieser positiv getesteten Personen wurden Infektionsketten früh unterbrochen. Aufgrund der hohen Datenschutzanforderungen kann nicht erhoben werden, wie viele Personen eine Warnung erhalten haben. Bekannt ist jedoch die Anzahl in die App eingegebener Covidcodes: zurzeit wurden 83’117 Covidcodes eingegeben, die wiederum Warnungen bei anderen Nutzenden ausgelöst haben. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Kontinuierliche Weiterentwicklung der SwissCovid App&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Seit der Lancierung am 25. Juni 2020 wurde die SwissCovid App kontinuierlich weiterentwickelt. Dies sowohl auf der Benutzeroberfläche wie auch technisch im Hintergrund. Unter anderem konnte aufgrund der Systemanpassung am Betriebssystem von Apple die SwissCovid App auch iPhone-Nutzerinnen und Nutzern älterer Geräte zugänglich gemacht werden. Während der zweiten Welle im Herbst 2020 zeigte sich, dass die Generierung der Covidcodes die kantonalen Stellen an ihre Kapazitätsgrenzen brachte. Zu ihrer Entlastung wurden testende Ärztinnen und Ärzte, Apotheken, Mitarbeitende von Testzentren und die Mitarbeitenden der Infoline SwissCovid zur Ausstellung von Covidcodes berechtigt. Die rechtlichen Grundlagen wurden ebenfalls angepasst, um die Interoperabilität mit der deutschen Corona-Warn-App zu ermöglichen, von welcher seit März 2020 insbesondere die rund 60'000 Grenzgängerinnen und Grenzgänger profitieren. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Ausblick&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Zurzeit wird an einer Erweiterung der SwissCovid App gearbeitet, die es ermöglichen soll, noch mehr Personen anonym und unkompliziert über ein Ansteckungsrisiko zu informieren. Benachrichtigungen der SwissCovid App erfolgen schnell und sollen Menschen dazu motivieren, sich auf das Coronavirus testen zu lassen. &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Bundesamt für Gesundheit, Kommunikation, Infoline Coronavirus +41 58 463 00 00</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>L’application SwissCovid est disponible depuis un an</title>
      <lead>Il y a un an, le 25 juin 2020, la Suisse a été l’un des premiers pays à introduire une application de traçage de proximité, SwissCovid. L’occasion pour l’OFSP de tirer un bilan intermédiaire. Environ deux millions de personnes l’utilisent activement. Elles aident ainsi à interrompre les chaînes de transmission, peuvent être averties plus vite d’un risque d’infection et apportent une contribution essentielle à la lutte contre la pandémie. </lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Le 27 juin 2020, soit deux jours après son lancement, l’application SwissCovid avait été téléchargée 1,19 million de fois. Actuellement, 3,18 millions de personnes l’ont installée. En 2020, elle a été l’application la plus téléchargée en Suisse. On a également constaté une hausse rapide du nombre d’utilisateurs. Jusqu’à 2 millions de personnes l’utilisent activement. On en dénombre actuellement 1,7 million. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Efficacité des applications de traçage de proximité&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;D’un point de vue épidémiologique, lors de la première phase, il était important de déterminer si le nombre d’appels reçus par l’infoline suite à des notifications sur l’application correspondait au nombre de cas, et donc de savoir si suffisamment de personnes étaient averties par SwissCovid. Sur la base de ces analyses, les valeurs seuils utilisées pour évaluer la distance ont été adaptées et ont permis d’accroître l’efficacité. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Dès l’automne 2020, l’évaluation des formulaires de déclaration des médecins a permis de démontrer que des personnes asymptomatiques se sont fait tester après avoir reçu une notification de l’application et ont reçu un résultat positif. En isolant ces personnes, des chaînes de transmission ont pu être interrompues. En raison des exigences élevées en matière de protection des données, il n’est pas possible de savoir combien de personnes ont reçu une notification. Cependant, le nombre de codes COVID saisis dans l’application est connu : 83x 117, qui ont à leur tour déclenché des notifications chez les autres utilisateurs. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Développement continu de l’application SwissCovid&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Depuis son lancement le 25 juin 2020, l’application a été développée en continu, qu’il s’agisse de l’interface utilisateur ou de la technique en arrière-plan. En l’adaptant notamment au système d’exploitation d’Apple, les utilisateurs d’iPhones plus anciens ont pu accéder à l’application. Durant la deuxième vague à l’automne 2020, la génération des codes COVID a mené les services cantonaux à leurs limites. Afin de les décharger, les médecins et les pharmaciens pratiquant des tests ainsi que les collaborateurs des centres de test et de l’infoline SwissCovid ont été autorisés à générer ces codes. Les bases légales ont également été adaptées afin de permette l’interopérabilité avec l’application allemande Corona-Warn, dont profitent quelque 60 000 frontaliers depuis mars 2020. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Perspectives&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Une extension de SwissCovid est en cours de réalisation. Elle permettra d’informer encore plus de personnes d’un risque d’infection de manière simple et anonyme. Les notifications SwissCovid sont envoyées rapidement et doivent motiver la population à se faire tester contre le coronavirus. &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Office fédéral de la santé publique, Médias et communication, Infoline coronavirus +41 58 463 00 00</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>L’app SwissCovid è a disposizione degli utenti da un anno</title>
      <lead>Un anno fa, il 25 giugno 2020, la Svizzera è stata uno dei primi Paesi a introdurre un’app di tracciamento di prossimità, l’app SwissCovid. A un anno di distanza, l’UFSP stila un bilancio intermedio. Quasi due milioni di persone utilizzano attivamente l’app SwissCovid. Aiutano così a interrompere le catene d’infezione e riescono ad essere avvisati più rapidamente di un rischio di contagio. Gli utenti forniscono in questo modo un contributo sostanziale per la lotta contro la pandemia.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Il 27 giugno 2020 (due giorni dopo il suo lancio), l’app SwissCovid ha raggiunto 1,19 milioni di download. Ad oggi l’app è stata scaricata da 3,18 milioni di persone ed è stata la più scaricata in Svizzera nel 2020. Anche il numero di utenti ha registrato un rapido aumento: fino a due milioni di persone utilizzano attivamente l’app SwissCovid, attualmente 1,7 milioni. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Efficacia delle app di tracciamento di prossimità&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Dal punto di vista epidemiologico, nella prima fase era importante stabilire se il numero di chiamate che pervenivano alla Infoline in seguito a segnalazioni da parte dell’app fossero correlate con il numero di casi e cioè se un numero sufficiente di persone veniva avvisato mediante lʼapp. Sulla base di queste analisi sono state adeguate le soglie di attenuazione impiegate per stimare la distanza, aumentando così l’efficacia. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Già nell’autunno del 2020, sulla base dell’analisi dei moduli di dichiarazione medici si è osservato che persone asintomatiche si sono sottoposte al test in seguito a una segnalazione dell’app e sono risultate positive. Con l’isolamento di queste persone, le catene d’infezione sono state interrotte tempestivamente. A causa degli elevati requisiti in materia di protezione dei dati non è possibile rilevare quante persone hanno ricevuto una segnalazione. È tuttavia noto il numero di codici Covid inseriti nell’app: ad oggi ne sono stati inseriti 83 117, che hanno a loro volta generato segnalazioni presso altri utenti. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Perfezionamento continuo dell’app SwissCovid&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Dal suo lancio il 25 giugno 2020, l’app SwissCovid è stata continuamente perfezionata, sia nell’interfaccia utente, sia a livello tecnico. Con l’adeguamento al sistema operativo di Apple, è stato possibile rendere accessibile l’app SwissCovid anche a utenti iPhone con apparecchi più datati. Durante la seconda ondata nell’autunno 2020 si è osservato che la generazione di codici Covid ha portato i servizi cantonali ai loro limiti di capacità. Per sgravarli, sono stati autorizzati al rilascio di codici Covid anche medici e farmacie che effettuano test, collaboratori dei centri di test e dell’Infoline SwissCovid. Sono inoltre state adeguate le basi giuridiche per permettere l’interoperabilità con l’app di segnalazione tedesca, la Corona-Warn-App, della quale da marzo 2020 beneficiano in particolare i circa 60 000 frontalieri. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Prospettive&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Attualmente si lavora a un ampliamento dell’app SwissCovid che dovrebbe permettere di informare ancora più persone in modo anonimo e semplice circa un rischio di contagio. Le notifiche dell’app SwissCovid sono trasmesse rapidamente e mirano a motivare le persone a sottoporsi al test per il coronavirus. &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Ufficio federale della sanità pubblica UFSP, Sezione comunicazione, Infoline Coronavirus +41 58 463 00 00</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>The SwissCovid app has been available to users for one year</title>
      <lead>One year ago on 25 June 2020, Switzerland became one of the first countries to introduced a proximity tracing app, the SwissCovid app. After one year, the FOPH is taking stock of what has been achieved so far and also looking to the future. Up to approximately two million people actively use the SwissCovid app. This allows them to help interrupt chains of infection and means they can be alerted more quickly about any risk of infection. Users thus make a key contribution to combating the pandemic. </lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;On 27 June 2020 (two days after its release), the SwissCovid app had been downloaded 1.19 million times – the app has now been installed by 3.18 million people. It was the most downloaded app in Switzerland in 2020. A rapid increase has also been observed in the number of users. Up to 2 million people actively use the SwissCovid app, with the current number of active users standing at 1.7 million. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Effectiveness of proximity tracing apps&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;From an epidemiological perspective, it was important to find out during the initial phase whether the number of calls received by the Infoline following alerts issued by the app correlated with the number of cases. In other words, whether enough people were being warned by the app. Based on these investigations, the threshold values that are used to estimate distance were adjusted, thus increasing effectiveness.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As early as autumn 2020, it was possible to show on the basis of medical reporting forms that symptom-free individuals had got themselves tested after being issued an alert by the app and received a positive result. The fact that these positively tested individuals went into isolation allowed for chains of infection to be interrupted at an early stage. Due to the stringent data protection requirements, it is not possible to ascertain how many people have received a warning. What is known, however, is the number of covidcodes entered in the app: at present, 83,117 covidcodes have been entered, which in turn triggered warnings to be issued to other users. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Continual further development of the SwissCovid app&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Since being launched on 25 June 2020, the SwissCovid app has been developed further on an ongoing basis. This is true as regards both the user interface and the technical aspects running in the background. Among other things, a system adaptation to Apple’s operating system means that the SwissCovid app can now also be accessed by iPhone users with older devices. During the second wave in autumn 2020, it became apparent that the generation of covidcodes was pushing the cantonal authorities to their limits in terms of capacity. To ease the burden on them, doctors who perform tests as well as pharmacies, test centre staff and employees of the SwissCovid Infoline were authorised to issue covidcodes. The legal basis was also adjusted in order to enable interoperability with the German Corona-Warn-App, a development from which approximately 60,000 cross-border commuters, in particular, have been able to benefit since March 2020. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Outlook&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Work is currently under way on an extension to the SwissCovid app that will make it possible to inform even more people about a risk of infection in an anonymous and uncomplicated manner. Notifications from the SwissCovid app are sent out quickly and are intended to motivate people to get tested for the coronavirus. &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Federal Office of Public Health, Communications, Coronavirus Infoline +41 58 463 00 00</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <keywords>
      <keyword id="109" org-id="317">
        <name lang="de">2019-nCoV-DE</name>
        <name lang="fr">2019-nCoV-FR</name>
        <name lang="it">2019-nCoV-IT</name>
        <name lang="en">2019-nCoV-EN</name>
      </keyword>
    </keywords>
    <topics>
      <topic id="15">
        <name lang="de">Gesundheit</name>
        <name lang="fr">Santé</name>
        <name lang="it">sanità</name>
        <name lang="en">Health</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="41">
        <name lang="de">Soziales</name>
        <name lang="fr">Social</name>
        <name lang="it">Opere sociali</name>
        <name lang="en">Social Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
