<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="83782" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2021-06-04</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="324" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>301</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Swissmedic, Schweizerisches Heilmittelinstitut</name>
      <name lang="fr">Swissmedic, Institut suisse des produits thérapeutiques</name>
      <name lang="it">Swissmedic, Istituto svizzero per gli agenti terapeutici</name>
      <name lang="en">Swiss Agency for Therapeutic Products</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.swissmedic.ch/</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.swissmedic.ch/?lang=3</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.swissmedic.ch/?lang=4</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.swissmedic.ch/?lang=2</www>
      <email lang="de"/>
      <email lang="fr"/>
      <email lang="it"/>
      <email lang="en"/>
    </originator>
    <department id="301">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement des Innern</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'intérieur</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'interno</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Home Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Covid-19 Impfstoff von Pfizer/BioNTech in der Schweiz für Jugendliche freigegeben</title>
      <lead>Swissmedic genehmigt Indikationserweiterung von «Comirnaty®» für 12 bis 15-Jährige: Swissmedic hat das von Pfizer am 7. Mai 2021 eingereichte Gesuch für die Indikationserweiterung sorgfältig geprüft und kann die befristete Zulassung des Covid-19 Impfstoffs von Pfizer/BioNTech zur Prävention der Coronavirus-Krankheit für Jugendliche im Alter von 12 bis 15 Jahren erweitern.</lead>
      <text link="no">Swissmedic prüfte das Gesuch für die Indikationserweiterung beschleunigt im rollenden Verfahren. Die Resultate der fortlaufenden Studie über Jugendliche wurden eingereicht und begutachtet. Der Impfstoff muss – wie auch bei Personen über 16 Jahren – zweimal verabreicht werden. Bei der untersuchten Altersgruppe hat der Impfstoff in der klinischen Studie eine Wirksamkeit von gegen 100 Prozent gezeigt. Die jungen Studienteilnehmenden erhielten die gleiche Dosis wie Erwachsene und die Immunreaktion war mit den älteren Studienteilnehmenden (16 bis 25 Jahre) vergleichbar. Auch die Nebenwirkungen bei Jugendlichen entsprachen den in klinischen Studien mit 16 bis 25-jährigen und Erwachsenen gemeldeten unerwünschten Wirkungen. Am häufigsten traten Schmerzen an der Injektionsstelle, Müdigkeit, Kopfschmerzen, Schüttelfrost, Muskelschmerzen, Fieber oder Gelenkschmerzen auf. Die Nebenwirkungen dauerten in der Regel ein bis drei Tage und können nach der zweiten Dosis ausgeprägter sein.</text>
      <contact>Swissmedic Medienstelle +41 58 462 02 76 media@swissmedic.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Autorisation du vaccin contre le Covid-19 de Pfizer / BioNTech pour les adolescents en Suisse</title>
      <lead>Swissmedic approuve l’extension de l'indication de Comirnaty® aux adolescents de 12 à 15 ans: Après avoir examiné attentivement la demande d’extension de l’indication déposée par Pfizer le 7 mai 2021, Swissmedic élargit aux adolescents âgés de 12 à 15 ans l’autorisation ordinaire à durée limitée délivrée pour le vaccin de Pfizer / BioNTech destiné à prévenir la maladie à coronavirus.</lead>
      <text link="no">Swissmedic a examiné cette demande d’extension de l'indication dans le cadre d’une procédure évolutive rapide. Les résultats de l’essai qui porte actuellement sur les adolescents ont été présentés à l’institut et analysés. Comme pour les personnes de plus de 16 ans, il y a lieu d’administrer deux doses du vaccin. Au niveau de la tranche d’âge qui est étudiée lors de l’essai clinique, le vaccin a affiché une efficacité de près de 100 %. Les adolescents qui ont participé à ce dernier ont reçu la même dose que les adultes, et la réaction immunitaire qu’ils ont développée était comparable à celle des participants plus âgés à l’essai (qui avaient entre 16 et 25 ans). Quant aux effets secondaires observés chez les adolescents, ils correspondaient eux aussi à ceux déclarés lors des essais cliniques pour les 16-25 ans et les adultes. Les plus fréquents étaient des douleurs au site d’injection, une fatigue générale, des maux de tête, des frissons, des courbatures, de la fièvre et des douleurs articulaires. Ces effets indésirables, qui peuvent être plus marqués après l’administration de la seconde dose, disparaissaient en règle générale un à trois jours plus tard.</text>
      <contact>Swissmedic Service de presse +41 58 462 02 76 media@swissmedic.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Il vaccino anti-COVID-19 di Pfizer/BioNTech approvato in Svizzera per i giovani</title>
      <lead>Swissmedic approva l’estensione dell’indicazione di «Comirnaty®» per i giovani dai 12 ai 15 anni: Swissmedic ha esaminato attentamente la domanda di estensione dell’indicazione presentata da Pfizer il 7 maggio 2021. Swissmedic estende l’omologazione ordinaria temporanea del vaccino di Pfizer/BioNTech per la prevenzione della malattia da coronavirus per i giovani dai 12 ai 15 anni.</lead>
      <text link="no">Swissmedic ha esaminato la domanda di estensione dell’indicazione nell’ambito di una procedura di valutazione progressiva accelerata. I risultati dello studio in corso sui giovani sono stati presentati e valutati. Il vaccino deve essere somministrato due volte, come per le persone di età superiore ai 16 anni. Durante lo studio clinico, il vaccino ha dimostrato un’efficacia di quasi il 100 per cento nella fascia di età considerata. I giovani partecipanti allo studio hanno ricevuto la stessa dose degli adulti e la reazione immunitaria è stata paragonabile a quella dei partecipanti più anziani (dai 16 ai 25 anni). Anche gli effetti collaterali in questa fascia di età sono stati analoghi a quelli notificati durante gli studi clinici concernenti i giovani dai 16 ai 25 anni e gli adulti. I sintomi più frequenti sono stati dolore al sito di iniezione, stanchezza, mal di testa, brividi, dolori muscolari, febbre o dolori articolari. Gli effetti collaterali, che sono durati generalmente da uno a tre giorni, possono essere più pronunciati dopo la seconda dose.</text>
      <contact>Swissmedic Ufficio stampa +41 58 462 02 76 media@swissmedic.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Pfizer/BioNTech COVID-19 vaccine approved for young people in Switzerland</title>
      <lead>Swissmedic approves indication extension for Comirnaty® for 12 to 15-year-olds: Swissmedic has carefully examined the indication-extension application submitted by Pfizer on 7 May 2021. Swissmedic is extending the temporary ordinary authorisation of the Pfizer/BioNTech coronavirus vaccine to include young people aged between 12 and 15.</lead>
      <text link="no">Swissmedic reviewed the application for extension in an accelerated rolling procedure. The results of the ongoing study of the vaccine in young people were submitted and evaluated. As for persons aged 16 and over, the vaccine must be administered in two doses. The vaccine showed around 100 percent efficacy in the clinical trial for the investigated age group. The young trial participants received the same dose as adults, and the immune response was comparable with that of the older trial participants (16 to 25-year-olds). The side effects in the young people also corresponded to the adverse reactions reported in clinical trials with 16 to 25-year-olds and adults. The most frequent ones were pain at the injection site, fatigue, headache, shivering, muscle pain, fever and joint pain. The side effects usually lasted between one and three days, and may be more pronounced after the second dose.</text>
      <contact>Swissmedic Media Unit +41 58 462 02 76 media@swissmedic.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="15">
        <name lang="de">Gesundheit</name>
        <name lang="fr">Santé</name>
        <name lang="it">sanità</name>
        <name lang="en">Health</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
