<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="75994" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2019-08-06</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="323" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>701</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidg. Materialprüfungs- und Forschungsanstalt</name>
      <name lang="fr">Laboratoire fédéral d'essai des matériaux et de recherche</name>
      <name lang="it">Laboratorio federale di prova dei materiali e di ricerca</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Laboratory for Materials Testing and Research</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.empa.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.empa.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.empa.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.empa.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">contact@empa.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">contact@empa.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">contact@empa.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">contact@empa.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="701">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Wirtschaft, Bildung und Forschung</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'économie, de la formation et de la recherche</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'economia, della formazione e della ricerca</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Economic Affairs, Education and Research</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Dübendorf, St. Gallen und Thun</city>
      <title>Täuschend echt</title>
      <lead>Das Herz stellt die moderne Medizin noch immer vor grosse Herausforderungen. Über zehn Millionen Menschen in Europa leiden an einer Herzschwäche, und nicht wenige davon brauchen ein Spenderherz. Um die Wartezeit zu überbrücken, werden ihnen künstliche Herzpumpen eingesetzt, Komplikationen sind dabei nicht selten. Das Projekt «Zurich Heart» unter Mitwirkung der Empa entwickelt Lösungen.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Eine künstliche Herzpumpe ist für viele Patienten mit einer Herzinsuffizienz die Rettung – allerdings eine, die oft nicht ohne Nebenwirkungen bleibt. Es besteht die Gefahr von Blutgerinnseln oder einer Abstossungsreaktion gegen das fremde Material, was zu schweren Immunreaktionen führen kann. Forschende des Universitätsspitals Zürich lancierten daher gemeinsam mit Kolleginnen und Kollegen der Universität Zürich und der ETH Zürich bereits 2011 das Projekt «Zurich Heart». Beteiligt daran sind Mediziner, Ingenieure, Biologen und Materialwissenschaftler mit dem Ziel, gängige Herzpumpen weiterzuentwickeln und gleichzeitig neue Lösungen zu erarbeiten, um die bisherigen Risiken auszumerzen. In rund zehn Teilprojekten arbeiten die Forscherinnen und Forscher verschiedener Universitäten und Forschungsinstitute an neuen Ansätzen – unter anderem an der Empa.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h3&gt;Empa mehrfach beteiligt&lt;/h3&gt; &lt;p&gt;Gleich mehrere Teams der Empa sind Teil von «Zurich Heart» und arbeiten an einer neuen Generation von Herzpumpen, die so «getarnt» werden sollen, dass die menschlichen Abwehrzellen sie nicht von einem echten Herzen unterscheiden können. Natürliche Blutgefässe – unter anderem das Herz – sind auf der Innenseite mit sogenannten Endothelzellen ausgekleidet, die den Austausch zwischen Blut und Körpergewebe regulieren. Eine künstliche Herzpumpe muss also über eine Fläche verfügen, auf der sich körpereigene Endothelzellen ansiedeln können. Diese Gewebeoberfläche gaukelt dem Blut vor, dass es sich nicht um ein künstliches Organ, sondern um ein echtes Herz handelt.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Forschenden rund um Eduardo Mazza, Leiter der Empa-Abteilung «Experimental Continuum Mechanics», Professor an der ETH Zürich und Co-Projektleiter von «Zurich Heart», ist es gelungen, eine Membran zu entwickeln, die optimale Bedingungen für die Besiedelung durch Endothelzellen bietet. Diese Membran bietet nicht nur die passende Grundlage für die notwendigen Zellen, sondern dämpft zudem die natürliche Pumpbewegung – denn bei zu starken Kontraktionen können sich die Zellen auch auf einer noch so verlockend präparierten Unterlage kaum festhalten und werden vom Blut weggespült.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h3&gt;Hexagon-Lösung&lt;/h3&gt; &lt;p&gt;Damit sich die Endothelzellen auf der Membran wohlfühlen und sich entsprechend festhalten, hat Aldo Ferrari, Forscher an der ETH Zürich und an der Empa, ein Substrat mit einer speziellen Struktur entwickelt, mit dem die Membran ausgestattet wird: Wie bei einer Bienenwabe reihen sich einzelne Sechsecke aneinander und bieten den Zellen optimal Platz, um sich darin einzunisten und nicht weggeschwemmt zu werden.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Eine erfolgreiche Methode, denn das Forscherteam hat sowohl durch In-vitro- als auch durch In-vivo-Versuche bestätigen können, dass die Zellen auch nach mehreren Pumpbewegungen an der Membran haften bleiben und so eine potenzielle Lösung für die Entwicklung von biokompatibleren Herzpumpen liefern. Doch selbst nach diesen erfolgreichen Versuchen stehen weitere Herausforderungen an. Ziel ist es, nicht nur die Membran, sondern die gesamte Innenfläche einer Pumpe mit dieser Hexagonstruktur auszukleiden.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h3&gt;Nächste Schritte eingeleitet&lt;/h3&gt; &lt;p&gt;«Zurich Heart» startet nun in die zweite Phase. «Wir wollen einige der innerhalb von ‹Zurich Heart› entwickelten Lösungen in klinisch relevante Produkte umsetzen», so Mazza. Das kann indes mehrere Jahre dauern, daher ist «Zurich Heart» zeitlich nicht limitiert. Die erste Generation der Doktoranden, die in «Zurich Heart» involviert waren, haben nun abgeschlossen und zahlreiche Publikationen und Patente mit positiven Rückmeldungen erarbeitet.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;«Wir sind mit unserem Teilprojekt der hybriden Membran deutlich weiter gekommen, als wir ursprünglich erwartet hatten», so Mazza. Mit seinem Team plant er bereits die nächsten Schritte: Das Langzeitverhalten einer solch «endothelisierten» Herzpumpe ist noch nicht erforscht, das möchten Mazza nun angehen. Schliesslich muss so eine Herzpumpe mehrere Millionen Schläge überstehen. «Unsere Motivation zu dieser Forschung hat sich in diesen Jahren weiter verstärkt», schliesst Mazza und ist zuversichtlich, dass auch die kommenden Projekte wichtige Informationen und Lösungen für und rund um das menschliche Herz liefern werden.&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Informationen Prof. Dr. Edoardo Mazza Experimental Continuum Mechanics Tel. +41 58 765 41 19 Edoardo.Mazza@empa.ch Redaktion / Medienkontakt Cornelia Zogg Kommunikation Tel. +41 58 765 45 99 redaktion@empa.ch</contact>
      <link id="192229">
        <title>press release</title>
        <uri>https://www.empa.ch/web/s604/zurich-heart-2019</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Dübendorf, St. Gallen und Thun</city>
      <title>Faussement réel</title>
      <lead>Le cœur reste l’un des grands défis de la médecine moderne. En Europe, plus de 10 millions de personnes souffrent d’une insuffisance cardiaque et beaucoup d’entre elles ont besoin d’une greffe du cœur. Dans l’attente, on leur pose une pompe cardiaque artificielle, mais ces pompes ne sont pas à l’abri de complications. Le projet «Zurich Heart», auquel l’Empa participe, étudie comment résoudre ces questions</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;La pose d’une pompe cardiaque artificielle est pour bien des patients le geste qui sauve. Mais cette mesure s’accompagne souvent d’effets secondaires. Il existe un danger de formation de caillots sanguins ou de phénomènes de rejet des matériaux étrangers, ce qui peut entraîner de fortes réactions immunitaires. C’est pourquoi, en 2011 déjà, des chercheurs de l’Hôpital universitaire de Zurich ont lancé avec des collègues de l’Université et de l’EPF de Zurich le projet «Zurich Heart». Y participent des médecins, ingénieurs, biologistes et chercheurs en matériaux. Leur objectif: perfectionner les pompes existantes et trouver de nouvelles solutions aux problèmes identifiés. Une dizaine de sous-projets testant de nouvelles approches sont en cours, avec la participation de chercheuses et chercheurs de diverses universités et divers instituts, dont l’Empa.&lt;/p&gt; L’Empa est très présent &lt;p&gt;Plusieurs équipes de l’Empa participent à «Zurich Heart» et travaillent sur une nouvelle génération de pompes cardiaques «camouflées», c’est-à-dire revêtues de manière que les anticorps ne les distinguent pas d’un cœur authentique. On sait que les vaisseaux sanguins naturels – dont les vaisseaux cardiaques – sont revêtus intérieurement de cellules dites endothéliales qui régulent les échanges entre le sang et les tissus voisins. Les pompes cardiaques artificielles doivent donc offrir une enveloppe colonisable aux cellules endothéliales du receveur, une surface que son sang ne percevra pas comme artificielle mais comme celle du cœur original. Le groupe de chercheurs d’Edoardo Mazza, qui dirige le département «Experimental Continuum Mechanics» de l’EPF et assurer la co-direction du projet «Zurich Heart», a réussi à mettre au point une membrane présentant d’excellentes conditions de colonisation par des cellules endothéliales. En plus de servir de substrat à ces indispensables cellules, la membrane amortit les impulsions de la pompe. Ce qui est nécessaire dans la mesure où, quel que soit l’attrait du substrat, les cellules ne pourraient pas s’y fixer et seraient emportées par le courant sanguin si de trop fortes secousses l’agitaient.&lt;/p&gt; Une solution hexagonale &lt;p&gt;Pour que les cellules endothéliales se sentent bien sur la membrane et puissent s’y fixer, Aldo Ferrari, chercheur à l’EPFZ et à l’Empa, en a texturé la surface en réseau hexagonal. Ce léger nid d’abeille offre aux cellules un espace où se nicher et résister au courant. La méthode est efficace, comme l’équipe l’a montré in vitro et in vivo : les cellules sont restées fixées à la membrane après plusieurs cycles de pompage, ce qui ouvre la voie au développement de pompes cardiaques biocompatibles. Ce succès ne résout par pour autant tous les défis, l’objectif n’étant pas de revêtir une membrane test, mais tout l’intérieur de la pompe de cette structure texturée.&lt;/p&gt; Les prochaines étapes sont déjà amorcées &lt;p&gt;«Zurich Heart» entre maintenant dans sa seconde phase. «Nous voulons transformer quelques unes des solutions développées par «Zurich Heart» en produits adaptés à la clinique», précise Mazza. Cela peut durer plusieurs années, raison pour laquelle le projet n’a pas de limite fixe. La première génération des doctorants qui ont participé à «Zurich Heart» a maintenant terminé et publié ses travaux et déposé de nombreuses demandes de brevet. Les retours sont positifs. «Notre sous-projet de membrane hybride a progressé bien au-delà de nos attentes», ajoute Mazza qui, avec son équipe, prépare déjà l’étape suivante: l’étude du comportement à long terme d’une pompe cardiaque «endothéliumisée». Les pompes cardiaques doivent en effet assurer leur fonction sur plusieurs millions de battements. «Toutes ces années, notre motivation n’a fait qu’augmenter», conclut-il, confiant que les travaux à venir livreront de précieuses informations et déboucheront sur des solutions applicables en cardiologie humaine.&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Information Prof. Dr. Edoardo Mazza Experimental Continuum Mechanics Tél.+41 58 765 41 19 Edoardo.Mazza@empa.ch Rédaction / Contact médias Cornelia Zogg Communications Tél. +41 58 765 45 99 redaktion@empa.ch</contact>
      <link id="192229">
        <title>press release</title>
        <uri>https://www.empa.ch/web/s604/zurich-heart-2019</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Dübendorf, St. Gallen und Thun</city>
      <title>Deceptively real</title>
      <lead>The human heart still poses great challenges to modern medicine. More than ten million people in Europe suffer from heart failure, and quite a few of them need a donor organ. Artificial heart pumps are used to bridge the waiting time, but complications are not uncommon. The "Zurich Heart" project, in which Empa is a partner, is developing solutions.</lead>
      <text link="no">For many patients with heart failure, an artificial heart pump is a lifesaver – but one that often causes side effects. There is a risk of blood clots or a rejection of the foreign material, which can lead to severe immune responses. Researchers at Zurich University Hospital, together with col-leagues from the University of Zurich and ETH Zurich, therefore launched the "Zurich Heart" project back in 2011. The project involves physicians, engineers, biologists and materials scientists with the aim of developing common heart pumps further and at the same time coming up with new solutions to eradicate existing risks. Researchers from various universities and research institutes – including Empa – are working on new approaches in around ten subprojects. Empa involved in several projects Several Empa teams are part of Zurich Heart and are working on a new generation of heart pumps that will be "camouflaged" in such a way that human immune cells cannot distinguish them from a real heart. Natural blood vessels – including the heart – are lined on the inside with endothelial cells that regulate the exchange between blood and the body's tissues. An artificial heart pump must thus have a surface, on which the body's own endothelial cells can settle. This tissue surface fools the blood into believing that it is not an artificial organ but a real heart. Researchers led by Eduardo Mazza, head of Empa's Experimental Continuum Mechanics lab, professor at ETH Zurich and co-project leader of Zurich Heart, have succeeded in developing a membrane that offers optimal conditions for the colonization of endothelial cells. This membrane not only provides a suitable basis for the necessary cells, but also dampens the natural pumping movement – if the contractions are too strong, cells can hardly hold on to even the most temptingly prepared surface and are washed away by the blood. Hexagon solution Aldo Ferrari, a researcher at ETH Zurich and Empa, has developed a substrate with a special structure that makes endothelial cells feel comfortable on the membrane so that they can hold on to it. Like a honeycomb, individual hexagons line up in a row and offer the cells an optimal space to nest in them and not be washed away. The method has proven successful; the researchers were able to confirm in both in vitro and in vivo experiments that the cells adhere to the membrane even after several pumping movements and thus provide a potential solution for the development of more biocompatible heart pumps. Despite these successful initial trials further challenges remain, however. The aim is to not only coat the membrane but also the entire inner surface of the pump with the hexagonal structure. Next steps already initiated Zurich Heart is now entering its second phase. "We want to translate some of the solutions devel-oped within Zurich Heart into clinically relevant products," says Mazza. This could take several years, though, so Zurich Heart has no time limit. The first generation of PhD students involved in Zurich Heart have now completed their theses and produced numerous publications and patents with positive feedback. "With our hybrid membrane project, we have come much further than we had originally expected," says Mazza. With his team he is already planning the next steps: The longterm behavior of such an "endothelialized" heart pump has not yet been investigated, and Mazza now wants to address this issue. After all, such a heart pump has to withstand several mil-lion beats. "Our motivation has increased even further in recent years", Mazza concludes. He is confident that the upcoming projects will yield important knowledge as well as practical solutions for and around the human heart. </text>
      <contact>Further information Prof. Dr. Edoardo Mazza Experimental Continuum Mechanics Phone +41 58 765 41 19 Edoardo.Mazza@empa.ch Editor / Media contact Cornelia Zogg Communications Phone +41 58 765 45 99 redaktion@empa.ch</contact>
      <link id="192229">
        <title>press release</title>
        <uri>https://www.empa.ch/web/s604/zurich-heart-2019</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="8">
        <name lang="de">Bildung und Forschung</name>
        <name lang="fr">Formation et recherche</name>
        <name lang="it">Formazione e ricerca</name>
        <name lang="en">Education and Research</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="45">
        <name lang="de">Technologie</name>
        <name lang="fr">Technologie</name>
        <name lang="it">Tecnologia</name>
        <name lang="en">Technology</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
