<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="22338" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2008-10-30</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="201" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>201</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="201">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Bundesrätin Calmy-Rey am World Economic Forum in Istanbul</title>
      <lead/>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Bundesrätin Micheline Calmy-Rey, Vorsteherin des Eidgenössischen Departements für auswärtige Angelegenheiten (EDA), wird am World Economic Forum on Europe and Central Asia teilnehmen, das vom 30. Oktober bis zum 1. November 2008 in Istanbul stattfindet. Bundesrätin Calmy-Rey wird morgen Freitag, 31. Oktober 2008, in Istanbul eintreffen.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Im Rahmen ihrer Teilnahme am World Economic Forum on Europe and Central Asia wird die EDA-Vorsteherin Gelegenheit zu bilateralen Gesprächen haben. So ist auch ein Treffen mit dem türkischen Aussenminister Babacan vorgesehen.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Presse- und Informationsdienst Bundeshaus West CH-3003 Bern Tel.: +41 (0)31 322 31 53 Fax: +41 (0)31 324 90 47 E-Mail: info@eda.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>La Conseillère fédérale Calmy-Rey participera au World Economic Forum à Istanbul</title>
      <lead/>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;La Conseillère fédérale Mme Micheline Calmy-Rey, Cheffe du Département fédéral des affaires étrangères (DFAE), participera au World Economic Forum on Europe and Central Asia organisé à Istanbul du 30 octobre au 1er novembre 2008. Mme Calmy-Rey arrivera à Istanbul demain, vendredi 31 octobre 2008. &amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Dans le cadre de sa participation au World Economic Forum on Europe and Central Asia, la Cheffe du DFAE aura l’occasion d’avoir des entretiens bilatéraux. Une rencontre est notamment prévue avec le Ministre turc des affaires étrangères, M.&amp;nbsp;Ali Babacan.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Service de presse et d'information Palais fédéral ouest CH-3003 Berne Tél.: (+41) 031 322 31 53 Fax: (+41) 031 324 90 47 E-Mail: info@eda.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>La consigliera federale Micheline Calmy-Rey al World Economic Forum di Istanbul</title>
      <lead/>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;La consigliera federale Micheline Calmy-Rey, Capo del Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri (DFAE), parteciperà al World Economic Forum on Europe and Central Asia, in programma ad Istanbul dal 30 ottobre al 1° novembre 2008. Micheline Calmy-Rey arriverà ad Istanbul domani, venerdì 31 ottobre 2008.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Nell’ambito della sua partecipazione al World Economic Forum on Europe and Central Asia la responsabile del DFAE avrà l’occasione di condurre dei colloqui bilaterali. È pure previsto un incontro con il Ministro degli affari esteri turco Ali Babacan.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Servizio stampa e informazione Palazzo federale ovest CH-3003 Berna Tel.: (+41) 031 322 31 53 Fax: (+41) 031 324 90 47 E-Mail: info@eda.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Federal Councillor Calmy-Rey to attend the World Economic Forum in Istanbul</title>
      <lead/>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Federal Councillor Micheline Calmy-Rey, head of the Swiss Federal Department of Foreign Affairs (FDFA), will attend the World Economic Forum on Europe and Central Asia, which will take place from 30 October to 1 November 2008 in Istanbul. Mrs Calmy Rey will arrive in Istanbul tomorrow Friday 31 October.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;At the World Economic Forum on Europe and Central Asia the Head of the FDFA will take the opportunity to conduct a number of bilateral meetings. Among these, she plans to meet the Turkish Foreign Minister, Ali Babacan.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Press and Information Service Bundeshaus West CH-3003 Bern Tel.: (+41) 031 322 31 53 Fax: (+41) 031 324 90 47 E-Mail: info@eda.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
