<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="92044" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2022-12-05</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="710" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>701</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Wettbewerbskommission</name>
      <name lang="fr">Commission de la concurrence</name>
      <name lang="it">Commissione della concorrenza</name>
      <name lang="en">Competition Commission</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.weko.admin.ch/</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.weko.admin.ch/</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.weko.admin.ch/</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.weko.admin.ch/</www>
      <email lang="de">weko@weko.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">weko@weko.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">weko@weko.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">weko@weko.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="701">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Wirtschaft, Bildung und Forschung</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'économie, de la formation et de la recherche</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'economia, della formazione e della ricerca</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Economic Affairs, Education and Research</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Das Sekretariat der WEKO untersucht den Arbeitsmarkt im Bankensektor</title>
      <lead>Eine grosse Anzahl von Banken in der Deutschschweiz haben regelmässig Informationen über die Löhne von verschiedenen Kategorien ihrer Angestellten ausgetauscht. Weil dieses Verhalten kartellrechtlich problematisch sein könnte, wurde eine Vorabklärung eröffnet. </lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Das Sekretariat der Wettbewerbskommission (WEKO) hat gegen 34 Bankinstitute in sechs Deutschschweizer Regionen eine Vorabklärung eröffnet. Ziel des Verfahrens ist, abzuklären, ob die Informationsaustausche über die Löhne und Lohnbestandteile von verschiedenen Kategorien von Angestellten Anhaltspunkte für unerlaubte Abreden im Sinn des Kartellgesetzes darstellen. Bei Bedarf können die Ermittlungen auf weitere Regionen und andere Unternehmen ausgedehnt werden. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Der Arbeitsmarkt rückt immer mehr in den Fokus der Tätigkeit der Wettbewerbsbehörden rund um den Globus. In der Schweiz ist es das erste Mal, dass das Sekretariat der WEKO mögliche Abreden auf dem Arbeitsmarkt untersucht, die in den Anwendungsbereich des Kartellgesetzes fallen können, da sie nicht Verhandlungsergebnisse von Sozialpartnern darstellen.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Patrik Ducrey Direktor 058 464 96 78 079 345 01 44 patrik.ducrey@weko.admin.ch Olivier Schaller Vizedirektor 058 462 21 23 079 703 80 07 olivier.schaller@weko.admin.ch</contact>
      <attachment id="239597">
        <title>Das Sekretariat der WEKO untersucht den Arbeitsmarkt im Bankensektor</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>77</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/74266.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Le Secrétariat de la COMCO enquête sur le marché du travail dans le domaine bancaire</title>
      <lead>Un grand nombre de banques en Suisse alémanique échangent régulièrement des informations sur les salaires de certaines catégories de ses employés. Etant donné que ces comportements pourraient être problématiques au regard de la loi sur les cartels, une enquête préalable a été ouverte.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Le Secrétariat de la Commission de la concurrence (COMCO) a ouvert une enquête préalable qui vise 34 établissements bancaires dans six régions de la Suisse alémanique. Le but de la procédure est d’examiner si ces échanges d’informations sur les salaires de certaines catégories de ses employés constituent des indices d’accords illicites au sens du droit des cartels. Si nécessaire, la procédure pourra être élargie à d’autres régions géographiques et à d’autres entreprises.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Le marché du travail occupe toujours plus les autorités de la concurrence au niveau mondial. En Suisse, c’est la première fois que le Secrétariat de la COMCO analyse de possibles accords sur le marché du travail qui peuvent tomber dans le champ d’application de la loi sur les cartels lorsqu’ils ne sont pas le résultat de négociations entre partenaires sociaux.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Patrik Ducrey Directeur 058 464 96 78 079 345 01 44 patrik.ducrey@comco.admin.ch Olivier Schaller Vice-directeur 058 462 21 23 079 703 80 07 olivier.schaller@comco.admin.ch</contact>
      <attachment id="239600">
        <title>Le Secrétariat de la COMCO enquête sur le marché du travail dans le domaine bancaire</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>75</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/74267.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>La Segreteria della COMCO indaga sul mercato del lavoro nel settore bancario</title>
      <lead>Un numero elevato di banche in Svizzera tedesca scambia regolarmente delle informazioni sui salari di alcune categorie dei loro impiegati. Visto che questo comportamento potrebbe essere problematico da un punto di vista della legge sui cartelli, è stata aperta un’inchiesta preliminare.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;La Segreteria della Commissione della concorrenza (COMCO) ha aperto un’inchiesta preliminare che concerne 34 istituti bancari in sei regioni della Svizzera tedesca. Lo scopo del procedimento è di esaminare se gli scambi d’informazioni sui salari di alcune categorie dei loro impiegati costituiscano degli accordi illeciti ai sensi del diritto sui cartelli. Se necessario, il procedimento potrà essere estesa a altre regioni geografiche e a altre imprese. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; Il mercato del lavoro occupa sempre più le autorità in materia di concorrenza a livello mondiale. In Svizzera, è la prima volta che la Segreteria della COMCO analizza dei possibili accordi sul mercato del lavoro che rientrano nel campo d’applicazione della legge sui cartelli, salvo se sono il risultato di negoziati con i partner sociali. &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Patrik Ducrey Direttore 058 464 96 78 079 345 01 44 patrik.ducrey@comco.admin.ch Olivier Schaller Vicedirettore 058 462 21 23 079 703 80 07 olivier.schaller@comco.admin.ch</contact>
      <attachment id="239602">
        <title>La Segreteria della COMCO indaga sul mercato del lavoro nel settore bancario</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>73</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/74268.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>COMCO Secretariat investigates the labour market in the banking sector</title>
      <lead>A large number of banks in the German-speaking part of Switzerland regularly exchange information about the salaries of certain categories of employees. As this behaviour could be problematic under the Cartel Act, a preliminary investigation has been initiated.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;The Secretariat of the Competition Commission (COMCO) has opened a preliminary investigation against 34 banks in six regions of German-speaking Switzerland. The purpose of the procedure is to examine whether there are indications that the exchange of information on the salaries of certain categories of employees amounts to illegal agreements within the meaning of antitrust law. If necessary, the procedure can be extended to other geographical regions and companies.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The labour market is becoming increasingly important for competition authorities worldwide. In Switzerland, the COMCO Secretariat is for the first time analysing possible labour market agreements that may fall within the scope of the Cartel Act as they are not the result of negotiations between social partners. &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Patrik Ducrey Director +41 58 464 96 78 +41 79 345 01 44 patrik.ducrey@comco.admin.ch Olivier Schaller Vice-Director +41 58 462 21 23 +41 79 703 80 07 olivier.schaller@comco.admin.ch</contact>
      <attachment id="239605">
        <title>COMCO Secretariat investigates the labour market in the banking sector</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>75</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/74270.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="2">
        <name lang="de">Arbeit</name>
        <name lang="fr">Travail</name>
        <name lang="it">Lavoro</name>
        <name lang="en">Labour</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="5">
        <name lang="de">Behörden</name>
        <name lang="fr">Autorités</name>
        <name lang="it">Autorità</name>
        <name lang="en">Authorities</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="35">
        <name lang="de">Finanzplatz</name>
        <name lang="fr">Place financière</name>
        <name lang="it">Piazza finanziaria</name>
        <name lang="en">Financial Centre</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
