<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="92056" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2022-12-05</pubdate>
    <blocking-period>2022-12-05</blocking-period>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="318" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>301</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Bundesamt für Statistik</name>
      <name lang="fr">Office fédéral de la statistique</name>
      <name lang="it">Ufficio federale di statistica</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Statistical Office</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.statistik.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.statistique.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.statistica.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.statistics.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@bfs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@bfs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@bfs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@bfs.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="301">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement des Innern</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'intérieur</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'interno</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Home Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Neuchâtel</city>
      <title>22% der Intensivpflegestunden für Patientinnen und Patienten mit Covid-19</title>
      <lead>2021 wurde bei rund 43 300 Hospitalisierungen eine Covid-19-Diagnose gestellt. Diese Zahl ist höher als 2020 (40 893). In den Jahren 2020 und 2021 machten diese Hospitalisierungen 3% aller Spitalaufenthalte aus, nahmen aber 22% der in der Intensivpflege verbrachten Stunden in Anspruch. 11% der mit einer Covid-19-Diagnose hospitalisierten Personen sind im Spital gestorben. Zwischen März und Dezember 2021 wurden rund 1400 Personen aufgrund unerwünschter Nebenwirkungen einer Covid-19-Impfung hospitalisiert. Dies sind einige Daten aus der jüngsten Publikation des Bundesamtes für Statistik (BFS).</lead>
      <text link="no">Diese Medienmitteilung und weitere Informationen zum Thema finden Sie auf der Website des BFS (siehe Link unten).</text>
      <contact>Jean-François Marquis, BFS, Sektion Gesundheitsversorgung, Tel.: +41 58 463 67 54, E-Mail: jeanfrancois.marquis@bfs.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="239648">
        <title>Kompletter Text und Mediendossier</title>
        <uri>https://www.bfs.admin.ch/news/de/2022-0165</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Neuchâtel</city>
      <title>Soins intensifs: 22% des heures pour les patients avec le COVID-19</title>
      <lead>Près de 43 300 hospitalisations en 2021 ont concerné des personnes avec un diagnostic de COVID-19, un nombre en augmentation par rapport à 2020 (40 893). Sur les deux années 2020 et 2021, ces hospitalisations ont représenté 3% de l’ensemble des séjours, mais 22% des heures passées en soins intensifs. 11% des personnes hospitalisées avec ce diagnostic sont décédées à l’hôpital. Par ailleurs, de mars à décembre 2021, quelque 1400 personnes ont été hospitalisées avec un diagnostic d’effets indésirables de vaccins contre le COVID-19. Ce sont quelques-unes des données qui ressortent de la dernière publication de l’Office fédéral de la statistique (OFS).</lead>
      <text link="no">Vous trouverez ce communiqué de presse et d'autres informations sur ce thème sur le site web de l'OFS (cf. lien ci-dessous).</text>
      <contact>Jean-François Marquis, OFS, Section Services de santé, tél.: +41 58 463 67 54, e-mail: jeanfrancois.marquis@bfs.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="239649">
        <title>Texte intégral et dossier de presse</title>
        <uri>https://www.bfs.admin.ch/news/fr/2022-0165</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Neuchâtel</city>
      <title>Terapia intensiva: il 22% delle ore destinato ai pazienti con COVID-19</title>
      <lead>Nel 2021, quasi 43 300 ospedalizzazioni riguardavano persone con una diagnosi di COVID-19, un numero in aumento rispetto al 2020 (40 893). Nel biennio 2020–21, queste ospedalizzazioni hanno rappresentato il 3% dell’insieme dei ricoveri ospedalieri, ma il 22% delle ore trascorse in terapia intensiva. Delle persone ricoverate con questa diagnosi, l’11% è deceduto in ospedale. Inoltre, tra marzo e dicembre 2021 circa 1400 persone sono state ricoverate in ospedale con una diagnosi di caso di effetti indesiderati dei vaccini anti-COVID-19. Questi sono alcuni risultati tratti dall’ultima pubblicazione dell’Ufficio federale di statistica (UST).</lead>
      <text link="no">Il presente comunicato stampa e ulteriori informazioni sul tema sono reperibili sulla pagina Internet dell'UST (link sotto).</text>
      <contact>Jean-François Marquis, UST, sezione Sistema sanitario, tel.: +41 58 463 67 54, e-mail: jeanfrancois.marquis@bfs.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="239650">
        <title>Testo integrale e dossier per i media</title>
        <uri>https://www.bfs.admin.ch/news/it/2022-0165</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Neuchâtel</city>
      <title>22% of intensive care hours for COVID-19 patients</title>
      <lead>Almost 43 300 hospital admissions in 2021 were for people with a COVID-19 diagnosis, an increase in number compared with 2020 (40 893). Over the two years 2020 and 2021, these admissions accounted for 3% of all hospitalisations, but for 22% of hours spent in intensive care. 11% of people admitted with this diagnosis died in hospital. Furthermore, from March to December 2021, around 1400 people were admitted to hospital with a diagnosis of adverse reactions to COVID-19 vaccines. These are some of the results of the latest publication from the Federal Statistical Office (FSO).</lead>
      <text link="no">This press release and further information on the topic can be found on the FSO website (see link below).</text>
      <contact>Jean-François Marquis, FSO, Health services section, tel.: +41 58 463 67 54, email: jeanfrancois.marquis@bfs.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="239651">
        <title>Complete text and press kit - Please note that the English version only includes the release's lead</title>
        <uri>https://www.bfs.admin.ch/news/en/2022-0165</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <keywords>
      <keyword id="317.15" org-id="318">
        <name lang="de">Gesundheit</name>
        <name lang="fr">Santé</name>
        <name lang="it">Salute</name>
        <name lang="en">Health</name>
      </keyword>
    </keywords>
    <topics>
      <topic id="15">
        <name lang="de">Gesundheit</name>
        <name lang="fr">Santé</name>
        <name lang="it">sanità</name>
        <name lang="en">Health</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="43">
        <name lang="de">Statistik</name>
        <name lang="fr">Statistiques</name>
        <name lang="it">Statistica</name>
        <name lang="en">Statistics</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
