<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="44119" revoked="no">
    <version>2</version>
    <pubdate>2012-04-12</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="201" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>201</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="703" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>701</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Staatssekretariat für Wirtschaft</name>
      <name lang="fr">Secrétariat d'Etat à l'économie</name>
      <name lang="it">Segreteria di Stato dell'economia</name>
      <name lang="en">State Secretariat for Economic Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.seco.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.seco.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.seco.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.seco.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@seco.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@seco.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@seco.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@seco.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="yes" id="811" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>801</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Bundesamt für Umwelt BAFU</name>
      <name lang="fr">Office fédéral de l'environnement OFEV</name>
      <name lang="it">Ufficio federale dell'ambiente UFAM</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Office for the Environment FOEN</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.bafu.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.bafu.admin.ch/fr</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.bafu.admin.ch/it</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.bafu.admin.ch/en</www>
      <email lang="de">info@bafu.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@bafu.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@bafu.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@bafu.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="201">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <department id="701">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Wirtschaft, Bildung und Forschung</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'économie, de la formation et de la recherche</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'economia, della formazione e della ricerca</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Economic Affairs, Education and Research</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <department id="801">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Umwelt, Verkehr, Energie und Kommunikation</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'environnement, des transports, de l'énergie et de la communication</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'ambiente, dei trasporti, dell'energia e delle comunicazioni</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of the Environment, Transport, Energy and Communications</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.uvek.admin.ch/uvek/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.uvek.admin.ch/uvek/fr/home.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.uvek.admin.ch/uvek/it/home.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.uvek.admin.ch/uvek/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-uvek.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-uvek.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-uvek.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-uvek.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Genf als Standort für Umweltbelange stärken</title>
      <lead>Die Schweiz kandidiert als Sitzstaat für das permanente Sekretariat des Green Climate Fund (GCF). Am 12. April hat sie eine entsprechende Offerte für den Sitz in Genf eingereicht. Gleichzeitig kandidiert die Schweiz für einen Sitz im Exekutivrat des GCF. Damit können Synergien geschaffen werden, denn verschiedene Organisationen im Umweltbereich sind in Genf bereits vertreten.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Ohne internationale Unterstützung schaffen es Entwicklungsländer, welche Armutsprobleme bewältigen müssen, nicht, ihre Treibhausgasemissionen zu reduzieren und die notwendigen Massnahmen zur Anpassung an den Klimawandel vorzunehmen. Die finanzielle Unterstützung dieser Länder im Klimabereich will die internationale Staatengemeinschaft auf jährlich 100 Milliarden US Dollar erhöhen. Der Green Climate Fund, welcher 2010 durch die Abkommen von Cancun gegründet wurde, soll in diesem Zusammenhang eine bedeutende Rolle spielen, mittelfristig Summen im zweistelligen Milliardenbereich verwalten und in Entwicklungsländern investieren. Als Treuhänderin für den GCF ist in der Anfangsphase die Weltbank vorgesehen.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Ab 2014 soll das Sekretariat des GCF einen definitiven Standort haben. Der Bundesrat hat an seiner Sitzung vom 4. April beschlossen, zum einen den Einsitz der Schweiz im Exekutivrat des GCF anzustreben und zum andern eine Kandidatur der Schweiz als Sitzstaat für das permanente Sekretariat in Genf einzureichen. Der Genfer Staatsrat hat sich ebenfalls entschlossen, die Schweizer Sitzstaat-Kandidatur zu unterstützen. Aus Gründen der Effizienz ist es sinnvoll, inhaltlich verwandte Prozesse und Organisationen institutionell und geographisch zu konzentrieren. Genf und die Genfersee-Region sind ein wichtiges Zentrum der internationalen Umweltpolitik, in welchem zahlreiche internationale Organisationen einschliesslich Nichtregierungsorganisationen ihren Sitz haben.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Für Klimafragen ist beispielsweise der Hauptsitz der meteorologischen Weltorganisation WMO mit dem Sekretariat des Zwischenstaatlichen Ausschusses für Klimaänderungen IPCC und der Globalen Erdbeobachtungsinitiative GEO sehr relevant. 2011 wurde Genf zudem als Standort für die Einrichtung des Sekretariats des „Global Framework for Climate Services“ (GFCS) bestimmt.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Das UNO Umweltprogramm (UNEP) verfügt über ein Regionalbüro in Genf. Andere in der Finanzierung von Klimamassnahmen aktive Organisationen, namentlich die Weltbank und das UN Entwicklungsprogramm (UNDP), haben dort Vertretungen. Dies macht Genf zu einem Knotenpunkt für die politische und wissenschaftliche Arbeit im Umweltbereich allgemein und zunehmend auch im Klimabereich. Der GCF passt demnach sehr gut in diese institutionelle Landschaft und kann zu einer bedeutenden Aufwertung des internationalen Genf beitragen.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Neben der Schweiz haben bereits Deutschland und Südkorea eine Sitzstaatofferte in Aussicht gestellt. In Bonn befindet sich derzeit das provisorische Sekretariat des GCF für welches ein definitiver Standort ab 2014 gesucht wird. Den Entscheid über den definitiven Sitz fällen der GCF-Exekutivrat und die Konferenz der Vertragsparteien der UNO-Klimakonvention. Der Exekutivrat prüft im Verlauf des laufenden Jahres die eingereichten Sitzstaatkandidaturen und wird im Dezember 2012 einen konkreten Sitzvorschlag unterbreiten.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;b&gt;Auskünfte:&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/b&gt;Michel Mordasini, Chef des Kooperationsbereichs Globale Zusammenarbeit DEZA, 031 322 34 76&lt;br /&gt;Franz Perrez, Chef Abteilung Internationales BAFU, 079 251 90 15&lt;br /&gt;Daniel Birchmeier, Leiter Strategische Fragen, Wirtschaftliche Zusammenarbeit und Entwicklung SECO, 031 324 08 99&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Kommunikation EDA Bundeshaus West CH-3003 Bern Tel. Kommunikationsservice: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Medienstelle: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Renforcer Genève dans son rôle de plateforme internationale pour les questions environnementales</title>
      <lead>La Suisse est candidate pour accueillir le siège du secrétariat permanent du Fonds vert pour le climat (Green Climate Fund, GCF). Le 12 avril, elle a officiellement présenté la candidature de Genève. Également candidate à un siège au conseil exécutif du GCF, la Suisse fait valoir comme argument la possibilité de créer des synergies, diverses organisations actives dans le domaine de l’environnement étant déjà présentes à Genève. </lead>
      <text link="no">Sans l’aide internationale, les pays en développement qui doivent lutter contre la pauvreté ne parviennent pas à réduire leurs émissions de gaz à effet de serre et à prendre les mesures d’adaptation aux changements climatiques. La communauté internationale souhaite mobiliser 100 milliards USD par an pour aider ces pays à faire face aux défis climatiques. Créé en 2010 par les accords de Cancún, le Fonds vert pour le climat doit jouer à cet égard un rôle important puisqu’il sera chargé à moyen terme de gérer plusieurs dizaines de milliards de dollars et d’investir ces montants dans les pays en développement. La Banque mondiale assurera dans un premier temps les fonctions d’administrateur fiduciaire du GCF.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Dès 2014, le secrétariat du GCF devra avoir un emplacement définitif. Lors de sa séance du 4 avril, le Conseil fédéral a décidé de présenter la candidature de la Suisse, d’une part, pour siéger au conseil exécutif du GCF et, d’autre part, pour accueillir à Genève son secrétariat permanent. Le Conseil d’Etat genevois a décidé d’apporter son soutien à la candidature suisse pour l’accueil du secrétariat. La concentration institutionnelle et géographique des organisations aux activités connexes est judicieuse et permettrait de gagner en efficacité. Siège de nombreuses organisations internationales et organisations non gouvernementales, la ville de Genève et la région lémanique constituent un pôle majeur de la politique environnementale internationale.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Genève abrite en effet le siège de l’Organisation météorologique mondiale (OMM) ainsi que le secrétariat du Groupe d’experts intergouvernemental sur l’évolution du climat (GIEC) et celui du Groupe intergouvernemental sur l’observation de la terre (GEO), des organismes qui jouent un rôle important dans les questions climatiques. La ville de Genève a également été choisie, en 2011, pour accueillir le secrétariat du Cadre mondial des services climatiques (&lt;i&gt;Global Framework for Climate Services&lt;/i&gt;, GFCS).&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Le Programme des Nations Unies pour l’environnement (PNUE) dispose d’un bureau régional à Genève. D’autres organisations participant au financement de mesures climatiques, comme la Banque mondiale et le Programme des Nations Unies pour le développement (PNUD), y sont également représentées. La présence de toutes ces instances fait de Genève le point de convergence des activités politiques et scientifiques menées, de manière générale, dans le domaine de l’environnement, mais aussi, et ce de plus en plus, dans le domaine du climat. Le GCF s’intègrerait donc parfaitement dans le paysage institutionnel genevois et pourrait contribuer à accroître encore davantage la visibilité de la Genève internationale.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Outre la Suisse, l’Allemagne et la Corée du Sud ont également annoncé leur candidature pour accueillir le siège du GCF. Provisoirement installé à Bonn, le secrétariat du GCF devra avoir un emplacement définitif dès 2014. La décision finale sur le choix du site sera prise par le conseil exécutif du GCF et la conférence des États parties à la Convention-cadre des Nations Unies sur les changements climatiques. Le conseil exécutif examinera les candidatures dans le courant de l’année et soumettra une proposition concrète en décembre 2012.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;b&gt;Renseignements:&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/b&gt;Michel Mordasini, chef du domaine de direction Coopération globale (DDC), 031 322 34 76&lt;br /&gt;Franz Perrez, chef de la division Affaires internationales (OFEV), 079 251 90 15&lt;br /&gt;Daniel Birchmeier, responsable des questions stratégiques, Coopération et développement économiques (SECO), 031 324 08 99</text>
      <contact>Communication DFAE Palais fédéral ouest CH-3003 Berne Tél. Service de communication: +41 58 462 31 53 Tél. Service de presse: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <revisions>
        <revision date="2012-04-12 15:05" type="R"/>
      </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Rafforzare il ruolo di Ginevra come centro delle politiche ambientali internazionali</title>
      <lead>La Svizzera si è candidata ad ospitare la sede del Segretariato permanente del Fondo verde per il clima (Green Climate Fund). Il 12 aprile ha presentato un’offerta per accogliere la sede del Fondo a Ginevra. Al contempo si è candidata a un seggio nel Consiglio esecutivo. L'insediamento della nuova organizzazione in Svizzera consentirà la creazione di sinergie, poiché a Ginevra sono già presenti diverse organizzazioni operanti nel settore ambientale.</lead>
      <text link="no">Senza un sostegno internazionale, i Paesi in via di sviluppo, attanagliati dai problemi legati alla povertà, non sono in grado di ridurre le loro emissioni di gas serra e di realizzare i provvedimenti necessari per l’adattamento al cambiamento climatico. La comunità internazionale intende rafforzare il sostegno finanziario in ambito climatico destinato a questi Paesi, aumentando il contributo a 100 miliardi di dollari l’anno. Al Fondo verde per il clima, istituito nel 2010 con gli accordi di Cancun, è stato affidato l’importante mandato di gestire a medio termine decine di miliardi di dollari con l’obiettivo di investirli nei Paesi in via di sviluppo. La Banca mondiale agirà provvisoriamente da fiduciaria del Fondo.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Dal 2014 il Segretariato del Fondo dovrà avere una sede definitiva. Nella sua seduta del 4 aprile, il Consiglio federale ha deciso di candidare la Svizzera a un seggio nel Consiglio esecutivo e di proporre Ginevra come sede del Segretariato permanente del Fondo. Il Consiglio di Stato ginevrino ha deciso di appoggiare la candidatura della Svizzera in questa sede del Segretariato. La Confederazione ritiene infatti che sia più efficiente concentrare a livello sia geografico che istituzionale i processi e le organizzazioni inerenti a settori collegati. Ginevra e la regione del Lemano rappresentano un importante centro della politica ambientale internazionale grazie alle numerose organizzazioni internazionali governative e non governative presenti sul territorio.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Per le questioni ambientali riveste un ruolo preminente ad esempio la sede principale dell’Organizzazione meteorologica mondiale (OMM/WMO) con il Segretariato dell’&lt;i&gt;Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change &lt;/i&gt;(IPCC) e il &lt;i&gt;Group on Earth Observations&lt;/i&gt; (GEO). Nel 2011, Ginevra è stata scelta come sede del Segretariato del &lt;i&gt;Global Framework for Climate Services&lt;/i&gt; (GFCS).&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Nella città lemana hanno sede anche l’ufficio regionale del Programma delle Nazioni Unite per l’ambiente (UNEP) e talune rappresentanze di organizzazioni attive nel finanziamento di provvedimenti climatici quali la Banca mondiale e il Programma delle Nazioni Unite per lo sviluppo (UNDP). Ginevra è pertanto un punto nodale per l'attività politica e scientifica nel settore ambientale in generale e in misura crescente anche nell’ambito climatico. Il Fondo verde per il clima si inserisce perfettamente in questo contesto istituzionale e può pertanto contribuire in maniera significativa a valorizzare la Ginevra internazionale.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Oltre alla Svizzera, anche la Germania e la Corea del Sud hanno annunciato la propria candidatura. Bonn attualmente ospita la sede provvisoria del Segretariato del Fondo verde per il clima, al quale si intende dare una sede definitiva a partire dal 2014. La decisione spetterà al Consiglio esecutivo del Fondo e alla Conferenza delle parti contraenti della Convenzione delle Nazioni Unite sui cambiamenti climatici. Il Consiglio esecutivo esaminerà le candidature nel corso dell’anno e nel dicembre 2012 presenterà una proposta concreta in merito alla nuova sede.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;b&gt;Contatti:&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/b&gt;Michel Mordasini, Capo del settore cooperazione globale DSC, 031 322 34 76&lt;br /&gt;Franz Perrez, Capo della divisione Affari internazionali UFAM, 079 251 90 15&lt;br /&gt;Daniel Birchmeier, Responsabile Questioni strategiche, Cooperazione e sviluppo economici SECO, 031 324 08 99</text>
      <contact>Comunicazione DFAE Palazzo federale ovest CH-3003 Berna Tel. Servizio di comunicazione: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Servizio stampa: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Strengthening Geneva as a Hub for Environmental Concerns</title>
      <lead>Switzerland has announced its candidacy as host State for the permanent Secretariat of the Green Climate Fund (GCF). On April 12th it submitted its offer to domicile the Fund in Geneva. At the same time, Switzerland is running for a seat on the GCF’s Executive Board. This would make it possible to create synergies as various organizations active in the domain of the environment are already represented in Geneva. </lead>
      <text link="no">Without international support, developing countries, which have to cope with problems caused by poverty, are unable to reduce their greenhouse gas emissions and undertake the measures necessary to adapt to climate change. The international community is seeking to increase the climate-targeted financial support provided to these countries to an annual amount of USD 100 billion. The Green Climate Fund, founded in 2010 with the Cancun agreements, is slated to play a key role in this regard. It is to administer sums in the order of tens of billions, and invest in developing countries. In the start-up phase, the World Bank is to act as trustee for the GCF.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;By 2014, the Secretariat of the GCF is to have a definitive home. At its 4 April 2012 meeting, the Federal Council decided to strive for a Swiss seat on the Executive Board of the GCF, while simultaneously submitting Switzerland’s candidacy as host State for the permanent Secretariat in Geneva. The government of the Canton of Geneva has decided to support Switzerland’s candidacy as host State for the Secretariat. For reasons of efficiency, it is sensible to institutionally and geographically concentrate processes and organizations that are related in content. Geneva and the region bordering the Lake of Geneva form a major hub for international environmental policy and a centre in which numerous international organizations and NGOs are headquartered.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Geneva hosts the headquarters of the World Meteorological Organization, along with the Secretariat of the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change, and the Global Earth Observation Initiative. All these organizations have utmost relevance in climate issues. In addition, in 2011 Geneva was designated as the location for the Secretariat of the Global Framework for Climate Services.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;A Regional Office of the United Nations Environment Programme is located in Geneva. Other organizations active in the financing of climate measures, namely the World Bank and the UN Development Programme, have representations there. This makes Geneva a strategically significant location for political and scientific work in the environmental domain, and increasingly in the climate domain as well. The GCF fits very well into this institutional landscape and can contribute significantly to enhancing international Geneva.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;In addition to Switzerland, both Germany and South Korea have also offered themselves as prospective host countries of the GCF. At present, the provisional Secretariat of the GCF is in Bonn. The decision on the definitive location, from 2014, is in the hands of the GFC Executive Board and the Conference of the Parties to the UN Framework Convention on Climate Change. During the course of the year, the Executive Board will examine the candidacies and will submit a concrete proposal in December 2012.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;b&gt;Information:&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/b&gt;Michel Mordasini, Head of SDC’s Global Cooperation Department, 031 322 34 76&lt;br /&gt;Franz Perrez, Head of the International Division at the FOEN, 079 251 90 15&lt;br /&gt;Daniel Birchmeier, Responsible for Strategic Issues at Economic Cooperation and Development Division of SECO, 031 324 08 99</text>
      <contact>FDFA Communication Federal Palace West Wing CH-3003 Bern, Switzerland Tel. Communication service: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Press service: +41 58 460 55 55 E-mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @SwissMFA</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <offers>
      <offer id="143" org-id="811">
        <name lang="de">Medienmitteilungen des BAFU</name>
        <name lang="fr">Communiqués de l'OFEV</name>
        <name lang="it">Comunicati dell'UFAM</name>
        <name lang="en">Media releases of the FOEN</name>
      </offer>
    </offers>
    <keywords>
      <keyword id="560" org-id="811">
        <name lang="de">Internationales</name>
        <name lang="fr">Affaires internationales</name>
        <name lang="it">Affari Internazionali</name>
        <name lang="en">International Affairs</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="620" org-id="811">
        <name lang="de">Klima</name>
        <name lang="fr">Climat</name>
        <name lang="it">Clima</name>
        <name lang="en">Climate</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="173" org-id="811">
        <name lang="de">Bundesamt für Umwelt: Startseite</name>
        <name lang="fr">Office fédéral de l'environnement: page d'accueil</name>
        <name lang="it">Ufficio federale dell'ambiente: pagina iniziale</name>
        <name lang="en">Federal Office for the Environment: Homepage</name>
      </keyword>
    </keywords>
    <topics>
      <topic id="29">
        <name lang="de">Umwelt und Natur</name>
        <name lang="fr">Environnement et nature</name>
        <name lang="it">Ambiente e natura</name>
        <name lang="en">Environment and Nature</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
