<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="44287" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2012-04-25</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="1070" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>1070</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Der Bundesrat</name>
      <name lang="fr">Conseil fédéral</name>
      <name lang="it">Il Consiglio federale</name>
      <name lang="en">The Federal Council</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.admin.ch/gov/de/start.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.admin.ch/gov/fr/accueil.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.admin.ch/gov/it/pagina-iniziale.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.admin.ch/gov/en/start.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="301" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>301</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement des Innern</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'intérieur</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'interno</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Home Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="801" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>801</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Umwelt, Verkehr, Energie und Kommunikation</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'environnement, des transports, de l'énergie et de la communication</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'ambiente, dei trasporti, dell'energia e delle comunicazioni</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of the Environment, Transport, Energy and Communications</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.uvek.admin.ch/uvek/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.uvek.admin.ch/uvek/fr/home.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.uvek.admin.ch/uvek/it/home.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.uvek.admin.ch/uvek/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-uvek.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-uvek.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-uvek.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-uvek.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="701" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>701</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Wirtschaft, Bildung und Forschung</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'économie, de la formation et de la recherche</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'economia, della formazione e della ricerca</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Economic Affairs, Education and Research</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="317" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>301</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Bundesamt für Gesundheit</name>
      <name lang="fr">Office fédéral de la santé publique</name>
      <name lang="it">Ufficio federale della sanità pubblica</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Office of Public Health</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.bag.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.bag.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.bag.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.bag.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">media@bag.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">media@bag.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">media@bag.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">media@bag.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="811" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>801</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Bundesamt für Umwelt BAFU</name>
      <name lang="fr">Office fédéral de l'environnement OFEV</name>
      <name lang="it">Ufficio federale dell'ambiente UFAM</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Office for the Environment FOEN</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.bafu.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.bafu.admin.ch/fr</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.bafu.admin.ch/it</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.bafu.admin.ch/en</www>
      <email lang="de">info@bafu.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@bafu.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@bafu.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@bafu.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="703" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>701</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Staatssekretariat für Wirtschaft</name>
      <name lang="fr">Secrétariat d'Etat à l'économie</name>
      <name lang="it">Segreteria di Stato dell'economia</name>
      <name lang="en">State Secretariat for Economic Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.seco.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.seco.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.seco.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.seco.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@seco.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@seco.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@seco.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@seco.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="1070">
      <name lang="de">Der Bundesrat</name>
      <name lang="fr">Conseil fédéral</name>
      <name lang="it">Il Consiglio federale</name>
      <name lang="en">The Federal Council</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.admin.ch/gov/de/start.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.admin.ch/gov/fr/accueil.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.admin.ch/gov/it/pagina-iniziale.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.admin.ch/gov/en/start.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <department id="301">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement des Innern</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'intérieur</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'interno</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Home Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <department id="801">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Umwelt, Verkehr, Energie und Kommunikation</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'environnement, des transports, de l'énergie et de la communication</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'ambiente, dei trasporti, dell'energia e delle comunicazioni</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of the Environment, Transport, Energy and Communications</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.uvek.admin.ch/uvek/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.uvek.admin.ch/uvek/fr/home.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.uvek.admin.ch/uvek/it/home.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.uvek.admin.ch/uvek/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-uvek.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-uvek.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-uvek.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-uvek.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <department id="701">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Wirtschaft, Bildung und Forschung</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'économie, de la formation et de la recherche</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'economia, della formazione e della ricerca</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Economic Affairs, Education and Research</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Bundesrat führt Nano-Aktionsplan fort: Neue Internetplattform für das Publikum</title>
      <lead>Der Bundesrat will den Aktionsplan Synthetische Nanomaterialien bis Ende 2015 mit den vorhandenen Ressourcen weiterführen, aber gleichzeitig Prioritäten setzen. Er verabschiedete einen entsprechenden Bericht, der auch über die bisherige Umsetzung des Aktionsplanes aus dem Jahre 2008 Bilanz zieht. Ab sofort kann sich die Öffentlichkeit zudem auf www.infonano.ch über Nanotechnologie und Nanomaterialien informieren.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Mit dem Aktionsplan und seiner Fortführung will der Bundesrat den Nano-Standort Schweiz und den sicheren Umgang mit synthetischen Nanomaterialien fördern und weiter entwickeln. Dabei geht es in erster Linie darum, methodische Grundlagen für nanospezifische Vorschriften zu erarbeiten und so die Voraussetzungen für entsprechende Regulierungen zu schaffen sowie den Dialog mit Industrie, Wirtschaft, Wissenschaft, Forschung und Konsumentenschutzorganisationen weiterzuführen. Heute werden Nanomaterialien so wie herkömmliche Materialien vom Chemikalien- Lebensmittel- und Arzneimittelrecht erfasst. Die Daten- und Sicherheitsanforderungen bei Anmelde- und Zulassungsverfahren sind identisch. Die heutigen Grundlagen reichen für materielle nanospezifische Rechtsanpassungen noch nicht aus. Bis spätestens Ende 2014 soll ein neuer Bericht Auskunft über den Stand der Dinge geben. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Die seit 2008 erarbeiteten Massnahmen zum Umgang mit Nanomaterialien sollen laufend den neuen Erkenntnissen angepasst werden. Zu den Massnahmen gehören unter anderem ein Kriterienkatalog (Vorsorgeraster), um mögliche Gesundheits- und Umweltrisiken abzuschätzen. Gleichzeitig wurde ein Konzeptpapier zur Entsorgung von industriellen, nanomaterialhaltigen Abfällen erarbeitet und ein Leitfaden für die Sicherheitsdatenblätter zur Weitergabe von Informationen über Nanomaterialien in Industrie und Gewerbe verfasst. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Dabei arbeitet die Schweiz nicht isoliert, sondern methodische Grundlagen und Testmethoden werden international und koordiniert entwickelt. Unter Federführung der OECD, der Organisation für wirtschaftliche Zusammenarbeit und Entwicklung, wird beispielsweise überprüft, ob Testrichtlinien für Chemikalien auch auf Nanomaterialien angewendet werden können. Die Internationale Organisation für Standardisierung ISO ihrerseits definiert Begriffe der Nanotechnologie, die auch Grundlage für künftige schweizerischen Vorschriften sind. Das Nationale Forschungsprogramm NFP 64 „Chancen und Risiken von Nanomaterialien" will zusammen mit europäischen Forschungsprogrammen und Hochschulprojekten Fragen zu Wirkmechanismen und Teststrategien beantworten, um gefährliche Nanomaterialien rasch und zuverlässig erkennen zu können. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mit der neuen Internetplattform www.infonano.ch, einem departementsübergreifenden Gemeinschaftsprojekt verschiedener Bundesstellen, kommt der Bundesrat einem Bedürfnis von Konsumentenseite entgegen. Dies zeigte auch die Studie „Nanotechnologien aus der Sicht von Konsumenten", die das Bundesamt für Gesundheit BAG in den vergangenen zwei Jahren durchführen liess. Via Website soll sich die breite Öffentlichkeit umfassend und immer aktuell über, Chancen, allfällige Risiken und Gefahren von Nanomaterialen für Gesundheit und Umwelt informieren können. &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>BAG: Eva van Beek, Sektion Kommunikation, Tel. 031 322 95 05 oder media@bag.admin.ch BAFU: Andreas Weber Tel. 031 322 90 00, andreas.weber@bafu.admin.ch SECO: Kaspar Schmid, Ressort Chemikalien und Arbeit, Tel. 043 322 21 54, abch@ seco.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="96438">
        <title>Bericht des Bundesrates:</title>
        <uri>http://www.bag.admin.ch/nanotechnologie/12167/index.html?lang=de</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="96439">
        <title>Website InfoNano:</title>
        <uri>http://www.infonano.ch</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="96440">
        <title>Studie „Nanotechnologien aus der Sicht von Konsumenten“:</title>
        <uri>http://www.bag.admin.ch/nanotechnologie/12197/index.html?lang=de</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Nouveau site Internet pour le public : le Conseil fédéral poursuit le plan d’action sur les nanomatériaux</title>
      <lead>Le Conseil fédéral a décidé de poursuivre le plan d’action sur les nanomatériaux synthétiques jusqu’à fin 2015 avec les ressources disponibles, tout en fixant des priorités. Il adopte un rapport sur le sujet, qui dresse notamment le bilan sur la concrétisation du plan d’action de 2008. Dès à présent, le site www.infonano.ch fournit des informations sur les nanotechnologies et les nanomatériaux.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;En reconduisant le plan d'action, le Conseil fédéral entend promouvoir et poursuivre le développement du pôle des nanotechnologies en Suisse tout en assurant une utilisation sûre des nanomatériaux synthétiques. Il s'agit en premier lieu d'élaborer des bases méthodologiques, et de créer ainsi les conditions pour les réglementations spécifiques, tout en maintenant le dialogue avec l'industrie, l'économie, la science, la recherche et les organisations de protection des consommateurs. A l'heure actuelle, les nanomatériaux sont couverts, comme les autres produits, par les législations sur les produits chimiques, les denrées alimentaires et les produits thérapeutiques. Les exigences en matière d'enregistrement et de notifications en vue d'assurer la sécurité en matière de santé et de protection de l'environnement sont identiques. Des prescriptions spécifiques en matière de nanotechnologie font défaut car les bases actuelles ne sont pas suffisantes pour une adaptation matérielle de la législation. Un nouveau rapport, prévu pour 2014 au plus tard, fera le point de la situation. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Les mesures élaborées depuis 2008 pour l'utilisation des nanomatériaux doivent être adaptées en permanence aux nouvelles connaissances. Ces mesures comportent notamment un catalogue de critères (grille de précaution), destiné à évaluer les risques pour la santé et l'environnement. Parallèlement, un concept d'élimination des déchets industriels contenant des nanomatériaux a vu le jour ainsi qu'un guide sur les fiches de données de sécurité destinées à informer l'industrie et le commerce. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;La Suisse ne travaille pas de façon isolée ; les bases méthodologiques et les méthodes de tests sont développées au niveau international, de manière coordonnée. Ainsi, sous l'égide de l'Organisation de coopération et de développement (OCDE), on vérifie, par exemple, si les lignes directrices pour les essais afin de déterminer les propriétés des produits chimiques peuvent aussi s'appliquer aux nanomatériaux. L'Organisation internationale de normalisation (ISO), quant à elle, définit certaines notions de la nanotechnologie qui serviront également de base à de futures prescriptions suisses. Le Programme national de recherche PNR 64 « Opportunités et risques des nanomatérieux » a pour but de cerner les mécanismes d'action et les stratégies de tests, en coordination avec des programmes de recherche européens et des projets de hautes écoles, afin de reconnaître rapidement et clairement les nanomatériaux dangereux. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;En lançant le site Internet www.infonano.ch, un projet interdépartemental mené conjointement par plusieurs services de l'administration fédérale, le Conseil fédéral répond à un besoin des consommateurs. C'est d'ailleurs ce qui ressort de l'étude « Les nanotechnologies vues par les consommateurs », réalisée sur mandat de l'Office fédéral de la santé publique (OFSP) durant ces deux années dernières. Le nouveau site Internet doit permettre à un large public d'accéder à des informations complètes et actuelles sur les chances, les risques et les dangers que représentent les nanomatériaux pour la santé et l'environnement. &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>OFSP : Eva van Beek, section Communication, tél. : 031 322 95 05, media@bag.admin.ch OFEV : Andreas Weber Tel. 031 322 90 00, andreas.weber@bafu.admin.ch SECO : Kaspar Schmid, section Produits chimiques et travail, tél. : 043 322 21 54, abch@seco.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="96441">
        <title>Rapport du Conseil fédéral :</title>
        <uri>http://www.bag.admin.ch/nanotechnologie/12167/index.html?lang=fr</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="96442">
        <title>Site Internet :</title>
        <uri>http://www.infonano.ch</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="96443">
        <title>Etude « Les nanotechnologies vues par les consommateurs » :</title>
        <uri>http://www.bag.admin.ch/nanotechnologie/12197/index.html?lang=fr</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Il Consiglio federale decide di dare un seguito al Piano d'azione sui nanomateriali e crea una nuova piattaforma Internet per il pubblico</title>
      <lead>Il Consiglio federale intende dare un seguito al Piano d'azione sui nanomateriali di sintesi fino alla fine del 2015 utilizzando le risorse a disposizione, fissando al contempo delle priorità. Ha approvato un rapporto in tal senso che traccia anche un bilancio dell'implementazione del Piano d'azione avviato nel 2008 attuata finora. Il pubblico può sin d'ora informarsi sul sito www.infonano.ch in merito alla nanotecnologia e ai nanomateriali.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Con il Piano d'azione e il suo prosieguo, il Consiglio federale intende promuovere e sviluppare ulteriormente la piazza svizzera di nanotecnologia e l'utilizzazione sicura di nanomateriali di sintesi.&lt;b&gt; &lt;/b&gt;Si tratta innanzitutto di elaborare le basi metodologiche per prescrizioni nanospecifiche al fine di creare le condizioni necessarie al disciplinamento di questa materia nonché di proseguire il dialogo con l'industria, l'economia, la scienza, la ricerca e le organizzazioni per la protezione dei consumatori. Oggi, la regolamentazione dei nanomateriali e delle sostanze convenzionali è retta dal diritto sulle sostanze chimiche, sulle derrate alimentari e sui medicamenti. Nell'ambito delle procedure di notificazione e omologazione, i requisiti relativi ai dati e alla sicurezza sono identici.&lt;b&gt; &lt;/b&gt;Le basi normative attuali non sono ancora sufficienti per adeguamenti giuridici materiali nanospecifici. Al più tardi entro la fine del 2014, un nuovo rapporto fornirà informazioni sulla situazione.&lt;b&gt; &lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Le misure elaborate nel 2008 per l'utilizzazione dei nanomateriali devono essere costantemente adeguate alle nuove conoscenze in materia. Tra queste vi è l'allestimento di un catalogo dei criteri (griglia di prevenzione) finalizzato alla valutazione di eventuali rischi per la salute e l'ambiente. È anche stato approntato un documento programmatico per lo smaltimento di scorie industriali contenenti nanomateriali e redatta una guida per le schede dei dati di sicurezza inerenti alla trasmissione di informazioni sui nanomateriali nell'industria e nell'artigianato.&lt;b&gt; &lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In questo ambito la Svizzera non opera isolatamente ma agisce in modo coordinato e sul piano internazionale per sviluppare basi metodologiche e metodi per test. Sotto l'egida dell'OCSE, l'Organizzazione per la cooperazione e lo sviluppo economici, viene ad esempio esaminata la possibilità di applicare ai nanomateriali direttive riguardanti test destinate a prodotti chimici. L'Organizzazione Internazionale per la Standardizzazione ISO definisce a sua volta concetti di nanotecnologia che costituiscono la base per future prescrizioni svizzere. Il&lt;b&gt; &lt;/b&gt;Programma nazionale di ricerca PNR 64 «Opportunità e rischi dei nanomateriali» si prefigge, in collaborazione con programmi di ricerca europei e progetti universitari, di rispondere a domande relative a modalità d'azione e strategie per test, al fine di individuare velocemente e in modo affidabile i nanomateriali pericolosi. &lt;b&gt; &lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Con la nuova piattaforma www.infonano.ch, un progetto comune sviluppato da diversi servizi federali dei vari Dipartimenti, il Consiglio federale risponde a una necessità espressa dai consumatori.&lt;b&gt; &lt;/b&gt;Ciò è emerso anche dallo studio «Nanotechnologien aus der Sicht von Konsumenten» (Nanotecnologia dal punto di vista dei consumatori), condotto su mandato dell'Ufficio federale della sanità pubblica (UFSP) durante i due anni scorsi.&lt;br /&gt;Tramite il sito web, un vasto pubblico deve poter informarsi in modo completo e costantemente aggiornato sulle opportunità che offrono i nanomateriali, ma anche sui rischi che essi comportano per la salute e l'ambiente. &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>UFSP: Eva van Beek, Sezione comunicazione, tel. 031 322 95 05 o media@bag.admin.ch UFAM: Andreas Weber tel. 031 322 90 00, andreas.weber@bafu.admin.ch SECO: Kaspar Schmid, Settore prodotti chimici e lavoro, tel. 043 322 21 54, abch@ seco.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="96444">
        <title>Rapporto del Consiglio federale</title>
        <uri>http://www.bag.admin.ch/nanotechnologie/12167/index.html?lang=it</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="96445">
        <title>Pagina web InfoNano:</title>
        <uri>http://www.infonano.ch</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="96446">
        <title>Studio «Nanotecnologie viste dall’ottica dei consumatori »:</title>
        <uri>http://www.bag.admin.ch/nanotechnologie/12197/index.html?lang=it</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Federal Council Continues Nano Action Plan: New Internet Platform for the Public</title>
      <lead>Relying on the existing resources, the Federal Council continues the action plan for synthetic nanomaterials through the end of 2015, while at the same time setting priorities. It has adopted a report to that effect, which also takes stock of the implementation progress of the 2008 action plan. Effective immediately, the public can also access further information on nanotechnology and nanomaterials on www.infonano.ch. </lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;By continuing the action plan, the Federal Council aims to promote and develop the safe handling of synthetic nanomaterials as well as Switzerland as a nano-location. The primary focus is on developing a methodical basis for nano-specific provisions, thereby creating the prerequisites for appropriate regulation while continuing the dialogue with industry, economic stakeholders, the scientific and research communities as well as consumer organisations. Today, nanomaterials as well as conventional materials are regulated through chemicals, food and therapeutic products legislation. Data and safety requirements for registration and approval procedures are identical. The scientific basis is still insufficient for substantial nano-specific regulatory adjustments. By the end of 2014, a new report will provide an update on the situation. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The measures devised for the handling of nanomaterials since 2008 are to be continually updated to reflect new insights. The measures include a set of criteria (precautionary matrix) permitting an assessment of health and environmental risks. At the same time, a draft paper on the disposal of industrial waste containing nanomaterials was developed and guidelines were written for the creation of safety data sheets to pass on information about nanomaterials in industry and trade. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Switzerland is not working in isolation; the development of test methods and a methodical basis is coordinated internationally. Under the aegis of the OECD, the Organisation for Economic Co-operation and Development, a review is being conducted to determine whether test guidelines developed for chemicals are equally applicable to nanomaterials. And the International Organization for Standardization (ISO) is developing nanotechnology terms which will form the basis for future Swiss provisions. The National Research Programme NFP 64, "Opportunities and risks of nanomaterials", aims to answer questions regarding mechanisms of action and test strategies in collaboration with European research programmes and university projects in order to recognise dangerous nanomaterials quickly and reliably. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;With the new internet platform www.infonano.ch, an interdepartmental project of several federal organs, the Federal Council heeds a consumer need. This was also demonstrated by the study "Nanotechnologies from the consumers' point of view" which was conducted on behalf of the Federal Office of Public Health (FOPH) over the past two years. The site aims to provide comprehensive and current information on opportunities, risks and dangers of nanomaterials' effects on health and the environment. &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>FOPH: Eva van Beek, Communications Section, ph. +41 31 322 95 05 or media@bag.admin.ch FOEN: Andreas Weber ph. +41 31 322 90 00, andreas.weber@bafu.admin.ch SECO: Kaspar Schmid, Chemicals and Labour Department, ph. +41 43 322 21 54, abch@ seco.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="96447">
        <title>Report of the Federal Council</title>
        <uri>http://www.bag.admin.ch/nanotechnologie/12167/index.html?lang=en</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="96448">
        <title>Website InfoNano:</title>
        <uri>http://www.infonano.ch</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="96449">
        <title>Study “Nanotechnologies from the consumers’ point of view”:</title>
        <uri>http://www.bag.admin.ch/nanotechnologie/12197/index.html?lang=en</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <offers>
      <offer id="143" org-id="811">
        <name lang="de">Medienmitteilungen des BAFU</name>
        <name lang="fr">Communiqués de l'OFEV</name>
        <name lang="it">Comunicati dell'UFAM</name>
        <name lang="en">Media releases of the FOEN</name>
      </offer>
    </offers>
    <keywords>
      <keyword id="230" org-id="811">
        <name lang="de">Chemikalien</name>
        <name lang="fr">Produits chimiques</name>
        <name lang="it">Prodotti chimici</name>
        <name lang="en">Chemicals</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="173" org-id="811">
        <name lang="de">Bundesamt für Umwelt: Startseite</name>
        <name lang="fr">Office fédéral de l'environnement: page d'accueil</name>
        <name lang="it">Ufficio federale dell'ambiente: pagina iniziale</name>
        <name lang="en">Federal Office for the Environment: Homepage</name>
      </keyword>
    </keywords>
    <topics>
      <topic id="47">
        <name lang="de">Wirtschaft</name>
        <name lang="fr">Économie</name>
        <name lang="it">Economia</name>
        <name lang="en">Economic Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
