<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="44765" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2012-06-01</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="yes" id="602" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>601</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Generalsekretariat EFD</name>
      <name lang="fr">Secrétariat général DFF</name>
      <name lang="it">Segreteria generale DFF</name>
      <name lang="en">Secretariat-General FDF</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.efd.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.efd.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.efd.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.efd.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="601">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Finanzdepartement</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des finances</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale delle finanze</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Finance</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.efd.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.dff.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.efd.admin.ch/efd/it/home.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.efd.admin.ch/efd/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Staatsbesuch von Bundespräsidentin Widmer-Schlumpf in der Tschechischen Republik</title>
      <lead>Bundespräsidentin Eveline Widmer Schlumpf stattet der Republik Tschechien nächsten Montag und Dienstag einen offiziellen Staatsbesuch ab. Im Mittelpunkt steht ein Empfang bei Staatspräsident Václav Klaus auf der Prager Burg.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Während ihres Staatsbesuchs in Tschechien wird Bundespräsidentin Widmer-Schlumpf auch mit Ministerpräsident Petr Nečas, der Präsidentin des Abgeordnetenhauses, Miroslava Němcová, und Senatspräsident Milan Štĕch zusammentreffen. Auf dem Programm stehen zudem Gespräche mit Schweizer Wirtschaftsvertretern in Tschechien, eine Besichtigung des Klosters Strahov, eine Ehrenzeremonie beim Nationaldenkmal Vitkov und ein Besuch der Prager Altstadt.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Kommunikation EFD Tel. +41 58 462 60 33 E-Mail: info@gs-efd.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Visite d'Etat de la présidente de la Confédération Eveline Widmer-Schlumpf en République tchèque</title>
      <lead>Lundi et mardi prochains, la présidente de la Confédération Eveline Widmer-Schlumpf effectuera une visite d'Etat en République tchèque. Elle sera reçue par le président tchèque Václav Klaus au château de Prague.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;A l'occasion de sa visite, la présidente de la Confédération Eveline Widmer-Schlumpf rencontrera également le premier ministre Petr Nečas, la présidente de la Chambre des députés Miroslava Nĕmcová et le président du sénat Milan Štĕch. Au programme figureront également des discussions avec des représentants de l'économie suisse en République tchèque, une visite du couvent de Strahov, une cérémonie d'honneur au monument national de Vítkov et une visite de la vieille ville de Prague. &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Communication DFF Tél. +41 58 462 60 33 Courriel: info@gs-efd.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Visita di Stato della presidente della Confederazione Widmer-Schlumpf nella Repubblica ceca</title>
      <lead>Il prossimo lunedì la presidente della Confederazione Eveline Widmer Schlumpf si recherà nella Repubblica ceca per una visita ufficiale di due giorni, dove sarà ricevuta dal presidente ceco Václav Klaus al Castello di Praga.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Durante la sua visita nella Repubblica ceca la presidente della Confederazione Widmer-Schlumpf incontrerà anche il primo ministro Petr Nečas, la presidente della Camera dei deputati Miroslava Nĕmcová e il presidente del Senato Milan Štĕch. Sono inoltre previsti colloqui con esponenti svizzeri del mondo economico nella Repubblica ceca, una visita del Monastero di Strahov, una cerimonia commemorativa presso il monumento nazionale di Vitkov e una visita del centro storico di Praga.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Comunicazione DFF Tel. +41 58 462 60 33 E-Mail: info@gs-efd.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>State visit of President Widmer-Schlumpf to the Czech Republic</title>
      <lead>President Eveline Widmer-Schlumpf will make an official state visit to the Czech Republic next Monday and Tuesday. The highlight will be a reception hosted by President Václav Klaus in Prague Castle.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;During the state visit in the Czech Republic, President Widmer-Schlumpf will also meet the Prime Minister Petr Nečas, the Speaker of the Chamber of Deputies Miroslava Němcová and the President of the Senate Milan Štĕch. Also on the agenda are talks with Swiss representatives of the private sector in the Czech Republic, a visit to the Strahov monastery, a ceremony at the Vitkov national monument and a visit to the old town in Prague. &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Communication FDF Tel. +41 58 462 60 33 Mail: info@gs-efd.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <keywords>
      <keyword id="234" org-id="602">
        <name lang="de">Eveline Widmer-Schlumpf, Bundespräsidentin 2012</name>
        <name lang="fr">Eveline Widmer-Schlumpf, présidente de la Confédération en 2012</name>
        <name lang="it">Eveline Widmer-Schlumpf, presidente della Confederazione 2012</name>
        <name lang="en">Eveline Widmer-Schlumpf, President of the Swiss Confederation 2012</name>
      </keyword>
    </keywords>
    <topics>
      <topic id="33">
        <name lang="de">Bundespräsident/-in</name>
        <name lang="fr">Président/e de la Confédération</name>
        <name lang="it">Presidente della Confederazione</name>
        <name lang="en">President of the Swiss Confederation</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
    <catalogueElements>
      <catalogueElement id="60">
        <name lang="de">Widmer-Schlumpf Eveline (2007-2015)</name>
        <name lang="fr">Widmer-Schlumpf Eveline (2007-2015)</name>
        <name lang="it">Widmer-Schlumpf Eveline (2007-2015)</name>
        <name lang="en">Widmer-Schlumpf Eveline (2007-2015)</name>
      </catalogueElement>
    </catalogueElements>
  </message>
</messages>
