<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="44982" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2012-06-16</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="811" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>801</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Bundesamt für Umwelt BAFU</name>
      <name lang="fr">Office fédéral de l'environnement OFEV</name>
      <name lang="it">Ufficio federale dell'ambiente UFAM</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Office for the Environment FOEN</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.bafu.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.bafu.admin.ch/fr</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.bafu.admin.ch/it</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.bafu.admin.ch/en</www>
      <email lang="de">info@bafu.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@bafu.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@bafu.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@bafu.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="201" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>201</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="705" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>701</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Bundesamt für Landwirtschaft</name>
      <name lang="fr">Office fédéral de l'agriculture</name>
      <name lang="it">Ufficio federale dell'agricoltura</name>
      <name lang="en">Swiss Federal Office for Agriculture</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.blw.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.blw.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.blw.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.blw.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@blw.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@blw.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@blw.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@blw.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="703" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>701</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Staatssekretariat für Wirtschaft</name>
      <name lang="fr">Secrétariat d'Etat à l'économie</name>
      <name lang="it">Segreteria di Stato dell'economia</name>
      <name lang="en">State Secretariat for Economic Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.seco.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.seco.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.seco.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.seco.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@seco.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@seco.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@seco.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@seco.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="812" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>801</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Bundesamt für Raumentwicklung</name>
      <name lang="fr">Office fédéral du développement territorial</name>
      <name lang="it">Ufficio federale dello sviluppo territoriale</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Office for Spatial Development</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.are.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.are.admin.ch/are/fr/home.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.are.admin.ch/are/it/home.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.are.admin.ch/are/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@are.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@are.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@are.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@are.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="601" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>601</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Finanzdepartement</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des finances</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale delle finanze</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Finance</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.efd.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.dff.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.efd.admin.ch/efd/it/home.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.efd.admin.ch/efd/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="801">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Umwelt, Verkehr, Energie und Kommunikation</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'environnement, des transports, de l'énergie et de la communication</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'ambiente, dei trasporti, dell'energia e delle comunicazioni</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of the Environment, Transport, Energy and Communications</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.uvek.admin.ch/uvek/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.uvek.admin.ch/uvek/fr/home.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.uvek.admin.ch/uvek/it/home.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.uvek.admin.ch/uvek/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-uvek.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-uvek.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-uvek.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-uvek.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <department id="201">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <department id="701">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Wirtschaft, Bildung und Forschung</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'économie, de la formation et de la recherche</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'economia, della formazione e della ricerca</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Economic Affairs, Education and Research</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <department id="601">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Finanzdepartement</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des finances</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale delle finanze</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Finance</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.efd.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.dff.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.efd.admin.ch/efd/it/home.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.efd.admin.ch/efd/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Abschluss der Vorbereitungskonferenz für Rio+20 ohne Einigung</title>
      <lead>Am Freitagabend, 15. Juni 2012, musste in Rio de Janeiro die letze Vorbereitungskonferenz für die Rio+20 UNO Konferenz über Nachhaltige Entwicklung ohne Einigung abgeschlossen werden. Die Verhandlungen werden nun unter Leitung Brasiliens weiter geführt. Am Gipfel soll das Engagement für eine Nachhaltige Entwicklung erneuert und der Grünen Wirtschaft mehr Gewicht verliehen werden.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Hauptthemen der UNO-Nachhaltigkeitskonferenz von Rio de Janeiro vom 20. bis 22. Juni 2012 sind der Beitrag einer grünen Wirtschaft zur Nachhaltigen Entwicklung und Armutsreduktion sowie die Verbesserung der Institutionen, die sich auf internationaler Ebene mit der Nachhaltigen Entwicklung beschäftigen. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Vor dem eigentlichen Gipfel fand vom 13. bis 15. Juni in Rio die letzte Vorverhandlungsrunde auf Unterhändlerstufe statt. Die von Botschafter Franz Perrez, Chef der Abteilung Internationales im BAFU, geleitete Schweizer Delegation setzte sich insbesondere für eine ausgewogene Berücksichtigung aller Dimensionen der Nachhaltigkeit ein, für ein klares Engagement der internationalen Gemeinschaft zugunsten einer grünen Wirtschaft, welche zur Nachhaltigen Entwicklung und Armutsbekämpfung beitragen soll, für eine effizientere Ausgestaltung und Stärkung der für Nachhaltigkeit und Umwelt zuständigen UN Institutionen, und für die Schaffung globaler Nachhaltigkeitsziele. Sie engagierte sich zudem für klare Ziele und Massnahmen namentlich in den Bereichen nachhaltige Konsum- und Produktionsverhalten, Chemikalien- und Abfallmanagement, Landwirtschaft, Schutz vor Naturgefahren, Gesundheit, Berge und Armutsbekämpfung. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Die letzte Vorverhandlungsrunde musste am Freitagabend kurz vor Mitternacht ohne Einigung auf ein Abschlussdokument abgeschlossen werden. In den meisten Verhandlungsbereichen bestehen noch viele und zum Teil grosse Differenzen. Eine Einigung auf alle inhaltlichen Kernelemente einer Grünen Wirtschaft konnte wegen des Widerstandes der Gruppe der Entwicklungsländer noch nicht erreicht werden. Jedoch konnte das Verhältnis zwischen Nachhaltiger Entwicklung und Grüner Wirtschaft insofern geklärt werden, als dass letztere zum Erreichen von Nachhaltiger Entwicklung beitragen soll. Die USA blockieren den Beschluss eines 10 Jahresprogramms für nachhaltige Konsum- und Produktionsverhalten. Betreffend die Stärkung der für Nachhaltigkeit und Umwelt zuständigen UN Institutionen liegen immer noch mehrere Vorschläge vor, so auch der Schweizer Vorschlag für die Schaffung eines Rates für Nachhaltige Entwicklung. Konkrete und effektive Massnahmen zur effizienteren Ausgestaltung und Stärkung des internationalen Umweltregimes werden insbesondere von einzelnen grossen Entwicklungsländer sowie den USA und Kanada abgelehnt. Bezüglich des Vorschlags, globale Ziele zur Nachhaltigen Entwicklung auszuarbeiten, zeichnet sich dagegen eine Lösung ab.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Die Verhandlungen werden nun in einem informelleren Rahmen unter Leitung Brasiliens weiter geführt. Dafür können bis zur Ankunft der Staats- und Regierungschefs und Ministerinnen und Ministern noch 4 weitere Verhandlungstage genutzt werden. Botschafter Franz Perrez geht jedoch davon aus, dass auch während der Konferenz am Schlussdokument weiter verhandelt werden muss. «Wir können bis zum Abschluss der Konferenz am 22. Juni zumindest in einzelnen Punkten ein gutes Ergebnis erreichen», meint Franz Perrez. «Insbesondere ein Beschluss, globale Ziele für die Nachhaltige Entwicklung auszuarbeiten, wäre ein grosser Erfolg.» Derartige Ziele würden das Engagement der internationalen Gemeinschaft unterstreichen und der Staatengemeinschaft Orientierung bei der Verwirklichung der Nachhaltigen Entwicklung geben.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Schweiz in Rio auf höchster Ebene vertreten&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Bundespräsidentin Eveline Widmer-Schlumpf wird am 20. Juni 2012 an der Eröffnung der Konferenz teilnehmen, vor der Plenarversammlung eine Rede halten und bis am 21. Juni an den Verhandlungen auf Präsidentenstufe teilnehmen. Bundesrätin Doris Leuthard nimmt am 21. und 22. Juni an den Verhandlungen teil. &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Sektion Medien BAFU Telefon: +41 58 462 90 00 Email: mediendienst@bafu.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="98536">
        <title>Schweizer Plattform für Rio+20</title>
        <uri>http://rio20.ch</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>La conférence préparatoire de Rio+20 s’achève sans accord</title>
      <lead>Le 15 juin au soir, la dernière réunion préparatoire à la Conférence de l’ONU sur le développement durable, Rio+20, s’est terminée sans accord. Les négociations se poursuivent désormais sous les auspices du Brésil. Lors du sommet, il s’agira de renouveler l’engagement en faveur du développement durable et de renforcer le principe d’une économie verte. </lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Les principaux thèmes de la Conférence de l'ONU sur le développement durable qui se tiendra à Rio de Janeiro du 20 au 22 juin 2012 sont la contribution de l'économie verte au développement durable et à la réduction de la pauvreté, ainsi que l'amélioration des institutions internationales concernées. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Du 13 au 15 juin, s'est tenu à Rio le dernier tour des négociations préparatoires au niveau technique. La délégation suisse, menée par l'ambassadeur Franz Perrez, chef de la division Affaires internationales de l'OFEV, a mis l'accent tout particulièrement sur une prise en compte équitable de toutes les dimensions du développement durable, un engagement clair de la communauté internationale en faveur de l'économie verte, qui doit contribuer à la fois au développement durable et à la réduction de la pauvreté, une réforme et un renforcement des institutions onusiennes concernées et l'élaboration d'objectifs globaux de développement durable. La Suisse s'est par ailleurs engagée en faveur d'objectifs et de mesures claires dans les domaines suivants: modes de consommation et de production durables, gestion des produits chimiques et des déchets, agriculture, protection contre les dangers naturels, santé, montagnes, réduction de la pauvreté.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Le dernier tour des négociations préparatoires s'est achevé vendredi soir peu avant minuit sans accord sur un document final. De nombreuses divergences, certaines de taille, subsistent dans la plupart des domaines. Il n'a pas encore été possible de trouver un compromis sur le contenu de tous les principaux éléments de l'économie verte en raison de l'opposition du groupe des pays en développement. Toutefois, le lien entre développement durable et économie verte a pu être clarifié, dans la mesure où cette dernière doit contribuer au premier. Les USA s'opposent à la décision d'un programme décennal sur les modes de consommation et de production durables. En ce qui concerne le renforcement des institutions onusiennes concernées, plusieurs propositions restent d'actualité, dont celle de la Suisse, qui souhaite la création d'un Conseil du développement durable. Les mesures concrètes de réforme et de renforcement du régime environnemental international sont rejetées par certains grands pays en développement, ainsi que par les USA et le Canada. En revanche, une solution se dessine au sujet de la proposition d'élaborer des objectifs globaux de développement durable.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Les négociations se poursuivent désormais de manière informelle sous les auspices du Brésil, ce qui permet aux délégués de mettre à profit quatre jours supplémentaires d'ici l'arrivée des chefs d'Etat et de gouvernement ainsi que des ministres. L'ambassadeur Franz Perrez estime cependant qu'il sera nécessaire de continuer les négociations sur le document final pendant la conférence. «Sur certains points au moins, nous pouvons aboutir à un résultat satisfaisant d'ici la fin de la conférence. La décision d'élaborer des objectifs globaux de développement durable, notamment, constituerait un grand succès» conclue-t-il. De tels objectifs permettraient de souligner l'engagement de la communauté internationale et de guider les Etats dans la réalisation du développement durable.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;La Suisse représentée au plus haut niveau à Rio&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;La Présidente de la Confédération Eveline Widmer-Schlumpf assistera à l'ouverture de la conférence le 20 juin et tiendra un discours devant l'assemblée plénière. Elle participera aux négociations au niveau présidentiel jusqu'au 21 juin. La Conseillère fédérale Doris Leuthard participera aux négociations les 21 et 22 juin.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Section Médias OFEV Téléphone: +41 58 462 90 00 Courriel: mediendienst@bafu.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="98537">
        <title>Plateforme suisse pour Rio+20</title>
        <uri>http://rio20.ch/fr/</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Conferenza preparatoria per Rio+20: conclusa senza accordo</title>
      <lead>La sera di venerdì 15 giugno, a Rio de Janeiro, l’ultima conferenza preparatoria per la Conferenza delle Nazioni Unite sullo sviluppo sostenibile Rio+20 si è conclusa senza accordo. I negoziati proseguiranno ora sotto la direzione del Brasile. Al vertice verrà rinnovato l’impegno per uno sviluppo sostenibile e verrà dato maggiore rilievo all’economia verde.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Al centro della Conferenza dell'ONU sullo sviluppo sostenibile che si terrà a Rio de Janeiro dal 20 al 22 giugno 2012 vi sono il contributo di un'economia verde allo sviluppo sostenibile e alla lotta contro la povertà e il miglioramento delle istituzioni che si occupano di sviluppo sostenibile a livello internazionale.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Prima del vertice, si è svolta dal 13 al 15 giugno a Rio l'ultima tornata di trattative a livello di negoziatori. La delegazione svizzera, guidata dall'ambasciatore Franz Perrez, capo della divisione Affari internazionali dell'UFAM, si è impegnata in particolare per una maggiore considerazione di tutti gli aspetti legati alla sostenibilità, per un chiaro impegno della comunità internazionale a favore di un'economia verde, che deve contribuire allo sviluppo sostenibile e alla lotta contro la povertà, per un'organizzazione più efficiente e un rafforzamento delle istituzioni delle Nazioni Unite responsabili in materia di sostenibilità e di ambiente, nonché per la definizione di obiettivi globali di sostenibilità. Inoltre, la delegazione si è impegnata a favore di obiettivi chiari e di misure in particolare nei seguenti ambiti: comportamento di consumo e di produzione sostenibili, gestione di prodotti chimici e rifiuti, agricoltura, protezione contro i pericoli naturali, salute, montagne e lotta contro la povertà.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;L'ultima tornata di negoziati ha dovuto essere conclusa venerdì sera poco prima di mezzanotte senza un accordo su un documento finale. Nella maggior parte dei temi? (settori) negoziali sussistono ancora molte e in parte notevoli divergenze. Un accordo su tutti i contenuti relativi agli elementi chiave di un'economia verde non ha ancora potuto essere trovato a causa della resistenza opposta dal gruppo dei Paesi in via di sviluppo. Tuttavia, ha potuto essere chiarito il rapporto tra sviluppo sostenibile ed economia verde, come elemento ultimo determinante per lo sviluppo sostenibile. Gli Stati Uniti si sono opposti all'approvazione di un programma decennale volto a un comportamento di consumo e di produzione sostenibile. Per quanto concerne il rafforzamento delle istituzioni dell'ONU responsabili in materia di sostenibilità e ambiente, sono ancora sul tavolo diverse proposte, tra le quali quella avanzata dalla Svizzera per l'istituzione di un Consiglio per lo sviluppo sostenibile. Misure concrete ed effettive per un'organizzazione efficiente e un rafforzamento del regime ambientale internazionale vengono respinte in particolare da alcuni dei maggiori Paesi in via di sviluppo come pure da Stati Uniti e Canada. Per quanto concerne la proposta di definire obiettivi globali di sostenibilità, si delinea invece una soluzione.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I negoziati proseguiranno ora in un quadro più informale sotto la guida del Brasile. A tal fine sono disponibili ancora un massimo di quattro giorni di trattative prima dell'arrivo dei capi di Stato e di governo e dei ministri. L'ambasciatore Franz Perrez parte tuttavia dal presupposto che anche durante la Conferenza occorrerà proseguire i negoziati sul documento finale. «Entro la chiusura della Conferenza, il 22 giugno, possiamo raggiungere buoni risultati almeno su singoli punti», sostiene Perrez. «In particolare, la decisione di definire obiettivi globali per lo sviluppo sostenibile costituirebbe un notevole successo». Detti obiettivi consentirebbero di sottolineare l'impegno della comunità internazionale e l'orientamento della comunità di Stati nella realizzazione dello sviluppo sostenibile.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;La Svizzera rappresentata ai massimi livelli&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;La presidente della Confederazione Eveline Widmer-Schlumpf sarà presente il 20 giugno 2012 all'apertura della Conferenza, terrà un discorso davanti all'assemblea plenaria e parteciperà fino al 21 giugno ai negoziati a livello presidenziale. La consigliera federale Doris Leuthard parteciperà il 21 e 22 giugno ai negoziati.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Sezione Media Telefono: +41 58 462 90 00 E-mail: mediendienst@bafu.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="98538">
        <title>Piattaforma svizzera per Rio+20</title>
        <uri>http://rio20.ch/it/</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Rio+20 preparatory conference ends without agreement</title>
      <lead>The final preparatory conference for the Rio+20 UN Conference on Sustainable Development was forced to conclude without agreement on the night of Friday, 15 June. Negotiations will now continue under the aegis of Brazil. The commitment to sustainable development is due to be renewed and greater significance given to the green economy at the summit.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;The main topics of the UN Conference on Sustainability in Rio de Janeiro from 20 to 22 June 2012 are the contribution of a green economy to sustainable development, the eradication of poverty and the improvement of the institutions that deal with sustainable development at international level. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The final round of negotiations at preparatory committee level took place from 13 to 15 June in Rio. The Swiss delegation, which is led by Ambassador Franz Perrez, Head of the International Affairs Division at the FOEN, supported, in particular, the balanced consideration of all aspects of sustainability, the clear commitment of the international community to a green economy that would contribute to sustainable development and poverty eradication, the more efficient organisation and strengthening of the UN institutions responsible for sustainability and the environment, and the definition of global sustainable development goals. It also supported the adoption of clear objectives and measures, specifically in the areas of consumption and production behaviour, chemicals and waste management, agriculture, protection against natural hazards, health, mountains, and the eradication of poverty. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The final round of negotiations had to be concluded shortly before midnight on Friday without agreement being reached on a concluding document. Many and, in some cases, significant differences still exist in most areas. Agreement could not yet be achieved on all of the substantive, core elements of a green economy due to the opposition of the group of developing countries. However, it was possible to clarify the relationship between sustainable development and the green economy in that the latter should contribute to the attainment of the former. The USA is blocking the decision to adopt a ten-year programme for sustainable consumption and production behaviour. With regard to the strengthening of the UN institutions responsible for sustainability and the environment, several suggestions are still on the table, including Switzerland's proposal for the creation of a Council for Sustainable Development. Concrete and effective measures on the more efficient organisation and strengthening of the international environmental regime are rejected, in particular by individual major developing countries and the USA and Canada. However, a solution is emerging in relation to the proposal for the formulation of sustainable development goals. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The negotiations will now be continued on a more informal basis under the leadership of Brazil. Four additional days are available for these negotiations until the arrival of the heads of state and government and ministers at the conference. Ambassador Franz Perrez assumes, however, that negotiations on the final document will have to continue during the conference. "We can achieve a good outcome on individual points, at least, by the end of the conference on 22 June," he says. "A resolution on the formulation of global goals for sustainable development, in particular, would constitute a major success." Such goals would underscore the commitment of the international community and provide direction to the community of states in the attainment of sustainable development. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Switzerland represented in Rio at the highest level&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Eveline Widmer-Schlumpf, President of the Swiss Confederation, will participate in the opening of the conference on 20 June 2012, deliver a speech at the plenary meeting and participate at presidential level until 21 June. Federal Councillor Doris Leuthard will participate in the negotiations on 21 and 22 June. &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Media Section Telephone: +41 58 462 90 00 E-mail: mediendienst@bafu.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="98539">
        <title>Swiss Platform for Rio+20</title>
        <uri>http://rio20.ch/en/</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <offers>
      <offer id="46" org-id="812">
        <name lang="de">Nachhaltige Entwicklung</name>
        <name lang="fr">Développement durable</name>
        <name lang="it">Sviluppo sostenibile</name>
        <name lang="en">Sustainable spatial development</name>
      </offer>
      <offer id="47" org-id="812">
        <name lang="de">Raumplanung</name>
        <name lang="fr">Aménagement du territoire</name>
        <name lang="it">Pianificazione del territorio</name>
        <name lang="en">Spatial planning</name>
      </offer>
    </offers>
    <keywords>
      <keyword id="139" org-id="601">
        <name lang="de">Energiebesteuerung</name>
        <name lang="fr">Imposition de l'énergie</name>
        <name lang="it">Imposizione dell'energia</name>
        <name lang="en">Energy tax</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="204" org-id="601">
        <name lang="de">Verschiedenes Diverses</name>
        <name lang="fr">Autres: divers</name>
        <name lang="it">Diversi: altro</name>
        <name lang="en">Misc.</name>
      </keyword>
    </keywords>
    <topics>
      <topic id="25">
        <name lang="de">Raumplanung</name>
        <name lang="fr">Aménagement du territoire</name>
        <name lang="it">Pianificazione del territorio</name>
        <name lang="en">Spatial Planning</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
