<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="45315" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2012-07-06</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="815" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>801</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössische Kommunikationskommission ComCom</name>
      <name lang="fr">Commission fédérale de la communication ComCom</name>
      <name lang="it">Commissione federale delle comunicazioni ComCom</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Communications Commission ComCom</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.comcom.admin.ch/</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.comcom.admin.ch/</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.comcom.admin.ch/</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.comcom.admin.ch/</www>
      <email lang="de">comcom@comcom.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">comcom@comcom.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">comcom@comcom.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">comcom@comcom.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="801">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Umwelt, Verkehr, Energie und Kommunikation</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'environnement, des transports, de l'énergie et de la communication</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'ambiente, dei trasporti, dell'energia e delle comunicazioni</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of the Environment, Transport, Energy and Communications</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.uvek.admin.ch/uvek/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.uvek.admin.ch/uvek/fr/home.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.uvek.admin.ch/uvek/it/home.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.uvek.admin.ch/uvek/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-uvek.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-uvek.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-uvek.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-uvek.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Weg frei für neueste Mobilfunktechnologien</title>
      <lead>Keine der drei Konzessionärinnen Orange, Sunrise und Swisscom hat eine Beschwerde gegen die neuen Mobilfunkkonzessionen eingereicht. Damit ist das weltweit umfangreichste Vergabeverfahren von Frequenzen endgültig und erfolgreich abgeschlossen. Mit der Neuvergabe aller bisherigen und zusätzlicher Frequenzen hat die Eidgenössische Kommunikationskommission (ComCom) den Weg für stark breitbandige mobile Dienste (z.B. Videostreaming, Cloud-Dienste) freigemacht. Dies kann nun mit effizienteren, leistungsfähigeren Technologien der vierten Generation wie LTE (Long Term Evolution) geschehen. Die Konsumentinnen und Konsumenten werden damit in Zukunft von einer sehr guten Mobilfunkversorgung und qualitativ hoch stehenden Angeboten profitieren.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Im Februar 2012 hatte das Bundesamt für Kommunikation (BAKOM) im Auftrag der ComCom alle Mobilfunkfrequenzen versteigert. Neben den heute mit der GSM- und UMTS-Technologie genutzten Frequenzen wurden zusätzliche Frequenzen in den Bereichen 2600 MHz und 800 MHz (Digitale Dividende) vergeben. Somit stehen den Konzessionärinnen künftig deutlich mehr Frequenzen zur Verfügung als bisher. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Die weltweit einmalige Gesamtvergabe aller Mobilfunkfrequenzen in einer einzigen Auktion ist erfolgreich verlaufen und hat einen Gesamterlös von über 996 Millionen Franken ergeben. Die ComCom hat die Konzessionen Anfang Juni 2012 den Firmen Orange, Sunrise und Swisscom erteilt. Die Konzessionärinnen haben keine Beschwerden gegen die Konzessionen und das Vergabeverfahren eingereicht. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Jede der drei Betreiberinnen Orange, Sunrise und Swisscom konnte eine zukunftssichere Frequenzausstattung erwerben, die deutlich grösser ist als ihre bisherige. Damit ist sichergestellt, dass die stark wachsende Nachfrage nach mobilen Breitbanddiensten auch langfristig befriedigt werden kann. Heute verfügen bereits ein grosser Teil der Kundinnen und Kunden über ein Smartphone und die über Mobilfunknetze transportierten Daten verdoppeln sich alle 12 Monate. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mit dem Inkrafttreten der neuen Mobilfunkkonzessionen ist der Weg frei für hohe Investitionen in die neuesten Mobilfunktechnologien wie etwa LTE (Long Term Evolution of UMTS). Aufgrund der frühzeitigen Frequenzvergabe und einer Nutzungsdauer bis Ende 2028 können die Konzessionäre nun langfristig planen und auf einer gefestigten Grundlage investieren. Die Konsumentinnen und Konsumenten in der Schweiz werden auch künftig von qualitativ hoch stehenden Mobilfunkdiensten und weiter ansteigenden Übertragungsraten profitieren. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Vgl. Sie auch die Medienmitteilung vom 23.2.2012 und den zugehörigen Medienrohstoff &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>+41 58 463 52 90</contact>
      <link id="99826">
        <title>Medienmitteilung und Medienrohstoff vom 23.2.2012</title>
        <uri>http://www.comcom.admin.ch/aktuell/00429/00457/00560/index.html?lang=de&amp;msg-id=43520</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Feu vert pour les nouvelles technologies de téléphonie mobile</title>
      <lead>Aucun des trois concessionnaires, Orange, Sunrise et Swisscom, n’a fait recours contre les nouvelles concessions de téléphonie mobile. Ainsi, la plus large procédure d'adjudication de fréquences réalisée à l'échelle internationale s'est achevée avec succès. En réattribuant l'ensemble des fréquences, la Commission fédérale de la communication (ComCom) a ouvert la voie à l'utilisation de technologies de téléphonie mobile à très large bande (par ex. videostreaming, services Cloud). Cet objectif ne pourra être atteint qu'avec l’utilisation de technologies de téléphonie mobile plus efficaces et plus performantes de quatrième génération comme le LTE (Long Term Evolution). Les consommateurs pourront dès lors bientôt profiter d'une très bonne couverture ainsi que d'offres de qualité. </lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Au mois de février 2012, sur mandat de la ComCom, l'Office fédéral de la communication (OFCOM) avait mis aux enchères toutes les fréquences de téléphonie mobile. Outre les fréquences utilisées aujourd'hui avec les technologies GSM et UMTS, des fréquences supplémentaires ont été mises aux enchères dans les bandes 2600 MHz et 800 MHz (dividende numérique). Les concessionnaires disposeront ainsi d'un nombre de fréquences bien plus élevé qu'auparavant. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;La procédure, unique à l'échelle internationale, d'adjudication de l’ensemble des fréquences s'est achevée avec succès et a permis de générer des recettes de plus de 996 millions de francs. Au début du mois de juin 2012, la ComCom a attribué les concessions aux entreprises Orange, Sunrise et Swisscom. Les concessionnaires n'ont pas déposé de recours contre les concessions ni contre la procédure d'adjudication. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Chacun des trois opérateurs Orange, Sunrise et Swissom a ainsi pu acquérir une dotation en fréquences répondant à ses futurs besoins. Ils disposent dorénavant d'un plus grand nombre de fréquences et peuvent ainsi répondre à long terme à la demande croissante en services mobiles à haut débit. Aujourd'hui, un grand nombre de clients possèdent un smartphone et les données transférées via les réseaux mobiles doublent tous les 12 mois. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;L'entrée en vigueur des nouvelles concessions de téléphonie mobile permet d'ouvrir la voie aux investissements dans les technologies de téléphonie mobile de dernière génération comme le LTE (Long Term Evolution of UMTS). Sûrs de détenir des fréquences acquises jusqu'en 2028, les opérateurs disposent désormais d'une base solide pour planifier leurs investissements à long terme. En Suisse, les consommateurs pourront donc continuer de profiter de services mobiles de qualité et de vitesses de transfert accrues.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Cf. aussi le communiqué du 23.02.2012 et le dossier de presse &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Secrétariat de la ComCom, tél. +41 (0)31 323 52 90</contact>
      <link id="99827">
        <title>communiqué et dossier de presse du 23.02.2012</title>
        <uri>http://www.comcom.admin.ch/aktuell/00429/00457/00560/index.html?lang=fr&amp;msg-id=43520</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Via libera per le tecnologie di telefonia mobile di ultima generazione</title>
      <lead>Le concessionarie Orange, Sunrise und Swisscom non hanno formato alcun ricorso contro le nuove concessioni di telefonia mobile. La più ampia procedura di attribuzione di frequenze a livello mondiale ha dunque conosciuto un esito positivo e si conclude definitivamente. Con la nuova assegnazione di tutte le attuali e future frequenze, la Commissione federale delle comunicazioni (ComCom) ha aperto la strada ai servizi di telefonia mobile a banda larga (ad es. video streaming, cloud computing), che verranno offerti attraverso le tecnologie di comunicazione moderne e più efficienti della quarta generazione, come l'LTE (Long Term Evolution). L’offerta di servizi di telefonia mobile continuerà a rispondere anche in futuro agli elevati standard qualitativi, a tutto vantaggio dei consumatori.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Su mandato della ComCom, nel febbraio 2012 l'Ufficio federale delle comunicazioni (UFCOM) ha messo all'asta tutte le frequenze di telefonia mobile. Oltre a quelle attuali, sfruttate attraverso le tecnologie GSM e UMTS, sono state attribuite nuove frequenze nelle gamme dei 2600 MHz e 800 MHz, appartenenti al cosiddetto dividendo digitale. In futuro i concessionari disporranno così di un ventaglio di frequenze molto più ampio. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;L'assegnazione di tutte le frequenze di telefonia mobile nel quadro di una sola asta, unica nel suo genere, ha avuto esito positivo, generando ricavi totali per oltre 996 milioni di franchi. All'inizio di giugno, la ComCom ha attribuito le frequenze alle ditte Orange, Sunrise e Swisscom. Le concessionarie non hanno formato ricorso contro le decisioni e la procedura di assegnazione. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Le tre ditte Orange, Sunrise e Swisscom hanno potuto realizzare un'acquisizione importante per il futuro, aggiudicandosi un ventaglio di frequenze di gran lunga più ampio rispetto al passato. In tal modo è garantito che la domanda di servizi mobili a banda larga, caratterizzata da una forte crescita, possa essere soddisfatta anche a lungo termine. Già oggi molti clienti dispongono di uno smartphone e il volume dei dati trasmessi attraverso le reti di telefonia mobile raddoppia ogni 12 mesi. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Con l'entrata in vigore delle nuove concessioni di telefonia mobile si apre la strada a ingenti investimenti nelle più recenti tecnologie di telefonia mobile, come ad esempio l'LTE (Long Term Evolution of UMTS). L’assegnazione delle frequenze effettuata con largo anticipo e una durata d’utilizzo sino a fine 2028 permettono ai concessionari di fare piani a lungo termine e offrono una solida base d’investimento. Anche in futuro, le consumatrici e i consumatori svizzeri potranno pertanto beneficiare di servizi di telefonia mobile di elevata qualità e di una crescente velocità di trasmissione dei dati. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Vedi anche il comunicato stampa e la documentazione stampa dal 23.2.2012 &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Segreteria ComCom, tel. +41 (0)31 323 52 90</contact>
      <link id="99828">
        <title>comunicato stampa e documentazione dal 23.2.2012</title>
        <uri>http://www.comcom.admin.ch/aktuell/00429/00457/00560/index.html?lang=it&amp;msg-id=43520</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>The way is free for the latest mobile technologies</title>
      <lead>Since no licensee has lodged a complaint against the new mobile radio licences, the world's most extensive frequency award procedure is definitively and successfully concluded. With the new allocation of all existing and additional frequencies, the Federal Communications Commission (ComCom) has opened up the way for high-speed broadband mobile services (such as video streaming and cloud services). This can now take place using more efficient, more powerful fourth-generation technologies such as LTE (Long Term Evolution). Consumers will therefore be able to benefit also in future from very good mobile telephony coverage and high-quality products. </lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;In February 2012, the Federal Office of Communications (OFCOM), on behalf of ComCom, auctioned all mobile phone frequencies. In addition to the frequencies employed today using GSM and UMTS technology, additional frequencies were awarded in the 2600 MHz and 800 MHz ranges (the 'digital dividend'). Thus in the future significantly more spectrum will be available to licensees than before. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The overall award of all mobile radio frequencies in a single auction, unique worldwide, was conducted successfully and generated total revenue in excess of CHF 996 million. ComCom awarded the licences at the beginning of June 2012 to Orange, Sunrise and Swisscom. No licensee has lodged a complaint against the licences and the award procedure. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Each of the three operators – Orange, Sunrise and Swisscom – was able to acquire a future-proof spectrum allocation significantly larger than their previous one. This will ensure that it will be possible to meet the rapidly growing demand for mobile broadband services, even in the long term. Today, a large proportion of customers have already a smartphone and the data which is carried over mobile radio networks is doubling every 12 months. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The entry into force of the new mobile radio licences opens up the way for significant investment in the latest mobile technologies such as LTE (Long Term Evolution of UMTS). The early award of frequencies and a term which extends to the end of 2028 will now enable licensees to plan for the long term and make their investments on a solid basis. In the future, consumers in Switzerland will also benefit from high-quality mobile services and transmission speeds which will continue to increase. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;See also media release and media background material from 23.2.2012&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>ComCom Secretariat, tel. +41 (0)31 323 52 90</contact>
      <link id="99829">
        <title>media release and media background material from 23.2.2012</title>
        <uri>http://www.comcom.admin.ch/aktuell/00429/00457/00560/index.html?lang=en&amp;msg-id=43520</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <offers>
      <offer id="120" org-id="815">
        <name lang="de">Medienmitteilungen</name>
        <name lang="fr">Communiqués de presse</name>
        <name lang="it">Comunicati stampa</name>
        <name lang="en">Press releases</name>
      </offer>
    </offers>
    <keywords>
      <keyword id="140" org-id="815">
        <name lang="de">Bundesamt für Kommunikation (BAKOM)</name>
        <name lang="fr">Office fédéral de la communication (OFCOM)</name>
        <name lang="it">Ufficio federale delle comunicazioni (UFCOM)</name>
        <name lang="en">Federal Office of Communications (OFCOM)</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="630" org-id="815">
        <name lang="de">Kommunikationskommission, Eidg. ComCom</name>
        <name lang="fr">Commission fédérale de la communication ComCom</name>
        <name lang="it">Commissione federale delle comunicazioni ComCom</name>
        <name lang="en">Federal Communications Commission ComCom</name>
      </keyword>
    </keywords>
    <topics>
      <topic id="28">
        <name lang="de">Telekommunikation</name>
        <name lang="fr">Télécommunications</name>
        <name lang="it">Telecomunicazione</name>
        <name lang="en">Telecommunications</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
