<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="45624" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2012-08-17</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="yes" id="1060" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>601</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Staatssekretariat für internationale Finanzfragen</name>
      <name lang="fr">Secrétariat d'Etat aux questions financières internationales</name>
      <name lang="it">Segreteria di Stato per le questioni finanziarie internazionali</name>
      <name lang="en">State Secretariat for International Financial Matters</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.sif.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.sif.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.sif.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.sif.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@sif.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@sif.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@sif.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@sif.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="601">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Finanzdepartement</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des finances</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale delle finanze</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Finance</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.efd.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.dff.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.efd.admin.ch/efd/it/home.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.efd.admin.ch/efd/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Treffen zwischen Bundespräsidentin Eveline Widmer-Schlumpf und Premierminister Mario Monti im Engadin</title>
      <lead>Bundespräsidentin und Finanzministerin Eveline Widmer-Schlumpf und der italienische Premierminister Mario Monti trafen sich heute in Silvaplana, wo sich Mario Monti derzeit in den Ferien aufhält.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Mario Monti und Eveline Widmer-Schlumpf führten einen Meinungsaustausch über die aktuelle internationale Wirtschafts- und Finanzlage und die Herausforderungen, die sich daraus für die EU, die Schweiz und Italien ergeben. Im Zentrum des Gesprächs standen die gemeinsamen Anstrengungen der beiden Regierungen zur Bekämpfung der Steuerhinterziehung. Im Nachgang zum Treffen vom 12. Juni 2012 in Rom zogen die schweizerische Bundespräsidentin und der italienische Premierminister eine Zwischenbilanz über die laufenden Arbeiten der im Mai 2012 von den beiden Finanzministerien eingesetzten bilateralen Arbeitsgruppe für Finanz- und Steuerfragen. Sie bekräftigten die grosse Bedeutung, die sie raschen Fortschritten bei der konstruktiven Lösung der verbleibenden Fragen beimessen. Sie erwarten von der Arbeitsgruppe, dass sie ihnen bis diesen Herbst konkrete Vorschläge unterbreitet.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Mario Tuor, Kommunikation SIF +41 79 547 63 81, mario.tuor@sif.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Rencontre entre la présidente de la Confédération Eveline Widmer-Schlumpf et le premier ministre italien Mario Monti en Engadine</title>
      <lead>Eveline Widmer-Schlumpf, présidente de la Confédération et ministre des finances, et Mario Monti, premier ministre italien, se sont rencontrés aujourd'hui à Silvaplana, où Mario Monti passe actuellement ses vacances.</lead>
      <text link="no">Mario Monti et Eveline Widmer-Schlumpf ont échangé leurs vues sur la situation économique et financière actuelle au niveau international et sur les défis que celle-ci pose à l'Union européenne ainsi qu'à la Suisse et à l'Italie. Les efforts communs des deux gouvernements pour lutter contre la soustraction fiscale étaient au cœur de la discussion. Dans le sillage de leur rencontre du 12 juin dernier à Rome, la présidente de la Confédération et le premier ministre italien ont tiré un bilan intermédiaire des travaux menés par le groupe de travail bilatéral sur les questions financières et fiscales institué par les deux ministères des finances. Ils ont souligné l'importance qu'ils attachent à la résolution rapide et constructive des questions encore en suspens. Ils attendent du groupe de travail qu'il présente des propositions concrètes d'ici cet automne.</text>
      <contact>Mario Tuor, communication SFI +41 79 547 63 81, mario.tuor@sif.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Incontro tra la presidente della Confederazione Eveline Widmer-Schlumpf e il presidente del Consiglio italiano Mario Monti in Engadina</title>
      <lead>In data odierna la presidente della Confederazione Eveline Widmer-Schlumpf e il presidente del Consiglio italiano Mario Monti si sono incontrati a Silvaplana, dove Mario Monti sta trascorrendo alcuni giorni di vacanza.</lead>
      <text link="no">Mario Monti ed Eveline Widmer-Schlumpf hanno avuto uno scambio di opinioni sull'attuale situazione economica e finanziaria internazionale come pure sulle sfide che ne discendono per l'UE, la Svizzera e l'Italia. I colloqui hanno riguardato principalmente gli sforzi comuni intrapresi da entrambi i Governi per combattere la sottrazione d'imposta. Con riferimento all'incontro del 12 giugno 2012 a Roma, la Presidente della Confederazione e il presidente del Consiglio italiano hanno tracciato un bilancio intermedio dei lavori finora svolti dal Gruppo di lavoro istituito congiuntamente nel mese di maggio del 2012 dai due Ministeri delle finanze per affrontare determinate questione finanziarie e fiscali. Essi hanno ribadito la grande importanza che attribuiscono a rapidi progressi nella ricerca di soluzioni costruttive alle questioni irrisolte. Nel corso dell'autunno il gruppo di lavoro dovrebbe sottoporre loro proposte concrete.</text>
      <contact>Mario Tuor, Comunicazione SFI, + 41 (0)79 547 63 81, mario.tuor@sif.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>President Eveline Widmer-Schlumpf and Italy's Prime Minister, Mario Monti, meet in the Engadine</title>
      <lead>Switzerland's President and Finance Minister, Eveline Widmer-Schlumpf, and Italy's Prime Minister, Mario Monti, met in Silvaplana today, where Mario Monti is currently on holiday.</lead>
      <text link="no">Mr. Monti and Mrs. Widmer-Schlumpf exchanged views on the current international economic and financial situation and the challenges it poses for the EU, Switzerland and Italy. Their discussion focused on the joint efforts of both governments to fight tax evasion. Following up on the meeting which took place on 12 June in Rome, the Swiss President and the Italian Prime Minister reviewed the ongoing work and the progress achieved by the bilateral working group on financial and tax issues set up by the two finance ministers in May 2012. They confirmed the great importance they attach to swift progress in finding constructive solutions to the remaining issues. They expect the working group to present them with concrete proposals this autumn.</text>
      <contact>Mario Tuor, SIF Communications +41 79 547 63 81, mario.tuor@sif.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <offers>
      <offer id="291" org-id="1060">
        <name lang="de">Wirtschaft, Währung, Finanzplatz</name>
        <name lang="fr">Economie, monnaie, place financière</name>
        <name lang="it">Economia, Moneta, Piazza finanziaria</name>
        <name lang="en">Economic, Monetary and Financial Affairs</name>
      </offer>
    </offers>
    <keywords>
      <keyword id="235" org-id="1060">
        <name lang="de">Internationale Steuerpolitik</name>
        <name lang="fr">Politique fiscale internationale</name>
        <name lang="it">Politica fiscale internazionale</name>
        <name lang="en">International tax policy</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="126" org-id="1060">
        <name lang="de">Finanzplatz Schweiz</name>
        <name lang="fr">Place financière suisse</name>
        <name lang="it">Piazza finanziaria svizzera</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland as a financial centre</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="137" org-id="1060">
        <name lang="de">Internationale Doppelbesteuerung</name>
        <name lang="fr">Double imposition internationale</name>
        <name lang="it">Doppia imposizione internazionale</name>
        <name lang="en">International double taxation</name>
      </keyword>
    </keywords>
    <topics>
      <topic id="33">
        <name lang="de">Bundespräsident/-in</name>
        <name lang="fr">Président/e de la Confédération</name>
        <name lang="it">Presidente della Confederazione</name>
        <name lang="en">President of the Swiss Confederation</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="35">
        <name lang="de">Finanzplatz</name>
        <name lang="fr">Place financière</name>
        <name lang="it">Piazza finanziaria</name>
        <name lang="en">Financial Centre</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="44">
        <name lang="de">Steuern</name>
        <name lang="fr">Impôts</name>
        <name lang="it">Imposte</name>
        <name lang="en">Taxation</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="47">
        <name lang="de">Wirtschaft</name>
        <name lang="fr">Économie</name>
        <name lang="it">Economia</name>
        <name lang="en">Economic Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
