<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="46153" revoked="no">
    <version>2</version>
    <pubdate>2012-09-28</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="1070" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>1070</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Der Bundesrat</name>
      <name lang="fr">Conseil fédéral</name>
      <name lang="it">Il Consiglio federale</name>
      <name lang="en">The Federal Council</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.admin.ch/gov/de/start.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.admin.ch/gov/fr/accueil.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.admin.ch/gov/it/pagina-iniziale.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.admin.ch/gov/en/start.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="yes" id="602" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>601</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Generalsekretariat EFD</name>
      <name lang="fr">Secrétariat général DFF</name>
      <name lang="it">Segreteria generale DFF</name>
      <name lang="en">Secretariat-General FDF</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.efd.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.efd.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.efd.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.efd.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="1070">
      <name lang="de">Der Bundesrat</name>
      <name lang="fr">Conseil fédéral</name>
      <name lang="it">Il Consiglio federale</name>
      <name lang="en">The Federal Council</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.admin.ch/gov/de/start.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.admin.ch/gov/fr/accueil.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.admin.ch/gov/it/pagina-iniziale.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.admin.ch/gov/en/start.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <department id="601">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Finanzdepartement</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des finances</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale delle finanze</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Finance</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.efd.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.dff.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.efd.admin.ch/efd/it/home.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.efd.admin.ch/efd/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Neuer Vizepräsident und neues Mitglied des FINMA-Verwaltungsrates</title>
      <lead>Der Bundesrat hat an seiner heutigen Sitzung Paul Müller zum neuen Vizepräsidenten des Verwaltungsrates der Eidgenössischen Finanzmarktaufsicht (FINMA) gewählt. Paul Müller tritt per 1. Oktober 2012 die Nachfolge von Monica Mächler an, von deren Rücktritt der Bundesrat unter Verdankung der geleisteten Dienste Kenntnis genommen hat. Zum neuen Mitglied des FINMA-Verwaltungsrats wurde Franz Wipfli-Späni gewählt.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Monica Mächler hatte ihren Rücktritt als Vizepräsidentin und Mitglied des FINMA-Verwaltungsrates am 19. März 2012 angekündigt. Sie führte als Direktorin (2007-2008) das Bundesamt für Privatversicherungen in die FINMA über und war seit 2009 Vizepräsidentin des FINMA-Verwaltungsrates, aus dem sie per 30. September 2012 zurücktritt. Zu ihrem Nachfolger als Vizepräsident wählte der Bundesrat heute Paul Müller. Müller gehört seit 2009 dem FINMA-Verwaltungsrat an und war zuvor CEO Schweiz und Mitglied der Konzernleitung der Swiss Life.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Zum neuen Mitglied des FINMA-Verwaltungsrates wählte der Bundesrat Franz Wipfli-Späni. Wipfli-Späni war bis zu seiner Pensionierung im Jahr 2008 in verschiedenen leitenden Funktionen für die Zürich Versicherungsgruppe tätig, u.a. als CEO der Zürich Versicherungsgruppe Österreich und als Mitglied der erweiterten Konzernleitung der Zurich Financial Services. Sein aktuelles Mandat als Mitglied des Verwaltungsrates der KPT Versicherungsgruppe wird er mit dem Amtsantritt als FINMA-Verwaltungsrat am 1. Oktober 2012 niederlegen.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Beide Ernennungen erfolgen für den Rest der laufenden Amtsperiode des FINMA-Verwaltungsrates 2012-2015.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Roland Meier, Mediensprecher EFD 031 322 60 86, roland.meier@gs-efd.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Nouveau vice-président et nouveau membre du conseil d'administration de la FINMA</title>
      <lead>Lors de sa séance d'aujourd'hui, le Conseil fédéral a nommé Paul Müller vice-président du conseil d'administration de l'Autorité fédérale de surveillance des marchés financiers (FINMA). Paul Müller entrera en fonction le 1er octobre 2012 et succédera ainsi à Monica Mächler, dont le Conseil fédéral a pris acte de la démission et qu'il remercie pour les services rendus. Quant à Franz Wipli-Späni, il a été élu nouveau membre du conseil d'administration de la FINMA.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Monica Mächler avait annoncé, le 19 mars 2012, sa démission de son poste de vice-présidente et de membre du conseil d'administration de la FINMA. Directrice de l'Office fédéral des assurances privées (OFAP) de 2007 à 2008, elle occupait depuis 2009 le poste de vice-présidente du conseil d'administration de la FINMA qu'elle quitte au 30 septembre 2012. Aujourd'hui, le Conseil fédéral a nommé son successeur au poste de vice-président en la personne de Paul Müller. Membre du conseil d'administration de la FINMA depuis 2009, ce dernier a auparavant été CEO pour la Suisse et membre de la direction de Swiss Life.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Le Conseil fédéral a également nommé Franz Wipli-Späni nouveau membre du conseil d'administration de la FINMA. Avant de prendre sa retraite en 2008, Franz Wipli-Späni a assumé diverses fonctions dirigeantes au sein de groupe d'assurance Zurich, notamment celles de CEO du groupe Zurich Autriche et de membre de la direction élargie de l'entreprise Zurich Financial Services. Il renonce à son actuel mandat de membre du conseil d'administration du groupe d'assurance CPT pour devenir membre du conseil d'administration de la FINMA au 1er octobre 2012.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Les deux nominations sont valables pour le reste de la période administrative en cours du conseil d'administration de la FINMA, qui s'étend de 2012 à 2015. &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Roland Meier, porte-parole du DFF, 031 322 60 86, roland.meier@gs-efd.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Nuovo vicepresidente e nuovo membro nel consiglio di amministrazione della FINMA</title>
      <lead>In occasione della sua seduta odierna il Consiglio federale ha nominato Paul Müller quale nuovo vicepresidente del consiglio di amministrazione dell’Autorità federale di vigilanza sui mercati finanziari (FINMA). Paul Müller entrerà in funzione il 1° ottobre 2012 e succede a Monica Mächler, delle cui dimissioni il Consiglio federale ha preso atto ringraziandola per i servizi resi. Il Governo ha inoltre nominato Franz Wipfli-Späni membro del consiglio di amministrazione della FINMA.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Il 19 marzo 2012 Monica Mächler ha annunciato le proprie dimissioni da vicepresidente e membro del consiglio di amministrazione della FINMA. Nel periodo 2007-2008 ha contribuito al trasferimento dell'Ufficio federale delle assicurazioni private, del quale era direttrice, nella FINMA. Dal 2009 era vicepresidente del consiglio di amministrazione della FINMA dal quale ha dato le dimissioni per il 30 settembre 2012. In data odierna il Consiglio federale ha nominato Paul Müller quale suo successore alla carica di vicepresidente. Dal 2009 il signor Müller è membro del consiglio di amministrazione della FINMA e precedentemente è stato amministratore delegato per la Svizzera e membro della direzione del gruppo Swiss Life.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Il Consiglio federale ha inoltre nominato Franz Wipfli-Späni quale nuovo membro del consiglio di amministrazione della FINMA. Fino al 2008, anno del suo pensionamento, il signor Wipfli-Späni ha rivestito diverse funzioni dirigenziali presso il gruppo assicurativo Zürich, tra l'altro in veste di amministratore delegato dello stesso gruppo assicurativo per l'Austria e di membro della direzione allargata del gruppo assicurativo Zurich financial services. Egli rinuncerà al suo attuale mandato di membro del consiglio di amministrazione del gruppo assicurativo CPT con effetto al 1° ottobre 2012, data di entrata in funzione nel consiglio di amministrazione della FINMA.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Le due nomine hanno effetto per il rimanente periodo del mandato del consiglio di amministrazione della FINMA 2012-2015.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Roland Meier, portavoce DFF tel. 031 322 60 86, roland.meier@gs-efd.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>New Vice-Chair and new member of the FINMA Board of Directors</title>
      <lead>At its meeting today, the Federal Council elected Paul Müller as the Vice-Chair of the Board of Directors of the Swiss Financial Market Supervisory Authority (FINMA). Paul Müller will succeed Monica Mächler on 1 October 2012. The Federal Council took note of Ms. Machler's resignation and thanked her for services rendered. Franz Wipfli-Späni was elected as a new member of the FINMA Board of Directors. </lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Monica Mächler had announced her resignation as Vice-Chair of the FINMA Board of Directors on 19 March 2012. As Director (2007-2008), she oversaw the transfer of the Federal Office of Private Insurance to FINMA and since 2009 had been the Vice-Chair of the FINMA Board of Directors, a post from which she resigned on 30 September 2012. Today, the Federal Council elected Paul Müller to succeed her as Vice-Chair. Mr. Müller has been on the FINMA Board of Directors since 2009 and before that he was CEO Switzerland and a member of the Corporate Executive Board of Swiss Life.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Federal Council elected Franz Wipfli-Späni as a member of the FINMA Board of Directors. Up until his retirement in 2008, Mr. Wipfli-Späni had held various senior positions at Zurich Insurance Group, including CEO of Zurich Kosmos Austria and member of the Group Management Board of Zurich Financial Services. He will resign from his current mandate as a member of the Board of Directors of KPT Insurance Group when he assumes his position in the FINMA Board of Directors on 1 October 2012. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Both nominations are applicable for the remainder of the current term of office of the FINMA Board of Directors (2012-2015). &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Roland Meier, Media Spokesperson FDF, tel. 031 322 60 86, roland.meier@gs-efd.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="10">
        <name lang="de">Bundesrat</name>
        <name lang="fr">Conseil fédéral</name>
        <name lang="it">Consiglio federale</name>
        <name lang="en">Federal Council</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="35">
        <name lang="de">Finanzplatz</name>
        <name lang="fr">Place financière</name>
        <name lang="it">Piazza finanziaria</name>
        <name lang="en">Financial Centre</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="47">
        <name lang="de">Wirtschaft</name>
        <name lang="fr">Économie</name>
        <name lang="it">Economia</name>
        <name lang="en">Economic Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
