<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="47106" revoked="no">
    <version>3</version>
    <pubdate>2012-12-08</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="yes" id="811" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>801</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Bundesamt für Umwelt BAFU</name>
      <name lang="fr">Office fédéral de l'environnement OFEV</name>
      <name lang="it">Ufficio federale dell'ambiente UFAM</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Office for the Environment FOEN</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.bafu.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.bafu.admin.ch/fr</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.bafu.admin.ch/it</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.bafu.admin.ch/en</www>
      <email lang="de">info@bafu.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@bafu.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@bafu.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@bafu.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="801">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Umwelt, Verkehr, Energie und Kommunikation</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'environnement, des transports, de l'énergie et de la communication</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'ambiente, dei trasporti, dell'energia e delle comunicazioni</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of the Environment, Transport, Energy and Communications</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.uvek.admin.ch/uvek/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.uvek.admin.ch/uvek/fr/home.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.uvek.admin.ch/uvek/it/home.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.uvek.admin.ch/uvek/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-uvek.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-uvek.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-uvek.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-uvek.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Klimakonferenz in Doha beschliesst zweite Kyoto-Periode</title>
      <lead>Die UNO-Klimakonferenz in Doha (Katar) ging am 8. Dezember 2012 mit einer Einigung zu Ende. Das Kyoto-Protokoll wird bis 2020 weitergeführt. Für die Zeit danach wurde der Abschluss eines umfassenden Klimaabkommens bekräftigt. Aus Sicht der Schweizer Delegation wurde damit das Minimalziel erreicht.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Das Resultat der UNO-Klimakonferenz von Doha, die am Samstag, 8. Dezember 2012, zu Ende gegangen ist, fällt aus Sicht der Schweizer Delegation zwiespältig aus. Positiv ist die Weiterführung des Kyoto-Protokolls und die Zustimmung zu einer zweiten Verpflichtungsperiode (Kyoto 2) durch die EU, Australien, Norwegen, die Schweiz, Liechtenstein, Monaco, Kroatien und Island. Dadurch wird das bislang einzige verbindliche Abkommen zur Verminderung der Klima schädigenden Treibhausgase bis 2020 weitergeführt.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Weniger positiv ist folgender Umstand: Die in Kyoto 2 engagierten Länder sind für rund 14 Prozent des weltweiten Treibhausgasausstosses verantwortlich. Der Ausstoss der anderen grossen Verursacher wie unter anderem die USA, China, Japan, Brasilien, Südafrika, Indien oder Kanada ist damit nicht abgedeckt. Diese Staaten bekräftigten zwar ihr letztes Jahr in Durban angekündigtes Engagement und sagten eine gewisse Reduktion ihres Ausstosses zu. Zu verbindlichen Zielen wollten sie sich jedoch einmal mehr nicht verpflichten.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Damit, und mit den in Kyoto 2 gesteckten Zielen, sind die Staaten weit davon entfernt, die 2-Grad-Grenze einzuhalten, innerhalb welcher der Klimawandel als noch bewältigbar gilt. Immerhin bekräftigten alle Staaten den 2011 an der Klimakonferenz von Durban gefällten Entscheid, bis 2020 ein Klimaabkommen auf die Beine zu stellen, das alle Staaten und nicht nur die Industrieländer in die Pflicht nimmt. Zudem wurde den Entwicklungsländern die Weiterführung von Finanzhilfen zugesagt für die Bewältigung des Klimawandels. Auch die Schweiz führt ihre Finanzhilfe im bisherigen Rahmen fort und wird diese weiter ausbauen.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Aus Sicht der Schweizer Delegation hat Doha nur das Minimalziel erreicht. Es sind weiterhin grosse Anstrengungen nötig, um den nötigen Umbau hin zu einer Klima verträglichen und somit CO2-armen Wirtschaft und Gesellschaft zu bewerkstelligen. Auch wenn die an den internationalen Klimaverhandlungen beschlossenen Massnahmen nicht genügend sind, führt an solchen Treffen vorläufig kein Weg vorbei. Die Schweiz kann in diesem Forum als Kleinstaat mit dem gleichen Stimmrecht wie die grossen Staaten ihre Interessen vertreten. &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Sektion Medien BAFU Telefon: +41 58 462 90 00 Email: mediendienst@bafu.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="104790">
        <title>BAFU-Fokus: 18. UNO-Klimakonferenz in Doha</title>
        <uri>http://www.bafu.admin.ch/dokumentation/fokus/12020/12394/index.html?lang=de</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>A Doha, la Conférence sur le climat décide de reconduire le Protocole de Kyoto</title>
      <lead>A Doha (Qatar), la Conférence de l’ONU sur le climat s’est terminé le 8 décembre 2012 sur un accord, à savoir la prolongation du Protocole de Kyoto jusqu’en 2020. Pour la suite, la volonté de conclure un accord exhaustif sur le climat a été réaffirmée. La délégation suisse considère que l’objectif minimal est atteint.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Le résultat de la Conférence de Doha, qui s'est achevée samedi 8 décembre 2012, s'avère contradictoire aux yeux de la délégation suisse. La poursuite du Protocole de Kyoto et la convention d'une nouvelle période d'engagement (Kyoto 2) par l'UE, l'Australie, la Norvège, la Suisse, le Liechtenstein, Monaco, la Croatie et l'Islande sont des éléments positifs. En effet, elles signifient le maintien jusqu'en 2020 du seul accord contraignant signé jusqu'ici en matière de réduction des émissions de gaz à effet de serre (GEF).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Il est moins réjouissant de constater que les pays engagés dans Kyoto 2 sont responsables de quelque 14 % des émissions mondiales de GEF. La reconduction du Protocole ne couvre donc pas les émissions des autres gros pollueurs comme les Etats-Unis, la Chine, le Japon, le Brésil, l'Afrique du Sud, l'Inde ou le Canada. Ces Etats ont réaffirmé leur engagement pris à Durban l'an dernier et convenu d'une certaine réduction de leurs émissions, mais ils ont une nouvelle fois refusé de s'engager de façon contraignante.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Par conséquent et malgré Kyoto 2, nous sommes loin de respecter la limite maximale de deux degrés de réchauffement, mesure dans laquelle les changements climatiques sont considérés comme maîtrisables. Tous les pays ont toutefois confirmé leur décision prise en 2011 lors de la Conférence de Durban, à savoir mettre en place d'ici à 2020 un accord sur le climat qui soit contraignant pour tous et non uniquement les pays industrialisés. Par ailleurs, les pays en développement se sont vu promettre le maintien des moyens financiers à investir dans la maîtrise des changements climatiques. A ce sujet, la Suisse maintient son aide financière et envisage de l'augmenter à l'avenir.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;La délégation suisse estime que Doha n'a atteint qu'un objectif minimal. Des efforts conséquents doivent encore être fournis si l'on veut transformer l'économie et la société pour les rendre respectueuses du climat, c'est-à-dire pauvres en émissions de CO2. Même si les mesures décidées dans le cadre des négociations internationales sur le climat sont insuffisantes, ces rendez-vous demeurent actuellement incontournables. Dans ces rencontres, le droit de votre d'un petit Etat comme la Suisse a autant de poids que celui d'un grand pays.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Section Médias OFEV Téléphone: +41 58 462 90 00 Courriel: mediendienst@bafu.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="104791">
        <title>OFEV: Fokus - 18e Conférence des Nations Unies sur le climat à Doha</title>
        <uri>http://www.bafu.admin.ch/dokumentation/fokus/12020/12394/index.html?lang=fr</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>La Conferenza di Doha sul clima decide di prorogare il Protocollo di Kyoto</title>
      <lead>La Conferenza delle Nazioni Unite sul clima si è conclusa l'8 dicembre 2012 a Doha (Qatar) con un accordo. Il Protocollo di Kyoto sarà prorogato fino al 2020. Per il periodo successivo è stata riaffermata la volontà di giungere a un accordo globale sul clima. La delegazione svizzera ritiene che sia stato raggiunto solo l'obiettivo minimo. </lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;La delegazione svizzera traccia un bilancio in chiaroscuro del risultato della Conferenza delle Nazioni Unite sul clima, conclusasi a Doha sabato 8 dicembre 2012. Possono essere considerate positive la proroga del Protocollo di Kyoto e l'approvazione di un suo secondo periodo di adempimento (Kyoto 2) da parte di UE, Australia, Norvegia, Svizzera, Principati del Liechtenstein e di Monaco, Croazia e Islanda. Ciò consente di prorogare fino al 2020 l'unico accordo vincolante attualmente in vigore contro la riduzione dei gas serra climalteranti.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Meno positivo è invece il fatto che i Paesi che si sono impegnati in Kyoto 2 siano responsabili soltanto del 14 per cento circa delle emissioni globali di gas serra. Le emissioni degli altri grandi emettitori come gli Stati Uniti, la Cina, il Giappone, il Brasile, il Sudafrica, l'India o il Canada non sono tuttavia coperte da tale accordo. I Paesi appena elencati hanno confermato il loro impegno annunciato l'anno scorso a Durban e garantito una certa riduzione delle loro emissioni. Ma, ancora una volta, si sono rifiutati di aderire a obiettivi di riduzione vincolanti. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Adottando sia tale linea che gli obiettivi stabiliti nell'ambito di Kyoto 2, gli Stati sono ben lungi dal rispettare il limite di 2 gradi, soglia che dovrebbe evitare le conseguenze più drammatiche del mutamento climatico. Tutti gli Stati hanno comunque riaffermato la decisione, presa nel 2011 nel quadro della Conferenza di Durban, di dar vita entro il 2020 a una Convenzione sul clima vincolante per tutti gli Stati e non soltanto per i Paesi industrializzati. Inoltre, ai Paesi in via di sviluppo è stata garantita la proroga dei fondi per finanziare misure specifiche contro i cambiamenti climatici. La Svizzera, dal canto suo, manterrà l'aiuto finanziario ai livelli attuali e lo amplierà ulteriormente. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Secondo la delegazione svizzera, a Doha è stato raggiunto soltanto l'obiettivo minimo. Per realizzare l'indispensabile cammino verso un'economia e una società climacompatibili, e quindi a basse emissioni di CO2, occorrono ancora sforzi notevoli. Anche se le misure decise nell'ambito dei negoziati internazionali sul clima risultano insufficienti, al momento non è possibile rinunciare a conferenze di questo tipo. In questo consesso uno Stato piccolo come la Svizzera può usufruire dello stesso diritto di voto di uno Stato grande per difendere i suoi interessi.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Sezione Media Telefono: +41 58 462 90 00 E-mail: mediendienst@bafu.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="104792">
        <title>UFAM: Focus - 18a Conferenza dell’ONU sul clima a Doha</title>
        <uri>http://www.bafu.admin.ch/dokumentation/fokus/12020/12394/index.html?lang=it</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions>
        <revision date="2012-12-10 13:19" type="R"/>
        <revision date="2012-12-11 09:29" type="R"/>
      </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Climate conference in Doha decides on second Kyoto period</title>
      <lead>The UN Climate Change Conference in Doha (Qatar) ended on 8 December 2012 with an agreement. The Kyoto Protocol will be continued until 2020 and the conclusion of a comprehensive climate agreement was confirmed for the post-2020 period. From the perspective of the Swiss delegation the conference achieved the minimum of what it set out to do.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;In the view of the Swiss delegation, the outcome of the UN Climate Change Conference in Doha, which ended on Saturday 8 December 2012, is mixed. A positive aspect is the decision to continue the Kyoto Protocol and the agreement of the EU, Australia, Norway, Switzerland, Liechtenstein, Monaco, Croatia and Iceland to engage in a second commitment period (Kyoto 2). This means that the only binding international agreement on the reduction of climate-damaging greenhouse gas emissions that existed up to now will be extended to 2020. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The following detail is less positive, however: the countries that have undertaken a commitment to Kyoto 2 are responsible for around 14 percent of global greenhouse gas emissions. This does not include the emissions generated by the other major polluters including the USA, China, Japan, Brazil, South Africa and Canada. These states confirmed the commitment they made last year in Durban and agreed to a reduction in their emissions. However, once again, they did not want to commit to binding reduction targets.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Based on this and the targets set by Kyoto 2, the states are still a long way from complying with the two degree limit, below which climate change is viewed as being manageable. However, all of the states reiterated the decision taken at the Durban Climate Change Conference in 2011 for the establishment of a climate agreement by 2020, which will involve commitments by all states, and not only the industrialised countries. Financial support for the continuation of climate change mitigation was also approved for the developing countries. Switzerland will also continue to provide financial assistance within the established framework and will develop it further.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In the view of the Swiss delegation Doha only achieved the minimum of what it set out to do. Substantial efforts are still required to complete the development towards a climate-compatible and, hence, low-CO2 society and economy. Although the measures decided on at the international climate negotiations are not sufficient to achieve this, such summits remain crucial for the foreseeable future. This forum affords Switzerland as a small state the same voting rights in representing its interests as it does the major states. &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Media Section Telephone: +41 58 462 90 00 E-mail: mediendienst@bafu.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="104793">
        <title>FOEN: Focus - 18th UN Climate Change Conference in Doha</title>
        <uri>http://www.bafu.admin.ch/dokumentation/fokus/12020/12394/index.html?lang=en</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <offers>
      <offer id="143" org-id="811">
        <name lang="de">Medienmitteilungen des BAFU</name>
        <name lang="fr">Communiqués de l'OFEV</name>
        <name lang="it">Comunicati dell'UFAM</name>
        <name lang="en">Media releases of the FOEN</name>
      </offer>
    </offers>
    <keywords>
      <keyword id="560" org-id="811">
        <name lang="de">Internationales</name>
        <name lang="fr">Affaires internationales</name>
        <name lang="it">Affari Internazionali</name>
        <name lang="en">International Affairs</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="240" org-id="811">
        <name lang="de">CO2-Abgabe</name>
        <name lang="fr">CO2 taxe</name>
        <name lang="it">CO2 tassa</name>
        <name lang="en">CO2 tax</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="173" org-id="811">
        <name lang="de">Bundesamt für Umwelt: Startseite</name>
        <name lang="fr">Office fédéral de l'environnement: page d'accueil</name>
        <name lang="it">Ufficio federale dell'ambiente: pagina iniziale</name>
        <name lang="en">Federal Office for the Environment: Homepage</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="1803" org-id="811">
        <name lang="de">Emissionshandel</name>
        <name lang="fr">Échange de quotas d’émission</name>
        <name lang="it">Scambio di quote di emissioni</name>
        <name lang="en">Emissions trading</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="1812" org-id="811">
        <name lang="de">Klimakonferenz Kopenhagen</name>
        <name lang="fr">Klimakonferenz Kopenhagen</name>
        <name lang="it">Klimakonferenz Kopenhagen</name>
        <name lang="en">Klimakonferenz Kopenhagen</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="1816" org-id="811">
        <name lang="de">Klima: Anpassung</name>
        <name lang="fr">Climat: adaptation</name>
        <name lang="it">Clima: adattamento</name>
        <name lang="en">Climate: adaptation</name>
      </keyword>
    </keywords>
    <topics>
      <topic id="29">
        <name lang="de">Umwelt und Natur</name>
        <name lang="fr">Environnement et nature</name>
        <name lang="it">Ambiente e natura</name>
        <name lang="en">Environment and Nature</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
