<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="47337" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2012-12-21</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="201" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>201</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="201">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Die Schweiz und die Weltbank unterzeichnen ein Abkommen über die Rückführung von kasachischen Vermögenswerten</title>
      <lead>Über einen Treuhandfonds der Weltbank führt die Schweiz 48 Mio. USD an Kasachstan zurück. Die Gelder sollen der Bevölkerung Kasachstans zugute kommen. Eine entsprechende Vereinbarung haben die Direktion für Entwicklung und Zusammenarbeit (DEZA) und die Weltbank am 20. Dezember 2012 abgeschlossen. Diese Rückerstattung entspricht der langjährigen Politik der Schweiz im Kampf gegen den Missbrauch ihres Finanzplatzes. </lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Hintergrund der Rückerstattung ist ein Verfahren der Genfer Justizbehörden wegen Verdachts auf Geldwäscherei. Das Verfahren hat 2011 zur Konfiskation der nun zu restituierenden Vermögenswerte geführt. Dabei sind die am Verfahren beteiligten Parteien übereingekommen, die in der Schweiz blockierten Gelder in der Höhe von rund USD 48 Mio. für Projekte der Weltbank zugunsten der kasachischen Bevölkerung zu verwenden. Sie werden in Kasachstan für Projekte in den Bereichen Jugendpolitik und Energieeffizienz verwendet werden.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Die Schweiz bemüht sich seit über 20 Jahren zu verhindern, dass ihr Finanzplatz als sicherer Hafen für unrechtmässig erworbene Vermögenswerte missbraucht wird. Bezüglich der Rückerstattung von gestohlenen Geldern politisch exponierter Personen an die Herkunftsländer nimmt sie international eine Vorreiterrolle ein. Gemäss Schätzungen der Weltbank wurden in den letzten fünfzehn Jahren weltweit rund USD 5 Milliarden an betroffene Länder rückerstattet. Die Schweiz trug mit über USD 1.7 Milliarden zu gut einem Drittel dazu bei, mehr als jeder andere Finanzplatz. Die Schweiz setzt sich dafür ein, dass die restituierten Gelder als konkreter Beitrag zur Verbesserung der Lebensbedingungen der Bevölkerung in den betroffenen Ländern verwendet werden. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Kommunikation EDA Bundeshaus West CH-3003 Bern Tel. Kommunikationsservice: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Medienstelle: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>La Suisse et la Banque mondiale signent un accord sur la restitution de valeurs patrimoniales kazakhes</title>
      <lead>La Suisse va restituer 48 millions USD au Kazakhstan par l’intermédiaire d’un fonds fiduciaire de la Banque mondiale. Cet argent profitera à la population kazakhe. Un accord a été signé à cet effet le 20 décembre 2012 entre la Direction du développement et de la coopération (DDC) et la Banque mondiale. Cette restitution d’avoirs s’inscrit dans la droite ligne de la politique menée par la Suisse depuis de longues années pour protéger sa place financière des abus. </lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;La restitution des fonds fait suite à une procédure pour blanchiment d'argent ouverte par la justice genevoise dans le cadre de laquelle avaient été confisqués en 2011 les avoirs en question. Les parties à la procédure ont convenu d’affecter les avoirs bloqués en Suisse, qui s’élèvent à environ 48 millions USD, à des projets développés par la Banque mondiale en faveur de la population kazakhe. Ces projets concernent plus précisément les domaines de la politique de la jeunesse et de l’efficacité énergétique.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;La Suisse poursuit depuis plus de 20 ans une politique tendant à éviter que sa place financière ne serve de refuge à des avoirs illicites. Elle joue d’ailleurs un rôle de pionnier au niveau international en matière de restitution d’avoirs acquis illégalement par des personnes politiquement exposées. La Banque mondiale estime à près de 5 milliards USD le montant des avoirs qui ont été restitués à leurs pays d’origine au cours des quinze dernières années. La Suisse a contribué un tiers de ce montant: notre pays a en effet déjà restitué plus de 1,7 milliard USD, soit davantage que toute autre place financière. La Suisse met tout en œuvre pour que ces fonds soient utilisés de manière concrète dans l’amélioration des conditions de vie de la population des pays d’origine. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Communication DFAE Palais fédéral ouest CH-3003 Berne Tél. Service de communication: +41 58 462 31 53 Tél. Service de presse: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>La Svizzera e la Banca mondiale firmano un accordo per la restituzione di averi patrimoniali kazaki</title>
      <lead>La Svizzera restituisce 48 milioni di dollari al Kazakhstan tramite un fondo fiduciario della Banca mondiale. Questi averi saranno impiegati in favore della popolazione kazaka. Il 20 dicembre 2012 la Direzione dello sviluppo e della cooperazione (DSC) e la Banca mondiale hanno siglato un accordo in questo senso. La restituzione s’iscrive nel quadro della politica che la Svizzera persegue da anni nella lotta contro gli abusi della propria piazza finanziaria.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;La restituzione fa seguito ad una procedura giudiziaria promossa dalla giustizia ginevrina per sospetto di riciclaggio di denaro, che ha portato alla confisca nel 2011 degli averi oggetto della restituzione. Le parti coinvolte nella procedura hanno raggiunto un accordo, in base al quale gli averi bloccati in Svizzera, per una somma totale di circa 48 milioni di dollari, saranno impiegati per progetti della Banca mondiale in favore della popolazione kazaka, segnatamente per progetti nell’ambito della politica a favore della gioventù e dell’efficienza energetica.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Da oltre 20 anni la Svizzera si adopera affinché la sua piazza finanziaria non venga abusata quale rifugio per averi di provenienza illecita. Riguardo alla restituzione ai Paesi d’origine di averi acquisiti in modo illecito da persone politicamente esposte, la Svizzera assume un ruolo pionieristico a livello internazionale. Secondo le stime della Banca mondiale negli ultimi quindici anni sono stati restituiti ai Paesi coinvolti circa 5 miliardi di dollari. La Svizzera vi ha contribuito più di ogni altra piazza finanziaria con un importo superiore a 1,7 miliardi di dollari, pari a oltre un terzo della somma complessiva. In particolare la Svizzera presta attenzione affinché gli averi vengano restituiti in modo trasparente e utilizzati effettivamente per migliorare le condizioni di vita della popolazione nei Paesi interessati. &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Comunicazione DFAE Palazzo federale ovest CH-3003 Berna Tel. Servizio di comunicazione: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Servizio stampa: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Switzerland and the World Bank sign agreement on the restitution of Kazakh assets</title>
      <lead>Switzerland is using a World Bank trust fund as a means to return USD 48 million in assets to Kazakhstan. These funds are meant to benefit the people of Kazakhstan. The Agreement was signed by the Swiss Agency for Development and Cooperation (SDC) and the World Bank on 20 December 2012. This restitution is in keeping with Switzerland’s longstanding policy in combating the abuse of its financial centre. </lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;This restitution of Kazakh assets takes place within the context of a criminal investigation initiated by the Geneva judicial authorities on suspicions of money laundering. In 2011, the proceedings led to the confiscation of the assets that are now to be returned. The parties involved in the proceedings reached an agreement to use the some USD 48 million of funds confiscated in Switzerland for projects to the benefit of the Kazakh population. The money will be earmarked to finance projects in Kazakhstan in the domains of youth policy and energy efficiency.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;For over 20 years, Switzerland has been engaged in efforts to prevent its financial centre from being misused as a safe haven for illicitly acquired assets. With respect to the restitution of money stolen by politically exposed persons (PEPs) to the countries of origin, Switzerland plays a leading role on the international scene. According to World Bank estimates, over the last fifteen years, some USD 5 billion have been returned to the countries of origin worldwide. With a total of funds exceeding USD 1.7 billion, Switzerland contributed to a good third of this amount, more than any other financial centre. Switzerland is committed to ensuring that the monies returned be used as a concrete contribution to improving the living conditions of the population in the countries concerned. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>FDFA Communication Federal Palace West Wing CH-3003 Bern, Switzerland Tel. Communication service: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Press service: +41 58 460 55 55 E-mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @SwissMFA</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
