<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="79006" revoked="no">
    <version>3</version>
    <pubdate>2020-05-04</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="703" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>701</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Staatssekretariat für Wirtschaft</name>
      <name lang="fr">Secrétariat d'Etat à l'économie</name>
      <name lang="it">Segreteria di Stato dell'economia</name>
      <name lang="en">State Secretariat for Economic Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.seco.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.seco.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.seco.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.seco.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@seco.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@seco.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@seco.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@seco.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="1089" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>701</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Innosuisse – Schweizerische Agentur für Innovationsförderung</name>
      <name lang="fr">Innosuisse – Agence suisse pour l’encouragement de l’innovation</name>
      <name lang="it">Innosuisse – Agenzia svizzera per la promozione dell’innovazione</name>
      <name lang="en">Innosuisse – Swiss Innovation Promotion Agency</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.innosuisse.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.innosuisse.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.innosuisse.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.innosuisse.ch</www>
      <email lang="de"/>
      <email lang="fr"/>
      <email lang="it"/>
      <email lang="en"/>
    </originator>
    <department id="701">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Wirtschaft, Bildung und Forschung</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'économie, de la formation et de la recherche</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'economia, della formazione e della ricerca</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Economic Affairs, Education and Research</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>COVID19: Liquiditätshilfen für Startups sind operativ</title>
      <lead>Der Bundesrat hat am 22. April 2020 entschieden, aussichtsreiche Startups mit Coronabedingten Liquiditätsengpässen über das Bürgschaftswesen zu unterstützen. Die vom Bund anerkannten Bürgschaftsorganisationen verschaffen Startups einen leichteren Zugang zu Bankkrediten. Das Staatssekretariat für Wirtschaft SECO hat in Absprache mit den interessierten Kantonen und den Bürgschaftsorganisationen nun dafür die praktischen Voraussetzungen geschaffen. Bürgschaftsanträge können ab 7. Mai bis am 31. August 2020 eingereicht werden. </lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Gestützt auf das bestehende Bürgschaftswesen wurde ein besonderes Bürgschaftsverfahren zur Sicherung von Bankkrediten an qualifizierte Startup-Unternehmen geschaffen. Die Bürgschaft wird zu 65% vom Bund und zu 35% vom Kanton oder vom Kanton vermittelten Dritten getragen. Auf diesem Weg verbürgen Bund und Kanton (bzw. Dritte) gemeinsam zu 100% einen Betrag von bis zu CHF 1 Mio. pro Startup-Unternehmen. Der insgesamt verbürgte Betrag darf dabei höchstens einem Drittel der laufenden Kosten 2019 des Startups entsprechen. In begründeten Fällen kann der Kanton in seiner Beurteilung davon abweichen.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Startups stellen über die Webseite &lt;strong&gt;https://covid19.easygov.swiss/fuer-startups&lt;/strong&gt; einen Bürgschaftsantrag. Der Bürgschaftsantrag wird mit allen nötigen Unterlagen aus EasyGov dem teilnehmenden Kanton übermittelt. Eine vom Kanton bezeichnete Stelle prüft die Voraus-&lt;br /&gt;setzungen und leitet ihre Beurteilung des Bürgschaftsantrags an die zuständige Bürgschaftsorganisation weiter. Die Bürgschaftsorganisation entscheidet unter Berücksichtigung der Beurteilung der vom Kanton bezeichneten Stelle abschliessend über die Bürgschaft.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Auf dieser Grundlage kann das Unternehmen bei einer beliebigen Bank einen verbürgten Kredit beantragen. Berücksichtigt werden Bürgschaftsanträge, die vom 7. Mai bis 31. August 2020 via die oben genannte Plattform vollständig eingereicht wurden.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Die Kantone Waadt und Neuenburg haben als erste Kantone ihre Teilnahme an den Unterstützungsmassnahmen für Startups bestätigt. Die Liste der beteiligten Kantone wird laufend aktualisiert und die zuständigen Stellen sowie sämtliche Angaben zum Verfahren sind auf &lt;strong&gt;https://covid19.easygov.swiss/fuer-startups&lt;/strong&gt; publiziert.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Die zuständigen kantonalen Stellen können bei der Beurteilung bei Bedarf auf ein Expertengremium zurückgreifen, das von Innosuisse – der Schweizerischen Agentur für Innovationsförderung koordiniert wird. Dieses Gremium gibt eine Einschätzung ab, ob die antragstellen-den Unternehmen die Voraussetzung als wissenschafts- oder technologiebasierte Startups erfüllen.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;Die nachfolgenden dreizehn national ausgerichteten Organisationen des schweizerischen Start-up-Ökosystems beteiligen sich pro bono im Expertengremium: Business Angels Switzerland, Digital Switzerland, Gebert Rüf Stiftung, Impact Hub,&lt;br /&gt;Innosuisse, Mass Challenge, SEF4KMU, SICTIC, Swiss Entrepreneurs Foundation, Swiss Startup Group, &gt;&gt;Venture&gt;&gt;, VentureLab (IFJ), W.A. de Vigier Foundation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class="nsbtextkasten"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Welche Startup-Unternehmen sind berechtigt?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;• Startups mit Sitz in einem teilnehmenden Kanton und Gründung nach dem 01.01.2010, aber vor dem 01.03.2020&lt;br /&gt;• Aktiengesellschaften (AG) und Gesellschaften mit beschränkter Haftung (GmbH)&lt;br /&gt;mit Sitz in der Schweiz.&lt;br /&gt;• Startups, die nicht dem Landwirtschaftsbereich zugeordnet sind.&lt;br /&gt;• Startups, die sich nicht in einem Konkurs- oder Nachlassverfahren oder in Liquidation befinden.&lt;br /&gt;• Startups, die aufgrund der COVID-19-Pandemie wirtschaftlich erheblich beeinträchtigt sind und unter Liquiditätsengpässen leiden. Die Liquiditätshilfe bietet keinen Ersatz für Finanzierungsrunden.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Welche Angaben werden benötigt?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;• Laufende Kosten 2019. Die laufenden Kosten umfassen insbesondere die Löhne, die nicht aktivierungsfähigen Investitionen, die Mieten, Kosten für Patentanmeldungen und Patentanwälte, sowie die Kosten für interne oder ausgelagerte Forschungs- und Entwicklungs-Prozesse.&lt;br /&gt;• Jahresabschlussrechnungen zum Beleg der laufenden Kosten 2019 oder wenn nicht verfügbar 2018&lt;br /&gt;• Businesspläne&lt;br /&gt;• Angaben zum Unternehmen, inkl. Kontaktdaten einer Kontaktperson des Unternehmens.&lt;br /&gt;• Angaben zur kreditgebenden Bank.&lt;br /&gt;• Kreditvereinbarung und/oder Kreditanträge für allfällig erhaltene Kredite gemäss COVID-19-Solidarbürgschaftsverordnung vom 25. März 2020&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Weitere Voraussetzungen&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;• Das Startup-Unternehmen bestätigt, dass es zum Zeitpunkt der Einreichung des Antrags gemäss Art. 725 OR nicht in Überschuldung ist.&lt;br /&gt;• Das Geschäftsmodell des Startups ist skalierbar, wissenschafts- oder technologiebasiert und innovativ.&lt;br /&gt;• Allfällige Kredite gemäss COVID-19-Solidarbürgschaftsverordnung vom 25. März 2020 werden angerechnet.&lt;br /&gt;• Die Bürgschaftsorganisation entscheidet unter Berücksichtigung der Beurteilung des Kantons über die Bürgschaft. Auf dieser Grundlage kann das Unternehmen bei einer beliebigen Bank einen verbürgten Kredit beantragen.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Staatssekretariat für Wirtschaft SECO Holzikofenweg 36 CH-3003 Bern Tel. +41 58 462 56 56 Fax +41 58 462 56 00</contact>
      <link id="200654">
        <title>https://covid19.easygov.swiss/fuer-startups</title>
        <uri>https://bit.ly/3b9aohj</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions>
        <revision date="2020-05-04 14:59" type="R"/>
        <revision date="2020-05-05 10:27" type="R"/>
      </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>COVID-19 : les aides en matière de liquidités pour les start-up sont opérationnelles</title>
      <lead>Le 22 avril 2020, le Conseil fédéral a décidé d’utiliser le système de cautionnement pour soutenir les start-up prometteuses rencontrant des problèmes de liquidités liés au coronavirus. L’accès de ces entreprises aux crédits bancaires sera ainsi facilité par les organisations de cautionnement reconnues par la Confédération. Le Secrétariat d’État à l’économie SECO a élaboré, en concertation avec les cantons intéressés et les organisations de cautionnement, les conditions pratiques de cet instrument. Les demandes de cautionnement peuvent être soumises du 7 mai au 31 août 2020.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Une procédure de cautionnement particulière a été créée sur la base du système de cautionnement existant afin de garantir l’octroi de crédits bancaires à des start-up qualifiées. Ce cautionnement est assuré à 65 % par la Confédération et à 35 % par le canton ou par un tiers mandaté par le canton. De ce fait, la Confédération et le canton (ou un tiers) cautionnent intégralement un montant à hauteur de 1 million de francs par start-up. Ce dernier peut au maximum équivaloir à un tiers des frais courants 2019. Le canton peut, dans des cas motivés, diverger de ce montant dans son évaluation.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;À la différence de la procédure classique valable pour le cautionnement des PME, la start-up dépose une demande de cautionnement sur le site Internet &lt;strong&gt;https://covid19.easygov.swiss/fr/pour-startups&lt;/strong&gt;. Cette dernière est transmise, accompagnée de tous les documents requis, par EasyGov au canton participant. L’instance désignée par le canton examine les conditions et transmet son évaluation de la demande, ainsi que les documents y afférents à l’organisation de cautionnement compétente. L’organisation décide alors, en tenant compte de l’évaluation de l’instance désignée par le canton, d’octroyer ou non le cautionnement. Sur cette base, l’entreprise peut solliciter un crédit cautionné auprès de n’importe quelle banque. Seules les demandes de cautionnement complètes soumises entre le 7 mai et le 31 août 2020 inclus par le biais de la plateforme citée ci-dessus seront prises en compte.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Les cantons de Vaud et de Neuchâtel ont été les premiers à confirmer leur participation aux mesures de soutien aux start-up. La liste des cantons participants est actualisée en permanence ; les instances compétentes ainsi que l’ensemble des indications concernant la procédure sont publiées sur &lt;strong&gt;https://covid19.easygov.swiss/fr/pour-startups&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Pour l'évaluation des demandes, les services cantonaux compétents peuvent faire appel, si nécessaire, à un comité d'experts coordonné par Innosuisse – l’Agence suisse pour l’encouragement de l’innovation. Ce comité évaluera les entreprises qui soumettent une demande pour savoir si elles se qualifient en tant que start-up fondées sur la science ou la technologie. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Les treize organisations suivantes de l’écosystème suisse des start-up et d’envergure nationale participent à titre volontaire au comité d’experts : Business Angels Switzerland, Digital Switzerland, Gebert Rüf Stiftung, Impact Hub, Innosuisse, Mass Challenge, SEF4KMU, SICTIC, Swiss Entrepreneurs Foundation, Swiss Startup Group, &gt;&gt;Venture&gt;&gt;, VentureLab (IFJ), W.A. de Vigier Foundation. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class="nsbtextkasten"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Quelles entreprises sont éligibles ?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;• Start-up dont le siège se trouve dans un canton participant et fondées après le 01.01.2010 mais avant le 01.03.2020&lt;br /&gt;• Sociétés anonymes (SA) et sociétés à responsabilité limitée (sàrl) dont le siège est en Suisse&lt;br /&gt;• Start-up dont l’activité ne relève pas du domaine agricole&lt;br /&gt;• Start-up ne se trouvant ni en faillite, ni en procédure concordataire, ni en liquidation&lt;br /&gt;• Start-up rencontrant de graves difficultés économiques suite à la pandémie de COVID-19 et souffrant de problèmes de liquidités&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Quelles données sont nécessaires ?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;• Frais courants. Les frais courants englobent en particulier les salaires, les investissements non portés à l’actif, les loyers, les frais relatifs aux demandes de brevets et aux conseils en brevets, ainsi que ceux relatifs aux processus internes ou externalisés de recherche et développement.&lt;br /&gt;• Comptes annuels à titre de justificatif des frais courants de 2019 ou, si non disponibles, de 2018&lt;br /&gt;• Business plans&lt;br /&gt;• Données relatives à l’entreprise, y c. les coordonnées d’un(e) interlocuteur/interlocutrice au sein de l’entreprise&lt;br /&gt;• Données relatives à la banque créancière&lt;br /&gt;• Convention de crédit et/ou demandes de crédit relatives aux éventuels crédits obtenus au sens de l’ordonnance sur les cautionnements solidaires liés au COVID-19 du 25 mars 2020&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Conditions supplémentaires&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;• La start-up confirme qu’elle ne se trouve pas en situation de surendettement au sens de l’art. 725 CO au moment du dépôt de la demande.&lt;br /&gt;• Le modèle d’affaires est évolutif, fondé sur la science ou les technologies et novateur.&lt;br /&gt;• Les éventuels crédits au sens de l’ordonnance sur les cautionnements solidaires liés au COVID-19 du 25 mars 2020 sont pris en compte.&lt;br /&gt;• L’organisation de cautionnement décide alors, en tenant compte de l’évaluation du canton, d’octroyer ou non le cautionnement. Sur cette base, l’entreprise peut solliciter un crédit auprès de n’importe quelle banque.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Secrétariat d'Etat à l'économie SECO Holzikofenweg 36 CH-3003 Berne tél. +41 58 462 56 56 fax +41 58 462 56 00</contact>
      <link id="200655">
        <title>https://covid19.easygov.swiss/fr/pour-startups</title>
        <uri>https://bit.ly/2WrDSln</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions>
        <revision date="2020-05-04 14:59" type="R"/>
        <revision date="2020-05-05 10:27" type="R"/>
      </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>COVID-19: i sostegni in termini di liquidità per le start-up sono operativi</title>
      <lead>Il 22 aprile 2020 il Consiglio federale ha deciso di sostenere, per mezzo di fideiussioni, le start-up promettenti che hanno problemi di liquidità a causa della crisi dovuta al coronavirus. Le organizzazioni di fideiussione riconosciute dalla Confederazione agevolano le start-up nell’ottenimento di crediti bancari. La Segreteria di Stato dell’economia SECO, in accordo con i Cantoni interessati e le organizzazioni di fideiussione, ha ora messo a punto i presupposti pratici a tal fine. Le richieste di fideiussione possono essere presentate dal 7 maggio al 31 agosto 2020.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Sulla base dell’attuale regime di fideiussioni è stata creata una procedura di fideiussione particolare per garantire crediti bancari a start-up qualificate. Questa fideiussione è garantita al 65 per cento dalla Confederazione e al 35 per cento dal Cantone o da terzi reperiti dal Cantone. In questo modo, la Confederazione e il Cantone (o eventuali terzi) garantiscono congiuntamente al 100 per cento un importo massimo di un milione di franchi per ciascuna start-up. La somma complessiva garantita può corrispondere al massimo a un terzo delle spese correnti della start-up relative al 2019. In casi giustificati, il Cantone può derogare da questo principio nella sua valutazione.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Le start-up presentano una richiesta di fideiussione tramite il sito web &lt;strong&gt;https://covid19.easygov.swiss/it/per-le-start-up&lt;/strong&gt;. Tale richiesta viene trasmessa al Cantone aderente insieme a tutti i documenti necessari attraverso EasyGov. Un servizio designato dal Cantone verifica i requisiti e inoltra la valutazione della richiesta all’organizzazione di fideiussione competente. Quest’ultima decide in via definitiva in merito alla fideiussione tenendo conto della valutazione espressa dal servizio designato dal Cantone.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Su tale base, l’impresa può richiedere un credito garantito presso qualsiasi banca. Vengono prese in considerazione le richieste di fideiussione presentate in forma completa dal 7 maggio al 31 agosto 2020 attraverso la piattaforma summenzionata.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Il Canton Vaud ed il Canton Neuchâtel sono stati i primi due Cantoni a confermare la loro adesione al programma di sostegno per le start-up. L’elenco dei Cantoni aderenti viene aggiornato costantemente ed è consultabile alla pagina &lt;strong&gt;https://covid19.easygov.swiss/it/per-le-start-up&lt;/strong&gt; dove sono pubblicati i servizi competenti nonché tutte le informazioni relative alla procedura.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Se necessario, ai fini della valutazione i servizi cantonali competenti possono richiedere il supporto di un organo di esperti coordinato da Innosuisse, l’Agenzia svizzera per la promozione dell’innovazione. Tale organo valuta se l’impresa richiedente soddisfa i requisiti come start-up fondata sulla scienza o sulla tecnologia.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Le 13 seguenti organizzazioni con orientamento nazionale appartenenti all’ecosistema svizzero delle start-up partecipano gratuitamente all’organo di esperti: Business Angels Switzerland, Digital Switzerland, Gebert Rüf Stiftung, Impact Hub, Innosuisse, Mass Challenge, SEF4KMU, SICTIC, Swiss Entrepreneurs Foundation, Swiss Startup Group, &gt;&gt;Venture&gt;&gt;, VentureLab (IFJ), W.A. de Vigier Foundation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class="nsbtextkasten"&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Quali imprese vi hanno diritto?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;• Start-up con sede in un Cantone aderente e costituite dopo il 1° gennaio 2010 ma prima del 1° marzo 2020.&lt;br /&gt;• Società anonime (SA) o società a garanzia limitata (Sagl) con sede in Svizzera.&lt;br /&gt;• Start-up che non sono attive nel settore dell’agricoltura.&lt;br /&gt;• Nei confronti dell’impresa non è in corso una procedura di fallimento o concordataria né una procedura di liquidazione.&lt;br /&gt;• Start-up che, in seguito alla pandemia di COVID-19, subiscono un notevole pregiudizio economico e si ritrovano a corto di liquidità.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Quali dati sono richiesti?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;• Spese correnti. Le spese correnti comprendono soprattutto i salari, gli investimenti non iscrivibili all’attivo, gli affitti, le spese per le domande di brevetti e i consulenti in brevetti, nonché quelle per i processi di ricerca e sviluppo (R&amp;S) interni o esternalizzati.&lt;br /&gt;• Rendiconti annuali a riprova delle spese correnti del 2019 o, se queste ultime non sono disponibili, di quelle del 2018.&lt;br /&gt;• Business plan.&lt;br /&gt;• Dati relativi all’impresa, inclusi i dati di contatto di un interlocutore all’interno dell’impresa.&lt;br /&gt;• Dati relativi alla banca creditrice.&lt;br /&gt;• Richieste di credito pendenti e/o accordi per crediti eventualmente già ottenuti ai sensi dell’ordinanza sulle fideiussioni solidali COVID-19 del 25 marzo 2020&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ulteriori requisiti&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;• La start-up conferma di non avere, al momento della presentazione della richiesta, un’eccedenza di debiti ai sensi dell’art. 725 CO.&lt;br /&gt;• Il modello di business è scalabile, innovativo, basato sulla scienza o sulla tecnologia.&lt;br /&gt;• Si tiene conto di eventuali crediti ai sensi dell’ordinanza sulle fideiussioni solidali COVID-19 del 25 marzo 2020.&lt;br /&gt;• L’organizzazione di fideiussione decide in merito alla fideiussione tenendo conto della valutazione espressa dal Cantone. Su tale base, l’impresa può richiedere un credito presso qualsiasi banca.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Segreteria di Stato dell'economia SECO Holzikofenweg 36 CH-3003 Berna tel. +41 58 462 56 56 fax +41 58 462 56 00</contact>
      <link id="200656">
        <title>https://covid19.easygov.swiss/it/per-le-start-up</title>
        <uri>https://bit.ly/2KZM0UT</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions>
        <revision date="2020-05-04 14:59" type="R"/>
        <revision date="2020-05-05 10:27" type="R"/>
      </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>COVID19: liquidity support for startups up and running</title>
      <lead>On 22 April 2020, the Federal Council agreed a guarantee scheme to support promising startups encountering liquidity problems caused by the coronavirus. The government-accredited loan guarantee organisations facilitate access to bank loans for startups. The State Secretariat for Economic Affairs SECO has thus set out the practical criteria for this in consultation with interested cantons and the loan guarantee organisations. Loan guarantee applications can be submitted from 7 May up to 31 August 2020.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Based on the existing loan guarantee scheme, a special guarantee procedure was created to secure bank loans for eligible startup companies. 65% of the loan guarantee is provided by the federal government and 35% is provided by the canton or third parties appointed by the canton. In this way, the federal government and the canton (or third party) jointly guarantee 100% of an amount of up to CHF 1 million per startup company. The total amount guaranteed may not exceed one third of the startup’s 2019 running costs. In justified cases, the canton may deviate from this in its evaluation.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Startups submit a loan guarantee application via the website &lt;strong&gt;https://covid19.easygov.swiss/en/for-startups&lt;/strong&gt;. The loan guarantee application is sent to the participating canton together with all the required documents from EasyGov. A body appointed by the canton reviews the criteria and forwards its evaluation of the loan guarantee application to the responsible loan guarantee organisation. The loan guarantee organisation makes the final decision on the loan guarantee taking into account the evaluation by the body appointed by the canton. On that basis, the company can apply for a guaranteed loan from any bank. Loan guarantee applications which were submitted in full from 7 May up to 31 August 2020 using the above-mentioned platform are taken into consideration. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The cantons of Vaud and Neuchâtel were the first to have confirmed their participation in the support measures for startups. The list of participating cantons is updated on an ongoing basis and the responsible bodies and all information about the procedure is published at &lt;strong&gt;https://covid19.easygov.swiss/en/for-startups&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;strong&gt;.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The responsible cantonal bodies can make use of an expert group which is coordinated by Innosuisse – the Swiss Innovation Agency – during the evaluation if required. This group submits an assessment of whether the companies applying meet the requirement as science- or technology-based startups.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;The following 13 organisations in the Swiss startup ecosystem with a national focus participate pro bono in the expert group:&lt;br /&gt;Business Angels Switzerland, Digital Switzerland, Gebert Rüf Stiftung, Impact Hub, Innosuisse, Mass Challenge, SEF4KMU, SICTIC, Swiss Entrepreneurs Foundation, Swiss Startup Group, &gt;&gt;Venture&gt;&gt;, VentureLab (IFJ), W.A. de Vigier Foundation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class="nsbtextkasten"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Which companies are eligible?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;• Startups based in a participating canton and founded after 1 January 2010 but before 1 March 2020&lt;br /&gt;• Companies limited by shares (AG) and companies with limited liability (GmbH) based in Switzerland.&lt;br /&gt;• Startups that are not part of the agricultural sector.&lt;br /&gt;• The startup is not in bankruptcy or composition proceedings or in liquidation&lt;br /&gt;• Startups that are suffering significant financial and liquidity problems due to the COVID-19 pandemic.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What information is required?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;• Current expenses. In particular, current expenses comprise wages, investment that is not eligible for capitalisation, rents, costs of patent applications and patent lawyers as well as costs for internal or outsourced research and development processes.&lt;br /&gt;• Annual financial statements as evidence of current expenses in 2019 or, if not available, in 2018&lt;br /&gt;• Business plans&lt;br /&gt;• Company details, including contact details of a contact at the company.&lt;br /&gt;• Details of the lending bank.&lt;br /&gt;• Loan agreement and/or loan applications for any loans received in accordance with the COVID-19 Joint and Several Loan Guarantee Ordinance (COVID-19-Solidarbürgschaftsverordnung) of 25 March 2020&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Additional requirements&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;• The startup will confirm that it is not insolvent pursuant to Art. 725 CO at the date it submits the application.&lt;br /&gt;• The business model is scalable, science- or technology-based and innovative.&lt;br /&gt;• Any loans pursuant to the COVID-19 Joint and Several Loan Guarantee Ordinance (COVID-19-Solidarbürgschaftsverordnung) of 25 March 2020 will be included.&lt;br /&gt;• The loan guarantee organisation will decide on the guarantee, taking account of the canton’s assessment. On this basis, the company can apply for a loan with any bank.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>State Secretariat for Economic Affairs SECO Holzikofenweg 36 CH-3003 Bern Tel. +41 58 462 56 56 Fax +41 58 462 56 00</contact>
      <link id="200657">
        <title>https://covid19.easygov.swiss/en/for-startups</title>
        <uri>https://bit.ly/2WqYJW6</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions>
        <revision date="2020-05-04 14:59" type="R"/>
        <revision date="2020-05-05 10:27" type="R"/>
      </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="47">
        <name lang="de">Wirtschaft</name>
        <name lang="fr">Économie</name>
        <name lang="it">Economia</name>
        <name lang="en">Economic Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
