<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="79135" revoked="no">
    <version>5</version>
    <pubdate>2020-05-15</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="405" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>401</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Staatssekretariat für Migration</name>
      <name lang="fr">Secrétariat d’Etat aux migrations</name>
      <name lang="it">Segreteria di Stato della migrazione</name>
      <name lang="en">State Secretariat for Migration</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.sem.admin.ch/sem/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.sem.admin.ch/sem/fr/home.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.sem.admin.ch/sem/it/home.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.sem.admin.ch/sem/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@sem.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@sem.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@sem.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@sem.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="401">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Justiz- und Polizeidepartement</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de justice et police</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale di giustizia e polizia</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Justice and Police</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.ejpd.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.ejpd.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.ejpd.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.ejpd.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-ejpd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">Info@gs-ejpd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-ejpd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-ejpd.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern-Wabern</city>
      <title>Coronavirus: Lockerungen im Grenzverkehr zwischen Österreich, Deutschland und der Schweiz</title>
      <lead>Die gegenseitige Einreise wird zwischen der Schweiz, Deutschland und Österreich wieder erlaubt für Personen, die ihre Lebenspartnerinnen und Lebenspartner oder ihre Verwandten besuchen oder an wichtigen Familienanlässen teilnehmen wollen. Das Gleiche gilt für Besitzer von selbst genutzten Liegenschaften und Schrebergärten sowie von Landwirtschafts-, Jagd- oder Forstflächen. Ebenso dürfen Personen einreisen, die Tiere versorgen müssen. </lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Dank der positiven Entwicklung der pandemischen Situation im Zusammenhang mit dem Coronavirus und der stark zurückgegangenen Ansteckungszahlen können Deutschland, Österreich und die Schweiz die aktuell geltenden Einreisebeschränkungen für unverheiratete Personen lockern, die in einer grenzüberschreitenden Beziehung leben. Diese Lockerung an den Landesgrenzen tritt in der Nacht von Freitag, 15. Mai, auf Samstag 16. Mai 2020, um Mitternacht in Kraft. Die Grenzkontrollbehörden sind entsprechend instruiert.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Das Eidgenössische Justiz- und Polizeidepartement (Staatssekretariat für Migration), das Bundesministerium des Innern, für Bau und Heimat der Bundesrepublik Deutschland und das Bundesministerium für Inneres der Republik Österreich haben sich dafür auf eine gemeinsame Absichtserklärung verständigt. Diese Lockerungen gelten auch für Personen, die Verwandte besuchen oder an einem wichtigen familiären Anlass teilnehmen wollen sowie für Personen, die eine Liegenschaft, einen Schrebergarten oder eine Landwirtschafts-, Jagd- oder Forstfläche im Nachbarland unterhalten, pflegen oder nutzen oder Tiere versorgen müssen. Die Einreise nach Österreich für Pflege, Unterhalt oder Nutzung von Liegenschaften setzt bis auf Weiteres einen Haupt- oder Nebenwohnsitz in Österreich voraus. Liegenschaftsbesitzer und -besitzerinnen müssen bei der Einreise nach Österreich nach wie vor ein ärztliches Zeugnis mit einem negativen SARS-CoV-2 Test, der nicht älter als vier Tage ist, mitführen.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Wer eine dieser Lockerungen in Anspruch nehmen will, muss eine Selbstdeklaration ausfüllen und diese am Grenzübergang bei einer Kontrolle vorweisen können. Das Formular kann auf der Website der drei Ministerien heruntergeladen und ausgedruckt werden. Falsche Angaben oder Missbräuche können nach Massgabe der jeweiligen innerstaatlichen Bestimmungen geahndet werden. Alle anderen Einreisebeschränkungen bleiben vorerst in Kraft. Selbstverständlich gelten für die einreisenden Personen während ihres Aufenthaltes die Vorgaben und Empfehlungen des jeweiligen Staates zum Schutz der Gesundheit.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Um den Fluss des Waren- und Personenverkehrs, insbesondere der Grenzgänger, weiter zu verbessern, haben die drei Staaten auch vereinbart, wo immer möglich geschlossene Grenzübergänge wieder zu öffnen und die Kontrollen an diesen eng abzustimmen. Die Eidgenössische Zollverwaltung hat seit Anfang April 2020 bereits über 20 Grenzübergänge wieder geöffnet.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Sofern es die pandemische Entwicklung zulässt, sollen zudem sämtliche Reisebeschränkungen zwischen der Schweiz, Deutschland, Österreich und Frankreich gemäss einer Absprache zwischen den zuständigen Ministerien der vier Länder am 15. Juni 2020 aufgehoben werden. An der Grenze zu Italien bleiben alle Einreisebeschränkungen bis auf Weiteres in Kraft. Gespräche mit Italien über Lockerungen des Grenzverkehrs finden statt, sobald die pandemische Situation dies zulässt.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Der Bundesrat hat am 29. April 2020 entschieden, dass er die corona-bedingten Einreisebeschränkungen parallel zu den wirtschaftlichen Öffnungsetappen schrittweise lockern will. Erste Schritte hat er per 11. Mai 2020 in Kraft gesetzt. Weitere Schritte folgen, sofern die pandemische Situation dies erlaubt. Der Bundesrat wird die Details der kommenden Lockerungen bei den Einreise- und Aufenthaltsbeschränkungen an seiner Sitzung vom 27. Mai besprechen.&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Information und Kommunikation SEM, medien@sem.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="201105">
        <title>Weisung (Fassung vom 16. Mai 2020)</title>
        <uri>https://www.sem.admin.ch/dam/data/sem/aktuell/aktuell/einreisestopp/weisung-covid-19-d.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="201106">
        <title>Selbstdeklaration Besuche</title>
        <uri>https://www.sem.admin.ch/dam/data/sem/aktuell/aktuell/einreisestopp/selbstdeklaration-besuch-d.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="201107">
        <title>Selbstdeklaration Besitzer/innen</title>
        <uri>https://www.sem.admin.ch/dam/data/sem/aktuell/aktuell/einreisestopp/selbstdeklaration-besitzer-d.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="201114">
        <title>Gemeinsame Absichtserklärung</title>
        <uri>https://www.sem.admin.ch/dam/data/sem/aktuell/aktuell/einreisestopp/mou-20200515-d.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions>
        <revision date="2020-05-19 11:48" type="R"/>
      </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne-Wabern</city>
      <title>Coronavirus : assouplissement des restrictions du trafic frontalier entre l’Autriche, l’Allemagne et la Suisse</title>
      <lead>La Suisse, l’Allemagne et l’Autriche autorisent à nouveau mutuellement l’entrée pour les personnes qui souhaitent rendre visite à leur partenaire de vie ou à leurs proches ou participer à un événement familial majeur. Elles font de même pour les propriétaires de biens immobiliers ou de jardins à usage personnel, de terres agricoles, de réserves de chasse ou de forêts. Les restrictions sont également assouplies pour les personnes qui doivent prendre soin d’animaux.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;L’évolution favorable de la pandémie de coronavirus et la forte baisse des courbes d’infection amènent l’Allemagne, l’Autriche et la Suisse à assouplir leurs restrictions d’entrée pour les personnes non mariées qui vivent une relation transfrontalière. Cet assouplissement prend effet dans la nuit du vendredi 15 au samedi 16 mai 2020 à minuit ; les autorités chargées des contrôles à la frontière recevront les instructions ad hoc.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Le Département fédéral de justice et police, par l’entremise du Secrétariat d’État aux migrations, le ministère fédéral de l’Intérieur, des Travaux publics et de la Patrie de la République fédérale d’Allemagne et le ministère fédéral de l’Intérieur de la République d’Autriche se sont entendus sur une déclaration d’intention commune concernant ces assouplissements mutuels. Pourront également en bénéficier les personnes qui souhaitent rendre visite à des proches ou participer à un événement familial majeur, les propriétaires de biens immobiliers ou de parcelles de jardin à usage personnel et les personnes qui entretiennent, cultivent ou exploitent des terres agricoles, une réserve de chasse ou de la forêt ou qui doivent prendre soin d’animaux dans le pays voisin. Jusqu’à nouvel avis, l’entrée en Autriche à des fins d’utilisation, d’entretien ou d’exploitation de biens immobiliers n’est cependant possible qu’à condition d’y être propriétaire d’une résidence principale ou secondaire. Pour entrer en Autriche, les propriétaires doivent être munis d’un certificat médical attestant qu’un test de dépistage du SARS-CoV-2 ne datant pas de plus de quatre jours a été effectué et qu’il est négatif.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Toute personne souhaitant prétendre à ces assouplissements doit remplir une déclaration à présenter, en cas de contrôle, au point de passage frontalier. Le formulaire idoine peut être téléchargé et imprimé sur le site web des trois ministères. Les fausses informations et les abus seront sanctionnés conformément aux dispositions pénales de l’État concerné. Toutes les autres restrictions d’entrée restent en vigueur pour le moment. Bien entendu, les contraintes en matière de protection de la santé édictées par chacun des États concernés ainsi que leurs recommandations s’appliquent à quiconque, et ce, pendant toute la durée du séjour.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Afin d’optimiser la circulation des marchandises et des personnes, en particulier pour les frontaliers, les trois pays sont également convenus de rouvrir leurs points de passage frontalier partout où ils le peuvent et d’y coordonner les contrôles. L’Administration fédérale des douanes a d’ores et déjà procédé, depuis début avril 2020, à la réouverture de plus de 20 postes-frontières.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Par ailleurs, pour autant que l’évolution de la pandémie le permette, les restrictions de voyage entre la Suisse, l’Allemagne, l’Autriche et la France devraient pouvoir être levées le 15 juin prochain, après concertation entre les ministères compétents de ces quatre États. Les restrictions d’entrée aux frontière avec l’Italie resteront par contre toutes en vigueur jusqu’à nouvel ordre. Des discussions sur l’assouplissement du trafic frontalier seront menées avec l’Italie dès que la situation de la pandémie le permettra.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Le 29 avril dernier, le Conseil fédéral avait décidé d’assouplir progressivement les restrictions d’entrée dictées par la pandémie de coronavirus au fur et à mesure du déploiement de la réouverture économique. Les premiers assouplissements sont entrés en vigueur le 11 mai 2020. D’autres suivront si l’évolution de la pandémie le permet. Lors de sa séance du 27 mai prochain, le Conseil fédéral discutera des détails des prochains assouplissements des restrictions en matière d’entrée et de séjour. &lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Information et communication SEM, medien@sem.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="201108">
        <title>Directive (version du 16 mai 2020)</title>
        <uri>https://www.sem.admin.ch/dam/data/sem/aktuell/aktuell/einreisestopp/weisung-covid-19-f.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="201109">
        <title>Déclaration visite</title>
        <uri>https://www.sem.admin.ch/dam/data/sem/aktuell/aktuell/einreisestopp/selbstdeklaration-besuch-f.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="201110">
        <title>Déclaration propriétaires</title>
        <uri>https://www.sem.admin.ch/dam/data/sem/aktuell/aktuell/einreisestopp/selbstdeklaration-besitzer-f.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="201115">
        <title>Gemeinsame Absichtserklärung</title>
        <uri>https://www.sem.admin.ch/dam/data/sem/aktuell/aktuell/einreisestopp/mou-20200515-f.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions>
        <revision date="2020-05-19 11:48" type="R"/>
      </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna-Wabern</city>
      <title>Coronavirus: allentamento delle restrizioni nel traffico al confine tra Austria, Germania e Svizzera</title>
      <lead>Chi desidera far visita al proprio partner o ai parenti oppure partecipare a importanti eventi di famiglia può di nuovo superare il confine tra Svizzera, Germania e Austria. Lo stesso vale per chi possiede a uso proprio immobili e orti nonché aree agricole, venatorie e forestali. Questi allentamenti valgono anche per chi deve accudire animali. </lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Visti gli sviluppi positivi della situazione pandemica causata dal coronavirus e il forte calo dei contagi, la Germania, l’Austria e la Svizzera possono allentare le vigenti restrizioni all’entrata applicate alle persone non sposate che vivono una relazione transfrontaliera. Questi allentamenti al confine nazionale entreranno in vigore nella notte tra venerdì 15 e sabato 16 maggio 2020 a mezzanotte. Le autorità di controllo alle frontiere hanno ricevuto le istruzioni del caso.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Il Dipartimento federale di giustizia e polizia (Segreteria di Stato della migrazione), il Ministero federale tedesco dell’interno, dei lavori pubblici e della patria e il Ministero dell’interno austriaco hanno concordato una dichiarazione d’intenti comune. Gli allentamenti si applicano anche a chi desidera far visita ai parenti o partecipare a importanti eventi di famiglia, come pure a chi gestisce, cura o utilizza un immobile, un orto oppure un’area agricola, venatoria o silvestre nel Paese limitrofo. Inoltre, valgono anche per chi deve accudire animali. Fino a nuovo avviso, l’entrata in Austria per la cura, la manutenzione e l’utilizzo di immobili presuppone un domicilio primario o secondario in tale Paese. Inoltre, i proprietari di immobili devono ancora portare con sé un certificato medico con un test per SARS-CoV-2 negativo effettuato al massimo quattro giorni prima.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Chi intende ricorre a questi allentamenti, deve compilare un’autocertificazione ed esibirla in caso di controllo al momento del passaggio di confine. Il modulo può essere scaricato e stampato dal sito internet dei tre dicasteri. Informazioni false o abusi possono essere puniti conformemente alle disposizioni del relativo Stato. Tutte le altre restrizioni all’entrata restano al momento in vigore. Ovviamente chi entra in un altro Paese deve rispettare durante il soggiorno le prescrizioni e le raccomandazioni ivi vigenti in materia di tutela della salute.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Per migliorare ulteriormente il flusso delle merci e delle persone, in particolare dei lavoratori frontalieri, i tre Stati hanno inoltre convenuto di riaprire, se possibile, i valichi ancora chiusi e di concordare congiuntamente il controllo a tali valichi. Dall’inizio di aprile 2020, l’Amministrazione federale delle dogane ha già riaperto più di 20 valichi.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Se l’evoluzione pandemica lo permetterà, verranno inoltre abolite a partire dal 15 giugno 2020 tutte le restrizioni al traffico delle persone tra Svizzera, Germania, Austria e Francia; questo è quanto hanno convenuto i dicasteri responsabili dei quattro Paesi. Al confine con l’Italia le attuali restrizioni all’entrata permangono fino a nuovo ordine. Non appena la situazione pandemica lo consentirà, saranno avviati con l’Italia colloquio per allentare le restrizioni al traffico al confine.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Il 29 aprile il Consiglio federale aveva deciso di attenuare progressivamente le restrizioni d’entrata dovute al coronavirus in parallelo alla ripresa graduale dell’economia. I primi allentamenti sono entrati in vigore l’11 maggio 2020. Nella misura in cui la situazione lo permetterà, saranno fatti ulteriori passi in tale direzione. Il Collegio esecutivo discuterà i futuri allentamenti riguardanti le restrizioni all’entrata e al soggiorno nella sua seduta del 27 maggio.&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Informazione e comunicazione SEM, medien@sem.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="201111">
        <title>Istruzione (versione del 16 maggio 2020)</title>
        <uri>https://www.sem.admin.ch/dam/data/sem/aktuell/aktuell/einreisestopp/weisung-covid-19-i.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="201112">
        <title>Autodichiarazione visite</title>
        <uri>https://www.sem.admin.ch/dam/data/sem/aktuell/aktuell/einreisestopp/selbstdeklaration-besuch-i.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="201113">
        <title>Autodichiarazione proprietari</title>
        <uri>https://www.sem.admin.ch/dam/data/sem/aktuell/aktuell/einreisestopp/selbstdeklaration-besitzer-i.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="201116">
        <title>Gemeinsame Absichtserklärung</title>
        <uri>https://www.sem.admin.ch/dam/data/sem/aktuell/aktuell/einreisestopp/mou-20200515-i.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions>
        <revision date="2020-05-15 16:48" type="R"/>
        <revision date="2020-05-19 11:48" type="R"/>
      </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern-Wabern</city>
      <title>Coronavirus: Easing of travel restrictions between Austria, Germany and Switzerland</title>
      <lead>The borders between Switzerland, Germany and Austria are to open again for unmarried couples in long-term cross-border relationships, and for those wishing to visit relatives or attend important family events. Restrictions will also be lifted for people who own a property for personal use, tend allotments, or maintain agricultural or hunting land or woodland. People needing to take care of animals may also cross the border.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Thanks to the positive developments regarding the coronavirus pandemic, reflected in a sharp drop in the number of infections, Germany, Austria and Switzerland have decided to lift the travel restrictions that currently apply to unmarried couples in cross-border relationships. The easing of these restrictions will come into effect at midnight tonight. The border control authorities have been notified accordingly.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;A memorandum of understanding to this effect has been signed by the Federal Department of Justice and Police (State Secretariat for Migration), the German Federal Ministry of the Interior, Building and Community and the Austrian Federal Ministry of the Interior. These conditions also apply for persons wishing to visit relatives or attend an important family event, as well as for persons who have a property, tend an allotment, or hold agricultural and hunting land or woodland in a neighbouring country, or who have to look after animals. Until further notice, persons wishing to enter Austria to tend, maintain or use property must have a primary or secondary residence there. To enter Austria, property owners will still be required to produce a medical certificate, not more than four days old, stating that the holder has tested negative for SARS-CoV-2.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Anyone wishing to make use of this exception must complete a self-declaration form and present it at the border. The form can be downloaded from the websites of the respective ministries and printed out. Property owners should offer additional proof in the form of land register certificate or a rental agreement. Persons making false declarations or abusing the rules may be prosecuted under the law in the country concerned. All other travel restrictions remain in place for the time being. The public health requirements and recommendations valid in the relevant state will of course apply to those entering the country during their stay.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;In order to further ease the movement of goods and people, particularly cross-border commuters, the three states have also agreed to reopen border crossings wherever possible and to closely coordinate checks. The Federal Customs Administration has already opened 20 border crossings since the beginning of April.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;As long as the epidemiological situation allows, all remaining travel restrictions between Switzerland, Germany, Austria and France should be lifted from 15 June under an agreement reached between the relevant ministries of the four countries. All travel restrictions at the border to Italy will remain in place until further notice. Discussions about easing restrictions will take place with the Italian authorities as soon as the epidemiological situation allows.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;On 29 April, the Federal Council decided to gradually ease coronavirus-related entry restrictions in parallel with steps to reopen the economy. The first steps came into force on 11 May. Further steps will follow as long as the epidemiological situation allows. The Federal Council will discuss the next stage of easing entry and residence restrictions at its meeting on 27 May.&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Information and communication SEM, medien@sem.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="201105">
        <title>Weisung (Fassung vom 16. Mai 2020)</title>
        <uri>https://www.sem.admin.ch/dam/data/sem/aktuell/aktuell/einreisestopp/weisung-covid-19-d.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="201106">
        <title>Selbstdeklaration Besuche</title>
        <uri>https://www.sem.admin.ch/dam/data/sem/aktuell/aktuell/einreisestopp/selbstdeklaration-besuch-d.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="201107">
        <title>Selbstdeklaration Besitzer/innen</title>
        <uri>https://www.sem.admin.ch/dam/data/sem/aktuell/aktuell/einreisestopp/selbstdeklaration-besitzer-d.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="201108">
        <title>Directive (version du 16 mai 2020)</title>
        <uri>https://www.sem.admin.ch/dam/data/sem/aktuell/aktuell/einreisestopp/weisung-covid-19-f.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="201109">
        <title>Déclaration visite</title>
        <uri>https://www.sem.admin.ch/dam/data/sem/aktuell/aktuell/einreisestopp/selbstdeklaration-besuch-f.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="201110">
        <title>Déclaration propriétaires</title>
        <uri>https://www.sem.admin.ch/dam/data/sem/aktuell/aktuell/einreisestopp/selbstdeklaration-besitzer-f.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="201111">
        <title>Istruzione (versione del 16 maggio 2020)</title>
        <uri>https://www.sem.admin.ch/dam/data/sem/aktuell/aktuell/einreisestopp/weisung-covid-19-i.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="201112">
        <title>Autodichiarazione visite</title>
        <uri>https://www.sem.admin.ch/dam/data/sem/aktuell/aktuell/einreisestopp/selbstdeklaration-besuch-i.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="201113">
        <title>Autodichiarazione proprietari</title>
        <uri>https://www.sem.admin.ch/dam/data/sem/aktuell/aktuell/einreisestopp/selbstdeklaration-besitzer-i.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="201114">
        <title>Gemeinsame Absichtserklärung</title>
        <uri>https://www.sem.admin.ch/dam/data/sem/aktuell/aktuell/einreisestopp/mou-20200515-d.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions>
        <revision date="2020-05-15 16:18" type="R"/>
        <revision date="2020-05-19 11:48" type="R"/>
      </revisions>
    </content>
    <keywords>
      <keyword id="124" org-id="405">
        <name lang="de">Zuwanderung</name>
        <name lang="fr">Immigration</name>
        <name lang="it">Immigrazione</name>
        <name lang="en">Immigration</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="129" org-id="405">
        <name lang="de">Pandemie</name>
        <name lang="fr">Pandémie</name>
        <name lang="it">Pandemia</name>
        <name lang="en">Pandemic</name>
      </keyword>
    </keywords>
    <topics>
      <topic id="20">
        <name lang="de">Migration</name>
        <name lang="fr">Migrations</name>
        <name lang="it">Migrazione</name>
        <name lang="en">Migration</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
