<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="99114" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2023-11-29</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="323" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>701</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidg. Materialprüfungs- und Forschungsanstalt</name>
      <name lang="fr">Laboratoire fédéral d'essai des matériaux et de recherche</name>
      <name lang="it">Laboratorio federale di prova dei materiali e di ricerca</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Laboratory for Materials Testing and Research</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.empa.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.empa.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.empa.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.empa.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">contact@empa.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">contact@empa.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">contact@empa.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">contact@empa.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="701">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Wirtschaft, Bildung und Forschung</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'économie, de la formation et de la recherche</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'economia, della formazione e della ricerca</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Economic Affairs, Education and Research</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Dübendorf, St. Gallen und Thun</city>
      <title>Technologie- und Wissenstransfer für die Energiewende auf Gemeindeebene / Netzwerk «MUNICIPAL» zu Gast bei der Empa</title>
      <lead>Unter dem Motto «Ideenfindungs- und Ko-Kreationsprozesse zur Förderung des Technologietransfers» diskutierten am 24. November 2023 an der Empa in Dübendorf rund 60 Teilnehmende aus Forschung, Wirtschaft, Kantonen und Gemeinden innovative Ansätze zur Energiewende. Im Hinblick auf eine konkrete Umsetzung in Gemeinden kamen dabei neue Ideen aus den Bereichen Mobilität, Wärmeproduktion und Renovierung zur Sprache.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Im Verlauf des Netzwerktreffens wurde deutlich, dass in vielen Gemeinden in den drei zentralen Bereichen Mobilität, Wärme und Renovierung immer noch Strategien und entsprechende Massnahmen fehlen. Dabei zeigten unter anderem Expertinnen und Experten der Empa auf, wie genaue Betriebsdaten zur Schweizer Fahrzeugflotte (PKW, LKW) den Umbau der Flotte, den Zubau von Ladestationen oder «Shared Mobility»-Konzepte fördern und wie Gebäudesimulationen energetische Sanierungsstrategien unterstützen können. Der Kanton Luzern stellte dar, wie ein öffentlich zugängliches Online-Tool mit GIS-Daten im Bereich Wärme/Kälte den Ausstieg aus Gas und Öl voranbringen kann.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Häufiges Problem: veraltete, nicht zugängliche Daten&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In der Diskussion unterstrichen die Teilnehmenden, dass es in allen Bereichen an guten Daten mangle. So sei zum Beispiel das hiesige Gebäude- und Wohnungsregister (GWR) oft nicht aktuell. Oft verfügten die Gemeinden über weit bessere Daten, diese seien aber meist nicht digitalisiert und daher schwer zu nutzen. Es fehle den Kommunen an Geld und Personalressourcen, um diese zentralen Daten elektronisch aufzuarbeiten. Zudem seien viele Daten aus Datenschutzgründen einem breiten Publikum nicht zugänglich und könnten deshalb für die dringend nötige Sensibilisierung der Öffentlichkeit nicht genutzt werden.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;«Wer will, sucht Wege. Wer nicht will, sucht Gründe (nichts zu tun)», schloss einer der Referenten seinen Vortrag. Insgesamt waren sich die Teilnehmenden einig, dass es in allen drei Bereichen mehr Mut zum Risiko brauche und dass ein Warten auf die perfekte Lösung oft kontraproduktiv sei.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Schnelles Handeln gefragt&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Die Bedeutung des schnellen Handelns legte die Stadt Zürich anhand des Ausbaus ihrer thermischen Netze dar. Der Vergleich zwischen einem optimierten konventionellen Ausbau (90% CO2-neutral) und einem «ideologischen» Ausbau (100% CO2-neutral) zeigt, dass der Endausbau der 2. Variante mindestens drei Jahre später erfolgen würde. Damit wäre diese Variante erst 2048 bezüglich des Gesamt-CO2-Ausstosses im Vorteil. Fazit der Stadt: Variante 1 mit möglichen späteren Nachbesserungen sei daher vorzuziehen.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Im Verlaufe des Netzwerktreffens wurde auch deutlich, dass schnelles Handeln einen intensiveren Austausch mit allen Betroffenen und Anspruchsgruppen erfordert. Denn, wie es sich im Workshop zur Mobilität zeigte, bedeutet eine nachhaltige Mobilität nicht einfach einen Umstieg auf Elektroautos, sondern heisst insgesamt weniger Mobilität mit dem eigenen Auto oder sogar weniger Mobilität an sich. Und dies wäre, wie Vieles im Bereich der Energiewende, nur durch einen weit(er)reichenden Dialog mit allen Interessierten zu erreichen.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Björn Niesen Managing Director Research Focus Area Energy Tel. +41 58 765 11 22 bjoern.niesen@empa.ch</contact>
      <attachment id="267321">
        <title>Mit welchen Schritten können Schweizer Gemeinden die Energiewende schaffen? Probleme und Lösungsansätze wurden an der Empa Akademie gemeinsam diskutiert. Bild: Empa</title>
        <format>jpg</format>
        <size-kb>243</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/84923.jpg</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="267324">
        <title>So bauen wir unser Energiesystem um: Forschung auf drei Ebenen. Grafik: Empa</title>
        <format>jpg</format>
        <size-kb>201</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/84926.jpg</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="267327">
        <title>Sanierungsmassnahmen: Optimale Lösungen nach Baujahr. Grafik: Empa</title>
        <format>png</format>
        <size-kb>292</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/84929.png</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <link id="267319">
        <title>Empa Homepage</title>
        <uri>https://www.empa.ch/web/s604/municipial</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="267320">
        <title>Municipal Homepage</title>
        <uri>https://www.municipal-netzwerk.ch/</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Dübendorf, St. Gallen und Thun</city>
      <title>Transfert de technologie et de connaissances pour la transition énergétique au niveau communal / Le réseau "MUNICIPAL" invité à l'Empa</title>
      <lead>Sous la devise "Processus de recherche d'idées et de co-création pour la promotion du transfert de technologie", une soixantaine de participants issus de la recherche, de l'économie, des cantons et des communes ont discuté le 24 novembre 2023 à l'Empa à Dübendorf d'approches innovantes pour le tournant énergétique. Dans l'optique d'une mise en œuvre concrète dans les communes, de nouvelles idées ont été évoquées dans les domaines de la mobilité, de la production de chaleur et de la rénovation. </lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Au cours de la rencontre du réseau, il est apparu clairement que de nombreuses communes manquaient encore de stratégies et de mesures correspondantes dans les trois domaines centraux de la mobilité, du chauffage et de la rénovation. Des experts de l'Empa ont notamment montré comment des données d'exploitation précises sur le parc automobile suisse (voitures, camions) peuvent favoriser la transformation du parc, l'installation de stations de recharge ou les concepts de "mobilité partagée" et comment les simulations de bâtiments peuvent soutenir les stratégies de rénovation énergétique. Le canton de Lucerne a expliqué comment un outil en ligne accessible au public et contenant des données SIG dans le domaine du chauffage et du refroidissement peut favoriser l'abandon du gaz et du pétrole.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Problème fréquent : données obsolètes et inaccessibles&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Lors de la discussion, les participants ont souligné le manque de bonnes données dans tous les domaines. Par exemple, le registre des bâtiments et des logements (RBL) local n'est souvent pas à jour. Les communes disposent souvent de bien meilleures données, mais celles-ci ne sont généralement pas numérisées et donc difficiles à utiliser. Les communes manquent d'argent et de ressources en personnel pour traiter ces données centrales sous forme électronique. En outre, de nombreuses données ne sont pas accessibles à un large public pour des raisons de protection des données et ne peuvent donc pas être utilisées pour sensibiliser le public, ce qui est pourtant une nécessité absolue.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;"Celui qui veut chercher des moyens. Celui qui ne veut pas, cherche des raisons (de ne rien faire)", a conclu l'un des intervenants. Dans l'ensemble, les participants étaient d'accord pour dire qu'il fallait avoir plus de courage pour prendre des risques dans les trois domaines et qu'attendre la solution parfaite était souvent contre-productif.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Il faut agir vite&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;L'importance d'agir rapidement a été exposée par la ville de Zurich à travers l'extension de ses réseaux thermiques. La comparaison entre une extension conventionnelle optimisée (neutre en CO2 à 90%) et une extension "idéologique" (neutre en CO2 à 100%) montre que l'extension finale de la 2e variante aurait lieu au moins trois ans plus tard. Ainsi, cette variante ne serait avantagée qu'en 2048 en termes d'émissions totales de CO2. Conclusion de la ville : la variante 1, avec d'éventuelles améliorations ultérieures, serait donc préférable.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Au cours de la réunion du réseau, il est également apparu clairement qu'une action rapide nécessitait un échange plus intense avec toutes les personnes concernées et les groupes d'intérêt. Car, comme l'a montré l'atelier sur la mobilité, une mobilité durable ne signifie pas simplement passer aux voitures électriques, mais signifie globalement moins de mobilité avec sa propre voiture, voire moins de mobilité en soi. Et cela ne pourrait être atteint, comme beaucoup de choses dans le domaine de la transition énergétique, que par un dialogue étendu avec toutes les parties intéressées.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Dr. Björn Niesen Managing Director Research Focus Area Energy Tél. +41 58 765 11 22 bjoern.niesen@empa.ch</contact>
      <attachment id="267322">
        <title>Avec quelles étapes les communes suisses peuvent-elles réussir le tournant énergétique ? Les problèmes et les solutions possibles ont été discutés ensemble à l'Académie Empa. Image : Empa</title>
        <format>jpg</format>
        <size-kb>243</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/84924.jpg</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="267325">
        <title>Restructurer le système énergétique : recherche sur trois échelles. Illustration: Empa</title>
        <format>jpg</format>
        <size-kb>202</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/84927.jpg</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="267328">
        <title>Mesures de restructuration: Solution optimale en fonction de l’année de construction. Image : Empa</title>
        <format>png</format>
        <size-kb>106</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/84930.png</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <link id="267319">
        <title>Empa Homepage</title>
        <uri>https://www.empa.ch/web/s604/municipial</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="267320">
        <title>Municipal Homepage</title>
        <uri>https://www.municipal-netzwerk.ch/</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Dübendorf, St. Gallen und Thun</city>
      <title>Technology and knowledge transfer for the energy transition at municipal level / MUNICIPAL network hosted by Empa</title>
      <lead>Under the motto "Idea generation and co-creation processes to promote technology transfer", around 60 participants from research, business, cantons and municipalities discussed innovative approaches to the energy transition at Empa in Dübendorf on 24 November. New ideas in the areas of mobility, heat production and renovation were discussed in the context of practical solutions for municipalities. </lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;During the course of the networking event, it became clear that many municipalities still lack strategies and effective measures in the three key areas of mobility, heating and renovation. Experts from Empa, among others, showed how precise operating data on the Swiss vehicle fleet (cars and trucks) can promote the conversion of the fleet, the addition of charging stations or shared mobility concepts and how building simulations can support energy-efficient renovation strategies. The canton of Lucerne presented how a publicly accessible online tool with GIS data in the heating/cooling sector can promote the phase-out of gas and oil.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;A common problem: outdated and inaccessible data&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In the discussion, the participants emphasized that there is a lack of good data in all areas. For example, the local building and housing register (GWR) is often not up to date. Municipalities often have far better data. However, it is usually not digitized and therefore difficult to make use of. Municipalities lack financial and human resources to electronically process this crucial dataset. Moreover, much of the data is not accessible to the public due to data protection and thus cannot be used to raise public awareness, which is urgently needed.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;"Those who are willing look for solutions. Those who don't are looking for reasons (to do nothing)," one of the speakers concluded their presentation. Overall, the participants agreed that more courage to take risks is needed in all areas and that waiting for the perfect solution is often counterproductive&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Swift action required&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The City of Zurich demonstrated the importance of acting quickly by expanding its thermal networks. The comparison between an optimized conventional expansion (90% CO2-neutral) and an "ideological" expansion (100% CO2-neutral) shows that the final expansion step of the second variant would only be realized at least three years later. This means that, in terms of total CO2 emissions, this variant would not have an advantage until the year 2048. The conclusion of the city: Variant 1 with possible subsequent improvements is preferable.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;In the course of the network event, it also became clear that rapid action requires a more intensive exchange with all stakeholders and interest groups. As it became clear in the workshop on mobility, sustainable mobility does not simply mean switching to electric cars. It means less mobility with one's own car – or even less mobility in general. And this, like many things related to the energy transition, can only be achieved through a far-reaching dialog with all stakeholders.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Dr. Björn Niesen Managing Director Research Focus Area Energy Phone +41 58 765 11 22 bjoern.niesen@empa.ch</contact>
      <attachment id="267323">
        <title>What steps can Swiss municipalities take to achieve the energy transition? Problems and solutions were discussed at the Empa Academy. Image: Empa</title>
        <format>jpg</format>
        <size-kb>243</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/84925.jpg</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="267326">
        <title>The path to transforming our energy system: Research on three levels. Graphic: Empa</title>
        <format>jpg</format>
        <size-kb>201</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/84928.jpg</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="267329">
        <title>Renovation measures: Optimum solutions by year of construction. Image: Empa</title>
        <format>png</format>
        <size-kb>301</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/84931.png</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <link id="267319">
        <title>Empa Homepage</title>
        <uri>https://www.empa.ch/web/s604/municipial</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="267320">
        <title>Municipal Homepage</title>
        <uri>https://www.municipal-netzwerk.ch/</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="8">
        <name lang="de">Bildung und Forschung</name>
        <name lang="fr">Formation et recherche</name>
        <name lang="it">Formazione e ricerca</name>
        <name lang="en">Education and Research</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="11">
        <name lang="de">Energie</name>
        <name lang="fr">Énergie</name>
        <name lang="it">Energia</name>
        <name lang="en">Energy</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="45">
        <name lang="de">Technologie</name>
        <name lang="fr">Technologie</name>
        <name lang="it">Tecnologia</name>
        <name lang="en">Technology</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
