<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="98738" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2023-11-21</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="302" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>301</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Generalsekretariat EDI</name>
      <name lang="fr">Secrétariat général DFI</name>
      <name lang="it">Segreteria generale DFI</name>
      <name lang="en">General Secretariat FDHA</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="201" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>201</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="301">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement des Innern</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'intérieur</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'interno</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Home Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <department id="201">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Bundespräsident Berset und Bundesrat Cassis empfangen Ungarns Premier Orbán</title>
      <lead>Bundespräsident Alain Berset und Bundesrat Ignazio Cassis, Vorsteher des Eidgenössischen Departements für auswärtige Angelegenheiten (EDA), haben am Dienstag, 21. November 2023, eine ungarische Delegation unter der Leitung von Premierminister Viktor Orbán zu einem Höflichkeitsbesuch empfangen. Im Zentrum des Austausches standen die bilateralen Beziehungen, die europapolitischen Ziele der Schweiz, der ungarische Vorsitz der Europäischen Union (EU) in der zweiten Jahreshälfte 2024 sowie aktuelle internationale Themen. </lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Beide Seiten würdigten die historisch guten bilateralen Beziehungen zwischen der Schweiz und Ungarn, die unter anderem in der Aufnahme von 12'000 ungarischen Flüchtlingen nach dem Aufstand von 1956 begründet sind. Erwähnt wurden auch die Handelsbeziehungen, wobei die rund 900 in Ungarn tätigen Schweizer Firmen dort 29'000 Stellen generieren. Die Schweizer Delegation betonte die Bedeutung von verlässlichen und vorhersehbaren Rahmenbedingungen für Investitionsentscheide. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Ebenfalls zur Sprache kam die Zusammenarbeit mit Ungarn als einem der Empfängerländer des zweiten Schweizer Beitrags an ausgewählte EU-Staaten. Im Zentrum stehen Berufsbildung, Forschung und Innovation. Der Bundespräsident erklärte, dass die Schweiz grossen Wert darauf legt, verschiedene Akteure, insbesondere auch die Zivilgesellschaft, in die Umsetzung der Programme und Projekte einzubeziehen. Mit Blick auf die Europapolitik bekräftigte die Schweizer Seite das Ziel, den bilateralen Weg mit der EU zu stabilisieren und weiterzuentwickeln. Ebenfalls besprochen wurde die ungarische EU-Ratspräsidentschaft in der zweiten Jahreshälfte 2024.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Beim Austausch über aktuelle internationale Fragen standen unter anderem die Lage im Nahen Osten und der russische Angriffskrieg gegen die Ukraine auf der Agenda, wobei die Schweizer Delegation die Wichtigkeit des humanitären Völkerrechts betonte sowie die Rolle der Organisation für Sicherheit und Zusammenarbeit in Europa (OSZE). Diese ist aus Sicht der Schweiz eine wichtige Plattform, um den Austausch auch mit Staaten zu pflegen, die hinsichtlich der europäischen Sicherheitsarchitektur nicht gleichgerichtete Werte vertreten.&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Kommunikation GS-EDI, Tel. +41 58 462 85 79, media@gs-edi.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="265951">
        <title>Bilaterale Beziehungen Schweiz–Ungarn</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home/vertretungen-und-reisehinweise/ungarn/bilatereale-beziehungenschweizungarn.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Le président de la Confédération Berset et le conseiller fédéral Cassis reçoivent le premier ministre de la Hongrie Orbán</title>
      <lead>Le président de la Confédération Alain Berset et le conseiller fédéral Ignazio Cassis, chef du Département fédéral des affaires étrangères (DFAE), ont reçu mardi 21 novembre 2023 une délégation hongroise conduite par le premier ministre Viktor Orbán, dans le cadre d’une visite de courtoisie. Les échanges ont principalement porté sur les relations bilatérales, sur les objectifs de la Suisse en matière de politique européenne, sur la présidence hongroise de l’Union européenne (UE) au second semestre 2024 ainsi que sur des thèmes de l’actualité internationale.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Les deux parties ont salué les bonnes relations bilatérales entre la Suisse et la Hongrie, qui trouvent notamment leur origine dans l'accueil de 12000 réfugiés hongrois après le soulèvement de 1956. Ont également été mentionnées les relations commerciales, les quelque 900 entreprises suisses actives en Hongrie y générant 29'000 emplois. La délégation suisse a souligné l'importance pour les décisions d'investissement d'un environnement juridique fiable et prévisible. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Il a également été question de la coopération avec la Hongrie en sa qualité de pays bénéficiaire de la deuxième contribution suisse versée à certains États de l'UE. La priorité est ici donnée à la formation professionnelle, à la recherche et à l'innovation. Le président de la Confédération a rappelé que la Suisse considère qu'il est essentiel d'associer à la mise en œuvre des programmes et projets un certain nombre acteurs, notamment la société civile. En ce qui concerne la politique européenne, la partie suisse a réaffirmé son objectif de stabiliser et de développer la voie bilatérale avec l'UE. La présidence hongroise du Conseil de l'UE au second semestre 2024 a également été abordée.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Lors de l'échange qui a été consacré à l'actualité internationale, les parties ont notamment évoqué la situation du Proche-Orient et la guerre d'agression russe contre l'Ukraine, la délégation suisse soulignant l'importance du droit international humanitaire ainsi que le rôle de l'Organisation pour la sécurité et la coopération en Europe (OSCE). Pour la Suisse, celle-ci est une plateforme importante dans la mesure où elle permet d'échanger aussi avec des États qui défendent des valeurs différentes au sujet de l'architecture de sécurité européenne.&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Communication SG-DFDI, tél. +41 58 462 85 79, media@gs-edi.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="265952">
        <title>Relations bilatérales Suisse–Hongrie</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae/representations-et-conseils-pour-les-voyages/hongrie/suisse-hongrie.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Il presidente della Confederazione Berset e il consigliere federale Cassis accolgono il premier ungherese Orbán</title>
      <lead>Martedì 21 novembre 2023, il presidente della Confederazione Alain Berset e il consigliere federale Ignazio Cassis, responsabile del Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri (DFAE), hanno ricevuto una delegazione ungherese guidata dal Primo ministro Viktor Orbán per una visita di cortesia. Al centro dei colloqui sono stati posti le relazioni bilaterali, gli obiettivi della Svizzera nel quadro della politica europea, la Presidenza ungherese dell’Unione europea (UE) nel secondo semestre del 2024 nonché alcuni temi d’attualità internazionale. </lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Entrambe le parti hanno lodato le relazioni bilaterali tra la Svizzera e l'Ungheria, storicamente buone, che trovano radici tra l'altro nell'accoglienza di 12 000 profughi ungheresi dopo la rivoluzione del 1956. Sono anche state citate le relazioni commerciali, con circa 900 imprese svizzere attive in Ungheria che generano circa 29 000 posti di lavoro in loco. La delegazione svizzera ha sottolineato l'importanza di disporre di condizioni quadro affidabili e prevedibili per le decisioni in materia di investimenti. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Le parti hanno tematizzato anche la collaborazione con l'Ungheria, Paese destinatario di una parte del secondo contributo della Svizzera ad alcuni Stati membri dell'UE. L'accento è posto sulla formazione professionale, la ricerca e l'innovazione. Il presidente della Confederazione ha spiegato che la Svizzera attribuisce grande importanza al coinvolgimento di diversi attori, in particolare anche della società civile, nella messa in atto dei programmi e dei progetti. Nell'ottica della politica europea, la Svizzera ha ribadito l'obiettivo di stabilizzare e sviluppare ulteriormente la via bilaterale con l'UE. Si è anche parlato della Presidenza ungherese del Consiglio dell'Unione europea nel secondo semestre del 2024.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Per quanto riguarda le questioni dell'attualità internazionale, sono state discusse la situazione in Vicino Oriente e la guerra d'aggressione russa contro l'Ucraina. La delegazione svizzera ha sottolineato l'importanza del diritto umanitario internazionale e il ruolo dell'Organizzazione per la sicurezza e la cooperazione in Europa (OSCE), ritenuta una piattaforma rilevante per curare i contatti anche con quei Paesi che non condividono i medesimi valori nell'ambito dell'architettura di sicurezza europea.&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Comunicazione SG-DFAE, tel. +41 58 462 85 79, media@gs-edi.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="265953">
        <title>Relazioni bilaterali Svizzera–Ungheria</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae/rappresentanze-e-consigli-di-viaggio/ungheria/svizzera-ungheria.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>President Berset and Federal Councillor Cassis receive Hungary’s Prime Minister Orbán</title>
      <lead>On Tuesday 21 November, federal councillors Alain Berset, president of the Swiss Confederation and Ignazio Cassis, head of the Federal Department of Foreign Affairs (FDFA), received a courtesy visit from a delegation from Hungary headed by the country’s prime minister, Viktor Orbán. The exchange centred on bilateral relations, Switzerland's European policy objectives, Hungary's presidency of the Council of the European Union in the second half of 2024 and current international issues. </lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Both parties acknowledged the historically strong bilateral relations between Switzerland and Hungary, which are due in part to Switzerland's acceptance of 12,000 Hungarian refugees following the 1956 uprising. Trade relations were also mentioned; around 900 Swiss companies operate in Hungary, generating 29,000 jobs there. The Swiss delegation emphasised the importance of reliable and predictable conditions to encourage investment in the country. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;A further topic was cooperation with Hungary, which is one of the recipients of the second Swiss contribution to selected EU countries. Vocational education and training, research and innovation are key aspects of this cooperation. Mr Berset explained that Switzerland attaches great importance to involving a range of stakeholders, in particular civil society, in the implementation of programmes and projects. With regard to European policy, the Swiss side reaffirmed its goal of stabilising and further developing the bilateral approach with the EU. The Hungarian presidency of the EU Council in the second half of 2024 was also discussed.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;In discussions on current international issues, the topics included the situation in the Middle East and the Russian war of aggression against Ukraine, with the Swiss delegation emphasising the importance of international humanitarian law and the role of the Organization for Security and Cooperation in Europe (OSCE). In Switzerland's view, this is an important platform for maintaining dialogue with countries that do not share the same values with regard to the security architecture in Europe.&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>GS-FDHA Communication, Tel. +41 58 462 85 79, media@gs-edi.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="265954">
        <title>Bilateral relations Switzerland–Hungary</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/fdfa/representations-and-travel-advice/hungary/switzerland-hungary.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
