<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="98520" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2023-11-09</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="323" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>701</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidg. Materialprüfungs- und Forschungsanstalt</name>
      <name lang="fr">Laboratoire fédéral d'essai des matériaux et de recherche</name>
      <name lang="it">Laboratorio federale di prova dei materiali e di ricerca</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Laboratory for Materials Testing and Research</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.empa.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.empa.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.empa.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.empa.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">contact@empa.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">contact@empa.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">contact@empa.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">contact@empa.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="701">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Wirtschaft, Bildung und Forschung</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'économie, de la formation et de la recherche</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'economia, della formazione e della ricerca</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Economic Affairs, Education and Research</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Dübendorf, St. Gallen und Thun</city>
      <title>Weitsicht bewiesen</title>
      <lead>Als innovativer Instrumentenmacher für die Chirurgie gründete Heinz A. Oertli in jungen Jahren die Oertli Instrumente AG. Wie grosse Ideen im Kleinen gedeihen und zu nachhaltigen Unternehmensgründungen heranwachsen, weiss er aus eigener Erfahrung. Jetzt fördert Heinz A. Oertli mit einem gleichnamigen Fonds im Rahmen des Zukunftsfonds innovative Projekte an der Empa.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;An Ideen hat es ihm nie gefehlt – Heinz A. Oertli machte sich im Alter von 24 Jahren als Instrumentenmacher für die Augenchirurgie selbstständig, mitsamt seinem Ideenreichtum. Dank seinen begehrten Innovationen wuchs der ursprüngliche Einmannbetrieb zügig zu einem Qualitätswerk im St. Galler Rheintal mit heute rund 220 Mitarbeitenden an, das er allerdings vor rund 30 Jahren in andere Hände übergab. Die jüngste Idee des mittlerweile über 90-Jährigen Erfinders kam ihm vor einiger Zeit bei einem Besuch der Empa in St. Gallen: Die Forschung an der Innovationsschmiede Empa, insbesondere im Bereich der Instrumentenentwicklung, könnte man doch zusätzlich mit privaten Mitteln voranbringen.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Die Gemeinsamkeit des ehemaligen Instrumentenmachers mit den Materialforschenden der Empa gehen dabei über den Innovationsgeist hinaus: Auch die Faszination für innovative Materialien und Technologien hielten Oertli bereits zu Beginn seiner Unternehmertätigkeit in Bann. Als Pionier in seinem Gebiet suchte er für die Augenchirurgie neue Materialien für rostfreie, antimagnetische Präzisionsinstrumente. Fündig wurde er in der Uhrenindustrie, die vergleichbare Ansprüche an ihre Werkzeuge stellt. Diesen ihm eigenen Tüftlersinn fördert Heinz A. Oertli nun mit einem gleichnamigen Fonds im Rahmen des Empa Zukunftsfonds.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Drucksensor zur Selbstheilung&lt;/b&gt;&lt;p&gt;Nun unterstützt der 2022 gegründete «Heinz A. Oertli-Fonds» die ersten beiden Projekte. Eines davon befasst sich mit neuen Therapiemöglichkeiten für den Grünen Star. Ziel ist es, das Auge zu befähigen, sich ohne ärztliche Hilfe selbst zu behandeln. Bei Menschen, die an einem Glaukom leiden, sterben die Nervenzellen in der Netzhaut mit der Zeit ab – bis hin zur Erblindung. Bei einem Grossteil der Betroffenen stellt ein erhöhter Innendruck im Auge ein Risiko für die Ausbildung des Grünen Star dar. Empa-Forschende um Yashoda Chandorkar und Markus Rottmar vom «Biointerfaces»-Labor in St. Gallen entwickeln nun gemeinsam mit der Abteilung für Ophthalmologie am Tierspital Zürich ein selbstregulierendes System aus einem winzigen hochempfindlichen Sensor, der den Augendruck misst und über ein Ventil aus einem bioverträglichen Hydrogel den Druck der Kammerflüssigkeit im Auge normalisiert.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Löten statt nähen&lt;/b&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ein zweites Projekt, das ebenfalls durch den «Heinz A. Oertli-Fonds» unterstützt wird, hat zum Ziel, dank einem laser-basierten Klebeverfahren das hochempfindliche Augengewebe bei Operationen zu schonen. Bisher ist bei Eingriffen an der Linse bei Grauem Star oder bei Hornhaut-Operationen der Einsatz von Nadel und Faden üblich. Laser-basiertes Arbeiten wird derzeit zwar angewendet, allerdings basiert es auf einem Schweissverfahren bei entsprechend hohen Temperaturen. Inge Herrmann, ETH-Professorin und Leiterin der «Nanoparticle Systems Engineering»-Gruppe an der Empa in St. Gallen, entwickelt mit ihrem Team ein minimal-invasives Laserlötverfahren, mit dem Wunden am Auge effizient und schonend geschlossen werden können. Das biologische Lötmaterial mit sogenannten Nanoabsorbern soll die mechanischen Eigenschaften im Gewebe verbessern, die Heilung beschleunigen und die Narbenbildung mindern. Das Projekt kann nun dank der Unterstützung durch den «Heinz A. Oertli-Fonds» in Zusammenarbeit mit dem Kantonsspital St. Gallen und dem Universitätsspital Zürich starten.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;b&gt;Forschungsförderung durch den Zukunftsfonds &lt;/b&gt;&lt;p&gt;Der Zukunftsfonds der Empa sucht für herausragende Forschungsprojekte, die anderweitig (noch) nicht unterstützt werden, private Drittmittel. Weitere Informationen finden Sie unter: https://www.empa.ch/web/zukunftsfonds&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Loris Pandiani Empa Zukunftsfonds Tel.: +41 58 765 47 03 loris.pandiani@empa.ch</contact>
      <attachment id="265238">
        <title>Inge Herrmann, Leiterin der «Nanoparticle Systems Engineering»-Gruppe an der Empa in St. Gallen, entwickelt mit ihrem Team ein Laserlötverfahren, mit dem Wunden am Auge effizient und schonend geschlossen werden können. Bild: Empa</title>
        <format>jpg</format>
        <size-kb>4496</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/83971.jpg</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <link id="265241">
        <title>Link zur Medienmitteilung auf der Webseite der Empa</title>
        <uri>https://www.empa.ch/web/s604/oertli-fonds</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Dübendorf, St. Gallen und Thun</city>
      <title>Une vision à long terme</title>
      <lead>Fabricant d'instruments innovants pour la chirurgie, Heinz A. Oertli a fondé très jeune la société Oertli Instrumente AG. Il sait par expérience comment les grandes idées s'épanouissent à petite échelle et se transforment en créations d'entreprises durables. Aujourd'hui, Heinz A. Oertli encourage des projets innovants à l'Empa avec un fonds du même nom dans le cadre du Zukunftsfonds.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Il n'a jamais manqué d'idées – Heinz A. Oertli s'est mis à son compte à l'âge de 24 ans en tant que fabricant d'instruments pour la chirurgie ophtalmique, avec sa richesse d'idées. Grâce à ses innovations très recherchées, l'entreprise unipersonnelle d'origine s'est rapidement développée pour devenir une usine de qualité dans la vallée du Rhin saint-galloise, employant aujourd'hui près de 220 personnes, qu'il a toutefois transmise à d'autres personnes il y a environ 30 ans. L'idée la plus récente de l'inventeur, aujourd'hui âgé de plus de 90 ans, lui est venue il y a quelque temps lors d'une visite de l'Empa à Saint-Gall : On pourrait faire avancer la recherche à l'Empa, le creuset de l'innovation, en particulier dans le domaine du développement d'instruments, avec des fonds privés.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Le point commun entre l'ancien fabricant d'instruments et les chercheurs en matériaux de l'Empa va au-delà de l'esprit d'innovation : dès le début de son activité d'entrepreneur, Heinz A. Oertli était fasciné par les matériaux et les technologies innovants. Pionnier dans son domaine, il a cherché de nouveaux matériaux pour des instruments de précision inoxydables et antimagnétiques destinés à la chirurgie ophtalmique. Il a trouvé ce qu'il cherchait dans l'industrie horlogère, qui a des exigences comparables pour ses outils. Ce sens de l'invention qui lui est propre, Heinz A. Oertli l'encourage désormais en créant un fonds du même nom dans le cadre du l'Empa Zukunftsfonds.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Capteur de pression pour l'autoguérison &lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Désormais, le "Heinz A. Oertli Fonds", créé en 2022, soutient les deux premiers projets. L'un d'eux porte sur de nouvelles possibilités de traitement du glaucome. L'objectif est de permettre à l'œil de se traiter lui-même sans l'aide d'un médecin. Chez les personnes souffrant de glaucome, les cellules nerveuses de la rétine meurent avec le temps – jusqu'à la cécité. Chez une grande partie des personnes concernées, une pression interne élevée dans l'œil représente un risque de développement du glaucome. Yashoda Chandorkar et Markus Rottmar, chercheurs de l'Empa au laboratoire "Biointerfaces" de Saint-Gall, développent maintenant, en collaboration avec le département d'ophtalmologie de l'hôpital vétérinaire de Zurich, un système autorégulateur composé d'un minuscule capteur ultrasensible qui mesure la pression oculaire et normalise la pression du liquide de la chambre oculaire par le biais d'une valve en hydrogel biocompatible. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Souder au lieu de coudre &lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Un deuxième projet, également soutenu par le "Heinz A. Oertli Fonds", a pour objectif de ménager les tissus oculaires très sensibles lors des opérations grâce à un procédé de brasage basé sur le laser. Jusqu'à présent, l'utilisation d'une aiguille et d'un fil était courante pour les interventions sur le cristallin en cas de cataracte ou pour les opérations de la cornée. Le travail au laser est certes utilisé actuellement, mais il repose sur un procédé de soudage à des températures élevées. Inge Herrmann, professeur à l'ETH et directrice du groupe "Nanoparticle Systems Engineering" à l'Empa à Saint-Gall, développe avec son équipe un procédé de brasage au laser peu invasif qui permet de refermer efficacement et en douceur les plaies de l'œil. Le matériau de brasage biologique avec ce que l'on appelle des nanoabsorbants doit améliorer les propriétés mécaniques dans les tissus, accélérer la guérison et réduire la formation de cicatrices. Le projet peut maintenant démarrer grâce au soutien du "Heinz A. Oertli Fonds", en collaboration avec l'Hôpital cantonal de Saint-Gall et l'Hôpital universitaire de Zurich. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;La promotion des talents &lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Le Zukunftsfonds de l'Empa recherche des fonds tiers privés pour des projets de recherche exceptionnels qui ne sont pas (encore) soutenus par ailleurs. Pour plus d'informations : https://www.empa.ch/web/zukunftsfonds&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Loris Pandiani Empa Zukunftsfonds Tél. +41 58 765 47 03 loris.pandiani@empa.ch</contact>
      <attachment id="265239">
        <title>Inge Herrmann, responsable du groupe "Nanoparticle Systems Engineering" à l'Empa à Saint-Gall, développe avec son équipe un procédé de brasage au laser qui permet de refermer efficacement et en douceur les plaies de l'œil. Image : Empa</title>
        <format>jpg</format>
        <size-kb>4496</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/83972.jpg</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <link id="265242">
        <title>Lien vers le communiqué de presse sur le site de l'Empa</title>
        <uri>https://www.empa.ch/web/s604/oertli-fonds</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Dübendorf, St. Gallen und Thun</city>
      <title>Showing foresight</title>
      <lead>As an innovative developer of surgical tools, Heinz A. Oertli founded the company "Oertli Instrumente" at a young age. He knows from own experience how great ideas flourish on a small scale and grow into sustainable start-ups. Now Heinz A. Oertli is supporting innovative projects at Empa with a fund of his very name as part of Empa's "Zukunftsfonds".</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;He has never been short of ideas – Heinz A. Oertli started his own business at the age of 24 as an instrument maker for ophthalmic surgery, along with a wealth of ideas. Thanks to his sought-after innovations, the original one-man business quickly grew into a quality factory in the Rhine Valley of St. Gallen with currently around 220 employees, although he handed it over to other hands around 30 years ago. The latest idea of the inventor, who is now over 90 years old, came to him some time ago during a visit to Empa in St. Gallen: Research at the innovation hotbed Empa, especially in the field of instrument development, could be promoted with private funds.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The common ground between the former instrument maker and Empa's materials scientists goes beyond the spirit of innovation: Oertli was fascinated by innovative materials and technologies right from the start of his entrepreneurial activity. As a pioneer in his field, he was looking for new materials for stainless, anti-magnetic precision instruments for eye surgery. He found what he was looking for in the watch industry, which places similar demands on its tools. Heinz A. Oertli is now promoting this inventive spirit, which is peculiar to him, with a fund of his very name as part of the "Zukunftsfonds", the fundraising endeavor of Empa.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Pressure sensor for self-healing&lt;/b&gt;&lt;p&gt;Now the "Heinz A. Oertli Fonds," established in 2022, is supporting the first two projects. One of them deals with new therapeutic options for glaucoma. The goal is to enable the eye to treat itself without medical assistance. In people suffering from glaucoma, the nerve cells in the retina die over time – leading to blindness. In a large proportion of those affected, increased internal pressure in the eye poses a risk for the development of glaucoma. Empa researchers led by Yashoda Chandorkar and Markus Rottmar from the Biointerfaces lab in St. Gallen, together with the Department of Ophthalmology at the Animal Hospital in Zurich, are now developing a self-regulating system consisting of a tiny, highly sensitive sensor that measures the eye pressure and normalizes the pressure of the chamber fluid in the eye via a valve made of a biocompatible hydrogel.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Soldering instead of sewing&lt;/b&gt;&lt;p&gt;The second project aims to protect the highly sensitive eye tissue during operations thanks to a laser-based adhesive procedure. Until now, the use of needle and thread has been common practice for interventions on the lens in cataract or corneal surgeries. Lasers are also currently being used for a welding process at rather high temperatures. Inge Herrmann, professor at ETH Zurich and head of the Nanoparticle Systems Engineering group at Empa in St. Gallen, is working with her team to develop a minimally invasive laser soldering process that can be used to close wounds on the eye efficiently and gently. The biological soldering material with so-called nanoabsorbers is intended to improve the mechanical properties in the tissue, accelerate healing and reduce scarring. Thanks to the support of the "Heinz A. Oertli Fonds", the project can now start in cooperation with the Cantonal Hospital St. Gallen and the University Hospital Zurich.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt;Promoting research &lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Empa's Zukunftsfonds is looking for private donors for exceptionally talented young researchers and for outstanding research projects that are not (yet) supported elsewhere. The Vaduz-based Uniscientia Foundation is funding the present project. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Loris Pandiani Empa Zukunftsfonds Phone +41 58 765 47 03 loris.pandiani@empa.ch</contact>
      <attachment id="265240">
        <title>Inge Herrmann, head of the "Nanoparticle Systems Engineering" group at Empa in St. Gallen, and her team are developing a laser soldering process that can be used to close eye wounds efficiently and gently. Picture: Empa</title>
        <format>jpg</format>
        <size-kb>4496</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/83973.jpg</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <link id="265243">
        <title>Link to the press release on the Empa website</title>
        <uri>https://www.empa.ch/web/s604/oertli-fonds</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="8">
        <name lang="de">Bildung und Forschung</name>
        <name lang="fr">Formation et recherche</name>
        <name lang="it">Formazione e ricerca</name>
        <name lang="en">Education and Research</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="45">
        <name lang="de">Technologie</name>
        <name lang="fr">Technologie</name>
        <name lang="it">Tecnologia</name>
        <name lang="en">Technology</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
