<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="98496" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2023-11-07</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="201" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>201</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="201">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Schweiz führt erstmals politische Konsultationen mit Kenia</title>
      <lead>Ein Jahr nach der Vereinbarung, künftig regelmässige politische Gespräche zu führen, weilte der Chef der Abteilung Afrika im EDA, Botschafter Philipp Stalder, zu politischen Konsultationen in Nairobi. Im Zentrum seines Treffens standen bilaterale Themen, die Wirtschafts- und Handelsbeziehungen, die Rolle der Schweiz im UNO-Sicherheitsrat sowie der Klimawandel. Das ostafrikanische Land ist aufgrund seiner Bedeutung für die politische Stabilität der Region sowie des wirtschaftlichen Potenzials ein wichtiger Partner für die Schweiz. </lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Kenia spielt für die politische Stabilität in Ostafrika eine wichtige Rolle und ist in dieser Region ein Wirtschaftsmotor. Die Schweiz ist seit der Unabhängigkeit Kenias im Jahr 1963 vor Ort präsent. Anfänglich stand die Entwicklungszusammenarbeit im Vordergrund. Später wurden die Aktivitäten auf die Bereiche Wirtschaft, Korruptionsbekämpfung und Förderung der Menschenrechte ausgedehnt. Im Frühjahr 2022 vereinbarten die Schweiz und Kenia in einem Memorandum of Understanding (MoU), regelmässig politische Gespräche zu führen. Am 7. November 2023 hat nun Botschafter Philipp Stalder, Leiter der Abteilung Afrika im EDA, in Nairobi erstmals politische Konsultationen mit Kenia geführt. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Im Zentrum der Gespräche standen verschiedene laufende bilaterale Verhandlungen, die Stärkung der Wirtschafts- und Handelsbeziehungen und die Rolle der Schweiz im UNO-Sicherheitsrat. Weitere Schwerpunkte lagen auf dem Umgang mit dem Klimawandel und der stabilisierenden Rolle Kenias in einer von Krisen und Konflikten geprägten Region. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Kenia wird in der Subsahara-Strategie 2021-24 wegen seines hohen Wirtschaftswachstums als eine «wirtschaftliche Löwin» bezeichnet. Das Handelsvolumen zwischen der Schweiz und Kenia belief sich im Jahr 2022 auf 182 Millionen CHF. Die Schweiz führt fast ausschliesslich landwirtschaftliche Produkte ein und exportiert hauptsächlich pharmazeutische und chemische Erzeugnisse nach Kenia. Ende 2022 lebten 826 Schweizer Staatsangehörige in Kenia. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Geografisch gehört Kenia zum Grossen Horn von Afrika, einer geografischen und thematischen Schwerpunktregion der Subsahara-Afrika-Strategie 2021–2024. Die Region gehört zu den dynamischsten, aber auch fragilsten und am stärksten von Konflikten betroffenen Regionen der Welt. Das Grosse Horn von Afrika ist aufgrund seiner Stellung als Bindeglied zwischen dem Nahen Osten und Afrika, aber auch &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;als Nadelöhr für den Welthandel zudem ein wichtiger geostrategischer Raum. &lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Kommunikation EDA Bundeshaus West CH-3003 Bern Tel. Medienstelle: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Pour la première fois, la Suisse mène des consultations politiques avec le Kenya</title>
      <lead>Un an après que la Suisse et le Kenya ont convenu d’instaurer entre eux un dialogue politique régulier, le chef de la division Afrique du DFAE, l’ambassadeur Philipp Stalder, s’est rendu à Nairobi pour des consultations politiques. Les questions bilatérales, les relations économiques et commerciales ainsi que le rôle de la Suisse au Conseil de sécurité de l’ONU ont été au cœur des discussions. Le Kenya est un partenaire de poids pour la Suisse, en raison de son importance pour la stabilité politique de la région mais également de son potentiel économique. </lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Le Kenya joue un rôle clé dans la stabilité politique de l’Afrique de l’Est et constitue l’un des moteurs économiques de la région. La Suisse est présente sur place depuis l’indépendance du pays, proclamée en 1963. Si au début, les activités de la Suisse portaient essentiellement sur la coopération au développement, elles se sont étendues par la suite aux domaines de l’économie, de la lutte contre la corruption et de la promotion des droits de l’homme. Au printemps 2022, la Suisse et le Kenya ont convenu dans un protocole d’entente de mener des entretiens politiques à intervalles réguliers. Le 7 novembre 2023, à Nairobi, l’ambassadeur Philipp Stalder, chef de la division Afrique du DFAE, a mené pour la première fois des consultations politiques avec le Kenya. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Les discussions ont porté essentiellement sur diverses négociations bilatérales en cours, sur le renforcement des relations économiques et commerciales ainsi que sur le rôle de la Suisse au sein du Conseil de sécurité de l’ONU. La gestion du changement climatique et le rôle stabilisateur du Kenya dans une région marquée par les crises et les conflits ont également été évoqués. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Dans la stratégie pour l’Afrique subsaharienne 2021-2024, le Kenya est qualifié de «lionne économique», en référence à sa forte croissance économique. En 2022, les échanges commerciaux entre la Suisse et le Kenya ont atteint un montant de 182 millions de francs. La Suisse importe du Kenya presque exclusivement des produits agricoles, tandis qu’elle y exporte en majeure partie des produits pharmaceutiques et chimiques. Fin 2022, 826 ressortissants suisses vivaient au Kenya. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Le Kenya est l’un des pays de la grande Corne de l’Afrique, une région inscrite dans les priorités thématiques et géographiques de la stratégie pour l’Afrique subsaharienne 2021-2024. La région est l’une des plus dynamiques du monde, mais aussi l’une des plus fragiles et des plus touchées par les conflits. Trait d’union entre le Proche-Orient et l’Afrique et lieu de passage obligé du commerce mondial, la grande Corne de l’Afrique revêt une importance géostratégique majeure. &lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Communication DFAE Palais fédéral ouest CH-3003 Berne Tél. Service de presse: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>La Svizzera tiene per la prima volta consultazioni politiche con il Kenia</title>
      <lead>A un anno dalla firma di un accordo che prevede lo svolgimento di regolari colloqui politici in futuro, il capo della Divisione Africa del DFAE, l’ambasciatore Philipp Stalder, si è recato a Nairobi per prendere parte a consultazioni politiche. Gli incontri si sono focalizzati su temi bilaterali, sulle relazioni economiche e commerciali, sul ruolo della Svizzera nel Consiglio di sicurezza dell’ONU e sui cambiamenti climatici. Considerati la sua importanza per la stabilità politica nella regione e il suo potenziale economico, il Kenia è un partner di rilievo per la Svizzera. </lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Il Kenia svolge un ruolo di primo piano nella stabilità politica dell’Africa orientale ed è un importante motore economico nella regione. La Svizzera è presente nel Paese africano dal 1963, anno in cui quest’ultimo ha dichiarato la sua indipendenza. Inizialmente l’attenzione era rivolta alla cooperazione allo sviluppo, mentre in seguito le attività in loco sono state estese ai settori dell’economia, della lotta alla corruzione e della promozione dei diritti umani. Nella primavera del 2022 Svizzera e Kenia hanno confermato in una dichiarazione d’intenti la propria volontà di tenere regolari colloqui politici. Il 7 novembre 2023 l’ambasciatore Philipp Stalder, capo della Divisione Africa del Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri (DFAE), ha tenuto per la prima volta consultazioni politiche con il Kenia, a Nairobi. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;I colloqui si sono concentrati su varie trattative bilaterali in corso, sul potenziamento delle relazioni economiche e commerciali e sull’operato della Svizzera nel Consiglio di sicurezza dell’ONU. Altre questioni affrontate riguardano la gestione dei cambiamenti climatici e il ruolo del Kenia nella stabilizzazione di una regione segnata da crisi e conflitti. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;In virtù della sua elevata crescita, l’economia keniota è considerata una «leonessa economica» nella Strategia Africa subsahariana 2021–2024. Nel 2022 il volume degli scambi commerciali tra i due Paesi è stato pari a 182 milioni di franchi. La Svizzera importa dal Kenia quasi esclusivamente prodotti agricoli e vi esporta prevalentemente prodotti chimici e farmaceutici. Alla fine del 2022 nel Paese africano vivevano 826 cittadine e cittadini di nazionalità svizzera. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Dal punto di vista geografico il Kenia si situa nel Grande Corno d’Africa, una regione tematica e geografica prioritaria della Strategia Africa subsahariana 2021–2024 che rientra tra le più dinamiche al mondo, ma anche tra le più fragili e tra quelle maggiormente colpite da conflitti. Poiché funge da ponte tra il Medio Oriente e l’Africa &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;e da punto di passaggio obbligato del commercio mondiale, il Grande Corno d’Africa rappresenta un’area di grande rilevanza geostrategica. &lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Comunicazione DFAE Palazzo federale ovest CH-3003 Berna Tel. Servizio stampa: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Switzerland conducts first political consultations with Kenya</title>
      <lead>One year after the agreement to hold regular political talks in future, the head of the FDFA's Africa Division, Ambassador Philipp Stalder, travelled to Nairobi for political consultations. Talks revolved around bilateral issues, economic and trade relations, Switzerland's role in the UN Security Council and climate change. The East African country is a key partner for Switzerland on account of its importance for the political stability of the region and its economic potential. </lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Kenya plays an important role in the political stability of East Africa and is an economic powerhouse in the region. Switzerland has maintained a diplomatic presence in Kenya since Kenya's independence in 1963. Switzerland's activities initially focused on development cooperation, but were later extended to cover economic affairs, anti-corruption efforts and human rights promotion. In spring 2022, Switzerland and Kenya agreed in a Memorandum of Understanding (MoU) to hold regular political talks. On 7 November 2023, Ambassador Philipp Stalder, head of the FDFA's Africa Division, conducted political consultations in Nairobi for the first time. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The talks centred on various ongoing bilateral negotiations, efforts to strengthen economic and trade relations and Switzerland's role in the UN Security Council. Other key topics included ways of dealing with climate change and Kenya's stabilising role in a region beset by crises and conflicts. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Kenya is described as a lion economy in the Sub-Saharan Africa Strategy 2021–24 due to its strong economic growth. The trade volume between Switzerland and Kenya totalled CHF 182 million in 2022. Switzerland imports almost exclusively agricultural products and exports mainly pharmaceutical and chemical products to Kenya. At the end of 2022, 826 Swiss citizens were living in Kenya. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Kenya is part of the Greater Horn of Africa, a geographical and thematic priority region of the Sub-Saharan Africa Strategy 2021–24. The region is one of the most dynamic, but also one of the most fragile and conflict-stricken parts of the world. Due to its position as a link between the Middle East and Africa as well as a gateway for global trade, the Greater Horn of Africa is also important in geostrategic terms. &lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>FDFA Communication Federal Palace West Wing CH-3003 Bern, Switzerland Tel. Press service: +41 58 460 55 55 E-mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @SwissMFA</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
