<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="98608" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2023-11-16</pubdate>
    <blocking-period>2023-11-16</blocking-period>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="318" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>301</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Bundesamt für Statistik</name>
      <name lang="fr">Office fédéral de la statistique</name>
      <name lang="it">Ufficio federale di statistica</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Statistical Office</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.statistik.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.statistique.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.statistica.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.statistics.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@bfs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@bfs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@bfs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@bfs.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="301">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement des Innern</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'intérieur</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'interno</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Home Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Neuchâtel</city>
      <title>In den Schweizer Bibliotheken sind neun von zehn Direktionsposten von Frauen besetzt</title>
      <lead>2022 entwickelten sich die meisten Indikatoren zur Tätigkeit der Bibliotheken nach zwei pandemiegeprägten Jahren wieder positiv: Die Eintritte nahmen gegenüber 2021 um 28% zu, die Anzahl organisierter Veranstaltungen um 42% und die Teilnehmerzahl an den Veranstaltungen um 54%. Neue Ergebnisse zeigen, dass 80% des bezahlten Bibliothekspersonals Frauen sind. Auf Direktionsebene beläuft sich ihr Anteil sogar auf 88%. Dies geht aus den jüngst veröffentlichten detaillierten Ergebnissen der Schweizerischen Bibliotheksstatistik des Bundesamtes für Statistik (BFS) hervor.</lead>
      <text link="no">Diese Medienmitteilung und weitere Informationen zum Thema finden Sie auf der Website des BFS (siehe Link unten)</text>
      <contact>Laurène Stauffer, BFS, Sektion Politik, Kultur, Medien, Tel.: +41 58 463 61 58, E-Mail: poku@bfs.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="265693">
        <title>Kompletter Text und Mediendossier</title>
        <uri>https://www.bfs.admin.ch/news/de/2023-0612</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Neuchâtel</city>
      <title>Neuf postes de direction sur dix dans les bibliothèques suisses sont occupés par des femmes</title>
      <lead>La plupart des indicateurs d’activité des bibliothèques ont progressé en 2022, après deux années marquées par la pandémie de Covid-19: entrées (+28% par rapport à 2021), événements organisés (+42%) et participants à ces événements (+54%). De nouveaux résultats montrent que les femmes composent le 80% du personnel salarié des bibliothèques, voire 88% au niveau de la direction. Ces données font partie des résultats détaillés de la Statistique suisse des bibliothèques que l’Office fédéral de la statistique (OFS) vient de publier.</lead>
      <text link="no">Vous trouverez ce communiqué de presse et d'autres informations sur ce thème sur le site web de l'OFS (voir le lien ci-dessous)</text>
      <contact>Laurène Stauffer, OFS, Section Politique, culture, médias, tél.: +41 58 463 61 58, e-mail: poku@bfs.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="265694">
        <title>Texte intégral et dossier de presse</title>
        <uri>https://www.bfs.admin.ch/news/fr/2023-0612</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Neuchâtel</city>
      <title>Nelle biblioteche svizzere nove posti dirigenziali su dieci sono occupati da donne</title>
      <lead>Dopo due anni segnati dalla pandemia di COVID-19, nel 2022 la maggior parte degli indicatori di attività delle biblioteche è migliorata: ingressi (+28% rispetto al 2021), eventi organizzati (+42%) e partecipanti a questi eventi (+54%). Nuovi risultati mostrano che le donne rappresentano l’80% del personale salariato delle biblioteche e addirittura l’88% a livello dirigenziale. Questi dati costituiscono alcuni dei risultati dettagliati della statistica svizzera delle biblioteche, che l’Ufficio federale di statistica (UST) ha appena pubblicato.</lead>
      <text link="no">Il presente comunicato stampa e ulteriori informazioni sul tema sono reperibili sulla pagina Internet dell'UST (link sotto)</text>
      <contact>Laurène Stauffer, UST, sezione Politica, cultura e media, tel.: +41 58 463 61 58, e-mail: poku@bfs.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="265695">
        <title>Testo integrale e dossier per i media</title>
        <uri>https://www.bfs.admin.ch/news/it/2023-0612</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Neuchâtel</city>
      <title>Nine out of ten senior management positions in Swiss libraries are held by women</title>
      <lead>Most library activity indicators improved in 2022, after two years marked by the COVID-19 pandemic: admissions (+28% compared with 2021), events organised (+42%) and participants in these events (+54%). New results show that women account for 80% of salaried library staff, and even 88% at senior management level. These data are some of the detailed results of the Swiss Library Statistics just published by the Federal Statistical Office (FSO).</lead>
      <text link="no">This press release and further information on this topic can be found on the FSO website (see link below)</text>
      <contact>Laurène Stauffer, FSO, Politics, Culture and Media Section, tel.: +41 58 463 61 58, email: poku@bfs.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="265696">
        <title>Please note that the English version only includes the release's lead</title>
        <uri>https://www.bfs.admin.ch/news/en/2023-0612</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <keywords>
      <keyword id="317.17" org-id="318">
        <name lang="de">Kultur, Informationsgesellschaft, Sport</name>
        <name lang="fr">Culture, société de l'information, sport</name>
        <name lang="it">Cultura, media</name>
        <name lang="en">Culture, information society, sports</name>
      </keyword>
    </keywords>
    <topics>
      <topic id="7">
        <name lang="de">Bibliotheken und Archive</name>
        <name lang="fr">Bibliothèques et archives</name>
        <name lang="it">Biblioteche e archivi</name>
        <name lang="en">Libraries and Archives</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="18">
        <name lang="de">Kultur</name>
        <name lang="fr">Culture</name>
        <name lang="it">Cultura</name>
        <name lang="en">Culture</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="43">
        <name lang="de">Statistik</name>
        <name lang="fr">Statistiques</name>
        <name lang="it">Statistica</name>
        <name lang="en">Statistics</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
