<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="99081" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2023-11-29</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="1070" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>1070</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Der Bundesrat</name>
      <name lang="fr">Conseil fédéral</name>
      <name lang="it">Il Consiglio federale</name>
      <name lang="en">The Federal Council</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.admin.ch/gov/de/start.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.admin.ch/gov/fr/accueil.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.admin.ch/gov/it/pagina-iniziale.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.admin.ch/gov/en/start.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="302" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>301</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Generalsekretariat EDI</name>
      <name lang="fr">Secrétariat général DFI</name>
      <name lang="it">Segreteria generale DFI</name>
      <name lang="en">General Secretariat FDHA</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="1070">
      <name lang="de">Der Bundesrat</name>
      <name lang="fr">Conseil fédéral</name>
      <name lang="it">Il Consiglio federale</name>
      <name lang="en">The Federal Council</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.admin.ch/gov/de/start.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.admin.ch/gov/fr/accueil.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.admin.ch/gov/it/pagina-iniziale.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.admin.ch/gov/en/start.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <department id="301">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement des Innern</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'intérieur</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'interno</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Home Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Neuer Masterplan für offene Verwaltungsdaten</title>
      <lead>Der Bundesrat hat an seiner Sitzung vom 29. November 2023 den Masterplan 2024–2027 für offene Verwaltungsdaten (Open Government Data, OGD) in der Schweiz verabschiedet. Er folgt auf die Open-Government-Data-Strategie 2019–2023 der Schweiz. Der neue Masterplan legt die Aktivitäten im Bereich offene Verwaltungsdaten bis 2027 fest und begleitet das Inkrafttreten des Bundesgesetzes über den Einsatz elektronischer Mittel zur Erfüllung von Behördenaufgaben (EMBAG).</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Das Bereitstellen offener Verwaltungsdaten fördert die Transparenz, Partizipation und Innovation in allen Bereichen der Gesellschaft. Der vom Bundesamt für Statistik (BFS) erarbeitete Masterplan Open Government Data 2024-2027 (OGD-Masterplan 2024-2027) verfolgt ebendieses Ziel. Er umfasst die Stossrichtungen, Ziele und Massnahmen für den Zeitraum 2024-2027 und definiert die Prioritäten der Umsetzung in der Bundesverwaltung einschliesslich der dezentralen Einheiten. Zudem dient er als Referenzdokument für die Kantone, Gemeinden und staatsnahen Betriebe, die aufgefordert sind, die Bereitstellung öffentlicher Verwaltungsdaten zu fördern. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Ein Masterplan mit fünf praktischen Stossrichtungen&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Um die Einheiten der Bundesverwaltung bei der Umsetzung von Artikel 10 EMBAG, der den Grundsatz «open by default» gesetzlich verankert, zu unterstützen, wurden im Masterplan fünf Stossrichtungen im Bereich offene Verwaltungsdaten definiert: Verfügbarkeit, Qualität der (Meta-)Daten, Infrastruktur, Synergien zwischen verschiedenen Bereichen sowie Austausch zwischen Anbietenden und Nutzenden von OGD in der Schweiz. Diese Stossrichtungen helfen den Einheiten der Bundesverwaltung dabei, sich anhand von Zielen, Massnahmen und Indikatoren mit den wichtigen OGD-Grundsätzen vertraut zu machen und das volle Potenzial der OGD im Rahmen der rechtlichen, organisatorischen, technischen und semantischen Vorgaben auszuschöpfen. Mit der Umsetzung des OGD-Masterplans 2024-2027 soll die Schweiz in Bezug auf OGD wettbewerbsfähig bleiben und den internationalen Standards entsprechen. Zudem stärkt die Geschäftsstelle OGD, die beim BFS angesiedelt ist, ihre Rolle als Anlaufstelle im Bereich offene Verwaltungsdaten.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Open Government Data oder offene Verwaltungsdaten&lt;br /&gt; &lt;/b&gt;OGD sind Daten der Verwaltung, die der Öffentlichkeit unentgeltlich, zeitnah, in maschinenlesbarer Form und in einem offenen Format zur Verfügung gestellt werden. Dazu gehören unterschiedlichste Datensätze wie die Gemeindegrenzen der Schweiz, Bevölkerungsstatistiken, aktuelle Wetterdaten, historische Dokumente sowie Publikationen der Bundesverwaltung. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Publikationen&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Verfügbar unter bfs.admin.ch&lt;br /&gt;- Masterplan Open Government Data» 2024-2027&lt;br /&gt;- Evaluation der «Open Government Data»-Strategie 2019-2023&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="nsbtextkasten"&gt;&lt;b&gt;Die OGD-Strategie 2019-2023 endet mit positiven Ergebnissen&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;In der Laufzeit der OGD-Strategie 2019-2023 wurden positive Ergebnisse erzielt. Die Mehrheit der vorgesehenen Massnahmen wurde umgesetzt. Das Hauptziel - die rechtliche Verankerung des Grundsatzes &lt;i&gt;open by default&lt;/i&gt; - wurde mit der Einführung von Artikel 10 EMBAG erreicht. Ebenfalls umgesetzt wurden folgende Massnahmen: Entwicklung des Portals opendata.swiss sowie Fortsetzung seines Betriebs und Sicherstellung der Finanzierung seiner 2026 geplanten Migration; Erhöhung der Anzahl Datensätze auf opendata.swiss und Verbesserung der Qualität; Umsetzung verschiedener Kommunikationsmassnahmen, die die Sichtbarkeit des Themas OGD, die Zusammenarbeit, die Nutzung von opendata.swiss sowie die Mehrfachnutzung von Daten steigern; neue Weiterbildung im Bereich offene Verwaltungsdaten. Die noch nicht umgesetzten Massnahmen, die relevant bleiben, werden im OGD-Masterplan 2024-2027 wieder aufgenommen.&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Petra Keller Guéguen, BFS, Stab, Tel.: +41 58 463 62 04, E-Mail: Petra.KellerGueguen@bfs.admin.ch Medienstelle BFS, Tel.: +41 58 463 60 13, E-Mail: media@bfs.admin.ch</contact>
      <attachment id="267183">
        <title>OGD-Masterplan</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>785</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/84861.pdf</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="267188">
        <title>Evaluation der Open-Government-Data-Strategie 2019-2023</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>906</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/84865.pdf</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </attachment>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Nouveau plan directeur pour les données publiques ouvertes</title>
      <lead>Lors de sa séance du 29 novembre 2023, le Conseil fédéral a approuvé le nouveau plan directeur 2024-2027 pour les données publiques ouvertes (Open Government Data, OGD) en Suisse. Il fait suite à la stratégie sur les données en libre accès en Suisse 2019-2023. Ce plan directeur détermine les activités en matière dans ce domaine jusqu’en 2027 et accompagne l’entrée en vigueur de la loi fédérale sur l’utilisation des moyens électroniques pour l’exécution des tâches des autorités (LMETA).</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Publier les données des administrations publiques en libre accès renforce la transparence, la participation et l'innovation dans tous les domaines de la société. Elaboré par l'Office fédéral de la statistique, le plan directeur Open Government Data (OGD) 2024-2027 (Masterplan OGD 2024-2027) poursuit cet objectif. Il contient les orientations, buts et mesures pour la période 2024-2027 et définit des priorités de mise en œuvre pour l'administration fédérale (y compris les unités décentralisées). Il s'agit également un document de référence important pour les cantons, les communes et les entreprises parapubliques, encouragés à promouvoir la publication en libre accès des données publiques. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Un plan directeur avec cinq orientations pratiques&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Afin de soutenir les unités administratives dans la mise en œuvre de l'art. 10 de la LMETA qui ancre le principe de libre accès par défaut (&lt;i&gt;open by default&lt;/i&gt;) dans la loi, le plan directeur définit cinq orientations pour les données en libre accès: la disponibilité, la qualité des (méta)données, l'infrastructure, les synergies avec d'autres domaines et les échanges entre fournisseurs et utilisateurs d'OGD en Suisse. Ces orientations ont été traduites en objectifs, mesures et indicateurs, visant à aider les unités administratives fédérales à se familiariser avec les principes importants de l'OGD et à exploiter le potentiel des données publiques dans le cadre des exigences juridiques, organisationnelles, techniques et sémantiques. La mise en œuvre du Masterplan OGD 2024-2027doit également permettre à la Suisse de rester compatible et compétitive en matière d'OGD sur le plan international. Le secrétariat OGD, rattaché à l'OFS, renforce également son rôle de centre d'information pour les données publiques en libre accès.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Open Government Data: les données des autorités en libre accès&lt;br /&gt; &lt;/b&gt;Par Open Government Data (OGD), on entend les données des autorités mises gratuitement à la disposition du public, en temps utile, sous forme lisible par un ordinateur et dans un format ouvert. Cela concerne toutes sortes de données, par exemple les limites communales de la Suisse, des statistiques démographiques, des données météorologiques actuelles, des documents historiques ou les publications de l'administration suisse. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Publications&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Disponibles sur bfs.admin.ch&lt;br /&gt;- Masterplan Open Government Data 2024-2027&lt;br /&gt;- Évaluation de la stratégie Open Government Data 2019-2023&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="nsbtextkasten"&gt;&lt;b&gt;La stratégie 2019-2023 prend fin avec des résultats positifs&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;La période couverte par la stratégie OGD 2019-2023 prend fin avec des résultats positifs. Une majorité des mesures prévues dans la stratégie ont été mises en œuvre. L'objectif central - l'ancrage juridique du principe &lt;i&gt;open by default&lt;/i&gt; - a été rempli avec l'introduction de l'art. 10 LMETA. Les mesures suivantes ont également été réalisées: le portail opendata.swiss a été développé, son exploitation poursuivie et le financement de sa migration en 2026 assuré; la quantité de jeux de données sur opendata.swiss continuent d'augmenter et leur qualité de s'améliorer; diverses mesures de communication visant à augmenter la visibilité de la thématique OGD, la collaboration, l'utilisation d'opendata.swiss et les cas de réutilisation des données ont été mises en place; une formation dans le domaine des données publiques ouvertes est désormais proposée. Les mesures encore d'actualité n'ayant pas été achevées sur la période en question sont reconduites dans le Masterplan OGD 2024-2027.&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Petra Keller Guéguen, OFS, État-Major, tél.: +41 58 463 62 04, e-mail: Petra.KellerGueguen@bfs.admin.ch Service des médias de l’OFS: tél.: +41 58 463 60 13, e-mail: media@bfs.admin.ch</contact>
      <attachment id="267184">
        <title>Masterplan OGD</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>758</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/84862.pdf</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="267189">
        <title>Evaluation de la stratégie en matière de libre accès aux données publiques en Suisse 2019-2023</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>879</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/84866.pdf</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </attachment>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Nuovo piano direttore sui dati pubblici aperti</title>
      <lead>Nella sua seduta del 29 novembre 2023, il Consiglio federale ha approvato il nuovo piano direttore 2024–2027 sui dati pubblici aperti (masterplan OGD) in Svizzera. Fa seguito alla strategia sul libero accesso ai dati pubblici in Svizzera 2019–2023 (strategia OGD). Il piano direttore definisce le attività in materia di dati pubblici aperti (open government data, OGD) fino al 2027 e accompagna l’entrata in vigore della legge federale concernente l’impiego di mezzi elettronici per l’adempimento dei compiti delle autorità (LMeCaA).</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Pubblicare i dati liberamente accessibili delle amministrazioni pubbliche accresce la trasparenza, la partecipazione e l'innovazione in tutti gli ambiti della società. Elaborato dall'Ufficio federale di statistica, il masterplan OGD 2024-2027 persegue tale obiettivo. Contiene orientamenti, obiettivi e misure per il periodo 2024-2027 e definisce le priorità di attuazione per l'Amministrazione federale (comprese le unità decentralizzate). Si tratta inoltre di un importante documento di riferimento per Cantoni, Comuni e aziende parastatali, che sono incoraggiati a promuovere la pubblicazione dei dati delle amministrazioni pubbliche in formato liberamente accessibile. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Un masterplan con cinque orientamenti pratici&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Per sostenere le unità amministrative nell'attuazione dell'articolo 10 della LMeCaA, che sancisce il principio secondo cui esse sono tenute a rendere i dati pubblici liberamente accessibili (&lt;i&gt;open by default&lt;/i&gt;), il masterplan definisce cinque orientamenti in materia di dati aperti: disponibilità, qualità dei (meta)dati, infrastruttura, sinergie con altri ambiti e scambi tra fornitori e utenti di OGD in Svizzera. Questi orientamenti sono stati tradotti in obiettivi, misure e indicatori, allo scopo di aiutare le unità amministrative federali a familiarizzarsi con i principi importanti degli OGD e a sfruttare il potenziale dei dati pubblici nel quadro dei requisiti legali, organizzativi, tecnici e semantici. L'attuazione del masterplan OGD 2024-2027 dovrebbe inoltre consentire alla Svizzera di rimanere competitiva a livello internazionale in termini di OGD e della loro compatibilità. La Segreteria OGD, annessa all'UST, sta inoltre rafforzando il suo ruolo di centro di informazione sugli OGD.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Open government data: dati liberamente accessibili delle amministrazioni pubbliche&lt;br /&gt; &lt;/b&gt;Per open government data (OGD) si intendono i dati delle amministrazioni pubbliche messi a disposizione del pubblico gratuitamente, tempestivamente, in forma leggibile a macchina e in formato aperto. Tra di essi si trovano le serie di dati più disparate, come i confini dei Comuni svizzeri, statistiche demografiche, dati meteorologici aggiornati, documenti storici o le pubblicazioni delle amministrazioni svizzere. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Pubblicazioni&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Disponibili su:bfs.admin.ch&lt;br /&gt;- Masterplan OGD 2024-2027&lt;br /&gt;- Valutazione della strategia OGD 2019-2023&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="nsbtextkasten"&gt;&lt;b&gt;La strategia OGD 2019-2023 giunge al termine con risultati positivi&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Il periodo coperto dalla strategia OGD 2019-2023 giunge al termine con risultati positivi. La maggior parte delle misure previste nella strategia sono state attuate. L'obiettivo centrale, ovvero quello di creare i fondamenti giuridici per il principio &lt;i&gt;open by default&lt;/i&gt;, è stato raggiunto con l'introduzione dell'articolo 10 LMeCaA. Sono inoltre state attuate le misure seguenti: il portale opendata.swiss è stato sviluppato, il suo utilizzo si è consolidato ed è stato assicurato il finanziamento della sua migrazione nel 2026; la quantità di set di dati (dataset) su opendata.swiss continua a crescere e la loro qualità a migliorare; sono state messe in atto diverse misure di comunicazione volte ad aumentare la visibilità del tema OGD, la collaborazione, l'utilizzo di opendata.swiss e i casi di utilizzo multiplo dei dati; è stata introdotta una formazione sui dati pubblici aperti. Le misure ancora rilevanti e non interamente attuate nel periodo in questione sono state reintegrate nel masterplan OGD 2024-2027.&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Petra Keller Guéguen, UST, Stato maggiore, tel.: +41 58 463 62 04, e-mail: Petra.KellerGueguen@bfs.admin.ch Ufficio stampa dell’UST, tel.: +41 58 463 60 13, e-mail: media@bfs.admin.ch</contact>
      <attachment id="267185">
        <title>Masterplan OGD (in francese)</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>758</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/84863.pdf</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="267191">
        <title>Evaluation de la stratégie en matière de libre accès aux données publiques en Suisse 2019-2023 (Francese)</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>879</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/84867.pdf</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </attachment>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>New master plan for open government data</title>
      <lead>At its meeting of 29 November 2023, the Federal Council approved the new 2024-2027 master plan for Open Government Data (OGD) in Switzerland. It follows on from the 2019-2023 strategy for open access data in Switzerland. This master plan defines activities in this field up to 2027 and goes hand in hand with the entry into force of the Federal Act on the Use of Electronic Means to Conduct Official Tasks (EMOTA).</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;The 2024-2027 Open Government Data master plan, drawn up by the Federal Statistical Office, pursues the objective of making public administration data freely available in order to increase transparency, participation and innovation in all areas of society. The plan sets out the desired principles, goals and measures for the 2024-2027 period and defines implementation priorities for the federal administration (including decentralised units). The document also serves as an important reference for the cantons, communes and state-related enterprises encouraged to promote the open publication of official data. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;A master plan with five practical principles&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;To support the administrative units in implementing Art. 10 of the EMOTA, which enshrines the principle of open access by default (&lt;i&gt;open by default&lt;/i&gt;) in law, the master plan defines five principles for open access data: availability, quality of (meta)data, infrastructure, synergies with other fields and exchanges between OGD providers and users in Switzerland. These principles have been translated into objectives, measures and indicators, aimed at helping the federal administrative units to familiarise themselves with the main principles of OGD and to exploit the potential of official data within the framework of legal, organisational, technical and semantic requirements. The implementation of the 2024-2027 OGD master plan also strives to help Switzerland maintain its compatibility and remain competitive in the field of OGD at international level. The OGD Office, attached to the FSO, is also strengthening its role as an information centre for official open access data.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Open Government Data: Open access to government data&lt;br /&gt; &lt;/b&gt;Open Government Data (OGD) refers to government data made available to the public free of charge, in a timely manner, in machine-readable form and in an open format. This includes all kinds of data, such as Switzerland's communal boundaries, population statistics, current meteorological data, historical documents or publications from the Swiss administration. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Publications&lt;/b&gt; &lt;p&gt;Available at bfs.admin.ch&lt;br /&gt;- 2024-2027 master plan for Open Government Data (available in French and German)&lt;br /&gt;- Assessment of the 2019-2023 Open Government Data strategy (available in French and German&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="nsbtextkasten"&gt;&lt;b&gt;The 2019-2023 strategy draws to a close with positive results&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The period covered by the OGD 2019-2023 strategy is ending with positive results. The majority of measures planned in the strategy have been implemented. The key objective - the enshrining in law of the &lt;i&gt;open by default&lt;/i&gt; principle - has been achieved with the introduction of Art. 10 EMOTA. The following measures have also been implemented: the opendata.swiss portal was developed, it continues to operate and the financing of its migration in 2026 has been secured; the quantity of datasets on opendata.swiss continues to grow and their quality to improve; various communication measures aimed at increasing the visibility of the topic of OGD have been put in place, together with cooperation, the use of opendata.swiss and cases of data reuse. Training in open public data is also now available. Measures that are still relevant and were not completed during the period in question have been reincorporated into the 2024-2027 OGD master plan.&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Petra Keller Guéguen, FSO, Staff Division, tel.: +41 58 463 62 04, email: Petra.KellerGueguen@bfs.admin.ch FSO Media Service, tel.: +41 58 463 60 13, email: media@bfs.admin.ch</contact>
      <attachment id="267187">
        <title>Masterplan OGD (French)</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>758</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/84864.pdf</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="267192">
        <title>Evaluation de la stratégie en matière de libre accès aux données publiques en Suisse 2019-2023 (in French)</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>879</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/84868.pdf</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </attachment>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="5">
        <name lang="de">Behörden</name>
        <name lang="fr">Autorités</name>
        <name lang="it">Autorità</name>
        <name lang="en">Authorities</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="10">
        <name lang="de">Bundesrat</name>
        <name lang="fr">Conseil fédéral</name>
        <name lang="it">Consiglio federale</name>
        <name lang="en">Federal Council</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
