<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="98706" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2023-11-21</pubdate>
    <blocking-period>2023-11-21</blocking-period>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="318" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>301</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Bundesamt für Statistik</name>
      <name lang="fr">Office fédéral de la statistique</name>
      <name lang="it">Ufficio federale di statistica</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Statistical Office</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.statistik.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.statistique.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.statistica.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.statistics.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@bfs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@bfs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@bfs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@bfs.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="301">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement des Innern</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'intérieur</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'interno</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Home Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Neuchâtel</city>
      <title>Landwirtschaftliche Gesamtrechnung: Schätzung 2023 - 2023 ist ein durchzogenes Jahr für die Schweizer Landwirtschaft</title>
      <lead>Die Schweizer Landwirtschaft dürfte 2023 eine Bruttowertschöpfung von 4,5 Milliarden Franken generieren, was gemessen am Vorjahr einem Anstieg von 4,2% entspricht. Grund für dieses Wachstum sind hauptsächlich reichere Ernten im Futterbau. Demgegenüber setzten der durchzogene Frühling und die darauffolgende Trockenheit den Ackerkulturen sowie dem Früchte- und Gemüsebau zu. Die tierische Produktion war insgesamt mit jener von 2022 vergleichbar. Diese ersten Schätzungen für das laufende Jahr beruhen auf der Landwirtschaftlichen Gesamtrechnung, die das Bundesamt für Statistik (BFS) erarbeitet.</lead>
      <text link="no">Diese Medienmitteilung und weitere Informationen zum Thema finden Sie auf der Website des BFS (siehe Link unten).</text>
      <contact>Franz Murbach, BFS, Sektion Umwelt, Nachhaltige Entwicklung, Raum, Tel.: +41 58 463 65 97, E-Mail: franz.murbach@bfs.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="265836">
        <title>Kompletter Text und Mediendossier</title>
        <uri>https://www.bfs.admin.ch/news/de/2023-0306</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Neuchâtel</city>
      <title>Les comptes économiques de l’agriculture: estimations pour 2023 - Une année 2023 mitigée pour l’agriculture suisse</title>
      <lead>L’agriculture suisse devrait générer en 2023 une valeur ajoutée brute de 4,5 milliards de francs, en hausse de 4,2% par rapport à l’année précédente, notamment en raison de récoltes fourragères plus importantes. Par contre, le printemps maussade et la sécheresse qui l'a suivi ont péjoré de nombreuses cultures des champs ainsi que les fruits et légumes. La production animale est dans l’ensemble comparable à celle de 2022. Ces premières estimations pour l’année en cours se basent sur les comptes économiques de l’agriculture établis par l’Office fédéral de la statistique (OFS).</lead>
      <text link="no">Vous trouverez ce communiqué de presse et d'autres informations sur ce thème sur le site web de l'OFS (cf. lien ci-dessous).</text>
      <contact>Franz Murbach, OFS, Section Environnement, développement durable, territoire, tél.: +41 58 463 65 97, e-mail: franz.murbach@bfs.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="265837">
        <title>Texte intégral et dossier de presse</title>
        <uri>https://www.bfs.admin.ch/news/fr/2023-0306</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Neuchâtel</city>
      <title>Conti economici dell’agricoltura: stime per il 2023 - Un 2023 dolceamaro per l’agricoltura svizzera</title>
      <lead>Nel 2023 l’agricoltura svizzera dovrebbe generare un valore aggiunto lordo di 4,5 miliardi di franchi, il che corrisponderebbe a un aumento del 4,2% rispetto all’anno precedente, in particolare grazie a raccolti di foraggio più cospicui. Tuttavia, la primavera uggiosa e il periodo di siccità che l’ha seguita hanno avuto ripercussioni negative su diverse colture campicole, frutta e ortaggi. Nel complesso, la produzione animale è assimilabile a quella del 2022. Queste prime stime per l’anno corrente si basano sui conti economici dell’agricoltura dell’Ufficio federale di statistica (UST).</lead>
      <text link="no">Il presente comunicato stampa e ulteriori informazioni sul tema sono reperibili sulla pagina Internet dell'UST (link sotto).</text>
      <contact>Franz Murbach, UST, sezione Ambiente, sviluppo sostenibile, territorio, tel.: +41 58 463 65 97, e-mail: franz.murbach@bfs.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="265838">
        <title>Testo integrale e dossier per i media</title>
        <uri>https://www.bfs.admin.ch/news/it/2023-0306</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Neuchâtel</city>
      <title>Economic accounts for agriculture: estimates for 2023 - A mixed 2023 for Swiss agriculture</title>
      <lead>In 2023, Swiss agriculture is expected to generate a gross value added of CHF 4.5 billion, an increase of 4.2% compared with the previous year, in particular because of larger forage harvests. In contrast, a gloomy spring followed by drought adversely affected many field crops as well as fruit and vegetables. Animal production was broadly comparable to that of 2022. These initial estimates for the current year are based on the economic accounts for agriculture compiled by the Federal Statistical Office (FSO).</lead>
      <text link="no">This press release and further information on the topic can be found on the FSO website (see link below).</text>
      <contact>Franz Murbach, FSO, Section Environment, Sustainable Development, Territory, tel.: +41 58 463 65 97, e-mail: franz.murbach@bfs.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="265839">
        <title>Complete text and press kit - Please note that the English version only includes the release's lead</title>
        <uri>https://www.bfs.admin.ch/news/en/2023-0306</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <keywords>
      <keyword id="317" org-id="318">
        <name lang="de">Statistische Grundlagen und Übersichten (Statistische Grundlagen)</name>
        <name lang="fr">Bases statistiques et produits généraux (Bases statistiques)</name>
        <name lang="it">Basi statistiche e presentazioni generali (Basi statistiche)</name>
        <name lang="en">Statistical basis and overviews (Statistical basis)</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="317.8" org-id="318">
        <name lang="de">Land- und Forstwirtschaft</name>
        <name lang="fr">Agriculture et sylviculture</name>
        <name lang="it">Agricoltura e selvicoltura</name>
        <name lang="en">Agriculture and forestry</name>
      </keyword>
    </keywords>
    <topics>
      <topic id="38">
        <name lang="de">Landwirtschaft</name>
        <name lang="fr">Agriculture</name>
        <name lang="it">Agricoltura</name>
        <name lang="en">Agriculture</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="43">
        <name lang="de">Statistik</name>
        <name lang="fr">Statistiques</name>
        <name lang="it">Statistica</name>
        <name lang="en">Statistics</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
