<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="98550" revoked="no">
    <version>2</version>
    <pubdate>2023-11-10</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="yes" id="1060" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>601</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Staatssekretariat für internationale Finanzfragen</name>
      <name lang="fr">Secrétariat d'Etat aux questions financières internationales</name>
      <name lang="it">Segreteria di Stato per le questioni finanziarie internazionali</name>
      <name lang="en">State Secretariat for International Financial Matters</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.sif.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.sif.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.sif.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.sif.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@sif.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@sif.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@sif.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@sif.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="601">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Finanzdepartement</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des finances</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale delle finanze</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Finance</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.efd.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.dff.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.efd.admin.ch/efd/it/home.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.efd.admin.ch/efd/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Schweiz und Italien vereinbaren dauerhafte Steuerregeln für das Homeoffice</title>
      <lead>Bundesrätin Karin Keller-Sutter und der italienische Wirtschafts- und Finanzminister Giancarlo Giorgetti haben am 10. November 2023 im Rahmen einer Videokonferenz eine Erklärung unterzeichnet. Diese regelt die Frage der Besteuerung von Homeoffice für Grenzgängerinnen und Grenzgänger dauerhaft. </lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Ab dem 1. Januar 2024 haben gemäss der Erklärung alle Grenzgängerinnen und Grenzgänger im Sinne des im Dezember 2020 unterzeichneten Grenzgängerabkommens die Möglichkeit, bis zu 25 Prozent ihrer Arbeitszeit im Homeoffice zu leisten. Diese bleibt ohne Auswirkungen auf den Staat, der die Einkünfte aus unselbständiger Erwerbstätigkeit besteuern darf und auf den Status als Grenzgänger. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Zudem wurde beschlossen, die von beiden Ländern am 20. April 2023 vereinbarte Übergangslösung zu erweitern. Die zuständigen Behörden beider Staaten werden bis Ende November 2023 Sonderregeln für die Besteuerung von Homeoffice von Grenzgängerinnen und Grenzgängern für den Zeitraum vom 1. Februar 2023 bis zum 31. Dezember 2023 vereinbaren.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Bundesrätin Karin Keller-Sutter zeigt sich zufrieden: «Die Lösung, die wir mit Italien für die künftige Besteuerungen von Grenzgängerinnen und Grenzgängern vereinbart haben, ist gut für die Schweizer Unternehmen und ihre Mitarbeitenden. Sie bringt Klarheit und Sicherheit im Umgang mit der Besteuerung von Homeoffice, reduziert den administrativen Aufwand und garantiert eine Gleichbehandlung aller betroffenen Grenzgängerinnen und Grenzgänger.»&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Staatssekretariat für internationale Finanzfragen SIF Medienanfragen: Kommunikation, Tel.-Nr. +41 58 462 46 16, info@sif.admin.ch Fachfragen: Sekretariat Doppelbesteuerung, Tel.-Nr. +41 58 462 71 29, dba@sif.admin.ch</contact>
      <attachment id="265438">
        <title>Dichiarazione di intenti</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>118</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/84015.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>La Suisse et l’Italie définissent des règles durables pour l’imposition du télétravail</title>
      <lead>Lors d’une vidéoconférence qui s’est tenue le 10 novembre 2023, la conseillère fédérale Karin Keller-Sutter et le ministre italien de l’économie et des finances, Giancarlo Giorgetti, ont signé une déclaration visant à régler durablement la question de l’imposition du télétravail des frontaliers. </lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Selon la déclaration, tous les frontaliers au sens de l’accord sur l’imposition des frontaliers signé en novembre 2020 ont la possibilité d’effectuer, à compter du 1er janvier 2024, jusqu’à 25 % de leur temps de travail à domicile. Celui-ci n’a pas d’incidence sur l’État qui peut imposer les revenus provenant d’une activité lucrative dépendante et sur le statut de frontalier. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;La Suisse et l’Italie ont en outre décidé de prolonger la solution transitoire instaurée le 20 avril 2023. Les autorités compétentes des deux États arrêteront d’ici la fin du mois de novembre 2023 les règles spéciales applicables à l’imposition du télétravail effectué par les frontaliers au cours de la période allant du 1er février 2023 au 31 décembre 2023. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Satisfaite, la conseillère fédérale Karin Keller-Sutter a affirmé que la solution trouvée avec l’Italie pour l’imposition future des frontaliers est une bonne solution pour les entreprises suisses et leurs collaborateurs. Selon elle, cette solution apporte clarté et sécurité en ce qui concerne l’imposition du télétravail, réduit les charges administratives et garantit une égalité de traitement de tous les frontaliers concernés. &lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Secrétariat d’État aux questions financières internationales SFI Demandes des médias: Communication, n° tél. +41 58 462 46 16, info@sif.admin.ch Questions techniques: Secrétariat de l’unité Conventions contre les doubles impositions, n° tél. +41 58 462 71 29, dba@sif.admin.ch</contact>
      <attachment id="265438">
        <title>Dichiarazione di intenti</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>118</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/84015.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <revisions>
        <revision date="2023-11-10 14:42" type="R"/>
      </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>La Svizzera e l’Italia concordano una regolamentazione fiscale durevole per il telelavoro</title>
      <lead>Il 10 novembre 2023 la consigliera federale Karin Keller-Sutter e il ministro dell’economia e delle finanze italiano Giancarlo Giorgetti hanno firmato nell’ambito di una videoconferenza una dichiarazione di intenti volta a regolamentare durevolmente la questione dell’imposizione del telelavoro dei lavoratori frontalieri.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;In base alla dichiarazione di intenti, dal 1° gennaio 2024 tutti i lavoratori frontalieri ai sensi dell’Accordo sui frontalieri firmato nel dicembre 2020 avranno la possibilità di svolgere la loro attività in modalità di telelavoro presso il proprio domicilio fino al 25 per cento del tempo di lavoro. Ciò non avrà ripercussioni né sullo Stato legittimato a imporre l’attività di lavoro dipendente, né sullo status di lavoratore frontaliere.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;È stata inoltre decisa un’estensione della soluzione transitoria convenuta dalle due parti il 20 aprile 2023. Le autorità competenti di entrambi gli Stati definiranno, entro fine novembre 2023, regole speciali per l’imposizione del telelavoro dei lavoratori frontalieri per il periodo dal 1° febbraio 2023 al 31 dicembre 2023.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;La consigliera federale Karin Keller-Sutter si dichiara soddisfatta: la soluzione a cui la Svizzera è pervenuta con l’Italia nell’ambito dell’imposizione futura dei lavoratori frontalieri è favorevole per le imprese svizzere e i loro dipendenti, apporta chiarezza e certezza nell’imposizione del telelavoro, riduce gli oneri amministrativi e garantisce la parità di trattamento di tutti i lavoratori frontalieri interessati.&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Segreteria di Stato per le questioni finanziarie internazionali SFI Domande dei media: Comunicazione tel. +41 58 462 46 16, info@sif.admin.ch Domande specialistiche: Segreteria Doppie imposizioni tel. +41 58 462 71 29, dba@sif.admin.ch</contact>
      <attachment id="265438">
        <title>Dichiarazione di intenti</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>118</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/84015.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Switzerland and Italy agree permanent tax treatment for home working</title>
      <lead>On 10 November 2023 in the course of a videoconference, Federal Councillor Karin Keller-Sutter and Italian Minister of Economy and Finance Giancarlo Giorgetti signed a declaration regulating the taxation of home working for cross-border commuters.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;According to the declaration, from 1 January 2024 all cross-border commuters as defined in the agreement on cross-border commuters signed in December 2020 will be able to work from home for up to 25% of their working hours, without this affecting either the country which is eligible to collect tax on income from salaried employment or the status of cross-border commuters.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;It was also decided to expand the interim solution agreed between the two countries on 20 April 2023. By end-November 2023, the competent authorities of both states will agree on special rules for the taxation of home working for cross-border commuters for the period from 1 February 2023 to 31 December 2023.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Federal Councillor Karin Keller-Sutter expressed her satisfaction: "The solution that we have agreed with Italy for the future taxation of cross-border commuters is good for Swiss businesses and their employees. It brings clarity and security to the taxation of home working, reduces the administrative burden and guarantees the equal treatment of all the cross-border commuters concerned."&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>State Secretariat for International Finance SIF Media enquiries: Communications Tel. +41 58 462 46 16, info@sif.admin.ch Specific tax questions: Double Taxation Agreements Secretariat Tel. +41 58 462 71 29, dba@sif.admin.ch</contact>
      <attachment id="265438">
        <title>Dichiarazione di intenti</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>118</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/84015.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <offers>
      <offer id="291" org-id="1060">
        <name lang="de">Wirtschaft, Währung, Finanzplatz</name>
        <name lang="fr">Economie, monnaie, place financière</name>
        <name lang="it">Economia, Moneta, Piazza finanziaria</name>
        <name lang="en">Economic, Monetary and Financial Affairs</name>
      </offer>
    </offers>
    <keywords>
      <keyword id="235" org-id="1060">
        <name lang="de">Internationale Steuerpolitik</name>
        <name lang="fr">Politique fiscale internationale</name>
        <name lang="it">Politica fiscale internazionale</name>
        <name lang="en">International tax policy</name>
      </keyword>
    </keywords>
    <topics>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="44">
        <name lang="de">Steuern</name>
        <name lang="fr">Impôts</name>
        <name lang="it">Imposte</name>
        <name lang="en">Taxation</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="47">
        <name lang="de">Wirtschaft</name>
        <name lang="fr">Économie</name>
        <name lang="it">Economia</name>
        <name lang="en">Economic Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
