<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="102659" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2024-10-03</pubdate>
    <blocking-period>2024-10-03</blocking-period>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="318" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>301</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Bundesamt für Statistik</name>
      <name lang="fr">Office fédéral de la statistique</name>
      <name lang="it">Ufficio federale di statistica</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Statistical Office</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.statistik.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.statistique.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.statistica.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.statistics.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@bfs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@bfs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@bfs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@bfs.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="301">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement des Innern</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'intérieur</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'interno</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Home Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Neuchâtel</city>
      <title>Schweizerische Gesundheitsbefragung 1997–2022: Schlafstörungen nehmen seit 25 Jahren zu und betreffen ein Drittel der Bevölkerung</title>
      <lead>2022 gab ein Drittel der Bevölkerung an, unter Schlafstörungen zu leiden. Dieser Anteil hat sich gegenüber 1997 um 5 Prozentpunkte erhöht. Bei Frauen und jungen Menschen zwischen 15 und 39 Jahren war der Anstieg besonders markant. Schlafstörungen hängen eng mit der psychischen und physischen Gesundheit zusammen. Dies sind einige Ergebnisse aus der neuen Publikation des Bundesamtes für Statistik (BFS) zu Schlafstörungen.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Diese Medienmitteilung und weitere Informationen zum Thema finden Sie auf der Website des BFS (siehe Link unten).&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Brigitte Müller, BFS, Sektion Gesundheit der Bevölkerung, Tel.: +41 58 465 61 67, E-Mail: brigitte.mueller@bfs.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="280230">
        <title>Kompletter Text und Mediendossier</title>
        <uri>https://www.bfs.admin.ch/news/de/2024-0165</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Neuchâtel</city>
      <title>Enquête suisse sur la santé 1997—2022: En hausse sur 25 ans, les troubles du sommeil affectent un tiers de la population</title>
      <lead>En 2022, un tiers de la population souffrait de troubles du sommeil. Cela représente une augmentation de 5 points de pourcentage depuis 1997. Les femmes et les jeunes de 15 à 39 ans sont particulièrement touchés par cette hausse. La santé psychique et la santé physique sont fortement associées aux troubles du sommeil. Ce sont là quelques résultats de la nouvelle publication de l’Office fédéral de la statistique (OFS) consacrée aux troubles du sommeil.</lead>
      <text link="no">Vous trouverez ce communiqué de presse et d'autres informations sur ce thème sur le site web de l'OFS (cf. lien ci-dessous).</text>
      <contact>Martine Kaeser, OFS, section Santé de la population, tél.: +41 58 463 66 94, e-mail: martine.kaeser@bfs.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="280231">
        <title>Texte intégral et dossier de presse</title>
        <uri>https://www.bfs.admin.ch/news/fr/2024-0165</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Neuchâtel</city>
      <title>Indagine sulla salute in Svizzera 1997–2022: In aumento per 25 anni, i disturbi del sonno colpiscono un terzo della popolazione</title>
      <lead>Nel 2022 un terzo della popolazione soffriva di disturbi del sonno, il che rappresenta un aumento di 5 punti percentuali dal 1997. Tale aumento ha riguardato in particolare le donne e i giovani dai 15 ai 39 anni. La salute psichica e quella fisica sono strettamente connesse ai disturbi del sonno. Questi sono alcuni dei risultati della nuova pubblicazione dell’Ufficio federale di statistica (UST) dedicata ai disturbi del sonno. </lead>
      <text link="no">Il presente comunicato stampa e ulteriori informazioni sul tema sono reperibili sulla pagina Internet dell'UST (link sotto).</text>
      <contact>Brigitte Müller, UST, sezione Salute della popolazione, tel.: +41 58 465 61 67, e-mail: brigitte.mueller@bfs.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="280232">
        <title>Testo integrale e dossier per i media</title>
        <uri>https://www.bfs.admin.ch/news/it/2024-0165</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Neuchâtel</city>
      <title>Swiss Health Survey 1997—2022: Sleep disorders have been increasing for 25 years, affecting a third of the population</title>
      <lead>In 2022, a third of the population suffered from sleep disorders. This is a five percentage point increase from 1997. The increase concerned women and young people aged 15 to 39 in particular. There is a strong correlation between sleeping disorders and mental and physical health. These are some of the results from the Federal Statistical Office’s (FSO) latest publication.</lead>
      <text link="no">This press release and further information on the topic can be found on the FSO website (see link below).</text>
      <contact>Brigitte Müller, FSO, Population Health, tel.: +41 58 465 61 67, email: brigitte.mueller@bfs.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="280233">
        <title>Complete text and press kit - Please note that the English version only includes the release's lead</title>
        <uri>https://www.bfs.admin.ch/news/en/2024-0165</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <keywords>
      <keyword id="317" org-id="318">
        <name lang="de">Statistische Grundlagen und Übersichten (Statistische Grundlagen)</name>
        <name lang="fr">Bases statistiques et produits généraux (Bases statistiques)</name>
        <name lang="it">Basi statistiche e presentazioni generali (Basi statistiche)</name>
        <name lang="en">Statistical basis and overviews (Statistical basis)</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="317.15" org-id="318">
        <name lang="de">Gesundheit</name>
        <name lang="fr">Santé</name>
        <name lang="it">Salute</name>
        <name lang="en">Health</name>
      </keyword>
    </keywords>
    <topics>
      <topic id="15">
        <name lang="de">Gesundheit</name>
        <name lang="fr">Santé</name>
        <name lang="it">sanità</name>
        <name lang="en">Health</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="43">
        <name lang="de">Statistik</name>
        <name lang="fr">Statistiques</name>
        <name lang="it">Statistica</name>
        <name lang="en">Statistics</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
