<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="102724" revoked="no">
    <version>2</version>
    <pubdate>2024-10-09</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="1070" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>1070</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Der Bundesrat</name>
      <name lang="fr">Conseil fédéral</name>
      <name lang="it">Il Consiglio federale</name>
      <name lang="en">The Federal Council</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.admin.ch/gov/de/start.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.admin.ch/gov/fr/accueil.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.admin.ch/gov/it/pagina-iniziale.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.admin.ch/gov/en/start.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="201" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>201</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="1070">
      <name lang="de">Der Bundesrat</name>
      <name lang="fr">Conseil fédéral</name>
      <name lang="it">Il Consiglio federale</name>
      <name lang="en">The Federal Council</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.admin.ch/gov/de/start.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.admin.ch/gov/fr/accueil.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.admin.ch/gov/it/pagina-iniziale.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.admin.ch/gov/en/start.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <department id="201">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Humanitäre Minenräumung in der Ukraine: Bundesrat verstärkt Zusammenarbeit mit der Fondation suisse de déminage (FSD)</title>
      <lead>Der Bund unterstützt die Arbeit der in Genf ansässigen Fondation suisse de déminage (FSD) in der Ukraine bis 2027 mit 30 Millionen Franken. Das hat der Bundesrat an seiner Sitzung vom 9. Oktober 2024 entschieden. Mit seiner Entscheidung unterstreicht der Bundesrat die Bedeutung der humanitären Minenräumung für den Wiederaufbau der Ukraine.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Es wird vermutet, dass in der Ukraine rund 139’000 km2 mit Minen und anderen Kampfmitteln belastet sind. Um die Gefahr zu reduzieren, die von den Kampfmitteln für die ukrainische Bevölkerung ausgeht, hat der Bundesrat im September 2023 rund 100 Millionen Franken für den Zeitraum von 2024 bis 2027 zur Verfügung gestellt. Diese Summe wird je zur Hälfte vom EDA und vom VBS getragen. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;An seiner heutigen Sitzung hat der Bundesrat entschieden, die Unterstützung der Arbeit der in Genf ansässigen Fondation suisse de déminage (FSD) zu verstärken. Deshalb hat er 30 Millionen Franken für ein Projekt von FSD bewilligt. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Die Umsetzung dieser Bundesratsentscheidung wird an der &lt;i&gt;Ukraine Mine Action Conference UMAC2024 &lt;/i&gt;vorgestellt, die am 17. und 18. Oktober 2024 in Lausanne stattfindet. Bundespräsidentin Viola Amherd und Bundesrat Ignazio Cassis werden die Schweiz an der Konferenz vertreten, die gemeinsam mit der Ukraine durchgeführt wird. An der Konferenz werden unter dem Motto «People. Partners. Progress.» rund 50 Staaten, internationale und regionale Organisationen sowie Vertreterinnen und Vertreter von NGO, Wissenschaft und Privatsektor die Bedeutung der Minenräumung als zentralen Bestandteil des sozialen und wirtschaftlichen Wiederaufbaus thematisieren. &lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>für weitere Informationen: Kommunikation EDA Tel. Medienstelle +41 58 460 55 55 kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Déminage humanitaire en Ukraine : le Conseil fédéral renforce sa collaboration avec la Fondation suisse de déminage (FSD)</title>
      <lead>Le 9 octobre 2024, le Conseil fédéral a décidé d’accorder à la FSD, basée à Genève, un financement de 30 millions de francs jusqu’en 2027 pour son travail en Ukraine. Le Conseil fédéral souligne ainsi l’importance du déminage humanitaire pour la reconstruction de l’Ukraine.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;On estime que près de 139’000 km2 du territoire ukrainien sont contaminés par des mines et d’autres engins explosifs. Afin de réduire le danger que représentent les munitions de guerre pour la population ukrainienne, le Conseil fédéral a débloqué en septembre 2023 environ 100 millions de francs pour la période de 2024 à 2027. Cette somme est financée à parts égales par le DFAE et le DDPS. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Lors de sa séance de ce jour, le Conseil fédéral a décidé de renforcer son soutien aux activités de la Fondation suisse de déminage (FSD), basée à Genève, dont il subventionnera un des projets à hauteur de 30 millions de francs. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;La mise en œuvre de cette décision du Conseil fédéral sera présentée lors de la conférence sur le déminage en Ukraine (&lt;i&gt;Ukraine Mine Action Conference UMAC2024&lt;/i&gt;), qui se tiendra à Lausanne les 17 et 18 octobre 2024. Lors de cet événement, organisé conjointement par la Suisse et l’Ukraine, la présidente de la Confédération Viola Amherd et le conseiller fédéral Ignazio Cassis porteront les couleurs de la Confédération. La conférence, dont le slogan sera «People. Partners. Progress.», réunira les représentants d’une cinquantaine d’États, d’organisations internationales et régionales ainsi que des représentants d’ONG, du monde scientifique et du secteur privé, qui se pencheront sur l’importance du déminage en tant qu’élément central de la reconstruction sociale et économique. &lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Pour plus d'informations: Communication DFAE Tél. Service de presse +41 58 460 55 55 kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Sminamento umanitario in Ucraina: il Consiglio federale rafforza la collaborazione con la Fondazione svizzera per lo sminamento</title>
      <lead>La Confederazione sosterrà il lavoro svolto in Ucraina dalla Fondazione svizzera per lo sminamento, con sede a Ginevra, stanziando un contributo di 30 milioni di franchi fino al 2027. È quanto stabilito dal Consiglio federale nella sua seduta del 9 ottobre 2024. Questa decisione mette in evidenza l’importanza dello sminamento umanitario per la ricostruzione del Paese.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Secondo le stime, circa 139 000 chilometri quadrati di territorio ucraino sono contaminati da mine e altri ordigni bellici. Nel settembre del 2023 il Consiglio federale ha messo a disposizione, per il periodo 2024–2027, quasi 100 milioni di franchi destinati a ridurre il rischio rappresentato da questi ordigni esplosivi per la popolazione. L’importo è a carico, in parti uguali, del Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri (DFAE) e del Dipartimento federale della difesa, della protezione della popolazione e dello sport (DDPS). &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Nella seduta odierna il Consiglio federale ha deciso di intensificare il suo sostegno al lavoro della Fondazione svizzera per lo sminamento (Fondation suisse de déminage, FSD), con sede a Ginevra, e ha approvato un contributo di 30 milioni di franchi a uno dei suoi progetti. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Dell’attuazione di questa decisione si parlerà durante l’UMAC2024 (Ukraine Mine Action Conference), che si terrà a Losanna il 17 e il 18 ottobre 2024. La presidente della Confederazione Viola Amherd e il consigliere federale Ignazio Cassis rappresenteranno la Svizzera a questa conferenza, organizzata in collaborazione con l’Ucraina. Una cinquantina di Stati, organizzazioni internazionali e regionali e membri di ONG, mondo accademico e settore privato si riuniranno all’insegna del motto «People. Partners. Progress.» per discutere dell’importanza dello sminamento come parte integrante e fondamentale della ricostruzione sociale ed economica del Paese. &lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Informazioni: Comunicazione DFAE Tel. Servizio stampa +41 58 460 55 55 kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Humanitarian demining in Ukraine: Federal Council reinforces cooperation with the Fondation suisse de déminage (FSD)</title>
      <lead>The Swiss government is to provide CHF 30 million to support the work of the Geneva-based Fondation suisse de déminage (FSD) in Ukraine until 2027. The decision, which was made at the Federal Council's meeting on 9 October 2024, underscores the importance of humanitarian demining in Ukraine's reconstruction.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;It is estimated that around 139,000km2 of Ukraine is contaminated with mines and other explosive ordnance. In September 2023, the Federal Council made around CHF 100 million available for the 2024-27 period to reduce the risk posed by explosive ordnance to the Ukrainian population. Half of this amount will be provided by the FDFA and the other half by the Federal Department of Defence, Civil Protection and Sport (DDPS). &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;At its meeting today, the Federal Council decided to reinforce its support for the FSD, approving CHF 30 million in funding for one of the foundation's projects. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The implementation of this Federal Council decision will be presented at the Ukraine Mine Action Conference (UMAC2024), which will take place in Lausanne on 17 and 18 October. President Viola Amherd and Federal Councillor Ignazio Cassis will represent Switzerland at the conference, which is being jointly hosted with Ukraine. The conference, which will take place under the motto 'People. Partners. Progress.', will bring together around 50 states, international and regional organisations, and representatives from NGOs, academia and the private sector to discuss the key role played by humanitarian demining in social and economic recovery. &lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>For further information: FDFA Communication Tel. Press service +41 460 55 55 kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
