<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="102656" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2024-10-01</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="yes" id="502" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>501</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Generalsekretariat VBS</name>
      <name lang="fr">Secrétariat général du DDPS</name>
      <name lang="it">Segreteria generale del DDPS</name>
      <name lang="en">General Secretariat DDPS</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.vbs.admin.ch/</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.vbs.admin.ch/</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.vbs.admin.ch/</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.vbs.admin.ch/</www>
      <email lang="de">postmaster.vbs@gs-vbs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">postmaster.vbs@gs-vbs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">postmaster.vbs@gs-vbs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">postmaster.vbs@gs-vbs.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="501">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Verteidigung, Bevölkerungsschutz und Sport</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de la défense, de la protection de la population et des sports</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale della difesa, della protezione della popolazione e dello sport</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Defence, Civil Protection and Sports</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.vbs.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.vbs.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.vbs.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.vbs.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@gs-vbs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@gs-vbs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@gs-vbs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@gs-vbs.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Staats- und Regierungschefs feiern 70-Jahr-Jubiläum des CERN in Genf</title>
      <lead>Repräsentantinnen und Repräsentanten der Staaten, die der Europäischen Organisation für Kernforschung CERN angehören oder mit ihr verbunden sind, haben am Dienstag, 1. Oktober 2024, in Genf deren 70-Jahr-Jubiläum gefeiert. Bundespräsidentin Viola Amherd würdigte im Namen der Schweiz als Gründungsmitglied und Gaststaat die Errungenschaften des CERN. </lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Die Institution stehe für den Wissensdrang des Menschen und sei zugleich ein starkes Beispiel für die Erfolge, die von Staaten ausgehen, die nicht gegen-, sondern miteinander arbeiten, erklärte die Bundespräsidentin. Staats- und Regierungschefs, Ministerinnen und Minister aus den 24 Mitgliedsstaaten des CERN, den assoziierten Ländern und aus Staaten mit Beobachterstatus nahmen an dem Jubiläumsanlass teil. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Das CERN wurde 1954 mit dem Ziel gegründet, die Zusammenarbeit europäischer Staaten bei der friedlichen Nutzung der Kern- und Teilchenphysik sicherzustellen. Die Organisation gewährleistet die Spitzenforschung in der Hochenergiephysik. Seit seiner Gründung liefert das CERN entscheidende Beiträge zum Verständnis der Grundbausteine der Materie und zu den fundamentalen Kräften, die zwischen diesen Bausteinen wirken. Die Entdeckung des Higgs-Teilchens am CERN wurde mit dem Physiknobelpreis 2013 gekrönt. Im Zuge seiner Arbeiten in Genf hat Tim Berners-Lee zudem das Konzept des World Wide Web entwickelt. Am CERN sind heute 2500 Personen angestellt; die Organisation arbeitet mit rund 10'000 Gastforschenden aus aller Welt. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Die Bundespräsidentin würdigte in ihrer Rede die Leistungen der Mitarbeitenden des CERN seit dessen Gründung und die Zusammenarbeit mit der Organisation und den beteiligten Staaten. Sie verwies auf die aussenpolitische Strategie 2024-2027 des Bundesrats, mit der die Weichen gestellt sind, um die langfristige Entwicklung der Organisation zu fördern. In der Herbstsession stimmte das Parlament einer Gesetzesänderung zu, die dem Bund die Kompetenz gibt, die Bauten des CERN auf Schweizer Boden auf der Grundlage eines Sachplans zu genehmigen.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Die Bundespräsidentin nutzte das Zusammentreffen der Staats- und Regierungschefs in Genf für bilaterale Gespräche. Mit EU-Kommissionspräsidentin Ursula von der Leyen erörterte sie den Fortgang der laufenden Verhandlungen zwischen der Schweiz und der Europäischen Union (EU) sowie die Sicherheitslage in Europa. Beim Treffen mit dem slowakischen Präsidenten Peter Pellegrini kamen neben dem Krieg in der Ukraine auch bilaterale Themen zur Sprache, darunter die Zusammenarbeit zwischen der Schweiz und der Slowakei in Forschungsfragen. &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Kommunikation VBS +41 58 464 50 58 kommunikation@gs-vbs.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="280218">
        <title>Europäisches Laboratorium für Teilchenphysik CERN, Genf</title>
        <uri>https://www.sbfi.admin.ch/sbfi/de/home/forschung-und-innovation/internationale-f-und-i-zusammenarbeit/internationale-forschungsorganisationen/cern.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="280219">
        <title>CERN 70 – Inspiring the Future</title>
        <uri>https://cern70.cern/</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="280224">
        <title>Rede von Bundespräsidentin Viola Amherd zum 70-jährigen Bestehen des CERN</title>
        <uri>https://www.vbs.admin.ch/de/nsb?id=102655</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Célébration du 70e anniversaire du CERN à Genève</title>
      <lead>Les représentants des États membres de l’Organisation européenne pour la recherche nucléaire (CERN) et des États qui collaborent avec elle se sont réunis le 1er octobre 2024 à Genève pour célébrer son 70e anniversaire. La présidente de la Confédération Viola Amherd a salué les réalisations du CERN, dont la Suisse est l’un des États fondateurs et hôtes. </lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;La présidente de la Confédération a déclaré que cette institution symbolise la soif de connaissance de l’humanité et qu’elle est également un très bon exemple des succès qu’obtiennent les États qui ne travaillent pas les uns contre les autres, mais ensemble. Cette célébration a réuni les chefs d’État et de gouvernement et les ministres des 24 États membres et des États membres associés du CERN ainsi que des États ayant le statut d’observateur. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Le CERN, fondé en 1954 avec l’objectif de garantir la coopération entre les États européens en vue d’une utilisation pacifique de la physique nucléaire et de la physique des particules, promeut la recherche de pointe dans le domaine de la physique des hautes énergies. Depuis sa création, il apporte des contributions décisives à la compréhension des composants fondamentaux de la matière ainsi que des forces qui les relient. C’est au CERN qu’a eu lieu la découverte de la particule de Higgs récompensée par le prix Nobel de physique en 2013, et que Tim Berners-Lee a développé le concept du World Wide Web. Aujourd’hui, cette organisation emploie 2500 personnes et collabore avec environ 10 000 chercheurs invités du monde entier. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Dans son discours, la présidente de la Confédération a loué les réalisations accomplies par les collaborateurs du CERN depuis sa création et la coopération entre l’organisation et les États participants. Elle a également évoqué la stratégie de politique extérieure 2024-2027 du Conseil fédéral, qui pose les jalons pour favoriser le développement à long terme du CERN. Lors de la session d’automne, le Parlement a modifié une loi qui donne à la Confédération la compétence d’approuver les constructions du CERN sur le sol suisse, en se fondant sur un plan sectoriel.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Cette rencontre réunissant à Genève des chefs d’État et de gouvernement a également donné l’occasion à la présidente de la Confédération de mener des entretiens bilatéraux. Les échanges avec la présidente de la Commission européenne Ursula von der Leyen ont porté sur l’avancement des négociations en cours entre la Suisse et l’Union européenne et sur la sécurité en Europe. Lors de la rencontre avec le président slovaque Peter Pellegrini, outre la guerre en Ukraine, différents thèmes bilatéraux ont été abordés, parmi lesquels la coopération entre la Suisse et la Slovaquie dans le domaine de la recherche. &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Communication DDPS +41 58 464 50 58 kommunikation@gs-vbs.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="280221">
        <title>CERN, Laboratoire européen pour la physique des particules, Genève</title>
        <uri>https://www.sbfi.admin.ch/sbfi/fr/home/recherche-et-innovation/cooperation-internationale-r-et-i/organisations-internationales-de-recherche/cern.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="280220">
        <title>CERN 70 – Inspirer le futur</title>
        <uri>https://cern70.cern/fr/home/</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="280225">
        <title>Discours de la présidente de la Confédération Viola Amherd à l'occasion du 70e anniversaire du CERN</title>
        <uri>https://www.vbs.admin.ch/fr/nsb?id=102655</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Ginevra: capi di Stato e di Governo celebrano il 70° anniversario del CERN</title>
      <lead>Il 1° ottobre 2024 si sono tenuti a Ginevra i festeggiamenti per il 70° anniversario dell’Organizzazione europea per la ricerca nucleare (CERN). Vi hanno partecipato i rappresentanti degli Stati membri dell’Organizzazione e degli Stati che con essa collaborano. La presidente della Confederazione Viola Amherd ha reso omaggio alle conquiste del CERN, di cui la Svizzera è Paese fondatore e ospite. </lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;La presidente della Confederazione ha sottolineato come l’Organizzazione sia espressione della sete di conoscenza del genere umano e contemporaneamente un esempio perfetto dei risultati che si possono ottenere quando, invece di competere, gli Stati collaborano. Ai festeggiamenti hanno partecipato capi di Stato e di Governo e i ministri dei 24 Paesi membri del CERN, dei Paesi associati e degli Stati con lo statuto di osservatori.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Il CERN, fondato nel 1954 allo scopo di favorire la cooperazione tra gli Stati europei sull’impiego pacifico della fisica nucleare e delle particelle, promuove la ricerca di punta nel settore della fisica delle alte energie. Sin dalla sua istituzione, fornisce un contributo decisivo alla comprensione dei componenti di base della materia e delle forze fondamentali che agiscono tra di loro. Nel 2013 la scoperta presso il CERN del bosone di Higgs è stata premiata con il Nobel per la fisica. Ed è sempre al CERN che nel 1989 lo scienziato Tim Berners-Lee ideò il world wide web. Oggi, l’Organizzazione europea per la ricerca nucleare impiega 2500 persone e collabora con circa 10 000 ricercatori in tutto il mondo. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Nel suo discorso, la presidente della Confederazione ha reso omaggio ai risultati ottenuti dal CERN nei suoi 70 anni di vita grazie all’impegno dei suoi collaboratori e alla cooperazione tra l’Organizzazione e gli Stati partecipanti. Ha poi ricordato la Strategia di politica estera del Consiglio federale per gli anni 2024–2027, con la quale sono state gettate le basi per promuovere a lungo termine lo sviluppo dell’Organizzazione. Nel corso della sessione autunnale, il Parlamento ha adottato una modifica di legge che attribuisce alla Confederazione la facoltà di approvare i piani settoriali concernenti l’edificazione o la modifica di costruzioni del CERN sul territorio svizzero.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;La presenza a Ginevra di numerosi capi di Stato e di Governo ha offerto alla presidente della Confederazione l’occasione di condurre colloqui bilaterali. Con la presidente della Commissione dell’UE Ursula von der Leyen ha discusso delle trattative in corso tra la Svizzera e l’UE e della situazione della sicurezza in Europa&lt;i&gt;. &lt;/i&gt;Durante l’incontro con il presidente della Slovacchia&lt;i&gt; &lt;/i&gt;Peter Pellegrini, la presidente della Confederazione ha parlato della guerra in Ucraina e della cooperazione tra i due Paesi nel campo della ricerca.&lt;i&gt; &lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Comunicazione DDPS +41 58 464 50 58 kommunikation@gs-vbs.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="280219">
        <title>CERN 70 – Inspiring the Future</title>
        <uri>https://cern70.cern/</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="280222">
        <title>CERN, Laboratorio europeo di fisica delle particelle, Ginevra</title>
        <uri>https://www.sbfi.admin.ch/sbfi/it/home/ricerca-e-innovazione/cooperazione-internazionale-r-e-i/organizzazioni-di-ricerca-internazionali/cern.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="280226">
        <title>Discorso della presidente della Confederazione Viola Amherd per il 70° anniversario del CERN</title>
        <uri>https://www.vbs.admin.ch/it/nsb?id=102655</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Heads of state and government celebrate 70 years of CERN in Geneva</title>
      <lead>On 1 October, representatives of the countries that belong to or are associated with the European Organisation for Nuclear Research (CERN) gathered in Geneva to celebrate its 70th anniversary. On behalf of Switzerland as a founding member and host country, President Viola Amherd paid tribute to CERN's achievements. </lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;CERN as an institution symbolises humanity's thirst for knowledge and is also a powerful example of the successes that can be achieved when states work together rather than against each other, said President Amherd. Heads of state and government, ministers from CERN's 24 member states and representatives of associated and observer countries attended the anniversary event.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;CERN was founded in 1954 to ensure cooperation between European countries in the peaceful use of nuclear and particle physics. The organisation is committed to cutting-edge research in the field of high-energy physics. Since its inception, CERN has made ground-breaking contributions to our understanding of the fundamental building blocks of matter and the forces that act between them. In 2013, the Nobel Prize in Physics was awarded for the discovery of the Higgs particle at CERN. It was while working at CERN that Tim Berners-Lee invented the World Wide Web. Today, CERN employs 2,500 people and works with around 10,000 visiting scientists from all over the world.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;In her speech, Ms Amherd paid tribute to the achievements of CERN's staff since the organisation’s foundation, and to the fruitful cooperation between Switzerland and the organisation and its participating countries. She also referred to Switzerland's Foreign Policy Strategy 2024-2027, which sets the course for supporting CERN’s development in the long term. In the autumn session, Parliament approved an amendment to the law giving the Confederation the power to authorise CERN buildings on Swiss territory on the basis of a sectoral plan.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Ms Amherd used the meeting of heads of state and government as an opportunity for bilateral talks. With President of the European Commission Ursula von der Leyen, she discussed the ongoing negotiations between Switzerland and the European Union, and the security situation in Europe. During her meeting with Slovak President Peter Pellegrini, she discussed bilateral issues, including research cooperation between Switzerland and Slovakia, as well as the war in Ukraine.&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>DDPS Communications +41 58 464 50 58 kommunikation@gs-vbs.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="280219">
        <title>CERN 70 – Inspiring the Future</title>
        <uri>https://cern70.cern/</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="280223">
        <title>CERN, the European Organisation for Nuclear Research, Geneva</title>
        <uri>https://www.sbfi.admin.ch/sbfi/en/home/research-and-innovation/international-cooperation-r-and-i/international-research-organisations/cern.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="280227">
        <title>Address by President Viola Amherd on the occasion of the 70th anniversary of CERN</title>
        <uri>https://www.vbs.admin.ch/en/nsb?id=102655</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <keywords>
      <keyword id="5981" org-id="502">
        <name lang="de">Dossier Departementschef</name>
        <name lang="fr">Dossier Departementschef</name>
        <name lang="it">Dossier Departementschef</name>
        <name lang="en">Dossier Departementschef</name>
      </keyword>
    </keywords>
    <topics>
      <topic id="33">
        <name lang="de">Bundespräsident/-in</name>
        <name lang="fr">Président/e de la Confédération</name>
        <name lang="it">Presidente della Confederazione</name>
        <name lang="en">President of the Swiss Confederation</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="34">
        <name lang="de">Europa</name>
        <name lang="fr">Europe</name>
        <name lang="it">Europa</name>
        <name lang="en">Europe</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="40">
        <name lang="de">Sicherheit</name>
        <name lang="fr">Sécurité</name>
        <name lang="it">Sicurezza</name>
        <name lang="en">Security</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="45">
        <name lang="de">Technologie</name>
        <name lang="fr">Technologie</name>
        <name lang="it">Tecnologia</name>
        <name lang="en">Technology</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
