<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="102718" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2024-10-09</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="1070" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>1070</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Der Bundesrat</name>
      <name lang="fr">Conseil fédéral</name>
      <name lang="it">Il Consiglio federale</name>
      <name lang="en">The Federal Council</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.admin.ch/gov/de/start.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.admin.ch/gov/fr/accueil.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.admin.ch/gov/it/pagina-iniziale.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.admin.ch/gov/en/start.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="201" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>201</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="1070">
      <name lang="de">Der Bundesrat</name>
      <name lang="fr">Conseil fédéral</name>
      <name lang="it">Il Consiglio federale</name>
      <name lang="en">The Federal Council</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.admin.ch/gov/de/start.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.admin.ch/gov/fr/accueil.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.admin.ch/gov/it/pagina-iniziale.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.admin.ch/gov/en/start.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <department id="201">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Hochseeschiffe unter Schweizer Flagge: Bundesrat lockert Vorschriften</title>
      <lead>Die Hürden für die Registrierung von Schiffen unter der Schweizer Flagge sind hoch. Damit wieder mehr Schiffe unter Schweizer Flagge zur See fahren können, hat der Bundesrat an seiner Sitzung vom 9. Oktober 2024 die Registrierungsvoraussetzungen gelockert. Die entsprechenden Verordnungen wurden angepasst. Sie sind Teil der geplanten Revision der Seeschifffahrtsgesetzgebung. </lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Wegen den geltenden restriktiven Registrierungsvoraussetzungen ist es gegenwärtig nur eingeschränkt möglich, Schiffe unter Schweizer Flagge zu registrieren. Die gewerblich genutzte Schweizer Hochseeflotte ist allein im Verlauf der letzten Jahre um rund 75 Prozent geschrumpft. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Gleichstellung mit anderen Unternehmen&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Um die Einflaggung von Schiffen und Jachten zu erleichtern, werden die Voraussetzungen für die Registrierung gelockert und den für Unternehmen geltenden üblichen Bestimmungen des Obligationenrechts angepasst. Konkret betrifft dies die bestehenden Auflagen betreffend Nationalität der Eigentümer, der wirtschaftlich Berechtigten sowie der Verwaltung und Geschäftsführung. Zudem werden die Verordnungsbestimmungen dahingehend angepasst, dass Schifffahrtsunternehmen, gleich wie andere Unternehmen, ohne entsprechende Auflagen mehrheitlich fremdfinanziert werden können.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Anpassung an internationale Praxis bei Jachten&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Die Schweiz trägt der sich verändernden Praxis im internationalen Flaggenwesen und der Entwicklung in Richtung grösserer Schiffe beziehungsweise Jachten Rechnung. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Neu können auch juristische Personen nicht gewerbsmässig genutzte Schiffe unter eigenem Namen ins Schweizerische Jachtregister eintragen. Bisher war dies ausschliesslich natürlichen Personen und Vereinen vorbehalten.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Die Jachtenverordnung wird zudem so angepasst, dass ein Flaggenschein in Zukunft fünf statt wie bisher drei Jahre gültig ist. Ein Flaggenschein ist notwendig, damit eine Jacht die Schweizer Flagge führen darf.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Nebst den Anpassungen der Seeschifffahrtsverordnung und der Jachtenverordnung wird mit einer Anpassung der Verordnung über die Seeschifffahrtsgebühren die Gebührenerhebung durch eine Pauschalierung vereinfacht. Die Änderungen treten am 1. Januar 2025 in Kraft. Sie sind Teil der in der maritimen Strategie des Bundesrates vorgesehenen Revision der Seeschifffahrtsgesetzgebung. Im nächsten Schritt sind Anpassungen des Bundesgesetzes über die Seeschifffahrt unter der Schweizer Flagge sowie weitere, weniger dringliche Verordnungsanpassungen vorgesehen.&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>für weitere Informationen: Kommunikation EDA Tel. Medienstelle +41 58 460 55 55 kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Navires de haute mer sous pavillon suisse : le Conseil fédéral assouplit les prescriptions</title>
      <lead>Les obstacles à l’enregistrement sous pavillon suisse sont importants. À sa séance du 9 octobre 2024, le Conseil fédéral a décidé d’assouplir les conditions d’enregistrement afin que davantage de navires puissent à nouveau naviguer en mer sous pavillon suisse. Il a adapté les ordonnances correspondantes dans le cadre de la révision prévue de la législation sur la navigation maritime. </lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;L’enregistrement de navires sous pavillon suisse est actuellement soumis à de nombreuses restrictions. Rien qu’au cours des dernières années, la flotte suisse de haute mer à usage commercial a diminué d’environ 75 %. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Égalité avec les autres entreprises&lt;/b&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Afin de faciliter la mise sous pavillon suisse des navires et des yachts, les conditions d’enregistrement sont assouplies et alignées sur les dispositions usuelles du code des obligations applicables aux entreprises. Concrètement, cela concerne les obligations relatives à la nationalité des propriétaires, des ayants droit économiques ainsi que des membres des organes d’administration et de direction. Par ailleurs, les entreprises de navigation pourront à l’avenir, à l’instar des autres entreprises, être financées majoritairement par des fonds de tiers sans devoir répondre à des conditions supplémentaires.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Alignement sur la pratique internationale pour les yachts&lt;/b&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;La Suisse tient compte de l’évolution des pratiques en matière de pavillon à travers le monde, ainsi que du fait que les navires et les yachts ont tendance à être de plus en plus grands. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Les personnes morales pourront ainsi enregistrer les bateaux utilisés à titre non professionnel sous leur propre nom dans le registre suisse des yachts, une possibilité aujourd’hui réservée aux personnes physiques et aux associations.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;En outre, la durée de validité du certificat de pavillon prévu par l’ordonnance sur les yachts passera de trois à cinq ans. Ce document est nécessaire pour pouvoir battre pavillon suisse.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Outre l’ordonnance sur la navigation maritime et l’ordonnance sur les yachts, l’ordonnance sur les émoluments dans la navigation maritime est également adaptée : la perception des émoluments est simplifiée grâce à l’introduction d’un émolument forfaitaire. Les modifications entrent en vigueur le 1er janvier 2025. Elles s’inscrivent dans le cadre de la révision de la législation sur la navigation maritime prévue dans la stratégie maritime du Conseil fédéral. Une adaptation de la loi fédérale sur la navigation maritime sous pavillon suisse ainsi que d’autres modifications d’ordonnances, moins urgentes, sont prévues dans un second temps.&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Pour plus d'informations: Communication DFAE Tél. Service de presse +41 58 460 55 55 kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Navi d’alto mare battenti bandiera svizzera: il Consiglio federale allenta le norme applicabili</title>
      <lead>Gli ostacoli per la registrazione di navi battenti bandiera svizzera sono notevoli. Affinché un maggior numero di imbarcazioni possa tornare a solcare i mari con la bandiera della Confederazione, nella sua seduta del 9 ottobre 2024 il Consiglio federale ha deciso di allentare i requisiti in materia. Le relative ordinanze sono state adeguate nel quadro della revisione della legislazione sulla navigazione marittima. </lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;A causa dei severi requisiti applicabili, attualmente la registrazione di navi battenti bandiera svizzera è possibile solo in misura limitata. Solamente nel corso degli ultimi anni, la flotta commerciale d’alto mare svizzera si è ridotta del 75 per cento circa. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Parità di trattamento con le altre imprese&lt;/b&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Per facilitare l’immatricolazione di navi e yacht, i requisiti per la registrazione vengono pertanto allentati e adeguati alle consuete disposizioni del Codice delle obbligazioni applicabili alle imprese. Concretamente ciò riguarda i vincoli esistenti per quel che concerne la nazionalità dei proprietari, degli aventi economicamente diritto, dell’amministrazione e della gestione aziendale. Si è inoltre deciso di adeguare le disposizioni delle ordinanze in modo che le imprese di navigazione possano essere finanziate a maggioranza da capitale di terzi senza dover soddisfare ulteriori condizioni, alla stregua di altre imprese.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Adattamento alla prassi internazionale per gli yacht&lt;/b&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;La Svizzera tiene conto dell’evoluzione della prassi in materia di bandiere a livello internazionale e della tendenza verso l’utilizzo di navi e yacht più grandi. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Ora anche le persone giuridiche potranno iscrivere a proprio nome imbarcazioni non commerciali nel registro svizzero degli yacht, una possibilità che in precedenza era riservata esclusivamente alle persone fisiche e alle associazioni.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;L’adeguamento dell’ordinanza sugli yacht prevede inoltre che la validità del certificato di bandiera sia prolungata da tre a cinque anni. Tale certificato è necessario affinché uno yacht possa battere bandiera svizzera.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;In aggiunta alle modifiche dell’ordinanza sulla navigazione marittima e dell’ordinanza sugli yacht, un adeguamento dell’ordinanza sugli emolumenti nella navigazione marittima consentirà di semplificare la riscossione degli emolumenti grazie a una forfetizzazione. Le modifiche, che entreranno in vigore il 1° gennaio 2025, fanno parte della revisione della legislazione sulla navigazione marittima prevista dal Consiglio federale nella sua Strategia marittima. Nelle prossime fasi si procederà alla modifica della legge federale sulla navigazione marittima sotto bandiera svizzera e altri adeguamenti meno urgenti alle ordinanze.&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Informazioni: Comunicazione DFAE Tel. Servizio stampa +41 58 460 55 55 kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Seagoing vessels flying the Swiss flag: Federal Council relaxes regulations</title>
      <lead>The hurdles for registering a ship under the Swiss flag are high. To enable more ships to sail under the Swiss flag, the Federal Council relaxed the registration requirements at its meeting on 27 September 2024. The corresponding ordinances have been amended, as part of the planned revision of maritime shipping legislation. </lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Due to the restrictive nature of the existing registration requirements, the possibility of registering ships under the Swiss flag is currently limited. The Swiss merchant fleet has shrunk by around 75% in the last few years alone. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Equal treatment compared to other companies &lt;/b&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;In order to facilitate the flagging of ships and yachts, the requirements for registration will be relaxed and adapted to the provisions of the Swiss Code of Obligations usually applicable to companies. Specifically, this concerns the existing requirements relating to the nationality of the owners, the beneficial owners and the administration and management. In addition, the provisions of the ordinance will be amended to the effect that shipping companies, like other companies, can be majority debt-financed without corresponding conditions. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Adaptation to international practice for yachts &lt;/b&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Switzerland is taking account of the changes in international flagging practice and the trend towards larger ships and yachts. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Legal entities can now also register non-commercial vessels under their own name in the Swiss Yacht Register. Previously, this was reserved exclusively for individuals and associations. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The Yachts Ordinance will also be amended so that a certificate of flag registration will in future be valid for five years instead of the current three. Such a certificate is required for a yacht to fly the Swiss flag. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;In addition to the amendments to the ordinances governing maritime navigation and yachts, the ordinance on maritime fees will be amended to simplify the levying of charges by means of a flat-rate system. The changes will enter into force on 1 January 2025 and come as part of the planned revision of maritime shipping legislation provided for in the Federal Council's maritime strategy. The next step will be to amend the Federal Act on Navigation under the Swiss Flag, as well as other, less urgent, amendments of ordinances.&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>For further information: FDFA Communication Tel. Press service +41 460 55 55 kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
