<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="102768" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2024-10-14</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="yes" id="502" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>501</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Generalsekretariat VBS</name>
      <name lang="fr">Secrétariat général du DDPS</name>
      <name lang="it">Segreteria generale del DDPS</name>
      <name lang="en">General Secretariat DDPS</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.vbs.admin.ch/</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.vbs.admin.ch/</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.vbs.admin.ch/</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.vbs.admin.ch/</www>
      <email lang="de">postmaster.vbs@gs-vbs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">postmaster.vbs@gs-vbs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">postmaster.vbs@gs-vbs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">postmaster.vbs@gs-vbs.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="501">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Verteidigung, Bevölkerungsschutz und Sport</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de la défense, de la protection de la population et des sports</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale della difesa, della protezione della popolazione e dello sport</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Defence, Civil Protection and Sports</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.vbs.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.vbs.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.vbs.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.vbs.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@gs-vbs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@gs-vbs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@gs-vbs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@gs-vbs.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Bundespräsidentin Amherd besucht Polen im Hinblick auf die EU-Ratspräsidentschaft des Landes</title>
      <lead>Bundespräsidentin Viola Amherd reist diese Woche nach Warschau, wo sie am Donnerstag, 17. Oktober 2024, mit dem polnischen Präsidenten Andrzej Duda zusammenkommen wird. Zudem sind Gespräche mit Sejmmarschall Szymon Hołownia und Frau Senatsmarschall Małgorzata Kidawa-Błońska geplant, die den beiden Parlamentskammern vorstehen. Polen übernimmt in der ersten Jahreshälfte 2025 turnusgemäss die EU-Ratspräsidentschaft.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Die Gespräche mit Polen, das Anfang 2025 die EU-Ratspräsidentschaft übernimmt, werden den bilateralen Beziehungen zwischen der Schweiz und Polen, der Sicherheitslage in Europa sowie den laufenden Verhandlungen zwischen der Schweiz und der Europäischen Union (EU) gewidmet sein. Zur Sprache kommen wird auch die bilaterale Zusammenarbeit im Rahmen des Zweiten Schweizer Beitrags an ausgewählte EU-Mitgliedstaaten. Mit einer Gesamtsumme von 320,1 Millionen Franken erhält Polen den höchsten Betrag unter den 15 Ländern, die vom Zweiten Schweizer Beitrag profitieren. Das Kooperationsprogramm ist insbesondere auf sozial benachteiligte Regionen ausgerichtet und fördert zudem die Forschung und Innovation an polnischen Universitäten. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Die Schweiz und Polen pflegen politisch, wirtschaftlich und kulturell enge Beziehungen. Mit einem Handelsvolumen von 6 Milliarden Franken (2023, ohne Gold) und Schweizer Direktinvestitionen von rund 6,4 Milliarden Franken (2022) ist Polen der wichtigste Partner der Schweiz in Zentraleuropa. Intensiviert hat sich zudem der Austausch in den Bereichen Bildung, Forschung und Innovation sowie Migration. Die Schweiz und Polen arbeiten auch auf multilateraler Ebene eng zusammen, insbesondere im Rahmen der Weltbank und des Internationalen Währungsfonds (IMF).&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Kommunikation VBS +41 58 464 50 58 kommunikation@gs-vbs.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="280449">
        <title>Bilaterale Beziehungen Schweiz–Polen</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home/vertretungen-und-reisehinweise/polen/bilatereale-beziehungenschweizpolen.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>La présidente de la Confédération Viola Amherd en visite à Varsovie à la veille de la présidence polonaise du Conseil de l'UE</title>
      <lead>La présidente de la Confédération Viola Amherd se rendra cette semaine à Varsovie, où elle rencontrera le président polonais Andrzej Duda le jeudi 17 octobre 2024. Des entretiens sont en outre prévus avec le président de la Diète Szymon Hołownia et la présidente du Sénat Małgorzata Kidawa-Błońska. La Pologne assumera la présidence tournante du Conseil de l'UE au premier semestre 2025.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Les discussions avec la Pologne, qui assumera la présidence tournante du Conseil de l'UE début 2025, seront consacrées aux relations bilatérales entre la Suisse et la Pologne, à la situation en matière de sécurité en Europe et aux négociations en cours entre la Suisse et l'UE. Il sera aussi question de la coopération bilatérale dans le cadre de la deuxième contribution de la Suisse en faveur de certains États membres de l’UE. Avec 320,1 millions de francs, la Pologne reçoit le montant le plus élevé parmi les 15 pays qui bénéficient de la deuxième contribution de la Suisse. Le programme de coopération vise en particulier à aider les régions socialement défavorisées et à encourager la recherche et l'innovation dans les universités polonaises. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;La Suisse et la Pologne entretiennent des relations étroites sur les plans politique, économique et culturel. La Pologne est le principal partenaire commercial de la Suisse en Europe centrale. En 2023, le volume des échanges a atteint 6 milliards de francs (sans l'or) et, en 2022, celui des investissements directs suisses, environ 6,4 milliards de francs. Au cours des dernières années, les deux pays ont renforcé leurs échanges dans les domaines de la formation, de la recherche et de l'innovation et de la migration. La Suisse et la Pologne coopèrent également étroitement au niveau multilatéral, notamment dans le cadre de la Banque mondiale et du Fonds monétaire international.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Communication DDPS +41 58 464 50 58 kommunikation@gs-vbs.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="280450">
        <title>Relations bilatérales Suisse–Pologne</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae/representations-et-conseils-pour-les-voyages/pologne/suisse-pologne.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>La Presidente della Confederazione Amherd visita la Polonia in vista della presidenza di quest’ultima al Consiglio dell’UE</title>
      <lead>Questa settimana la Presidente della Confederazione Viola Amherd si recherà a Varsavia, dove giovedì 17 ottobre 2024 incontrerà il Presidente polacco Andrzej Duda. Sono previsti colloqui anche con i due presidenti delle Camere del Parlamento, Szymon Hołownia (Sejm, la Camera bassa) e Małgorzata Kidawa-Błońska (Senato). La Polonia assumerà la presidenza di turno del Consiglio dell'UE nella prima metà del 2025. </lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;I colloqui con la Polonia, che assumerà la presidenza del Consiglio dell’UE all’inizio del 2025, saranno incentrati sulle relazioni bilaterali tra Svizzera e Polonia, sulla situazione in Europa sotto il profilo della sicurezza e sui negoziati in corso tra la Svizzera e l’Unione europea (UE). Si discuterà anche della cooperazione bilaterale nell’ambito del secondo contributo svizzero ad alcuni Stati membri dell’UE. Con un importo totale di 320,1 milioni di franchi, la Polonia riceverà la quota più elevata dei 15 Paesi che beneficiano di tale contributo. Il programma di cooperazione si rivolge in particolare alle regioni socialmente svantaggiate e promuove altresì la ricerca e l’innovazione nelle università polacche.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;La Svizzera e la Polonia intrattengono stretti legami sul piano politico, economico e culturale. Con un volume di scambi commerciali pari a 6 miliardi di franchi (2023, escluso l’oro) e investimenti diretti svizzeri per circa 6,4 miliardi di franchi (2022), la Polonia è il partner più importante della Svizzera nell’Europa centrale. Sono stati intensificati anche gli scambi nei settori dell’educazione, della ricerca, dell’innovazione e della migrazione. La Svizzera e la Polonia collaborano inoltre strettamente a livello multilaterale, in particolare nell’ambito della Banca Mondiale e del Fondo Monetario Internazionale (FMI).&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Comunicazione DDPS +41 58 464 50 58 kommunikation@gs-vbs.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="280451">
        <title>Relazioni bilaterali Svizzera–Polonia</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae/rappresentanze-e-consigli-di-viaggio/polonia/svizzera-polonia.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>President Amherd visits Poland in the run-up to Polish presidency of the Council of the EU</title>
      <lead>President Viola Amherd will travel to Warsaw this week. During her visit, she will meet with Polish President Andrzej Duda on 17 October and also hold talks with the heads of Poland’s parliamentary chambers, Marshall of the Sejm Szymon Hołownia and Marshall of the Senate Małgorzata Kidawa-Błońska. Poland will assume the rotating presidency of the Council of the EU in the first half of 2025.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;With a view to Poland assuming the presidency of the Council of the EU at the beginning of 2025, talks during Ms Amherd’s visit will focus on bilateral relations between Switzerland and Poland, the security situation in Europe and the ongoing negotiations between Switzerland and the European Union. Other topics will include bilateral cooperation on the second Swiss contribution to selected EU member states. With overall funding of CHF 320.1 million, Poland will be the largest beneficiary of the 15 countries receiving funding from the second Swiss contribution. This cooperation programme aims to reach socially disadvantaged regions while also supporting research and innovation at Polish universities. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Switzerland and Poland maintain close political, economic and cultural ties. Poland is Switzerland’s most important Central European partner, with a trade volume of CHF 6 billion (2023, excluding gold) and Swiss direct investment of around CHF 6.4 billion (2022). Talks on education, research, innovation and migration have intensified between the two countries as well. Switzerland and Poland also work closely in multilateral contexts such as the World Bank and the International Monetary Fund (IMF).&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>DDPS Communications +41 58 464 50 58 kommunikation@gs-vbs.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="280452">
        <title>Bilateral relations Switzerland–Poland</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/fdfa/representations-and-travel-advice/poland/switzerland-poland.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="33">
        <name lang="de">Bundespräsident/-in</name>
        <name lang="fr">Président/e de la Confédération</name>
        <name lang="it">Presidente della Confederazione</name>
        <name lang="en">President of the Swiss Confederation</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="34">
        <name lang="de">Europa</name>
        <name lang="fr">Europe</name>
        <name lang="it">Europa</name>
        <name lang="en">Europe</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="40">
        <name lang="de">Sicherheit</name>
        <name lang="fr">Sécurité</name>
        <name lang="it">Sicurezza</name>
        <name lang="en">Security</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
