<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="102881" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2024-10-23</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="yes" id="703" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>701</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Staatssekretariat für Wirtschaft</name>
      <name lang="fr">Secrétariat d'Etat à l'économie</name>
      <name lang="it">Segreteria di Stato dell'economia</name>
      <name lang="en">State Secretariat for Economic Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.seco.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.seco.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.seco.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.seco.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@seco.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@seco.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@seco.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@seco.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="yes" id="1080" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>701</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Staatssekretariat für Bildung, Forschung und Innovation</name>
      <name lang="fr">Secrétariat d'Etat à la formation, à la recherche et à l'innovation</name>
      <name lang="it">Segreteria di Stato per la formazione, la ricerca e l'innovazione</name>
      <name lang="en">State Secretariat for Education, Research and Innovation</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.sbfi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.sbfi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.sbfi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.sbfi.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@sbfi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@sbfi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@sbfi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@sbfi.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="1070" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>1070</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Der Bundesrat</name>
      <name lang="fr">Conseil fédéral</name>
      <name lang="it">Il Consiglio federale</name>
      <name lang="en">The Federal Council</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.admin.ch/gov/de/start.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.admin.ch/gov/fr/accueil.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.admin.ch/gov/it/pagina-iniziale.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.admin.ch/gov/en/start.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="701" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>701</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Wirtschaft, Bildung und Forschung</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'économie, de la formation et de la recherche</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'economia, della formazione e della ricerca</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Economic Affairs, Education and Research</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="yes" id="1060" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>601</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Staatssekretariat für internationale Finanzfragen</name>
      <name lang="fr">Secrétariat d'Etat aux questions financières internationales</name>
      <name lang="it">Segreteria di Stato per le questioni finanziarie internazionali</name>
      <name lang="en">State Secretariat for International Financial Matters</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.sif.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.sif.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.sif.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.sif.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@sif.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@sif.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@sif.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@sif.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="701">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Wirtschaft, Bildung und Forschung</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'économie, de la formation et de la recherche</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'economia, della formazione e della ricerca</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Economic Affairs, Education and Research</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <department id="1070">
      <name lang="de">Der Bundesrat</name>
      <name lang="fr">Conseil fédéral</name>
      <name lang="it">Il Consiglio federale</name>
      <name lang="en">The Federal Council</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.admin.ch/gov/de/start.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.admin.ch/gov/fr/accueil.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.admin.ch/gov/it/pagina-iniziale.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.admin.ch/gov/en/start.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <department id="601">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Finanzdepartement</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des finances</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale delle finanze</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Finance</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.efd.admin.ch/de</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.efd.admin.ch/fr</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.efd.admin.ch/it</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.efd.admin.ch/en</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Die Schweiz an der Jahrestagung 2024 des Internationalen Währungsfonds und der Weltbank sowie am Treffen der G20-Finanzministerinnen und -minister in Washington</title>
      <lead>Bundesrätin Karin Keller-Sutter und Bundesrat Guy Parmelin, begleitet von Nationalbankpräsident Martin Schlegel, nehmen vom 23. bis 25. Oktober 2024 an der Jahrestagung des Internationalen Währungsfonds (IWF) und der Weltbank in Washington teil. Während der Tagung findet auch ein Treffen der G20-Finanzministerinnen und -minister sowie der Notenbankgouverneurinnen und -gouverneure statt. Zudem wird die Schweizer Delegation die Tagung für bilaterale Treffen nutzen.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Im Zentrum der Jahrestagung stehen globale wirtschaftliche und entwicklungspolitische Herausforderungen. Die Mittelausstattung und Kreditvergabe sowie die Gouvernanz und die Ausrichtung des IWF und der Weltbank sind ebenfalls zentrale Themen. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Angesichts finanzpolitischer Herausforderungen sind gesunde Staatsfinanzen und ein offener wirtschaftlicher Austausch mit klaren Regeln zentral für die Schweiz. Von grosser Bedeutung ist auch ein widerstandsfähiges Finanzsystem. Deshalb setzt sich die Schweiz dafür ein, dass systemrelevante Banken im Krisenfall abgewickelt werden können. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Aus Sicht der Schweiz soll der IWF auf eine Finanz-, Geld- und Wirtschaftspolitik fokussieren, die nachhaltig Wachstum und Stabilität begünstigt. Die Schweiz tritt ausserdem ein für massvolle IWF-Finanzhilfen, die von Reformprogrammen begleitet werden. Dabei betont die Schweiz ihr langjähriges finanzielles Engagement zugunsten ärmerer Länder. Die Schweiz begrüsst ferner den Beitritt des Fürstentums Liechtenstein zum IWF und zur von ihr geleiteten Stimmrechtsgruppe.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Die Schweiz begrüsst die laufenden Reformen des Finanz- und Geschäftsmodells der Weltbank, um die Wirksamkeit ihrer Aktivitäten zu erhöhen. Sie setzt sich dafür ein, dass die Weltbank ihre Aktivitäten systematisch mit anderen Entwicklungsakteuren koordiniert sowie Umwelt-, Sozial- und Gouvernanzstandards in ihren Projekten konsequent umsetzt. Weiter unterstützt die Schweiz Initiativen, die privates Kapital mobilisieren, um die nachhaltigen Entwicklungsziele zu erreichen.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Im Vorfeld der Tagung findet ein G20-Treffen der Finanzministerinnen und -minister sowie der Notenbankgouverneurinnen und -gouverneure statt. Die Schweiz wird sich dort unter anderem für die Stärkung der globalen Finanzstabilität sowie für Rechtssicherheit und gleich lange Spiesse bei internationalen Steuerregeln einsetzen.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Zudem erneuert Bundesrat Parmelin in Washington D.C. ein Memorandum of Understanding (MoU) zwischen der Schweiz und den USA im Bereich der Berufsbildung.&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Kommunikation EFD, Tel. +41 58 462 60 33, kommunikation@gs-efd.admin.ch Kommunikation WBF, Tel. +41 58 462 20 07, info@gs-wbf.admin.ch Kommunikation EDA, Tel. +41 58 460 55 55, kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>La Suisse aux assemblées annuelles 2024 du FMI et du GBM ainsi qu’à la réunion des ministres des finances du G20 à Washington</title>
      <lead>Du 23 au 25 octobre 2024, les conseillers fédéraux Karin Keller-Sutter et Guy Parmelin et le président de la direction générale de la Banque nationale suisse, Martin Schlegel, participeront aux assemblées annuelles du Fonds monétaire international (FMI) et du Groupe de la Banque mondiale (GBM) à Washington. À cette occasion, ils rencontreront les ministres des finances et les gouverneurs des banques centrales des États membres du G20. La délégation suisse profitera aussi de ce rassemblement pour mener des entretiens bilatéraux.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Les assemblées annuelles porteront sur les défis qui se posent à l’échelle mondiale en matière d’économie et de développement. Parmi les thèmes centraux figureront également la dotation de fonds, l’octroi de crédits, la gouvernance et l’orientation du FMI et de la Banque mondiale. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Face aux défis de la politique budgétaire, la Suisse estime qu’il faut des finances publiques saines et des échanges économiques ouverts qui obéissent à des règles claires. En outre, il est crucial que le système financier soit résistant. C’est pourquoi la Suisse milite pour que les banques d’importance systémique puissent être liquidées si elles se trouvent en difficulté. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Par ailleurs, la Suisse invite le FMI à poursuivre une politique budgétaire, monétaire et économique qui favorise la croissance et la stabilité sur le long terme. Elle plaide également pour qu’il octroie des aides financières mesurées, assorties de mesures de réforme, en soulignant à cet égard son engagement financier de longue date en faveur des pays pauvres. Enfin, elle se réjouit de l’adhésion au FMI de la Principauté de Liechtenstein et de son entrée dans le groupe de vote qu’elle dirige.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;La Suisse se félicite des réformes relatives au modèle financier et à la stratégie commerciale de la Banque mondiale, visant à faire en sorte que celle-ci soit plus efficace dans son action. Elle s’engage afin que la Banque mondiale coordonne systématiquement ses activités avec les autres acteurs du développement et qu’elle applique rigoureusement les normes sociales et environnementales ainsi que les normes de gouvernance dans le cadre de ses projets. Elle apporte également son soutien à des initiatives visant à mobiliser des fonds privés à l’appui de la réalisation des objectifs de développement durable.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Une rencontre des ministres des finances et des gouverneurs des banques centrales des États membres du G20 aura lieu en amont des assemblées annuelles. La Suisse plaidera notamment pour le renforcement de la stabilité financière mondiale, la sécurité juridique et l’égalité de traitement en matière de réglementation fiscale internationale.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Enfin, le conseiller fédéral Guy Parmelin reconduira à Washington un mémorandum d’entente entre la Suisse et les États-Unis portant sur la formation professionnelle.&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Communication DFF, tél. +41 58 462 60 33, kommunikation@gs-efd.admin.ch Communication DEFR, tél. +41 58 462 20 07, info@gs-wbf.admin.ch Communication DFAE, tél. +41 58 460 55 55, kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>La Svizzera partecipa alla riunione annuale del Fondo monetario internazionale e della Banca mondiale nonché all’incontro dei ministri delle finanze del G20 a Washington</title>
      <lead>La consigliera federale Karin Keller-Sutter, il consigliere federale Guy Parmelin e il presidente della Banca nazionale svizzera, Martin Schlegel, parteciperanno alla riunione annuale del Fondo monetario internazionale (FMI) e della Banca mondiale che si terrà a Washington dal 23 al 25 ottobre 2024. Durante il vertice avrà luogo anche l’incontro tra i ministri delle finanze del G20 e i governatori delle banche centrali. Infine, la delegazione svizzera approfitterà dell’evento per svolgere incontri bilaterali.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Fra i temi all’ordine del giorno della riunione annuale figurano le sfide dell’economia e della politica di sviluppo a livello globale. Anche la dotazione di fondi e la concessione di crediti nonché la governance e l’orientamento del FMI e della Banca mondiale rientrano tra i temi centrali del vertice. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Alla luce delle sfide di carattere politico-finanziario, per la Svizzera sono essenziali finanze pubbliche sane e scambi commerciali aperti con regole chiare. Anche un sistema finanziario resiliente è di grande importanza. Per questo motivo la Svizzera si adopera affinché sia possibile liquidare le banche di rilevanza sistemica nel caso dovessero ritrovarsi in condizioni di crisi. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Secondo la Svizzera, il FMI deve concentrarsi su una politica finanziaria, monetaria ed economica che incoraggi la crescita e la stabilità sostenibili. La Svizzera è inoltre favorevole alla concessione di aiuti finanziari cospicui da parte del FMI, che si fondino su piani di riforma. In questo contesto sottolinea il suo impegno finanziario pluriennale a favore dei Paesi più poveri. La Svizzera accoglie con favore anche l’adesione del Principato del Liechtenstein al FMI nonché al gruppo di voto diretto dalla Svizzera.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;La Svizzera appoggia le riforme in corso per migliorare i modelli finanziari e aziendali della Banca mondiale, al fine di accrescere l’efficacia delle sue attività. Si impegna affinché la Banca mondiale coordini sistematicamente le sue attività con gli altri attori attivi nel settore dello sviluppo e applichi in modo coerente gli standard ambientali, sociali e di governance nell’ambito dei propri progetti. Oltre a ciò, sostiene iniziative che mobilitano capitale privato per raggiungere gli obiettivi di sviluppo sostenibile.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;La riunione sarà preceduta da un incontro tra i ministri delle finanze del G20 e i governatori delle banche centrali. Tra le questioni che la Svizzera sosterrà in tale sede vi sono il rafforzamento della stabilità finanziaria globale, la certezza del diritto e la promozione di condizioni paritarie nelle regolamentazioni fiscali internazionali.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Inoltre, il consigliere federale Guy Parmelin rinnoverà a Washington D.C. il Memorandum d’intesa (MoU) tra la Svizzera e gli Stati Uniti nel settore della formazione professionale.&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Comunicazione DFF, tel. +41 58 462 60 33, kommunikation@gs-efd.admin.ch Comunicazione DEFR, tel. +41 58 462 20 07, info@gs-wbf.admin.ch Comunicazione DFAE, tel. +41 58 460 55 55, kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Switzerland at 2024 IMF and World Bank Annual Meetings and G20 Finance Ministers Meeting in Washington</title>
      <lead>Federal Councillors Karin Keller-Sutter and Guy Parmelin, accompanied by Martin Schlegel, Chairman of the Governing Board of the Swiss National Bank, will attend the Annual Meetings of the International Monetary Fund (IMF) and the World Bank in Washington from 23 to 25 October 2024. A meeting of G20 finance ministers and central bank governors will also take place during the Annual Meetings. The Swiss delegation will additionally use the event for bilateral talks.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;The Annual Meetings will focus on global economic and development policy challenges. The funding, lending, governance and orientation of the IMF and World Bank are likewise key themes on the agenda. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;In view of the fiscal policy challenges, healthy public finances and an open economic exchange with clear rules are crucial for Switzerland. A resilient financial system is also of prime importance. That is why Switzerland is committed to ensuring the resolution of systemically important banks in the event of a crisis. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;In Switzerland's view, the IMF should focus on financial, monetary and economic policies that promote sustainable growth and stability. Moreover, it advocates moderate IMF financial assistance that is accompanied by reform programmes, while underlining its longstanding financial commitment to low-income countries. Furthermore, Switzerland welcomes the Principality of Liechtenstein's accession to the IMF and to the Swiss-led constituency.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Switzerland welcomes the ongoing reform to the World Bank's financial and business model, which is designed to increase the effectiveness of its activities. It is committed to ensuring that the World Bank systematically coordinates its activities with other development players and consistently implements environmental, social and governance standards in its projects. Furthermore, Switzerland supports initiatives that mobilise private capital to achieve the Sustainable Development Goals.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;A meeting of G20 finance ministers and central bank governors will take place in the run-up to the Annual Meetings. During this, Switzerland will advocate the strengthening of global financial stability, as well as legal certainty and a level playing field with respect to international tax rules, among other things.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;In addition, while in Washington D.C., Federal Councillor Parmelin will renew a memorandum of understanding (MoU) between Switzerland and the United States in the area of vocational education and training.&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>FDF Communications, tel. +41 58 462 60 33, kommunikation@gs-efd.admin.ch EAER Communications, tel. +41 58 462 20 07, info@gs-wbf.admin.ch FDFA Communication, tel. +41 58 460 55 55, kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <offers>
      <offer id="291" org-id="1060">
        <name lang="de">Wirtschaft, Währung, Finanzplatz</name>
        <name lang="fr">Economie, monnaie, place financière</name>
        <name lang="it">Economia, Moneta, Piazza finanziaria</name>
        <name lang="en">Economic, Monetary and Financial Affairs</name>
      </offer>
    </offers>
    <keywords>
      <keyword id="126" org-id="1060">
        <name lang="de">Finanzplatz Schweiz</name>
        <name lang="fr">Place financière suisse</name>
        <name lang="it">Piazza finanziaria svizzera</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland as a financial centre</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="123" org-id="1060">
        <name lang="de">IWF und Weltbank</name>
        <name lang="fr">FMI et Banque mondiale</name>
        <name lang="it">FMI e Banca mondiale</name>
        <name lang="en">IMF and World Bank</name>
      </keyword>
    </keywords>
    <topics>
      <topic id="35">
        <name lang="de">Finanzplatz</name>
        <name lang="fr">Place financière</name>
        <name lang="it">Piazza finanziaria</name>
        <name lang="en">Financial Centre</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="44">
        <name lang="de">Steuern</name>
        <name lang="fr">Impôts</name>
        <name lang="it">Imposte</name>
        <name lang="en">Taxation</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="47">
        <name lang="de">Wirtschaft</name>
        <name lang="fr">Économie</name>
        <name lang="it">Economia</name>
        <name lang="en">Economic Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
