<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="102828" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2024-10-17</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="yes" id="502" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>501</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Generalsekretariat VBS</name>
      <name lang="fr">Secrétariat général du DDPS</name>
      <name lang="it">Segreteria generale del DDPS</name>
      <name lang="en">General Secretariat DDPS</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.vbs.admin.ch/</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.vbs.admin.ch/</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.vbs.admin.ch/</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.vbs.admin.ch/</www>
      <email lang="de">postmaster.vbs@gs-vbs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">postmaster.vbs@gs-vbs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">postmaster.vbs@gs-vbs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">postmaster.vbs@gs-vbs.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="201" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>201</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="505" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>501</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Gruppe Verteidigung</name>
      <name lang="fr">Groupement de la Défense</name>
      <name lang="it">Aggruppamento Difesa</name>
      <name lang="en">Defence</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.vtg.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.vtg.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.vtg.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.vtg.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@vtg.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@vtg.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@vtg.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@vtg.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="1102" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>501</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Staatssekretariat für Sicherheitspolitik</name>
      <name lang="fr">Secrétariat d’État à la politique de sécurité</name>
      <name lang="it">Segreteria di Stato della politica di sicurezza</name>
      <name lang="en">State Secretariat for Security Policy</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.sepos.admin.ch/de</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.sepos.admin.ch/fr</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.sepos.admin.ch/it</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.sepos.admin.ch/de</www>
      <email lang="de"/>
      <email lang="fr"/>
      <email lang="it"/>
      <email lang="en"/>
    </originator>
    <department id="501">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Verteidigung, Bevölkerungsschutz und Sport</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de la défense, de la protection de la population et des sports</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale della difesa, della protezione della popolazione e dello sport</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Defence, Civil Protection and Sports</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.vbs.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.vbs.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.vbs.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.vbs.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@gs-vbs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@gs-vbs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@gs-vbs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@gs-vbs.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <department id="201">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Humanitäre Minenräumung: Bund geht umfassende Partnerschaft mit ukrainischem Katastrophenschutz und Schweizer Minenräumungsfirma ein</title>
      <lead>Um die Gefahr zu vermindern, die in der Ukraine von Minen und anderen Kampfmitteln ausgeht, unterstützt der Bund den zivilen ukrainischen Dienst für Katastrophenhilfe. Eine Partnerschaft mit dem Schweizer Unternehmen Global Clearance Solutions (GCS) sieht vor, drei Minenräumsysteme in die Ukraine zu liefern und gleichzeitig den ukrainischen Partnern ein umfangreiches Ausbildungs-, Mentoring- und Logistikpaket anzubieten. Der Bund übernimmt die Kosten dieses Gesamtpakets in Höhe von 4.6 Millionen Franken. Damit unterstreicht er die Bedeutung der humanitären Minenräumung für den Wiederaufbau des Landes.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Wo Minen oder andere Kampfmittel im Boden vermutet werden, ist die Sicherheit der Zivilbevölkerung gefährdet, landwirtschaftliche Arbeit eingeschränkt und ein Wiederaufbau des Landes nicht möglich. In der Ukraine wird die Fläche des Gebietes, das möglicherweise von Minen und anderen Kampfmitteln belastet ist, auf 139'000 Quadratkilometer geschätzt. Das entspricht rund 3,5 Mal der Fläche der Schweiz. Die humanitäre Minenräumung in der Ukraine ist deshalb eine Priorität der Schweiz. Mit dem Schweizer Unternehmen Global Clearance Solutions (GCS) hat der Bund einen Vertrag zur Lieferung von drei Minenräumsystemen in die Ukraine abgeschlossen. Empfängerin ist der zivile ukrainische Dienst für Katastrophenhilfe (State Emergency Service of Ukraine, SESU). Die Lieferung inklusive des Trainings- und Mentorenprogramm hat einen Umfang von 4.6 Millionen Franken.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Das Projekt verfolgt das Ziel, die Kapazitäten der zivilen ukrainischen Behörden zu stärken. Damit sollen Räumarbeiten in der humanitären Minenräumung in der Ukraine sicherer, effizienter und wirksamer durchgeführt werden können. Neben der Lieferung der drei Minenräumsystemen umfasst der Vertrag deshalb ein umfangreiches Ausbildungs-, Mentoring- und Logistikpaket. GCS verfügt in der Ukraine über ein eigenes Wartungszentrum und ein Operations-Team. Damit können umfangreiche Schulungen durchführt und ein nachhaltiger und effizienter Einsatz der Räumsysteme gewährleistet werden.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Finanziert wird die Partnerschaft und Lieferung der Minenräumsysteme von den 100 Millionen Franken, die der Bundesrat am 29. September 2023 zur Unterstützung der humanitären Minenräumung in der Ukraine zur Verfügung gestellt hat. Dieser Betrag wird zu gleichen Teilen vom VBS und vom EDA bereitgestellt. Die Schweiz stellt damit ihre Expertise zur Bewältigung dieser immensen humanitären Herausforderung zur Verfügung. Ausserdem führt die Schweiz unter der Leitung von Bundespräsidentin Viola Amherd und Bundesrat Ignazio Cassis gemeinsam mit der Ukraine am 17. und 18. Oktober 2024 in Lausanne die Ukraine Mine Action Conference durch. Dort wird die Bedeutung der Minenräumung für den Wiederaufbau der Ukraine thematisiert.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Bei der humanitären Minenräumung in der Ukraine arbeitet der Bund eng mit dem Genfer Internationalen Zentrum für humanitäre Minenräumung (GICHD) zusammen. Das GICHD unterstützt die ukrainischen Behörden bei der Ausarbeitung eines nationalen Minenräumprogramms. Ausserdem unterstützt der Bund die Minenräumarbeiten der Fondation suisse de déminage (FSD) vor Ort. Vor einem Jahr hat das VBS eine ferngesteuerte Minenräummaschine der Schweizer Stiftung Digger beschafft und der Ukraine übergeben.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Kommunikation VBS +41 58 464 50 58 kommunikation@gs-vbs.admin.ch Kommunikation EDA +41 58 460 55 55 Global Clearance Solutions +41 55 511 15 00 media@gcs.ch</contact>
      <link id="280771">
        <title>Ukraine Mine Action Conference UMAC2024</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home/das-eda/aktuell/dossiers/krieg-gegen-ukraine/umac2024.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="280775">
        <title>Rede von Bundespräsidentin Viola Amherd</title>
        <uri>https://www.admin.ch/gov/de/start/dokumentation/medienmitteilungen.msg-id-102827.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Déminage humanitaire : la Confédération conclut un partenariat avec le service ukrainien d’aide en cas de catastrophe et une entreprise suisse de déminage</title>
      <lead>Afin de réduire le danger que représentent les mines et autres moyens de combat en Ukraine, la Confédération soutient le service civil ukrainien d’aide en cas de catastrophe. Un partenariat avec l’entreprise suisse Global Clearance Solutions (GCS) a pour but de fournir trois systèmes de déminage aux partenaires ukrainiens avec une offre regroupant aussi des formations, du mentorat et un volet logistique. La Confédération prend en charge les coûts de l’ensemble à hauteur de 4,6 millions de francs, mettant ainsi en évidence l’importance du déminage humanitaire pour la reconstruction du pays.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;La présence éventuelle de mines ou d’autres moyens de combat enfouis dans le sol menace la sécurité de la population, limite le travail agricole et rend la reconstruction du pays impossible. En Ukraine, on estime à 139 000 kilomètres carrés le territoire susceptible d’être pollué par des mines et d’autres moyens de combat, ce qui correspond à environ 3,5 fois la superficie de la Suisse. Le déminage humanitaire en Ukraine est donc une priorité pour notre pays. La Confédération a conclu un contrat avec GCS pour la livraison de trois systèmes de déminage en Ukraine destinés au service civil ukrainien d’aide en cas de catastrophe (State Emergency Service of Ukraine, SESU). Le montant prévu pour cette offre, qui comprend également un programme d’entraînement et de mentorat, s’élève à 4,6 millions de francs.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Le projet a pour objectif de renforcer les capacités des autorités civiles ukrainiennes et de rendre ainsi les opérations de déminage en Ukraine plus sûres, plus rapides et plus efficaces. Outre la livraison des trois systèmes de déminage, le contrat comprend des formations, du mentorat et un volet logistique. GCS dispose de son propre centre de maintenance en Ukraine et d’une équipe opérationnelle, ce qui permet de mettre sur pied des formations approfondies et de garantir une utilisation durable et efficace des systèmes de déminage.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Le partenariat et la livraison de ces systèmes seront financés avec les 100 millions de francs mis à disposition par le Conseil fédéral le 29 septembre 2023 pour soutenir le déminage humanitaire en Ukraine. Ce montant est fourni à parts égales par le DDPS et le DFAE. La Suisse propose ainsi son expertise pour relever cet immense défi humanitaire. De plus, les 17 et 18 octobre 2024, la Suisse organisera à Lausanne l’Ukraine Mine Action Conference, aux côtés de l’Ukraine et sous la direction de la présidente de la Confédération Viola Amherd et du conseiller fédéral Ignazio Cassis. Cette conférence sera centrée sur l’importance du déminage pour la reconstruction de l’Ukraine.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Pour le déminage humanitaire en Ukraine, la Confédération travaille en étroite collaboration avec le Centre international de déminage humanitaire à Genève (GICHD). Le GICHD aide les autorités ukrainiennes à élaborer un programme national de déminage. En outre, la Confédération soutient sur place les opérations de la Fondation suisse de déminage (FSD). Il y a un an, le DDPS a fait l’acquisition d’un engin de déminage télécommandé de la fondation suisse Digger qu’il a remis à l’Ukraine.&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Communication DDPS +41 58 464 50 58 kommunikation@gs-vbs.admin.ch Communication DFAE +41 58 460 55 55 Global Clearance Solutions +41 55 511 15 00 media@gcs.ch</contact>
      <link id="280772">
        <title>Ukraine Mine Action Conference UMAC2024</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae/dfae/aktuell/dossiers/krieg-gegen-ukraine/umac2024.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="280776">
        <title>Discours de la présidente de la Confédération Viola Amherd</title>
        <uri>https://www.admin.ch/gov/fr/accueil/documentation/communiques.msg-id-102827.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Sminamento umanitario: la Confederazione avvia un ampio partenariato con il servizio ucraino di protezione dalle catastrofi e un’azienda di sminamento svizzera</title>
      <lead>Per ridurre il pericolo derivante dalle mine e da altri ordigni bellici in Ucraina, la Confederazione sostiene il servizio civile ucraino per l’aiuto in caso di catastrofe. Un partenariato con l’azienda svizzera Global Clearance Solutions (GCS) prevede la fornitura di tre sistemi di sminamento in Ucraina e offre ai partner ucraini un pacchetto completo di formazione, mentoring e logistica. La Confederazione si assume i costi dell’intero pacchetto, pari a 4,6 milioni di franchi, sottolineando così l’importanza dello sminamento umanitario per la ricostruzione del Paese. </lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Nei luoghi dove si sospetta la presenza nel suolo di mine o altri ordigni bellici, la sicurezza della popolazione civile è minacciata, il lavoro agricolo è limitato e la ricostruzione del Paese è impossibile. Si stima che 139 000 chilometri quadrati del territorio ucraino siano contaminati da mine e altri ordigni bellici, una superficie pari a circa 3,5 volte quella della Svizzera. Per questo motivo, per la Svizzera lo sminamento umanitario in Ucraina è una priorità. La Confederazione ha stipulato un contratto con l’azienda svizzera Global Clearance Solutions (GCS) per la fornitura di tre sistemi di sminamento all’Ucraina. Il destinatario è il servizio civile ucraino per l’aiuto in caso di catastrofe (State Emergency Service of Ukraine, SESU). La fornitura, compreso il programma di formazione e di mentoring, ha un costo pari a 4,6 milioni di franchi.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Il progetto ha l’obiettivo di rafforzare le capacità delle autorità civili ucraine. In questo modo i lavori di sgombero relativi allo sminamento umanitario in Ucraina potranno essere svolti in modo più sicuro, efficiente ed efficace. Oltre alla fornitura dei tre sistemi di sminamento, il contratto prevede un pacchetto completo di formazione, mentoring e logistica. L’azienda GCS dispone di un proprio centro di manutenzione e di un team operativo in Ucraina. Ciò consente di svolgere formazioni approfondite e garantisce un impiego più sostenibile e più efficiente del sistema di sgombero.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Il partenariato e la fornitura dei sistemi di sminamento saranno finanziati dai 100 milioni di franchi che il Consiglio federale ha messo a disposizione il 29 settembre 2023 per sostenere lo sminamento umanitario in Ucraina. I fondi sono forniti in parti uguali da DDPS e DFAE. La Svizzera mette inoltre a disposizione le proprie competenze per affrontare questa immensa sfida umanitaria. Inoltre il 17 e 18 ottobre 2024 la Svizzera, sotto la direzione della presidente della Confederazione Viola Amherd e del consigliere federale Ignazio Cassis, organizza insieme all’Ucraina l’Ukraine Mine Action Conference a Losanna. In tale occasione sarà tematizzata l’importanza dello sminamento umanitario per la ricostruzione dell’Ucraina. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Nell’ambito dello sminamento umanitario in Ucraina, la Confederazione collabora strettamente con il centro internazionale di sminamento umanitario di Ginevra (GICHD). Il GICHD sostiene le autorità ucraine nell’elaborazione di un programma nazionale di sminamento. La Confederazione sostiene inoltre i lavori di sminamento della Fondation suisse de déminage (FSD) in loco. Un anno fa il DDPS ha acquistato un veicolo di sminamento telecomandato dalla fondazione svizzera Digger e l’ha consegnato all’Ucraina. &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Comunicazione DDPS +41 58 464 50 58 kommunikation@gs-vbs.admin.ch Comunicazione DFAE +41 58 460 55 55 Global Clearance Solutions +41 55 511 15 00 media@gcs.ch</contact>
      <link id="280773">
        <title>Ukraine Mine Action Conference UMAC2024</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae/dfae/aktuell/dossiers/krieg-gegen-ukraine/umac2024.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="280777">
        <title>Discorso della presidente della Confederazione Viola Amherd</title>
        <uri>https://www.admin.ch/gov/it/pagina-iniziale/documentazione/comunicati-stampa.msg-id-102827.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Humanitarian mine clearance: Confederation establishes comprehensive partnership with Ukraine’s civil protection service and Swiss mine clearance company</title>
      <lead>In order to reduce the danger posed by mines and other explosive ordnance in Ukraine, the Swiss government is supporting Ukraine’s civil protection service through a partnership with the Swiss company Global Clearance Solutions (GCS). The partnership involves supplying three mine clearance systems to Ukraine alongside a comprehensive training, mentoring and logistics package. The package, which amounts to CHF 4.6 million, is being funded by the federal government and underlines the importance of humanitarian mine clearance for the country’s recovery.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Mines and other explosive ordnance in the ground pose a danger to the civilian population, restrict agricultural work and hinder the reconstruction of a country. In Ukraine, around 139,000 square kilometres of land are estimated to be contaminated by mines and other explosive ordnance. That is equivalent to about three and a half times the surface area of Switzerland. Humanitarian mine clearance in Ukraine is therefore a priority for Switzerland. For that reason, the federal government has signed a contract with the Swiss company Global Clearance Solutions (GCS) for the delivery of three mine clearance systems to the State Emergency Service of Ukraine (SESU). The package, which includes a training and mentoring programme, is worth CHF 4.6 million.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The project aims to strengthen the capacities of the Ukrainian civil authorities so that humanitarian demining operations can be carried out more safely, efficiently and effectively. In addition to the delivery of the three demining systems, the contract includes an extensive training, mentoring and logistics package. GCS has its own maintenance centre and operations team in Ukraine, enabling the company to provide extensive training and deploy the demining systems sustainably and efficiently.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The partnership and the demining systems are being financed out of the CHF 100 million that the Federal Council made available on 29 September 2023 to support humanitarian mine clearance in Ukraine. The total amount will be funded equally by the DDPS and the FDFA. Through this support package, Switzerland is providing its expertise to help overcome an immense humanitarian challenge. In addition, Switzerland, under the lead of President Viola Amherd and Federal Councillor Ignazio Cassis, is jointly hosting the Ukraine Mine Action Conference with Ukraine in Lausanne on 17 and 18 October. The importance of mine clearance for Ukraine’s recovery will be discussed at the conference.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The federal government is working closely with the Geneva International Centre for Humanitarian Demining (GICHD) on humanitarian mine clearance in Ukraine. The GICHD is supporting the Ukrainian authorities in developing a national demining programme. In addition, the federal government is supporting the demining work of the Swiss Foundation for Mine Action (FSD) on the ground in Ukraine. A year ago, the DDPS presented Ukraine with a remote-controlled demining machine from the Swiss DIGGER Foundation.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>DDPS Communications +41 58 464 50 58 kommunikation@gs-vbs.admin.ch FDFA Communications +41 58 460 55 55 Global Clearance Solutions +41 55 511 15 00 media@gcs.ch</contact>
      <link id="280774">
        <title>Ukraine Mine Action Conference UMAC2024</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/fdfa/fdfa/aktuell/dossiers/krieg-gegen-ukraine/umac2024.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="280778">
        <title>Address by President Viola Amherd</title>
        <uri>https://www.admin.ch/gov/en/start/documentation/media-releases.msg-id-102827.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <keywords>
      <keyword id="1011" org-id="502">
        <name lang="de">Dossier Ukraine</name>
        <name lang="fr">Dossier Ukraine</name>
        <name lang="it">Dossier Ucraina</name>
        <name lang="en">Dossier Ukraine</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="5981" org-id="502">
        <name lang="de">Dossier Departementschef</name>
        <name lang="fr">Dossier Departementschef</name>
        <name lang="it">Dossier Departementschef</name>
        <name lang="en">Dossier Departementschef</name>
      </keyword>
    </keywords>
    <topics>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
