<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="102638" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2024-10-01</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="1102" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>501</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Staatssekretariat für Sicherheitspolitik</name>
      <name lang="fr">Secrétariat d’État à la politique de sécurité</name>
      <name lang="it">Segreteria di Stato della politica di sicurezza</name>
      <name lang="en">State Secretariat for Security Policy</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.sepos.admin.ch/de</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.sepos.admin.ch/fr</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.sepos.admin.ch/it</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.sepos.admin.ch/de</www>
      <email lang="de"/>
      <email lang="fr"/>
      <email lang="it"/>
      <email lang="en"/>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="505" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>501</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Gruppe Verteidigung</name>
      <name lang="fr">Groupement de la Défense</name>
      <name lang="it">Aggruppamento Difesa</name>
      <name lang="en">Defence</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.vtg.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.vtg.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.vtg.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.vtg.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@vtg.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@vtg.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@vtg.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@vtg.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="502" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>501</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Generalsekretariat VBS</name>
      <name lang="fr">Secrétariat général du DDPS</name>
      <name lang="it">Segreteria generale del DDPS</name>
      <name lang="en">General Secretariat DDPS</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.vbs.admin.ch/</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.vbs.admin.ch/</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.vbs.admin.ch/</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.vbs.admin.ch/</www>
      <email lang="de">postmaster.vbs@gs-vbs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">postmaster.vbs@gs-vbs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">postmaster.vbs@gs-vbs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">postmaster.vbs@gs-vbs.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="501">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Verteidigung, Bevölkerungsschutz und Sport</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de la défense, de la protection de la population et des sports</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale della difesa, della protezione della popolazione e dello sport</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Defence, Civil Protection and Sports</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.vbs.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.vbs.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.vbs.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.vbs.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@gs-vbs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@gs-vbs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@gs-vbs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@gs-vbs.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Der Staatssekretär für Sicherheitspolitik und der Chef der Armee nehmen am Warsaw Security Forum teil</title>
      <lead>Am 1. und 2. Oktober 2024 tauschen sich auf dem Warsaw Security Forum (WSF) Expertinnen und Experten aus Europa und Nordamerika über aktuelle sicherheitspolitische Entwicklungen und Herausforderungen aus. Die Schweiz wird durch Markus Mäder, Staatssekretär für Sicherheitspolitik, und Korpskommandant Thomas Süssli, Chef der Armee, vertreten. </lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Als eine der grössten sicherheitspolitischen Konferenzen Europas diskutiert das WSF auch dieses Jahr viele Themen, wobei der Krieg in der Ukraine und dessen Auswirkungen auf die europäische Sicherheit im Vordergrund stehen. Zudem sollen Energiesicherheit, Klimaveränderung und Resilienz von Demokratien beleuchtet werden. Das WSF setzt auf verschiedene Diskussionsformate und bietet eine Plattform für den Austausch zwischen Regierungsvertretungen, internationalen Organisationen sowie Wissenschaft und Organisationen aus der Zivilgesellschaft. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Aktive Teilnahme und Vernetzung &lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Staatssekretär Mäder wird an einer Paneldiskussion „Different Dimensions of Total Defence“ auftreten, bei der ganzheitliche Konzepte von Sicherheit und Verteidigung und das Zusammenspiel ziviler und militärischer Instrumente im Mittelpunkt stehen. &lt;br /&gt;Zudem wird die Schweizer Delegation bilaterale Gespräche mit internationalen Amtskolleginnen und -kollegen führen, insbesondere zur sicherheitspolitischen und bilateralen Kooperation.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Mathias Volken Armeesprecher +41 58 488 90 96</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Le secrétaire d’État à la politique de sécurité et le chef de l’Armée participent au Forum de Varsovie sur la sécurité</title>
      <lead>Lors du Forum de Varsovie sur la sécurité (Warsaw Security Forum, WSF) les 1er et 2 octobre 2024, des spécialistes d’Europe et d’Amérique du Nord discuteront des développements et des défis actuels en matière de politique de sécurité. La Suisse y sera représentée par Markus Mäder, secrétaire d’État à la politique de sécurité, et par le commandant de corps Thomas Süssli, chef de l’Armée. </lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Cette année encore, le WSF, l’une des plus importantes conférences d’Europe sur la sécurité, porte sur de nombreux sujets avec, au premier plan, la guerre en Ukraine et ses répercussions sur la sécurité européenne. La sécurité énergétique, le changement climatique et la résilience des démocraties sont également au cœur des débats. Le WSF propose différents formats de discussion et une plateforme d’échange entre membres de gouvernements, organisations internationales, milieux scientifiques et organisations de la société civile. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Participation active et réseautage&lt;/h2&gt;Markus Mäder participera à une table ronde qui aura pour sujet les stratégies globales de sécurité et de défense et la combinaison des instruments civils et militaires (Different Dimensions of Total Defence).&lt;br /&gt;La délégation suisse mènera en outre des entretiens bilatéraux avec des homologues internationaux, en particulier sur la coopération bilatérale en matière de politique de sécurité. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Mathias Volken Porte-parole de l’armée +41 58 488 90 96</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Il segretario di Stato della politica di sicurezza e il capo dell’esercito partecipano al Secu-rity Forum di Varsavia</title>
      <lead>Il 1° e il 2 ottobre 2024, in occasione del Warsaw Security Forum (WSF), esperti provenienti dall’Europa e dall’America del Nord discuteranno degli sviluppi e delle sfide attuali poste dalla politica di sicurezza. La Svizzera sarà rappresentata da Markus Mäder, segretario di Stato della politica di sicurezza, e dal comandante di corpo, capo dell’esercito, Thomas Süssli. </lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Il WSF è una delle maggiori conferenze europee dedicate alla politica di sicurezza e anche quest’anno i temi all’ordine del giorno sono numerosi. In primo piano vi è comunque la guerra in Ucraina con le sue ripercussioni sulla sicurezza in Europa. In agenda vi sono inoltre la sicurezza energetica, i cambiamenti climatici e la resilienza delle democrazie. Il WSF si basa su vari formati di discussione e offre una piattaforma di scambio per le rappresentanze dei Governi, organizzazioni internazionali, il mondo scientifico e organizzazioni della società civile. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Partecipazione attiva e interconnessioni &lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Il Segretario di Stato Mäder parteciperà a una tavola rotonda intitolata «Different Dimensions of Total Defence» (Diverse dimensioni della difesa totale), incentrata sui concetti complessivi di sicurezza e di difesa e sull’interazione tra strumenti civili e militari. &lt;br /&gt;Inoltre la delegazione svizzera condurrà colloqui bilaterali con gli omologhi internazionali in particolare nell’ambito della cooperazione in materia di politica di sicurezza e bilaterale.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Mathias Volken Portavoce dell’esercito +41 58 488 90 96</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>State Secretary for Security Policy and Chief of the Armed Forces to attend Warsaw Security Forum</title>
      <lead>On 1 and 2 October, experts from Europe and North America will exchange views on current security policy developments and challenges at the Warsaw Security Forum (WSF). Switzerland will be represented at the event by Markus Mäder, State Secretary for Security Policy, and Thomas Süssli, Chief of the Armed Forces.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;The WSF is one of the largest security policy conferences in Europe. A wide range of topics will be addressed this year, in particular the war in Ukraine and its impact on European security. Emphasis will also be placed on energy security, climate change and the resilience of democracies. The WSF employs a variety of presentation formats and serves as a platform for discussions between government representatives, international organisations, academia and civil society.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Active participation and networking &lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;State Secretary Mäder will take part in a high-level panel discussion on ‘Different Dimensions of Total Defence’, which will examine holistic concepts of security and defence and the interplay between civilian and military instrument.&lt;br /&gt;The Swiss delegation will also hold bilateral talks with international counterparts on security policy and bilateral cooperation.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Mathias Volken Swiss Armed Forces Spokesperson +41 58 488 90 96</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <keywords>
      <keyword id="505" org-id="502">
        <name lang="de">Sicherheitspolitik</name>
        <name lang="fr">Politique de sécurité</name>
        <name lang="it">Politica di sicurezza</name>
        <name lang="en">Security Policy</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="1011" org-id="502">
        <name lang="de">Dossier Ukraine</name>
        <name lang="fr">Dossier Ukraine</name>
        <name lang="it">Dossier Ucraina</name>
        <name lang="en">Dossier Ukraine</name>
      </keyword>
    </keywords>
    <topics>
      <topic id="3">
        <name lang="de">Armee</name>
        <name lang="fr">Armée</name>
        <name lang="it">Esercito</name>
        <name lang="en">Armed Forces</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="34">
        <name lang="de">Europa</name>
        <name lang="fr">Europe</name>
        <name lang="it">Europa</name>
        <name lang="en">Europe</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="40">
        <name lang="de">Sicherheit</name>
        <name lang="fr">Sécurité</name>
        <name lang="it">Sicurezza</name>
        <name lang="en">Security</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
