<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="102932" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2024-10-31</pubdate>
    <blocking-period>2024-10-31</blocking-period>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="318" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>301</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Bundesamt für Statistik</name>
      <name lang="fr">Office fédéral de la statistique</name>
      <name lang="it">Ufficio federale di statistica</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Statistical Office</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.statistik.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.statistique.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.statistica.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.statistics.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@bfs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@bfs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@bfs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@bfs.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="301">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement des Innern</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'intérieur</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'interno</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Home Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Neuchâtel</city>
      <title>Starkes Wachstum der KMU im Jahr 2022</title>
      <lead>Kleine und mittlere Unternehmen (KMU) erhalten die Schweizer Wirtschaft am Leben. Im Jahr 2022 beschäftigten sie rund 3,2 Millionen Personen. Gegenüber 2021 kamen 60 000 neue Stellen hinzu. Im Zeitraum 2011–2022 stieg der Anteil der Unternehmen mit weniger als 10 Beschäftigten auf Kosten der Unternehmen mit 10 bis 49 Beschäftigten. In den tourismusorientierten Branchen entwickelte sich die Beschäftigung ab 2019 unterschiedlich. Was den Warenexport und -import angeht, schnitten die grossen KMU und jene in multinationalen Gruppen am besten ab. Dies sind einige Ergebnisse aus der Publikation «Porträt der Schweizer KMU» des Bundesamtes für Statistik (BFS). </lead>
      <text link="no">Diese Medienmitteilung und weitere Informationen zum Thema finden Sie auf der Website des BFS (siehe Link unten)</text>
      <contact>Nicolas Vallon, BFS, Sektion Wirtschaftsstruktur und -analysen, Tel.: +41 58 465 03 95, E-Mail: nicolas.vallon@bfs.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="281101">
        <title>Kompletter Text und Mediendossier</title>
        <uri>https://www.bfs.admin.ch/news/de/2024-0418</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Neuchâtel</city>
      <title>Forte croissance pour les PME en 2022</title>
      <lead>Les petites et moyennes entreprises (PME) font battre le pouls de l’économie suisse. En 2022, elles ont employé près de 3,2 millions de personnes. 60 000 emplois ont été créés entre 2021 et 2022. Si on considère l’ensemble de la période 2011-2022, la part des entreprises de moins de 10 emplois s’est accrue aux dépens des entreprises comptant 10 à 49 emplois. L’évolution de l’emploi a été contrastée pour les activités liées au tourisme depuis 2019. Sur le plan des exportations et importations de biens, elles ont été d’autant plus performantes qu’elles étaient grandes et appartenaient à un groupe. Ce sont là quelques résultats de la publication «Portrait des PME suisses» de l’Office fédéral de la statistique (OFS). </lead>
      <text link="no">Vous trouverez ce communiqué de presse et d'autres informations sur ce thème sur le site web de l'OFS (voir le lien ci-dessous)</text>
      <contact>Nicolas Vallon, OFS, Section Structure et analyses économiques, tél.: +41 58 465 03 95, e-mail: nicolas.vallon@bfs.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="281102">
        <title>Texte intégral et dossier de presse</title>
        <uri>https://www.bfs.admin.ch/news/fr/2024-0418</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Neuchâtel</city>
      <title>Forte crescita per le PMI nel 2022</title>
      <lead>Le piccole e medie imprese (PMI) sono il cuore pulsante dell’economia svizzera. Nel 2022 fornivano occupazione a quasi 3,2 milioni di persone. Tra il 2021 e il 2022 sono stati creati 60 000 impieghi. Se si considera l’intero periodo dal 2011 al 2022, la quota delle imprese con meno di 10 impieghi è aumentata a scapito di quella delle imprese con un numero di impieghi compreso tra 10 e 49. Dal 2019 l’andamento dell’occupazione per le attività legate al turismo è stato caratterizzato da sviluppi contrastanti. Sul piano delle esportazioni e importazioni di beni, le PMI che hanno realizzato le performance migliori sono state quelle più grandi e facenti capo a un gruppo. Questi sono alcuni dei risultati della pubblicazione sul profilo delle PMI svizzere edita dall’Ufficio federale di statistica (UST). </lead>
      <text link="no">Il presente comunicato stampa e ulteriori informazioni sul tema sono reperibili sulla pagina Internet dell'UST (link sotto)</text>
      <contact>Nicolas Vallon, UST, sezione Struttura e analisi economiche, tel.: +41 58 465 03 95, e-mail: nicolas.vallon@bfs.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="281103">
        <title>Testo integrale e dossier per i media</title>
        <uri>https://www.bfs.admin.ch/news/it/2024-0418</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Neuchâtel</city>
      <title>Strong growth for SMEs in 2022</title>
      <lead>Small and medium-sized enterprises (SMEs) are the beating heart of the Swiss economy. In 2022, they employed almost 3.2 million people. 60 000 jobs were created between 2021 and 2022. Over the whole 2011-2022 period, the proportion of enterprises with fewer than 10 jobs increased at the expense of those with 10 to 49 jobs. Jobs in tourism-related activities have experienced mixed growth since 2019. SMEs involved in the export and import of goods performed even better when large in size and part of a group. These are some of the findings from the publication 'Portrait of Swiss SMEs' by the Federal Statistical Office (FSO). </lead>
      <text link="no">This press release and further information on this topic can be found on the FSO website (see link below)</text>
      <contact>Nicolas Vallon, FSO, Economic Structure and Analyses section, tel.: +41 58 465 03 95, email: nicolas.vallon@bfs.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="281104">
        <title>Please note that the English version only includes the release's lead</title>
        <uri>https://www.bfs.admin.ch/news/en/2024-0418</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <keywords>
      <keyword id="317.7" org-id="318">
        <name lang="de">Industrie und Dienstleistungen</name>
        <name lang="fr">Industrie et services</name>
        <name lang="it">Industria e servizi</name>
        <name lang="en">Industry and services</name>
      </keyword>
    </keywords>
    <topics>
      <topic id="43">
        <name lang="de">Statistik</name>
        <name lang="fr">Statistiques</name>
        <name lang="it">Statistica</name>
        <name lang="en">Statistics</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="47">
        <name lang="de">Wirtschaft</name>
        <name lang="fr">Économie</name>
        <name lang="it">Economia</name>
        <name lang="en">Economic Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
