<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="59683" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2015-11-27</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="810" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>801</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Bundesamt für Kommunikation</name>
      <name lang="fr">Office fédéral de la communication</name>
      <name lang="it">Ufficio federale delle comunicazioni</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Office of Communications</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.bakom.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.ofcom.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.ufcom.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.ofcom.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">media@bakom.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">media@bakom.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">media@bakom.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">media@bakom.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="801">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Umwelt, Verkehr, Energie und Kommunikation</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'environnement, des transports, de l'énergie et de la communication</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'ambiente, dei trasporti, dell'energia e delle comunicazioni</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of the Environment, Transport, Energy and Communications</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.uvek.admin.ch/uvek/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.uvek.admin.ch/uvek/fr/home.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.uvek.admin.ch/uvek/it/home.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.uvek.admin.ch/uvek/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-uvek.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-uvek.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-uvek.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-uvek.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Biel/Bienne</city>
      <title>Weltfunkkonferenz: Schweiz erreicht ihre Ziele</title>
      <lead>An der heute zu Ende gehenden Weltfunkkonferenz (WRC-15) in Genf konnten auf globaler Ebene neue Frequenzen bereitgestellt werden, um mit der Entwicklung der mobilen Breitbandkommunikation Schritt zu halten. Nach vierwöchigen Verhandlungen ist eine Einigung erzielt worden. Die Schweizer Delegation zieht eine positive Bilanz: Die vom Bundesrat festgelegten Ziele konnten erreicht werden.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;An der von der Internationalen Fernmeldeunion (ITU) organisierten Weltfunkkonferenz in Genf wurden auf globaler Ebene zusätzliche Frequenzressourcen für die mobile Breitbandkommunikation identifiziert. Diese Frequenzen können nun den Mobilfunkbetreibern in der Schweiz zur Verfügung gestellt werden. Darüber hinaus wurde die Durchführung von Studien beschlossen, damit an der nächsten Konferenz (WRC-19) neue Frequenzen für mobile Breitbandanwendungen der 5. Generation (5G) bereitgestellt werden können.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;An der Konferenz wurden ausserdem Frequenzen für die Flugüberwachung in der Zivilluftfahrt zugewiesen und die Frequenzbereiche für Anwendungen zur Erdbeobachtung erweitert. Letztere spielen eine wichtige Rolle bei der Klimaüberwachung, im Kampf gegen den Klimawandel und bei der Vorhersage von Naturkatastrophen. Schliesslich wurde an der Konferenz die Durchführung zusätzlicher Studien betreffend unbemannter Flugzeuge vorgeschlagen, deren Nutzungsbedingungen noch von der Zivilluftfahrtorganisation (ICAO) definiert werden müssen. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; Die Schweizer Delegation hat die Schlussakte unterzeichnet, mit der das Radioreglement – ein völkerrechtlicher Vertrag, in dem die Nutzung des Funkfrequenzspektrums und die Satelliten-Orbitalpositionen geregelt sind – angepasst wird. Angeführt wurde die Delegation von Philippe Horisberger, dem stellvertretenden Direktor des Bundesamtes für Kommunikation (BAKOM). Das BAKOM wird nun mit den Arbeiten zur Umsetzung der Ergebnisse der WRC-15 auf nationaler Ebene beginnen.&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Bundesamt für Kommunikation BAKOM Medienstelle, +41 58 460 55 50, media@bakom.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="144372">
        <title>ITU - Radioreglement (auf französisch und englisch verfügbar)</title>
        <uri>http://www.itu.int/fr/ITU-R/Pages/default.aspx</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="144373">
        <title>Radioreglement vom 17. November 1995</title>
        <uri>https://www.admin.ch/opc/de/classified-compilation/20053379/index.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Biel/Bienne</city>
      <title>Conférence mondiale des radiocommunications: objectifs atteints par la Suisse</title>
      <lead>La Conférence mondiale des radiocommunications (CMR-15), qui se termine aujourd'hui à Genève, a permis d'identifier de nouvelles fréquences, au niveau mondial, pour faire face au développement de la communication mobile à large bande. Un consensus s'est ainsi dégagé après quatre semaines de négociations. La délégation suisse tire un bilan positif : les objectifs fixés par le Conseil fédéral ont été atteints.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;La Conférence, organisée par l'Union internationale des télécommunications (UIT) à Genève, a permis d'identifier, au niveau mondial, des fréquences supplémentaires pour la communication mobile large bande. Ces fréquences pourront être mises à disposition des opérateurs de téléphonie mobiles en Suisse. Il a également été décidé de lancer des études afin que la prochaine Conférence (CMR-19) puisse identifier des fréquences pour les applications mobiles large bande de 5e génération (5G). &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;La Conférence a par ailleurs attribué des fréquences pour le suivi des vols de l'aviation civile. En outre, des capacités de radiocommunication supplémentaires ont été octroyées pour des applications liées à l'observation de la terre et qui jouent un rôle essentiel pour la surveillance du climat, la lutte contre les changements climatiques et la prévision de catastrophes naturelles. Enfin, la Conférence a proposé des études supplémentaires au sujet des avions sans pilotes, dont l'Organisation internationale de l'aviation civile (OACI) devra encore définir les conditions d'utilisation. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; La délégation suisse a signé les Actes finals révisant le Règlement des radiocommunications, à savoir le traité international qui régit l'utilisation du spectre des fréquences radioélectriques et les orbites des satellites. Elle était dirigée par Philippe Horisberger, directeur suppléant de l'Office fédéral de la communication (OFCOM). L'OFCOM va maintenant entamer les travaux de mise en œuvre des résultats de la CMR-15 au niveau national. &lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Office fédéral de la communication OFCOM Service de presse, +41 58 460 55 50, media@bakom.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="144368">
        <title>UIT - Règlement des radiocommunications</title>
        <uri>http://www.itu.int/fr/ITU-R/Pages/default.aspx</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="144369">
        <title>Règlement des radiocommunications du 17 novembre 1995</title>
        <uri>http://www.admin.ch/opc/fr/classified-compilation/20053379/index.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Biel/Bienne</city>
      <title>Conferenza mondiale delle radiocomunicazioni: obiettivi raggiunti per la Svizzera</title>
      <lead>La Conferenza mondiale delle radiocomunicazioni (CMR-15), che si conclude oggi a Ginevra, ha permesso di identificare nuove frequenze a livello mondiale per far fronte allo sviluppo della comunicazione mobile a banda larga. Dopo quattro settimane di negoziazioni è stato infine raggiunto un consenso. La delegazione svizzera trae un bilancio positivo: gli obiettivi prefissati dal Consiglio federale sono stati raggiunti.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;La Conferenza, organizzata dall'Unione internazionale delle telecomunicazioni (UIT) a Ginevra, ha permesso di identificare a livello mondiale frequenze supplementari per la comunicazione mobile a banda larga. Queste frequenze potranno quindi essere messe a disposizione degli operatori di radiocomunicazione mobile in Svizzera. È stato inoltre deciso di avviare studi affinché la prossima Conferenza (CMR-19) possa identificare frequenze per le applicazioni mobili a banda larga di 5a generazione (5G). &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;La Conferenza ha peraltro attribuito frequenze per il monitoraggio dei voli dell'aviazione civile. Inoltre, sono state concesse capacità di radiocomunicazione supplementari alle applicazioni legate all'osservazione terrestre, applicazioni che svolgono un ruolo determinante per il controllo continuo del clima, la lotta contro il cambiamento climatico e la prevenzione delle catastrofi naturali. Da ultimo, la Conferenza ha proposto studi complementari in merito agli aerei senza pilota, per cui l'Organizzazione dell'aviazione civile internazionale (OACI) dovrà ancora definire le condizioni di utilizzazione. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; La delegazione svizzera ha firmato gli Atti finali relativi alla revisione del Regolamento delle radiocomunicazioni, ossia il trattato internazionale che disciplina l'utilizzazione dello spettro delle radiofrequenze e delle posizioni orbitali dei satelliti. La delegazione è stata presieduta da Philippe Horisberger, direttore supplente dell'Ufficio federale delle comunicazioni (UFCOM). L'UFCOM si accinge ora ad avviare i lavori di attuazione dei risultati della CMR-15 a livello nazionale. &lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Ufficio federale delle comunicazioni UFCOM Servizio stampa, +41 58 460 55 50, media@bakom.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="144370">
        <title>UIT - Regolamento delle radiocomunicazioni (disponibile in francese e inglese)</title>
        <uri>http://www.itu.int/fr/ITU-R/Pages/default.aspx</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="144371">
        <title>Regolamento delle radiocomunicazioni del 17 novembre 1995</title>
        <uri>https://www.admin.ch/opc/it/classified-compilation/20053379/index.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Biel/Bienne</city>
      <title>World Radiocommunications Conference: Switzerland’s objectives achieved</title>
      <lead>The World Radiocommunications Conference (WRC-15), which closes today in Geneva, enabled identification at the global level of new spectrum to accommodate the development of mobile broadband communications. Consensus was reached after four weeks of negotiations. This represents a success for the Swiss delegation, with all objectives set by the Federal Council achieved.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;The Conference, organized by the International Telecommunication Union (ITU) in Geneva, enabled identification at the global level&lt;b&gt; &lt;/b&gt;of additional spectrum for mobile broadband communications. These frequencies can be made available to the mobile telephony operators in Switzerland. It was also decided to launch studies ahead of the next Conference (WRC-19) in order to identify spectrum for mobile broadband of the 5th generation (5G).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Conference also allocated frequencies for global flight tracking in civil aviation. Furthermore, additional radiocommunication capacity was granted to Earth observation applications, which are crucial for climate monitoring, combating climate change and predicting natural disasters. Finally, the conference proposed additional studies on remotely piloted aircraft, the terms of use of which must be defined by the International Civil Aviation Organisation (ICAO). &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; The Swiss delegation has signed the final acts revising the Radio Regulations, the international treaty governing the use of the radio-frequency spectrum and satellite orbits. The delegation was led by Philippe Horisberger, Deputy Director General of the Federal Office of Communications (OFCOM). OFCOM will now begin work on implementing the WRC-15 results at the national level.&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Federal Office of Communications OFCOM Press service, +41 58 460 55 50, media@bakom.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="144378">
        <title>ITU - Radio Regulations</title>
        <uri>http://www.itu.int/ITU-R/</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="144379">
        <title>Radio Regulations (available in German, French and Italian only)</title>
        <uri>https://www.admin.ch/opc/de/classified-compilation/20053379/index.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <offers>
      <offer id="67" org-id="810">
        <name lang="de">Medienmitteilungen Telecom</name>
        <name lang="fr">Communiqués de presse télécommunications</name>
        <name lang="it">Comunicati stampa telecomunicazioni</name>
        <name lang="en">Press releases Telecom</name>
      </offer>
    </offers>
    <keywords>
      <keyword id="140" org-id="810">
        <name lang="de">Bundesamt für Kommunikation (BAKOM)</name>
        <name lang="fr">Office fédéral de la communication (OFCOM)</name>
        <name lang="it">Ufficio federale delle comunicazioni (UFCOM)</name>
        <name lang="en">Federal Office of Communications (OFCOM)</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="470" org-id="810">
        <name lang="de">Funk</name>
        <name lang="fr">Radiocommunication</name>
        <name lang="it">Radiocomunicazione</name>
        <name lang="en">Radiocommunication</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="1260" org-id="810">
        <name lang="de">Telekommunikation</name>
        <name lang="fr">Télécommunications</name>
        <name lang="it">Telecomunicazioni</name>
        <name lang="en">Telecommunications</name>
      </keyword>
    </keywords>
    <topics>
      <topic id="19">
        <name lang="de">Medien</name>
        <name lang="fr">Médias</name>
        <name lang="it">Media</name>
        <name lang="en">Media</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="28">
        <name lang="de">Telekommunikation</name>
        <name lang="fr">Télécommunications</name>
        <name lang="it">Telecomunicazione</name>
        <name lang="en">Telecommunications</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="36">
        <name lang="de">Informatik und E-Government</name>
        <name lang="fr">Informatique et cyberadministration</name>
        <name lang="it">Informatica ed e-government</name>
        <name lang="en">IT and E-Government</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
