<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="59467" revoked="no">
    <version>2</version>
    <pubdate>2015-11-16</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="811" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>801</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Bundesamt für Umwelt BAFU</name>
      <name lang="fr">Office fédéral de l'environnement OFEV</name>
      <name lang="it">Ufficio federale dell'ambiente UFAM</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Office for the Environment FOEN</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.bafu.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.bafu.admin.ch/fr</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.bafu.admin.ch/it</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.bafu.admin.ch/en</www>
      <email lang="de">info@bafu.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@bafu.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@bafu.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@bafu.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="705" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>701</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Bundesamt für Landwirtschaft</name>
      <name lang="fr">Office fédéral de l'agriculture</name>
      <name lang="it">Ufficio federale dell'agricoltura</name>
      <name lang="en">Swiss Federal Office for Agriculture</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.blw.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.blw.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.blw.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.blw.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@blw.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@blw.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@blw.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@blw.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="801">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Umwelt, Verkehr, Energie und Kommunikation</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'environnement, des transports, de l'énergie et de la communication</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'ambiente, dei trasporti, dell'energia e delle comunicazioni</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of the Environment, Transport, Energy and Communications</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.uvek.admin.ch/uvek/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.uvek.admin.ch/uvek/fr/home.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.uvek.admin.ch/uvek/it/home.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.uvek.admin.ch/uvek/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-uvek.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-uvek.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-uvek.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-uvek.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <department id="701">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Wirtschaft, Bildung und Forschung</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'économie, de la formation et de la recherche</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'economia, della formazione e della ricerca</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Economic Affairs, Education and Research</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Bund gründet Netzwerk für Klimadienstleistungen</title>
      <lead>Bei Entscheiden das Wissen zum Klima einbeziehen – aber wie? Die Klimadienstleistungen des National Centre for Climate Services NCCS helfen Behörden, Politik, Wirtschaft und Gesellschaft klimabedingte Risiken und Chancen zu erkennen. Damit können Risiken reduziert, Chancen genutzt und Kosten optimiert werden. Die vom NCCS und den verschiedenen Fachstellen bereitgestellten Grundlagen tragen dazu bei, angesichts des Klimawandels die Weichen für die Zukunft richtig zu stellen.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Klimadienstleistungen (Climate Services) sind wissenschaftlich basierte Informationen über das vergangene, heutige und zukünftige Klima und seine Folgen. Sie sind Grundlage für Entscheide zum Umgang mit den Auswirkungen des Klimas. Klimadienstleistungen sind auch Vorrausetzung dafür, dem Klimawandel bereits bei der Planung und Umsetzung von Massnahmen zu berücksichtigen und somit langfristig Kosten zu sparen.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Das NCCS des Bundes mit Sitz an der MeteoSchweiz koordiniert die Erarbeitung und Verbreitung von Climate Services und stellt sie in verständlicher Form zur Verfügung. Als Schnittstelle zwischen Wissenschaft und Praxis fördert es den Dialog und die gemeinsame und interdisziplinäre Entwicklung der Klimadienstleistungen. Dabei sorgt das Netzwerk dafür, dass diese auf die Bedürfnisse der Nutzerinnen und Nutzer ausgerichtet sind. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Schwerpunktthemen&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Das NCCS erarbeitet Klimadienstleistungen zu mehreren Schwerpunktthemen. So sollen die heutige Variabilität des Klimas in der Schweiz und die möglichen künftigen Veränderungen aufgezeigt werden. Weiter wird untersucht, wie sich der Klimawandel beispielsweise auf die Wasserressourcen, die Naturgefahren wie Hochwasser oder Rutschungen, die Waldgesundheit, die Verbreitung von Baumarten oder von Schädlingen in der Landwirtschaft auswirkt. Anschauliche Szenarien für extreme Wetterereignisse sollen nicht zuletzt neben notwendigen Präventionsmassnahmen die Ereignisbewältigung und auch den Bevölkerungsschutz weiter verbessern. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Auf verschiedenen Ebenen den Dialog fördern &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Alle praxisnahen und regelmässig aufdatierten Informationen und Grundlagen zum Klima werden im Rahmen des NCCS an einem Ort verfügbar sein. Die Webseite www.nccs.ch wird zu einer Webplattform für Behörden, Entscheidungsträger und -trägerinnen aus Politik und Wirtschaft, Verbände sowie für die Gesellschaft ausgebaut. Ergänzend finden Vernetzungsanlässe statt, die den Austausch fördern und mögliche Forschungslücken identifizieren. Dieser Dialog bildet die Grundlage für die Erarbeitung und Weiterentwicklung der bestmöglichen Klimadienstleistungen. Bei Bedarf organisiert das NCCS interdisziplinäre Workshops für einzelne Sektoren wie die Landwirtschaft oder zu spezifischen Themen wie beispielsweise den Klimaszenarien.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Das NCCS – Kurz erklärt&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Im Rahmen des vom Bundesrat verabschiedeten Aktionsplans zur Anpassung an den Klimawandel in der Schweiz übernimmt das NCCS die Stärkung der sektorübergreifenden Zusammenarbeit bei der Erarbeitung der Daten und Informationen und verbessert damit die gemeinsamen, praxisnahen Grundlagen. Der Bund folgt mit dem NCCS der Empfehlung aus dem Globalen Rahmenwerk für Klimadienste (Global Framework for Climate Services GFCS), welches 2009 von der Weltorganisation für Meteorologie WMO an der dritten Weltklimakonferenz in Genf lanciert wurde. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Am NCCS sind das Bundesamt für Meteorologie und Klimatologie MeteoSchweiz, das Bundesamt für Umwelt BAFU, das Bundesamt für Landwirtschaft BLW, das Bundesamt für Bevölkerungsschutz BABS, die ETH Zürich und die Eidgenössische Forschungsanstalt für Wald, Schnee und Landschaft WSL beteiligt. Die Geschäftsstelle ist bei MeteoSchweiz in Zürich angesiedelt. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Neben den genannten Bundesämtern und Forschungsinstitutionen sind zurzeit die Agroscope, das Forschungsinstitut für biologischen Landbau FiBL und die Universität Bern mitbeteiligt. Ziel ist, weitere Institutionen für die Mitarbeit zu gewinnen. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Diese und weitere Fragen stehen im Fokus des NCCS:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Wird es stärker regnen und deswegen grössere Hochwasser geben? Was bedeutet dies für meine Gemeinde?&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Verursachen Schädlinge im Obst-, Wein- und Ackerbau künftig mehr Verluste? Was bedeutet dies für den Pflanzenschutz?&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Wie stark werden die Hitzewellen zunehmen? Was bedeutet dies für die Bevölkerung?&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Welche Baumarten sollen wir heute fördern? Welche liefern trotz höheren Temperaturen und grösserer Trockenheit guten Holzertrag und Lebensraum für Tiere und Pflanzen?&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Wie werden sich die Wasserressourcen verändern? Was bedeutet dies für die Gesellschaft?&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;</text>
      <contact>Sektion Medien BAFU Telefon: +41 58 462 90 00 Email: mediendienst@bafu.admin.ch</contact>
      <attachment id="143427">
        <title>Faltblatt NCCS</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>1193</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/41746.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <link id="143423">
        <title>National Centre for Climate Services NCCS</title>
        <uri>http://www.meteoschweiz.admin.ch/home/forschung-und-zusammenarbeit/nccs.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="143431">
        <title>BAFU-Publikation "Anpassung an den Klimawandel in der Schweiz"</title>
        <uri>http://www.bafu.admin.ch/publikationen/publikation/01762/index.html?lang=de</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>La Confédération crée un réseau pour les services climatologiques</title>
      <lead>Inclure l’aspect climatique dans les décisions, oui : mais comment ? Les services climatologiques du National Centre for Climate Services (NCCS) aident les autorités, le monde politique, l’économie et la société civile à identifier les risques et les opportunités liés au climat, en vue de réduire les premiers, tirer profit des secondes, et optimiser les coûts. Les données de base préparées par le NCCS et les divers offices représentent une aide précieuse pour décider des voies à suivre face au changement climatique.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Les services climatologiques (Climate Services) sont constitués par des informations et des données à caractère scientifique sur le climat passé, présent et à venir, et sur son influence. Données de base indispensables pour décider de la gestion des effets du climat, ils constituent une condition incontournable à la prise en compte du changement climatique au niveau de la planification et de la mise en œuvre de mesures, ce qui permettra de réaliser des économies à long terme.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Le NCCS de la Confédération, établi au sein de MétéoSuisse, coordonne l’élaboration et la diffusion des services climatiques, et les met à disposition sous une forme compréhensible. En tant que plaque tournante entre la science et la pratique, il favorise le dialogue entre les différents partenaires et le développement commun et interdisciplinaire de services climatiques. En outre, le réseau veille en outre à ce que ces services soient adaptés aux besoins des utilisatrices et utilisateurs. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Thèmes prioritaires&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Le NCCS élabore des services climatologiques ayant trait à de nombreux thèmes prioritaires. Il aura, entre autres, pour tâche la mise en évidence de la variabilité actuelle du climat en Suisse et des possibles changements à venir, l’étude de l’influence du changement climatique sur les ressources en eau, les dangers naturels comme les crues ou les glissements de terrain, la santé des forêts, la répartition des espèces d’arbres ou des nuisibles dans l’agriculture. L’établissement de scénarios clairs relatifs à des événements climatiques extrêmes permettra, non seulement de parer efficacement aux catastrophes naturelles en prenant les mesures de prévention nécessaires, mais aussi de continuer à améliorer la protection de la population. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Favoriser le dialogue à divers échelons&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Toutes les informations et données pratiques sur le climat seront disponibles en un seul lieu dans le cadre du NCCS. Le site www.nccs.ch sera développé sous forme de plateforme Internet pour les autorités, les décideurs du monde politique et économique, les associations et la société civile. Il y aura également des rencontres entre partenaires, destinées à encourager les échanges et identifier les éventuelles lacunes au niveau de la recherche. Ce dialogue est indispensable pour élaborer et développer des services climatologiques optimaux. Au besoin, le NCCS organisera des ateliers interdisciplinaires pour certains secteurs comme l’agriculture ou sur des thèmes spécifiques comme les scénarios climatiques. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Le NCCS en bref&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Dans le cadre du plan d’action sur le changement climatique en Suisse approuvé par le Conseil fédéral, le NCCS est chargé du renforcement de la collaboration intersectorielle pour l’élaboration des données et l’amélioration de bases communes axées sur la pratique. La Confédération crée le NCCS suite à la recommandation du Cadre mondial pour les services climatologiques (Global Framework for Climate Services GFCS), lancé en 2009 par l’Organisation mondiale de météorologie (OMM) lors de la 3e Conférence mondiale sur le climat à Genève. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Participent au NCCS : l’Office fédéral de météorologie et de climatologie MétéoSuisse, l’Office fédéral de l’environnement OFEV, l’Office fédéral de l’agriculture OFAG, l’Office fédéral de la protection de la population OFPP, l’EPF de Zurich et l’Institut fédéral de recherche sur la forêt, la neige et le paysage WSL. Le secrétariat a son siège à MétéoSuisse à Zurich. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Participent également Agroscope, l’Institut de recherche sur la culture biologique FiBL et l’Université de Berne. Il est prévu de trouver encore d’autres institutions prêtes à collaborer. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Quelques questions parmi d’autres au centre de l’attention du NCCS : &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Va-t-il pleuvoir plus fort, avec, comme conséquence, de plus grandes crues? Qu’est-ce que cela signifie pour ma commune ? &lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Les nuisibles dans la culture des arbres fruitiers, les vignes et les champs causeront-ils plus de dégâts à l’avenir ? Qu’est-ce que cela signifie pour la lutte phytosanitaire ? &lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Dans quelle mesure les vagues de chaleur vont-elles augmenter ? Quelles en seront les conséquences pour la population ? &lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Quelles essences d’arbres faut-il favoriser actuellement ? Lesquelles ont un bon rendement en bois tout en fournissant des habitats adéquats pour les animaux et les plantes malgré la hausse des températures et de la sécheresse ? &lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Comment les ressources en eau vont-elles évoluer ? Quelles en seront les conséquences pour la société ? &lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;</text>
      <contact>Section Médias OFEV Téléphone: +41 58 462 90 00 Courriel: mediendienst@bafu.admin.ch</contact>
      <attachment id="143428">
        <title>Fiche NCCS</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>1348</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/41747.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <link id="143424">
        <title>National Centre for Climate Services NCCS</title>
        <uri>http://www.meteosuisse.admin.ch/home/recherche-et-collaboration/nccs.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="143432">
        <title>Publication de l'OFEV "Adaptation aux changements climatiques en Suisse"</title>
        <uri>http://www.bafu.admin.ch/publikationen/publikation/01762/index.html?lang=fr</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>La Confederazione istituisce una rete per i servizi climatici</title>
      <lead>Includere le conoscenze sul clima quando si prendono delle decisioni – ma come? I servizi climatici del National Centre for Climate Services (NCCS) aiutano le autorità, il mondo politico ed economico e la società a riconoscere i rischi e le opportunità legati al clima. Ciò consente di ridurre i rischi, cogliere le opportunità e ottimizzare i costi. Le basi messe a disposizione dal NCCS e dai diversi servizi specializzati contribuiscono ad affrontare in modo appropriato il futuro, tenendo conto dei cambiamenti climatici.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;I servizi climatici (Climate Services) sono informazioni sul clima passato, attuale e futuro e sulle sue conseguenze. Essi forniscono le basi per tutte quelle decisioni nelle quali occorre prendere in considerazione gli effetti del clima. Questi servizi costituiscono inoltre la premessa per tenere conto dei cambiamenti climatici già durante la pianificazione e l’attuazione delle misure risparmiando, a lunga scadenza, sui costi. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Il NCCS della Confederazione, con sede presso MeteoSvizzera, coordina l’elaborazione e la diffusione dei servizi climatici e li mette a disposizione in forma comprensibile. In qualità di interfaccia tra chi si occupa degli aspetti scientifici e chi è chiamato a operare nella pratica, l’NCCS promuove il dialogo e lo sviluppo congiunto e interdisciplinare dei servizi climatici. In questo contesto il NCCS assicura che questi servizi siano orientati alle esigenze degli utenti. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Le tematiche prioritarie&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Il NCCS elabora servizi climatici su diverse tematiche prioritarie. In tal modo si vuole illustrare l’attuale variabilità del clima in Svizzera e le possibili alterazioni future. Inoltre si studiano gli effetti dei cambiamenti climatici ad esempio sulle risorse idriche, sui pericoli naturali quali le piene o le frane, sulla salute dei boschi, sulla diffusione delle specie arboree o dei parassiti nell’agricoltura. Scenari illustrativi riguardo gli eventi meteorologici estremi consentono altresì di migliorare ulteriormente, oltre alle necessarie misure di prevenzione, anche la gestione degli eventi e la protezione della popolazione. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Promuovere il dialogo su più livelli &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Tutte le informazioni e le basi di dati sul clima, orientate alla pratica e aggiornate regolarmente, saranno messe a disposizione in modo centralizzato nel quadro del NCCS. Il sito www.nccs.ch costituirà una piattaforma Internet per le autorità, le persone del mondo politico ed economico chiamate a prendere decisioni, le associazioni e la società. Sono inoltre, previsti eventi di networking al fine di promuovere i contatti e gli scambi e individuare le possibili lacune nella ricerca. Questo dialogo costituisce la base per ottimizzare l’elaborazione e lo sviluppo dei servizi climatici. All’occorrenza il NCCS organizza workshop interdisciplinari per settori particolari quali l’agricoltura o su temi specifici, quali ad esempio gli scenari climatici.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Il NCCS in breve&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Nel quadro del piano d’azione per l’adattamento ai cambiamenti climatici in Svizzera approvato dal Consiglio federale, il NCCS ha il compito di consolidare la collaborazione intersettoriale nell’elaborazione dei dati e delle informazioni migliorando le basi congiunte orientate alla pratica. Con la creazione del NCCS la Confederazione ha dato seguito alla raccomandazione relativa al Quadro globale per i servizi climatici (Global Framework for Climate Services, GFCS) lanciato nel 2009 dall’Organizzazione meteorologica mondiale (OMM) in occasione della terza conferenza mondiale sul clima a Ginevra. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Al NCCS partecipano l’Ufficio federale di meteorologia e climatologia MeteoSvizzera, l’Ufficio federale dell’ambiente (UFAM), l’Ufficio federale dell’agricoltura (UFAG), l’Ufficio federale della protezione della popolazione (UFPP), il Politecnico federale di Zurigo e l’Istituto federale di ricerca per la foresta, la neve e il paesaggio WSL. Il segretariato si trova presso la sede di MeteoSvizzera a Zurigo. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Oltre agli uffici federali e agli istituti di ricerca summenzionati, attualmente sono in corso collaborazioni con Agroscope, l’Istituto di ricerche dell’agricoltura biologica FiBL e l’Università di Berna. L’obiettivo è di coinvolgere altri enti. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Il NCCS pone l’accento su queste e altre domande:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Le piogge aumenteranno di intensità causando piene straordinarie? Cosa significa per il mio comune?&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;In futuro i parassiti provocheranno maggiori perdite nella frutticoltura, viticoltura e agricoltura? Cosa significa per la protezione fitosanitaria?&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;In che misura aumenteranno i periodi di canicola? Cosa significa per la popolazione?&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Quali specie arboree dobbiamo favorire oggi? Quali specie hanno una buona resa di legname e offrono un habitat per la fauna e la flora nonostante le temperature in aumento e una maggiore siccità?&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Come cambierà la disponibilità di risorse idriche? Cosa significa per la società?&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;</text>
      <contact>Sezione Media Telefono: +41 58 462 90 00 E-mail: mediendienst@bafu.admin.ch</contact>
      <attachment id="143429">
        <title>Scheda NCCS</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>1191</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/41748.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <link id="143425">
        <title>National Centre for Climate Services NCCS</title>
        <uri>http://www.meteosvizzera.admin.ch/home/ricerca-e-collaborazioni/national-center-for-climate-services-nccs.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="143433">
        <title>Pubblicazione dell'UFAM "Adattamento ai cambiamenti climatici in Svizzera"</title>
        <uri>http://www.bafu.admin.ch/publikationen/publikation/01762/index.html?lang=it</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Federal government establishes network for climate services</title>
      <lead>How can we draw on existing knowledge about the climate as part of the decision-making process? The National Centre for Climate Services NCCS helps government departments, politicians, the business sector and society to recognise the risks and opportunities. This in turn enables the risks to be reduced, opportunities to be exploited and costs to be optimised. The groundwork which is laid by the NCCS and various specialist departments helps to set the relevant players on the right track for a future in the context of climate change.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Climate services comprise research-based information on past, current and future climate and its consequences. They serve as the basis for decision-making with regard to dealing with climatic effects. Moreover, they are indispensable in the planning and implementation of climate change related measures, and in saving costs in the long term. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Under the auspices of the Confederation, and based within MeteoSwiss, NCCS coordinates the preparation and dissemination of climate services in a comprehensible form. As an interface between science and practical applications, the NCCS encourages dialogue and fosters a collaborative and interdisciplinary approach to the development of climate services. The Centre thus ensures that it focuses on the needs of the users. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Key focus areas&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The NCCS develops climate services in several key focus areas. One of these is the documentation of the current variability of the climate system in Switzerland along with possible changes in the future. Other investigations focus, for example, on the impact of climate change on water resources, natural hazards such as floods or landslides, forest health, the distribution of tree species or the spread of pests in the agricultural sector. Scenarios for extreme climatic events are designed to improve the preventative measures, help to deal more effectively with hazard events, and improve civil protection.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fostering dialogue on numerous levels&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Thanks to the NCCS, all practical and regularly updated information and data on the climate will be available in one place. The www.nccs.ch website will be expanded to become a web platform for government departments, decision makers-in the political and business sectors, associations and the broader public. Network events will also be held to promote the exchange of knowledge and identify possible gaps in research. This dialogue serves as the foundation for the preparation and further development of the best possible climate services. When required, the NCCS organises interdisciplinary workshops for individual sectors such as the agricultural sector or on specific topics such as climate scenarios.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The NCCS in brief&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As part of the Federal Council's action plan for adaptation to climate change in Switzerland, the NCCS is responsible for strengthening cross-sector collaboration in processing the data and information, which in turn serves to improve the joint information base of applied knowledge. The NCCS is the Federal government's response to the recommendations of the Global Framework for Climate Services GFCS, which was launched in 2009 by the World Meteorological Organisation WMO at the Third World Climate Conference in Geneva. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The parties involved in the NCCS include the Federal Office of Meteorology and Climatology MeteoSwiss, the Federal Office for the Environment FOEN, the Federal Office for Agriculture FOAG, the Swiss Federal Office for Civil Protection FOCP, the Swiss Federal Institute of Technology in Zurich (ETH Zurich) and the Swiss Federal Institute for Forest, Snow and Landscape Research WSL. The office is located at the MeteoSwiss headquarters in Zurich.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In addition to the above government offices and research institutions, Agroscope, the Research Institute of Organic Agriculture FiBL and the University of Berne are currently also involved in the NCCS. The aim is to attract additional institutions to join the NCCS. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The questions below are among the issues focused on by the NCCS:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Will it rain more and will we therefore have bigger floods? What does this mean for my town?&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Will pests cause more losses in future in the fruit, wine and crop farming sectors? What does this mean for crop protection?&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;How much worse will the heat waves get? What does this mean for the population?&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Which tree species should we promote today? Which species have a good yield in wood and provide a good habitat for animals and plants, even in times of higher temperatures and drought?&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;How will our water resources change? What implications does this have for society?&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;</text>
      <contact>Media Section Telephone: +41 58 462 90 00 E-mail: mediendienst@bafu.admin.ch</contact>
      <attachment id="143430">
        <title>Fact Sheet NCCS</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>1191</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/41749.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <link id="143426">
        <title>National Centre for Climate Services NCCS</title>
        <uri>http://www.meteoswiss.admin.ch/home/research-and-cooperation/nccs.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="143431">
        <title>BAFU-Publikation "Anpassung an den Klimawandel in der Schweiz"</title>
        <uri>http://www.bafu.admin.ch/publikationen/publikation/01762/index.html?lang=de</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <offers>
      <offer id="143" org-id="811">
        <name lang="de">Medienmitteilungen des BAFU</name>
        <name lang="fr">Communiqués de l'OFEV</name>
        <name lang="it">Comunicati dell'UFAM</name>
        <name lang="en">Media releases of the FOEN</name>
      </offer>
    </offers>
    <keywords>
      <keyword id="620" org-id="811">
        <name lang="de">Klima</name>
        <name lang="fr">Climat</name>
        <name lang="it">Clima</name>
        <name lang="en">Climate</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="173" org-id="811">
        <name lang="de">Bundesamt für Umwelt: Startseite</name>
        <name lang="fr">Office fédéral de l'environnement: page d'accueil</name>
        <name lang="it">Ufficio federale dell'ambiente: pagina iniziale</name>
        <name lang="en">Federal Office for the Environment: Homepage</name>
      </keyword>
    </keywords>
    <topics>
      <topic id="29">
        <name lang="de">Umwelt und Natur</name>
        <name lang="fr">Environnement et nature</name>
        <name lang="it">Ambiente e natura</name>
        <name lang="en">Environment and Nature</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
