<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="31975" revoked="no">
    <version>3</version>
    <pubdate>2010-02-25</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="811" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>801</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Bundesamt für Umwelt BAFU</name>
      <name lang="fr">Office fédéral de l'environnement OFEV</name>
      <name lang="it">Ufficio federale dell'ambiente UFAM</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Office for the Environment FOEN</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.bafu.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.bafu.admin.ch/fr</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.bafu.admin.ch/it</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.bafu.admin.ch/en</www>
      <email lang="de">info@bafu.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@bafu.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@bafu.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@bafu.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="801">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Umwelt, Verkehr, Energie und Kommunikation</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'environnement, des transports, de l'énergie et de la communication</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'ambiente, dei trasporti, dell'energia e delle comunicazioni</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of the Environment, Transport, Energy and Communications</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.uvek.admin.ch/uvek/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.uvek.admin.ch/uvek/fr/home.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.uvek.admin.ch/uvek/it/home.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.uvek.admin.ch/uvek/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-uvek.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-uvek.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-uvek.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-uvek.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Verhandlungserfolg der Schweiz: globale Abfall- und Chemikalienpolitik wird gestärkt</title>
      <teaser>Vom 22. bis am 24. Februar 2010 tagten in Bali die drei globalen Konventionen im Chemikalien- und Abfallbereich erstmals gemeinsam. Die Vertragsparteien folgten einem Vorschlag der Schweiz und beschlossen, die Leitung der drei Konventionssekretariate in Genf zusammenzulegen.</teaser>
      <lead>Vom 22. bis am 24. Februar 2010 tagten in Bali die drei globalen Konventionen im Chemikalien- und Abfallbereich erstmals gemeinsam. Die Vertragsparteien folgten einem Vorschlag der Schweiz und beschlossen, die Leitung der drei Konventionssekretariate in Genf zusammenzulegen.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Üblicherweise führen internationale Umweltkonventionen getrennte Treffen durch. Mit dem von der Schweiz angeregten Ziel, im Abfall- und Chemikalienbereich künftig stärker zusammenzuarbeiten, tagten die Vertragsparteien der Rotterdamer-, Stockholmer- und Basler Konvention (siehe Kasten) erstmals gleichzeitig.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Die Schweiz hatte 2006 den Prozess der verstärkten Zusammenarbeit ausgelöst, indem sie vorschlug, die Sekretariate der drei Konventionen, welche alle ihren Sitz in Genf haben, unter eine gemeinsame Leitung zu stellen. Dadurch lassen sich die Synergien zwischen den drei Konventionen besser nutzen und deren Arbeit einheitlicher gestalten und ausrichten.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Die Vertragsparteien der drei Konventionen sind am 24. Februar 2010 in Bali dem Schweizer Antrag gefolgt und haben entschieden, die Leitung der Sekretariate zu zentralisieren und einer Person zu übertragen.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h3&gt;KASTEN&lt;br /&gt; &lt;strong&gt;Drei globale Konventionen im Chemikalien- und Abfallbereich&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt; &lt;p&gt;Für den verantwortungsvollen Umgang mit gefährlichen Chemikalien und Abfall zum Schutz von Mensch und Umwelt sind in den letzten Jahrzehnten verschiedene internationale Regulierungen und Instrumente geschaffen worden. Insbesondere sind drei globale Konventionen ausgehandelt und in Kraft gesetzt worden, die ihre Sekretariate alle in Genf haben:&lt;/p&gt; &lt;ul&gt; &lt;li&gt;Basler Übereinkommen über die Kontrolle der grenzüberschreitenden Verbringung gefährlicher Abfälle und ihrer Entsorgung&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;Rotterdamer Übereinkommen über das Verfahren der vorherigen Zustimmung nach Inkenntnissetzung für bestimmte gefährliche Chemikalien sowie Pestizide im internationalen Handel (auch PIC Konvention genannt)&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;Stockholmer Übereinkommen über persistente organische Schadstoffe (auch POPs Konvention genannt)&lt;br /&gt; &lt;/li&gt; &lt;/ul&gt;</text>
      <contact>Franz Perrez, Stellvertretender Chef der Abteilung Internationales BAFU, Tel. +41 79 251 90 15 (bitte Zeitverschiebung +7 Stunden beachten)</contact>
      <link id="66538">
        <title>BAFU-Thema: International</title>
        <uri>http://www.bafu.admin.ch/international/index.html?lang=de</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Grâce à la Suisse, la politique en matière de déchets et produits chimiques se globalise</title>
      <teaser>Pour la première fois, les trois conventions internationales dans le domaine des déchets et des produits chimiques ont siégé ensemble du 22 au 24 février à Bali. Accédant à la requête de la Suisse, les parties ont décidé de centraliser la direction des secrétariats à Genève.</teaser>
      <lead>Pour la première fois, les trois conventions internationales dans le domaine des déchets et des produits chimiques ont siégé ensemble du 22 au 24 février à Bali. Accédant à la requête de la Suisse, les parties ont décidé de centraliser la direction des secrétariats à Genève.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Habituellement, les parties aux conventions internationales dans le domaine de l'environnement organisent des conférences séparées. Suivant la proposition suisse de resserrer la coopération dans le domaine des déchets et des produits chimiques, les parties aux conventions de Bâle, de Stockholm et de Rotterdam (voir encadré) ont siégé ensemble pour la première fois.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;C'est en 2006 que la Suisse a lancé ce processus, en proposant de réunir sous une direction commune les secrétariats des trois conventions, qui ont toutes leur siège à Genève, afin d'exploiter au mieux les synergies entre les trois entités ainsi que de coordonner et d'unifier les efforts de travail.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Les parties aux trois conventions ont décidé le 24 février 2010, à Bali, de centraliser les secrétariats sous la direction d'une seule personne, accédant ainsi à la requête de la Suisse.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h3&gt;ENCADRÉ:&lt;br /&gt; Trois conventions internationales dans le domaine des déchets et des produits chimiques.&lt;/h3&gt; &lt;p&gt;Afin de rendre le traitement des déchets et des produits chimiques dangereux compatible avec les impératifs en matière de protection de l'environnement et de la santé, divers instruments normatifs internationaux ont été créés. Parmi ceux-ci, trois conventions ont été négociées et sont entrées en vigueur. Elles ont toutes leur secrétariat à Genève:&lt;/p&gt; &lt;ul&gt; &lt;li&gt;la Convention de Bâle sur le contrôle des mouvements transfrontières de déchets dangereux et leur élimination;&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;la Convention de Rotterdam sur la procédure de consentement préalable en connaissance de cause applicable à certains produits chimiques et pesticides dangereux qui font l'objet d'un commerce international (appelée aussi Convention PIC);&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;la Convention de Stockholm sur les polluants organiques persistants (appelée aussi Convention POP).&lt;/li&gt; &lt;/ul&gt;</text>
      <contact>M. Franz Perrez, suppléant du chef de la division Affaires internationales de l’OFEV, tél. +41 79 251 90 15. (Veuillez prendre en compte le décalage horaire: +7 heures).</contact>
      <link id="66539">
        <title>OFEV: Affaires internationales</title>
        <uri>http://www.bafu.admin.ch/international/index.html?lang=fr</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Successo negoziale svizzero: rafforzata la politica sui rifiuti e sui prodotti chimici</title>
      <teaser>Dal 22 al 24 febbraio 2010 si è tenuta a Bali la prima riunione congiunta delle tre Convenzioni internazionali nel settore dei rifiuti e dei prodotti chimici. Le Parti hanno accettato la proposta avanzata dalla Svizzera di riunire la direzione dei segretariati delle Convenzioni, tutti con sede a Ginevra.</teaser>
      <lead>Dal 22 al 24 febbraio 2010 si è tenuta a Bali la prima riunione congiunta delle tre Convenzioni internazionali nel settore dei rifiuti e dei prodotti chimici. Le Parti hanno accettato la proposta avanzata dalla Svizzera di riunire la direzione dei segretariati delle Convenzioni, tutti con sede a Ginevra.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Di regola, le Convenzioni internazionali in materia ambientale organizzano riunioni separate. Dando seguito alla proposta della Svizzera di rafforzare la collaborazione internazionale nel settore dei rifiuti e dei prodotti chimici, le Parti delle Convenzioni di Rotterdam, Stoccolma e Basilea (vedi riquadro) hanno tenuto la loro prima riunione congiunta.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;La Svizzera ha avviato nel 2006 il processo di collaborazione rafforzata proponendo una direzione congiunta dei segretariati delle tre Convenzioni, tutti con sede a Ginevra. Tale proposta consente di sfruttare al meglio le sinergie delle Convenzioni e di armonizzarne e orientarne in modo mirato le attività.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Il 24 febbraio 2010, le Parti delle tre Convenzioni riunite a Bali hanno accettato la proposta avanzata dalla Svizzera e deciso di centralizzare la direzione dei segretariati affidandola a una sola persona.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h3&gt;RIQUADRO:&lt;br /&gt; Tre convenzioni internazionali nel settore dei rifiuti e dei prodotti chimici&lt;/h3&gt; &lt;p&gt;Per garantire la gestione responsabile dei rifiuti e dei prodotti chimici pericolosi a tutela dell'uomo e dell'ambiente, negli ultimi decenni sono state adottate alcune normative e introdotti diversi strumenti. Sono state negoziate e attuate in particolare tre convenzioni globali. I segretariati di tali convenzioni hanno tutti sede a Ginevra:&lt;/p&gt; &lt;ul&gt; &lt;li&gt;Convenzione di Basilea sul controllo dei movimenti oltre frontiera di rifiuti pericolosi e sulla loro eliminazione&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;Convenzione di Rotterdam concernente la procedura di assenso preliminare con conoscenza di causa per taluni prodotti chimici e antiparassitari nel commercio internazionale (detta anche Convenzione PIC)&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;Convenzione di Stoccolma sugli inquinanti organici persistenti (detta anche Convenzione POP)&lt;/li&gt; &lt;/ul&gt;</text>
      <contact>Franz Perrez, supplente del capo della divisione Affari internazionali dell’UFAM, tel. +41 79 251 90 15 (si prega di rispettare il fuso orario di +7 ore)</contact>
      <link id="66540">
        <title>UFAM: Affari Internazionali</title>
        <uri>http://www.bafu.admin.ch/international/index.html?lang=it</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Swiss initiative successful: Global waste and chemicals policy boosted</title>
      <teaser>The three global conventions on chemicals and wastes held their first joint meeting in Bali from 22 to 24 February 2010. Taking Switzerland’s lead, the parties to the conventions decided to appoint a joint head of the three convention secretariats in Geneva.</teaser>
      <lead>The three global conventions on chemicals and wastes held their first joint meeting in Bali from 22 to 24 February 2010. Taking Switzerland’s lead, the parties to the conventions decided to appoint a joint head of the three convention secretariats in Geneva.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;International environmental conventions normally hold separate meetings. Now, with the goal - prompted by Switzerland - of cooperating more closely on wastes and chemicals, the parties to the Rotterdam, Stockholm and Basel Conventions (see Box) have convened jointly for the first time.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Switzerland had launched the process of intensified cooperation in 2006 when it suggested that the secretariats of the three conventions, all of which are seated in Geneva, should have a joint head. This makes it easier to harness synergies and streamline the conventions' work.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The parties to the three conventions, meeting in Bali, followed the Swiss proposal on 24 February 2010. They have resolved to centralise management of the secretariats and appoint a person to the position of joint head.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h3&gt;BOX:&lt;br /&gt; Three global conventions on chemicals and wastes&lt;/h3&gt; &lt;p&gt;Several international regimes and instruments designed to ensure the responsible management of hazardous chemicals and wastes have been established in recent decades. Their ultimate objective is to safeguard human health and environmental quality. In particular, three global conventions have been negotiated and have entered into force, all with secretariats in Geneva:&lt;/p&gt; &lt;ul&gt; &lt;li&gt;the Basel Convention on the Control of Transboundary Movements of Hazardous Wastes and Their Disposal;&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;the Rotterdam Convention on the Prior Informed Consent Procedure for Certain Hazardous Chemicals and Pesticides in International Trade (also known as the PIC Convention);&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;the Stockholm Convention on Persistent Organic Pollutants (also known as the POPs Convention).&lt;/li&gt; &lt;/ul&gt;</text>
      <contact>Franz Perrez, Deputy Head of the International Affairs Division, FOEN, tel. +41 79 251 90 15 (please note time difference of +7 hours)</contact>
      <link id="66541">
        <title>FOEN: International Affairs</title>
        <uri>http://www.bafu.admin.ch/international/index.html?lang=en</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions>
        <revision date="2010-02-25 12:22" type="R"/>
      </revisions>
    </content>
    <offers>
      <offer id="143" org-id="811">
        <name lang="de">Medienmitteilungen des BAFU</name>
        <name lang="fr">Communiqués de l'OFEV</name>
        <name lang="it">Comunicati dell'UFAM</name>
        <name lang="en">Media releases of the FOEN</name>
      </offer>
    </offers>
    <keywords>
      <keyword id="10" org-id="811">
        <name lang="de">Abfall</name>
        <name lang="fr">Dechets</name>
        <name lang="it">Rifiuti</name>
        <name lang="en">Waste</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="230" org-id="811">
        <name lang="de">Chemikalien</name>
        <name lang="fr">Produits chimiques</name>
        <name lang="it">Prodotti chimici</name>
        <name lang="en">Chemicals</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="560" org-id="811">
        <name lang="de">Internationales</name>
        <name lang="fr">Affaires internationales</name>
        <name lang="it">Affari Internazionali</name>
        <name lang="en">International Affairs</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="173" org-id="811">
        <name lang="de">Bundesamt für Umwelt: Startseite</name>
        <name lang="fr">Office fédéral de l'environnement: page d'accueil</name>
        <name lang="it">Ufficio federale dell'ambiente: pagina iniziale</name>
        <name lang="en">Federal Office for the Environment: Homepage</name>
      </keyword>
    </keywords>
    <topics>
      <topic id="29">
        <name lang="de">Umwelt und Natur</name>
        <name lang="fr">Environnement et nature</name>
        <name lang="it">Ambiente e natura</name>
        <name lang="en">Environment and Nature</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
