<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="66169" revoked="no">
    <version>2</version>
    <pubdate>2017-03-28</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="201" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>201</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="201">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Sicherheit, Europa, bilaterale Themen: Bundesrat Didier Burkhalter trifft deutschen Aussenminister Sigmar Gabriel in Berlin</title>
      <lead>Am 30. März 2017 wird Bundesrat Didier Burkhalter in Berlin mit dem neuen deutschen Aussenminister Sigmar Gabriel zusammentreffen. Im Zentrum des bilateralen Gesprächs werden die Kooperation beider Länder zur Stärkung von Frieden und Sicherheit stehen, ebenso die Politik der Schweiz gegenüber der EU sowie bilaterale Aspekte.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Didier Burkhalter, der Vorsteher des Eidgenössischen Departements für auswärtige Angelegenheiten EDA, trifft am kommenden Donnerstag den neuen deutschen Aussenminister Sigmar Gabriel zum offiziellen Gespräch. Neben dem ersten Kontakt zwischen beiden Amtskollegen – Sigmar Gabriel ist seit Ende Januar 2017 deutscher Aussenminister - steht die Kontinuität der engen Zusammenarbeit zwischen der Schweiz und Deutschland im Zentrum des Gesprächs. Ein Schwerpunkt gilt dabei der Kooperation beider Staaten zur Stärkung von Frieden und Sicherheit. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Bundesrat Burkhalter und Aussenminister Sigmar Gabriel werden zudem über die Situation in Europa sprechen. Auch die Politik der Schweiz gegenüber der EU wird Thema des Gesprächs sein. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Das Verhältnis zwischen der Schweiz und Deutschland ist geprägt durch enge Beziehungen in verschiedensten Bereichen. So ist Deutschland der wichtigste Handelspartner der Schweiz (2016: 94 Mrd. CHF). CHF. Rund 300'000 deutsche Staatsangehörige leben derzeit in der Schweiz, knapp 90‘000 Schweizerinnen und Schweizer in Deutschland. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Die Pflege und Vertiefung der bilateralen Beziehungen zu den Nachbarstaaten der Schweiz ist eine der Prioritäten der aussenpolitischen Strategie des Bundesrates.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Kommunikation EDA Bundeshaus West CH-3003 Bern Tel. Kommunikationsservice: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Medienstelle: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <link id="165049">
        <title>Bilaterale Beziehungen Schweiz–Deutschland</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home/vertretungen-und-reisehinweise/deutschland/bilatereale-beziehungenschweizdeutschland.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions>
        <revision date="2017-03-28 17:49" type="R"/>
      </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Sécurité, Europe, questions bilatérales: rencontre entre le conseiller fédéral Didier Burkhalter et le ministre allemand des affaires étrangères Sigmar Gabriel à Berlin</title>
      <lead>Le 30 mars 2017, le conseiller fédéral Didier Burkhalter rencontrera le nouveau ministre allemand des affaires étrangères Sigmar Gabriel à Berlin. Leur échange portera sur la coopération entre leurs pays en vue de renforcer la paix et la sécurité, sur la politique européenne de la Suisse ainsi que sur des thématiques bilatérales.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Didier Burkhalter, chef du Département fédéral des affaires étrangères (DFAE), aura un entretien officiel jeudi prochain avec son homologue allemand, Sigmar Gabriel. Outre un premier contact entre les deux ministres (Sigmar Gabriel est entré en fonction à la fin janvier 2017), cette rencontre permettra d’assurer la continuité de la coopération entre la Suisse et l’Allemagne, notamment dans l’optique de renforcer la paix et la sécurité. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Les deux ministres des affaires étrangères évoqueront aussi la situation en Europe, et aborderont la question de la politique européenne de la Suisse. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;La Suisse et l’Allemagne ont noué des relations étroites dans les domaines les plus variés. Ainsi, l’Allemagne est-elle aujourd’hui le plus important partenaire commercial de la Suisse, avec un volume d’échanges de 94 milliards de francs suisses en 2016. Près de 300'000 citoyens allemands vivent en Suisse actuellement, alors que 90'000 de nos compatriotes ont élu domicile outre-Rhin. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Dans sa stratégie de politique étrangère, le Conseil fédéral s’est donné pour priorité de consolider et de développer les relations bilatérales avec les pays voisins de la Suisse.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Communication DFAE Palais fédéral ouest CH-3003 Berne Tél. Service de communication: +41 58 462 31 53 Tél. Service de presse: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <link id="165050">
        <title>Relations bilatérales Suisse–Allemagne</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae/representations-et-conseils-aux-voyageurs/allemagne/suisse-allemagne.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Sicurezza, Europa, questioni bilaterali: a Berlino il consigliere federale Didier Burkhalter incontra il ministro degli esteri tedesco Sigmar Gabriel</title>
      <lead>Il 30 marzo 2017 Didier Burkhalter incontrerà a Berlino Sigmar Gabriel, nuovo ministro degli esteri tedesco. I colloqui saranno incentrati sulla cooperazione tra i due Paesi per il rafforzamento della pace e della sicurezza, sulla politica della Svizzera nei confronti dell’UE e su altre questioni bilaterali.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Giovedì 30 marzo 2017, Didier Burkhalter, capo del Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri (DFAE), incontrerà il nuovo ministro degli esteri tedesco Sigmar Gabriel nell’ambito di un colloquio ufficiale. Al centro di questo primo incontro tra i due ministri – Sigmar Gabriel ricopre questa funzione dal gennaio 2017 – figurerà l’intensa e stabile collaborazione tra la Svizzera e la Germania. A tale riguardo sarà dato particolare rilievo alla cooperazione tra i due Paesi per il rafforzamento della pace e della sicurezza. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I due ministri discuteranno inoltre sulla situazione in Europa e sulla politica della Svizzera nei confronti dell’UE.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Le relazioni tra la Svizzera e la Germania sono caratterizzate da un’assidua collaborazione nei più svariati settori. La Germania è il più importante partner commerciale della Svizzera, con scambi commerciali che hanno raggiunto 94 miliardi di franchi nel 2016. Attualmente circa 300 000 cittadine e cittadini tedeschi risiedono in Svizzera, mentre sono quasi 90 000 le Svizzere e gli Svizzeri residenti in Germania. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;La tutela e il rafforzamento delle relazioni bilaterali con gli Stati limitrofi è una delle priorità della Strategia di politica estera del Consiglio federale.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Comunicazione DFAE Palazzo federale ovest CH-3003 Berna Tel. Servizio di comunicazione: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Servizio stampa: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <link id="165051">
        <title>Relazioni bilaterali Svizzera–Germania</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae/rappresentanze-e-consigli-di-viaggio/germania/svizzera-germania.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Federal Councillor Didier Burkhalter to meet German Foreign Minister Sigmar Gabriel in Berlin</title>
      <lead>On 30 March 2017, Federal Councillor Didier Burkhalter will meet with the new German Foreign Minister Sigmar Gabriel in Berlin. The talks will focus on cooperation between the two countries to strengthen peace and security, and also on Switzerland's policy regarding the EU and bilateral matters.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Didier Burkhalter, the head of the Federal Department of Foreign Affairs FDFA, will meet the new German Foreign Minister, Sigmar Gabriel, for official talks on Thursday. This will be the first contact between the two foreign ministers – Sigmar Gabriel took up his new post at the end of January 2017 – and their discussions will focus on how Switzerland and Germany will continue to work closely together. A key area of their talks will be cooperation between the two countries to strengthen peace and security. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;They will also discuss the situation in Europe, including Switzerland’s policy with regard to the EU. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Relations between Switzerland and Germany are characterised by close ties in a number of areas. Germany is Switzerland’s biggest trading partner, with trade between the two nations amounting to CHF 94 billion in 2016. Around 300,000 German nationals currently live in Switzerland and almost 90,000 Swiss nationals live in Germany &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Maintaining and strengthening bilateral relations with Switzerland’s neighbouring countries is one of the priorities of the Federal Council's foreign policy strategy.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>FDFA Communication Federal Palace West Wing CH-3003 Bern, Switzerland Tel. Communication service: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Press service: +41 58 460 55 55 E-mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @SwissMFA</contact>
      <link id="165052">
        <title>Bilateral relations between Switzerland and Germany</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home/representations-and-travel-advice/germany/switzerland-germany.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
