<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="66062" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2017-03-21</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="yes" id="1060" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>601</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Staatssekretariat für internationale Finanzfragen</name>
      <name lang="fr">Secrétariat d'Etat aux questions financières internationales</name>
      <name lang="it">Segreteria di Stato per le questioni finanziarie internazionali</name>
      <name lang="en">State Secretariat for International Financial Matters</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.sif.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.sif.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.sif.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.sif.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@sif.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@sif.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@sif.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@sif.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="601">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Finanzdepartement</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des finances</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale delle finanze</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Finance</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.efd.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.dff.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.efd.admin.ch/efd/it/home.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.efd.admin.ch/efd/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Die Schweiz und Pakistan unterzeichnen Doppelbesteuerungsabkommen</title>
      <lead>Die Schweiz und Pakistan haben am 21. März 2017 in Islamabad ein neues Doppelbesteuerungsabkommen (DBA) auf dem Gebiet der Steuern vom Einkommen unterzeichnet.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Das Abkommen soll das aktuell in Kraft stehende DBA mit Pakistan ersetzen. Es enthält unter anderem Verbesserungen im Bereich der Besteuerung von Dienstleistungsentgelten und von Gewinnen aus der Veräusserung von massgebenden Beteiligungen. Diese Regeln fördern den wirtschaftlichen Austausch im bilateralen Verhältnis. Das Abkommen enthält zudem eine Schiedsklausel, die garantieren soll, dass eine Doppelbesteuerung vermieden wird.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Das Abkommen enthält eine Bestimmung über den Informationsaustausch gemäss dem internationalen Standard und eine Missbrauchsbestimmung gemäss dem Mindeststandard des BEPS-Projekts der G20/OECD.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Die Kantone und betroffenen Wirtschaftsverbände haben den Abschluss des DBA mit Pakistan begrüsst. Für das Inkrafttreten muss es vom schweizerischen Parlament genehmigt werden und das nötige Genehmigungsverfahren in Pakistan durchlaufen.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Die Schweiz hat bisher 55 DBA unterzeichnet, die den internationalen Standard in Sachen Informationsaustausch erfüllen; davon sind 50 in Kraft.&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Anne Césard, Kommunikation Staatssekretariat für internationale Finanzfragen SIF Tel. +41 58 462 62 91, anne.cesard@sif.admin.ch</contact>
      <attachment id="164754">
        <title>Doppelbesteuerungsabkommen</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>110</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/47621.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>La Suisse et le Pakistan signent une convention contre les doubles impositions</title>
      <lead>La Suisse et le Pakistan ont signé le 21 mars 2017 à Islamabad une nouvelle convention contre les doubles impositions (CDI) en matière d'impôts sur le revenu.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Cette convention va remplacer la CDI actuellement en vigueur avec le Pakistan. Elle contient notamment des améliorations dans le domaine de l'imposition des rémunérations de services et des gains provenant de l'aliénation de participations prépondérantes. Ces règles encouragent les échanges économiques entre les deux États. La convention contient en outre une clause d'arbitrage garantissant que les doubles impositions seront évitées.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;La convention contient une disposition sur l'échange de renseignements conforme à la norme internationale et une clause contre les abus satisfaisante au standard minimal du projet BEPS du G20 et de l'OCDE.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Les cantons et les milieux économiques concernés ont accueilli favorablement la conclusion de la CDI avec le Pakistan. Pour pouvoir entrer en vigueur, la convention doit être approuvée par le Parlement suisse et subir la procédure d'approbation nécessaire au Pakistan.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;À ce jour, la Suisse a signé 55 CDI conformes à la norme internationale en matière d'échange de renseignements, dont 50 sont en vigueur.&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Anne Césard, Communication du Secrétariat d'État aux questions financières internationales SFI tél. +41 58 462 62 91, anne.cesard@sif.admin.ch</contact>
      <attachment id="164755">
        <title>Convention contre les doubles impositions</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>167</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/47622.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>La Svizzera e il Pakistan firmano una Convenzione intesa a evitare la doppia imposizione</title>
      <lead>Il 21 marzo 2017 la Svizzera e il Pakistan hanno firmato a Islamabad una nuova Convenzione intesa a evitare la doppia imposizione (CDI) in materia di imposte sul reddito.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;La Convenzione sostituisce la CDI attualmente in vigore con il Pakistan. Essa prevede miglioramenti nell’ambito dell’imposizione dei compensi per prestazioni di servizi e degli utili derivanti dall’alienazione di partecipazioni determinanti. Le nuove regole favoriscono lo scambio economico tra i due Paesi. Inoltre la Convenzione prevede una clausola arbitrale volta a garantire che la doppia imposizione sia evitata.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;La Convenzione contiene una disposizione sullo scambio di informazioni conforme allo standard internazionale e una norma contro gli abusi secondo lo standard minimo del progetto BEPS istituito dal G20 e dall’OCSE.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;I Cantoni e le cerchie economiche interessate sostengono la conclusione della CDI con il Pakistan. Affinché possa entrare in vigore, la CDI dovrà essere approvata dal Parlamento svizzero e seguire le necessarie procedure di approvazione in Pakistan.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Finora la Svizzera ha firmato 55 CDI che soddisfano lo standard internazionale in materia di scambio di informazioni. Di queste, 50 sono in vigore.&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Anne Césard, Comunicazione, Segreteria di Stato per le questioni finanziarie internazionali SFI tel. +41 58 462 62 91, anne.cesard@sif.admin.ch</contact>
      <attachment id="164755">
        <title>Convention contre les doubles impositions</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>167</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/47622.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Switzerland and Pakistan sign double taxation agreement</title>
      <lead>On 21 March 2017 in Islamabad, Switzerland and Pakistan signed a new double taxation agreement (DTA) with respect to taxes on income.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;The agreement should replace the DTA currently in force with Pakistan. It contains improvements with regard to the taxation of service fees and capital gains resulting from the sale of qualifying participations. These rules promote economic exchange in bilateral relations. The agreement also contains an arbitration clause, which should guarantee the avoidance of double taxation.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The agreement contains a provision on the exchange of information in accordance with the international standard and an anti-abuse provision in accordance with the minimum standard set by the BEPS project of the G20/OECD.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The cantons and business associations concerned welcomed the conclusion of the DTA with Pakistan. In order to enter into force, the DTA has to be approved by Parliament in Switzerland and the necessary approval procedure has to be carried out in Pakistan.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;So far, Switzerland has signed 55 DTAs that are in line with the international standard on the exchange of information; 50 of these are in force.&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Anne Césard, Communications, State Secretariat for International Financial Matters SIF Tel. +41 58 462 62 91, anne.cesard@sif.admin.ch</contact>
      <attachment id="164756">
        <title>Double taxation agreement</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>106</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/47623.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <offers>
      <offer id="291" org-id="1060">
        <name lang="de">Wirtschaft, Währung, Finanzplatz</name>
        <name lang="fr">Economie, monnaie, place financière</name>
        <name lang="it">Economia, Moneta, Piazza finanziaria</name>
        <name lang="en">Economic, Monetary and Financial Affairs</name>
      </offer>
    </offers>
    <keywords>
      <keyword id="235" org-id="1060">
        <name lang="de">Internationale Steuerpolitik</name>
        <name lang="fr">Politique fiscale internationale</name>
        <name lang="it">Politica fiscale internazionale</name>
        <name lang="en">International tax policy</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="137" org-id="1060">
        <name lang="de">Internationale Doppelbesteuerung</name>
        <name lang="fr">Double imposition internationale</name>
        <name lang="it">Doppia imposizione internazionale</name>
        <name lang="en">International double taxation</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="226" org-id="1060">
        <name lang="de">Automatischer Informationsaustausch (AIA)</name>
        <name lang="fr">Echange automatique de renseignements (EAR)</name>
        <name lang="it">Scambio automatico di informazioni</name>
        <name lang="en">Automatic exchange of information (AEOI)</name>
      </keyword>
    </keywords>
    <topics>
      <topic id="31">
        <name lang="de">Bund und Kantone</name>
        <name lang="fr">Confédération et cantons</name>
        <name lang="it">Confederazione e Cantoni</name>
        <name lang="en">Confederation and Cantons</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="35">
        <name lang="de">Finanzplatz</name>
        <name lang="fr">Place financière</name>
        <name lang="it">Piazza finanziaria</name>
        <name lang="en">Financial Centre</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="44">
        <name lang="de">Steuern</name>
        <name lang="fr">Impôts</name>
        <name lang="it">Imposte</name>
        <name lang="en">Taxation</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="47">
        <name lang="de">Wirtschaft</name>
        <name lang="fr">Économie</name>
        <name lang="it">Economia</name>
        <name lang="en">Economic Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
