<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="95027" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2023-05-10</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="1070" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>1070</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Der Bundesrat</name>
      <name lang="fr">Conseil fédéral</name>
      <name lang="it">Il Consiglio federale</name>
      <name lang="en">The Federal Council</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.admin.ch/gov/de/start.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.admin.ch/gov/fr/accueil.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.admin.ch/gov/it/pagina-iniziale.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.admin.ch/gov/en/start.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="302" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>301</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Generalsekretariat EDI</name>
      <name lang="fr">Secrétariat général DFI</name>
      <name lang="it">Segreteria generale DFI</name>
      <name lang="en">General Secretariat FDHA</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="1070">
      <name lang="de">Der Bundesrat</name>
      <name lang="fr">Conseil fédéral</name>
      <name lang="it">Il Consiglio federale</name>
      <name lang="en">The Federal Council</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.admin.ch/gov/de/start.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.admin.ch/gov/fr/accueil.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.admin.ch/gov/it/pagina-iniziale.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.admin.ch/gov/en/start.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <department id="301">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement des Innern</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'intérieur</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'interno</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Home Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Der Bundesrat will 2025 einen nationalen Adressdienst einführen</title>
      <lead>Der Bundesrat will die Adressverwaltung vereinfachen und zu diesem Zweck einen nationalen Adressdienst (NAD) schaffen. Er hat an seiner Sitzung vom 10. Mai 2023 die Botschaft zum neuen Bundesgesetz über das nationale System zur Abfrage von Adressen natürlicher Personen zuhanden des Parlaments verabschiedet. Der nationale Adressdienst ermöglicht bestimmten Verwaltungsstellen sowie Dritten mit gesetzlichem Auftrag, die Adressdaten der Wohnbevölkerung gesamtschweizerisch abzufragen. Gegenwärtig sind Adressabfragen nur auf Gemeinde- oder Kantonsebene möglich.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Durch den nationalen Adressdienst (NAD) können administrative Prozesse vereinfacht und öffentliche Aufgaben effizienter wahrgenommen werden. Das Bundesamt für Statistik (BFS) verwendet für den NAD die adressrelevanten Teile der Personendaten, die im Rahmen des Registerharmonisierungsgesetzes (RHG) aus den kommunalen und kantonalen Einwohnerregistern quartalsweise an das BFS geliefert werden. Im NAD werden die Daten mit tagesaktuellen Mutationsmeldungen ergänzt. Dieser eCH-Meldungstyp kommt bereits beim Austausch zwischen Einwohnerregistern und Bundespersonenregistern zum Einsatz. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Der Zugriff auf den NAD wird entsprechend dem Datenschutz und abhängig vom Verwendungszweck eingeschränkt. Die Daten dürfen von den Nutzern ausschliesslich im Rahmen der Erfüllung ihres definierten gesetzlichen Auftrags bezogen werden. Das BFS vergibt die Zugriffsberechtigungen und kontrolliert die Einhaltung der Nutzungsbedingungen. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Effizientes, modernes Datenmanagement&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Der NAD vereinfacht in vielfältiger Weise die Adressverwaltung bei den Verwaltungsstellen auf allen drei Staatsebenen sowie bei den berechtigten Dritten mit gesetzlichem Auftrag. Einige Beispiele sind die Reduktion von Zahlungsverlusten wegen unzustellbarer Rechnungen an nicht mehr auffindbare Personen, die Verminderung von Retouren bei schriftlicher Korrespondenz und die Verringerung des Aufwands für den Aufbau und die Pflege von Schnittstellen sowie für das Datenmanagement. Hinzu kommt ein qualitativer Mehrwert in Form verbesserter Datenqualität, einheitlicherer Verwaltungspraxis sowie besserer Transparenz der Datenverwendung durch die Behörden. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Der Aufbau des NAD ist ein Projekt der Digitalen Verwaltung Schweiz (DVS) und wird durch diese finanziert. Er soll 2025 starten. Die Betriebskosten des NAD sollen durch Gebühren der Nutzer vollständig gedeckt werden. Die Einwohnerdienste der Gemeinden, die die Adressdaten in den Einwohnerregistern pflegen, können den NAD gebührenfrei nutzen.&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Manuela Lenk, BFS, Abteilung Interoperabilität und Register Tel.: +41 58 469 28 41, E-Mail: manuela.lenk@bfs.admin.ch Medienstelle BFS Tel.: +41 58 463 60 13, E-Mail: media@bfs.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>En 2025, le Conseil fédéral entend créer un service national des adresses</title>
      <lead>Le Conseil fédéral veut simplifier la gestion des adresses et prévoit de créer un service à cet effet. Lors de sa séance du 10 mai 2023, il a adopté à l’intention du Parlement le message concernant la loi fédérale sur le système national de consultation des adresses des personnes physiques. Le service national des adresses (SNA) permettra à certains services administratifs ainsi qu’aux tiers chargés d’un mandat légal de consulter les adresses de la population résidante de toute la Suisse. Consulter ces données n’est actuellement possible qu’au niveau communal ou cantonal.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Le service national des adresses (SNA) simplifiera les processus administratifs et permettra aux autorités de remplir leurs tâches plus efficacement. Pour alimenter le SNA, l’Office fédéral de la statistique (OFS) utilisera les données personnelles spécifiques aux adresses que les registres communaux et cantonaux des habitants lui livrent chaque trimestre dans le cadre de la loi sur l’harmonisation des registres (LHR). Le SNA complétera les données à l’aide de mutations quotidiennes, un type de message eCH d’ores et déjà utilisé dans les échanges entre les registres des habitants et les registres fédéraux des personnes. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;L’accès au SNA sera régi par les exigences de la protection des données et restreint en fonction de l’utilisation des données. Les utilisateurs pourront obtenir uniquement les données dont ils ont besoin pour s’acquitter des tâches que leur confie la loi. L’OFS octroiera les autorisations d’accès et vérifiera le respect des conditions d’utilisation. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Une gestion des données efficace et moderne&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Le SNA simplifiera à plus d’un titre la gestion des données pour les services administratifs des trois niveaux de l’État de même que pour les tiers chargés d’un mandat légal. Parmi les avantages de ce système, mentionnons la réduction des impayés dus à l’impossibilité de remettre une facture à des personnes désormais introuvables, la diminution du nombre de retours dans la correspondance écrite et la baisse des dépenses consacrées à la création et à la maintenance d’interfaces ainsi qu’à la gestion des données. Le SNA apportera aussi des plus-values qualitatives: amélioration de la qualité des données, uniformisation des pratiques administratives et utilisation plus transparente des données par les autorités.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;La mise en place du SNA est un projet de l’Administration numérique suisse (ANS), qui assure son financement. Le service devrait être opérationnel à partir de 2025 et les émoluments versés par les utilisateurs couvriront entièrement ses frais d’exploitation. Les services communaux des habitants, qui assurent l’actualisation des adresses dans les registres des habitants, pourront consulter le SNA gratuitement.&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Manuela Lenk, division Interopérabilité et registres, OFS tél.: +41 58 469 28 41 e-mail: manuela.lenk@bfs.admin.ch Service des médias de l’OFS tél. +41 58 463 60 13 e-mail: media@bfs.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Il Consiglio federale intende introdurre un servizio nazionale degli indirizzi nel 2025</title>
      <lead>Il Consiglio federale intende semplificare la gestione degli indirizzi istituendo a tal fine un servizio nazionale degli indirizzi (SNI). Nella seduta del 10 maggio 2023 ha infatti adottato il messaggio concernente la nuova legge federale sul sistema nazionale di consultazione degli indirizzi delle persone fisiche per sottoporlo al Parlamento. Il servizio nazionale degli indirizzi consentirà a determinati servizi amministrativi e ad altri enti con mandato legale, di consultare su scala nazionale i dati relativi agli indirizzi delle persone residenti in Svizzera. Attualmente è possibile consultare indirizzi solo a livello comunale o cantonale.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Il servizio nazionale degli indirizzi (SNI) permetterà di semplificare i processi e di sbrigare in maniera più efficiente i compiti della pubblica amministrazione. Per l'SNI, l'Ufficio federale di statistica (UST) utilizzerebbe le parti dei dati personali riguardanti l'indirizzo che gli vengono forniti a cadenza trimestrale dai registri comunali e cantonali degli abitanti nel quadro della legge sull'armonizzazione dei registri (LArRa). Tali dati verranno aggiornati quotidianamente nell'SNI grazie alle notifiche di mutazione. Questo tipo di notifiche eCH viene già utilizzato nello scambio di informazioni tra i registri degli abitanti e i registri di persone della Confederazione.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;L'accesso all'SNI sarà soggetto a limitazioni nel rispetto della protezione dei dati e in funzione dello scopo di utilizzo. I dati potranno essere ottenuti dagli utenti esclusivamente nell'ambito dell'adempimento del loro mandato legale. Sarà compito dell'UST rilasciare le autorizzazioni di accesso e controllare il rispetto delle condizioni di utilizzo.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Gestione dei dati efficiente e moderna&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;L'SNI semplifica in vari modi la gestione degli indirizzi ad opera dei servizi amministrativi di tutti e tre i livelli statali e ad opera degli altri enti autorizzati da un mandato legale. Alcuni esempi di semplificazione sono la riduzione dei mancati pagamenti dovuti all'impossibilità di recapitare le fatture a persone non più rintracciabili, la diminuzione del numero di lettere rispedite al mittente nell'ambito della corrispondenza postale e la riduzione dell'onere richiesto per la creazione e la manutenzione delle interfacce nonché di quello per la gestione dei dati. Inoltre, si ottiene un valore aggiunto anche in termini di qualità grazie alla migliore qualità dei dati, alla prassi amministrativa più uniforme e alla maggiore trasparenza nell'uso dei dati da parte delle autorità.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;La creazione dell'SNI è un progetto di Amministrazione digitale Svizzera (ADS) ed è finanziato da quest'ultima. L'inizio del progetto è previsto per il 2025. I costi di esercizio dell'SNI saranno interamente coperti da tasse a carico degli utenti. I servizi comunali degli abitanti, che amministrano i dati relativi agli indirizzi iscritti nei registri degli abitanti, potranno utilizzare l'SNI gratuitamente.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Manuela Lenk, UST, Divisione Interoperabilità e registri, tel.: +41 58 469 28 41, e-mail: manuela.lenk@bfs.admin.ch Ufficio stampa dell’UST, tel.: +41 58 463 60 13, e-mail: media@bfs.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>The Federal Council wishes to introduce a national address service in 2025</title>
      <lead>The Federal Council wants to simplify address management and to this end, create a national address service (NAS). At its meeting of 10 May 2023, it approved a dispatch to Parliament on the new Federal Act on the national system for the retrieval of addresses of natural persons. The national address service will enable certain administrative offices and third parties with a legal mandate to retrieve the address data of the resident population throughout Switzerland. Address retrieval is currently only possible at communal or cantonal level. </lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;The national address service (NAS) will simplify administrative processes and lend greater efficiency to public services. For the NAS, the Federal Statistical Office (FSO) uses the address-relevant parts of individual data provided on a quarterly basis to the FSO under the Register Harmonisation Act (RHA) from the communal and cantonal population registers. In the NAS, data are completed with change notifications updated on a daily basis. This eCH (government standards) notification type is already used when data from the communal and cantonal population registers are communicated to the federal population registers. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Access to the NAS is restricted according to data protection and depending on the purpose for which data is to be used. Users can only obtain data in order to fulfil their defined, statutory mandate. The FSO issues access rights and verifies compliance with the terms of use. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Efficient, modern data management&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The NAS offers multiple simplifications for address management in the administrative agencies at all three levels of government as well as for authorised third parties with a statutory mandate. Reductions will be achieved, for example, in payment losses due to undeliverable invoices to persons who can no longer be found, in returns in written correspondence and in the effort required for setting up and maintaining interfaces as well as for data management. In addition, the NAS brings added value in the form of improved data quality, more uniform administrative practice as well as improved transparency of data use by the authorities. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Construction of the NAS is a project of Digital Public Services Switzerland (DPSS) by whom it is funded. The start is planned for 2025. The operating costs of the NAS will be fully covered by user-paid fees. The residents' register office of the communes, which manages address data in the population registers, will be able to use the NAS free of charge.&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Manuela Lenk, FSO, Interoperability and Registers Division, tel.: +41 58 469 28 41, e-mail: manuela.lenk@bfs.admin.ch FSO Media Service, tel.: +41 58 463 60 13, e-mail: media@bfs.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="5">
        <name lang="de">Behörden</name>
        <name lang="fr">Autorités</name>
        <name lang="it">Autorità</name>
        <name lang="en">Authorities</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="10">
        <name lang="de">Bundesrat</name>
        <name lang="fr">Conseil fédéral</name>
        <name lang="it">Consiglio federale</name>
        <name lang="en">Federal Council</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
