<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="94713" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2023-05-01</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="1070" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>1070</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Der Bundesrat</name>
      <name lang="fr">Conseil fédéral</name>
      <name lang="it">Il Consiglio federale</name>
      <name lang="en">The Federal Council</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.admin.ch/gov/de/start.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.admin.ch/gov/fr/accueil.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.admin.ch/gov/it/pagina-iniziale.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.admin.ch/gov/en/start.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="201" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>201</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="701" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>701</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Wirtschaft, Bildung und Forschung</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'économie, de la formation et de la recherche</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'economia, della formazione e della ricerca</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Economic Affairs, Education and Research</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="101" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>101</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Bundeskanzlei</name>
      <name lang="fr">Chancellerie fédérale</name>
      <name lang="it">Cancelleria federale</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Chancellery</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.bk.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.bk.admin.ch/index.html?lang=fr</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.bk.admin.ch/index.html?lang=it</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.bk.admin.ch/index.html?lang=en</www>
      <email lang="de">infokomm@admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">infokomm@admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">infokomm@admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">infokomm@admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="301" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>301</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement des Innern</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'intérieur</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'interno</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Home Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="1070">
      <name lang="de">Der Bundesrat</name>
      <name lang="fr">Conseil fédéral</name>
      <name lang="it">Il Consiglio federale</name>
      <name lang="en">The Federal Council</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.admin.ch/gov/de/start.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.admin.ch/gov/fr/accueil.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.admin.ch/gov/it/pagina-iniziale.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.admin.ch/gov/en/start.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <department id="201">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <department id="701">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Wirtschaft, Bildung und Forschung</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'économie, de la formation et de la recherche</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'economia, della formazione e della ricerca</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Economic Affairs, Education and Research</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <department id="101">
      <name lang="de">Bundeskanzlei</name>
      <name lang="fr">Chancellerie fédérale</name>
      <name lang="it">Cancelleria federale</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Chancellery</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.bk.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.bk.admin.ch/index.html?lang=fr</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.bk.admin.ch/index.html?lang=it</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.bk.admin.ch/index.html?lang=en</www>
      <email lang="de">infokomm@admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">infokomm@admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">infokomm@admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">infokomm@admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <department id="301">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement des Innern</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'intérieur</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'interno</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Home Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Botsuanas Präsident Masisi auf Staatsbesuch in der Schweiz</title>
      <lead>Im Rahmen seines Staatsbesuchs in der Schweiz ist der botsuanische Präsident Mokgweetsi Eric Keabetswe Masisi mit seiner Gattin Neo Jane Masisi am Montag, 1. Mai 2023, vom Bundesrat in corpore empfangen worden. Anschliessend besprach der Präsident mit einer Delegation des Bundesrates unter der Leitung von Bundespräsident Alain Berset die Weiterentwicklung der bilateralen Beziehungen und die jeweiligen Positionen zu aktuellen globalen Themen. </lead>
      <text link="no">Zur Delegation der Landesregierung an den offiziellen Gesprächen gehörten auch Bundesrat Guy Parmelin, Vorsteher des Eidgenössischen Departements für Wirtschaft, Bildung und Forschung (WBF) und Bundesrat Ignazio Cassis, Vorsteher des Eidgenössischen Departements für auswärtige Angelegenheiten (EDA). Beide Seiten würdigten den Umstand, dass die bilateralen Beziehungen zwischen der Schweiz und Botsuana in den vergangenen Jahren deutlich intensiviert werden konnten. Mit der Unterzeichnung einer Absichtserklärung zur künftigen Zusammenarbeit wurde am Montag der nächste Schritt vollzogen. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Die Zusammenarbeit im Gesundheitsbereich ist seit längerem ein zentrales Element der bilateralen Beziehungen. Gemeinsames Ziel ist es hier, den globalen Gesundheitsschutz und die Weltgesundheitsorganisation (WHO) zu stärken. Künftig soll der Austausch etwa auch bei Kultur und Wirtschaft stärker vorangebracht werden. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Die Umsetzung der Panafrikanischen Freihandelszone (AfCFTA), deren Abkommen Botsuana im Februar ratifiziert hat, bezeichnete die Schweizer Delegation als Meilenstein der wirtschaftlichen Integration in Afrika mit einem beträchtlichen Potenzial auch für hiesige Unternehmen. Der Bundesrat unterstrich zudem die Bedeutung von Nachhaltigkeitsklauseln um die Gespräche über die Modernisierung des Freihandelsabkommens zwischen der Europäischen Freihandelsassoziation (EFTA) und der Zollunion des Südlichen Afrika (SACU) erfolgreich abzuschliessen. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Ein wichtiger Teil des Gesprächs am Montag war regionalen Fragen gewidmet. Die botsuanische Hauptstadt Gaborone ist Sitz der Entwicklungsgemeinschaft des südlichen Afrika (SADC) und die Beziehungen zu Regionalorganisationen wie der SADC bilden einen Schwerpunkt der Schweizer Subsahara-Afrika-Strategie für die Jahre 2021-2024. Die Delegation des Bundesrates würdigte die Rolle der SADC beim Aufbau von regionalen Kapazitäten, um den Multilateralismus innerhalb Afrikas zu stärken. Zur Sprache kamen zudem zahlreiche internationale Fragen und Herausforderungen, darunter die Zusammenarbeit beider Länder im Rahmen der UNO, Demokratie und Menschenrechte sowie die Auswirkungen des russischen Angriffskriegs in der Ukraine auf Afrika. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;b&gt;Programm unterstreicht demokratische Tradition&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Neben dem Willen des Bundesrates, die Chancen in der politischen und wirtschaftlichen Zusammenarbeit mit Botsuana zu nutzen und den Austausch mit dem afrikanischen Kontinent insgesamt auszubauen, würdigt die Einladung zum Staatsbesuch auch demokratische Traditionen. Mit den «Kgotlas» gibt es in Botsuana Versammlungen, die mit den Schweizer Landsgemeinden vergleichbar sind. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Bereits beim Besuch von Bundespräsident Berset in Botsuana im Februar wurden die diesbezüglichen Gemeinsamkeiten betont; eine «Kgotla» stand ebenfalls auf dem Programm. Im Rahmen des Gegenbesuchs waren Präsident Masisi und Bundespräsident Berset am Sonntag, 30. April, gemeinsam an der Landsgemeinde in Appenzell Innerrhoden. Sie besuchten ausserdem die Kunsthalle Appenzell, die als ehemalige Ziegelhütte auch ein bedeutendes Industriedenkmal ist. Abgeschlossen wird der Staatsbesuch am Montagabend mit dem traditionellen Galadiner im Bernerhof.</text>
      <contact>Kommunikation GS-EDI Tel. +41 58 462 85 79 media@gs-edi.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="248908">
        <title>Bilaterale Beziehungen Schweiz–Botsuana</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home/vertretungen-und-reisehinweise/botsuana/bilatereale-beziehungenschweizbotsuana.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Le président du Botswana en visite d’État en Suisse</title>
      <lead>Le président botswanais Mokgweetsi Eric Keabetswe Masisi et son épouse Neo Jane Masisi ont été reçus par le Conseil fédéral le lundi 1er mai 2023 dans le cadre d’une visite d’État en Suisse. Le président s’est ensuite entretenu avec une délégation du Conseil fédéral, sous la conduite du président de la Confédération Alain Berset, sur le développement des relations bilatérales et leurs positions respectives sur les questions mondiales actuelles.</lead>
      <text link="no">La délégation du gouvernement était composée du conseiller fédéral Guy Parmelin, chef du Département fédéral de l’économie, de la formation et de la recherche (DEFR), et du conseiller fédéral Ignazio Cassis, chef du Département fédéral des affaires étrangères (DFAE). Les deux parties se sont félicitées du renforcement des relations bilatérales entre la Suisse et le Botswana de ces dernières années. Une nouvelle étape a été franchie lundi avec la signature d’une déclaration d’intention relative à une future coopération.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;La coopération dans le domaine de la santé est depuis longtemps au cœur des relations bilatérales. L’objectif commun est d’améliorer la protection de la santé dans le monde et de soutenir l’Organisation mondiale de la santé (OMS). À l’avenir, les échanges devraient également être renforcés dans les domaines de la culture et de l’économie.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;La mise en œuvre de la zone de libre-échange continentale africaine (ZLECAf), sur laquelle porte l’accord ratifié par le Botswana en février, a été qualifiée par la délégation suisse de jalon clé sur la voie de l’intégration économique en Afrique. Le potentiel est considérable, y compris pour les entreprises suisses. Le Conseil fédéral a également souligné l’importance des clauses de durabilité dans la perspective de mener à bien les discussions sur la modernisation de l’accord de libre-échange entre l’Association européenne de libre-échange (AELE) et l’Union douanière de l’Afrique australe (SACU).&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Les discussions de lundi ont été consacrées en grande partie à des questions régionales. La capitale botswanaise Gaborone est le siège de la Communauté de développement de l’Afrique australe (SADC) et les relations avec les organisations régionales telles que la SADC constituent une priorité de la stratégie suisse pour l’Afrique subsaharienne pour les années 2021 à 2024. La délégation du Conseil fédéral a par ailleurs salué le rôle de la SADC dans le développement des capacités au niveau régional et par conséquent dans le renforcement du multilatéralisme en Afrique. De nombreuses questions et défis internationaux ont également été abordés, notamment la coopération entre les deux pays dans le cadre de l’ONU, la démocratie et les droits de l’homme ainsi que les conséquences de la guerre en Ukraine sur l’Afrique.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;b&gt;Hommage aux traditions démocratiques&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Outre la volonté du Conseil fédéral de mettre à profit les occasions de coopération politique et économique avec le Botswana et de développer les échanges avec tout le continent africain, cette invitation pour une visite d’État rend également hommage aux traditions démocratiques. Il existe au Botswana des assemblées, appelées kgotlas, comparables aux landsgemeindes suisses.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Les similitudes à cet égard avaient déjà été soulignées en février lors de la visite du président de la Confédération au Botswana, où il avait d’ailleurs pu assister à une kgotla. À l’occasion de cette visite de réciprocité, les deux présidents se sont rendus ensemble à la Landsgemeinde d’Appenzell Rhodes-Intérieures le dimanche 30 avril. Ils ont également visité la Kunsthalle d’Appenzell qui, en tant qu’ancienne tuilerie, constitue aussi un monument industriel remarquable. La visite d’État s’achèvera lundi soir par le traditionnel dîner de gala au Bernerhof.</text>
      <contact>Communication SG-DFI tél. +41 58 462 85 79 media@gs-edi.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="248909">
        <title>Relations bilatérales Suisse–Botswana</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae/representations-et-conseils-pour-les-voyages/botswana/suisse-botswana.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Il presidente del Botswana Masisi in visita di Stato in Svizzera</title>
      <lead>Lunedì 1° maggio 2023 il presidente del Botswana Mokgweetsi Eric Keabetswe Masisi e la consorte Neo Jane Masisi sono stati ricevuti dal Consiglio federale nel quadro di una visita di Stato. In seguito il presidente Masisi ha avuto colloqui con una delegazione del Consiglio federale guidata dal presidente della Confederazione Alain Berset. Nell’incontro sono stati discussi lo sviluppo delle relazioni bilaterali e le posizioni dei due Paesi su temi globali di attualità.</lead>
      <text link="no">La delegazione del Consiglio federale ai colloqui ufficiali era composta, oltre che del Presidente della Confederazione, dei consiglieri federali Guy Parmelin, capo del Dipartimento federale dell’economia, della formazione e della ricerca (DEFR), e Ignazio Cassis, capo del Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri (DFAE). Le parti hanno constatato con soddisfazione il rafforzamento delle relazioni bilaterali tra i due Paesi in corso da alcuni anni a questa parte. Un’ulteriore tappa di questo percorso è stata raggiunta lunedì con la firma di una dichiarazione d’intenti relativa alla cooperazione futura.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Da tempo già la collaborazione nel settore sanitario è un elemento centrale delle relazioni bilaterali, finalizzato a migliorare la protezione della salute nel mondo e a sostenere l’Organizzazione mondiale della sanità (OMS). In futuro i due Paesi intendono rafforzare gli scambi in particolare anche nei settori della cultura e dell’economia.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;La delegazione svizzera ha sottolineato il ruolo chiave che la realizzazione dell’area di libero scambio continentale africana (AfCFTA) svolge per l’integrazione economica in Africa. Lo scorso mese di febbraio il Botswana ha ratificato il relativo trattato, da cui vi è da attendersi un potenziale considerevole anche per le imprese svizzere. Il Consiglio federale ha inoltre evidenziato l’importanza delle clausole di sostenibilità nel contesto dei colloqui volti a modernizzare l’accordo di libero scambio tra l’Associazione europea di libero scambio (AELS) e l’Unione doganale dell’Africa australe (SACU).&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;I colloqui sono stati incentrati soprattutto su temi regionali. A Gaborone, capitale del Botswana, ha sede la Comunità di sviluppo dell’Africa australe (SADC) e le relazioni con le organizzazioni regionali come la SADC sono una delle priorità della strategia della Svizzera per l’Africa subsahariana 2021–2024. La delegazione del Consiglio federale ha evidenziato il ruolo importante svolto dalla SADC per lo sviluppo delle capacità a livello regionale e per il rafforzamento del multilateralismo tra gli Stati africani. Nei colloqui sono state discusse inoltre numerose questioni e sfide internazionali, in particolare la cooperazione tra i due Paesi nell’ambito dell’ONU, la democrazia e i diritti dell’uomo, come pure le ripercussioni sull’Africa dell’aggressione russa all’Ucraina.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;b&gt;Un omaggio alle tradizioni democratiche&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Oltre a rispecchiare la volontà del Consiglio federale di rafforzare la cooperazione politica ed economica con il Botswana e di promuovere in generale gli scambi con l’intero continente africano, l’invito per la visita di Stato è anche l’occasione per rendere omaggio alle tradizioni democratiche dei due Paesi. Il Botswana conosce infatti assemblee, denominate kgotla, paragonabili alla Landsgemeinde svizzera.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Le similitudini tra i due consessi politici sono state sottolineate già in occasione della visita del presidente della Confederazione nel Botswana in febbraio, dove la delegazione svizzera ha potuto assistere a una kgotla. Nell’ambito della presente visita di reciprocità, domenica 30 aprile i due Presidenti sono stati presenti alla Landsgemeinde di Appenzello Interno. In seguito hanno visitato, sempre ad Appenzello, il Kunsthalle, il museo d’arte situato in un’ex fornace per la produzione di tegole, oggi monumento storico industriale. La visita di Stato si concluderà lunedì sera con la tradizionale cena di gala al Bernerhof.</text>
      <contact>Comunicazione SG-DFI tel. +41 58 462 85 79 media@gs-edi.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="248910">
        <title>Relazioni bilaterali Svizzera–Botswana</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae/rappresentanze-e-consigli-di-viaggio/botswana/svizzera-botswana.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Botswana's President Masisi on a state visit to Switzerland</title>
      <lead>As part of his state visit to Switzerland, Botswana's President Mokgweetsi Eric Keabetswe Masisi and his wife Neo Jane Masisi were received by the entire Federal Council on Monday, 1 May. This was followed by a meeting between President Masisi and a delegation from the Federal Council, led by President Alain Berset, on the development of bilateral relations and their respective positions on current global issues. </lead>
      <text link="no">The Swiss government delegation at the official talks also included Federal Councillor Guy Parmelin, head of the Federal Department of Economic Affairs, Education and Research (EAER), and Federal Councillor Ignazio Cassis, head of the Federal Department of Foreign Affairs (FDFA). Both sides commended the marked progress in Swiss–Botswanan bilateral relations in recent years. A further step was taken on Monday with the signing of a memorandum of understanding on future cooperation. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Cooperation in the health sector has long been a central element of bilateral relations. The shared goal here is to strengthen global health protection and the World Health Organisation (WHO). Future activities will also include more cultural and economic exchange. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The Swiss delegation praised the implementation of the African Continental Free Trade Area (AfCFTA), which Botswana ratified in February, as a milestone for economic integration in Africa, with significant potential for local companies as well. The Federal Council also noted the importance of sustainability clauses in order to successfully conclude the talks on modernising the free trade agreement between the European Free Trade Association (EFTA) and the Southern African Customs Union (SACU). &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;A significant share of Monday's talks was devoted to regional issues. Botswana's capital Gaborone hosts the Southern African Development Community (SADC), and relations with regional organisations such as the SADC constitute a focal point of Switzerland's Sub-Saharan Africa Strategy for 2021–24. The Federal Council delegation acknowledged the SADC's role in building regional capacity to strengthen multilateralism within Africa. Numerous international issues and challenges were also addressed, including the two countries' cooperation within the UN framework, issues of democracy and human rights, and the impact of the Russian war of aggression in Ukraine on Africa. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;b&gt;Democratic traditions high on the agenda&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;In extending an invitation for a state visit, the Federal Council wished to express not only its resolve to seize the opportunities for political and economic cooperation with Botswana and develop relations with the African continent as a whole, but also its appreciation of the country's democratic traditions. One such example is the people's assemblies known as kgotlas in Botswana, comparable to the Landsgemeinde in Switzerland. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The similarities had already been noted during President Berset's visit to Botswana in February, which included a visit to a kgotla. As part of the return visit, President Masisi and President Berset attended the Landsgemeinde in Appenzell Innerrhoden on Sunday, 30 April. They also visited the Appenzell Kunsthalle, an art gallery housed in a former brick factory which is also an important industrial monument. The state visit concludes on Monday evening with the traditional gala dinner at the Bernerhof.</text>
      <contact>GS-FDHA Communications Tel. +41 58 462 85 79 media@gs-edi.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="248911">
        <title>Bilateral relations Switzerland–Botswana</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/fdfa/representations-and-travel-advice/botswana/switzerland-botswana.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="47">
        <name lang="de">Wirtschaft</name>
        <name lang="fr">Économie</name>
        <name lang="it">Economia</name>
        <name lang="en">Economic Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
