<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="95452" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2023-05-26</pubdate>
    <blocking-period>2023-05-26</blocking-period>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="1082" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>601</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössische Münzstätte Swissmint</name>
      <name lang="fr">Monnaie fédérale Swissmint</name>
      <name lang="it">Zecca federale Swissmint</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Mint Swissmint</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.swissmint.ch/</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.swissmint.ch/swissmint/fr/home.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.swissmint.ch/swissmint/it/home.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.swissmint.ch/swissmint/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@swissmint.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@swissmint.ch</email>
      <email lang="it"/>
      <email lang="en">info@swissmint.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="601">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Finanzdepartement</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des finances</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale delle finanze</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Finance</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.efd.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.dff.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.efd.admin.ch/efd/it/home.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.efd.admin.ch/efd/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern, 26.05.2023</city>
      <title>Ausgabe der neuesten Sondermünze: Die Silbermünze «Schweizer Schiesssportverband» zu Ehren des 200-jährigen Bestehens</title>
      <lead>Im November letzten Jahres wurde mit der neuen Marke «Eidgenössische Sondermünzen» eine neue Ära bei Swissmint, der Eidgenössischen Münzstätte, eingeläutet. Ab dem 2. Juni 2023 ist die neueste Kreation «Schweizer Schiesssportverband» als Vorankündigung des 200-jährigen Jubiläums des SSV erhältlich. </lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Unter dem Namen «Eidgenössische Sondermünzen» produziert die Swissmint exklusive und limitierte Sammlermünzen. Die neueste Sondermünze «Schweizer Schiesssportverband» ist die Erste der Dilogie zu Ehren des SSV. Die Swissmint huldigt damit dem Schweizer Schiesssportverband, der vom 16. – 18. August 2024 sein 200-jähriges Bestehen feiert: Der Schweizer Schiesssportverband zählt zu den ältesten Sportverbänden der Schweiz. Er wurde am ersten eidgenössischen Schützenfest in Aarau 1824 gegründet, damals noch unter dem Namen «Schweizer Schützenverein». Heute ist der SSV mit rund 130’000 Mitgliedern der fünftgrösste Sportverband der Schweiz. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Die Sondermünzen sollen Projekte, Vereine und Persönlichkeiten würdigen&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Die 20g schwere, mit Silber 999.9 legierte Sondermünze «Schweizer Schiesssportverband» zeigt auf der Bildseite eine künstlerische Interpretation eines Auges und einer Zielscheibe. «Der Schiesssport erfordert höchste Präzision und Konzentration, dabei spielt das Auge eine wichtige Rolle. Wir treffen mit unserem Design also voll ins Schwarze», scherzt Jan Niklas Betz, Stv. Geschäftsleiter &amp; Leiter Marketing/Verkauf von Swissmint. Für die Wertseite wurden Elemente aus dem Vorläufer des späteren Schützentalers – früher noch ohne Nominalwert –, der damals zur Feier des Churer Schützenfestes 1842 hergestellt wurde, übernommen. Zusätzlich ist der Nominalwert von CHF 20 abgebildet. Die Münze wird in einer Auflage von 15'000 Stück unzirkuliert und 5'250 Stück in der Qualität «Polierte Platte» angeboten. &lt;b&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Die Dilogie wird durch die Jubiläumsmünze «200 Jahre Schweizer Schiesssportverband» aus Gold, die dann erst im 2024 herausgegeben wird, vervollständigt. «Sondermünzen zum 200 Jahr-Jubiläum des Schweizer Schiesssportverbandes sind eine sehr schöne Idee. Auch der Grundgedanke, anlässlich dieses grossen Jubiläums gleich zwei Münzen, eine Silbermünze und eine Goldmünze zu prägen, gefällt. Dass die Silbermünze bereits im Vorjahr veröffentlicht wird, soll unter anderem die Aufmerksamkeit der Schweizer Bevölkerung auf das bevorstehende SSV Jubiläum steigern», erzählt Jürg Richter, Buchautor, ausgebildeter Numismatiker und Leiter der Sincona AG. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Jede dieser Sondermünzen ist ein Kleinstkunstwerk&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Die Eidgenössische Münzstätte Swissmint prägt im Auftrag der Schweizerischen Eidgenossenschaft den Schweizer Franken. Seit 1855 entsteht dieser im Herzen der Schweiz und seit 1906 im beliebten Kirchenfeldquartier in Bern. Seit 1936 prägt die Swissmint zudem Sondermünzen zur Erinnerung an bedeutende historische und kulturelle Ereignisse oder zu Ehren grosser Persönlichkeiten. Jede dieser Sondermünzen ist ein Kleinstkunstwerk – in künstlerisch und handwerklich einzigartiger Tradition. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;xxx&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Schweizer Schiesssportverband SSV&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Der Schweizer Schiesssportverband (SSV) mit Hauptsitz in Luzern ist die Dachorganisation der Schweizer Schützinnen und Schützen. Der SSV ist mit rund 130’000 Mitgliedern der fünftgrösste Sportverband der Schweiz. Rund 60’000 Schützinnen und Schützen haben eine Lizenz. Der im Jahr 1824 gegründete Verband zählt rund 2600 Schützenvereine, die durch 34 Mitgliederverbände vertreten werden. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Die grosse Jubiläumsfeier findet vom 16. – 18. August 2024 auf dem Festgelände Schachen, in Aarau, statt. Alle weiteren Informationen zu den Festivitäten finden Sie hier.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Eidgenössische Münzstätte Swissmint&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Die Eidgenössische Münzstätte Swissmint prägt die Schweizer Umlaufmünzen für den täglichen Zahlungsverkehr. Für den numismatischen Markt gibt Swissmint regelmässig Zirkulations- und Sondermünzen in besonderer Qualität heraus. Die Sondermünzen in Bimetall, Silber, Gold sind mit einem offiziellen, staatlich garantierten Nennwert versehen und werden in unterschiedlichen Qualitäten geprägt.&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>media@swissmint.ch</contact>
      <attachment id="252333">
        <title>Medienmitteilung</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>1511</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/78945.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="252337">
        <title>Factseet Silbermünze "Schweizer Schiesssportverband"</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>1347</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/78949.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <link id="252341">
        <title>Medienbilder</title>
        <uri>https://www.swissmint.ch/swissmint/de/home/aktuell/medienbilder.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne, 26.05.2023</city>
      <title>Émission d'une pièce commémorative en argent pour le bicentenaire de la Fédération sportive suisse de tir</title>
      <lead>En novembre 2022, la nouvelle marque «Eidgenössische Sondermünzen» a marqué le début d'une nouvelle ère pour Swissmint, la Monnaie fédérale. À partir du 2 juin 2023, elle lance une nouvelle série spéciale en prélude au bicentenaire de la Fédération sportive suisse de tir.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Swissmint produit des pièces de collection exclusives, frappées en nombre limité, sous le nom de «Eidgenössische Sondermünzen». La toute nouvelle pièce de monnaie commémorative «Fédération sportive suisse de tir» est la première d'une série de deux pièces que Swissmint émet en l'honneur de l'organisation, qui fêtera son 200e anniversaire du 16 au 18 août 2024: la Fédération sportive suisse de tir (FST) compte parmi les plus anciennes fédérations sportives de Suisse. Elle a été fondée en 1824 à Aarau lors de la première Fête fédérale de tir et portait à l'époque le nom de «Société suisse des tireurs». Comptant aujourd'hui quelque 130 000 membres, c'est la cinquième plus grande fédération sportive de Suisse.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Des monnaies spéciales pour célébrer des projets, des fédérations ou des personnalités&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;La pièce spéciale «Fédération sportive suisse de tir» est en argent 999,9 ‰ et pèse 20 grammes. L'avers présente l'interprétation artistique d'un œil et d'une cible. «Le tir sportif nécessite une précision et une concentration extrêmes, et l'œil y joue un rôle essentiel. Notre motif met donc dans le mille!», plaisante Jan Niklas Betz, directeur suppléant et chef de la division Marketing et ventes de Swissmint. «Pour le revers, nous avons repris des éléments de la pièce - alors sans valeur nominale - produite pour célébrer la fête de tir de Coire en 1842, qui deviendra plus tard l'écu de tir.» La pièce comporte également sa valeur faciale (20 francs suisses). Le tirage comprendra 15 000 pièces non mises en circulation et 5250 pièces en qualité flan bruni.&lt;b&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Cette pièce en argent sera complétée en 2024 par la pièce commémorative «Bicentenaire de la Fédération sportive suisse de tir» en or. «Les pièces commémoratives du bicentenaire de la Fédération sportive suisse de tir forment un très beau projet. Nous avons aimé l'idée de frapper deux pièces - une en argent et une en or - pour marquer cette occasion. L'émission de la pièce d'argent une année plus tôt a notamment pour but d'attirer l'attention de la population suisse sur cet anniversaire de la FST», explique Jürg Richter, auteur de livres, numismate diplômé et directeur de Sincona SA.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Chaque pièce spéciale est une œuvre d'art miniature&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Swissmint frappe le franc suisse pour le compte de la Confédération, exécutant ses activités au cœur de la Suisse depuis 1855 et dans le fameux quartier de Kirchenfeld, à Berne, depuis 1906. Depuis 1936, Swissmint émet également des monnaies spéciales pour commémorer des événements historiques et culturels importants ou pour honorer des personnages remarquables. Chacune de ces pièces est une œuvre d'art miniature qui s'inscrit dans une tradition artistique et artisanale unique.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;xxx&lt;/i&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Fédération sportive suisse de tir&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;La Fédération sportive suisse de tir (FST), dont le siège est à Lucerne, est l'organisation faîtière des tireurs suisses. Comptant quelque 130 000 membres, c'est la cinquième plus grande fédération sportive de Suisse. Environ 60 000 tireurs sont titulaires d'une licence. Fondée en 1824, la fédération compte aujourd'hui environ 2600 sociétés de tir, représentées par 34 associations affiliées.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;La fête du bicentenaire aura lieu du 16 au 18 août 2024 sur l'aire de fête de Schachen, à Aarau. Vous trouverez toutes les informations complémentaires sur les festivités en cliquant sur le lien suivant: https://fst200.ch/fete.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Monnaie fédérale Swissmint&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Swissmint frappe les pièces de monnaie du pays qui sont utilisées dans les opérations quotidiennes de paiement. Elle émet aussi régulièrement des monnaies courantes ou spéciales de qualité particulière pour le marché de la numismatique. Les pièces spéciales bimétalliques, tout comme celles en argent ou en or, ont une valeur nominale officielle garantie par l'État et se déclinent en différentes qualités de frappe.&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>media@swissmint.ch</contact>
      <attachment id="252334">
        <title>Communiqué de presse</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>1513</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/78946.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="252338">
        <title>Fiche d'information pièce d'argent "Fédération sportive suisse de tir"</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>1345</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/78950.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <link id="252342">
        <title>Photos de presse</title>
        <uri>https://www.swissmint.ch/swissmint/fr/home/aktuell/medienbilder.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Bern, 26.05.2023</city>
      <title>Emissione di una moneta speciale in argento per il bicentenario della Federazione sportiva svizzera di tiro</title>
      <lead>Il lancio del marchio «Eidgenössische Sondermünzen», avvenuto nel novembre 2022, segna l’inizio di una nuova era per la Zecca federale Swissmint. Dal 2 giugno 2023 sarà disponibile una nuova moneta, emessa per il bicentenario della Federazione sportiva svizzera di tiro (FST) che si celebrerà l’anno prossimo.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Swissmint produce monete da collezione esclusive in edizione limitata sotto il marchio «Eidgenössische Sondermünzen». La nuova moneta speciale è la prima delle due monete che Swissmint emette in onore della FST, che celebrerà il suo bicentenario dal 16 al 18 agosto 2024. La FST è una delle associazioni sportive più antiche della Svizzera. Fondata nel 1824 in occasione della prima Festa federale di tiro ad Aarau, all’epoca era ancora denominata Società svizzera di tiro. Oggi la FST conta circa 130 000 membri ed è la quinta associazione sportiva svizzera per importanza.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Monete speciali: un modo per commemorare progetti, associazioni e personaggi famosi&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;La moneta speciale sulla FST, realizzata in argento con un titolo di 999,9 millesimi, pesa 20 grammi. Sul dritto della moneta sono raffigurati un occhio stilizzato e un bersaglio. «Il tiro sportivo richiede una precisione e una concentrazione estremamente elevate, ma anche un occhio acuto. Il motivo raffigurato nella moneta ha dunque fatto centro», conclude metaforicamente Jan Niklas Betz, direttore supplente e capo dell’unità Marketing e vendita di Swissmint. Sul rovescio della moneta sono stati ripresi alcuni elementi dell’antesignano del futuro tallero di tiro, allora privo di valore nominale, coniato nel 1842 per celebrare la Festa di tiro di Coira. Sulla moneta è impresso anche il valore nominale di 20 franchi svizzeri. La tiratura comprende 15 000 pezzi nella qualità «non messa in circolazione» e 5250 pezzi nella qualità «fondo specchio».&lt;b&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Questa moneta in argento sarà completata dalla moneta commemorativa in oro, che sarà emessa nel 2024, anno in cui ricorre il bicentenario della FST. «L’emissione delle monete speciali per il bicentenario della FST è una splendida iniziativa. Abbiamo apprezzato anche l’idea di coniare due monete, una in argento e l’altra in oro, per sottolineare l’importanza di questo evento. L’emissione della moneta in argento nell’anno che precede l’anniversario consente tra l’altro di richiamare l’attenzione della popolazione svizzera sull’imminente bicentenario della FST», ha affermato Jürg Richter, numismatico professionista, autore di pubblicazioni specialistiche nonché direttore della società SINCONA Swiss International Coin Auction AG.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Ogni moneta speciale è una piccola opera d’arte&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Swissmint effettua, su mandato della Confederazione Svizzera, la coniazione di tutte le monete del franco svizzero. Fondata nel 1855 nel cuore della Svizzera, dal 1906 ha sede nel quartiere Kirchenfeld a Berna. Inoltre, dal 1936 Swissmint conia monete speciali per commemorare eventi storici e culturali significativi o in onore di personaggi famosi. Ognuna di queste monete è una piccola opera d’arte, frutto di una tradizione artistica e artigianale unica nel suo genere.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;xxx&lt;/i&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Federazione sportiva svizzera di tiro (FST)&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;La FST, con sede principale a Lucerna, è l’organizzazione mantello dei tiratori svizzeri. Con circa 130 000 membri, è la quinta associazione sportiva svizzera per importanza. Circa 60 000 tiratori sono titolari di una licenza. Fondata nel 1824, la FST conta circa 2600 associazioni di tiro, rappresentate da 34 associazioni affiliate.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;I festeggiamenti per il bicentenario si svolgeranno dal 16 al 18 agosto 2024 ad Aarau, nell’area sportivo-ricreativa del quartiere Schachen. Maggiori informazioni al riguardo sono disponibili qui (in tedesco e francese).&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Zecca federale Swissmint&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;La Zecca federale Swissmint conia le monete circolanti svizzere destinate al traffico quotidiano dei pagamenti. Inoltre, per il mercato numismatico essa emette regolarmente monete speciali e monete circolanti di elevata qualità. Le monete speciali (bimetalliche, in argento o in oro) hanno un valore nominale garantito dallo Stato e sono coniate in diverse qualità.&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>media@swissmint.ch</contact>
      <attachment id="252335">
        <title>Comunicato stampa</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>1506</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/78947.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="252339">
        <title>Foglio informativo moneta d'argento "Federazione sportiva svizzera di tiro"</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>1343</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/78951.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <link id="252343">
        <title>Immagini per la stampa</title>
        <uri>https://www.swissmint.ch/swissmint/it/home/aktuell/medienbilder.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern, 26.05.2023</city>
      <title>Latest special coin to be issued: silver coin in honour of the Swiss Shooting Sports Federation's 200th anniversary</title>
      <lead>In November last year, a new era was ushered in at Swissmint, the Federal Mint, with the new Swiss special coins brand. From 2 June 2023, the latest creation, Swiss Shooting Sports Federation, will be available to mark the 200th anniversary of the organisation. </lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Swissmint produces exclusive and limited-edition collector coins under the name Swiss special coins. The latest Swiss Shooting Sports Federation special coin is the first of the two-part series in honour of the organisation. With it, Swissmint pays homage to the Swiss Shooting Sports Federation, which will celebrate its 200th anniversary from 16 to 18 August 2024: The Swiss Shooting Sports Federation is one of the oldest sports federations in Switzerland. It was founded at the first federal shooting festival in Aarau in 1824, under the name "Swiss Shooting Association". Today, it has around 130,000 members, making it the fifth largest sports federation in Switzerland. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Special coins are intended to honour projects, associations and personalities&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The 20g Swiss Shooting Sports Federation special coin, alloyed with 999.9 silver, shows an artist's interpretation of an eye and a target on the obverse. "Shooting sports require the highest precision and concentration, and the eye plays an important role in this. Our design is right on target," jokes Jan Niklas Betz, Deputy General Manager &amp; Head of Marketing/Sales at Swissmint. For the reverse side, elements were taken from the predecessor of what would later become the shooting taler – which did not have any nominal value at the time – that was produced to celebrate the Chur shooting festival in 1842. In addition, the nominal value of CHF 20 is depicted. 15,000 uncirculated coins and 5,250 coins in proof quality will be issued. &lt;b&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The anniversary "200 years of the Swiss Shooting Sports Federation" gold coin, to be issued in 2024, will complete the two-part series. "Special coins to mark the 200th anniversary of the Swiss Shooting Sports Federation are a very nice idea. We also loved the idea of minting two coins, a silver coin and a gold coin, to mark this great anniversary. The fact that the silver coin is being released in the year before the event is intended, among other things, to draw the attention of the Swiss population to the Federation's upcoming anniversary," says Jürg Richter, book author, qualified numismatist and head of Sincona AG. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Each of these special coins is a miniature work of art&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The Federal Mint Swissmint produces Swiss franc coins on behalf of the Swiss Confederation. These have been created in the heart of Switzerland since 1855, and in the popular Kirchenfeld district of Bern since 1906. Since 1936 Swissmint has also minted special coins to commemorate important historical and cultural events and to honour prominent figures. Each of these special coins is a miniature work of art in a unique tradition of artistry and craftsmanship. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;xxx&lt;/i&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Swiss Shooting Sports Federation&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The Swiss Shooting Sports Federation (SSV), with its headquarters in Lucerne, is the umbrella organisation for Swiss shooting sports. With around 130,000 members, the Swiss Shooting Sports Federation is the fifth-largest sports federation in Switzerland. Around 60,000 marksmen and women hold a licence. Founded in 1824, the Federation now comprises around 2,600 shooting clubs represented by 34 member associations.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The main anniversary celebration will take place from 16 to 18 August 2024 at the Schachen festival grounds in Aarau. All further information on the festivities can be found here.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Federal Mint Swissmint&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The Federal Mint Swissmint produces the country's coins for use in everyday payment transactions. It also regularly issues circulation and special coins for the numismatic market. Special coins in bimetal, silver or gold bear an official, state-guaranteed, nominal value and are available in various minting qualities.&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>media@swissmint.ch</contact>
      <attachment id="252336">
        <title>Press release</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>1509</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/78948.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="252340">
        <title>Fact sheet "Swiss Shooting Sports Federation" silver coin</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>1343</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/78952.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <link id="252345">
        <title>Press pictures</title>
        <uri>https://www.swissmint.ch/swissmint/en/home/aktuell/medienbilder.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="3">
        <name lang="de">Armee</name>
        <name lang="fr">Armée</name>
        <name lang="it">Esercito</name>
        <name lang="en">Armed Forces</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="7">
        <name lang="de">Bibliotheken und Archive</name>
        <name lang="fr">Bibliothèques et archives</name>
        <name lang="it">Biblioteche e archivi</name>
        <name lang="en">Libraries and Archives</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="13">
        <name lang="de">Öffentliche Finanzen</name>
        <name lang="fr">Finances publiques</name>
        <name lang="it">Finanze pubbliche</name>
        <name lang="en">Public Finances</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="18">
        <name lang="de">Kultur</name>
        <name lang="fr">Culture</name>
        <name lang="it">Cultura</name>
        <name lang="en">Culture</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="40">
        <name lang="de">Sicherheit</name>
        <name lang="fr">Sécurité</name>
        <name lang="it">Sicurezza</name>
        <name lang="en">Security</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="42">
        <name lang="de">Sport</name>
        <name lang="fr">Sport</name>
        <name lang="it">Sport</name>
        <name lang="en">Sport</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
