<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="95478" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2023-05-30</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="506" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>501</department-id>
      <name lang="de">armasuisse</name>
      <name lang="fr">Armasuisse</name>
      <name lang="it">Armasuisse</name>
      <name lang="en">Armasuisse</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.ar.admin.ch/</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.ar.admin.ch/</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.ar.admin.ch/</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.ar.admin.ch/</www>
      <email lang="de">info@armasuisse.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@armasuisse.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@armasuisse.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@armasuisse.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="502" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>501</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Generalsekretariat VBS</name>
      <name lang="fr">Secrétariat général du DDPS</name>
      <name lang="it">Segreteria generale del DDPS</name>
      <name lang="en">General Secretariat DDPS</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.vbs.admin.ch/</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.vbs.admin.ch/</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.vbs.admin.ch/</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.vbs.admin.ch/</www>
      <email lang="de">postmaster.vbs@gs-vbs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">postmaster.vbs@gs-vbs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">postmaster.vbs@gs-vbs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">postmaster.vbs@gs-vbs.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="505" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>501</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Gruppe Verteidigung</name>
      <name lang="fr">Groupement de la Défense</name>
      <name lang="it">Aggruppamento Difesa</name>
      <name lang="en">Defence</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.vtg.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.vtg.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.vtg.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.vtg.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@vtg.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@vtg.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@vtg.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@vtg.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="501">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Verteidigung, Bevölkerungsschutz und Sport</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de la défense, de la protection de la population et des sports</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale della difesa, della protezione della popolazione e dello sport</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Defence, Civil Protection and Sports DDPS</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.vbs.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.vbs.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.vbs.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.vbs.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@gs-vbs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@gs-vbs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@gs-vbs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@gs-vbs.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Neue Webseite «Militärmarken» zeigt Umsetzung der Militärmarkenstrategie von armasuisse</title>
      <lead>Für den Schutz, die Verteidigung und die Lizenzierung der Militärmarken, insbesondere «Swiss Army», «Swiss Military» und «Swiss Air Force», ist das Bundesamt für Rüstung armasuisse zuständig. Die neue Webseite «Militärmarken» zeigt die Strategie und Umsetzung, die zur Bewirtschaftung und zum Schutz der Militärmarken verfolgt wird. Mit der transparenten Informationspolitik soll der Öffentlichkeit den rechtmässigen Gebrauch der Militärmarken nähergebracht werden. </lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Das Bundesamt für Rüstung armasuisse ist beauftragt, die Militärmarken zu schützen, gegenüber unberechtigten Dritten durchzusetzen und zu lizenzieren. Der Auftrag geht auf eine Motion aus dem Jahre 2012 zurück und betrifft insbesondere die Marken «Swiss Army», «Swiss Military» und «Swiss Air Force».&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Gemäss der aktuellen Rechtsprechung des Bundesverwaltungsgerichts gelten die Militärmarken des Bundes als amtliche Zeichen. Sie sind im Namen der Schweizerischen Eidgenossenschaft im Markenregister eingetragen. Nur Firmen, die einen Lizenzvertrag unterzeichnet haben, sind berechtigt die Militärmarken für kommerzielle Zwecke zu nutzen. Auf der Webseite ist transparent einsehbar, welche Firmen für welche Militärmarken einen Lizenzvertrag abgeschlossen haben.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Im Rahmen der Lizenzverträge erfolgt der Markenschutz und die -verteidigung in Zusammenarbeit mit dem Institut für geistiges Eigentum, den Vertragspartnern von armasuisse und mandatierten Markenanwälten im In- und Ausland. Der globale Markenschutz, die Markenbewirtschaftung sowie Prozesskosten zur Verteidigung der geschützten Militärmarken werden mit den Lizenzeinnahmen finanziert. Restbeträge werden jährlich in die Bundeskasse überwiesen.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Mit der Webseite «Militärmarken» sensibilisiert armasuisse über den berechtigten kommerziellen Einsatz der Militärmarken durch Dritte. Zudem zeigt sie ihre Handlungen und Vorgehensweise hinsichtlich der konsequenten Durchsetzung der Markenpolitik zum Schutz der Militärmarken auf.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Jacqueline Stampfli Stv. Leiterin Kommunikation armasuisse +41 58 464 60 42</contact>
      <link id="252470">
        <title>Militärmarken</title>
        <uri>https://www.ar.admin.ch/de/militaermarken.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Le nouveau site Web «Marques militaires» présente la mise en œuvre de la stratégie d’armasuisse applicable aux marques militaires</title>
      <lead>L’Office fédéral de l'armement armasuisse est responsable de la protection, de la défense et de la commercialisation des marques militaires, et en particulier de «Swiss Army», «Swiss Military» et «Swiss Air Force». Le nouveau site Web «Marques militaires» présente la stratégie poursuivie et sa mise en œuvre pour la gestion et la protection des marques militaires. Cette politique d’information transparente vise à familiariser le grand public à l’emploi légitime des marques militaires.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;L’Office fédéral de l’armement armasuisse a pour mission de protéger les marques militaires, de les imposer vis-à-vis de tiers non autorisés et de concéder des licences pour celles-ci. Fruit d’une motion de 2012, ce mandat concerne en particulier les marques «Swiss Army», «Swiss Military» et «Swiss Air Force».&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Selon la jurisprudence actuelle du Tribunal fédéral administratif, les marques militaires de la Confédération sont considérées comme des signes officiels. Elles sont déposées au registre des marques au nom de la Confédération suisse. Seules les entreprises ayant signé un contrat de licence sont autorisées à utiliser les marques militaires à des fins commerciales. Le site Web indique avec transparence quelles entreprises ont conclu un contrat de licence et pour quelles marques militaires.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Dans le cadre de tels contrats, la protection et la défense des marques s’effectue en collaboration avec l’Institut Fédéral de la Propriété Intellectuelle, les cocontractants d’armasuisse et des avocats en droit des marques mandatés en Suisse et à l’étranger. La protection mondiale des marques, la gestion des marques et les frais de justice pour la défense des marques militaires protégées sont financés par les recettes des droits de licences. Les sommes restantes sont encaissées annuellement par la Confédération.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;À travers son site Web «Marques militaires», armasuisse entend sensibiliser à l’emploi commercial légitime des marques militaires par des tiers. Par ailleurs, elle détaille ses actions et ses approches pour l’application rigoureuse de la politique de marques aux fins de la protection des marques militaires.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Jacqueline Stampfli-Bieri Suppl. chef de la communication d’armasuisse +41 58 464 60 42</contact>
      <link id="252471">
        <title>Marques militaires</title>
        <uri>https://www.ar.admin.ch/fr/militaermarken.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Il nuovo sito web «Marchi militari» presenta la realizzazione della strategia di armasuisse per i marchi militari</title>
      <lead>L'Ufficio federale dell’armamento armasuisse è responsabile della protezione, della difesa e della concessione di licenze dei marchi militari, in particolare per «Swiss Army», «Swiss Military» e «Swiss Air Force». Il nuovo sito web «Marchi militari» illustra la strategia e la sua attuazione per la gestione e la tutela dei marchi militari. Una politica di informazione trasparente mira a far conoscere all’opinione pubblica l’importanza di un uso regolamentato dei marchi militari. </lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;L'Ufficio federale dell'armamento armasuisse ha ricevuto l’incarico di proteggere i marchi militari, di farli valere nei confronti di terzi non autorizzati e di concederli in licenza. Una mozione del 2012 sta alla base del mandato, che riguarda in particolare i marchi «Swiss Army», «Swiss Military» e «Swiss Air Force».&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Secondo l'attuale giurisprudenza del Tribunale amministrativo federale, i marchi militari della Confederazione sono considerati segni ufficiali e sono iscritti nel registro dei marchi a nome della Confederazione Svizzera. Solo le aziende che hanno firmato un contratto di licenza sono autorizzate a utilizzare i marchi militari per scopi commerciali. Sul sito web sono riportate informazioni trasparenti su quali aziende hanno stipulato un contratto di licenza e per quali marchi militari.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Nell’ambito dei contratti di licenza, la protezione e la difesa dei marchi avvengono in collaborazione con l’Istituto per la proprietà intellettuale, con i partner contrattuali di armasuisse e con gli avvocati specializzati nella tutela dei marchi incaricati in Svizzera e all’estero. La protezione globale dei marchi, la gestione degli stessi e le spese legali per la difesa dei marchi militari protetti sono finanziate con i ricavi delle licenze. Le rimanenze vengono trasferite annualmente alla cassa federale. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Con il sito web «Marchi militari» armasuisse intende sensibilizzare circa la fondatezza di un uso commerciale dei marchi da parte di terzi. Presenta inoltre il proprio operato e le procedure per una realizzazione coerente della politica dei marchi a protezione dei marchi militari.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Jacqueline Stampfli Sost. capo Comunicazione armasuisse +41 58 464 60 42</contact>
      <link id="252472">
        <title>Marchi militari</title>
        <uri>https://www.ar.admin.ch/it/militaermarken.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>New website “Military brands” shows armasuisse’s implementation of the military brand strategy</title>
      <lead>The Federal Office for Defence Procurement armasuisse is responsible for the protection, defence and licensing of the military brands, in particular “Swiss Army”, “Swiss Military” and “Swiss Air Force”. The new website “Military brands” shows the strategy and implementation that is being pursued for the management and protection of the military brands. The aim of the transparent information policy is to make the public aware of the lawful use of the military brands.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;The Federal Office for Defence Procurement armasuisse is tasked with protecting military brands, enforcing them against unauthorised third parties and licensing them. The mandate goes back to a motion from 2012 and concerns in particular the brands “Swiss Army”, “Swiss Military” and “Swiss Air Force”.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;According to the current jurisdiction of the Federal Administrative Court, the military brands are considered to be official signs of the Confederation. They are entered in the trademark register in the name of the Swiss Confederation. Only companies which have signed a licence agreement are entitled to use the military brands for commercial purposes. Transparent information is available on the website which shows which companies have concluded a licence agreement for which military brands.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Under the licence agreements, brand protection and defence is carried out in cooperation with the Swiss Federal Institute of Intellectual Property, armasuisse’s contractual partners and mandated brand lawyers at home and abroad. The global brand protection, brand management and legal costs for defending the protected military brands will be financed using the licensing income. Remaining amounts will be transferred annually to the Federal Treasury.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;With the website “Military brands”, armasuisse will raise awareness of the authorised commercial use of military brands by third parties. In addition, it shows its actions and procedures with regard to the consistent enforcement of the brand policy for protecting the military brands.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Jacqueline Stampfli Deputy Head of Communications armasuisse +41 58 464 60 42</contact>
      <link id="252473">
        <title>Military brands</title>
        <uri>https://www.ar.admin.ch/en/militaermarken.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <keywords>
      <keyword id="5180" org-id="505">
        <name lang="de">Armee</name>
        <name lang="fr">Armée</name>
        <name lang="it">Esercito</name>
        <name lang="en">armed forces</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="5310" org-id="505">
        <name lang="de">Rüstung / Beschaffung</name>
        <name lang="fr">Armement / Acquisition d'armement</name>
        <name lang="it">Armamento / Acquisto d'armamenti</name>
        <name lang="en">Armament / Procurement</name>
      </keyword>
    </keywords>
    <topics>
      <topic id="3">
        <name lang="de">Armee</name>
        <name lang="fr">Armée</name>
        <name lang="it">Esercito</name>
        <name lang="en">Armed Forces</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
