<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="95045" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2023-05-10</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="1070" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>1070</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Der Bundesrat</name>
      <name lang="fr">Conseil fédéral</name>
      <name lang="it">Il Consiglio federale</name>
      <name lang="en">The Federal Council</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.admin.ch/gov/de/start.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.admin.ch/gov/fr/accueil.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.admin.ch/gov/it/pagina-iniziale.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.admin.ch/gov/en/start.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="yes" id="703" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>701</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Staatssekretariat für Wirtschaft</name>
      <name lang="fr">Secrétariat d'Etat à l'économie</name>
      <name lang="it">Segreteria di Stato dell'economia</name>
      <name lang="en">State Secretariat for Economic Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.seco.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.seco.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.seco.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.seco.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@seco.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@seco.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@seco.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@seco.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="1070">
      <name lang="de">Der Bundesrat</name>
      <name lang="fr">Conseil fédéral</name>
      <name lang="it">Il Consiglio federale</name>
      <name lang="en">The Federal Council</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.admin.ch/gov/de/start.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.admin.ch/gov/fr/accueil.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.admin.ch/gov/it/pagina-iniziale.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.admin.ch/gov/en/start.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <department id="701">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Wirtschaft, Bildung und Forschung</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'économie, de la formation et de la recherche</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'economia, della formazione e della ricerca</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Economic Affairs, Education and Research</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>7,4 Milliarden Franken der Zentralbank der Russischen Föderation in der Schweiz</title>
      <lead>Die Gesamthöhe der in der Schweiz gehaltenen Reserven und Vermögenswerte der Zentralbank der Russischen Föderation beträgt rund 7,4 Milliarden Schweizer Franken. Das WBF hat den Bundesrat am 10. Mai 2023 darüber informiert. Der Bundesrat hatte am 29. März entschieden, die Reserven und Vermögenswerte einer Meldepflicht zu unterstellen. </lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Personen, Organisationen und Einrichtungen, die Reserven und Vermögenswerte der Zentralbank der Russischen Föderation halten, kontrollieren oder davon Gegenpartei sind, mussten dies dem SECO bis zum 12. April 2023 melden. Die Meldepflicht gilt gemäss den EU-Sanktionen gegenüber Russland auch in der EU. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Die Gesamthöhe der gemeldeten Reserven und Vermögenswerte der Zentralbank der Russischen Föderation in der Schweiz beträgt rund 7,4 Milliarden Schweizer Franken. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Jegliche Transaktionen im Zusammenhang mit der Verwaltung von Reserven und Vermögenswerten der Zentralbank der Russischen Föderation sind seit dem 25. März 2022 verboten. Somit handelt es sich bei Vermögenswerten der Zentralbank der Russischen Föderation um bewegungsunfähige Vermögenswerte. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Diese Summe der &lt;b&gt;&lt;i&gt;bewegungsunfähigen&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/b&gt; Vermögenswerte ist von der Summe der &lt;b&gt;&lt;i&gt;gesperrten&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/b&gt; Gelder und Vermögenswerte in der Schweiz (7,5 Mia. Schweizer Franken) zu unterscheiden. Letztere befinden sich im Eigentum oder unter Kontrolle von sanktionierten Personen, Unternehmen oder Organisationen und unterliegen der Vermögenssperre gemäss Artikel 15 der Verordnung über Massnahmen im Zusammenhang mit der Situation in der Ukraine.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Meldungen über die Reserven und Vermögenswerte der Zentralbank der Russischen Föderation sind auch künftig verpflichtend. Sie erfolgen regulär quartalsweise. Im Falle eines aussergewöhnlichen und unvorhergesehenen Verlusts oder Schadens besteht eine unverzügliche Meldepflicht an das SECO. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;In der EU laufen Diskussionen darüber, ob Vermögenswerte der Zentralbank der Russischen Föderation für Investitionen genutzt und deren Erträge für den Wiederaufbau der Ukraine verwendet werden sollen. Die Schweiz verfolgt diese Diskussionen eng.&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Rückfragen Medien: Kommunikation WBF info@gs-wbf.admin.ch 058 462 20 07 Rückfragen Unternehmen: sanctions@seco.admin.ch 058 464 08 12</contact>
      <link id="250223">
        <title>Massnahmen im Zusammenhang mit der Situation in der Ukraine (admin.ch)</title>
        <uri>https://bit.ly/2mr1pop</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>7,4 milliards de francs de la Banque centrale de la Fédération de Russie en Suisse</title>
      <lead>La somme totale des réserves et des actifs de la Banque centrale de la Fédération de Russie détenus en Suisse s’élève à quelque 7,4 milliards de francs. Le Département fédéral de l’économie, de la formation et de la recherche (DEFR) en a informé le Conseil fédéral le 10 mai 2023. Celui-ci avait décidé le 29 mars dernier de soumettre les réserves et les actifs à une déclaration obligatoire. </lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Les personnes, entités et organismes qui détiennent ou contrôlent des réserves et des actifs de la Banque centrale de la Fédération de Russie ou qui sont contreparties à ces réserves et actifs ont dû le déclarer au SECO le 12 avril 2023 au plus tard. L'obligation de déclarer est également applicable au sein de l'UE, conformément aux sanctions prononcées par celle-ci.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;La somme totale des réserves et des actifs de la Banque centrale de la Fédération de Russie déclarés en Suisse s'élève à quelque 7,4 milliards de francs.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Les transactions liées à la gestion des réserves et des actifs de la Banque centrale de la Fédération de Russie sont interdites depuis le 25 mars 2022. Les valeurs patrimoniales de la Banque centrale de la Fédération de Russie sont donc des actifs immobilisés.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Il convient de faire la distinction entre la somme des actifs &lt;b&gt;&lt;i&gt;immobilisés &lt;/i&gt;&lt;/b&gt;et la somme des avoirs et valeurs &lt;b&gt;&lt;i&gt;gelés &lt;/i&gt;&lt;/b&gt;en Suisse (7,5 milliards de francs). Ces derniers sont la propriété ou sous le contrôle de personnes, d'entreprises ou d'entités frappées par des sanctions et soumises au gel des avoirs prévu à l'art. 15 de l'ordonnance instituant des mesures en lien avec la situation en Ukraine.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Les déclarations relatives aux réserves et aux actifs de la Banque centrale de la Fédération de Russie resteront obligatoires. Elles doivent intervenir en principe chaque trimestre. En cas de perte ou de dommage exceptionnel et imprévu, la déclaration au SECO ne souffre aucun délai.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Des discussions sont en cours au sein de l'UE sur la possibilité d'utiliser les actifs de la Banque centrale de la Fédération de Russie à des fins d'investissements et d'affecter leurs revenus à la reconstruction de l'Ukraine. La Suisse suit le dossier de près.&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Renseignements (pour les médias) : Communication DEFR info@gs-wbf.admin.ch 058 462 20 07 Renseignements (pour les entreprises) : sanctions@seco.admin.ch 058 464 08 12</contact>
      <link id="250222">
        <title>Mesures en lien avec la situation en Ukraine</title>
        <uri>https://bit.ly/3NXgJ6B</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>7,4 miliardi di franchi della Banca centrale della Federazione Russa sono detenuti in Svizzera</title>
      <lead>Le riserve e i valori patrimoniali detenuti in Svizzera dalla Banca centrale della Federazione Russa ammontano complessivamente a circa 7,4 miliardi di franchi. Il 10 maggio 2023 il DEFR ha informato il Consiglio federale dopo che lo scorso 29 marzo quest’ultimo aveva deciso di sottoporre le riserve e i valori patrimoniali all’obbligo di notifica. </lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Le persone, le organizzazioni e gli organismi che detengono o controllano riserve e valori patrimoniali della Banca centrale della Federazione Russa, o per i quali agiscono da controparte, erano tenute a notificarlo alla SECO entro il 12 aprile 2023. In base alle sanzioni dell'UE nei confronti della Russia, l'obbligo di notifica si applica anche nell'UE. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;L'importo delle riserve e dei valori patrimoniali detenuti in Svizzera dalla Banca centrale della Federazione Russa ammonta a circa 7,4 miliardi di franchi.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Dal 25 marzo 2022 è vietata qualsiasi transazione relativa alla gestione di riserve e di valori patrimoniali della Banca centrale della Federazione Russa. Pertanto, i valori patrimoniali di quest'ultima sono considerati beni immobili.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;L'importo dei valori patrimoniali &lt;b&gt;immobili&lt;/b&gt; deve essere distinto dalla somma di averi e valori patrimoniali &lt;b&gt;bloccati&lt;/b&gt; in Svizzera (7,5 mia. di franchi). Questi ultimi sono posseduti o controllati da persone, imprese o organizzazioni sanzionate e sottostanno al blocco degli averi secondo l'articolo 15 dell'ordinanza che istituisce provvedimenti in relazione alla situazione in Ucraina.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Le riserve e i valori patrimoniali della Banca centrale della Federazione Russa continueranno a sottostare all'obbligo di notifica. Le notifiche vengono effettuate regolarmente su base trimestrale. In caso di perdite o danni straordinari e imprevisti è previsto l'obbligo di notifica immediata alla SECO. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Nell'UE si sta discutendo se i valori patrimoniali della Banca centrale della Federazione Russa vadano utilizzati a scopo di investimento e se i relativi proventi debbano essere destinati alla ricostruzione dell'Ucraina. La Svizzera segue da vicino queste discussioni.&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Per maggiori informazioni (media): Comunicazione DEFR info@gs-wbf.admin.ch 058 462 20 07 Per maggiori informazioni (imprese): sanctions@seco.admin.ch 058 464 08 12</contact>
      <link id="250221">
        <title>Provvedimenti in relazione alla situazione in Ucraina (admin.ch)</title>
        <uri>https://bit.ly/3pqUWdq</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>CHF 7.4 billion of Russian central bank assets held in Switzerland</title>
      <lead>The total amount of reserves and assets of the Russian central bank held in Switzerland is approximately CHF 7.4 billion. The Federal Council was informed of this on 10 May 2023, having decided on 29 March to make the reserves and assets subject to a reporting requirement. </lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Persons, organisations and entities that hold, control or are counterparties to reserves and assets of the Central Bank of the Russian Federation had to report this information to SECO by 12 April 2023. The reporting obligation also applies in the EU in accordance with the EU sanctions against Russia. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The total amount of reported reserves and assets of the Russian central bank held in Switzerland is around CHF 7.4 billion. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Since 25 March 2022 all transactions related to the management of reserves and assets of the Central Bank of the Russian Federation have been prohibited. This means that the bank's assets have been immobilised. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;This sum of &lt;b&gt;&lt;i&gt;immobilised &lt;/i&gt;&lt;/b&gt;assets should be distinguished from the sum of &lt;b&gt;&lt;i&gt;frozen &lt;/i&gt;&lt;/b&gt;funds and assets in Switzerland (CHF 7.5 billion); the latter are those owned or controlled by sanctioned persons, companies or entities and are subject to the freezing of assets as set out in Article 15 of the Ordinance on Measures Relating to the Situation in Ukraine.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;It will remain mandatory to report reserves and assets of the Russian central bank, and reporting will take place regularly, on a quarterly basis. In the event of extraordinary and unforeseen loss or damage, there is an obligation to report this immediately to SECO. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;In the EU there are ongoing discussions on whether assets of the Russian Central Bank should be invested and the proceeds used for the reconstruction of Ukraine. Switzerland is following these discussions closely.&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Media enquiries: EAER Information Service info@gs-wbf.admin.ch 058 462 20 07 Enquiries from companies: sanctions@seco.admin.ch 058 464 08 12</contact>
      <link id="250220">
        <title>Measures relating to the situation in Ukraine (de, fr, it) (admin.ch)</title>
        <uri>https://bit.ly/2mr1pop</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <offers>
      <offer id="255" org-id="703">
        <name lang="de">Sanktionen / Embargos und Exportkontrollen</name>
        <name lang="fr">sanctions / embargos et contrôles à l‘exportation</name>
        <name lang="it">Sanzioni / embarghi e controlli delle esportazioni</name>
        <name lang="en">sanctions / embargoes and export controls</name>
      </offer>
    </offers>
    <topics>
      <topic id="47">
        <name lang="de">Wirtschaft</name>
        <name lang="fr">Économie</name>
        <name lang="it">Economia</name>
        <name lang="en">Economic Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
