<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="95071" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2023-05-11</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="601" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>601</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Finanzdepartement</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des finances</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale delle finanze</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Finance</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.efd.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.dff.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.efd.admin.ch/efd/it/home.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.efd.admin.ch/efd/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="601">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Finanzdepartement</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des finances</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale delle finanze</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Finance</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.efd.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.dff.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.efd.admin.ch/efd/it/home.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.efd.admin.ch/efd/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>NCSC-Halbjahresbericht mit Fokusthema «Cybersicherheit bei KMU»</title>
      <lead>Der neue Halbjahresbericht des Nationalen Zentrums für Cybersicherheit (NCSC) befasst sich mit den wichtigsten Cybervorfällen der zweiten Jahreshälfte 2022 in der Schweiz und international. Im Fokus werden die wichtigsten Punkte rund um die Cybersicherheit bei KMU beleuchtet.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Die Digitalisierung schreitet auch in kleinen und mittleren Unternehmen voran. Zahlreiche Computer sind über Netzwerkschnittstellen miteinander verbunden. Prozesse wie Bestellungsabwicklung, Planung, Produktion und Logistik greifen immer mehr ineinander und werden digital gesteuert. Dadurch steigt die Anzahl Systeme, die aus dem Internet zugänglich sind und somit bestmöglich geschützt werden sollten. Doch oftmals wird gerade bei KMU der Cybersicherheit noch zu wenig Beachtung geschenkt. Aus diesem Grund wird im aktuellen Halbjahresbericht der Fokus auf die Cybersicherheit bei KMU gelegt und die wichtigsten Punkte zum Schutz vor Cyberbedrohungen aufgezeigt. Zudem geben ein Unternehmen und eine Polizeibehörde Einblick in den Ablauf konkreter Cybervorfälle.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Am häufigsten gemeldet: Betrug&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Im zweiten Halbjahr 2022 blieb der Meldeeingang beim NCSC sehr hoch und war mit 17'341 Meldungen praktisch identisch mit dem ersten Halbjahr 2022. Insgesamt erhielt das NCSC im vergangen Jahr 34'527 Meldungen. Davon stammen 85 Prozent aus der Bevölkerung und die restlichen 15 Prozent von Unternehmen, Vereinen und Behörden. Die Meldungen betreffen verschiedenste Betrugsformen. Dabei machen gefälschte Drohmails im Namen von Strafverfolgungsbehörden, sogenannte Fake-Extortion-E-Mails, fast einen Drittel der Meldungen aus. Weitere häufig gemeldete Betrugsformen sind CEO-Betrug sowie Rechnungsmanipulationsbetrug.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Ransomware auf gleichem Niveau&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Die Meldungen zu Ransomware sind konstant geblieben und machen fast die Hälfte aller Meldungen in der Kategorie Schadsoftware aus. Etwa ein Drittel der 76 Meldungen betrifft Privatpersonen, zwei Drittel Unternehmen. Bei den Angriffen gegen Unternehmen ist besonders die Ransomware «Lockbit» aktiv. Diese Schadsoftware ist bekannt dafür, dass neben der Verschlüsselung die Daten auch gestohlen und ins Netz gestellt werden, falls die Lösegeldsumme nicht bezahlt wird. Solche Double-Extortions (Zweifach-Erpressungen) werden immer häufiger beobachtet. Weil viele Firmen die Bedrohung durch Ransomware erkannt haben und über Backups verfügen, ist die reine Verschlüsselung für die Angreifer mittlerweile nicht mehr lukrativ genug. Die initiale Infektion bei Ransomware-Vorfällen ist neben E-Mails mit schädlichen Anhängen oder Links häufig auf eine Schwachstelle oder eine schlechte Konfiguration zurückzuführen.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Meldungen zu Hacking weiterhin stark ansteigend&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Im Vergleich zur Vorhalbjahresperiode haben sich die Meldungen bezüglich Hacking im zweiten Halbjahr mit 276 Meldungen nahezu verdoppelt. Insbesondere Social Media-Accounts sind bei Hackern ein beliebtes Ziel, um beispielsweise die Nutzerinnen und Nutzer zu erpressen oder die gehackten Accounts für das Vertreiben von Werbung für Investitions-Betrug zu verwenden.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Kommunikation NCSC Tel. 058 465 53 56 ncsc-media@gs-efd.admin.ch</contact>
      <attachment id="250382">
        <title>Halbjahresbericht NCSC</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>1479</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/78227.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Rapport semestriel du NCSC: la cybersécurité dans les PME</title>
      <lead>Le dernier rapport semestriel du Centre national pour la cybersécurité (NCSC) traite des principaux cyberincidents qui se sont produits au cours du second semestre de 2022 en Suisse et dans le reste du monde. Il se concentre en particulier sur la cybersécurité au sein des petites et moyennes entreprises (PME).</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;La transformation numérique s'opère aussi dans les PME. De nombreux ordinateurs sont aujourd'hui reliés entre eux par des interfaces réseau. Ainsi, des synergies de plus en plus grandes sont créées entre les divers processus, tels que le traitement des commandes, la planification, la production et la logistique, gérés par voie numérique. Cette évolution va de pair avec une augmentation du nombre de systèmes accessibles par Internet, qui requièrent une protection accrue. Or, les PME n'accordent souvent pas assez d'importance à ces questions. C'est pourquoi le rapport du NCSC met l'accent sur la place de la cybersécurité dans les entreprises et sur les points clés de la protection contre les cyberrisques. Une entreprise et une autorité de police y présentent en outre des cas concrets de cyberattaques.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;L'escroquerie, incident le plus courant&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Au deuxième semestre de 2022, le nombre de signalements est resté très élevé, se montant à 17 341, soit un niveau presque identique à celui du premier semestre. Au total, le NCSC a reçu 34 527 annonces l'année dernière. Environ 85 % proviennent de la population, tandis que les 15 % restants émanent d'entreprises, d'associations ou d'autorités. Elles concernent les formes de fraude les plus diverses. Presque un tiers des signalements portent sur des courriels de pseudo-extorsion, soit des courriels de menace prétendument envoyés par les autorités de poursuite pénale. L'arnaque au président et la fraude à la facturation sont également souvent signalées.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Nombre stable d'attaques par rançongiciel&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Les annonces relatives à des attaques par rançongiciel sont restées stables et représentent quasiment la moitié des signalements portant sur des maliciels. Sur 76 annonces reçues, un tiers provient de particuliers et deux tiers d'entreprises, lesquelles subissent surtout les assauts du maliciel «Lockbit». Les cybercriminels se servent de ce maliciel pour crypter les données ou les voler et les mettre en ligne si la rançon n'est pas versée. Ces doubles extorsions sont de plus en plus fréquentes. En effet, comme de nombreuses entreprises se protègent désormais contre les rançongiciels en créant des copies de sauvegarde, le simple cryptage des données n'est plus assez lucratif pour les cybercriminels. Dans les cas liés à des rançongiciels, si l'infection initiale n'est pas causée par l'ouverture d'une pièce jointe ou d'un lien transmis par courriel, elle est généralement due à une vulnérabilité ou à une mauvaise configuration.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Nouvelle recrudescence des annonces de piratages&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Au deuxième semestre, les annonces de piratages, qui se montent à 276, ont presque doublé par rapport au semestre précédent. Les comptes sur les médias sociaux sont une cible de choix pour les cybercriminels. Ceux-ci se servent par exemple des comptes piratés pour faire chanter les utilisateurs ou diffuser de la publicité pour des offres d'investissement fictives.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Communication NCSC Tél. +41 58 465 53 56 ncsc-media@gs-efd.admin.ch</contact>
      <attachment id="250383">
        <title>Rapport semestriel du NCSC</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>1572</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/78228.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Rapporto semestrale dell’NCSC: in primo piano, la cibersicurezza presso le PMI</title>
      <lead>Il nuovo rapporto semestrale del Centro nazionale per la cibersicurezza (NCSC) prende in esame i principali ciberincidenti verificatisi in Svizzera e all’estero nel secondo semestre del 2022. Il tema principale è la cibersicurezza presso le piccole e medie imprese (PMI).</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;La digitalizzazione avanza anche nelle PMI. Molti dispositivi informatici sono connessi fra loro tramite interfacce di rete. Processi come l’elaborazione degli ordini, la pianificazione, la produzione e la logistica sono sempre più interconnessi e vengono controllati digitalmente. Ciò aumenta il numero di sistemi accessibili via Internet, che devono quindi essere protetti nel miglior modo possibile. Tuttavia, spesso proprio le PMI non riservano alla cibersicurezza l’attenzione dovuta. Per questo motivo, il nuovo rapporto semestrale è incentrato sul tema della cibersicurezza presso le PMI e presenta gli aspetti più importanti in materia di protezione dalle ciberminacce. Un’impresa e un corpo di polizia forniscono inoltre testimonianze su ciberattacchi concreti.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;La truffa rimane il tipo di incidente più segnalato&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Nel secondo semestre del 2022 il numero di segnalazioni pervenute all’NCSC è rimasto molto elevato (17 341) ed è praticamente identico a quello del primo semestre del 2022. Lo scorso anno l’NCSC ha ricevuto complessivamente 34 527 segnalazioni, di cui l’85 per cento da privati, mentre il restante 15 per cento da imprese, associazioni e autorità. Le segnalazioni riguardano varie forme di truffa. Le e-mail minatorie inviate da presunte autorità di perseguimento penale, le cosiddette e-mail di «fake extortion», rappresentano quasi un terzo delle segnalazioni. Altri casi segnalati di frequente sono la truffa del CEO e la truffa mediante la manipolazione di una fattura.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Numero di ransomware invariato&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Le segnalazioni relative a ransomware sono rimaste costanti e costituiscono quasi la metà di tutte le segnalazioni nella categoria riguardante i malware. Dei 76 casi segnalati, circa un terzo proviene da privati e due terzi da imprese. Il ransomware «Lockbit» prende di mira in modo particolare le imprese. Quest’ultimo è noto per la crittografia dei dati ma anche per il furto degli stessi, nonché per la loro pubblicazione online se non viene pagato il riscatto. Si tratta di una doppia estorsione che sta diventando sempre più comune. Poiché molte aziende hanno capito la minaccia dei ransomware e utilizzano la strategia di backup, la semplice crittografia non è più redditizia per gli aggressori. Spesso la prima infezione negli incidenti di ransomware è dovuta a una vulnerabilità o a una configurazione errata, oltre che a e-mail contenenti allegati o link dannosi.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Segnalazioni di hacking ancora in forte ascesa&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Rispetto al primo semestre, nel secondo semestre il numero di hacking segnalati è quasi raddoppiato (276 segnalazioni). Gli account dei social media sono tra gli obiettivi preferiti dagli hacker, che ad esempio ricattano gli utenti o utilizzano gli account violati come mezzo pubblicitario per tentativi di truffe dell’investimento.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Comunicazione NCSC Tel. 058 465 53 56 ncsc-media@gs-efd.admin.ch</contact>
      <attachment id="250384">
        <title>Rapporto semestrale NCSC</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>1538</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/78229.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>NCSC semi-annual report focuses on cybersecurity in SMEs</title>
      <lead>The National Cybersecurity Centre's (NCSC) second semi-annual report deals with the most important cyberincidents of the second half of 2022 in Switzerland and internationally. It focuses on the most important issues surrounding cybersecurity in SMEs.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Digitalisation is also progressing in small and medium-sized enterprises. Numerous computers are connected to each other via network interfaces. Processes such as order processing, planning, production and logistics are increasingly interlinked and digitally managed. This increases the number of systems that are accessible from the internet and therefore need the best possible protection. However, SMEs in particular often pay too little attention to cybersecurity. For this reason, the current semi-annual report focuses on cybersecurity in SMEs and highlights the most important aspects of protection against cyberthreats. In addition, a business and a police authority provide insight into how specific cyberincidents unfold.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Most frequently reported: fraud&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;In the second half of 2022, the number of reports received by the NCSC remained very high at 17,341, which was practically identical to the first half of the year. In total, the NCSC received 34,527 reports last year. Of these, 85% came from the public and the remaining 15% from businesses, associations and authorities. The reports concerned various forms of fraud, with fake extortion emails, i.e. threatening emails in the name of prosecution authorities, accounting for almost one third of the reports. Other frequently reported forms of fraud included CEO fraud and invoice manipulation scams. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Unchanged amount of ransomware&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ransomware reports remained constant and accounted for almost half of all reports in the malware category. About one third of the 76 reports concerned private individuals, two thirds involved businesses. The LockBit ransomware is often used in attacks targeting businesses. This malware is known for the fact that not only is data encrypted, but it is also stolen and posted on the internet if the ransom is not paid. Such double extortion approaches are being observed more and more frequently. Since many businesses have recognised the threat of ransomware and now have backups, pure encryption is no longer lucrative enough for attackers. The initial infection in ransomware incidents is often due to a vulnerability or poor configuration, as well as emails with malicious attachments and links.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Hacking reports continued to rise sharply&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Compared to the previous half-year period, the number of reports regarding hacking almost doubled in the second half of the year, with 276 reports. In particular, social media accounts are a popular target for hackers, for example to blackmail users or to use the hacked accounts to distribute advertising for investment fraud.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>NCSC Communications Tel. 058 465 53 56 ncsc-media@gs-efd.admin.ch</contact>
      <attachment id="250385">
        <title>NCSC semi-annual report</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>1475</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/78230.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <offers>
      <offer id="345" org-id="601">
        <name lang="de">Cybersecurity</name>
        <name lang="fr">Cybersecurity</name>
        <name lang="it">Cybersecurity</name>
        <name lang="en">Cybersecurity</name>
      </offer>
      <offer id="350" org-id="601">
        <name lang="de">NCSC - Nationales Zentrum für Cybersicherheit</name>
        <name lang="fr">NCSC - Centre national pour la cybersécurité</name>
        <name lang="it">NCSC - Centro nazionale per la cibersicurezza</name>
        <name lang="en">NCSC - National Cyber Security Centre</name>
      </offer>
    </offers>
    <keywords>
      <keyword id="189" org-id="601">
        <name lang="de">Betrugsbekämpfung</name>
        <name lang="fr">Lutte contre la fraude douanière</name>
        <name lang="it">Lotta alla frode</name>
        <name lang="en">Combating customs fraud</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="175" org-id="601">
        <name lang="de">Informatik</name>
        <name lang="fr">Informatique</name>
        <name lang="it">Informatica</name>
        <name lang="en">IT</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="298" org-id="601">
        <name lang="de">Informatik-Sicherheit</name>
        <name lang="fr">Sécurité informatique</name>
        <name lang="it">Sicurezza informatica</name>
        <name lang="en">IT security</name>
      </keyword>
    </keywords>
    <topics>
      <topic id="36">
        <name lang="de">Informatik und E-Government</name>
        <name lang="fr">Informatique et cyberadministration</name>
        <name lang="it">Informatica ed e-government</name>
        <name lang="en">IT and E-Government</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="40">
        <name lang="de">Sicherheit</name>
        <name lang="fr">Sécurité</name>
        <name lang="it">Sicurezza</name>
        <name lang="en">Security</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
