<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="68345" revoked="no">
    <version>2</version>
    <pubdate>2017-10-06</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="201" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>201</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="801" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>801</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Umwelt, Verkehr, Energie und Kommunikation</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'environnement, des transports, de l'énergie et de la communication</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'ambiente, dei trasporti, dell'energia e delle comunicazioni</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of the Environment, Transport, Energy and Communications</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.uvek.admin.ch/uvek/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.uvek.admin.ch/uvek/fr/home.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.uvek.admin.ch/uvek/it/home.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.uvek.admin.ch/uvek/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-uvek.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-uvek.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-uvek.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-uvek.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="811" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>801</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Bundesamt für Umwelt BAFU</name>
      <name lang="fr">Office fédéral de l'environnement OFEV</name>
      <name lang="it">Ufficio federale dell'ambiente UFAM</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Office for the Environment FOEN</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.bafu.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.bafu.admin.ch/fr</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.bafu.admin.ch/it</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.bafu.admin.ch/en</www>
      <email lang="de">info@bafu.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@bafu.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@bafu.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@bafu.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="201">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <department id="801">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Umwelt, Verkehr, Energie und Kommunikation</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'environnement, des transports, de l'énergie et de la communication</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'ambiente, dei trasporti, dell'energia e delle comunicazioni</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of the Environment, Transport, Energy and Communications</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.uvek.admin.ch/uvek/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.uvek.admin.ch/uvek/fr/home.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.uvek.admin.ch/uvek/it/home.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.uvek.admin.ch/uvek/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-uvek.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-uvek.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-uvek.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-uvek.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Übergabe der Ratifikationsurkunde: Klimaübereinkommen von Paris tritt für die Schweiz am 5. November 2017 in Kraft</title>
      <lead>Mit der Übergabe der Ratifikationsurkunde am 6. Oktober 2017 in New York wird die Schweiz offiziell Mitglied des Klimaübereinkommens von Paris. Es wird für die Schweiz 30 Tage später, also am 5. November 2017, in Kraft treten. Es sieht unter anderem die Begrenzung der globalen Erwärmung auf deutlich unter 2 °C gegenüber vorindustriellen Werten vor. Die Schweiz hatte sich bei den Verhandlungen zum Klimaübereinkommen stark engagiert.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Botschafter Jürg Lauber, der Chef der Mission der Schweiz bei der UNO in New York, hat am Freitagvormittag dem UNO-Generalsekretär die Ratifikationsurkunde der Schweiz für das Klimaübereinkommen von Paris übergeben. Der UNO-Generalsekretär ist Depositar des Abkommens, das die 195 Mitgliedstaaten der Klimarahmenkonvention der Vereinten Nationen am 12. Dezember 2015 in Paris verabschiedet haben. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Die Schweiz wird somit als Mitglied an der Konferenz der Vertragsparteien des Übereinkommens von Paris teilnehmen, die im Rahmen der nächsten Klimakonferenz abgehalten wird. Diese findet vom 6. bis 17. November 2017 in Bonn (Deutschland) statt.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Eine neue Ära der internationalen Klimapolitik&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Das Klimaübereinkommen von Paris leitet eine neue Ära der internationalen Politik gegen die Klimaerwärmung ein. Es fördert eine schrittweise Reduktion fossiler Energien, mit dem Ziel, in der zweiten Hälfte des Jahrhunderts ein Gleichgewicht zwischen den Emissionen und dem Abbau von Treibhausgasen durch Senken zu erreichen.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Um die Erderwärmung global deutlich unter 2 Grad zu halten oder gar auf 1,5 Grad zu limitieren, verpflichtet das Pariser Übereinkommen alle Länder, ihre Treibhausgasemissionen zu reduzieren. Die öffentlichen und privaten Finanzflüsse müssen auf eine treibhausgasarme und gegenüber Klimaänderungen widerstandsfähige Entwicklung ausgerichtet werden. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Halbierung der Treibhausgasemissionen bis 2030&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mit der Ratifikation des Übereinkommens wird das von der Schweiz angekündigte Ziel, die Treibhausgasemissionen bis 2030 gegenüber 1990 um 50 Prozent zu reduzieren, verbindlich. Dieses Ziel wurde vom Parlament im Juni 2017 zeitgleich mit der Zustimmung zur Ratifikation verabschiedet. Gemäss dem Übereinkommen von Paris muss dieses Reduktionsziel in erster Linie durch eine Senkung der inländischen Emissionen erreicht werden. Dank einem Marktmechanismus, dessen Regeln von der internationalen Gemeinschaft bis 2018 genehmigt werden müssen, lässt es aber auch Emissionsverminderungen im Ausland zu. Der Anteil der inländischen Emissionsreduktionen und jener der Verminderungen in Drittländern wird im CO2-Gesetz festgelegt werden. Im Entwurf zur Revision des CO2-Gesetzes, der 2016 in die Vernehmlassung geschickt wurde, hat der Bundesrat vorgeschlagen, dass die Reduktion der Treibhausgasemissionen gegenüber 1990 höchstens zu 20 Prozent im Ausland erfolgen und für die Erreichung des Ziels der Schweiz für 2030 berücksichtigt werden darf. Die Botschaft zur Revision des CO2-Gesetzes sollte bis Ende 2017 an das Parlament überwiesen werden.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Kommunikation EDA Bundeshaus West CH-3003 Bern Tel. Kommunikationsservice: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Medienstelle: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Remise de l’instrument de ratification: l’accord de Paris sur le climat entre en vigueur le 5 novembre 2017 pour la Suisse</title>
      <lead>En déposant l’instrument de ratification le 6 octobre 2017 à New York, la Suisse adhère officiellement à l’accord de Paris sur le climat. Ce dernier entrera en vigueur en Suisse 30 jours plus tard, le 5 novembre 2017. Il prévoit notamment de maintenir le réchauffement climatique nettement en dessous de 2 °C par rapport aux niveaux préindustriels. La Suisse s’est beaucoup investie dans les négociations qui ont abouti à cet accord.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Vendredi matin, l’ambassadeur Jürg Lauber, chef de la mission permanente de la Suisse auprès des Nations Unies à New York, a remis au secrétaire général de l’ONU l’instrument de ratification de la Suisse relatif à l’accord de Paris sur le climat. Le secrétaire général de l’ONU est dépositaire de l’accord que les 195 États membres de la Convention-cadre des Nations Unies sur les changements climatiques ont adopté le 12 décembre 2015 à Paris.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;La Suisse participera ainsi en tant que membre à la Conférence des États parties de l’Accord de Paris, qui se tiendra durant la prochaine conférence sur le climat. Celle-ci aura lieu du 6 au 17 novembre 2017 à Bonn en Allemagne.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Une nouvelle ère de la politique climatique internationale&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;L’Accord de Paris sur le climat inaugure une nouvelle ère de la politique internationale contre le réchauffement climatique. Il promeut la sortie progressive des énergies fossiles en fixant comme objectif de parvenir à un équilibre entre les émissions et les absorptions par les puits de gaz à effet de serre au cours de la deuxième moitié du XXIe siècle.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Afin de contenir l’élévation de la température moyenne mondiale nettement en dessous de 2°C, voire même de la limiter à 1,5°C, l’Accord de Paris engage tous les États à réduire leurs émissions de gaz à effet de serre. Les flux financiers publics et privés doivent être orientés vers un développement limitant les émissions de gaz à effet de serre et renforçant les capacités d'adaptation aux changements climatiques. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Réduire les émissions de moitié d’ici à 2030&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Avec la ratification de l’accord, l’objectif annoncé par la Suisse de réduire les émissions de gaz à effet de serre de 50% par rapport au niveau de 1990 d’ici à 2030 devientcontraignant. Le Parlement a approuvé cet objectif en même temps qu’il a autorisé la ratification de l’accord, en juin 2017. L’Accord de Paris stipule que l’objectif de réduction doit être atteint en premier lieu par la réduction des émissions nationales. Il permet cependant de prendre en compte les réductions réalisées à l’étranger grâce aux mécanismes de marché, dont les règles doivent encore être approuvées par la communauté internationale d’ici à 2018. La proportion entre les réductions effectuées en Suisse et celles dans les pays tiers sera fixée dans la loi sur le CO2. Dans le projet de révision de la loi mis en consultation en 2016, le Conseil fédéral a proposé qu’une réduction de 20% au maximum des gaz à effet de serre par rapport au niveau de 1990 pouvait être réalisée à l’étranger et prise en compte dans l’atteinte de l’objectif 2030 de la Suisse. Le message sur la révision de la loi sur le CO2 devrait être transmis au Parlement à fin 2017. &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Communication DFAE Palais fédéral ouest CH-3003 Berne Tél. Service de communication: +41 58 462 31 53 Tél. Service de presse: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Consegna dello strumento di ratifica: per la Svizzera l’Accordo di Parigi sul clima entrerà in vigore il 5 novembre 2017</title>
      <lead>Con la consegna dello strumento di ratifica il 6 ottobre 2017 a New York, la Svizzera diventa ufficialmente membro dell’Accordo di Parigi sul clima, che entrerà in vigore il 5 novembre 2017. L’Accordo sul clima, nei cui negoziati la Svizzera si è attivamente impegnata, prevede tra l’altro di contenere l’aumento della temperatura mondiale al di sotto dei 2°C rispetto al periodo preindustriale.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Venerdì mattina l’ambasciatore Jürg Lauber, capomissione della Svizzera presso le Nazioni Unite a New York, ha consegnato al segretario generale dell’ONU lo strumento di ratifica della Svizzera per l’Accordo di Parigi sul clima. Il segretario generale delle Nazioni Unite è il depositario dell’Accordo adottato il 12 dicembre 2015 a Parigi dai 195 Stati membri della Convenzione sul clima delle Nazioni Unite. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;La Svizzera parteciperà quindi in qualità di membro alla conferenza delle parti dell’Accordo di Parigi sul clima che si terrà nel corso della prossima conferenza sul clima. Questa avrà luogo a Bonn (Germania) dal 6 al 17 novembre prossimi. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Una nuova era della politica climatica internazionale&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;L’Accordo di Parigi sul clima inaugura una nuova era della politica internazionale contro il riscaldamento globale. Sostiene infatti l’abbandono progressivo delle energie fossili per giungere a un equilibrio tra le emissioni e l’assorbimento da parte dei pozzi di gas a effetto serra nel corso della seconda metà del secolo.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Per contenere l’incremento della temperatura media mondiale al di sotto di 2 gradi, o addirittura di limitarlo a 1,5 gradi, l’Accordo di Parigi chiede a tutti gli Stati a ridurre le loro emissioni di gas a effetto serra. Inoltre mira a orientare i flussi finanziari privati e statali verso uno sviluppo a basse emissioni di gas serra e a migliorare la capacità di adattamento ai cambiamenti climatici. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dimezzare le emissioni entro il 2030&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Con la ratifica dell’accordo diventa effettivo l’obiettivo annunciato dalla Svizzera di ridurre del 50 per cento le proprie emissioni entro il 2030 rispetto ai valori del 1990. Questo obiettivo è stato approvato dal Parlamento, che ha al contempo autorizzato la ratifica, a giugno 2017. In base all’Accordo di Parigi l’obiettivo di riduzione dev’essere raggiunto principalmente riducendo le emissioni nazionali. È possibile però anche di includere le riduzioni ottenute all’estero grazie ai meccanismi di mercato, le cui regole dovranno essere approvate dalla comunità internazionale entro il 2018. La proporzione tra le riduzioni in Svizzera e quelle ottenute all’estero sarà fissata nella legge sul CO2. Nel progetto di revisione della legge, inviato in consultazione nel 2016, il Consiglio federale ha proposto che, per raggiungere gli obiettivi entro il 2030, si possa realizzare all’estero al massimo una riduzione del 20 per cento dei gas a effetto serra. Il messaggio sulla revisione della legge sul CO2 dovrebbe essere trasmesso al Parlamento entro la fine del 2017.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Comunicazione DFAE Palazzo federale ovest CH-3003 Berna Tel. Servizio di comunicazione: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Servizio stampa: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <revisions>
        <revision date="2017-10-06 18:09" type="R"/>
      </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Instrument of ratification deposited: Paris climate agreement to enter into force for Switzerland on 5 November 2017</title>
      <lead>Switzerland deposited its instrument of ratification in New York on 6 October 2017, making it an official party to the Paris Agreement. The agreement will come into effect for Switzerland 30 days later, on 5 November 2017. One of the agreement's main objectives is to maintain the increase in global temperatures well below 2°C above pre-industrial levels. Switzerland was actively involved in the negotiations leading up to the climate agreement.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Ambassador Jürg Lauber, Switzerland's head of mission to the UN in New York, deposited Switzerland's instrument of ratification of the Paris climate agreement with the UN Secretary-General on Friday morning. The UN Secretary-General is the depositary of the agreement, which was adopted on 12 December 2015 in Paris by the 195 parties to the United Nations Framework Convention on Climate Change.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Switzerland will therefore participate as a member in the conference of parties to the Paris Agreement at the next Climate Change Conference, to be held from 6 to 17 November this year in Bonn, Germany.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A new era in international climate policy&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Paris Agreement ushers in a new era of international policy on climate change. It promotes a gradual shift away from fossil fuels, with a view to balancing emissions by sources and removals by sinks of greenhouse gases (GHG) in the second half of this century.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The agreement seeks to maintain the increase in global temperatures well below 2°C, or even limit it to 1.5°C, by seeking a commitment from all states to reduce their GHG emissions. Funding from public and private sources will flow into formulating low-GHG emission development strategies and building capacities in climate change adaptation. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Emissions to be halved by 2030&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In ratifying the Paris Agreement, Switzerland's pledge to halve emissions by 2030 against its 1990 baseline becomes binding. This target was approved by Parliament in June 2017, at the same time as approving ratification. The agreement stipulates that the emissions reduction target should be met primarily by reducing domestic emissions. It does however include the possibility of achieving emissions reductions abroad with the use of market mechanisms, the rules for which are expected to be approved by the international community by 2018. The ratio of Switzerland's domestic reductions to those achieved in other countries will be set out in the CO2 Act. In the draft revision submitted for consultation in 2016, the Federal Council proposed that up to a maximum of 20% of GHG emissions reductions (with respect to 1990) could be achieved abroad and counted towards Switzerland's target for 2030. The dispatch on the revised CO2 Act is expected to be submitted to Parliament at the end of 2017.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>FDFA Communication Federal Palace West Wing CH-3003 Bern, Switzerland Tel. Communication service: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Press service: +41 58 460 55 55 E-mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @SwissMFA</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <offers>
      <offer id="143" org-id="811">
        <name lang="de">Medienmitteilungen des BAFU</name>
        <name lang="fr">Communiqués de l'OFEV</name>
        <name lang="it">Comunicati dell'UFAM</name>
        <name lang="en">Media releases of the FOEN</name>
      </offer>
      <offer id="145" org-id="811">
        <name lang="de">Newsletter Umweltrecht des BAFU</name>
        <name lang="fr">Newsletter Droit de l’environnement de l'OFEV</name>
        <name lang="it">Newsletter Diritto ambientale dell'UFAM</name>
        <name lang="en">Environmental law newsletter of the FOEN</name>
      </offer>
    </offers>
    <keywords>
      <keyword id="560" org-id="811">
        <name lang="de">Internationales</name>
        <name lang="fr">Affaires internationales</name>
        <name lang="it">Affari Internazionali</name>
        <name lang="en">International Affairs</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="980" org-id="811">
        <name lang="de">Recht</name>
        <name lang="fr">Recht</name>
        <name lang="it">Recht</name>
        <name lang="en">Recht</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="620" org-id="811">
        <name lang="de">Klima</name>
        <name lang="fr">Climat</name>
        <name lang="it">Clima</name>
        <name lang="en">Climate</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="173" org-id="811">
        <name lang="de">Bundesamt für Umwelt: Startseite</name>
        <name lang="fr">Office fédéral de l'environnement: page d'accueil</name>
        <name lang="it">Ufficio federale dell'ambiente: pagina iniziale</name>
        <name lang="en">Federal Office for the Environment: Homepage</name>
      </keyword>
    </keywords>
    <topics>
      <topic id="29">
        <name lang="de">Umwelt und Natur</name>
        <name lang="fr">Environnement et nature</name>
        <name lang="it">Ambiente e natura</name>
        <name lang="en">Environment and Nature</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
