<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="42530" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2011-12-05</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="yes" id="602" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>601</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Generalsekretariat EFD</name>
      <name lang="fr">Secrétariat général DFF</name>
      <name lang="it">Segreteria generale DFF</name>
      <name lang="en">Secretariat-General FDF</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.efd.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.efd.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.efd.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.efd.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="601">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Finanzdepartement</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des finances</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale delle finanze</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Finance</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.efd.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.dff.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.efd.admin.ch/efd/it/home.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.efd.admin.ch/efd/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>«Too big to fail»-Verordnungen in der Anhörung</title>
      <lead>Das Parlament hat am 30. September 2011 eine Änderung des Bankengesetzes zur Stärkung der Stabilität im Finanzsektor (Too big to fail) beschlossen. Mit der Gesetzesänderung soll verhindert werden, dass der Staat noch einmal einer systemrelevanten Bank, die in Schwierigkeiten geraten ist, beistehen muss, um grösseren Schaden für die Volkswirtschaft abzuwenden. Das Eidgenössische Finanzdepartement (EFD) hat heute die Anhörung zu entsprechenden Ausführungsbestimmungen in der Banken- und Eigenmittelverordnung eröffnet.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Die Verordnungen setzen die beschlossenen Änderung des Bankengesetzes um und folgen gleichzeitig den Vorgaben des Financial Stability Board (FSB) für globale systemrelevante Banken vom Oktober 2011. Die Änderungen regeln die erhöhten Anforderungen an die Eigenmittel, die Risikoverteilung und die Organisation von systemrelevanten Banken.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Die höheren Eigenmittelanforderungen gelten parallel zu den allgemeinen, für alle Banken geltenden Anforderungen. Sie bestehen aus einer Basiskomponente von 4,5 Prozent der risikogewichteten Positionen (RWA), welche die Bank mit hartem Kernkapital erfüllen muss. Im Weiteren haben systemrelevante Banken einen Eigenmittelpuffer von 8,5 Prozent der RWA zu halten, welcher zu mindestens 5,5 Prozent ebenfalls mit hartem Kernkapital zu erfüllen ist. 3 Prozent können mit sogenannten Contingent Convertible Bonds (CoCos) erfüllt werden, also mit Fremdkapital, das im Fall einer Krise der Bank in Eigenkapital umgewandelt wird oder auf das der Gläubiger entschädigungslos zu verzichten hat. Sodann müssen systemrelevante Banken als zusätzliche Anforderung eine progressive Komponente halten, die von der Bilanzgrösse und dem Marktanteil der betroffenen Bank abhängt. Diese Komponente kann vollständig mit CoCos erfüllt werden. Hinzu kommt gegebenenfalls ein für alle Banken geltender antizyklischer Puffer.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Flankierend zu diesen risikoabhängigen Eigenmittelanforderungen müssen die Eigenmittel einer Bank aber auch den Anforderungen an die Höchstverschuldungsquote (Leverage Ratio) genügen. Dabei dürfen die Eigenmittel einen minimalen Prozentsatz am Gesamtengagement, bestehend aus der Bilanzsumme und bestimmten Ausserbilanzpositionen, nicht unterschreiten.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Schliesslich enthalten die Verordnungsänderungen auch Bestimmungen zur Organisation von systemrelevanten Banken. Geregelt wird zum einen der Notfallplan zur Fortführung der systemrelevanten Funktionen im Falle drohender Insolvenz. Im Einklang mit den Vorgaben des FSB müssen die Banken der FINMA zum anderen Stabilisierungspläne und Informationen einreichen, mit der sie eine Abwicklungsplanung (zur Sanierung oder Liquidation der Bank) erstellen kann. Verbessern die Banken ihre Sanier- und Liquidierbarkeit im In- und Ausland über die Mindestanforderungen im Notfallplan hinaus, gewährt die FINMA dafür Erleichterungen auf der progressiven Komponente.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Die neuen Anforderungen an systemrelevante Banken müssen bis Ende 2018 stufenweise umgesetzt werden. Die erstmalige Verabschiedung der Ausführungsbestimmungen durch den Bundesrat ist vom Parlament zu genehmigen. Die besonderen Anforderungen an die Liquidität werden später in einer separaten Verordnung geregelt, die voraussichtlich im Verlaufe des Jahres 2012 in die Anhörung gebracht wird. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Kommunikation EFD Tel. +41 58 462 60 33 E-Mail: info@gs-efd.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="91333">
        <title>Dokumente zur Anhörung</title>
        <uri>http://www.efd.admin.ch/dokumentation/gesetzgebung/00571/02375/index.html?lang=de</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Audition sur les ordonnances traitant du thème du too big to fail</title>
      <lead>Le 30 septembre 2011, le Parlement a adopté une modification de la loi sur les banques visant à renforcer la stabilité du secteur financier (too big to fail). Le but de cette modification est d'éviter que l'Etat doive à nouveau soutenir une banque d'importance systémique en difficulté afin de prévenir des dommages encore plus importants pour l'économie. Le Département fédéral des finances (DFF) a ouvert aujourd'hui l'audition sur les dispositions d'exécution correspondantes de l'ordonnance sur les banques et de l'ordonnance sur les fonds propres. </lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Les ordonnances assurent la mise en œuvre de la modification de la loi sur les banques. Elles sont conformes aux prescriptions émises en octobre 2011 par le Conseil de stabilité financière (CSF) en ce qui concerne les banques d'importance systémique opérant au niveau international. Les modifications portent sur les exigences accrues en matière de fonds propres, sur la répartition des risques et sur l'organisation des banques d'importance systémique. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Les exigences accrues en matière de fonds propres viennent s'ajouter aux exigences générales applicables à toutes les banques. Elles se composent d'une exigence minimale de 4,5 % des actifs pondérés en fonction des risques, que la banque doit satisfaire grâce à des fonds propres de base de haute qualité. Les banques d'importance systémique doivent en outre disposer d'un volant de sécurité représentant 8,5 % des actifs pondérés en fonction des risques, exigence qui doit être satisfaite à raison d'au moins 5,5 % grâce à des fonds propres de base de haute qualité. Une part de 3 % peut être couverte par des &lt;i&gt;contingent convertible bonds&lt;/i&gt; (&lt;i&gt;CoCo&lt;/i&gt;), c'est-à-dire par des fonds de tiers qui peuvent être convertis en fonds propres ou auxquels le créancier doit renoncer sans dédommagement en cas de crise de la banque. Les banques d'importance systémique doivent également remplir une exigence supplémentaire sous la forme d'une composante progressive, qui dépend de la taille de leur bilan et de leur part de marché. Cette composante peut être couverte en totalité grâce à des &lt;i&gt;CoCo&lt;/i&gt;. A cela vient éventuellement s'ajouter un volant anticyclique applicable à toutes les banques. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Parallèlement à ces exigences liées aux risques, les fonds propres d'une banque sont aussi soumis à des exigences en matière de taux d'endettement maximum (&lt;i&gt;leverage ratio&lt;/i&gt;), selon lesquelles le niveau de fonds propres ne doit pas être inférieur à un pourcentage déterminé de l'engagement total, qui se compose du total du bilan et de certaines positions hors bilan.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Enfin, les modifications des ordonnances concernent également l'organisation des banques d'importance systémique. D'une part, un plan d'urgence doit permettre à la banque de maintenir ses fonctions systémiques même en cas de menace d'insolvabilité. D'autre part, conformément aux prescriptions du CSF, les banques doivent remettre à la FINMA des plans de stabilisation et des informations sur lesquels la FINMA peut se baser pour établir un plan d'assainissement ou de liquidation de la banque. Si les banques améliorent, en Suisse et à l'étranger, leur capacité d'assainissement et de liquidation au-delà des exigences minimales fixées dans le plan d'urgence, la FINMA leur accorde des assouplissements au niveau de la composante progressive. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Les nouvelles exigences applicables aux banques d'importance systémique seront mises en œuvre progressivement d'ici à 2018. Les dispositions d'exécution doivent être soumises à l'approbation du Parlement lors de leur première adoption par le Conseil fédéral. Les exigences particulières en matière de liquidités seront réglées ultérieurement dans une ordonnance séparée, qui fera l'objet d'une audition dans le courant de 2012.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Communication DFF Tél. +41 58 462 60 33 Courriel: info@gs-efd.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="91334">
        <title>Documents relativs à la procédure d'audition</title>
        <uri>http://www.efd.admin.ch/dokumentation/gesetzgebung/00571/02375/index.html?lang=fr</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Le ordinanze «too big to fail» sono in consultazione</title>
      <lead>Il 30 settembre 2011 il Parlamento ha deciso di modificare la legge sulle banche per rafforzare la stabilità nel settore finanziario (too big to fail). Con questa modifica si vuole impedire che lo Stato debba nuovamente aiutare una banca di rilevanza sistemica in difficoltà per evitare all’economia danni ancora più grossi. In data odierna il Dipartimento federale delle finanze (DFF) ha avviato un’indagine conoscitiva sulle relative disposizioni d’esecuzione contenute nell’ordinanza sulle banche e in quella sui fondi propri.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Le ordinanze attuano la modifica decisa nella legge sulle banche e seguono al contempo le prescrizioni del mese di ottobre 2011 del Financial Stability Board (FSB) per le banche che hanno un rilevanza sistemica globale. Le modifiche disciplinano le esigenze più elevate in materia di fondi propri, la ripartizione dei rischi e l'organizzazione delle banche di rilevanza sistemica. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Le esigenze più elevate in materia di fondi propri sono applicabili parallelamente a quelle valide per tutte le banche. Esse sono composte da una componente di base del 4,5 per cento delle posizioni ponderate in funzione del rischio, che la banca deve costituire con fondi propri di base. Le banche di rilevanza sistemica devono inoltre possedere un ammortizzatore in materia di fondi propri pari all'8,5 per cento degli attivi ponderati in funzione del rischio. Anche questo ammortizzatore deve essere costituito almeno nella misura del 5,5 per cento con fondi propri di base. Esso può inoltre essere costituito dal 3 per cento di cosiddetti contingent convertible bonds (CoCos), ovvero di capitale di terzi che in caso di crisi della banca viene convertito in capitale proprio o al quale il creditore vi deve rinunciare senza indennizzo. Le banche di rilevanza sistemica devono inoltre detenere una componente progressiva che dipende dall'ordine di grandezza del bilancio e dalla quota di mercato della banca stessa. Questa componente può essere interamente costituita mediante CoCos. A ciò si aggiunge, se del caso, un ammortizzatore anticiclico valido per tutte le banche. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Oltre a queste esigenze relative ai fondi propri in funzione dei rischi, i fondi propri di una banca devono pure soddisfare le esigenze poste alla quota d'indebitamento massimo (leverage ratio). Al riguardo, i fondi propri non devono essere inferiori a una percentuale minima degli impegni complessivi, costituiti dalla somma di bilancio e da determinate posizioni fuori bilancio.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Le modifiche delle ordinanze contengono anche disposizioni relative all'organizzazione di banche di rilevanza sistemica. Il mantenimento delle funzioni di rilevanza sistemica in caso di minaccia d'insolvenza viene disciplinato in un piano d'emergenza. In accordo con le prescrizioni del FSB, le banche devono presentare alla FINMA piani di stabilizzazione e informazioni sulla cui base essa può allestire un piano di attuazione (per il risanamento o la liquidazione della banca). Se, rispetto alle esigenze minime contenute nel piano d'emergenza, le banche migliorano le loro possibilità di risanamento e liquidazione in Svizzera e all'estero, la FINMA concede alleviamenti sulla componente progressiva. &lt;/p&gt;Le nuove esigenze per le banche di rilevanza sistemica dovranno progressivamente essere attuate entro il 2018. Il Parlamento deve approvare le disposizioni d'esecuzione adottate dal Consiglio federale. Le esigenze speciali relative alla liquidità saranno successivamente disciplinate in un'ordinanza separata che dovrebbe essere posta in consultazione nel 2012. </text>
      <contact>Comunicazione DFF Tel. +41 58 462 60 33 E-Mail: info@gs-efd.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="91335">
        <title>Documenti concernenti l’indagine conoscitiva (in francese)</title>
        <uri>http://www.efd.admin.ch/dokumentation/gesetzgebung/00571/02375/index.html?lang=it</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Hearing on "too big to fail" ordinances</title>
      <lead>On 30 September 2011, parliament approved the amendment of the Banking Act designed to strengthen financial sector stability (too big to fail). The legislative amendment should prevent the state from once again having to bail out a systemically important bank that is experiencing difficulties in order to avert major damage for the national economy. Today, the Federal Department of Finance (FDF) initiated the hearing on corresponding implementing provisions in the Banking Ordinance and Capital Adequacy Ordinance.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;The ordinances implement the approved amendment of the Banking Act and at the same time are in line with the requirements for global systemically important banks issued by the Financial Stability Board (FSB) in October 2011. The changes govern the increased capital, risk diversification and organisation requirements applicable to systemically important banks.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The higher capital requirements apply in parallel to the general requirements that are valid for all banks. They consist of a basic component representing 4.5% of risk-weighted assets (RWA) which banks must hold in the form of common equity Tier 1. Furthermore, systemically important banks must maintain a capital buffer of 8.5% of RWA, and at least 5.5% of this too must be in the form of common equity. 3% can be in the form of contingent convertible bonds (CoCos), i.e. debt capital that is converted into equity capital in the event of the bank experiencing a crisis or which the creditor has to forgo without receiving any compensation. Then, as an additional requirement, systemically important banks must hold a progressive component that depends on the total assets and market share of the bank in question. This component can be entirely in the form of CoCos. If need be, there will also be a countercyclical buffer that is applicable to all banks. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Alongside these risk-based capital requirements, banks must also meet the leverage ratio requirements. In this regard, the bank's equity may not fall below a set percentage of total exposure, consisting of the balance sheet total and certain off-balance sheet items.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Finally, the ordinance amendments contain provisions on the organisation of systemically important banks. On the one hand, they govern the emergency plan designed to maintain systemically important functions in the event of threatened insolvency. On the other hand and in accordance with the FSB requirements, banks must submit stabilisation plans and information to FINMA which it can use to draw up a resolution plan (to restructure or liquidate the bank in question). FINMA can grant less stringent requirements for the progressive component if individual banks improve their resolvability in Switzerland and abroad beyond the minimum requirements in the emergency plan.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The new requirements for systemically important banks must be gradually implemented by the end of 2018. The initial adoption of the implementing provisions by the Federal Council has to be approved by parliament. The special liquidity requirements will be covered at a later stage in a separate ordinance, which will probably be subject to a hearing during the course of 2012.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Communication FDF Tel. +41 58 462 60 33 Mail: info@gs-efd.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="91338">
        <title>Documents on the hearing (in German)</title>
        <uri>http://www.efd.admin.ch/dokumentation/gesetzgebung/00571/02375/index.html?lang=en</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <keywords>
      <keyword id="118" org-id="602">
        <name lang="de">Finanzmarktregulierung und -aufsicht</name>
        <name lang="fr">Réglementation et surveillance des marchés financiers</name>
        <name lang="it">Regolamentazione e vigilanza dei mercati finanziari</name>
        <name lang="en">Financial market regulation and supervision</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="126" org-id="602">
        <name lang="de">Finanzplatz Schweiz</name>
        <name lang="fr">Place financière suisse</name>
        <name lang="it">Piazza finanziaria svizzera</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland as a financial centre</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="1111" org-id="602">
        <name lang="de">Too big to fail</name>
        <name lang="fr">Too big to fail</name>
        <name lang="it">Too big to fail</name>
        <name lang="en">Too big to fail</name>
      </keyword>
    </keywords>
    <topics>
      <topic id="47">
        <name lang="de">Wirtschaft</name>
        <name lang="fr">Économie</name>
        <name lang="it">Economia</name>
        <name lang="en">Economic Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
