<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="11080" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2003-11-06</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="706" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>701</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Bundesamt für Veterinärwesen (BVET) - ab 2013 im EDI</name>
      <name lang="fr">Office vétérinaire fédéral (OVF) - dès 2013 au DFI</name>
      <name lang="it">Ufficio federale di veterinaria (UFV) - dal 2013 nel DFI</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal veterinary office (FVO) - as from 2013 in the FDHA</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.bvet.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.bvet.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.bvet.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.bvet.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@bvet.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@bvet.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@bvet.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@bvet.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="701">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Wirtschaft, Bildung und Forschung</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'économie, de la formation et de la recherche</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'economia, della formazione e della ricerca</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Economic Affairs, Education and Research</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Klassische Creutzfeldt-Jakob-Krankheit: Prionen im Muskel entdeckt</title>
      <lead>Forschende des Nationalen Referenzzentrums für Prion-Erkrankungen an der Universität Zürich konnten erstmals Spuren von Prionen in Muskel- und Milzgewebe von PatientInnen nachweisen, die an der klassischen Creutzfeldt-Jakob-Krankheit (CJD) verstorben sind. Prionen sind die Erreger von CJD und der Rinderkrankheit BSE. Über ihre Arbeit berichten die Forschenden in der Fachzeitschrift "New England Journal of Medicine ". Das Bundesamt für Gesundheit (BAG) und das Bundesamt für Veterinärwesen (BVET) erachten die bisherigen Präventionsmassnahmen in den Bereichen Lebensmittel und ärztliche Eingriffe auch in Anbetracht der neuen Resultate für ausreichend.</lead>
      <text link="no">Kontakt&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Marcel Falk Kommunikation 031 323 84 96&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;</text>
      <contact/>
      <attachment id="22392">
        <title>11/03 MR Prionen im Muskel</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>18</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/7115.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Forme classique de la maladie de Creutzfeldt-Jakob: des prions découverts dans le muscle</title>
      <lead>Des chercheurs du Centre national de référence pour les maladies à prions à l'Université de Zurich sont parvenus, pour la première fois, à mettre en évidence des prions dans du tissu musculaire et du tissu de la rate de patients décédés de la forme classique de la maladie de Creutzfeldt-Jakob (MCJ). Les prions sont les agents responsables de la MCJ et de la maladie des bovins appelée ESB. Les chercheurs décrivent leur travail dans la revue spécialisée New England Journal of Medicine . L'Office fédéral de la santé publique (OFSP) et l'Office vétérinaire fédéral (OVF) considèrent que les mesures de prévention prises jusqu'à présent dans les domaines des denrées alimentaires et des interventions médico-chirurgicales sont suffisantes, même compte tenu de ces nouveaux résultats.</lead>
      <text link="no">Contact&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Marcel Falk Communication 031 323 84 96&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;</text>
      <contact/>
      <attachment id="22391">
        <title>11/03 DP Prions dans du muscle</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>20</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/7114.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Forma classica della malattia di Creutzfeldt-Jakob: scoperta la presenza di prioni nei muscoli</title>
      <lead>Ricercatori del centro nazionale di riferimento per le malattie da prioni di Zurigo hanno potuto rilevare, per la prima volta, la presenza di tracce di prioni nei tessuti muscolare e splenico, in pazienti deceduti a causa della forma classica del morbo di Creutzfeldt-Jakob (MCJ). I prioni sono gli agenti patogeni all'origine della MCJ e della BSE, una malattia che colpisce i bovini. Il resoconto del lavoro svolto dai ricercatori appare nella rivista specializzata "New England Journal of Medicine ". Anche tenendo conto di questi nuovi risultati, l'Ufficio federale della sanità pubblica (UFSP) e l'Ufficio federale di veterinaria (UFV) reputano sufficienti le misure di prevenzione adottate finora, nei settori alimentare e degli interventi medico-chirurgici.</lead>
      <text link="no">Contatto&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Marcel Falk Communication 031 323 84 96&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;</text>
      <contact/>
      <attachment id="22393">
        <title>11/03 DS Prioni nei muscoli</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>20</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/7116.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Classic Creutzfeldt-Jakob disease: prions detected in muscle tissue</title>
      <lead>For the first time, researchers at the National Reference Centre for Prion Illnesses at the University of Zurich have been able to detect traces of prions in muscle and spleen tissue from patients who had died of classic Creutzfeldt-Jakob disease. Prions are the pathogens that cause CJD and BSE. The Zurich researchers report on their findings in the "New England Journal of Medicine ". Having studied the new research findings, both the Swiss Federal Office for Public Health and the Swiss Federal Veterinary Office have concluded that adequate prevention measures are currently in force for food safety and for surgical operations.</lead>
      <text link="no">Contact&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Marcel Falk Communication 031 323 84 96&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;</text>
      <contact/>
      <attachment id="22390">
        <title>11/03 PI Prions in muscle tissue</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>18</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/7113.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
  </message>
</messages>
