<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="86906" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2022-01-25</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="201" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>201</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="201">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Naher Osten: finanzieller Rückzug des EDA aus der Genfer Initiative</title>
      <lead>Die Schweiz unterstützt die Genfer Initiative seit ihrer Gründung im Jahr 2003. Aufgrund der Schlussfolgerungen einer externen Evaluation hat das Eidgenössische Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten (EDA) entschieden, sich schrittweise aus der Finanzierung der Initiative zurückzuziehen, die sie über zwei lokale Nichtregierungsorganisationen (NGO) unterstützt. Die Schweiz setzt sich im Rahmen ihres Kooperationsprogramms 2021–2024 weiterhin für Dialog und Frieden im Nahen Osten ein. Sie unterstützt die vom UNO-Sicherheitsrat formulierte Vision einer Region mit zwei demokratischen Staaten, Israel und Palästina, die Seite an Seite in Frieden und innerhalb sicherer und anerkannter Grenzen leben. Diese im Oktober 2020 bekräftigte Position des Bundesrates ist auch in der MENA-Strategie 2021–2024 verankert. </lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Über die Genfer Initiative unterstützte die Schweiz die Anstrengungen der israelischen und palästinensischen Zivilgesellschaft, die 2003 zum Genfer Abkommen und dessen Anhängen führten. Dieses Abkommen war ein bedeutsames Referenzdokument und hat gezeigt, dass es konkrete, realisierbare Vorschläge für eine Zweistaatenlösung gibt. Die Schweiz hat die Genfer Initiative seit 2003 mit rund 18 Millionen Franken unterstützt.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Angesichts der Empfehlungen einer ersten externen Evaluation im Jahr 2009 reduzierte das EDA seine Unterstützung schrittweise von 1 Million Franken (2009) auf 180’000 Franken (2021). &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Das EDA beurteilt die Kooperationen mit seinen Umsetzungspartnern in regelmässigen Abständen neu. Damit soll sichergestellt werden, dass das Geld der Steuerzahlerinnen und Steuerzahler gezielt und wirksam eingesetzt wird. Vor diesem Hintergrund und infolge der Stellungnahme des Bundesrates zur Motion Imark (18.3867) gab das EDA 2020 eine weitere externe Evaluation der Genfer Initiative in Auftrag. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Die Schlussfolgerungen dieser Evaluation sind eindeutig: Während die Initiative zu Beginn wichtig und relevant war, hat sie zunehmend an Effektivität und Einfluss verloren, auch wenn sich ihr Ziel mit der Schweizer Position für eine Zweistaatenlösung deckt. Gemäss Evaluation ist die Genfer Initiative im aktuellen politischen Kontext auch wenig relevant, da viele der beteiligten Akteure ihre Logik losgelöst von der heutigen Realität sehen. Zudem geniesst die Initiative sowohl in Israel als auch im Besetzten Palästinensischen Gebiet nur noch wenig politische Unterstützung. Aufgrund dieser Schlussfolgerungen und der in der MENA-Strategie festgelegten Grundsätze für die Zusammenarbeit mit NGOs, einschliesslich der Reduktion ihrer Anzahl, hat das EDA beschlossen, sich aus der Finanzierung der Genfer Initiative zurückzuziehen. Der Ausstieg erfolgt über zwei Jahre, bis Ende 2023, damit sich die Genfer Initiative darauf einstellen kann. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Zweistaatenlösung&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Die Schweiz engagiert sich bereits in neuen, innovativen Dialog- und Friedensinitiativen, die mehr Wirkung versprechen. Die bisherigen Zahlungen an die Genfer Initiative werden ab 2023 in diese Projekte investiert. Die friedensfördernden Aktivitäten werden parallel zum Engagement in der humanitären Hilfe und der Entwicklungszusammenarbeit im Rahmen des Kooperationsprogramms für den Nahen Osten 2021–2024 umgesetzt.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Die Schweiz ist trotz der zahlreichen Hindernisse überzeugt, dass nur eine von beiden Seiten verhandelte Zweistaatenlösung, die auf dem Völkerrecht und den international vereinbarten Parametern einschliesslich der Resolutionen des UNO-Sicherheitsrats basiert, zu einem dauerhaften Frieden zwischen Israelis und Palästinensern führen kann.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Kommunikation EDA Bundeshaus West CH-3003 Bern Tel. Kommunikationsservice: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Medienstelle: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <attachment id="226504">
        <title>Final Report: External Evaluation of the Geneva Initiative 2010-2020 (en)</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>2077</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/69994.pdf</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </attachment>
      <link id="226502">
        <title>MENA Strategie 2021-2024</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home/das-eda/publikationen.html/content/publikationen/de/eda/schweizer-aussenpolitik/Strategie_MENA_2021-2024</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="226503">
        <title>Schweizer Kooperationsprogramm für den Nahen Osten 2021–2024 (EN)</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/countries/occupied-palestinian-territory/en/home/international-cooperation/strategy.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Proche-Orient : le DFAE se désengage financièrement de l’Initiative de Genève</title>
      <lead>La Suisse soutient l’Initiative de Genève (IG) depuis sa création en 2003. Sur la base des conclusions d’une évaluation externe, le DFAE a décidé de progressivement se désengager financièrement de l’IG, qu’elle soutient au travers de deux ONG locales. Dans le cadre de son Programme de coopération 2021-2024, la Suisse reste pleinement engagée en faveur du dialogue et de la paix au Proche-Orient. Elle soutient la vision formulée par le Conseil de sécurité de l’ONU d’une région où deux États démocratiques, Israël et la Palestine, vivent côte à côte en paix à l’intérieur de frontières sûres et reconnues. Cette position, réaffirmée par le Conseil fédéral en octobre 2020, est ancrée dans la Stratégie MENA 2021-2024. </lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;A travers l’Initiative de Genève (IG), la Confédération a soutenu les efforts des sociétés civiles israélienne et palestinienne qui ont débouché en 2003 sur l’ Accord de Genève ainsi que ses annexes. Cet accord était un document de référence important et a démontré que des options concrètes pour une solution à deux Etats sont possibles. Le soutien de la Suisse à l’IG depuis 2003 se monte à quelque 18 millions de francs.&lt;br /&gt; Sur la base de recommandations d'une première évaluation externe en 2009, le Département fédéral des affaires étrangères (DFAE) a néanmoins progressivement diminué son soutien financier à l’IG au fil des années, passant de 1 million de francs en 2009 à 180'000 francs en 2021. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;En outre, le DFAE réévalue régulièrement ses engagements avec ses partenaires de mise en œuvre. Il s'agit de s'assurer que l'argent du contribuable est utilisé de manière ciblée et avec impact. Dans ce cadre, et suivant l’avis du Conseil fédéral à la motion Imark (18.3867), le DFAE a mandaté une nouvelle évaluation externe de l’IG en 2020. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Les conclusions de l’évaluation sont claires: si l’objectif de l’IG est aligné avec la position suisse pour une solution à deux Etats, son efficacité et son impact ont aujourd’hui diminué alors que l’initiative était au début importante et pertinente. L’évaluation note notamment la faible pertinence de l’IG par rapport au contexte politique actuel, constatant que nombre d’acteurs concernés voient sa logique détachée de la réalité présente. Elle manque aussi d’appui politique tant en Israël que dans le Territoire palestinien occupé. Sur la base de ces conclusions et conformément aux principes de collaboration avec les ONG énoncés dans la stratégie MENA, y compris la réduction de leur nombre, le DFAE a décidé de se désengager financièrement de l’IG. Ce désengagement s’étalera sur une période de deux ans, jusqu’à fin 2023, pour permettre à l’IG de s’y préparer. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Solution à deux Etats&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;La Suisse s’engage déjà pour de nouvelles initiatives de promotion du dialogue et de la paix innovantes qui présentent un plus grand potentiel d'impact. La Suisse affectera le financement de l’IG à ces nouveaux projets à partir de 2023. Les activités de promotion de la paix sont mises en œuvre en parallèle aux activités humanitaires et de développement, dans le cadre du Programme de Coopération Proche-Orient 2021-2024.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Malgré les obstacles nombreux, la Suisse est convaincue que seule une solution à deux États, négociée par les deux parties, conformément au droit international et aux paramètres convenus au niveau international, y compris les résolutions du Conseil de sécurité de l’ONU, peut conduire à une paix durable entre Israéliens et Palestiniens.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Communication DFAE Palais fédéral ouest CH-3003 Berne Tél. Service de communication: +41 58 462 31 53 Tél. Service de presse: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <attachment id="226507">
        <title>Final Report: External Evaluation of the Geneva Initiative 2010-2020 (en)</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>2077</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/69995.pdf</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </attachment>
      <link id="226505">
        <title>Stratégie MENA 2021-2024</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae/dfae/publikationen.html/content/publikationen/fr/eda/schweizer-aussenpolitik/Strategie_MENA_2021-2024</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="226506">
        <title>Programme de coopération suisse pour le Proche-Orient 2021–2024 (en)</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/countries/occupied-palestinian-territory/en/home/international-cooperation/strategy.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Medio Oriente: il DFAE annuncia la fine del sostegno finanziario all’Iniziativa di Ginevra</title>
      <lead>La Svizzera ha sostenuto l’Iniziativa di Ginevra sin dalla sua creazione nel 2003. Sulla base delle conclusioni di una valutazione esterna, il Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri (DFAE) ha deciso di revocare gradualmente il suo contributo finanziario all’Iniziativa, che ha sostenuto attraverso due ONG locali. Nel quadro del suo Programma di cooperazione 2021-2024, la Svizzera continua ad adoperarsi in favore del dialogo e della pace in Medio Oriente. Sostiene inoltre la visione formulata dal Consiglio di sicurezza dell’ONU: una regione con due Stati democratici, Israele e Palestina, che convivono pacificamente entro confini sicuri e riconosciuti. Questa posizione, ribadita dal Consiglio federale nell’ottobre del 2020, è ancorata nella Strategia MENA 2021–2024. </lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Attraverso l’Iniziativa di Ginevra, la Confederazione ha sostenuto gli sforzi della società civile israeliana e palestinese sfociati nel 2003 nella stesura dell’Accordo di Ginevra e dei relativi allegati. Il citato Accordo è un documento di riferimento significativo e la prova che esistono opzioni concrete plausibili per una soluzione a due Stati. Dal 2003 il sostegno della Svizzera all’Iniziativa di Ginevra ammonta complessivamente a circa 18 milioni di franchi.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Facendo seguito alle raccomandazioni formulate in una prima valutazione esterna del 2009, il DFAE ha ridotto gradualmente, negli anni, il suo sostegno finanziario all’Iniziativa, passando da 1 milione di franchi nel 2009 a 180 000 franchi nel 2021. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Inoltre, il DFAE riesamina regolarmente i suoi impegni con i partner esecutivi per accertarsi che il denaro delle e dei contribuenti venga usato in maniera mirata e porti ai risultati auspicati. Dando seguito alla risposta del Consiglio federale alla mozione Imark (18.3867), nel 2020 il DFAE ha commissionato una nuova valutazione esterna dell’Iniziativa di Ginevra. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Le conclusioni in essa formulate sono chiare: se all’inizio l’Iniziativa era importante e rilevante, ha in seguito perso sempre più efficacia e impatto, anche se il suo obiettivo è allineato con la posizione della Svizzera, favorevole a una soluzione a due Stati. La valutazione rileva inoltre la scarsa pertinenza dell’Iniziativa rispetto all’attuale contesto politico e fa notare che molti attori interessati considerano la sua logica come distaccata dalla realtà odierna. L’Iniziativa non riscuote sufficiente sostegno politico né in Israele né nel Territorio palestinese occupato. Sulla base di queste conclusioni e in virtù dei principi di collaborazione con le ONG stabiliti nella Strategia MENA, che prevedono anche la riduzione del loro numero, il DFAE ha deciso di revocare gradualmente il suo sostegno finanziario all’Iniziativa nell’arco dei prossimi due anni, cioè entro la fine del 2023, per permetterle in questo modo di prepararsi al cambiamento. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Soluzione a due Stati&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;La Svizzera si impegna già in nuove e innovative iniziative di promozione del dialogo e della pace che presentano un maggiore potenziale di impatto. I finanziamenti fino ad ora effettuati all’Iniziativa di Ginevra saranno investiti in questi progetti a partire dal 2023. Le attività di promozione della pace sono attuate in parallelo con le attività umanitarie e di sviluppo, nel quadro del Programma di cooperazione per il Medio Oriente 2021-2024.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Nonostante i numerosi ostacoli, la Svizzera è convinta che solo una soluzione a due Stati negoziata da entrambe le Parti nel rispetto del diritto internazionale e dei parametri concordati a livello internazionale – comprese le risoluzioni del Consiglio di sicurezza dell’ONU – possa condurre a una pace duratura tra Israeliani e Palestinesi.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Comunicazione DFAE Palazzo federale ovest CH-3003 Berna Tel. Servizio di comunicazione: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Servizio stampa: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <attachment id="226510">
        <title>Final Report: External Evaluation of the Geneva Initiative 2010-2020 (en)</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>2077</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/69996.pdf</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </attachment>
      <link id="226508">
        <title>Strategia MENA 2021-2024</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae/dfae/publikationen.html/content/publikationen/it/eda/schweizer-aussenpolitik/Strategie_MENA_2021-2024</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="226509">
        <title>Programma di cooperazione svizzera per il Vicino Oriente 2021–2024 (en)</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/countries/occupied-palestinian-territory/it/home/cooperazione-internazionale/strategia.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Middle East: the FDFA withdraws financial support for the Geneva Initiative</title>
      <lead>Switzerland has been supporting the Geneva Initiative (GI) since it was launched in 2003. Due to the conclusions of an external evaluation and following the regular review of the Federal Department of Foreign Affairs’ programmatic engagements, the FDFA has now decided to gradually withdraw its funding for the GI, which it supports through two local NGOs. Within the framework of its Cooperation Programme 2021–24, Switzerland remains fully committed to promoting peace in the Middle East and supports the vision formulated by the UN Security Council of a region where two democratic states, Israel and Palestine, live side by side in peace and within secure and recognised borders. This position, which was reaffirmed by the Federal Council in October 2020, is laid down in the MENA Strategy 2021–24. </lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Through the Geneva Initiative, the Swiss Confederation has supported the efforts of Israeli and Palestinian civil societies that led to the Geneva Accord and its annexes in 2003. The Accord was a significant reference document and showed that concrete options for a two-state solution are possible. Since 2003, Switzerland has contributed some CHF 18 million to the GI.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Based on the recommendations from an initial external evaluation in 2009, the FDFA has gradually decreased its financial support for the GI over the years, from CHF 1 million in 2009 to CHF 180,000 in 2021.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, the FDFA regularly reviews its engagements with its implementation partners. In so doing, it ensures that taxpayers' money is used in a targeted way and to the best effect. Within this context, and following the Federal Council's opinion on the Imark motion (18.3867), the FDFA commissioned another external evaluation of the GI in 2020.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The conclusions of the evaluation are clear: while the GI was important and effective in the beginning and the objective of the initiative is in line with Switzerland's position in favour of a two-state solution, its effectiveness and impact diminished. The evaluation also notes the GI's limited relevance in the current political context and finds that a number of stakeholders feel its rationale is disconnected from the current reality. The GI also lacks political support both in Israel and in the occupied Palestinian territory. Based on these conclusions and in accordance with the principles for collaboration with NGOs (which include reducing their number) set out in the MENA Strategy, the FDFA has decided to end its financial support for the GI. The financial support will be phased out over a period of two years, until the end of 2023, in order to allow the GI to prepare itself accordingly.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Two-state solution&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Switzerland already engages in new, innovative dialogue and peacebuilding initiatives that promise to have more impact. It will allocate the fundings of GI to other such initiatives beginning in late 2023. Peace promotion activities are implemented alongside humanitarian and development activities within the framework of the Cooperation Programme for the Near East 2021–24.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Despite the many obstacles, Switzerland firmly believes that only a two-state solution – negotiated by both parties, in accordance with international law and the internationally agreed parameters, including the UN Security Council resolutions – can bring about a lasting peace between Israelis and Palestinians.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>FDFA Communication Federal Palace West Wing CH-3003 Bern, Switzerland Tel. Communication service: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Press service: +41 58 460 55 55 E-mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @SwissMFA</contact>
      <attachment id="226513">
        <title>Final Report: External Evaluation of the Geneva Initiative 2010-2020</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>2077</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/69997.pdf</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </attachment>
      <link id="226511">
        <title>MENA Strategy 2021-2024</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/fdfa/fdfa/publikationen.html/content/publikationen/en/eda/schweizer-aussenpolitik/Strategie_MENA_2021-2024</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="226512">
        <title>Swiss Cooperation Programme for the Near East 2021–24</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/countries/occupied-palestinian-territory/en/home/international-cooperation/strategy.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="3">
        <name lang="de">Armee</name>
        <name lang="fr">Armée</name>
        <name lang="it">Esercito</name>
        <name lang="en">Armed Forces</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="30">
        <name lang="de">Ausserordentliche Lagen</name>
        <name lang="fr">Situations extraordinaires</name>
        <name lang="it">Situazioni straordinarie</name>
        <name lang="en">Special Situations</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="40">
        <name lang="de">Sicherheit</name>
        <name lang="fr">Sécurité</name>
        <name lang="it">Sicurezza</name>
        <name lang="en">Security</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
