<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="37471" revoked="no">
    <version>2</version>
    <pubdate>2011-01-31</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="201" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>201</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="201">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Bundespräsidentin Micheline Calmy-Rey auf Staatsbesuch beim EU-Vorsitz in Ungarn</title>
      <lead>Bundespräsidentin Micheline Calmy-Rey, Vorsteherin des Eidgenössischen Departements für auswärtige Angelegenheiten EDA, wird sich vom 2. bis 3. Februar 2011 zu einem Staatsbesuch in Ungarn aufhalten. Ungarn hat gegenwärtig die EU-Präsidentschaft inne.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Auf Einladung Ungarns wird Bundespräsidentin Calmy-Rey am Abend des 2. Februar 2011 zu einem Staatsbesuch in Budapest eintreffen. Auf dem Programm stehen unter anderem Gespräche mit Ungarns Präsident Pal Schmitt sowie dem ungarischen Aussenminister Janos Martonyi.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Ungarn hat gegenwärtig die EU-Präsidentschaft inne, weshalb die Beziehungen zwischen der Schweiz und der EU im Mittelpunkt der Gespräche von Bundespräsidentin Calmy-Rey in Budapest stehen werden.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Die Schweiz und Ungarn verbinden ausgezeichnete und intensive bilaterale Beziehungen. Bei ihrem letzten Besuch in Ungarn 2009 hatten die EDA-Vorsteherin und ihr ungarischer Amtskollege unter anderem eine konsularische Zusammenarbeit vereinbart. Ungarn gehört zu den jungen EU-Mitgliedstaaten, welche die Schweiz im Rahmen ihres Erweiterungsbeitrags zur Überwindung von wirtschaftlichen und sozialen Ungleichheiten in der erweiterten EU unterstützt.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;u&gt;Für weitere Informationen&lt;/u&gt;:&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Lars Knuchel&lt;br /&gt; Chef Information EDA&lt;br /&gt; +41 79 277 55 60&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Information EDA Bundeshaus West CH-3003 Bern Tel.: +41 (0)31 322 31 53 Fax: +41 (0)31 324 90 47 E-Mail: info@eda.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="79539">
        <title>Erweiterungsbeitrag: Schweiz - Ungarn</title>
        <uri>http://www.erweiterungsbeitrag.admin.ch/de/Home/Laender/Ungarn</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>La présidente de la Confédération Micheline Calmy-Rey en visite d'Etat auprès de la présidence de l'UE en Hongrie</title>
      <lead>La présidente de la Confédération Micheline Calmy-Rey, cheffe du Département fédéral des affaires étrangères DFAE, sera en visite d'Etat en Hongrie les 2 et 3 février 2011. La Hongrie assume actuellement la présidence de l'UE.</lead>
      <text link="no">La Hongrie a invité la présidente de la Confédération Micheline Calmy-Rey à se rendre à Budapest dans le cadre d’une visite d’Etat le 2 février 2011. Le programme prévoit entre autres des entretiens avec le président de la Hongrie Pal Schmitt et le ministre des affaires étrangères hongrois Janos Martonyi.&amp;nbsp;&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Etant donné que la Hongrie assume actuellement la présidence de l'UE, les discussions porteront surtout sur les relations entre la Suisse et l'UE. &amp;nbsp; &lt;p&gt;Les relations bilatérales entre la Suisse et la Hongrie sont excellentes et intensives. Lors de sa dernière visite en Hongrie en 2009, la cheffe du DFAE s'était notamment accordée avec son homologue hongrois sur une&amp;nbsp;coopération consulaire. La Hongrie fait partie des nouveaux Etats membres de l'UE que la Suisse soutient dans le cadre de sa contribution à l'élargissement, l’objectif étant de réduire les disparités économiques et sociales dans l'UE élargie.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;u&gt;Pour plus d’informations&lt;/u&gt;&amp;nbsp;:&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Lars Knuchel&lt;br /&gt; Chef de l’Information DFAE&amp;nbsp;&lt;br /&gt; +41&amp;nbsp;79&amp;nbsp;277&amp;nbsp;55&amp;nbsp;60&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Information DFAE Palais fédéral ouest CH-3003 Berne Tél.: (+41) 031 322 31 53 Fax: (+41) 031 324 90 47 E-Mail: info@eda.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="79540">
        <title>Contribution à l’élargissement: Suisse - Hongrie</title>
        <uri>http://www.erweiterungsbeitrag.admin.ch/fr/Home/Pays/Hongrie</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>La Presidente della Confederazione Micheline Calmy-Rey in visita di Stato alla presidenza UE in Ungheria</title>
      <lead>La Presidente della Confederazione Micheline Calmy-Rey, responsabile del Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri (DFAE), si recherà il 2 e il 3 febbraio 2011 in Ungheria per una visita di Stato. L’Ungheria detiene al momento la presidenza di turno dell’UE.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Su invito dell’Ungheria, la Presidente della Confederazione Calmy-Rey raggiungerà Budapest la sera del 2 febbraio 2011 per una visita di Stato. L'agenda prevede colloqui con il Presidente ungherese Pal Schmitt e con il ministro degli esteri Janos Martonyi.&amp;nbsp;&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Poiché l’Ungheria detiene la presidenza di turno dell’UE, le relazioni tra la Svizzera e l’Unione europea saranno al centro dei colloqui che la Presidente della Confederazione terrà a Budapest.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; I rapporti tra i due paesi sono eccellenti e intensi. In occasione della sua ultima visita in Ungheria nel 2009, la responsabile del DFAE e il suo omologo ungherese avevano convenuto una cooperazione consolare. L’Ungheria appartiene al gruppo di Stati membri dell’UE che beneficiano del sostegno elvetico nel quadro del contributo all’allargamento per la lotta alle disparità economiche e sociali.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;u&gt;Informazioni complementari:&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; &lt;/u&gt;Lars Knuchel&lt;br /&gt; Capo Informazione DFAE&amp;nbsp;&lt;br /&gt; +41 79 277 55 60&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Informazione DFAE Palazzo federale ovest CH-3003 Berna Tel.: (+41) 031 322 31 53 Fax: (+41) 031 324 90 47 E-Mail: info@eda.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="79541">
        <title>Contributo all’allargamento: Svizzera - Ungheria</title>
        <uri>http://www.erweiterungsbeitrag.admin.ch/it/Home/Paesi/Ungheria</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Federal President Micheline Calmy-Rey pays state visit to EU-President Hungary</title>
      <lead>Federal President Micheline Calmy-Rey, Head of the Federal Department for Foreign Affairs (FDFA), will be in Hungary for a state visit from 2 to 3 February 2011. Hungary currently holds the EU presidency.</lead>
      <text link="no">At the invitation of Hungary, Federal President Calmy-Rey will arrive in Budapest on 2 February 2011 for the start of her state visit. During her visit she will, amongst other things, hold discussions with Hungary’s president Pal Schmitt as well as with the Hungarian foreign minister Janos Martonyi.&amp;nbsp;&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Hungary currently holds the EU presidency, for which reason the main focus of the discussions held by Federal President Calmy-Rey in will be on Switzerland’s relationship with the EU. &lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Switzerland and Hungary enjoy excellent and intensive bilateral relations. On the occasion of her last visit to in 2009, the Head of the FDFA and her Hungarian counterpart agreed, amongst other things, on cooperation in consular matters. Hungary belongs to the group of new EU member states which benefits from Switzerland’s contribution to EU enlargement to help overcome economic and social disparities within the extended EU.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; &lt;u&gt;Further information&lt;/u&gt;: &lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Lars Knuchel&lt;br /&gt; Head of FDFA Information&lt;br /&gt; +41 79 277 55 60</text>
      <contact>Information FDFA Bundeshaus West CH-3003 Bern Tel.: (+41) 031 322 31 53 Fax: (+41) 031 324 90 47 E-Mail: info@eda.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="79542">
        <title>Contribution to EU enlargement: Switzerland - Hungary</title>
        <uri>http://www.erweiterungsbeitrag.admin.ch/en/Home/Countries/Hungary</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
