<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="37995" revoked="no">
    <version>2</version>
    <pubdate>2011-03-07</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="201" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>201</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="201">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Offizieller Besuch des georgischen Aussenministers Grigol Vashadze bei Bundespräsidentin Micheline Calmy-Rey</title>
      <lead>Bundespräsidentin Micheline Calmy-Rey hat heute den georgischen Aussenminister Grigol Vashadze in Bern zu einem offiziellen Besuch empfangen. Im Mittelpunkt der Gespräche standen bilaterale Themen, das Schweizer Schutzmachtmandat zwischen Georgien und Russland sowie internationale und multilaterale Fragen.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Im Zentrum der bilateralen Diskussionen stand die Entwicklung der politischen und wirtschaftlichen Beziehungen sowie der technischen Zusammenarbeit. Die Vertretung der diplomatischen und konsularischen Beziehungen Georgiens gegenüber Russland, welche die Schweiz seit März 2009 wahrnimmt, bildete ebenfalls einen Schwerpunkt der Gespräche. &amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Ein weiterer Ausdruck der guten Beziehungen zwischen Bern und Tbilisi ist der Beschluss Georgiens, neben seiner UNO-Vertretung in Genf eine Botschaft in Bern zu eröffnen. „Ihr neuer Botschafter und das Botschaftspersonal werden uns in Bern willkommen sein“, versicherte Bundespräsidentin Calmy-Rey ihrem Gast, Aussenminister Vashadze. &lt;b&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Erörtert wurde auch die Haltung der beiden Länder in der internationalen Zusammenarbeit, namentlich bei der Abrüstungskonferenz in Genf. Die Beziehungen Georgiens mit den Nachbarländern und Fragen der Energie im Südkaukasus waren weitere Diskussionspunkte.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Information EDA Bundeshaus West CH-3003 Bern Tel.: +41 (0)31 322 31 53 Fax: +41 (0)31 324 90 47 E-Mail: info@eda.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Visite officielle du ministre géorgien des affaires étrangères Grigol Vachadze auprès de la présidente de la Confédération Micheline Calmy-Rey</title>
      <lead>La présidente de la Confédération Micheline Calmy-Rey a reçu aujourd'hui le ministre géorgien des affaires étrangères Grigol Vachadze, en visite officielle à Berne. Les entretiens ont porté principalement sur des thèmes bilatéraux, sur le mandat de puissance protectrice de la Suisse ainsi que sur des questions internationales et multilatérales.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Le développement des relations politiques et économiques ainsi que la coopération technique étaient au centre des discussions bilatérales. La représentation des intérêts diplomatiques et consulaires géorgiens en Russie, que la Suisse assure depuis mars 2009, était également au cœur des entretiens. &amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;La décision de la Géorgie d’ouvrir une ambassade à Berne, en plus de sa mission auprès des Nations Unies à Genève, témoigne également des bonnes relations entre Berne et Tbilissi. "Nous accueillerons avec plaisir votre nouvel ambassadeur et le personnel de l'ambassade à Berne" a assuré la présidente de la Confédération Micheline Calmy-Rey à son hôte, le ministre des affaires étrangères Grigol Vachadze. &lt;b&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;La position des deux pays dans le domaine de la coopération internationale a été soulignée, particulièrement dans le cadre de la Conférence du désarmement à Genève. Les relations entre la Géorgie et ses voisins, ainsi que la question de l’énergie dans le Caucase du Sud ont également été abordées.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Information DFAE Palais fédéral ouest CH-3003 Berne Tél.: (+41) 031 322 31 53 Fax: (+41) 031 324 90 47 E-Mail: info@eda.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Visita ufficiale del ministro degli esteri georgiano Grigol Vashadze alla presidente della Confederazione Micheline Calmy-Rey</title>
      <lead>La presidente della Confederazione Micheline Calmy-Rey ha ricevuto oggi in visita ufficiale il ministro degli esteri georgiano Grigol Vashadze a Berna. Al centro dei colloqui stavano i temi bilaterali, il mandato della Svizzera in qualità di potenza protettrice tra la Georgia e la Russia nonché questioni internazionali e multilaterali.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Le discussioni bilaterali erano incentrate sullo sviluppo delle relazioni politiche ed economiche nonché della cooperazione tecnica. La rappresentanza delle relazioni diplomatiche e consolari della Georgia nei confronti della Russia, che la Svizzera svolge dal marzo del 2009, è stata un'altra tematica di fondo dei colloqui. &amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Un'ulteriore espressione delle buone relazioni tra Berna e Tbilisi è la decisione della Georgia di aprire un'ambasciata a Berna oltre alla sua rappresentanza ONU a Ginevra. «Il nuovo ambasciatore e il personale dell'ambasciata saranno i benvenuti a Berna», ha assicurato la presidente della Confederazione Micheline Calmy-Rey al suo ospite, il ministro degli esteri Vashadze. &lt;b&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Si è discusso anche sulla posizione dei due Paesi nell'ambito della cooperazione internazionale, in particolare all'interno della Conferenza sul Disarmo e sulle relazioni della Georgia con i Paesi limitrofi, sulle questioni dell'energia nel Caucaso meridionale.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Informazione DFAE Palazzo federale ovest CH-3003 Berna Tel.: (+41) 031 322 31 53 Fax: (+41) 031 324 90 47 E-Mail: info@eda.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions>
        <revision date="2011-03-07 16:32" type="R"/>
      </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Official visit by Georgian Foreign Minister Grigol Vashadze to Micheline Calmy-Rey, President of the Swiss Confederation</title>
      <lead>Swiss President Micheline Calmy-Rey today received the Foreign Minister of Georgia Grigol Vashadze in Bern for an official visit. The talks focused on bilateral topics, Switzerland's protecting power mandate between Georgia and Russia, and international and multilateral issues.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;The focus of the bilateral discussions was the development of political and economic relations and technical cooperation. The talks also centered on the representation of Georgia's diplomatic and consular interests in Russia, which Switzerland has assumed since March 2009. &amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Another sign of good relations between Bern and Tbilisi is Georgia's decision to open an embassy in Bern next to its UN mission in Geneva. "Your new ambassador and embassy staff will be welcome in Bern", President Calmy-Rey assured her guest, Foreign Minister Vashadze. &lt;b&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The two countries' positions in international cooperation, particularly at the disarmament conference in Geneva, were also discussed. Georgia's relations with neighbouring countries and energy issues in the South Caucasus were other points of discussion.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Information FDFA Bundeshaus West CH-3003 Bern Tel.: (+41) 031 322 31 53 Fax: (+41) 031 324 90 47 E-Mail: info@eda.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
