<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="38691" revoked="no">
    <version>5</version>
    <pubdate>2011-04-19</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="201" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>201</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="201">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Weltmalariatag – DEZA-Direktor Martin Dahinden eröffnet eine Ausstellung über Malaria</title>
      <lead>Weltweit leiden zwei Milliarden Menschen an Malaria, und jedes Jahr stirbt eine Million Kinder an dieser Krankheit. Trotz enormen Fortschritten bleibt sie ein grosses Hindernis für die Entwicklung. Aus Anlass des Weltmalariatages eröffnet DEZA-Direktor Martin Dahinden am 26. April in Bern eine Ausstellung, welche die Öffentlichkeit auf die Krankheit aufmerksam machen soll.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Die multimediale Ausstellung (Fotografien, Audio- und Videoinstallationen) gibt Einblick in diese komplexe Krankheit und ihre Folgen. Sie informiert über die Geschichte der Malaria, ihre Übertragung sowie die Präventions- und Behandlungsmöglichkeiten. Auch setzt sie sich mit den Herausforderungen auseinander, welche die Krankheit für die Entwicklung darstellt.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Gezeigt wird die Ausstellung, die vom 27. April bis am 7. Mai offen ist, im «Le Cap», Predigergasse&amp;nbsp;3, 1. Stock, in Bern (neben der Französischen Kirche). Der 2007 gegründeten SMG gehören elf schweizerische Akteure aus dem öffentlichen Sektor, der Privatwirtschaft und der Zivilgesellschaft an. Sie steht unter dem Vorsitz der Direktion für Entwicklung und Zusammenarbeit (DEZA). Der Weltmalariatag findet jedes Jahr am 25. April statt.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Interessierte Medienschaffende können ab 17.30 Uhr an der Eröffnung der Ausstellung teilnehmen.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Information EDA Bundeshaus West CH-3003 Bern Tel.: +41 (0)31 322 31 53 Fax: +41 (0)31 324 90 47 E-Mail: info@eda.admin.ch</contact>
      <attachment id="82553">
        <title>Einladung zur Eröffnung</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>1353</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/22815.pdf</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </attachment>
      <link id="82545">
        <title>Ausstellungsprogramm</title>
        <uri>http://www.deza.admin.ch/de/Home/Agenda/Agenda_Detailansicht?itemID=200057</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="82546">
        <title>Engagement der DEZA gegen Malaria</title>
        <uri>http://www.deza.admin.ch/de/Home/Themen/Gesundheit/Malaria</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions>
        <revision date="2011-04-19 11:48" type="R"/>
      </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Journée mondiale de lutte contre la malaria - Exposition inaugurée par le directeur de la DDC Martin Dahinden</title>
      <lead>La malaria affecte deux milliards de personnes à travers le monde et coûte la vie à un million d’enfants chaque année. Malgré les progrès effectués, elle reste un frein important au développement. Une exposition visant à sensibiliser l’opinion publique sera inaugurée le 26 avril à Berne en présence du directeur de la DDC Martin Dahinden. Cet événement est organisé à l’occasion de la Journée mondiale de lutte contre la malaria.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;L’exposition multimédiale (photographies, installations audio et video) mise sur pied par le Swiss Malaria Group (SMG) doit permettre aux visiteurs de se familiariser avec la complexité de la malaria et ses conséquences. Elle raconte notamment l’histoire de la maladie, sa transmission, sa prévention et les traitements possibles. Elle met aussi en lumière les défis et les obstacles posés par la maladie.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Présentée au Cap, à coté de l’Eglise française réformée, 1ère étage, Predigergasse 3 à Berne, l’exposition sera ouverte au public du 27 avril jusqu’au 7 mai. Le SMG, créé en 2007, rassemble onze acteurs suisses du secteur public, de l’économie privée et de la société civile. Il est chapeauté par la Direction du développement et de la coopération (DDC). La Journée mondiale de lutte contre la malaria est organisée chaque année le 25 avril.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Les médias intéressés peuvent participer à l’inauguration de l’exposition à partir de 17h30.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Information DFAE Palais fédéral ouest CH-3003 Berne Tél.: (+41) 031 322 31 53 Fax: (+41) 031 324 90 47 E-Mail: info@eda.admin.ch</contact>
      <attachment id="82554">
        <title>Invitation à l'ouverture</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>1353</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/22816.pdf</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </attachment>
      <link id="82547">
        <title>Programme de l'exposition</title>
        <uri>http://www.deza.admin.ch/fr/Accueil/Manifestations/Agenda_vue_detaillee?itemID=200057</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="82548">
        <title>Engagement de la DDC contre la Malaria</title>
        <uri>http://www.deza.admin.ch/fr/Accueil/Themes/Sante/Malaria</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions>
        <revision date="2011-04-19 11:48" type="R"/>
      </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Giornata mondiale contro la malaria - il direttore della DSC Martin Dahinden inaugura la mostra</title>
      <lead>La malaria colpisce due miliardi di persone al mondo. Ogni anno costa la vita a un milione di bambini. Malgrado i progressi finora ottenuti, la malattia resta un pesante freno allo sviluppo. In occasione della Giornata mondiale contro la malaria, il 26 aprile il direttore della DSC Martin Dahinden inaugurerà una mostra volta a sensibilizzare l'opinione pubblica.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;La mostra multimediale (fotografie, installazioni audio e video) organizzata dallo Swiss Malaria Group (SMG)&amp;nbsp;permette di familiarizzarsi con la complessità della malaria e delle sue conseguenze. Essa racconta in particolare la storia della malattia, la sua trasmissione, la sua prevenzione e i possibili trattamenti, mettendo in luce anche le sfide e gli ostacoli.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Presentata al «Le Cap», Predigergasse 3, Berna, primo piano (accanto alla Chiesa francese), la mostra rimarrà aperta al pubblico dal 27 aprile al 7 maggio. Istituito nel 2007, lo Swiss Malaria Group riunisce undici attori svizzeri del settore pubblico, dell'economia privata e della società civile. L'organizzazione fa capo alla Direzione dello sviluppo e della cooperazione (DSC). La giornata mondiale contro la malaria è organizzata ogni anno il 25 aprile.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I media interessati possono prendere parte all'inaugurazione della mostra a partire dalle ore 17.30.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Informazione DFAE Palazzo federale ovest CH-3003 Berna Tel.: (+41) 031 322 31 53 Fax: (+41) 031 324 90 47 E-Mail: info@eda.admin.ch</contact>
      <attachment id="82555">
        <title>Invitatione all'inaugurazione (fr)</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>1353</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/22817.pdf</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </attachment>
      <link id="82549">
        <title>Programma della esposizione (fr)</title>
        <uri>http://www.deza.admin.ch/fr/Accueil/Manifestations/Agenda_vue_detaillee?itemID=200057</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="82550">
        <title>Impegno della DSC contra la Malaria</title>
        <uri>http://www.deza.admin.ch/it/Pagina_iniziale/Temi/Salute/Malaria</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions>
        <revision date="2011-04-19 11:48" type="R"/>
      </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>World Malaria Day - Exhibition opened by Martin Dahinden, Director-General of the SDC</title>
      <lead>Malaria affects two billion people across the world and takes the lives of a million children each year. In spite of the progress that has been made, it remains a serious obstacle to development. An exhibition in Bern which aims to raise public awareness will be opened on 26 April in the presence of Martin Dahinden, Director-General of the SDC. This event has been organised in conjunction with World Malaria Day.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;A multimedia exhibition (photographs, audio and video installations) set up by the Swiss Malaria Group (SMG) will allow visitors to familiarise themselves with the complex nature of malaria and its consequences. In particular, it will tell the story of the disease, its transmission, its prevention and possible treatments. The exhibition will also highlight the challenges and the obstacles it poses.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;On view at the Cap, next to the French Reformed Church, 1st floor, Predigergasse 3 in Bern, the exhibition will be open to the public from 27 April to 7 May. The SMG, which was created in 2007, brings together eleven Swiss actors from the public sector, private enterprise and civil society. It operates under the aegis of the Swiss Agency for Development and Cooperation (SDC). World Malaria Day is held annually on 25 April.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Interested media may take part in the inauguration of the exhibition on 26 April beginning at 17:30.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Information FDFA Bundeshaus West CH-3003 Bern Tel.: (+41) 031 322 31 53 Fax: (+41) 031 324 90 47 E-Mail: info@eda.admin.ch</contact>
      <attachment id="82556">
        <title>Invitation for the opening event</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>1356</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/22818.pdf</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </attachment>
      <link id="82551">
        <title>Exhibition program</title>
        <uri>http://www.deza.admin.ch/en/Home/Events/Agenda_Detailed_view?itemID=200057</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="82552">
        <title>Commitment of the SCD against Malaria</title>
        <uri>http://www.deza.admin.ch/en/Home/Themes/Health/Malaria</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions>
        <revision date="2011-04-19 11:48" type="R"/>
      </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
