<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="40181" revoked="no">
    <version>2</version>
    <pubdate>2011-07-11</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="201" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>201</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="201">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Schweiz verstärkt ihre Präsenz in Benghazi</title>
      <lead>Die Schweiz will ihre Präsenz in Benghazi verstärken und entsendet einen Diplomaten in die ostlibysche Stadt, der ein Verbindungsbüro eröffnen soll. Bereits seit vier Monaten unterhält die Schweiz in Benghazi ein Programmbüro der Humanitären Hilfe.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Als einer der ersten Staaten eröffnete die Schweiz Mitte März 2011 ein Programmbüro der Humanitären Hilfe in Benghazi. Damit leistet die Schweiz einen Beitrag zur Linderung der Not der Menschen in Libyen. Dieses humanitäre Engagement der Schweiz wird fortgeführt.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Mit der Entsendung eines Sondergesandten nach Benghazi beabsichtigt die Schweiz, ihre Präsenz vor Ort zu verstärken und die Beziehungen zum Nationalen Libyschen Übergangsrats (National Transitional Council, NTC)&amp;nbsp; auf politischer Ebene zu intensivieren.&amp;nbsp;Der Sondergesandte hat&amp;nbsp; die Aufgabe,&amp;nbsp; die Interessen der Schweiz in Benghazi zu wahren, die Kontakte zum NTC zu pflegen und auszubauen sowie ein Verbindungsbüro zu eröffnen. Dieses soll in den Räumlichkeiten des Programmbüros der Humanitären Hilfe untergebracht sein.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Bis zur Etablierung einer rechtmässig gewählten Regierung ist der NTC der einzige Ansprechpartner der Schweiz in Libyen. Bundespräsidentin Micheline Calmy-Rey, Vorsteherin des Eidgenössischen Departements für auswärtige Angelegenheiten EDA,&amp;nbsp; traf sich bisher in Bern und in Tunis mit&amp;nbsp; Vertretern des NTC zu Gesprächen. Die Schweizer Botschaft in Tripolis ist seit dem 27. Februar 2011 aus Sicherheitsgründen geschlossen.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Information EDA Bundeshaus West CH-3003 Bern Tel.: +41 (0)31 322 31 53 Fax: +41 (0)31 324 90 47 E-Mail: info@eda.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="86197">
        <title>Einsatz der Humanitären Hilfe</title>
        <uri>http://www.deza.admin.ch/de/Dossiers/Die_Humanitaere_Hilfe_im_Einsatz/Lage_in_Libyen</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="86198">
        <title>Lage in Libyen</title>
        <uri>http://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home/recent/libyen.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions>
        <revision date="2011-07-28 14:43" type="R"/>
      </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>La Suisse renforce sa présence à Benghazi</title>
      <lead>La Suisse entend renforcer sa présence à Benghazi. Elle envoie un diplomate chargé d'ouvrir sur place un bureau de liaison en plus du bureau humanitaire qu'elle y entretient depuis quatre mois déjà.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;La Suisse a été l'un des premiers pays à ouvrir, mi-mars 2011, un bureau de l'Aide humanitaire à Benghazi pour contribuer à réduire les souffrances du peuple Libyen. Cet engagement est maintenu.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;En dépêchant sur place un envoyé spécial, la Suisse entend renforcer sa présence dans la deuxième ville de Libye et intensifier ses relations politiques avec le Conseil national de transition (CNT). L'envoyé spécial aura pour mission de défendre les intérêts de la Suisse à Benghazi, d'entretenir et de développer les contacts avec le CNT et d'ouvrir un bureau de liaison. Ce bureau sera installé dans les locaux du bureau de l'Aide humanitaire.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;En attendant l'élection d'un gouvernement légitime, le CNT est l'unique interlocuteur&amp;nbsp;de la Suisse en Libye. La présidente de la Confédération Micheline Calmy-Rey, cheffe du Département fédéral des affaires étrangères (DFAE), a déjà rencontré des représentants du CNT à Berne et à Tunis. L'ambassade de Suisse à Tripoli a été fermée le 27&amp;nbsp;février 2011 par mesure de sécurité.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Information DFAE Palais fédéral ouest CH-3003 Berne Tél.: (+41) 031 322 31 53 Fax: (+41) 031 324 90 47 E-Mail: info@eda.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="86199">
        <title>Engagement de l’Aide humanitaire</title>
        <uri>http://www.deza.admin.ch/fr/Dossiers/L_aide_humanitaire_sur_le_terrain/Situation_en_Libye</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="86200">
        <title>Situation en Libye</title>
        <uri>http://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/home/recent/libyen.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions>
        <revision date="2011-07-28 14:43" type="R"/>
      </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>La Svizzera amplia la propria presenza a Bengasi</title>
      <lead>La Svizzera intende ampliare la propria presenza a Bengasi e invia un agente diplomatico nella città della Libia orientale incaricato di creare un ufficio di collegamento. Quattro mesi fa la Svizzera ha aperto a Bengasi un ufficio programma per l’aiuto umanitario.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;La Svizzera è stata uno dei primi Stati ad aprire, a metà marzo 2011, un ufficio responsabile dell’aiuto umanitario a Bengasi. Con il nuovo ufficio la Svizzera intende contribuire ad alleviare le sofferenze del popolo libico. L’impegno umanitario della Svizzera sarà portato avanti.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Distaccando un inviato speciale a Bengasi, la Svizzera ha intenzione di ampliare la propria presenza in loco e di intensificare le relazioni con il Consiglio nazionale di transizione libico (National Transitional Council, NTC) sul piano politico. L’inviato speciale è incaricato di tutelare gli interessi della Svizzera a Bengasi, di coltivare e allargare i contatti con il NTC e di aprire un ufficio di collegamento. Il nuovo ufficio sorgerà nei locali dell’ufficio programma per l’aiuto umanitario.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Fintanto che non sarà instaurato un governo eletto legalmente, il NTC è l’unico&amp;nbsp;interlocutore della Svizzera in Libia. La presidente della Confederazione Micheline Calmy-Rey, capo del Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri DFAE, si è già incontrata a Berna e a Tunisi con i rappresentanti del NTC, con i quali ha potuto avere una serie di colloqui. L’Ambasciata di Svizzera a Tripoli è chiusa per motivi di sicurezza dal 27 febbraio scorso.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Informazione DFAE Palazzo federale ovest CH-3003 Berna Tel.: (+41) 031 322 31 53 Fax: (+41) 031 324 90 47 E-Mail: info@eda.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="86203">
        <title>Impegno umanitario</title>
        <uri>http://www.deza.admin.ch/it/Dossiers/L_Aiuto_umanitario_all_opera/Situazione_in_Libia</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="86204">
        <title>Situazione in Libia</title>
        <uri>http://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/home/recent/libyen.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions>
        <revision date="2011-07-28 14:43" type="R"/>
      </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Switzerland to strengthen its presence in Benghazi</title>
      <lead>Switzerland strengthens its presence in Benghazi, and sends a diplomat to the East Libyan city for the purpose of opening a liaison office. This will be in addition to the Swiss Humanitarian Aid Unit programme office which has already been up and running for the last four months.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;In mid-March 2011, Switzerland became one of the first countries to open a Humanitarian Aid programme office in Benghazi, and to make a contribution to alleviating the suffering being experienced by the people of Libya. Switzerland will continue with this humanitarian commitment.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;By sending a special envoy to Benghazi, Switzerland is signaling its intent to strengthen its presence there, and to intensify its political relations with the Libyan National Transitional Council (NTC). The Special Envoy is entrusted with the task of safeguarding Switzerland's interests in Benghazi, promoting and intensifying contact with the NTC, and with opening a liaison office. This will be situated in the premises of the Humanitarian Aid programme office.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Until such time as a legally elected government is in place, the NTC is the sole&amp;nbsp;partner for contact between Switzerland and Libya. So far the Federal President Micheline Calmy-Rey, Head of the Federal Department of Foreign Affairs, has met with representatives of the NTC for discussions in Bern and Tunis. For security reasons the Swiss Embassy in Tripoli has been closed since 27 February 2011.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Information FDFA Bundeshaus West CH-3003 Bern Tel.: (+41) 031 322 31 53 Fax: (+41) 031 324 90 47 E-Mail: info@eda.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="86201">
        <title>The Commitment of the Humanitarian Aid</title>
        <uri>http://www.deza.admin.ch/en/Dossiers/Humanitarian_Aid_out_on_mission/Situation_in_Libya</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="86202">
        <title>Situation in Libya</title>
        <uri>http://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home/recent/libyen.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions>
        <revision date="2011-07-28 14:43" type="R"/>
      </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
