<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="41020" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2011-09-07</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="1070" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>1070</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Der Bundesrat</name>
      <name lang="fr">Conseil fédéral</name>
      <name lang="it">Il Consiglio federale</name>
      <name lang="en">The Federal Council</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.admin.ch/gov/de/start.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.admin.ch/gov/fr/accueil.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.admin.ch/gov/it/pagina-iniziale.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.admin.ch/gov/en/start.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="601" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>601</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Finanzdepartement</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des finances</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale delle finanze</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Finance</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.efd.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.dff.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.efd.admin.ch/efd/it/home.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.efd.admin.ch/efd/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="1070">
      <name lang="de">Der Bundesrat</name>
      <name lang="fr">Conseil fédéral</name>
      <name lang="it">Il Consiglio federale</name>
      <name lang="en">The Federal Council</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.admin.ch/gov/de/start.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.admin.ch/gov/fr/accueil.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.admin.ch/gov/it/pagina-iniziale.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.admin.ch/gov/en/start.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <department id="601">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Finanzdepartement</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des finances</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale delle finanze</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Finance</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.efd.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.dff.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.efd.admin.ch/efd/it/home.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.efd.admin.ch/efd/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Bundesrat verabschiedet Botschaft zur Totalrevision des Versicherungsvertragsgesetzes</title>
      <lead>Der Bundesrat hat an seiner heutigen Sitzung die Botschaft zur Totalrevision des Versicherungsvertragsgesetzes (VVG) verabschiedet. Das geltende Gesetz ist über hundert Jahre alt und genügt den heutigen Anforderungen des modernen Versicherungsmarktes nicht mehr.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Der Gesetzesentwurf stützt sich auf die Ergebnisse des Vernehmlassungsverfahrens, auf eine umfangreiche Untersuchung über die Auswirkungen der Gesetzesänderungen und auf die Vorentscheide des Bundesrates vom Februar dieses Jahres. Das Versicherungsvertragsrecht wird äusserlich und inhaltlich an die veränderten Gegebenheiten angepasst. Es erhält einen zeitgemässen, übersichtlichen und den gewandelten Marktbedürfnissen angepassten Aufbau. Im Versicherungsvertrag sollen zwischen den Vertragsparteien gleich lange Spiesse geschaffen werden. Dies etwa dadurch, dass mit erweiterten vorvertraglichen und vertraglichen Informationspflichten grössere Transparenz geschaffen wird. Im Weiteren sollen übereilte Vertragsabschlüsse widerrufen werden können und es wird ein ordentliches dreijähriges Kündigungsrecht eingeführt. Eine wesentliche Verbesserung enthält die Vorlage zudem mit Blick auf die Verzugs- (v.a. Prämienzahlungsverzug) und Verjährungsbestimmungen. Ausserdem wird, etwa durch Vorschriften zu den Prämienanpassungsklauseln, das Bedürfnis berücksichtigt, den Vertrag während seiner Laufzeit unter bestimmten Voraussetzungen anpassen zu können.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Roland Meier Mediensprecher EFD +41 31 322 60 86 roland.meier@gs-efd.admin.ch</contact>
      <attachment id="87659">
        <title>Rohstoff</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>51</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/24155.pdf</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </attachment>
      <link id="87653">
        <title>Botschaft und Bundesgesetz</title>
        <uri>http://www.efd.admin.ch/dokumentation/gesetzgebung/00570/02291/index.html?lang=de</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Adoption par le Conseil fédéral du message sur la révision totale de la loi sur le contrat d’assurance</title>
      <lead>Lors de sa séance d’aujourd’hui, le Conseil fédéral a adopté le message concernant la révision totale de la loi sur le contrat d’assurance (LCA). Datant d’il y a plus de cent ans, la loi en vigueur ne répond plus aux dernières exigences d’un marché actuel des assurances.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Le projet de loi se fonde sur les résultats de la consultation, sur une analyse approfondie de l'impact de la révision de la loi et sur les décisions préalables prises par le Conseil fédéral en février dernier. Le droit du contrat d'assurance est adapté, tant sur le fond que sur la forme, aux circonstances actuelles. La LCA est ainsi dotée d'une structure moderne, claire et conforme aux nouveaux besoins du marché. Elle vise à mettre les parties au contrat d'assurance sur un pied d'égalité, en accroissant la transparence grâce à l'extension des obligations précontractuelles et contractuelles en matière d'information. Par ailleurs, les contrats conclus hâtivement devront pouvoir être révoqués et le droit de procéder à une résiliation ordinaire au bout de trois ans sera introduit. Le projet comprend également une amélioration importante des dispositions concernant la demeure (en particulier en cas de retard dans le paiement des primes) et la prescription. En outre, les dispositions relatives à l'adaptation des primes permettront de tenir compte du besoin de modifier le contrat sous certaines conditions et avant le terme prévu.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Roland Meier porte-parole du DFF +41 31 322 60 86 roland.meier@gs-efd.admin.ch</contact>
      <attachment id="87660">
        <title>Documentation de base</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>38</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/24156.pdf</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </attachment>
      <link id="87654">
        <title>Message et loi fédérale</title>
        <uri>http://www.efd.admin.ch/dokumentation/gesetzgebung/00570/02291/index.html?lang=fr</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Il Consiglio federale licenzia il messaggio concernente la revisione totale della legge sul contratto d’assicurazione</title>
      <lead>Nella sua seduta odierna il Consiglio federale ha licenziato il messaggio concernente la legge sul contratto d’assicurazione (LCA). La legge in vigore è ultracentenaria e non soddisfa più le attuali esigenze di un moderno mercato assicurativo.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Il disegno di legge si basa sui risultati della procedura di consultazione, su un'approfondita analisi delle ripercussioni delle modifiche di legge e sulle decisioni preliminari prese dal Consiglio federale nel mese di febbraio del corrente anno. Il diritto del contratto d'assicurazione è adeguato alle nuove circostanze sotto il profilo materiale e formale. Esso è strutturato in modo moderno, chiaro e conforme alle nuove necessità del mercato. Nel contratto d'assicurazione devono essere create condizioni di parità tra le parti contraenti, ad esempio mediante l'estensione dei diritti d'informare contrattuali e precontrattuali a garanzia di una maggiore trasparenza. Sono stati altresì introdotti il diritto di revoca che può essere esercitato in caso di conclusione avventata del contratto e un diritto di disdetta ordinario alla fine del terzo anno. Il disegno di legge contiene anche un miglioramento importante delle disposizioni sulla mora (in particolare nel pagamento dei premi) e sulla prescrizione. Inoltre con le disposizioni sulla clausola di adeguamento del premio si tiene conto dell'esigenza di poter adeguare il contratto a determinate condizioni nel corso della sua durata.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Roland Meier portavoce del DFF +41 31 322 60 86 roland.meier@gs-efd.admin.ch</contact>
      <attachment id="87661">
        <title>Documentazione</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>56</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/24157.pdf</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </attachment>
      <link id="87655">
        <title>Messaggio i legge federale (in francese)</title>
        <uri>http://www.efd.admin.ch/dokumentation/gesetzgebung/00570/02291/index.html?lang=it</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Federal Council adopts dispatch on total revision of Insurance Policies Act</title>
      <lead>At its meeting today, the Federal Council adopted the dispatch on the total revision of the Insurance Policies Act (IPA). The applicable law is over a hundred years old and is no longer sufficient to meet the current needs of the modern insurance market.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;The bill is based on the results of the consultation procedure, an extensive analysis of the implications of the legislative amendments and the preliminary decisions made by the Federal Council in February 2011. Insurance policies law will be adapted to the new circumstances in terms of both form and content. It will be given a modern and clear structure that is tailored to the changed market needs. A level playing field should be created for the contracting parties in insurance contracts. Consequently, greater transparency will be ensured by extended information obligations in the pre-contractual and contractual process. Furthermore, it should be possible for contracts concluded over-hastily to be revoked, and a routine three-year termination right will be introduced. The bill also contains a significant improvement regarding the provisions on delays (esp. late payment of premiums) and periods of limitation. In addition, thanks to the regulations on premium adjustment clauses, for example, account will be taken of the need to adapt the contract during its term under certain conditions.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Roland Meier Media Spokesperson FDF +41 31 322 60 86 roland.meier@gs-efd.admin.ch</contact>
      <attachment id="87662">
        <title>Basic information</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>59</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/24158.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <keywords>
      <keyword id="214" org-id="601">
        <name lang="de">Versicherungsaufsicht</name>
        <name lang="fr">Surveillance des assurances</name>
        <name lang="it">Sorveglianza delle assicurazioni</name>
        <name lang="en">Insurance supervision</name>
      </keyword>
    </keywords>
    <topics>
      <topic id="10">
        <name lang="de">Bundesrat</name>
        <name lang="fr">Conseil fédéral</name>
        <name lang="it">Consiglio federale</name>
        <name lang="en">Federal Council</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="37">
        <name lang="de">Konsum</name>
        <name lang="fr">Consommation</name>
        <name lang="it">Consumo</name>
        <name lang="en">Consumer Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
