<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="41151" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2011-09-14</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="201" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>201</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="201">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Offizieller Besuch des kuwaitischen Premierministers Sheikh Nasser Al-Mohammed Al-Ahmed Al-Jaber Al-Sabah bei Bundespräsidentin Micheline Calmy-Rey</title>
      <lead>Bundespräsidentin Micheline Calmy-Rey hat am 14. September 2011 den kuwaitischen Premierminister zu Gesprächen in Bern empfangen. Schwerpunkte der Erörterungen waren die bilateralen Beziehungen zwischen Kuwait und der Schweiz sowie die Entwicklung in der arabischen Welt.</lead>
      <text link="no">Der Besuch der kuwaitischen Delegation stellt den Gegenbesuch zur Reise von Bundespräsidentin Calmy-Rey nach Kuwait im November 2010 dar. Die heutigen Gespräche auf dem Landsitz Lohn bei Bern dienten der Intensivierung der bilateralen Beziehungen und der weiteren Förderung der wirtschaftlichen Zusammenarbeit zwischen der Schweiz und dem Golfstaat. Die Schweiz und Kuwait verbindet eine Reihe von Abkommen, so beispielsweise im Luftverkehrs- und Finanzbereich. An den Gesprächen wurden neben den bilateralen Themen auch die aktuellen Entwicklungen in der arabischen Welt, insbesondere in Libyen und Syrien, erörtert. &lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Am Nachmittag standen ein Treffen des Premierministers Sheikh Al-Sabah mit Nationalratspräsident Jean-René Germanier und eine Begegnung mit dem Berner Stadtpräsidenten Alexander Tschäppät auf dem Programm. Premierminister Sheikh Al-Sabah wird bei seinem Aufenthalt in Bern von einer hochrangigen Ministerdelegation begleitet. Diese Delegation trifft sich am Nachmittag zu einem Austausch mit Schweizer Wirtschaftsvertretern.</text>
      <contact>Information EDA Bundeshaus West CH-3003 Bern Tel.: +41 (0)31 322 31 53 Fax: +41 (0)31 324 90 47 E-Mail: info@eda.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Visite officielle du premier ministre koweïti Cheikh Nasser al-Mohammed al-Ahmed al-Jaber al-Sabah à la présidente de la Confédération Micheline Calmy-Rey</title>
      <lead>Le 14 septembre 2011, la présidente de la Confédération Micheline Calmy-Rey a reçu le premier ministre koweïti pour des entretiens à Berne. Les discussions ont porté sur les relations bilatérales entre le Koweït et la Suisse ainsi que sur les évolutions dans le monde arabe.</lead>
      <text link="no">La visite de la délégation koweïtie faisait suite au voyage de la présidente de la Confédération Micheline Calmy-Rey au Koweït en novembre 2010. Les entretiens menés au domaine de Lohn près de Berne avaient pour but d’approfondir les relations bilatérales et d’encourager la coopération économique entre la Suisse et cet Etat du Golfe. La Suisse et le Koweït sont liés par une série d’accords et de conventions, qui portent notamment sur le trafic aérien et le secteur financier. Les discussions ont permis d’évoquer, outre les questions bilatérales, l’actualité du monde arabe, notamment en Libye et en Syrie.&amp;nbsp;&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; L’après-midi, une rencontre était prévue entre le premier ministre Cheikh al-Sabah et le président du Conseil national Jean-René Germanier. Un autre échange de vues a eu lieu avec le président de la ville de Berne Alexander Tschäppät. Le premier ministre koweïti était accompagné à Berne par une délégation de ministres de haut rang, qui a pu discuter dans l’après-midi avec des représentants de l’économie suisse.</text>
      <contact>Information DFAE Palais fédéral ouest CH-3003 Berne Tél.: (+41) 031 322 31 53 Fax: (+41) 031 324 90 47 E-Mail: info@eda.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Visita ufficiale del primo ministro del Kuwait Sheikh Nasser Al-Mohammed Al-Ahmed Al-Jaber Al-Sabah alla presidente della Confederazione Micheline Calmy-Rey</title>
      <lead>Il 14 settembre 2011 la presidente della Confederazione Micheline Calmy-Rey ha ricevuto in visita ufficiale il primo ministro del Kuwait. Temi principali dell'incontro sono stati le relazioni tra Kuwait e Svizzera e gli sviluppi della situazione nel mondo arabo.</lead>
      <text link="no">La visita della delegazione kuwaitiana ricambia quella effettuata in Kuwait dalla presidente della Confederazione Calmy-Rey nel novembre 2010. Gli odierni colloqui, svoltisi nella tenuta di Lohn presso Berna, sono serviti a intensificare le relazioni bilaterali e a promuovere la cooperazione economica tra la Svizzera e il Paese del Golfo. Svizzera e Kuwait sono infatti uniti da una serie di accordi, tra cui quelli nel settore finanziario e del trasporto aereo. Oltre ai temi bilaterali si è discusso anche degli sviluppi dell'attuale situazione nel mondo arabo, in particolare in Libia e Siria.&amp;nbsp;&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; La visita ufficiale è proseguita nel pomeriggio con un colloquio&amp;nbsp;tra il primo ministro Sheikh Al-Sabah e il presidente del Consiglio nazionale&amp;nbsp;Jean-René Germanier e un incontro&amp;nbsp;con il sindaco&amp;nbsp;della città di Berna Alexander Tschäppät. Durante il suo soggiorno nella capitale&amp;nbsp;il primo ministro del Kuwait era accompagnato da una delegazione di alti ministri che nel pomeriggio si è incontrata per uno scambio di vedute con&amp;nbsp;rappresentanti dell'economia svizzera.</text>
      <contact>Informazione DFAE Palazzo federale ovest CH-3003 Berna Tel.: (+41) 031 322 31 53 Fax: (+41) 031 324 90 47 E-Mail: info@eda.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Kuwait's Prime Minister Sheikh Nasser Al-Mohammed Al-Ahmed Al-Jaber Al-Sabah pays an official visit to Federal President Micheline Calmy-Rey</title>
      <lead>On 14 September 2011, Federal President Micheline Calmy-Rey received the Kuwaiti Prime Minister in Bern for talks. Discussions focused on bilateral relations between Kuwait and Switzerland, and developments in the Arab world.</lead>
      <text link="no">The Kuwaiti delegation was returning the visit of Federal President to Kuwait in November 2010. Today's talks at the country residence of Lohn near Bern centred on intensifying bilateral relations and further promoting economic cooperation between Switzerland and the Gulf state. Switzerland and Kuwait already have agreements in place in a number of areas, such as air traffic and finance for example. Alongside topics related to bilateral relations the talks also considered current developments in the Arab world, in particular Libya and Syria.&amp;nbsp;&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; In the afternoon the programme included a meeting of the Prime Minister Sheikh Al-Sabah with the President of the National Council, Jean-René Germanier, and a meeting with the City Mayor of Berne, Alexander Tschäppät. Prime Minister Sheikh Al-Sabah was accompanied on his visit to Berne by a high-ranking delegation of ministers. This delegation met with representatives of Swiss business for an exchange of views in the afternoon.</text>
      <contact>Information FDFA Bundeshaus West CH-3003 Bern Tel.: (+41) 031 322 31 53 Fax: (+41) 031 324 90 47 E-Mail: info@eda.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
