<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="41312" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2011-09-21</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="201" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>201</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="201">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Vierländertreffen in Vaduz</title>
      <lead>Am 26. September reist Bundespräsidentin Micheline Calmy-Rey nach Vaduz zum traditionellen Vierländertreffen der Staatsoberhäupter der Schweiz, Deutschlands, Liechtensteins und Österreichs. Schwerpunkt der Gespräche bilden die jeweilige innenpolitische Lage, Fragen zu Europa und die Herausforderungen an die Bildungssysteme der vier Länder.</lead>
      <text link="no">Die Staatsoberhäupter der Schweiz, Liechtensteins, Österreichs und Deutschlands treffen sich seit dem Jahr 2004 jährlich zu einem informellen Gedankenaustausch über aktuelle politische Fragen. Neben Bundespräsidentin Micheline Calmy-Rey werden am diesjährigen Vierländertreffen Alois Erbprinz von Liechtenstein als Gastgeber sowie der deutsche Bundespräsident Christian Wulff und der österreichische Bundespräsident Heinz Fischer teilnehmen.&amp;nbsp;&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Schwerpunkt der Gespräche werden die Europapolitik, die Situation der Eurozone und internationale Finanzfragen sein. Vorgesehen ist zudem eine Diskussion zum Grundsatzthema Bildung in den vier Ländern. Am Nachmittag stehen in Vaduz eine Führung durch das Landesmuseum und ein Besuch des Landtagsgebäudes auf dem Programm.</text>
      <contact>Information EDA Bundeshaus West CH-3003 Bern Tel.: +41 (0)31 322 31 53 Fax: +41 (0)31 324 90 47 E-Mail: info@eda.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Rencontre quadrilatérale à Vaduz</title>
      <lead>La présidente de la Confédération, Mme Micheline Calmy-Rey, se rendra à Vaduz le 26 septembre pour la traditionnelle rencontre quadrilatérale entre les chefs d’Etat de la Suisse, de l’Allemagne, du Liechtenstein et de l’Autriche. Les entretiens porteront avant tout sur l’Europe ainsi que sur la situation intérieure et sur les défis se posant au système éducatif de chacun des quatre pays.</lead>
      <text link="no">Les chefs d’Etat de la Suisse, du Liechtenstein, de l’Autriche et de l’Allemagne se réunissent chaque année depuis 2004 dans l’un des quatre pays pour un échange informel consacré à l’actualité politique. Cette année, le prince héritier Alois du Liechtenstein accueillera la présidente de la Confédération, Mme Micheline Calmy-Rey, ainsi que le président de la République fédérale d’Allemagne, Christian Wulff et le président de la République d’Autriche, Heinz Fischer. &lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Les entretiens se concentreront sur la politique européenne, sur la situation de la zone euro et sur des questions de finance internationale. Une discussion de fond est prévue sur l’enseignement dans les quatre pays. L’après-midi sera consacré à une visite guidée du musée national et du bâtiment du Landtag (parlement).</text>
      <contact>Information DFAE Palais fédéral ouest CH-3003 Berne Tél.: (+41) 031 322 31 53 Fax: (+41) 031 324 90 47 E-Mail: info@eda.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Incontro quadripartito a Vaduz</title>
      <lead>Il 26 settembre la presidente della Confederazione Micheline Calmy-Rey si recherà a Vaduz per il tradizionale incontro quadripartito dei capi di Stato di Svizzera, Germania, Liechtenstein e Austria. Tra i principali temi dei colloqui, le rispettive situazioni politiche interne, l'Europa e le nuove sfide cui saranno confrontati i sistemi di formazione dei quattro Paesi.</lead>
      <text link="no">I capi di Stato di Svizzera, Liechtenstein, Austria e Germania si ritrovano regolarmente ogni anno dal 2004 per uno scambio informale di opinioni sull'attualità politica. Oltre alla presidente della Confederazione Micheline Calmy-Rey, all'incontro di quest'anno parteciperanno anche il principe ereditario Alois del Liechtenstein, Paese ospitante, il presidente tedesco Christian Wulff e il presidente austriaco Heinz Fischer.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; I colloqui verteranno in particolare sulla politica europea, sulla situazione nell'Eurozona e su questioni finanziarie internazionali. In agenda è prevista anche una discussione sul tema centrale della formazione nei quattro Paesi. Nel pomeriggio sono in programma a Vaduz una visita del museo nazionale e del Parlamento.</text>
      <contact>Informazione DFAE Palazzo federale ovest CH-3003 Berna Tel.: (+41) 031 322 31 53 Fax: (+41) 031 324 90 47 E-Mail: info@eda.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Four-country Meeting in Vaduz</title>
      <lead>On 26 September 2011, Swiss President Micheline Calmy-Rey will travel to Vaduz for the traditional four-country meeting of the Heads of State of Switzerland, Germany, Liechtenstein, and Austria. The discussions will focus on the domestic political situation in each of the countries, on European issues, and on the challenges facing the educational systems in the four countries.</lead>
      <text link="no">Since 2004, the Heads of State of Switzerland, Liechtenstein, Austria, and Germany have been holding annual meetings for an informal exchange of views on current political issues. In addition to Swiss President Micheline Calmy-Rey, the participants at this year’s four-country meeting will be Hereditary Prince Alois of Liechtenstein, as host, as well as German Federal President Christian Wulff and Austrian Federal President Heinz Fischer.&amp;nbsp;&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; The discussions will focus on European policy, the situation in the Eurozone, and issues of international finance. A discussion on the fundamental theme of education in the four countries is also on the agenda. In the afternoon, the programme in Vaduz will be rounded off by a guided tour of the Landesmuseum and a visit to the Landtag building (State Parliament).</text>
      <contact>Information FDFA Bundeshaus West CH-3003 Bern Tel.: (+41) 031 322 31 53 Fax: (+41) 031 324 90 47 E-Mail: info@eda.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
