<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="41397" revoked="no">
    <version>4</version>
    <pubdate>2011-09-27</pubdate>
    <blocking-period>2011-09-27</blocking-period>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="314" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>301</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Bundesamt für Kultur</name>
      <name lang="fr">Office fédéral de la culture</name>
      <name lang="it">Ufficio federale della cultura</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Office of Cultural Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.bak.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.bak.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.bak.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.bak.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@bak.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@bak.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@bak.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@bak.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="301">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement des Innern</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'intérieur</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'interno</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Home Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Das Bundesamt für Kultur vergibt den «Grand Prix Design 2011»</title>
      <lead>Das Bundesamt für Kultur zeichnet dieses Jahr vier international bekannte Designer mit dem «Grand Prix Design» aus. Die Preise gehen an den Produktdesigner Jörg Boner, an Dimitri Bruni und Manuel Krebs vom Grafikbüro NORM, an den Fotografen Ernst Scheidegger und den Schuhdesigner Walter Steiger. Ihre Arbeiten sowie die der Gewinnerinnen und Gewinner des «Eidgenössischen Preises für Design» werden im Rahmen einer Ausstellung gewürdigt. Sie findet unter dem Titel «Designpreise der Schweizerischen Eidgenossenschaft 2011» im mudac - Musée de design et d’arts appliqués contemporains in Lausanne statt. Die Vernissage ist am 18. Oktober.</lead>
      <text link="no">Mit dem «Grand Prix Design» ehrt das Bundesamt für Kultur jährlich Designerinnen und Designer oder ausgewiesene Designbüros, die auf nationaler und internationaler Ebene massgeblich zum Ruf des Schweizer Designs beitragen. Die Preise werden ausschliesslich an Designschaffende verliehen, die das 40. Altersjahr vollendet haben. &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Preisträger «Grand Prix Design 2011»&lt;br /&gt; &lt;/b&gt;Dieses Jahr wählte die Eidgenössische Designkommission vier Designer für den «Grand Prix Design» aus. Sie erhalten ein Preisgeld von jeweils 40‘000 Franken.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Der Produktdesigner Jörg Boner zählt zu den wichtigsten Schweizer Designer der mittleren Generation. Er wird für sein Werk und für seine Lehrtätigkeit ausgezeichnet. Dimitri Bruni und Manuel Krebs vom Zürcher Grafikbüro NORM sind seit Jahren in den Bereichen Buchdesign und Typographie erfolgreich tätig. Mit ihrem Schaffen haben sie unzählige Junggrafikerinnen und –grafiker beeinflusst. Der Fotograf Ernst Scheidegger wird für sein Lebenswerk ausgezeichnet, er hat sich sein Leben lang mit den Facetten angewandter Kunst beschäftigt. Seine Künstlerportraits werden seit Jahrzehnten weltweit publiziert und ausgestellt. Der in Paris tätige Walter Steiger designt seit über 40 Jahren Schuhe. Seine aussergewöhnlichen Entwürfe entstehen oft in enger Zusammenarbeit mit weltberühmten Modedesignern. Seine Designs sind noch heute von grösster Aktualität.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Preisträgerinnen und Preisträger «Eidgenössischer Preis für Design 2011»&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt; Die Eidgenössische Designkommission prämierte 24 Werke/Projekte von 33 Nachwuchstalenten. Dieses Jahr sind die Kategorien Mode-/Textildesign und Fotografie mit je sechs Preisen stark vertreten. In der Kategorie Grafikdesign wurden fünf Preise, im Industrie- und Produktdesign zwei Auszeichnungen vergeben. Aussergewöhnlich ist die starke Präsenz im Bereich Szenografie mit drei Preisen sowie das erstmals ein Preis in der Kategorie Designvermittlung vergeben wurde. Dieses Jahr wurde zudem ein Designer in der Kategorie Keramik ausgezeichnet.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Für den diesjährigen Wettbewerb reichten 266 Designerinnen und Designer ihre Dossiers ein. Die Preise bestehen wahlweise aus einem Geldbeitrag über 25‘000 Franken, Atelieraufenthalte in renommierten Büros oder freie Atelieraufenthalte in New York. Die Form des Preises bestimmen die Preisträgerinnen und Preisträger.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Der «Eidgenössische Preis für Design 2011» war der letzte Jahrgang mit Altersbegrenzung bis zum 40. Lebensjahr. Ab 2012 ist die Alterslimite aufgehoben. Es ist der wichtigste nationale Wettbewerb zur Förderung des jungen Schweizer Designs und wird seit 1918 veranstaltet.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Ausstellung der ausgezeichneten Arbeiten im mudac in Lausanne&lt;br /&gt; &lt;/b&gt;Die ausgezeichneten Arbeiten und Projekte werden ab 18. Oktober 2011 im mudac - Musée de design et d’arts appliqués contemporains in Lausanne ausgestellt. Die Szenografie realisiert Stephane Barbier Bouvet aus Lausanne. Gleichzeitig erscheint die alljährliche Publikation. Sie stellt die sowohl prämierten Arbeiten als auch die ausgezeichneten Designerinnen und Designer in Bild und Text vor. Die Publikation wird von Jonathan Hares, Lausanne gestaltet und erscheint im Verlag Birkhäuser. Zudem gibt es umfassende Informationen zu den Gewinnern (Jahrgang 2011 ab 18. Oktober 2011) auch online unter &lt;u&gt;www.swissdesignawards.ch&lt;/u&gt;.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Mediendossier und Bilder&lt;br /&gt; &lt;/b&gt;Umfassende Informationen und Pressebilder «Grand Prix Design 2011»: &lt;u&gt;www.bak.admin.ch/GPD2011&lt;/u&gt;.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Umfassende Informationen, Pressebilder sowie die Liste aller Gewinnerinnen und Gewinner&lt;br /&gt; «Eidgenössischer Preis für Design 2011»: &lt;u&gt;www.bak.admin.ch/SDA2011&lt;/u&gt;.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; &lt;strong&gt;Pressekonferenz&lt;br /&gt; &lt;/strong&gt;Dienstag 18. Oktober 2011, 10 Uhr im mudac, Lausanne&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Preisverleihung und Vernissage&lt;br /&gt; &lt;/b&gt;Dienstag, 18. Oktober&lt;br /&gt; 18 Uhr: Preisverleihung im Cinéma Capitole, av. Théâtre 6, Lausanne&lt;br /&gt; 19.30 Uhr: Ausstellungseröffnung im mudac, Lausanne&lt;br /&gt; Ab 20 Uhr: Apéro&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Anna Niederhäuser, Kuratorin, Sektion Kulturschaffen, Bundesamt für Kultur + 41 (0) 79 476 64 74, anna.niederhaeuser@bak.admin.ch Susanne Goldschmid, stv. Leiterin Kommunikation, Bundesamt für Kultur +41 (0) 31 322 92 34, susanne.goldschmid@bak.admin.ch Claire Favre Maxwell, Kuratorin, mudac + 41 (0) 315 25 30, claire.favre-maxwell@lausanne.ch</contact>
      <link id="88779">
        <title>Mediendossier und Bilder «Grand Prix Design 2011»</title>
        <uri>http://www.bak.admin.ch/GPD2011</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="88780">
        <title>Mediendossier, Bilder und Liste Gewinnerinnen und Gewinner «Eidgenössischer Preis für Design 2011»</title>
        <uri>http://www.bak.admin.ch/SDA2011</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="88781">
        <title>www.mudac.ch</title>
        <uri>http://www.mudac.ch/</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions>
        <revision date="2011-09-27 09:47" type="R"/>
        <revision date="2011-09-27 09:22" type="R"/>
      </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>L’Office fédéral de la culture décerne le «Grand Prix Design 2011»</title>
      <lead>L’Office fédéral de la culture distingue cette année par le «&amp;nbsp;Grand Prix Design&amp;nbsp;» quatre designers de renommée internationale. Les lauréats sont le designer-produit Jörg Boner, le studio de création graphique NORM (Dimitri Bruni et Manuel Krebs), le photographe Ernst Scheidegger et le designer de chaussures Walter Steiger. Leurs travaux, comme ceux des lauréats et lauréates du «&amp;nbsp;Prix fédéral de design&amp;nbsp;», seront récompensés dans le cadre d’une exposition intitulée «&amp;nbsp;Prix de design de la Confédération suisse 2011&amp;nbsp;» qui se tiendra au mudac (Musée de design et d’arts appliqués contemporains) à Lausanne. Le vernissage aura lieu le 18 octobre.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Avec le « Grand Prix Design », l’Office fédéral de la culture récompense chaque année des designers ou des bureaux de design confirmés qui donnent au design de notre pays la notoriété dont il jouit en Suisse et à l’étranger. Les prix récompensent exclusivement des designers âgés de 40 ans et plus.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Lauréats du «Grand Prix Design 2011»&lt;br /&gt; &lt;/strong&gt;La commission fédérale de design a désigné cette année quatre lauréats pour le « Grand Prix Design », qui reçoivent chacun un prix d’un montant de 40 000 francs.&lt;br /&gt; Le designer-produit Jörg Boner fait partie des plus importants designers suisses. Il est distingué pour son travail et son activité d’enseignement. Dimitri Bruni et Manuel Krebs, du studio de création graphique zurichois NORM, travaillent depuis des années dans les domaines du design du livre et de la typographie ; leur travail a influencé un nombre incalculable de jeunes graphistes. Le photographe Ernst Scheidegger est récompensé pour l’ensemble de son œuvre ; il s’est intéressé tout au long de sa vie aux multiples facettes de l’art appliqué. Ses portraits d’artistes sont publiés et exposés dans le monde entier depuis des décennies. Walter Steiger travaille à Paris et dessine des chaussures depuis plus de 40 ans. Ses projets exceptionnels naissent souvent en étroite collaboration avec des stylistes mondialement célèbres. Ses designs sont aujourd’hui encore d’une grande actualité.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Lauréates et lauréats du «Prix fédéral de design 2011»&lt;br /&gt; &lt;/b&gt;La commission fédérale de design a récompensé 24 œuvres/projets de 33 jeunes talents. Cette année, les catégories design de mode/de textile et la photographie sont bien représentées avec 6 prix chacune. Le graphisme reçoit cinq prix, et le design-produit et industriel deux. Le domaine scénographie est exceptionnellement bien représenté avec trois prix ; un prix a en outre été décerné pour la première fois dans la catégorie médiation de design. Finalement, une récompense va cette année à un céramiste.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;En 2011, 266 designers ont soumis un dossier de candidature. Les prix consistent au choix en une somme de 25 000 francs, un stage dans un bureau de design renommé ou un séjour en atelier à New York. Le choix est fait par les lauréats.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;L’édition 2011 du « Prix fédéral de design » était la dernière à imposer une limite d’âge de 40 ans. Cette limite sera levée dès l’année prochaine. Le « Prix fédéral de design » est le principal concours national qui soutient les jeunes designers suisses ; il est organisé depuis 1918.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Exposition des travaux primés au mudac à Lausanne&lt;br /&gt; &lt;/b&gt;Les travaux et les projets primés seront exposés à partir du 18 octobre 2011 au mudac (Musée de design et d’arts appliqués contemporains) à Lausanne. Stéphane Barbier Bouvet, de Lausanne, réalise la scénographie. La publication annuelle paraîtra parallèlement à l’exposition. Elle présente en détail, par des textes et des photos, les travaux primés et les designers distingués. La publication est réalisée par Jonathan Hares, Lausanne et paraît aux éditions Birkhäuser. Des informations détaillées sur les lauréats (édition 2011 dès le 18 octobre 2011) sont également disponibles en ligne sur &lt;u&gt;www.swissdesignawards.ch&lt;/u&gt;.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Dossier de presse et photos&lt;br /&gt; &lt;/b&gt;Les informations détaillées et photos destinées à l’impression «Grand Prix Design 2011» : &lt;u&gt;www.bak.admin.ch/GPD2011&lt;/u&gt;.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Les informations détaillées, photos destinées à l’impression et la liste de tous les lauréats&lt;br /&gt; « Prix fédéral de design 2011 » : &lt;u&gt;www.bak.admin.ch/SDA2011&lt;/u&gt;.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Conférence de presse&lt;br /&gt; &lt;/strong&gt;Jeudi 18 octobre 2011, 10 heures au mudac, Lausanne&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Remise des prix et vernissage&lt;br /&gt; &lt;/b&gt;Jeudi 18 octobre&lt;br /&gt; 18 heures : remise des prix au Cinéma Capitole, av. Théâtre 6, Lausanne&lt;br /&gt; 19 h 30 : vernissage au mudac, Lausanne&lt;br /&gt; Dès 20 heures : apéro (sur invitation)&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Anna Niederhäuser, curatrice, section Création culturelle, Office fédéral de la culture + 41 (0) 79 476 64 74, anna.niederhaeuser@bak.admin.ch Susanne Goldschmid, Cheffe suppléante Communication, Office fédéral de la culture +41 (0) 31 322 92 34, susanne.goldschmid@bak.admin.ch Claire Favre Maxwell, curatrice, mudac + 41 (0) 21 315 25 30, claire.favre-maxwell@lausanne.ch</contact>
      <link id="88781">
        <title>www.mudac.ch</title>
        <uri>http://www.mudac.ch/</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions>
        <revision date="2011-09-27 09:47" type="R"/>
      </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>L'Ufficio federale della cultura attribuisce il «Grand Prix Design» 2011</title>
      <lead>L'Ufficio federale della cultura attribuisce quest'anno il «Grand Prix Design» a quattro designer di fama internazionale: al designer di prodotti Jörg Boner, ai grafici Dimitri Bruni e Manuel Krebs dello studio NORM, al fotografo Ernst Scheidegger e allo stilista di calzature Walter Steiger. I loro lavori e i lavori dei vincitori e delle vincitrici del «Premio federale di design» saranno esposti in una mostra dal titolo «Premi di design della Confederazione Svizzera 2011» allestita al mudac, Musée de design et d’arts appliqués contemporains, di Losanna. La vernice si svolgerà il 18 ottobre prossimo.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Il «Grand Prix Design» è una distinzione che l'Ufficio federale della cultura attribuisce ogni anno a personalità e aziende che hanno contribuito in misura determinante, sul piano nazionale e internazionale, alla reputazione del design svizzero. I premi sono attribuiti esclusivamente a designer che hanno compiuto il 40° anno di età.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Vincitori e vincitrici del «Grand Prix Design 2011»&lt;br /&gt; &lt;/b&gt;Quest'anno la Commissione federale del design ha attribuito quattro premi di 40 000 franchi ciascuno a cinque personalità di spicco del design. Il designer di prodotti Jörg Boner è tra i principali protagonisti svizzeri della generazione di mezzo. La Confederazione lo premia per il suo impegno come progettista e docente. Il duo di grafici Dimitri Bruni e Manuel Krebs dello studio zurighese NORM sono attivi da anni con successo nell'ambito del design librario e della tipografia. Con i loro prodotti hanno influenzato innumerevoli grafici emergenti. Il fotografo Ernst Scheidegger è premiato per il suo operato: da sempre si è dedicato alle arti applicate in tutte le loro sfaccettature. Tra l'altro i suoi ritratti fotografici di artisti sono stati pubblicati ed esposti in tutto il mondo. Da oltre 40 anni, lo stilista Walter Steiger disegna calzature a Parigi. I suoi modelli, spesso realizzati in stretta collaborazione con stilisti prestigiosi, sono tuttora di grande attualità.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Vincitori e vincitrici del «Premio federale di design 2011»&lt;br /&gt; &lt;/b&gt;La Commissione federale del design ha premiato 24 lavori di 33 giovani talenti. Quest'anno sono state particolarmente beneficiate le categorie moda/tessili e fotografia con sei premi ciascuna. Nella categoria grafica sono stati assegnati cinque premi, nella categoria design industriale e di prodotti due premi. Significativa la presenza anche nella categoria scenografia, che si è aggiudicata tre premi. Nella categoria ceramica è stato attribuito un premio. Per la prima volta è stato vinto un premio nella categoria mediazione del design.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;All'edizione 2011 del «Premio federale di design» sono state presentate 266 candidature. I vincitori e le vincitrici possono scegliere tra un premio in denaro di 25 000 franchi, uno stage in prestigiosi studi di design o un soggiorno in un atelier a New York.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;L'edizione 2011 del «Premio federale di design» è stata l'ultima con un limite di età di 40 anni. Dal 1918 il Concorso è indetto regolarmente ogni anno per promuovere i giovani talenti nel design.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Mostra dei lavori premiati al mudac di Losanna&lt;br /&gt; &lt;/b&gt;I lavori e progetti premiati saranno esposti al pubblico dal 18 ottobre 2011 al mudac, Musée de design et d’arts appliqués contemporains, di Losanna. L'allestimento espositivo è stato curato da Stephane Barbier Bouvet di Losanna. A documentazione della mostra è pubblicato un volume, per i tipi della casa editrice Birkhäuser, che presenta i lavori premiati e i loro creatori in testi e immagini. La veste grafica è curata da Jonathan Hares di Losanna. Per informazioni dettagliate sui vincitori e le vincitrici (edizione 2011 dal 18 ottobre 2011 in poi) si rimanda anche al sito &lt;u&gt;www.swissdesignawards.ch&lt;/u&gt;.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Documentazione per la stampa e immagini&lt;br /&gt; &lt;/b&gt;Informazioni esaustive e immagini a risoluzione stampabile «Grand Prix Design 2011»: &lt;u&gt;www.bak.admin.ch/GPD2011&lt;/u&gt;.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Informazioni esaustive, immagini a risoluzione stampabile e la lista dei vincitori e delle vincitrici&lt;br /&gt; «Premio federale di design 2011»: &lt;u&gt;www.bak.admin.ch/SDA2011&lt;/u&gt;.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Conferenza stampa&lt;br /&gt; &lt;/strong&gt;Martedì 18 ottobre 2011, ore 10, mudac, Losanna&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Premiazione e vernice&lt;br /&gt; &lt;/b&gt;Martedì 18 ottobre 2011&lt;br /&gt; Ore 18: premiazione al Cinema Capitole, av. Théâtre 6, Losanna&lt;br /&gt; Ore 19.30: inaugurazione al mudac, Losanna&lt;br /&gt; Ore 20: aperitivo (su invito)&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Anna Niederhäuser, curatrice, sezione Produzione culturale, Ufficio federale della cultura tel. + 41 (0) 79 476 64 74, anna.niederhaeuser@bak.admin.ch Susanne Goldschmid, responsabile supplente Comunicazione, Ufficio federale della cultura +41 (0) 31 322 92 34, susanne.goldschmid@bak.admin.ch Claire Favre Maxwell, curatrice, mudac tel. +41 (0) 21 315 25 30, claire.favre-maxwell@lausanne.ch</contact>
      <link id="88781">
        <title>www.mudac.ch</title>
        <uri>http://www.mudac.ch/</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions>
        <revision date="2011-09-27 09:47" type="R"/>
      </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Federal Office of Culture awards the Grand Prix Design 2011</title>
      <lead>This year, the Federal Office of Culture is awarding the Grand Prix Design to four internationally renowned designers. The awards go to product designers Jörg Boner, Dimitri Bruni and Manuel Krebs from the graphic design studio NORM, photographer Ernst Scheidegger and shoe designer Walter Steiger. Their work, as well as the work of the winners of the Swiss Federal Design Awards 2011, will be honoured with an exhibition of the same name, which will be held at the mudac (Museum of Design and Contemporary Applied Arts) in Lausanne. The vernissage will take place on 18 October.</lead>
      <text link="no">Every year, the Federal Office of Culture awards the Grand Prix Design to designers or distinguished design studios to honour them for their significant contribution at national and international level to the reputation of Swiss design. The awards are given only to designers over the age of 40. &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Winners of the Grand Prix Design 2011&lt;br /&gt; &lt;/b&gt;This year, the Federal Design Commission nominated four designers for the Grand Prix Design. They will each receive prize winnings of CHF 40,000.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The product designer Jörg Boner ranks among the most important middle-generation Swiss designers. He will be honoured for his work and his teaching activities. Dimitri Bruni and Manuel Krebs from the graphic design studio NORM in Zurich have been successfully involved in book designing and typography for many years. Their work has influenced innumerable young graphic designers. The photographer Ernst Scheidegger will be honoured for his life’s work, which involves the exploration of the many facets of applied art. His portraits of artists have been published and exhibited worldwide for decades. Walter Steiger who works in Paris has been designing shoes for more than 40 years. He often creates his exceptional designs in close collaboration with world-famous fashion designers. His designs are still very much in style today.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Winners of the Swiss Federal Design Awards 2011&lt;br /&gt; &lt;/b&gt;The Federal Design Commission selected 24 works / projects by 33 young talents. The fashion/textile design and photography categories were strongly represented this year, each being awarded six prizes. Five prizes were awarded in the graphic design category, and two distinctions were awarded in the industrial and product design category. Exceptionally the strong presence in the field of scenography garnered three prizes and a prize was awarded for the first time in the design business category. This year, a designer was also selected in the ceramics category.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;In this year’s competition, 266 designers submitted their dossiers. The competition prizes consist either of a cash sum of CHF 25,000, internships with renowned studios or offices, or studio residencies in New York. The award winners decide on the form of their prize.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The Swiss Federal Design Awards 2011 is the last year in which the over-40 eligibility requirement will apply. From 2012 there will no longer be an age requirement. The Swiss Federal Design Awards is the most important national competition for the promotion of young Swiss design and has been held since 1918.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Exhibition of the award-winning work at the mudac in Lausanne&lt;br /&gt; &lt;/b&gt;The award-winning work and projects will be exhibited at the mudac (Museum of Design and Contemporary Applied Arts) in Lausanne from 18 October 2011. Stephane Barbier Bouvet from Lausanne has designed the scenography for the exhibition. At the same time, the annual publication will be published, featuring both the award-winning designers and their work. This year’s publication is designed by Jonathan Hares, Lausanne and is published by Birkhäuser. In addition detailed information about the winners (of 2011 from 18 October 2011) is also available online at &lt;u&gt;www.swissdesignawards.ch&lt;/u&gt;.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Media coverage and images&lt;br /&gt; &lt;/b&gt;More detailed information and printable images Grand Prix Design 2011: &lt;u&gt;www.bak.admin.ch/GPD2011.&lt;/u&gt;&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; More detailed information, printable images and a list of all the winners of the Swiss Federal Design Awards 2011: &lt;u&gt;www.bak.admin.ch/SDA2011&lt;/u&gt;.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Press conference&lt;br /&gt; &lt;/strong&gt;Tuesday 18 October 2011, 10 a.m. at the mudac, Lausanne&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Awards ceremony and Vernissage&lt;br /&gt; &lt;/b&gt;Tuesday, 18 October&lt;br /&gt; 6 p.m.: Award ceremony at the Cinéma Capitole, av. Théâtre 6, Lausanne&lt;br /&gt; 7:30 p.m.: Opening of the exhibition at the mudac, Lausanne&lt;br /&gt; From 8 p.m.: Reception (by invitation)&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Anna Niederhäuser, Curator, Design Section, Federal Office of Culture + 41 (0) 79 476 64 74, anna.niederhaeuser@bak.admin.ch Claire Favre Maxwell, Curator, mudac + 41 (0) 021 315 25 30, claire.favre-maxwell@lausanne.ch</contact>
      <revisions>
        <revision date="2011-09-27 10:14" type="R"/>
      </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="18">
        <name lang="de">Kultur</name>
        <name lang="fr">Culture</name>
        <name lang="it">Cultura</name>
        <name lang="en">Culture</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
