<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="41983" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2011-10-31</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="602" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>601</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Generalsekretariat EFD</name>
      <name lang="fr">Secrétariat général DFF</name>
      <name lang="it">Segreteria generale DFF</name>
      <name lang="en">Secretariat-General FDF</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.efd.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.efd.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.efd.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.efd.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="502" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>501</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Generalsekretariat VBS</name>
      <name lang="fr">Secrétariat général du DDPS</name>
      <name lang="it">Segreteria generale del DDPS</name>
      <name lang="en">General Secretariat DDPS</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.vbs.admin.ch/</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.vbs.admin.ch/</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.vbs.admin.ch/</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.vbs.admin.ch/</www>
      <email lang="de">postmaster.vbs@gs-vbs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">postmaster.vbs@gs-vbs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">postmaster.vbs@gs-vbs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">postmaster.vbs@gs-vbs.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="601">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Finanzdepartement</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des finances</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale delle finanze</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Finance</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.efd.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.dff.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.efd.admin.ch/efd/it/home.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.efd.admin.ch/efd/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <department id="501">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Verteidigung, Bevölkerungsschutz und Sport</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de la défense, de la protection de la population et des sports</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale della difesa, della protezione della popolazione e dello sport</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Defence, Civil Protection and Sports DDPS</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.vbs.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.vbs.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.vbs.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.vbs.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@gs-vbs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@gs-vbs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@gs-vbs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@gs-vbs.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Spionageangriffe auf Unternehmen gehören mittlerweile zur Tagesordnung – Dreizehnter MELANI-Halbjahresbericht</title>
      <lead>Im ersten Halbjahr 2011 hat die Melde- und Analysestelle Informationssicherung MELANI weltweit vermehrt Spionageangriffe auf verschiedenste Unternehmen festgestellt. Gestiegen sind ebenfalls die Hackerangriffe, um an sensible Daten zu gelangen. In der Schweiz enorm erhöht hat sich die Anzahl Skimmingfälle. Dies sind einige der Schwerpunkte des aktuellen Halbjahresberichts, der heute veröffentlicht worden ist.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Fast alle kriminellen Machenschaften im Internet haben das primäre Ziel, finanzielle Gewinne zu generieren. Um an die nötigen vertraulichen Daten zu gelangen, wählen die Angreifer oft den direkten Weg mittels Phishing. Sie nutzen damit die Gutgläubigkeit und Hilfsbereitschaft der Opfer aus, indem sie ihnen beispielsweise E-Mails mit gefälschten Absenderadressen zustellen, um die gesuchten Daten zu entlocken. Beispielsweise wurde das Europäische Emissionshandelsregister Opfer von Phishing-Angriffen.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Tägliche Spionageangriffe&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Generell häufen sich die Angriffe zusehends, und es ist davon auszugehen, dass mittlerweile jeden Tag versucht wird, in Firmennetze zu gelangen, um diese auszuspionieren. Im ersten Halbjahr 2011 ereigneten sich einige spektakuläre Spionageangriffe, beispielweise auf die US-Börse Nasdaq, das Französische Finanzministerium oder auf den amerikanischen Rüstungs- und Technologiekonzern Lockheed Martin. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Vermehrte Tätigkeiten der Cyberaktivisten&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Aktivisten aus der ganzen Welt koordinieren sich im Internet unter dem Label «Anonymous», um für ein freies Internet und gegen staatliche Kontrolle zu demonstrieren. &lt;br /&gt;Ihre Angriffsmethode sind Distributed Denial of Service (DDos)-Attacken. Damit werden Websites durch zahllose Anfragen überlastet, bis sie nicht mehr erreichbar sind.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Im Gegensatz zu Anonymous will das Hackerkollektiv Lulzsec mit seinen Aktionen in erster Linie auf Sicherheitslücken und Probleme im Internet aufmerksam machen. Nach erfolgreichen Angriffen veröffentlichte Lulzsec Daten, Ordnerstrukturen und Informationen zu den gehackten Systemen. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Kundendaten im Fokus &lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Um an Datenbanken zu gelangen oder Websites mit Schadcode zu infizieren, werden die entsprechenden Webserver meist mittels gestohlener Zugangsdaten gehackt. Dabei stellen viel besuchte Websites ein beliebtes Angriffsziel dar. Prominentestes BeispieI war vergangenen April der Angriff auf Sony, bei dem 80 Millionen Kundendaten entwendet wurden. Ebenfalls Opfer von Hackerangriffen wurde das amerikanische Sicherheitsunternehmen RSA, bei dem vor allem vertrauliche Informationen im Fokus lagen&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;In der Schweiz ist es Hackern gelungen, einen Tag vor der offiziellen Pressekonferenz auf dem Webserver des Jazz Festivals Montreux an das Programm zu gelangen und dieses zu veröffentlichen.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Sprunghafter Anstieg von Skimmingfällen&lt;/h3&gt;Während Skimming, das Ausspähen von Kreditkartendaten, im Ausland schon seit Langem ein grosses Problem darstellt, verzeichnete MELANI in der Schweiz im ersten Halbjahr 2011 einen sprunghaften Anstieg. Zählte man im ganzen letzten Jahr in der Schweiz 135 manipulierte Geldautomaten, waren es in den ersten vier Monaten diesen Jahres bereits 225. Vermehrt versuchen die Angreifer, nicht nur Bankomaten, sondern auch Zahlungsgeräte in Supermärkten oder an Billettautomaten zu manipulieren. Oft lässt sich die Täterschaft über Nacht einschliessen, um die nötigen Vorrichtungen anzubringen. Laut Polizeiangaben stammen die Täter fast ausschliesslich aus Osteuropa. &lt;p&gt;Der MELANI-Halbjahresbericht 2011/1 ist veröffentlicht unter: www.melani.admin.ch&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Max Klaus, stv. Leiter MELANI Informatikstrategieorgan Bund 031 323 45 07 max.klaus@isb.admin.ch</contact>
      <attachment id="89685">
        <title>Bericht MELANI 2011/1</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>493</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/24679.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <link id="89689">
        <title>Melde- und Analysestelle Informationssicherung MELANI</title>
        <uri>http://www.melani.admin.ch/</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Les entreprises plus que jamais victimes d’opérations de cyberespionnage – treizième rapport semestriel de MELANI</title>
      <lead>La Centrale d’enregistrement et d’analyse pour la sûreté de l’information MELANI a constaté au premier semestre 2011 une recrudescence sur le plan mondial de l’espionnage informatique au dépens de toutes sortes d’entreprises. Les cyberattaques lancées pour accéder à des données sensibles sont également en augmentation. En Suisse, le nombre de cas de skimming est grimpé en flèche. Ces thèmes et d’autres sont au cœur du rapport semestriel publié aujourd’hui.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Dans le monde d’Internet, les comportements criminels poursuivent presque toujours un but d’enrichissement. Bien souvent, les escrocs choisissent de s’adresser directement à leurs victimes par hameçonnage (phishing), afin d’accéder aux données confidentielles requises. Ils font appel à leur bonne foi, à leur crédulité ou à leur serviabilité, en leur envoyant p. ex. un courriel où l’adresse de l’expéditeur a été falsifiée pour leur soutirer les données convoitées. Par exemple, le système européen d’échange de quotas d’émission de gaz à effet de serre a lui aussi été victime d’attaques de phishing.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Banalisation du cyberespionnage&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;De façon générale, les attaques informatiques sont en augmentation et tout indique que désormais, les réseaux d’entreprise subissent des tentatives d’intrusion quotidiennes. Quelques opérations spectaculaires de cyberespionnage ont été révélées au premier semestre 2011, notamment contre la Bourse américaine Nasdaq, contre le Ministère français des finances ou la société américaine d’armement et de technologie militaire Lockheed Martin. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Redoublement d’activité des cyberactivistes&lt;/h3&gt;Des cyberactivistes du monde entier coordonnent sous le label Anonymous leurs protestations en ligne en faveur d’un Internet libre et contre les contrôles étatiques.&lt;br /&gt;Les attaques par déni de service distribué (DDoS) constituent leur mode opératoire préféré. Concrètement, ils inondent des sites Web de requêtes envoyées simultanément, afin de les rendre inaccessibles. &lt;p&gt;A la différence d’Anonymous, le collectif de pirates informatiques Lulzsec cherche avant tout par ses actions à sensibiliser aux failles de sécurité et aux problèmes posés par Internet. A chaque attaque fructueuse, son site a publié ensuite les données dérobées, les structures de classement et d’autres informations sur les systèmes piratés.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Attrait des données des clients&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;La technique utilisée pour parvenir jusqu’aux banques de données, pour défigurer des sites Web ou les infecter au moyen de programmes malveillants consiste à pirater leur serveur d’hébergement, généralement à l’aide de données d’accès volées. Les sites souvent consultés par les internautes constituent une cible de choix. L’incident le plus grave a impliqué, en avril dernier, Sony qui s’est fait dérober les données de 80 millions de clients. La société de sécurité américaine RSA a également été victime d’une attaque ciblée, qui a abouti à une fuite d’informations confidentielles. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;En Suisse, des cyberpirates se sont introduits sur le serveur du Montreux Jazz Festival, se sont emparés de son programme et l’ont publié la veille de la conférence de presse officielle.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Forte hausse des cas de skimming&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Alors que des réseaux de clonage de cartes de crédit (skimming) sévissent à l’étranger depuis longtemps, le nombre de cas enregistrés en Suisse par MELANI n’a explosé qu’au premier semestre 2011. En 2010, seuls 135 distributeurs automatiques de billets avaient été manipulés dans toute la Suisse, contre 225 au cours des quatre premiers mois de 2011.Les escrocs ne s’en prennent plus seulement aux bancomats, mais cherchent toujours plus à manipuler aussi les terminaux de paiement des supermarchés ou les automates à billets CFF. Bien souvent, ils se laissent enfermer la nuit pour mettre en place leurs dispositifs. De source policière, les auteurs des délits de skimming proviennent presque exclusivement d’Europe orientale.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Le rapport semestriel MELANI 2011/1 est publié sous: www.melani.admin.ch&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Max Klaus, directeur suppléant de MELANI Unité de stratégie informatique de la Confédération 031 323 45 07 max.klaus@isb.admin.ch</contact>
      <attachment id="89686">
        <title>Rapport MELANI 2011/1</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>508</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/24680.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <link id="89690">
        <title>Centrale d'enregistrement et d'analyse pour la sûreté de l'information MELANI</title>
        <uri>http://www.melani.admin.ch/index.html?lang=fr</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Attacchi di spionaggio contro imprese sono ormai all’ordine del giorno – tredicesimo rapporto semestrale MELANI</title>
      <lead>Nel primo semestre del 2011 la Centrale d’annuncio e d’analisi per la sicurezza dell’informazione (MELANI) ha registrato a livello mondiale un aumento di attacchi di spionaggio contro diverse imprese e di attacchi di hacker per accedere a dati sensibili. Inoltre, a livello nazionale, i casi di skimming sono aumentati in misura eccessiva. Questi sono alcuni dei punti trattati nell’attuale rapporto semestrale pubblicato in data odierna. </lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Lo scopo principale di quasi tutte le attività criminali in Internet è quello di trarre benefici finanziari. Per appropriarsi dei dati confidenziali necessari, gli aggressori optano spesso per la via diretta, ossia il phishing. Inviando ad esempio e-mail con mittenti falsificati e sfruttando in tal modo la buona fede e la disponibilità delle vittime, gli hacker riescono a carpire i dati ricercati. Per esempio, il registro europeo dello scambio di quote di emissioni è stato vittima di attacchi phishing.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Attacchi di spionaggio all’ordine del giorno&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;In generale gli attacchi sono in aumento. Si può quindi presupporre che nel frattempo i tentativi di accedere a reti aziendali per spiare le loro attività siano all’ordine del giorno. Nel primo semestre del 2011 si sono verificati alcuni attacchi di spionaggio spettacolari, come quelli contro la Borsa americana Nasdaq, contro il Ministero delle finanze francese o contro l’industria statunitense di armamenti e di tecnologia Lockheed Martin. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Attività dei cyberattivisti in continuo aumento&lt;/h3&gt;Attivisti da tutto il mondo si organizzano in Internet sotto il nome «Anonymous». Questo movimento rivendica il diritto di avere un Internet libero e protesta contro il controllo da parte dello Stato. I loro metodi di aggressione sono gli attacchi Distributed-Denial-of-Service (DDoS). Si tratta di sovraccaricare i siti web mediante infinite richieste per renderli inaccessibili. &lt;p&gt;Diversamente da Anonymous, le attività della comunità di hacker Lulzsec sono principalmente finalizzate ad attirare l’attenzione sulle lacune di sicurezza e sui problemi in Internet. Una volta riusciti gli attacchi, Lulzsec pubblica le informazioni, i dati e le strutture delle cartelle dei sistemi piratati. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Dati di clienti in primo piano&lt;/h3&gt;Per accedere a banche dati, violare siti web o infettarli con codici nocivi, le relative applicazioni web vengono spesso piratate con dati di accesso rubati. I siti Internet visitati frequentemente costituiscono un bersaglio prediletto. L’esempio più clamoroso è quello di Sony, che lo scorso aprile è stata obiettivo di attacchi (furto di 80 milioni di dati di clienti). L’impresa americana di sicurezza RSA è stata un’ulteriore vittima di attacchi. &lt;p&gt;In tal occasione gli hacker si sono concentrati soprattutto su informazioni confidenziali, mentre in Svizzera si sono procurati il programma del Jazz Festival di Montreux per pubblicarlo il giorno precedente la conferenza stampa ufficiale.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Aumento improvviso dei casi di skimming&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;All’estero lo skimming (attacchi di spionaggio a dati di carte di credito) rappresenta da tempo un grande problema. Secondo MELANI, nel primo semestre del 2011 tali attacchi sono aumentati improvvisamente anche in Svizzera. Infatti, da 135 bancomat manipolati nel 2010, il numero dei bancomat manipolati è passato già a 225 nel solo primo trimestre di quest’anno.Oltre ai bancomat, gli aggressori tentano anche di manipolare gli apparecchi di pagamento dei supermercati o dei distributori di biglietti. Spesso gli autori si fanno rinchiudere durante la notte per poter applicare i loro congegni. Secondo le indicazioni della polizia, si tratta quasi esclusivamente di persone dell’Europa dell’Est.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Il rapporto semestrale MELANI 2011/1 è pubblicato su: www.melani.admin.ch&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Max Klaus, capo sostituto MELANI Organo strategia informatica della Confederazione tel. 031 323 45 07 max.klaus@isb.admin.ch</contact>
      <attachment id="89687">
        <title>Rapporto MELANI 2011/1</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>491</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/24681.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <link id="89691">
        <title>Centrale d'annuncio e d'analisi per la sicurezza dell'informazione MELANI</title>
        <uri>http://www.melani.admin.ch/index.html?lang=it</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Espionage attacks on companies are now commonplace – Thirteenth MELANI semi-annual report</title>
      <lead>In the first half of 2011, the Reporting and Analysis Centre for Information Assurance (MELANI) detected higher numbers of espionage attacks on the most diverse range of companies worldwide. The number of hacker attacks aimed at accessing sensitive data also increased. There was a massive increase in skimming cases in Switzerland. These are some of the focus areas of the latest semi-annual report, which was published today.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;The primary objective of almost all online criminal activities is to generate financial gains. The attackers frequently choose the direct route by means of phishing in order to access the necessary confidential data. They thereby exploit the victims' good faith and helpfulness by sending them e-mails with false sender addresses, for example, in order to elicit the data they want. For an example, the European Emissions Trading Registry became the victim of phishing attacks.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Daily espionage attacks&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;In general, the attacks are increasing rapidly, and it must be assumed that attempts are now made every day to enter corporate networks in order to spy on them. During the first half of 2011, some spectacular espionage attacks took place on the US NASDAQ stock exchange, France's Ministry of Finance and the US defence and technology company Lockheed Martin, for instance. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Increased activity on the part of cyber activists&lt;/h3&gt;Under the label "Anonymous", activists around the globe coordinate their demonstrations for a free Internet and against government control. Their method of attack consists of distributed denial-of-service attacks (DDoS attacks). These saturate websites with innumerable requests, such that they are rendered unavailable. &lt;p&gt;In contrast to Anonymous, the hacker collective Lulzsec aims to use its actions primarily to draw attention to security vulnerabilities and problems on the Internet. After successful attacks, the hacker collective publishes data, folder structures and information on the hacked systems. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Client data in the spotlight &lt;/h3&gt;In order to access databases, deface websites or infect them with malicious code, the corresponding web servers are usually hacked using stolen access data. In this regard, frequently visited websites are popular targets for attacks. The most prominent example was the attack last April on Sony, whereby the data of 80 million clients was stolen. Another victim of hacker attacks was the US security company RSA, where the primary focus was on confidential information. &lt;p&gt;In Switzerland, hackers managed to access the programme of the Montreux Jazz Festival on the web server, and publish it one day before the official press conference.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Surge in skimming cases&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;While skimming, i.e. spying on credit card data, has been a major problem abroad for a long time, MELANI saw a surge in Switzerland during the first half of 2011. While 135 manipulated cash machines were found in the whole of 2010, 225 were discovered already in the first four months of this year.The attackers are increasingly trying to manipulate not only cash machines, but also payment devices in supermarkets and ticket machines. The perpetrators frequently have themselves locked in overnight in order to mount the necessary devices. According to the police, almost all of the perpetrators are from Eastern Europe.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The MELANI semi-annual report 2011/1 is published at: www.melani.admin.ch.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Max Klaus, Deputy Head of MELANI Federal Strategy Unit for IT 031 323 45 07 max.klaus@isb.admin.ch</contact>
      <attachment id="89688">
        <title>Report MELANI 2011/1</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>398</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/24682.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <link id="89693">
        <title>Reporting and Analysis Centre for Information Assurance MELANI</title>
        <uri>http://www.melani.admin.ch/index.html?lang=en</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <offers>
      <offer id="1" org-id="602">
        <name lang="de">Informatikstrategieorgan Bund ISB (ab 1.1.2012 Informatiksteuerungsorgan: bitte Abo anpassen)</name>
        <name lang="fr">Unité de stratégie informatique de la Confédération (depuis le 1.1.2012 unité de pilotage, veuillez adapter votre abonnement)</name>
        <name lang="it">Organo strategia informatica della Confederazione (OSIC), dal 1° gennaio 2012: Organo direzione informatica della Confederazione (ODIC); adeguare l’abbonamento</name>
        <name lang="en">Federal Strategy Unit for IT (FSUIT) (starting 1.1.2012 it is a Steering Unit, please adapt your subscription)</name>
      </offer>
    </offers>
    <topics>
      <topic id="17">
        <name lang="de">Kriminalität</name>
        <name lang="fr">Criminalité</name>
        <name lang="it">Criminalità</name>
        <name lang="en">Criminality</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="36">
        <name lang="de">Informatik und E-Government</name>
        <name lang="fr">Informatique et cyberadministration</name>
        <name lang="it">Informatica ed e-government</name>
        <name lang="en">IT and E-Government</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="40">
        <name lang="de">Sicherheit</name>
        <name lang="fr">Sécurité</name>
        <name lang="it">Sicurezza</name>
        <name lang="en">Security</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
