<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="42049" revoked="no">
    <version>2</version>
    <pubdate>2011-11-03</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="703" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>701</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Staatssekretariat für Wirtschaft</name>
      <name lang="fr">Secrétariat d'Etat à l'économie</name>
      <name lang="it">Segreteria di Stato dell'economia</name>
      <name lang="en">State Secretariat for Economic Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.seco.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.seco.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.seco.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.seco.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@seco.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@seco.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@seco.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@seco.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="701">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Wirtschaft, Bildung und Forschung</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'économie, de la formation et de la recherche</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'economia, della formazione e della ricerca</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Economic Affairs, Education and Research</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Umfassendes Engagement zur Bekämpfung von Kindersextourismus</title>
      <lead>Ein Jahr nach Lancierung von "Nicht wegsehen - www.stopchildsextourism.ch" ziehen die Kampagnenpartner aus Deutschland, Österreich und der Schweiz an einer Tagung vom 3. und 4. November in Bern Bilanz. Dank der Kampagne nahm das Bewusstsein für die Problematik in der Schweizer Bevölkerung zu. Neu unterstützt das SECO den Tourism Child Protection Code (www.TheCode.org), um Entwicklungsländer im Kampf gegen Kindersextourismus zu stärken.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Die Kampagne "Nicht wegsehen - www.stopchildsextourism.ch" zielt darauf ab, eine breite Öffentlichkeit für die Problematik der sexuellen Ausbeutung von Kindern und Jugendlichen im Tourismus zu sensibilisieren. Auf der Kampagnenwebseite kann ausserdem ein Meldeformular für Verdachtsfälle heruntergeladen werden. Schweizweit wurden im letzten Jahr mittels Schulungen und Standaktionen über 12 000 Personen angesprochen.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Getragen wird die trinationale Kampagne von Behörden und Kinderschutzorganisationen in enger Zusammenarbeit mit der Reisebranche. In der Schweiz sind dies das Staatssekretariat für Wirtschaft SECO sowie ECPAT Switzerland, die Fachstelle gegen Kindersextourismus der Stiftung Kinderschutz Schweiz. Vertreter aus Frankreich, Italien und Luxemburg prüfen derzeit eine Beteiligung an der Kampagne.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Nebst der Sensibilisierungsarbeit hierzulande kommt der Bekämpfung des Kindersextourismus in den Destinationen eine wichtige Rolle zu. Kinder und Jugendliche in Entwickungsländern sind besonders gefährdet, Opfer von Kindersextourismus zu werden. Vor diesem Hintergrund unterstützt das SECO im Rahmen der wirtschaftlichen Entwicklungszusammenarbeit die Stärkung des „Code of Conduct for the protection of children from sexual exploitation in travel and tourism“ (The Tourism Child Protection Code) und dessen Umsetzung mit 1,15 Millionen Dollar (2011-2013).&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Der Child Protection Code ist ein von der Tourismusbranche entwickelter und in Zusammenarbeit mit Nichtregierungsorganisationen implementierter Verhaltenskodex, der Tourismusdienstleistungsanbieter in den Kampf gegen Kindersextourismus einbezieht. Verschiedene Schweizer Reiseanbieter sind Mitglied des Tourism Child Protecion Code.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Staatssekretariat für Wirtschaft SECO Holzikofenweg 36 CH-3003 Bern Tel. +41 58 462 56 56 Fax +41 58 462 56 00</contact>
      <link id="157093">
        <title>Weitere Informationen zum Kampf gegen Kindersextourismus</title>
        <uri>http://www.stopchildsextourism.ch</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="157097">
        <title>The Code</title>
        <uri>http://www.TheCode.org</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Vaste campagne contre le tourisme sexuel impliquant des enfants</title>
      <lead>Un an après le lancement de la campagne «Ne pas détourner le regard – www.stopchildsextourism.ch», les partenaires allemands, autrichiens et suisses à l’origine de cette campagne ont tiré un bilan les 3 et 4 novembre à Berne. Cette campagne a contribué à sensibiliser la population suisse à ce problème. Le Secrétariat d’Etat à l’économie (SECO) soutient le Code de protection de l’enfance (www.TheCode.org), afin de combattre le tourisme sexuel impliquant des enfants dans les pays en développement.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;La campagne «Ne pas détourner le regard – www.stopchildsextourism.ch» a pour objectif de sensibiliser le grand public au problème de l’exploitation sexuelle des enfants et des adolescents dans le tourisme. En outre, un formulaire permettant de signaler les cas suspects peut être téléchargé sur le site de la campagne. L’année dernière, des formations et des actions de sensibilisation ont permis d’informer plus de 12 000 personnes dans toute la Suisse.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;La campagne trinationale est organisée par les autorités et les organisations de protection de l’enfance en étroite collaboration avec la branche du tourisme. En Suisse, elle est menée par le Secrétariat d’Etat à l’économie (SECO) et ECPAT Switzerland, le service spécialisé dans la lutte contre le tourisme sexuel impliquant des enfants de la Fondation suisse pour la protection de l’enfant. Des représentants de la France, de l’Italie et du Luxembourg envisagent de s’y associer.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;A côté du travail de sensibilisation en Suisse, la lutte contre le tourisme sexuel impliquant des enfants sur le lieu de vacances joue un rôle important. Les enfants et les adolescents des pays en développement sont particulièrement menacés par le tourisme sexuel. Dans ce contexte, le SECO soutient, dans le cadre de la coopération économique au développement, le renforcement du «Code de conduite pour la protection des enfants contre l’exploitation sexuelle dans le tourisme et l’industrie des voyages» (Code de protection de l’enfance) et sa mise en œuvre à hauteur de 1,15 million de dollars pour la période 2011-2013.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Le Code de protection de l’enfance est un code de conduite élaboré par la branche du tourisme et appliqué en collaboration avec des organisations non gouvernementales qui associe les prestataires de service du tourisme à la lutte contre le tourisme sexuel impliquant des enfants. De nombreuses agences de voyages suisses ont adhéré au Code de protection de l’enfance.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Secrétariat d'Etat à l'économie SECO Holzikofenweg 36 CH-3003 Berne tél. +41 58 462 56 56 fax +41 58 462 56 00</contact>
      <link id="157094">
        <title>Pour de plus amples informations à la lutte contre le tourisme sexuel impliquant des enfants</title>
        <uri>http://stopchildsextourism.ch/web/fr/</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="157097">
        <title>The Code</title>
        <uri>http://www.TheCode.org</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Impegno globale contro il turismo pedofilo</title>
      <lead>In occasione di un convegno che si è tenuto il 3 e 4 novembre, un anno dopo il lancio della campagna «Non chiudiamo gli occhi - www.stopchildsextourism.ch» i partner provenienti da Germania, Austria e Svizzera hanno stilato un bilanci. Grazie alla campagna di sensibilizzazione riguardo a questa problematica la consapevolezza della popolazione svizzera è cresciuta. Per rafforzare la lotta dei Paesi in via di sviluppo contro il turismo pedofilo attualmente la SECO sostiene il «Tourism Child Protection Code» (www.TheCode.org).</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;La campagna «Non chiudiamo gli occhi - www.stopchildsextourism.ch» mira a sensibilizzare un vasto pubblico sulla problematica dello sfruttamento sessuale di bambini e giovani minorenni nel settore turistico. Dal sito della campagna può essere scaricato un modulo di notifica di casi di sospettato abuso o sfruttamento sessuale. Grazie a formazioni e stand informativi l’anno scorso a livello nazionale sono state coinvolte oltre 12 000 persone.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;La campagna trinazionale è sostenuta dalle autorità e dalle organizzazioni per la tutela dell’infanzia in stretta collaborazione con il settore turistico. In Svizzera si annoverano la Segreteria di Stato dell’economia SECO e la ECPAT Switzerland (il servizio specializzato contro il turismo pedofilo della Fondazione Svizzera per la Protezione dell’Infanzia). Attualmente i rappresentanti di Francia, Italia e Lussemburgo valutano la partecipazione alla campagna.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Nel nostro Paese, accanto all’attività di sensibilizzazione, riveste un ruolo essenziale la lotta contro il turismo pedofilo nelle località turistiche. Il rischio di diventare vittime del turismo pedofilo colpisce soprattutto i bambini e i giovani minorenni nei Paesi in via di sviluppo. In questo contesto la SECO, nel quadro della cooperazione e sviluppo economici, sostiene il rafforzamento del «Code of Conduct for the protection of children from sexual exploitation in travel and tourism» (The Tourism Child Protection Code) e la sua applicazione con 1,15 milioni di dollari (2011-2013).&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Il «Child Protection Code» è un codice di condotta sviluppato dal settore turistico e implementato in collaborazione con organizzazioni non governative e operatori turistici per combattere il turismo pedofilo. Diversi organizzatori di viaggi svizzeri sono membri del «Tourism Child Protection Code».&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Segreteria di Stato dell'economia SECO Holzikofenweg 36 CH-3003 Berna tel. +41 58 462 56 56 fax +41 58 462 56 00</contact>
      <link id="157095">
        <title>Per ulteriori informazioni per combattere il turismo pedofilo</title>
        <uri>http://stopchildsextourism.ch/web/it/</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="157097">
        <title>The Code</title>
        <uri>http://www.TheCode.org</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Broad-based commitment to combating child sex tourism</title>
      <lead>One year after the launch of “Don’t look away – www.stopchildsextourism.ch”, the campaign partners from Germany, Austria and Switzerland are reporting results at their meeting on 3-4 November in Berne. The campaign has helped raise public awareness in Switzerland of this problem. SECO now also supports the Tourism Child Protection Code (www.TheCode.org), an initiative to help prevent child sex tourism in developing countries.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;The campaign “Don’t look away – www.stopchildsextourism.ch” seeks to raise public awareness of the problem of sexual exploitation of children and minors in tourism. An online form for reporting suspected cases is available for download on the campaign’s website. During the past year, various training and promotional events have been used to reach over 12,000 people throughout Switzerland.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The tri-national campaign is funded by public authorities and child-protection agencies in close cooperation with the travel industry. In Switzerland, these are the State Secretariat for Economic Affairs (SECO) and ECPAT Switzerland, a special unit set up within Kinderschutz Schweiz to combat child sex tourism. Representatives from France, Italy and Luxembourg are now also looking into the possibility of joining the initiative.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Apart from raising awareness at home, the campaign also focuses on preventing sexual exploitation of children in tourist destinations. Children and minors in the developing world are at particular risk of becoming victims of child sex tourism. As part of its economic development cooperation, SECO supports the expansion and implementation of the “Code of Conduct for the protection of children from sexual exploitation in travel and tourism” (Tourism Child Protection Code) with a contribution of USD 1.15 million (2011-2013).&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The Tourism Child Protection Code is a code of conduct developed by the tourism sector and implemented in association with various NGOs so as to include travel professionals in the fight against child sex tourism. Several Swiss travel agencies and tour operators have signed up to the Tourism Child Protection Code.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>State Secretariat for Economic Affairs SECO Holzikofenweg 36 CH-3003 Bern Tel. +41 58 462 56 56 Fax +41 58 462 56 00</contact>
      <link id="157096">
        <title>Further information in the fight against child sex tourism</title>
        <uri>http://stopchildsextourism.ch/web/en/</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="157097">
        <title>The Code</title>
        <uri>http://www.TheCode.org</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="47">
        <name lang="de">Wirtschaft</name>
        <name lang="fr">Économie</name>
        <name lang="it">Economia</name>
        <name lang="en">Economic Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
