<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="90806" revoked="no">
    <version>3</version>
    <pubdate>2022-10-20</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="201" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>201</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="201">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Nicolas Bideau wird interimistischer Chef von Kommunikation EDA</title>
      <lead>Aus familiären Gründen tritt der bisherige Kommunikationschef des EDA, Peter Düggeli, Ende 2022 von seiner Funktion zurück. Übergangsweise wird ab 14. November 2022 Nicolas Bideau, Chef von Präsenz Schweiz, die Leitung von Kommunikation EDA übernehmen. Auf diese Weise sind ein nahtloser Übergang und die Kontinuität der Kommunikation sichergestellt. Dies ist angesichts der Themenlage (Krieg gegen die Ukraine, Präsidialjahr, Europapolitik, Einsitz im UNO-Sicherheitsrat) wichtig. </lead>
      <text link="no">Wegen des Todes seiner Ehefrau hat sich Peter Düggeli entschieden, sein Amt als Kommunikationschef des EDA auf Ende 2022 zu beenden. Bundespräsident Ignazio Cassis dankt Peter Düggeli herzlich für seine Arbeit für das EDA.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Bereits am 14. November 2022 wird Nicolas Bideau interimistisch die Leitung von Kommunikation EDA übernehmen. Der derzeitige Chef von Präsenz Schweiz (PRS) war unter anderem eng in die Vorbereitung des Präsidialjahrs eingebunden und ist mit den Themen des EDA wie auch mit der Medienszene in der Schweiz gut vertraut. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Bis Nicolas Bideau wieder in seine angestammte Funktion als Chef von Präsenz Schweiz zurückkehrt, leitet der bisherige Chef der Abteilung Marketing und Kampagnen und Mitglied der PRS-Geschäftsleitung, Alexandre Edelmann, ab 14. November 2022 Präsenz Schweiz ad interim.</text>
      <contact>Kommunikation EDA Bundeshaus West CH-3003 Bern Tel. Kommunikationsservice: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Medienstelle: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Nicolas Bideau devient Chef Communication du DFAE ad intérim</title>
      <lead>Pour des raisons familiales, l’actuel chef de la communication du DFAE Peter Düggeli se retirera de ses fonctions fin 2022. À partir du 14 novembre 2022, Nicolas Bideau, actuel chef de Présence Suisse, assumera la fonction de Chef Communication ad intérim au sein du DFAE. Cet intérim permettra d’assurer une continuité des activités de communication, importante au vu des dossiers qui occupent l’actualité (guerre en Ukraine, année présidentielle, politique européenne, siège de la Suisse au Conseil de sécurité de l’ONU). </lead>
      <text link="no">En raison du décès de son épouse, Peter Düggeli a décidé de quitter ses fonctions de Chef communication du DFAE fin 2022. Le président de la Confédération Ignazio Cassis le remercie du travail qu’il a accompli pour le département.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Nicolas Bideau deviendra Chef communication du DFAE par intérim à partir du 14 novembre 2022. L’actuel chef de Présence Suisse (PRS) a été notamment étroitement impliqué dans la phase préparatoire de l’année présidentielle. Les dossiers du DFAE et le paysage médiatique suisse lui sont par ailleurs familiers. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;En attendant que Nicolas Bideau reprenne ses fonctions à la tête de Présence Suisse, Alexandre Edelmann, actuellement Chef de la division Marketing et campagnes et membre de la direction de PRS, en assurera la direction par intérim à compter du 14 novembre 2022.</text>
      <contact>Communication DFAE Palais fédéral ouest CH-3003 Berne Tél. Service de communication: +41 58 462 31 53 Tél. Service de presse: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <revisions>
        <revision date="2022-10-20 19:28" type="R"/>
        <revision date="2022-10-20 19:58" type="R"/>
      </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Nicolas Bideau assume la funzione di capo ad interim di Comunicazione DFAE</title>
      <lead>Per motivi familiari, l’attuale capo di Comunicazione DFAE Peter Düggeli lascerà il suo incarico alla fine del 2022. A partire dal 14 novembre sarà Nicolas Bideau, capo di Presenza Svizzera, a guidare ad interim Comunicazione DFAE. Sarà garantito in questo modo un passaggio di consegne senza interruzioni nel segno della continuità della comunicazione, un aspetto cruciale viste le importanti questioni in ballo (guerra contro l’Ucraina, anno presidenziale, politica europea, seggio della Svizzera nel Consiglio di sicurezza dell’ONU). </lead>
      <text link="no">In seguito al decesso della moglie, Peter Düggeli ha deciso di lasciare il suo incarico di capo di Comunicazione DFAE alla fine del 2022. Il presidente della Confederazione Ignazio Cassis lo ringrazia calorosamente per il lavoro svolto al Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri (DFAE).&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Nicolas Bideau assumerà l’incarico di responsabile ad interim di Comunicazione DFAE già il 14 novembre 2022. L’attuale capo di Presenza Svizzera è stato fortemente coinvolto nella preparazione dell’anno presidenziale e conosce bene i temi del DFAE così come il mondo dei media in Svizzera. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;In attesa che Nicolas Bideau ritorni alla sua carica di capo di Presenza Svizzera, dal 14 novembre 2022 ne assumerà la guida ad interim Alexandre Edelmann, attuale Capo Marketing e Campagne e membro della direzione di Presenza Svizzera.</text>
      <contact>Comunicazione DFAE Palazzo federale ovest CH-3003 Berna Tel. Servizio di comunicazione: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Servizio stampa: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Nicolas Bideau to head FDFA Communication on interim basis</title>
      <lead>The current head of FDFA Communication, Peter Düggeli, will be leaving his role at the end of 2022 for family reasons. Head of Presence Switzerland Nicolas Bideau will head FDFA Communication on an interim basis from 14 November 2022, ensuring a seamless transition and providing continuity in the department's communication. This will be essential in addressing matters such as the war in Ukraine, the presidential year, European policy, and Switzerland's seat on the UN Security Council. </lead>
      <text link="no">Head of FDFA Communication Peter Düggeli has decided to step down at the end of 2022 following the death of his wife. President of the Confederation Ignazio Cassis would like to extend his warmest thanks to Mr Düggeli for his work at the FDFA. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Nicolas Bideau will take over as interim head of FDFA Communication from 14 November 2022. Currently head of Presence Switzerland (PRS), Mr Bideau was closely involved in preparations for the presidential year and is well acquainted with FDFA topics and the Swiss media scene. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Alexandre Edelmann, current head of marketing and campaigns and member of the executive committee at PRS, will head Presence Switzerland on an interim basis from 14 November 2022 until Nicolas Bideau returns to the role.</text>
      <contact>FDFA Communication Federal Palace West Wing CH-3003 Bern, Switzerland Tel. Communication service: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Press service: +41 58 460 55 55 E-mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @SwissMFA</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
