<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="87171" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2022-02-14</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="324" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>301</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Swissmedic, Schweizerisches Heilmittelinstitut</name>
      <name lang="fr">Swissmedic, Institut suisse des produits thérapeutiques</name>
      <name lang="it">Swissmedic, Istituto svizzero per gli agenti terapeutici</name>
      <name lang="en">Swiss Agency for Therapeutic Products</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.swissmedic.ch/</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.swissmedic.ch/?lang=3</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.swissmedic.ch/?lang=4</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.swissmedic.ch/?lang=2</www>
      <email lang="de"/>
      <email lang="fr"/>
      <email lang="it"/>
      <email lang="en"/>
    </originator>
    <department id="301">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement des Innern</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'intérieur</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'interno</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Home Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Zulassungsgesuch für den Covid-19-Impfstoff von Novavax eingereicht</title>
      <lead>Future Health Pharma GmbH hat bei Swissmedic ein Zulassungsgesuch für den Impfstoffkandidaten Nuvaxovid von Novavax eingereicht. Er handelt sich um den ersten Proteinimpfstoff, für den in der Schweiz eine Zulassung beantragt wird.</lead>
      <text link="no">Novavax, der Hersteller des Impfstoffes, hat in der Schweiz keine Niederlassung und verfügt deshalb über keine Betriebsbewilligung. Das Pharmaunternehmen hat daher entschieden, bei Swissmedic das Zulassungsgesuch durch Future Health einreichen zu lassen. Diese wird nach der Zulassung des Präparats als Zulassungsinhaberin auftreten. &lt;p&gt;Future Health reichte das Gesuch nach der Zulassung des Impfstoffs durch die Europäische Arzneimittelbehörde EMA ein. Das Gesuch wurde im Verfahren nach Art. 13 des Heilmittelgesetzes eingereicht. Dies erlaubt es der Swissmedic, die Begutachtung dieser Behörde zu berücksichtigen.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Die eingereichte Dokumentation muss mit derjenigen der Referenzbehörde identisch sein, welche die Zulassung des Arzneimittels genehmigt hat. Zusätzlich sind die Begutachtungsberichte der Referenzbehörde einzureichen. Die Berücksichtigung der Ergebnisse ausländischer Zulassungsverfahren soll dazu beitragen, im Ausland bereits zugelassene Arzneimittel den Patientinnen und Patienten in der Schweiz möglichst rasch zur Verfügung zu stellen.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Nuvaxovid ist ein Proteinimpfstoff, der das Spike-Protein des Coronavirus enthält. Der Körper erkennt, dass es sich um einen Fremdstoff handelt. In der Folge bildet das Immunsystem Antikörper und ist damit bei einer allfälligen Ansteckung besser gewappnet. Der Impfstoff kann bis zu sechs Monaten in herkömmlichen Kühlschränken gelagert werden, was vor allem aus logistischer Sicht vorteilhaft ist.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Bisher hat Swissmedic in der Schweiz die Impfstoffe von Pfizer/BioNTech (Comirnaty), Moderna (Spikevax) und Johnson &amp; Johnson (COVID-19 Vaccine Janssen) zugelassen. &lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Swissmedic Medienstelle +41 58 462 02 76 media@swissmedic.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Transmission à Swissmedic d’une demande d’autorisation de mise sur le marché pour le vaccin contre le Covid-19 de Novavax</title>
      <lead>L’entreprise Future Health Pharma GmbH a déposé auprès de Swissmedic une demande d’autorisation pour le candidat-vaccin Nuvaxovid de Novavax. Il s’agit du premier vaccin à base de protéines pour lequel une autorisation de mise sur le marché est sollicitée en Suisse.</lead>
      <text link="no">Novavax, le fabricant de ce vaccin, n’a aucun établissement en Suisse et n’est donc titulaire d’aucune autorisation d'exploitation. Telle est la raison pour laquelle cette entreprise pharmaceutique a décidé de confier le dépôt de la demande d’autorisation pour ce vaccin à Future Health. Cette dernière sera donc le titulaire de l’autorisation lorsque le vaccin Nuvaxovid aura été autorisé. &lt;p&gt;Future Health a soumis ladite demande d’autorisation à Swissmedic après l’approbation de ce vaccin par l’EMA, l’Agence européenne du médicament. Elle s’est appuyé dans le cadre de la demande suisse sur la procédure visée à l'art. 13 de la loi sur les produits thérapeutiques (LPTh). Cette procédure permet à Swissmedic de prendre en considération l’expertise réalisée par cette autorité.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;La documentation présentée à Swissmedic doit être identique à celle qui a été remise à l’autorité de référence ayant approuvé l’autorisation du médicament, et les rapports d’expertise de l’autorité de référence doivent également être fournis. Le fait de prendre en considération les résultats de procédures d’autorisation menées à l’étranger vise à mettre le plus rapidement possible à la disposition des patients en Suisse des médicaments déjà autorisés à l’étranger.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Nuvaxovid est un vaccin à base de protéines renfermant la protéine « spicule » du coronavirus. L’organisme humain identifie cette protéine comme un élément étranger, le système immunitaire produit alors des anticorps, et il est ainsi mieux armé en cas de contamination éventuelle. Ce vaccin se conserve jusqu’à six mois dans un réfrigérateur classique, ce qui constitue surtout un avantage sur le plan logistique.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Les vaccins contre le Covid-19 que Swissmedic a autorisés jusqu’à présent en Suisse sont ceux de Pfizer/BioNTech (Comirnaty), de Moderna (Spikevax) et de Johnson &amp; Johnson (COVID-19 Vaccine Janssen).&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Swissmedic Relations médias +41 58 462 02 76 media@swissmedic.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Presentata la domanda di omologazione per il vaccino anti-COVID-19 di Novavax</title>
      <lead>Future Health Pharma GmbH ha presentato a Swissmedic la domanda di omologazione per il vaccino candidato Nuvaxovid di Novavax. Si tratta del primo vaccino basato sulle proteine per cui viene richiesta un’omologazione in Svizzera.</lead>
      <text link="no"> Novavax, in quanto fabbricante del vaccino, non ha una filiale in Svizzera e pertanto non dispone di un’autorizzazione d’esercizio. L’azienda farmaceutica ha quindi deciso di far pervenire la domanda di omologazione a Swissmedic tramite Future Health. Dopo che il preparato sarà stato omologato, questa azienda comparirà come titolare dell’omologazione. &lt;p&gt;Future Health ha inoltrato la domanda di omologazione del vaccino tramite l’Agenzia europea per i medicinali (EMA). La domanda è stata presentata nell’ambito della procedura ai sensi dell’art. 13 della legge sugli agenti terapeutici. Questo consente a Swissmedic di tenere conto della valutazione dell’EMA.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;La documentazione presentata deve essere identica a quella dell’autorità di riferimento che ha approvato l’omologazione del medicamento. Inoltre, devono essere inoltrati i rapporti d’esame dell’autorità di riferimento. Tenere conto dei risultati delle procedure di omologazione estere deve contribuire a mettere a disposizione dei pazienti svizzeri i medicamenti già omologati all’estero il più rapidamente possibile.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Nuvaxovid è un vaccino basato sulle proteine che contiene la proteina spike del coronavirus. Il corpo riconosce che si tratta di una sostanza estranea. Di conseguenza, il sistema immunitario produce anticorpi ed è meglio preparato a combattere una eventuale infezione. Il vaccino può essere conservato fino a sei mesi in frigoriferi convenzionali, il che è particolarmente vantaggioso dal punto di vista logistico.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Finora Swissmedic ha omologato i vaccini di Pfizer/BioNTech (Comirnaty), Moderna (Spikevax) e Johnson &amp; Johnson (COVID-19 Vaccine Janssen) in Svizzera.&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Swissmedic Ufficio stampa +41 58 462 02 76 media@swissmedic.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Authorisation application submitted for the COVID-19 vaccine from Novavax</title>
      <lead>Future Health Pharma GmbH has submitted an authorisation application to Swissmedic for vaccine candidate Nuvaxovid from Novavax. This is the first protein-based vaccine for which an authorisation application has been submitted in Switzerland.</lead>
      <text link="no"> Vaccine manufacturer Novavax does not have a place of business in Switzerland and therefore does not have an establishment licence. The pharmaceutical company has therefore decided to be represented in Switzerland for the authorisation application to Swissmedic by Future Health, which will act as the marketing authorisation holder after authorisation of the product. &lt;p&gt;Future Health submitted the authorisation application following authorisation of the vaccine by the European Medicines Agency (EMA). The application was submitted under the procedure according to Art. 13 of the Therapeutic Products Act (TPA). This enables Swissmedic to take the review by this authority into consideration.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The documentation submitted to Swissmedic must be identical to that on which the reference authority based its authorisation of the medicinal product. The assessment reports of the reference authority must also be submitted. The consideration of the results of foreign authorisation procedures is intended to help ensure that medicines that are already authorised abroad can be made available to patients in Switzerland as quickly as possible.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Nuvaxovid is a protein-based vaccine that contains the coronavirus spike protein. The human body recognises that this is a foreign substance. In response, the immune system produces antibodies and is therefore better equipped to tackle a possible infection. The vaccine can be stored for up to six months in conventional refrigerators, which is beneficial from a logistics perspective in particular.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;To date, Swissmedic has approved the Pfizer/BioNTech (Comirnaty), Moderna (Spikevax) and Johnson &amp; Johnson (COVID-19 Vaccine Janssen) vaccines in Switzerland.&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Swissmedic Media Unit +41 58 462 02 76 media@swissmedic.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="15">
        <name lang="de">Gesundheit</name>
        <name lang="fr">Santé</name>
        <name lang="it">sanità</name>
        <name lang="en">Health</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
