<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="86993" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2022-02-01</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="703" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>701</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Staatssekretariat für Wirtschaft</name>
      <name lang="fr">Secrétariat d'Etat à l'économie</name>
      <name lang="it">Segreteria di Stato dell'economia</name>
      <name lang="en">State Secretariat for Economic Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.seco.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.seco.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.seco.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.seco.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@seco.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@seco.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@seco.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@seco.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="701">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Wirtschaft, Bildung und Forschung</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'économie, de la formation et de la recherche</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'economia, della formazione e della ricerca</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Economic Affairs, Education and Research</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Steigende Preise drücken auf die Konsumentenstimmung</title>
      <lead>Die Konsumentenstimmung hat sich gemäss der Januar-Umfrage leicht eingetrübt. Zum einen werden die Aussichten für die allgemeine Wirtschaft weniger positiv beurteilt. Zum anderen lasten die steigenden Preise zusehends auf der Kaufneigung.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Der Index der Konsumentenstimmung (−4 Punkte) ist im Januar 2022 nach zwei sehr positiven Quartalen wieder in den Bereich des langjährigen Mittelwerts (−5 Punkte) zurückgekehrt.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Die Schweizer Haushalte blicken deutlich weniger optimistisch auf die wirtschaftliche Entwicklung in den kommenden zwölf Monaten. Mit 21 Punkten liegt der entsprechende Teilindex aber immer noch klar über dem langjährigen Mittel (−9 Punkte); die Befragten gehen somit weiterhin von einer Fortsetzung der Konjunkturerholung aus. Damit einhergehend wird auch die Lage am Arbeitsmarkt als günstig wahrgenommen: Der Teilindex zur Sicherheit der Arbeitsplätze verbessert sich noch einmal merklich und kommt mit −59 Punkten erstmals seit Beginn der Pandemie wieder im Bereich des langjährigen Mittels zu liegen. Auch wird erwartet, dass sich die Arbeitslosenzahlen in den kommenden zwölf Monaten weiterhin günstig entwickeln werden.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Trotz der insgesamt positiven Aussichten erwarten die Konsumentinnen und Konsumenten eine leicht unterdurchschnittliche Entwicklung der finanziellen Lage für die kommenden zwölf Monate (−3 Punkte). Auch die vergangene finanzielle Lage wird unterdurchschnittlich beurteilt: Der entsprechende Teilindex notiert bei −10 Punkten. Zu dieser Einschätzung dürften insbesondere die gestiegenen Konsumentenpreise beigetragen haben, welche die Kaufkraft der Schweizer Haushalte schmälern. Die vergangene Preisentwicklung (83 Punkte) wird im Vergleich zum Oktober 2021 (70 Punkte) noch einmal höher eingeschätzt. Auch für die kommenden zwölf Monate rechnen die Befragten mit steigenden Konsumentenpreisen. Der entsprechende Teilindex liegt mit 93 Punkten nun deutlich über dem langjährigen Mittelwert (67 Punkte).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Die Preisentwicklung dürfte auch zur Zurückhaltung der Konsumentinnen und Konsumenten bei grösseren Anschaffungen beitragen. Mit −23 Punkten verharrt der Teilindex weiterhin merklich unter dem Vorkrisenniveau und dem langjährigen Mittel von −7 Punkten.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Ronald Indergand, SECO, Leiter Ressort Konjunktur, Direktion für Wirtschaftspolitik, Tel.: +41 58 460 55 58 Simon Widmer, SECO, Wissenschaftlicher Mitarbeiter, Direktion für Wirtschaftspolitik, Tel.: +41 58 465 63 59 Fabian Maienfisch, Stv. Leiter Kommunikation und Mediensprecher SECO, Tel. +41 58 462 40 20</contact>
      <attachment id="226746">
        <title>Medienmitteilung und Grafiken</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>362</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/70057.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>La hausse des prix pèse sur le climat de consommation</title>
      <lead>L’enquête réalisée en janvier indique une légère détérioration du climat de consommation. Les perspectives de l’économie générale sont jugées moins favorables et la hausse des prix freine de plus en plus la propension à faire des achats.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Après deux trimestres largement positifs, l’indice du climat de consommation (−4 points) retrouve quasiment sa moyenne pluriannuelle (−5 points) en janvier 2022.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Les ménages suisses sont nettement moins optimistes quant à l’évolution de l’économie pour les douze prochains mois. Le sous-indice correspondant, qui s’établit à 21 points, reste toutefois largement supérieur à la moyenne pluriannuelle (−9 points) ; les personnes interrogées continuent donc de tabler sur une poursuite de la reprise conjoncturelle. La situation sur le marché du travail est, par conséquent, également jugée favorable : le sous-indice sur la sécurité de l’emploi s’améliore de nouveau de manière notable et retrouve le niveau de la moyenne pluriannuelle pour la première fois depuis le début de la pandémie en s’établissant à −59 points. Les ménages pensent également que les chiffres du chômage vont continuer d’évoluer favorablement au cours des douze prochains mois.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Malgré les perspectives globalement positives, les consommateurs s’attendent à ce que l’évolution de leur situation financière soit légèrement inférieure à la moyenne durant les douze prochains mois (−3 points). Même analyse pour la situation financière passée : le sous-indice correspondant se situe à −10 points. La hausse des prix à la consommation, qui rabote le pouvoir d’achat des ménages suisses, semble notamment avoir contribué à cette perception. L’évolution passée des prix (83 points) est perçue comme ayant été plus marquée qu’au mois d’octobre 2021 (70 points). Les personnes interrogées tablent également sur une hausse des prix à la consommation pour les douze prochains mois. Le sous-indice correspondant, qui s’établit à 93 points, est désormais nettement supérieur à la moyenne pluriannuelle (67 points).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;La hausse des prix pourrait expliquer en partie la faible propension des consommateurs à effectuer des achats importants. Le sous-indice correspondant (−23 points) reste bien en deçà du niveau d’avant la crise et de la moyenne pluriannuelle (−7 points).&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Ronald Indergand, SECO, chef du secteur Conjoncture, Direction de la politique économique, +41 58 460 55 58 Simon Widmer, SECO, collaborateur scientifique, Direction de la politique économique, +41 58 465 63 59 Fabian Maienfisch, Chef suppléant de la Communication et porte-parole SECO, tél. +41 58 462 40 20</contact>
      <attachment id="226747">
        <title>Communiqué de presse et graphiques</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>349</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/70058.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>L’aumento dei prezzi si ripercuote sulla fiducia dei consumatori</title>
      <lead>Secondo il sondaggio di gennaio, la fiducia dei consumatori si è leggermente indebolita: da un lato le prospettive generali dell’economia sono valutate in modo meno positive e dall’altra l’aumento dei prezzi pesa sempre di più sulla propensione all’acquisto.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Dopo due trimestri molto positivi l’indice della fiducia dei consumatori a gennaio 2022 (−4 punti) ritorna nella media a lungo termine (−5 punti).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I nuclei familiari svizzeri sono molto meno ottimisti sullo sviluppo economico dei prossimi dodici mesi, anche se con 21 punti il relativo indice parziale rimane nettamente al di sopra della media a lungo termine (−9 punti): gli interpellati si attendono che l’attuale ripresa economica prosegua il suo corso. Anche la situazione del mercato del lavoro viene percepita come favorevole: l’indice parziale sulla sicurezza degli impieghi continua anch’esso a migliorare in maniera marcata e, con −59 punti, rientra per la prima volta dall’inizio della pandemia nella media a lungo termine. Allo stesso modo, anche i dati sulla disoccupazione dovrebbero registrare un andamento favorevole nei prossimi dodici mesi.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Nonostante le prospettive siano nel complesso positive, per quanto riguarda la situazione finanziaria dei prossimi dodici mesi i consumatori si aspettano uno sviluppo leggermente inferiore alla media (−3 punti), stessa valutazione che riservano d’altronde alla situazione finanziaria dei mesi precedenti (−10 punti). Questa valutazione è probabilmente dovuta in particolare all’aumento dei prezzi al consumo, che riduce il potere d’acquisto delle famiglie svizzere. L’indice sull’evoluzione dei prezzi nei mesi passati (83 punti) risulta ancora più alto rispetto a ottobre 2021 (70 punti) e gli interpellati si aspettano un ulteriore aumento dei prezzi al consumo nei prossimi dodici mesi. Con un valore di 93 punti, il relativo indice parziale è ora chiaramente al di sopra della media a lungo termine (67 punti).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;L’aumento dei prezzi potrebbe anche rendere i consumatori meno propensi a fare acquisti importanti. Il relativo indice parziale si situa a −23 punti rimanendo notevolmente al di sotto sia del livello pre-crisi sia della media a lungo termine di −7 punti.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Ronald Indergand, SECO, capo del settore Congiuntura, Direzione politica economica, +41 58 460 55 58 Simon Widmer, SECO, collaboratore scientifico, Direzione politica economica, +41 58 465 63 59 Fabian Maienfisch, Vice caposettore Comunicazione e portavoce SECO, tel. +41 58 462 40 20</contact>
      <attachment id="226748">
        <title>Comunicato stampa e grafici</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>343</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/70059.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Rising prices dampen consumer sentiment</title>
      <lead>Consumer sentiment has weakened according to the January survey. On the one hand, the outlook for the general economy is assessed less positively. On the other hand, rising prices are increasingly weighing on the propensity to buy.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;After two very positive quarters, the consumer sentiment index (−4 points) in January 2022 has fallen back to the range of the long-term average (−5 points).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Swiss households are significantly less optimistic about economic prospects over the next 12 months. At 21 points, however, the corresponding sub-index value is still clearly above the long-term average (−9 points), so respondents continue to expect the economic recovery to continue. Furthermore, the situation on the labour market is also perceived as favourable: the sub-index on job security has once again noticeably improved and, at −59 points, is back in the range of the long-term average for the first time since the beginning of the pandemic. Unemployment figures are also expected to continue to develop favourably over the next 12 months. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Despite the generally positive outlook, consumers expect a slightly below-average development of the financial situation over the coming 12 months (−3 points). The past financial situation is also assessed as below average: the corresponding sub-index value stands at −10 points. This assessment is probably due in particular to higher consumer prices, which are reducing the purchasing power of Swiss households. The past price trend (83 points) is estimated to be even higher than in October 2021 (70 points). Respondents also expect consumer prices to rise over the next 12 months. At 93 points, the corresponding sub-index value is now significantly above the long-term average (67 points).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Price developments are also likely to contribute to consumers' reluctance to make major purchases. At −23 points, the sub-index value remains noticeably below the pre-crisis level and the long-term average of −7 points.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Ronald Indergand, SECO, Head, Short Term Economic Analyses Division, Economic Policy Directorate, Tel.: +41 58 460 55 58 Simon Widmer, SECO, Economist, Short Term Economic Analyses Division, Economic Policy Directorate, Tel.: +41 58 465 63 59 Fabian Maienfisch, Deputy Head of Communications and Media Spokesperson SECO, tel. +41 58 462 40 20</contact>
      <attachment id="226749">
        <title>Press release and graphs</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>361</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/70060.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <offers>
      <offer id="156" org-id="703">
        <name lang="de">BIP-Quartalsdaten und Konjunkturtendenzen</name>
        <name lang="fr">Données trimestrielles PIB et tendances conjoncturelles</name>
        <name lang="it">Tendenze congiunturali</name>
        <name lang="en">Quarterly data on GDP and economic trends</name>
      </offer>
    </offers>
    <topics>
      <topic id="2">
        <name lang="de">Arbeit</name>
        <name lang="fr">Travail</name>
        <name lang="it">Lavoro</name>
        <name lang="en">Labour</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="37">
        <name lang="de">Konsum</name>
        <name lang="fr">Consommation</name>
        <name lang="it">Consumo</name>
        <name lang="en">Consumer Affairs</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="43">
        <name lang="de">Statistik</name>
        <name lang="fr">Statistiques</name>
        <name lang="it">Statistica</name>
        <name lang="en">Statistics</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="47">
        <name lang="de">Wirtschaft</name>
        <name lang="fr">Économie</name>
        <name lang="it">Economia</name>
        <name lang="en">Economic Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
