<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="87187" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2022-02-17</pubdate>
    <blocking-period>2022-02-17</blocking-period>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="318" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>301</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Bundesamt für Statistik</name>
      <name lang="fr">Office fédéral de la statistique</name>
      <name lang="it">Ufficio federale di statistica</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Statistical Office</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.statistik.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.statistique.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.statistica.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.statistics.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@bfs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@bfs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@bfs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@bfs.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="301">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement des Innern</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'intérieur</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'interno</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Home Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Neuchâtel</city>
      <title>Lebensbedingungen in der Schweiz unter den besten in Europa</title>
      <lead>Im europäischen Vergleich sind der allgemeine Lebensstandard und die Lebenszufriedenheit in der Schweiz weiterhin sehr hoch. Dennoch waren 8,5% der Bevölkerung oder rund 720 000 Personen im Jahr 2020 von Einkommensarmut betroffen. Dies sind einige Ergebnisse der Erhebung 2020 über die Einkommen und Lebensbedingungen (SILC) des Bundesamtes für Statistik (BFS). Die Resultate bilden die Situation vor und zu Beginn der Covid-19-Pandemie ab.</lead>
      <text link="no">Diese Medienmitteilung und weitere Informationen zum Thema finden Sie auf der Website des BFS (siehe Link unten)</text>
      <contact>Martina Guggisberg, BFS, Sektion Einkommen, Konsum und Lebensbedingungen, Tel.: +41 58 463 62 38, E-Mail: Martina.Guggisberg@bfs.admin.ch Friederike Eberlein, BFS, Sektion Einkommen, Konsum und Lebensbedingungen, Tel.: +41 58 463 61 24, E-Mail: Friederike.Eberlein@bfs.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="227333">
        <title>Kompletter Text und Mediendossier</title>
        <uri>https://www.bfs.admin.ch/news/de/2022-0373</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Neuchâtel</city>
      <title>Les conditions de vie en Suisse parmi les plus favorables d’Europe</title>
      <lead>Le niveau de vie général et la satisfaction dans la vie en Suisse restent très élevés par rapport aux autres pays européens. Toutefois, 8,5% de la population suisse, soit environ 720 000 personnes, étaient touchées par la pauvreté en termes de revenu en 2020. Ce sont là quelques-uns des résultats de l’enquête 2020 sur les revenus et les conditions de vie (SILC) de l’Office fédéral de la statistique (OFS). Ces résultats décrivent la situation telle qu’elle se présentait avant et au début de la pandémie de COVID-19.</lead>
      <text link="no">Vous trouverez ce communiqué de presse et d'autres informations sur ce thème sur le site web de l'OFS (voir le lien ci-dessous)</text>
      <contact>Martina Guggisberg, OFS, Section Revenus, consommation &amp; conditions de vie, tél.: +41 58 463 62 38, e-mail: Martina.Guggisberg@bfs.admin.ch Stéphane Fleury, OFS, Section Revenus, consommation &amp; conditions de vie, tél.: +41 58 463 64 48, e-mail: Stephane.Fleury@bfs.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="227334">
        <title>Texte intégral et dossier de presse</title>
        <uri>https://www.bfs.admin.ch/news/fr/2022-0373</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Neuchâtel</city>
      <title>Condizioni di vita in Svizzera tra le più favorevoli d’Europa</title>
      <lead>Rispetto al resto dell’Europa, il tenore di vita generale e la soddisfazione per la propria vita in Svizzera si mantengono a livelli molto alti. Pur tuttavia, nel 2020 l’8,5% della popolazione, ossia circa 720 000 persone, era colpito da povertà reddituale. Sono alcuni risultati che emergono dall’indagine 2020 sui redditi e sulle condizioni di vita (SILC) dell’Ufficio federale di statistica (UST). I risultati raffigurano la situazione del periodo prima e iniziale della pandemia di COVID-19.</lead>
      <text link="no">Il presente comunicato stampa e ulteriori informazioni sul tema sono reperibili sulla pagina Internet dell'UST (link sotto)</text>
      <contact>Martina Guggisberg, UST, Sezione Reddito, consumo e condizioni di vita, tel.: +41 58 463 62 38, e-mail: Martina.Guggisberg@bfs.admin.ch Sybille Caira, UST, Sezione Reddito, consumo e condizioni di vita, tel.: +41 58 467 24 45, e-mail: Sybille.Caira@bfs.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="227335">
        <title>Testo integrale e dossier per i media</title>
        <uri>https://www.bfs.admin.ch/news/it/2022-0373</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Neuchâtel</city>
      <title>Living conditions in Switzerland among the best in Europe</title>
      <lead>In European comparison, the overall standard of living and satisfaction with life in Switzerland remain at a high level. Nevertheless, 8.5% of the population or some 720 000 people were affected by income poverty in 2020. These are some of the findings from the 2020 Survey on Income and Living Conditions (SILC) conducted by the Federal Statistical Office (FSO). The results describe the situation before and at the start of the COVID-19 pandemic.</lead>
      <text link="no">This press release and further information on this topic can be found on the FSO website (see link below)</text>
      <contact>Martina Guggisberg, FSO, Income, Consumption and Living Conditions section, tel.: +41 58 463 62 38, email: Martina.Guggisberg@bfs.admin.ch Friederike Eberlein, FSO, Income, Consumption and Living Conditions section, tel.: +41 58 463 61 24, email: Friederike.Eberlein@bfs.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="227336">
        <title>Please note that the English version only includes the release's lead</title>
        <uri>https://www.bfs.admin.ch/news/en/2022-0373</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <keywords>
      <keyword id="317.21" org-id="318">
        <name lang="de">Wirtschaftliche und soziale Situation der Bevölkerung</name>
        <name lang="fr">Situation économique et sociale de la population</name>
        <name lang="it">Reddito e qualità di vita della popolazione</name>
        <name lang="en">Economic and social data</name>
      </keyword>
    </keywords>
    <topics>
      <topic id="41">
        <name lang="de">Soziales</name>
        <name lang="fr">Social</name>
        <name lang="it">Opere sociali</name>
        <name lang="en">Social Affairs</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="43">
        <name lang="de">Statistik</name>
        <name lang="fr">Statistiques</name>
        <name lang="it">Statistica</name>
        <name lang="en">Statistics</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
