<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="87184" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2022-02-15</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="323" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>701</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidg. Materialprüfungs- und Forschungsanstalt</name>
      <name lang="fr">Laboratoire fédéral d'essai des matériaux et de recherche</name>
      <name lang="it">Laboratorio federale di prova dei materiali e di ricerca</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Laboratory for Materials Testing and Research</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.empa.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.empa.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.empa.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.empa.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">contact@empa.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">contact@empa.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">contact@empa.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">contact@empa.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="701">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Wirtschaft, Bildung und Forschung</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'économie, de la formation et de la recherche</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'economia, della formazione e della ricerca</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Economic Affairs, Education and Research</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Dübendorf, St. Gallen und Thun</city>
      <title>Flugsicherheit: Diagnose im Flug</title>
      <lead>Gemeinsam mit Teams aus England und Deutschland entwickelten Empa-Forscher ein Überwachungssystem für Flugzeug-Bauteile. In Zukunft könnten kleine Beschädigungen schon während des Fluges aufgespürt und überwacht werden, ohne dass das Flugzeug zur Wartung in den Hangar muss. Das senkt die Betriebskosten und erhöht zugleich die Sicherheit.</lead>
      <text link="no">Die Druckkabinen von Verkehrsflugzeugen, ebenso wie deren Flügel und Leitwerke, werden in regelmässigen Abständen auf Risse und Schäden untersucht. Alle sechs bis zehn Jahre muss jeder Jet zum sogenannten D-Check für ein bis zwei Monate in einen Hangar. Dort wird er weitgehend auseinandergebaut, selbst die Lackierung wird entfernt. Zusammen mit dem Ausfall an Flugzeit kann ein solcher D-Check leicht mehrere Millionen Franken kosten.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Geht es nicht auch einfacher? Könnte man nicht die belasteten Teile der Flugzeugstruktur auch permanent, also während des Fluges, überwachen und entstehende Schäden gezielt im Auge behalten? Im Rahmen eines EU-Projekts namens DIMES («Development of Integrated Measurement Systems») ist ein internationales Forschungskonsortium dieser Frage nachgegangen. Projektpartner sind neben der Empa Airbus, die University of Liverpool, die Firmen «Strain Solutions Limited» aus Grossbritannien und «Dantec Dynamics GmbH» aus Deutschland.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;b&gt;Ist da was? Wie schlimm ist es?&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;«Wir haben uns im Februar 2018 auf das Projekt beworben, das im Rahmen des «Clean Sky 2»-Programms der EU ausgeschrieben war», erklärt Erwin Hack, der Projektleiter an der Empa. Die Fragestellung war spannend: Mit möglichst robusten und preisgünstigen Komponenten sollten die Forscher den metallischen Flügel eines Airbus A320 und Kohlefaser-Verbundwerkstoffe im Kabinenpaneel eines Airbus A350 beobachten. «Die Sensoren sollten am Ende mehrere Fragen beantworten: Ist da ein Schaden? Wo ist der Schaden? Welcher Art ist der Schaden? Wie ernst ist die Beschädigung, und wie lange hält das Bauteil noch?»&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Das Konsortium erhielt den Zuschlag, und die Empa spielte dabei keine unwesentliche Rolle: Einerseits ist Hack Spezialist für die optische Überwachung von Bauteilen, für Wärmebildmessungen und für die Überwachung mittels Dehnungsmessstreifen und Bragg-Gittern. All diese Methoden sollten zugleich an den Flugzeugteilen eingesetzt werden. Und zum anderen verfügt die Empa über Maschinen, in denen die Teile eingespannt und tausende Male hintereinander gezielt durchgebogen werden konnten. Zusammen mit Silvain Michel von der Empa-Abteilung «Mechanical Systems Engineering» entwickelte Hack seine Teststrategie. Airbus lieferte aus Filton/UK das rund sieben Meter lange Flügelsegment eines Airbus A320-111, der 1988 bei einem Absturz beschädigt worden war.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;b&gt;Schadensbetrachtung mit vier Methoden&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Im November 2019 war das Flügelteil an der Empa eingespannt, die Untersuchungen konnten beginnen. Mit hydraulischen Pressen wurde der Flügel 70'000 Mal durchgebogen, während die Forscherinnen und Forscher Daten sammelten und die Ergebnisse analysierten. Die Biegeversuche vergrösserten – wie erwartet – die Bruchstellen, die der Flügel beim Absturz erlitten hatte, und führten zu neuen Rissen.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Den Gesamtzustand des Flügels «fühlten» die Forscher mit Dehnungsmessstreifen und faseroptischen Bragg-Sensoren. Die nähere Umgebung des Schadens beobachteten sie mit Kameras und Infrarotkameras – denn die Biegungstests erzeugen Wärme im geschädigten Flügelteil. Dort, wo die Wärme entsteht, gilt es, besonders genau hinzuschauen.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;b&gt;Die Pandemie stellt Herausforderungen&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;In einem nächsten Schritt galt es, die Untersuchungsmethoden aus dem Metall-Flügel auf Kohlefaser-Strukturen eines Flugzeugs anzupassen: Bei Airbus in Toulouse stand das Cockpit eines Airbus bereit, und die Empa erhielt Rumpfpanele eines Airbus A350 aus Hamburg. Beide Teile sind vor allem durch den Kabinendruck belastet, der bei jedem Flug aufgebaut und bei jeder Landung wieder entlastet wird.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Doch dann kam Corona. Nun konnten die Forscherteams aus Chesterfield und Liverpool, in Ulm und Dübendorf sich nicht mehr treffen und auch nicht zu ihren Versuchsobjekten reisen, die in Dübendorf, Toulouse und Filton in den Labors standen. Die Forscher lösten das Problem, indem sie ein spezielles Kommunikationssystem für Mechaniker entwickelten, bestehend aus Helmkamera, Kopfhörern und Mikrofon. So ausgerüstet konnte ein Spezialist in Toulouse das Modul in die Cockpitstruktur montieren – aus der Ferne geführt von Experten in England, Deutschland und von der Empa. Die Methode funktionierte so gut, dass schliesslich noch ein Luftfahrt-Forschungslabor im kanadischen Ottawa ins Projekt aufgenommen wurde. Dort wurde ein Flugzeugflügel mit dem Überwachungsmodul bestückt, ohne dass ein einziger Langstreckenflug zum Forschungsobjekt nötig war.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;b&gt;Einsatz bei statischen Strukturtests&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Ergebnis des Projekts ist ein kleines Modul aus handelsüblichen, preisgünstigen Komponenten, das zugleich vier Überwachungsmethoden beherrscht: Dehnungsmessungen mit Messstreifen und Bragg-Sensoren, optische Überwachung und thermoelastische Stress-Analyse. Die Daten aus den Sensoren werden in einem Minicomputer gesammelt und können von Ferne ausgelesen werden.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Zunächst darf das Modul noch nicht in Flugzeugen mitfliegen, sondern soll bei Strukturtests in Airbus-Entwicklungslabors beweisen, was es kann. Wenn die Technik weiter ausgereift ist, könnte sie entscheidend dabei helfen, die Sicherheit von Flugzeugen zu erhöhen und zugleich die Wartungskosten zu senken. Die nächste Generation von Airlinern könnte dank solcher Strukturüberwachung auch etwas leichter und damit Treibstoff-sparender gebaut werden als heute.</text>
      <contact>Dr. Erwin Hack Transport at Nanoscale Interfaces Tel. +41 58 765 4273 Erwin.Hack@empa.ch</contact>
      <attachment id="227316">
        <title>Expertenblick: Silvain Michel und Erwin Hack (rechts) untersuchen das Rumpfpaneel eines Airbus A350. Bild: Empa</title>
        <format>jpg</format>
        <size-kb>1883</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/70202.jpg</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="227317">
        <title>Sensormessung: Dehnungsmessstreifen und optische Bragg-Gitter überwachen die Schäden im Biegeversuch. Bild: Empa</title>
        <format>jpg</format>
        <size-kb>2457</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/70203.jpg</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <link id="227315">
        <title>Empa-Homepage</title>
        <uri>https://www.empa.ch/web/s604/dimes</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Dübendorf, St. Gallen und Thun</city>
      <title>Sécurité des avions: Diagnostic en vol</title>
      <lead>En collaboration avec des équipes anglaises et allemandes, des chercheurs de l'Empa ont mis au point un système de surveillance des composants des avions. A l'avenir, les petits dommages pourraient être détectés et surveillés pendant le vol, sans que l'avion doive rentrer au hangar pour l'entretien. Cela permettrait de réduire les coûts d'exploitation tout en améliorant la sécurité.</lead>
      <text link="no">Les cabines pressurisées des avions de ligne, tout comme leurs ailes et leur empennage, sont inspectées à intervalles réguliers pour détecter les fissures et les dommages. Tous les six à dix ans, chaque jet doit passer un à deux mois dans un hangar pour le "D-Check". Là, il est en grande partie démonté, même la peinture est enlevée. Si l'on ajoute à cela le temps de vol perdu, un tel D-Check peut facilement coûter plusieurs millions de francs.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Ne pourrait-on pas faire plus simple ? Ne pourrait-on pas surveiller en permanence, c'est-à-dire pendant le vol, les parties sollicitées de la structure de l'avion et surveiller de manière ciblée les dommages qui se produisent ? Dans le cadre d'un projet européen appelé DIMES ("Development of Integrated Measurement Systems"), un consortium de recherche international s'est penché sur cette question. Les partenaires du projet sont, outre l'Empa Airbus, l'Université de Liverpool, les entreprises "Strain Solutions Limited" de Grande-Bretagne et "Dantec Dynamics GmbH" d'Allemagne.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;b&gt;Y a-t'il quelque chose ?&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;"En février 2018, nous avons répondu à l'appel d'offres lancé dans le cadre du programme "Clean Sky 2" de l'UE", explique Erwin Hack, chef de projet à l'Empa. La problématique était passionnante : avec des composants aussi robustes et bon marché que possible, les chercheurs devaient observer l'aile métallique d'un Airbus A320 et les matériaux composites à base de fibres de carbone dans le panneau de la cabine d'un Airbus A350. "Les capteurs devaient à la fin répondre à plusieurs questions : Y a-t-il un dommage ? Où se trouve le dommage ? Quelle est la nature du dommage ? Quelle est la gravité du dommage et quelle est la durée de vie de la pièce" ?&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Le consortium a obtenu le mandat et l'Empa n'y a pas joué un rôle négligeable : d'une part, Erwin Hack est spécialisé dans la surveillance optique des composants, dans les mesures d'imagerie thermique et dans la surveillance au moyen de jauges de contrainte et de réseaux optiques de Bragg. Toutes ces méthodes devaient être utilisées simultanément sur les pièces de l'avion. Et d'autre part, l'Empa dispose de machines dans lesquelles les pièces peuvent être serrées et fléchies de manière ciblée des milliers de fois d'affilée. Erwin Hack a développé sa stratégie de test en collaboration avec Silvain Michel du département "Mechanical Systems Engineering" de l'Empa. Airbus a livré de Filton/UK le segment d'aile d'environ sept mètres de long d'un Airbus A320-111 endommagé lors d'un crash en 1988.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Quatre méthodes à la fois&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;En novembre 2019, la partie de l'aile était fixée et serrée à l'Empa et les examens pouvaient commencer. L'aile a été fléchie 70'000 fois à l'aide de presses hydrauliques, tandis que les chercheurs collectaient des données et analysaient les résultats. Comme prévu, les essais de flexion ont agrandi les points de rupture que l'aile avait subis lors du crash et ont entraîné de nouvelles fissures.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Les chercheurs ont "senti" l'état général de l'aile à l'aide de jauges de contrainte et de capteurs de Bragg à fibres optiques. Ils ont observé l'environnement proche du dommage avec des caméras et des caméras infrarouges - car les tests de flexion génèrent de la chaleur dans la partie endommagée de l'aile. Là où la chaleur est générée, il s'agit d'être particulièrement attentif.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;b&gt;Tâche supplémentaire&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;L'étape suivante consistait à adapter les méthodes d'analyse de l'aile métallique aux structures en fibre de carbone d'un avion : Chez Airbus à Toulouse, le cockpit d'un Airbus était prêt, et l'Empa a reçu des panneaux de fuselage d'un Airbus A350 de Hambourg. Les deux pièces sont surtout sollicitées par la pression de la cabine, qui s'accumule à chaque vol et se relâche à chaque atterrissage.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Mais le coronavirus est arrivé. Les équipes de chercheurs de Chesterfield et de Liverpool, d'Ulm et de Dübendorf ne pouvaient plus se rencontrer ni se rendre auprès de leurs cobayes, qui se trouvaient dans les laboratoires de Dübendorf, Toulouse et Filton. Les chercheurs ont résolu le problème en développant un système de communication spécial pour les mécaniciens, composé d'une caméra pour casque, d'écouteurs et d'un microphone. Ainsi équipé, un spécialiste de Toulouse a pu monter le module dans la structure du cockpit - guidé à distance par des experts d'Angleterre, d'Allemagne et de l'Empa. La méthode a si bien fonctionné qu'un laboratoire de recherche aéronautique d'Ottawa, au Canada, a finalement été intégré au projet. Une aile d'avion y a été équipée du module de surveillance, sans qu'un seul vol longue distance ne soit nécessaire pour atteindre l'objet de recherche du projet.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Utilisation&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Le résultat du projet est un petit module composé de composants courants et peu coûteux, qui comporte en même temps quatre méthodes de surveillance : les mesures de déformation avec des jauges et des capteurs de Bragg, la surveillance optique et l'analyse du stress thermoélastique. Les données des capteurs sont collectées dans un mini-ordinateur et peuvent être lues à distance.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Dans un premier temps, le module n'est pas encore autorisé à voler dans des avions, mais doit prouver ses capacités lors de tests structurels dans les laboratoires de développement d'Airbus. Une fois que la technologie aura été perfectionnée, elle pourrait jouer un rôle décisif dans l'amélioration de la sécurité des avions et dans la réduction des coûts de maintenance. Grâce à cette surveillance structurelle, la prochaine génération d'avions pourrait également être plus légère et donc plus économe en carburant qu'aujourd'hui.&lt;br /&gt;</text>
      <contact>Dr. Erwin Hack Transport at Nanoscale Interfaces Tél. +41 58 765 4273 Erwin.Hack@empa.ch</contact>
      <attachment id="227320">
        <title>Silvain Michel et Erwin Hack (à droite) examinent le panneau de fuselage d’un Airbus A350. Image: Empa</title>
        <format>jpg</format>
        <size-kb>1883</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/70206.jpg</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="227321">
        <title>Des jauges de contrainte et des réseaux optiques de Bragg surveillent les dommages lors des essais de flexion. Image: Empa</title>
        <format>jpg</format>
        <size-kb>2457</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/70207.jpg</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <link id="227315">
        <title>Empa-Homepage</title>
        <uri>https://www.empa.ch/web/s604/dimes</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Dübendorf, St. Gallen und Thun</city>
      <title>Aircraft security: Diagnosis during flight</title>
      <lead>Together with teams from England and Germany, Empa researchers developed a monitoring system for aircraft components. In the future, minor damage could be detected and monitored during flight without the aircraft having to go into the hangar for maintenance. This will reduce operating costs and increase safety at the same time.</lead>
      <text link="no">The pressurized cabins of commercial aircraft, as well as their wings and tail units, are inspected for cracks and damage at regular intervals. Every six to ten years, each jet has to undergo a D-check in a hangar for one to two months. There, it is largely disassembled, even the paint is removed. Together with the lost operating time, such a D-check can easily cost several million Swiss francs.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Couldn't it be simpler? Couldn't the stressed parts of the aircraft structure also be monitored permanently, i.e. during the flight, and any damage that occurs be specifically monitored? As part of an EU-funded project called DIMES (Development of Integrated Measurement Systems), an international research consortium has been investigating this idea. Besides Empa, the project partners are Airbus, the University of Liverpool, the companies Strain Solutions Ltd. from Great Britain and Dantec Dynamics GmbH from Germany.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;b&gt;Where is it? How bad is it?&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;"We applied for the project in February 2018, which was launched as part of the EU's Clean Sky 2 program," explains Erwin Hack, the project manager at Empa. The question was an exciting one: Using components that were as robust and inexpensive as possible, the researchers were to monitor the metallic wing of an Airbus A320 and carbon fiber composites in the cabin panel of an Airbus A350. Hack: "The sensors were to answer several questions at the same time: Is there any damage? Where is the damage? What is the nature of the damage? How serious is the damage, and how long will the component last?"&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The consortium was awarded the contract, and Empa played no small role: On the one hand, Hack is a specialist in optical monitoring of components, thermal imaging measurements and monitoring using strain gauges and Bragg gratings. All these methods were to be used on the aircraft parts at the same time. And secondly, Empa has the required infrastructure to clamp in the parts and selectively bent them thousands of times in succession. Hack developed his test strategy together with Silvain Michel from Empa's Mechanical Systems Engineering laboratory. Airbus supplied the approximately seven-meter-long wing segment of an Airbus A320-111 from Filton/UK, which had been damaged in a crash in 1988.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;b&gt;Four methods at once&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;In November 2019, the wing section was clamped in place at Empa, and the tests began. Hydraulic presses were used to bend the wing 70,000 times while the researchers collected data and analyzed the results. As expected, the bending tests enlarged the fractures the wing had suffered in the crash and led to new cracks.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The researchers "felt" the overall condition of the wing with strain gauges and fiber-optic Bragg sensors. They observed the immediate vicinity of the damage with cameras and infrared cameras – because the bending tests generate heat in the damaged wing section. Where heat is generated, it's important to look particularly closely.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;b&gt;Pandemic as a challenge&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The next step was to adapt the testing methods from metal wings to carbon fiber structures of an aircraft: Airbus in Toulouse provided the cockpit of an Airbus, and Empa received fuselage panels of an Airbus A350 from Hamburg. Both parts are stressed primarily by the cabin pressure, which is built up during each flight and released again during each landing.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;But then came Corona. Now the research teams in Chesterfield and Liverpool, in Ulm and Dübendorf, could no longer meet or travel to their test objects, which were in the laboratories in Dübendorf, Toulouse and Filton. The researchers solved the problem by developing a special communication system for mechanics, consisting of a helmet camera, head- and microphone. Thus equipped, a specialist in Toulouse was able to mount the module in the cockpit structure – guided remotely by experts in England, Germany and from Empa. The method worked so well that an aeronautics research laboratory in Ottawa, Canada, eventually joined the project. There, an aircraft wing was fitted with the monitoring module without the need for a single long-distance flight to the research object.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;b&gt;First use in structural tests&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The result of the project is a small module made of commercially available, low-cost components that can simultaneously handle four monitoring methods: strain measurements with measuring strips and Bragg sensors, optical monitoring and thermoelastic stress analysis. The data from the sensors is collected in a minicomputer and can be read out remotely.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Initially, the module will not be allowed to fly in aircraft yet, but will prove what it can do during structural tests in Airbus development labs. As the technology matures, it could play a key role in improving aircraft safety while reducing maintenance costs. The next generation of airliners could also be built somewhat lighter and thus more fuel-efficient than today thanks to such structural monitoring.&lt;br /&gt;</text>
      <contact>Dr. Erwin Hack Transport at Nanoscale Interfaces Phone +41 58 765 4273 Erwin.Hack@empa.ch</contact>
      <attachment id="227318">
        <title>Expert view: Silvain Michel and Erwin Hack (right) examine the fuselage panel of an Airbus A350. Image: Empa</title>
        <format>jpg</format>
        <size-kb>1883</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/70204.jpg</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="227319">
        <title>Sensor measurement: Strain gauges and optical Bragg gratings monitor damage in bending tests. Image: Empa</title>
        <format>jpg</format>
        <size-kb>2457</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/70205.jpg</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <link id="227315">
        <title>Empa-Homepage</title>
        <uri>https://www.empa.ch/web/s604/dimes</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="8">
        <name lang="de">Bildung und Forschung</name>
        <name lang="fr">Formation et recherche</name>
        <name lang="it">Formazione e ricerca</name>
        <name lang="en">Education and Research</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="45">
        <name lang="de">Technologie</name>
        <name lang="fr">Technologie</name>
        <name lang="it">Tecnologia</name>
        <name lang="en">Technology</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="46">
        <name lang="de">Verkehr</name>
        <name lang="fr">Transports</name>
        <name lang="it">Trasporti</name>
        <name lang="en">Transport</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
