<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="80542" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2020-09-28</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="1063" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>701</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Paul Scherrer Institut</name>
      <name lang="fr">Institut Paul Scherrer</name>
      <name lang="it">Istituto Paul Scherrer</name>
      <name lang="en">Paul Scherrer Institut</name>
      <www lang="de"/>
      <www lang="fr"/>
      <www lang="it"/>
      <www lang="en"/>
      <email lang="de">info@psi.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@psi.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@psi.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@psi.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="701">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Wirtschaft, Bildung und Forschung</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'économie, de la formation et de la recherche</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'economia, della formazione e della ricerca</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Economic Affairs, Education and Research</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Villigen</city>
      <title>Neues Verfahren für ultraschnelle Tumor-Therapie</title>
      <lead>Erstmals haben Forschende am Zentrum für Protonentherapie des Paul Scherer Instituts PSI in der Schweiz eine ultraschnelle, hoch dosierte Bestrahlung mit Protonen getestet. Dieses neue, experimentelle FLASH-Verfahren könnte die Strahlentherapie von Krebs revolutionieren und Patienten viele Wochen der Behandlung ersparen.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Blitze beeindrucken in der Natur durch ein kurzes, starkes Leuchten und eine hohe Energieentladung. FLASH - der englische Begriff für Blitz - steht auch in der Strahlenmedizin für eine ultrakurze und hoch dosierte, einmalige Bestrahlung und könnte künftig den Patienten viele Wochen an Behandlung ersparen. Am Zentrum für Protonentherapie ZPT testen PSI-Forschende deshalb, ob FLASH auch für die Protonenbestrahlung mit der am PSI entwickelten &lt;i&gt;Spot-Scanning-Technik&lt;/i&gt; geeignet ist. Für ihre Experimente arbeiten Damien Weber, Leiter und Chefarzt des ZPT, und sein Team am PSI mit dem Centre hospitalier universitaire vaudois (CHUV) in Lausanne zusammen. Dort wurde mit einer Genehmigung der Schweizerischen Akademie der Medizinischen Wissenschaften (SAMW) der bislang einzige Patient weltweit im FLASH-Verfahren bestrahlt, um einen bösartigen Tumor in der Haut zu heilen. Anders als das PSI verwenden die Forschenden am CHUV Elektronenstrahlen. Diese eignen sich ausschliesslich für sehr oberflächlich liegende Tumore. Demgegenüber erreichen die am PSI verwendeten Protonen auch tief im Körperinneren liegende Tumore und lassen sich exakt an der Stelle im Körper stoppen, wo sie ihre maximale Wirkung auf die Krebszellen entfalten sollen.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Kurz und heftig&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;«Wenn wir die hohe Präzision und die gute Wirkung der Protonentherapie mit einer FLASH-Bestrahlung erreichen, ohne gesundes Gewebe zu schädigen, wäre dies ein Riesenfortschritt», sagt Damien Weber. Behandlungen könnten damit viel kürzer und weniger belastend für Patienten werden. «Wenn das Prinzip funktioniert, müssten die Patienten nur wenige Male zur Bestrahlung kommen, idealerweise nur ein bis fünf Mal. Die frei werdenden Behandlungsplätze würden anderen Krebskranken zur Verfügung stehen.» Wegen der extrem kurzen Bestrahlung lasse sich mit der FLASH-Technik selbst Gewebe in der Lunge behandeln, das bei jedem Atemzug seine Lage verändere. Bevor das Verfahren allerdings technisch so ausgereift ist, dass es bei Patienten routinemässig zum Einsatz kommen kann, braucht es noch viele Jahre an technischer Entwicklung und sehr viele Tests. Bei FLASH wird eine Strahlendosisrate von bis zu 1000 Gray pro Sekunde verwendet, dies ist eine etwa hundertmal höhere Strahlendosis pro Sekunde gegenüber den sonst üblichen Behandlungen. Das zerstört zwar die Tumorzellen sehr effektiv. «Wir brauchen aber zuallererst Beweise, dass Protonenbestrahlung mit der FLASH-Technik gesundes Körpergewebe nicht schädigt», so Weber. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;In ihren Experimenten wollen die PSI-Forschenden deshalb die maximal mögliche Intensität des Stahls nutzen und diese ohne Verluste auf biologisches Gewebe richten, das weniger als ein Millimeter dick ist. Dafür hat Teilchenphysikerin Serena Psoroulas mit ihrem Team die Einstellungen für die Strahlführung in einer früheren Behandlungsstation für Protonentherapie des PSI, die sogenannte Gantry 1, optimiert. «Gerade die älteren Kollegen hier am PSI haben grosse Erfahrung, weil sie die Apparate selbst entwickelt, aufgebaut und getestet haben», so Psoroulas. Sie haben die Kontroll- und Sicherheitssysteme eingerichtet und die Programmcodes für die Bestrahlung geschrieben.» Dieses Knowhow zwischen ingenieurtechnischer Spitzenleistung, medizinischer Expertise und Physik haben die PSI-Forschenden jetzt genutzt, um die weltweit ersten Experimente der FLASH-Bestrahlung mit der am PSI entwickelten &lt;i&gt;Spot-Scanning-Technik&lt;/i&gt; durchzuführen.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Starker Partner&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Bislang haben die Forschenden zwei Serien von Experimenten mit der FLASH-Technik am PSI durchgeführt. Dafür arbeitet das Team von Weber eng mit der Strahlenbiologin Marie-Catherine Vozenin und ihrem Team vom CHUV zusammen. Alle Experimente in dem vom Schweizerischen Nationalfond SNF (Fördernummer 190663) und einem Industriepartner geförderten Projekt haben die beiden Forscherinnen gemeinsam geplant. Sie bestrahlen parallel und zeitgleich mit Protonen am PSI und mit Elektronenstrahlen am CHUV. Anschliessend wird im radiobiologischen Labor des CHUV analysiert, welche Auswirkungen die FLASH-Bestrahlung auf das biologische Gewebe hat. Die Forschenden am PSI schätzen die starke Partnerschaft mit dem CHUV besonders. Deshalb sind auch beide Institutionen Teil eines Konsortiums, das sich der Erforschung der FLASH-Therapie für den Einsatz an Patienten verschrieben hat. Damien Weber: «Durch unsere Synergien in der Zusammenarbeit und unsere gemeinsamen Experimente hoffen wir, die FLASH-Technik besser zu verstehen und weiterzuentwickeln.» In der Erfolgsgeschichte der Protonentherapie am PSI fängt ein neues Kapitel an. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Text: Sabine Goldhahn&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Über das PSI&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; Das Paul Scherrer Institut PSI entwickelt, baut und betreibt grosse und komplexe Forschungsanlagen und stellt sie der nationalen und internationalen Forschungsgemeinde zur Verfügung. Eigene Forschungsschwerpunkte sind Materie und Material, Energie und Umwelt sowie Mensch und Gesundheit. Die Ausbildung von jungen Menschen ist ein zentrales Anliegen des PSI. Deshalb sind etwa ein Viertel unserer Mitarbeitenden Postdoktorierende, Doktorierende oder Lernende. Insgesamt beschäftigt das PSI 2100 Mitarbeitende, das damit das grösste Forschungsinstitut der Schweiz ist. Das Jahresbudget beträgt rund CHF 400 Mio. Das PSI ist Teil des ETH-Bereichs, dem auch die ETH Zürich und die ETH Lausanne angehören sowie die Forschungsinstitute Eawag, Empa und WSL. </text>
      <contact>Dr. Mirjam van Daalen Verantwortliche für Kommunikation Paul Scherrer Institut 5232 Villigen PSI Telefon: +41 56 310 56 74 mirjam.vandaalen@psi.ch</contact>
      <link id="205743">
        <title>Bilder und weitere Informationen</title>
        <uri>http://psi.ch/de/node/39583</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Villigen</city>
      <title>Nouvelle méthode ultrarapide de traitement du cancer</title>
      <lead>Des chercheurs au Centre de protonthérapie de l’Institut Paul Scherrer PSI ont testé pour la première fois une irradiation protonique ultrarapide et fortement dosée. Cette nouvelle méthode FLASH expérimentale pourrait révolutionner le traitement du cancer par radiothérapie et épargner aux patients de nombreuses semaines de traitement.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Dans la nature, les éclairs nous impressionnent par leur éclat bref et violent, ainsi que par la puissance de leur décharge électrique. Dans le domaine de la radiothérapie, le terme FLASH - pour éclair en anglais - désigne une irradiation unique, ultracourte et fortement dosée. A l'avenir, cette méthode pourrait épargner aux patients de nombreuses semaines de traitement. Au Centre de protonthérapie (CPT), des chercheurs du PSI mènent des tests afin de déterminer si la méthode FLASH pourrait être appliquée à l'irradiation protonique avec la technique &lt;i&gt;Spot Scan&lt;/i&gt; développée au PSI. Pour leurs expériences, Damien Weber, médecin-chef et directeur du CPT, et son équipe collaborent avec le Centre hospitalier universitaire vaudois (CHUV) à Lausanne. C'est là que le premier patient au monde a été irradié avec la méthode FLASH pour le traitement de tumeurs malignes de la peau. Cette procédure, menée avec l'aval de l'Académie suisse des sciences médicales (ASSM), est la seule à avoir été conduite pour l'instant. A la différence du PSI, les chercheurs du CHUV utilisent des faisceaux d'électrons. Ces derniers se prêtent exclusivement au traitement de tumeurs situées en surface. Les protons utilisés au PSI, en revanche, atteignent aussi des tumeurs situées dans les profondeurs du corps et peuvent être stoppés de manière précise à un endroit de l'organisme, où ils déploient leur effet maximal sur les cellules cancéreuses.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Bref et violent &lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;«Si nous réussissions à atteindre le haut degré de précision et la bonne efficacité de la protonthérapie avec une irradiation FLASH, sans endommager les tissus sains, ce serait un progrès gigantesque», souligne Damien Weber. Les traitements pourraient être ainsi largement raccourcis et seraient moins lourds pour les patients. «Si le principe devait fonctionner, les patients ne devraient venir que pour un nombre limité de séances d'irradiation, seulement une à cinq fois dans l'idéal, poursuit le chercheur. Cela libèrerait des places qui seraient alors disponibles pour le traitement d'autres patients cancéreux.» En raison de l'extrême brièveté de l'irradiation, la technique FLASH peut être utilisée même dans des tissus comme ceux des poumons qui bougent à chaque respiration. Toutefois, il faudra encore beaucoup d'années de développement technique et de très nombreux tests avant que la méthode soit assez mûre pour devenir un traitement de routine utilisable chez les patients. Avec FLASH, le débit de dose utilisé atteint jusqu'à 1000 gray par seconde, soit une dose d'irradiation par seconde environ 100 fois plus élevée que lors des traitements conventionnels. Cela détruit certes les cellules cancéreuses de manière très efficace. «Mais nous avons besoin avant tout de preuves que l'irradiation protonique avec la technique FLASH ne détruit pas les tissus sains de l'organisme», rappelle Damien Weber. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Dans le cadre de leurs expériences, les chercheurs du PSI ont donc l'intention d'utiliser l'intensité maximale possible du faisceau et de le braquer sans pertes sur des tissus biologiques dont l'épaisseur ne dépasse pas un millimètre. Pour ce faire, Serena Psoroulas, spécialiste en physique des particules, et son équipe ont optimisé les réglages pour le guidage du faisceau dans une ancienne station de traitement par protonthérapie du PSI, appelée Gantry 1. «Les collègues plus âgés ici, au PSI, disposent d'une vaste expérience parce qu'ils ont développé, construit et testé eux-mêmes ces appareils, note Serena Psoroulas. Ils ont installé les systèmes de contrôle et de sécurité, et écrit les codes des programmes pour l'irradiation.» Les chercheurs du PSI ont à présent mis à profit ce savoir-faire à cheval entre excellence technique, expertise médicale et physique pour conduire les premières expériences au monde d'irradiation FLASH avec la technique &lt;i&gt;Spot Scan&lt;/i&gt; développée au PSI.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Partenariat solide &lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Jusqu'ici, les chercheurs ont mené deux séries d'expériences avec la technique FLASH au PSI. Dans ce cadre, l'équipe de Damien Weber a étroitement collaboré avec Marie-Catherine Vozenin, spécialiste en radiobiologie, et son équipe. Les deux chercheurs ont planifié ensemble toutes les expériences dans le cadre d'un projet soutenu par le Fonds national suisse (FNS, numéro de projet 190663) et un partenaire de l'industrie. Ils irradient en parallèle et au même moment avec des protons au PSI et des faisceaux d'électrons au CHUV. Ensuite, le Laboratoire de radiobiologie du CHUV analyse l'impact de l'irradiation FLASH sur les tissus biologiques. Les chercheurs au PSI apprécient tout particulièrement la solidité de leur partenariat avec le CHUV. C'est pourquoi les deux institutions sont aussi membres d'un consortium dédié à la recherche sur la radiothérapie FLASH pour son utilisation chez les patients. «Grâce à nos synergies dans la collaboration et nos expériences communes, nous espérons aboutir à une meilleure compréhension de la technique FLASH et à son évolution», conclut Damien Weber. Un nouveau chapitre de l'histoire florissante de la protonthérapie au PSI commence. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Texte: Sabine Goldhahn&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;À propos du PSI&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; L'Institut Paul Scherrer PSI développe, construit et exploite des grandes installations de recherche complexes et les met à la disposition de la communauté scientifique nationale et internationale. Les domaines de recherche de l'institut sont centrés sur la matière et les matériaux, l'énergie et l'environnement ainsi que la santé humaine. La formation des générations futures est un souci central du PSI. Pour cette raison, environ un quart de nos collaborateurs sont des postdocs, des doctorants ou des apprentis. Au total, le PSI emploie 2100 personnes, étant ainsi le plus grand institut de recherche de Suisse. Le budget annuel est d'environ CHF 400 millions. Le PSI fait partie du domaine des EPF, les autres membres étant l'ETH Zurich, l'EPF Lausanne, l'Eawag (Institut de Recherche de l'Eau), l'Empa (Laboratoire fédéral d'essai des matériaux et de recherche) et le WSL (Institut fédéral de recherches sur la forêt, la neige et le paysage).&lt;i&gt; &lt;/i&gt; </text>
      <contact>Dr. Mirjam van Daalen Responsable de la communication Paul Scherrer Institut CH-5232 Villigen PSI Téléphone: +41 56 310 56 74 mirjam.vandaalen@psi.ch</contact>
      <link id="205744">
        <title>Images et informations supplémentaires</title>
        <uri>http://psi.ch/fr/node/39583</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Villigen</city>
      <title>New technique for ultrafast tumour therapy</title>
      <lead>For the first time, researchers at the Centre for Proton Therapy at the Paul Scherrer Institute PSI in Switzerland have tested ultrafast, high-dose irradiation with protons. This new, experimental FLASH technique could revolutionise radiation therapy for cancer and save patients many weeks of treatment.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;In nature, lightning strikes with a short, strong flash of light and a high energy discharge. In radiation medicine, FLASH also stands for ultrashort, high-dose, one-time irradiation, and in the future it could save patients many weeks of treatment. At the Centre for Proton Therapy CPT, PSI researchers are testing whether FLASH is also suitable for proton irradiation using the &lt;i&gt;spot-scanning&lt;/i&gt; technology developed at PSI. For their experiments, CPT head and chief physician Damien Weber and his team at PSI are collaborating with the Centre hospitalier universitaire vaudois (CHUV) in Lausanne. There, with the approval of the Swiss Academy of Medical Sciences (SAMS), the only patient in the world to date has been irradiated using the FLASH technique in order to heal a malignant tumour in the skin. Unlike at PSI, the researchers at CHUV use electron beams. These are only suitable for very superficial tumours. In contrast, the protons used at PSI also reach tumours deep inside the body and can be stopped precisely at the site in the body where they should have their maximum effect on the cancer cells.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Short and intense&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;"If we can achieve the high precision and the good outcome of proton therapy with FLASH irradiation without damaging healthy tissue, this would be a huge step forward," says Damien Weber. Treatments could be much shorter and less stressful for patients. "If the principle works, the patients would only have to come for radiation treatment a few times, ideally only one to five times. The treatment appointments that open up as a result would be available to other cancer patients." Because of the extremely short irradiation, it is even possible to use the FLASH technique to treat tissue in the lungs, which changes its position with every breath. However, before the process is technically mature enough to be used routinely with patients, it will take many years of technical development and a great many tests. With FLASH, a radiation dose rate of up to 1,000 gray per second is applied; that is a radiation dose per second roughly a hundred times higher than in the usual treatments. This destroys the tumour cells very effectively. "But first and foremost, we need evidence that proton irradiation with the FLASH technique does not damage healthy body tissue," says Weber.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;In their experiments, the PSI researchers therefore want to use the maximum possible intensity of the beam and direct it without losses onto biological tissue that is less than a millimetre thick. For this purpose, particle physicist Serena Psoroulas and her team have optimised the beam guidance settings in a former treatment station for proton therapy at PSI, known as Gantry 1. "The older colleagues here at PSI in particular have a lot of experience because they developed, constructed, and tested the equipment themselves," says Psoroulas. "They have set up the monitoring and safety systems and written the program code for the irradiation." The PSI researchers have now used this know-how, which spans high-performance engineering, medical expertise, and physics, to carry out the world's first experiments in FLASH irradiation with the spot-scanning technology developed at PSI.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Strong partnership&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;So far, the researchers have carried out two series of experiments with the FLASH technique at PSI. Weber's team works closely with radiation biologist Marie-Catherine Vozenin and her team from CHUV. Together, the two researchers planned all of the experiments in the project, which is funded by the Swiss National Science Foundation (SNSF grant number 190663) and an industrial partner. In parallel and simultaneously, they irradiate tissue with protons at PSI and with electron beams at CHUV. The radiobiological laboratory at CHUV then analyses what effects the FLASH radiation has on biological tissue. The researchers at PSI especially appreciate the strong partnership with CHUV. Both institutions are also part of a consortium committed to exploring FLASH therapy for use on patients. Damien Weber: "Through our synergies in collaboration and our joint experiments, we hope to better understand and further develop FLASH technology." In the success story of proton therapy at PSI, a new chapter is beginning.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Text: Sabine Goldhahn&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;About PSI&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; The Paul Scherrer Institute PSI develops, builds and operates large, complex research facilities and makes them available to the national and international research community. The institute's own key research priorities are in the fields of matter and materials, energy and environment and human health. PSI is committed to the training of future generations. Therefore about one quarter of our staff are post-docs, post-graduates or apprentices. Altogether PSI employs 2100 people, thus being the largest research institute in Switzerland. The annual budget amounts to approximately CHF 400 million. PSI is part of the ETH Domain, with the other members being the two Swiss Federal Institutes of Technology, ETH Zurich and EPFL Lausanne, as well as Eawag (Swiss Federal Institute of Aquatic Science and Technology), Empa (Swiss Federal Laboratories for Materials Science and Technology) and WSL (Swiss Federal Institute for Forest, Snow and Landscape Research).&lt;i&gt; &lt;/i&gt;</text>
      <contact>Dr. Mirjam van Daalen Head of Communications Paul Scherrer Institute CH-5232 Villigen PSI Phone: +41 56 310 56 74 mirjam.vandaalen@psi.ch</contact>
      <link id="205745">
        <title>Images and additional information</title>
        <uri>http://psi.ch/en/node/39583</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="19">
        <name lang="de">Medien</name>
        <name lang="fr">Médias</name>
        <name lang="it">Media</name>
        <name lang="en">Media</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
