<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="95673" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2023-06-14</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="yes" id="1080" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>701</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Staatssekretariat für Bildung, Forschung und Innovation</name>
      <name lang="fr">Secrétariat d'Etat à la formation, à la recherche et à l'innovation</name>
      <name lang="it">Segreteria di Stato per la formazione, la ricerca e l'innovazione</name>
      <name lang="en">State Secretariat for Education, Research and Innovation</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.sbfi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.sbfi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.sbfi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.sbfi.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@sbfi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@sbfi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@sbfi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@sbfi.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="701">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Wirtschaft, Bildung und Forschung</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'économie, de la formation et de la recherche</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'economia, della formazione e della ricerca</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Economic Affairs, Education and Research</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Die Schweiz und das Vereinigte Königreich unterzeichnen ein Abkommen über die Anerkennung von Berufsqualifikationen</title>
      <lead>Bundesrat Guy Parmelin und die britische Wirtschafts- und Handelsministerin Kemi Badenoch haben am 14. Juni 2023 in London ein Abkommen über die Anerkennung von Berufsqualifikationen unterzeichnet. Für die Schweiz ist dies nach dem Abkommen mit Quebec 2022 das zweite Abkommen über die Anerkennung von Berufsqualifikationen ausserhalb der EU.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Die Schweiz und das Vereinigte Königreich sind im Bereich der Anerkennung von Berufsqualifikationen seit über 20 Jahren verbunden: zuerst über das Freizügigkeitsabkommen (FZA) mit der EU, anschliessend über das Abkommen über die erworbenen Rechte der Bürgerinnen und Bürger (CRA), das ein Übergangssystem bis Ende 2024 vorsieht. Die Schweiz und das Vereinigte Königreich haben nun ein Abkommen ausgehandelt, mit dem ab 2025 ein dauerhafter Rahmen für die gegenseitige Anerkennung von Berufsqualifikationen geschaffen wird. Das Abkommen geht zunächst in die Vernehmlassung und muss 2024 noch vom Parlament ratifiziert werden.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Das Abkommen ermöglicht den Zugang zu reglementierten Berufen in den beiden Ländern und bringt Vorteile für Schweizer Berufsleute und Unternehmen. Diese können im Vereinigten Königreich weiterhin ihre Dienstleistungen anbieten. Das Abkommen sieht zudem für spezifische Berufe günstigere Regeln vor, beispielsweise eine automatische Anerkennung. Dies kann über Absprachen über die gegenseitige Anerkennung (AGA) oder Anhänge zum Abkommen erfolgen. Mit solchen AGA oder Anhängen kann das System mit der Zeit weiter verbessert werden. Das Abkommen enthält bereits einen entsprechenden Anhang für Anwältinnen und Anwälte.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Die Förderung der internationalen Anerkennung von Schweizer Berufsabschlüssen ist eines der Ziele der internationalen Strategie des Bundesrates im Bereich Bildung, Forschung und Innovation (BFI). Um dieses Ziel zu erreichen, braucht es weitere Abkommen über die gegenseitige Anerkennung von Diplomen mit Ländern, deren Bildungssystem mit jenem der Schweiz vergleichbar ist. Das Vereinigte Königreich ist ein idealer Partner, da es sich wie die Schweiz durch ein renommiertes Bildungssystem auszeichnet.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Der Bundesrat hatte das Eidgenössische Departement für Wirtschaft, Bildung und Forschung (WBF) am 9. Juni 2023 ermächtigt, das Abkommen mit dem Vereinigten Königreich zu unterzeichnen. Gleichzeitig beschloss er, für das Abkommen und damit verbundene Gesetzesanpassungen eine Vernehmlassung zu eröffnen. Das Vernehmlassungsverfahren dauert bis zum 6. Oktober 2023.&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Kommunikationsdienst GS-WBF info@gs-wbf.admin.ch +41 58 462 20 07</contact>
      <link id="253385">
        <title>Link zu Vernehmlassungsunterlagen</title>
        <uri>https://www.sbfi.admin.ch/sbfi/de/home/aktuell/vernehmlassungen.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>La Suisse et le Royaume-Uni signent un accord sur la reconnaissance des qualifications professionnelles</title>
      <lead>Le Conseiller fédéral Guy Parmelin et Kemi Badenoch, Secrétaire d'État aux Affaires et au Commerce, ont signé le 14 juin 2023 à Londres un accord sur la reconnaissance des qualifications professionnelles. Pour la Suisse, il s’agit du deuxième accord sur la reconnaissance des qualifications professionnelles à être signé avec un territoire en dehors de l'UE, après celui conclu avec le Québec en 2022. </lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Pendant plus de vingt ans, la Suisse et le Royaume-Uni ont été liés, en matière de reconnaissance des qualifications professionnelles, par l'Accord sur la libre circulation des personnes (ALCP) avec l'UE, puis par l'Accord sur les droits acquis des citoyens (CRA), qui prévoit un système transitoire en la matière jusqu'à fin 2024. Afin de définir leur relation future en matière de reconnaissance des qualifications professionnelles, la Suisse et le Royaume-Uni ont dès lors négocié un accord destiné à offrir un cadre permanent à la reconnaissance de leurs qualifications professionnelles à partir de 2025. Cet accord, désormais soumis à une consultation publique, devra encore être ratifié par l'Assemblée fédérale l'année prochaine.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;L'accord permet l'accès aux professions réglementées dans les deux pays et offrira un avantage aux professionnels et entreprises suisses, qui pourront continuer à offrir leurs services au Royaume-Uni. L'accord prévoit aussi la possibilité de prévoir des règles plus favorables spécifiques à une profession, par exemple une reconnaissance automatique, par la conclusion d'Arrangements de reconnaissance mutuelle (ARM) ou par l'ajout d'annexes à l'accord. Ces futurs ARM ou annexes permettront une amélioration du système au fil du temps. L'accord prévoit d'ailleurs déjà une annexe spéciale pour les avocats.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;L'encouragement de la reconnaissance internationale des diplômes suisses est l'un des objectifs de la stratégie internationale du Conseil fédéral dans le domaine de la formation, de la recherche et de l'innovation. La réalisation de cet objectif doit notamment passer par l'extension des accords prévoyant la reconnaissance mutuelle des diplômes avec des pays dotés de systèmes de formation comparables.&lt;b&gt; &lt;/b&gt;Le Royaume-Uni représente un partenaire idéal puisqu'il partage avec notre pays la même excellence en matière de formation.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Lors de sa séance du 9 juin 2023, le Conseil fédéral avait autorisé le DEFR à signer l'accord avec le Royaume-Uni. Dans le même temps, il a lancé une procédure de consultation concernant l'accord et les adaptations légales qui y sont liées. La procédure de consultation dure jusqu'au 6 octobre 2023.&lt;b&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Service de communication SG-DEFR info@gs-wbf.admin.ch +41 58 462 20 07</contact>
      <link id="253386">
        <title>Lien vers les documents de la procédure de consultation</title>
        <uri>https://www.sbfi.admin.ch/sbfi/fr/home/actualite/consultations.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Svizzera e Regno Unito siglano un accordo sul riconoscimento delle qualifiche professionali</title>
      <lead>Il 14 giugno 2023 il consigliere federale Guy Parmelin e la ministra britannica dell’Economia e del Commercio Kemi Badenoch hanno firmato a Londra un Accordo sul riconoscimento delle qualifiche professionali. Per la Svizzera si tratta del secondo accordo di questo tipo con un Paese o territorio al di fuori dell’UE, dopo quello con il Québec del 2022.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Per quanto riguarda il riconoscimento delle qualifiche professionali, la Svizzera e il Regno Unito intrattengono rapporti contrattuali da oltre 20 anni. Prima in virtù dell'Accordo sulla libera circolazione delle persone (ALCP) con l'UE e poi dell'Accordo sui diritti acquisiti dei cittadini (&lt;i&gt;Citizens' Rights Agreement&lt;/i&gt;; CRA), che prevede un regime transitorio fino alla fine del 2024. Per disciplinare le loro future relazioni nell'ambito del riconoscimento delle qualifiche professionali, i due Paesi hanno ora siglato un nuovo Accordo che instaura un regime permanente per il riconoscimento reciproco delle qualifiche professionali a partire dal 2025. Il testo sarà presto sottoposto a consultazione e dovrà essere ratificato dall'Assemblea federale nel 2024.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;L'Accordo consente l'accesso alle professioni regolamentate in entrambi i Paesi e comporta vantaggi tanto per i professionisti quanto per le aziende svizzere. Queste ultime potranno infatti continuare a offrire i loro servizi nel Regno Unito. Per alcune professioni l'Accordo prevede inoltre norme più favorevoli, ad esempio il riconoscimento automatico attraverso accordi sul riconoscimento reciproco (ARR) separati o allegati aggiuntivi all'Accordo in questione. Questi due strumenti permetteranno di migliorare il sistema con il passare del tempo. Del resto, il presente Accordo prevede già un allegato speciale per la professione di avvocato.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Promuovere il riconoscimento internazionale delle qualifiche professionali svizzere rientra negli obiettivi della strategia internazionale del Consiglio federale nel campo della formazione, della ricerca e dell'innovazione. Per realizzarlo ci vogliono soprattutto ulteriori accordi sul riconoscimento reciproco dei diplomi con Paesi che vantano un sistema formativo paragonabile a quello svizzero. Il Regno Unito è quindi un partner ideale perché dotato di un sistema formativo di prim'ordine.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Nella riunione del 9 giugno 2023, il Consiglio federale ha autorizzato il Dipartimento federale dell'economia, della formazione e della ricerca (DEFR) a firmare l'Accordo con il Regno Unito. Nel contempo ha deciso di sottoporlo a una procedura di consultazione, comprese le relative modifiche di legge. La consultazione si concluderà il 6 ottobre 2023.&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Comunicazione SG-DEFR info@gs-wbf.admin.ch +41 58 462 20 07</contact>
      <link id="253387">
        <title>Link consultazioni</title>
        <uri>https://www.sbfi.admin.ch/sbfi/it/home/attualita/consultazioni.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Switzerland and United Kingdom sign agreement on mutual recognition of professional qualifications</title>
      <lead>Meeting in London on 14 June 2023, Federal Councillor Guy Parmelin and British Secretary of State for Business and Trade Kemi Badenoch signed an agreement on the mutual recognition of professional qualifications. For Switzerland, this is the second such agreement signed with a partner outside the EU, the first one being the agreement signed with Quebec in 2022.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Cooperation between Switzerland and the United Kingdom on the mutual recognition of professional qualifications began over twenty years ago. Initially, there was the Swiss-EU Agreement on the Free Movement of Persons (AFMP). After the United Kingdom withdrew from the European Union and by extension from the AFMP, Switzerland and the United Kingdom took steps to safeguard the rights of their respective citizens. The resulting Swiss-UK bilateral agreement provided for a transitional period up to the end of 2024. In order to establish a solid basis for the mutual recognition of professional qualifications from 2025 onwards, Switzerland and the United Kingdom have now entered into a new agreement, which will soon be opened for consultation. The Swiss Parliament still needs to ratify the agreement, which is expected to occur sometime in 2024.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The agreement enables citizens of both countries to take up employment in regulated professional activities. Swiss professionals and companies benefit from the agreement as it will enable them to continue offering their services in the United Kingdom. For specific professions, special privileges (e.g. automatic recognition) can be established either through mutual recognition arrangements (MRAs) or by adding annexes to the current agreement. These two options provide the contracting parties with the necessary means to adapt the system over time as needed. The agreement already contains specific provisions covering lawyers.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Encouraging the international recognition of Swiss professional qualifications is one of the stated objectives of the Federal Council's international strategy for education, research and innovation. In order to reach this objective, additional mutual recognition agreements are needed to cover qualifications awarded in countries whose education system is comparable to Switzerland's. The United Kingdom is an ideal partner for Switzerland as both countries have an outstanding education system.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;At its meeting on 9 June 2023, the Federal Council authorised the Federal Department of Economic Affairs, Education and Research (EAER) to sign the bilateral agreement with the United Kingdom. It also decided to initiate consultation for this agreement and proposed legislative amendments. The consultation round will continue until 6 October 2023.&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>GS-EAER Communication Service info@gs-wbf.admin.ch +41 58 462 20 07</contact>
      <link id="253388">
        <title>Link to consultation documents</title>
        <uri>https://www.sbfi.admin.ch/sbfi/de/home/aktuell/vernehmlassungen.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="2">
        <name lang="de">Arbeit</name>
        <name lang="fr">Travail</name>
        <name lang="it">Lavoro</name>
        <name lang="en">Labour</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="8">
        <name lang="de">Bildung und Forschung</name>
        <name lang="fr">Formation et recherche</name>
        <name lang="it">Formazione e ricerca</name>
        <name lang="en">Education and Research</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="10">
        <name lang="de">Bundesrat</name>
        <name lang="fr">Conseil fédéral</name>
        <name lang="it">Consiglio federale</name>
        <name lang="en">Federal Council</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="45">
        <name lang="de">Technologie</name>
        <name lang="fr">Technologie</name>
        <name lang="it">Tecnologia</name>
        <name lang="en">Technology</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="47">
        <name lang="de">Wirtschaft</name>
        <name lang="fr">Économie</name>
        <name lang="it">Economia</name>
        <name lang="en">Economic Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
