<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="82373" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2021-02-19</pubdate>
    <blocking-period>2021-02-19</blocking-period>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="318" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>301</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Bundesamt für Statistik</name>
      <name lang="fr">Office fédéral de la statistique</name>
      <name lang="it">Ufficio federale di statistica</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Statistical Office</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.statistik.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.statistique.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.statistica.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.statistics.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@bfs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@bfs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@bfs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@bfs.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="301">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement des Innern</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'intérieur</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'interno</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Home Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Neuchâtel</city>
      <title>Die Schweizer Logiernächte sind 2020 auf einen historischen Tiefstand gesunken</title>
      <lead>2020 verzeichnete die Schweizer Hotellerie 23,7 Millionen Logiernächte. Im Vergleich zu 2019 entspricht dies einer Abnahme um 40,0% (–15,8 Millionen). Grund für diesen Einbruch ist die ausserordentliche Lage im Zusammenhang mit Covid-19. So tief waren die Werte zuletzt Ende der 1950er-Jahren gewesen. Die ausländische Nachfrage sank um 66,1% (–14,3 Millionen) auf 7,3 Millionen Logiernächte. Bei den Schweizer Gästen fiel der Rückgang weniger drastisch aus. Sie generierten 16,4 Millionen Logiernächte (–8,6%/–1,5 Millionen). Soweit einige der definitiven Ergebnisse des Bundesamtes für Statistik (BFS).</lead>
      <text link="no">Diese Medienmitteilung und weitere Informationen zum Thema finden Sie auf der Website des BFS (siehe Link unten)</text>
      <contact>Vincenzo Carelli, BFS, Sektion Tourismus, Tel.: +41 58 463 62 80, E-Mail: Info-Tour@bfs.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="212372">
        <title>Kompletter Text und Mediendossier</title>
        <uri>https://www.bfs.admin.ch/news/de/2021-0290</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Neuchâtel</city>
      <title>Chute historique des nuitées hôtelières en Suisse en 2020</title>
      <lead>En 2020, l’hôtellerie en Suisse a comptabilisé 23,7 millions de nuitées. Ceci représente une baisse de 40,0% (–15,8 millions de nuitées) par rapport à 2019. Le contexte exceptionnel du COVID–19 explique cette chute inédite à un niveau qui n’avait plus été observé depuis la fin des années cinquante. La demande étrangère a totalisé 7,3 millions de nuitées, soit une baisse de 66,1% (–14,3 millions). De son côté, la demande suisse a diminué moins drastiquement (–8,6%/–1,5 million) à 16,4 millions de nuitées. Tels sont les résultats définitifs de l’Office fédéral de la statistique (OFS). </lead>
      <text link="no">Vous trouverez ce communiqué de presse et d'autres informations sur ce thème sur le site web de l'OFS (voir le lien ci-dessous)</text>
      <contact>Vincenzo Carelli, OFS, Vincenzo Carelli, tél.: +41 58 463 62 80, e-mail: Info-Tour@bfs.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="212373">
        <title>Texte intégral et dossier de presse</title>
        <uri>https://www.bfs.admin.ch/news/fr/2021-0290</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Neuchâtel</city>
      <title>Crollo storico dei pernottamenti in strutture alberghiere in Svizzera nel 2020</title>
      <lead>Nel 2020 il settore alberghiero svizzero ha contabilizzato 23,7 milioni di pernottamenti, pari al 40,0% in meno (–15,8 milioni di unità) rispetto al 2019. Il contesto straordinario della COVID-19 è alla base di questo crollo inedito a livelli che non erano stati osservati sin dalla fine degli Anni ‘50. La domanda straniera ha totalizzato 7,3 milioni di pernottamenti, registrando un calo del 66,1% (–14,3 milioni di unità). La domanda svizzera, dal canto suo, è calata meno drasticamente (–8,6%; –1,5 milioni) a 16,4 milioni di pernottamenti. Ecco quanto emerge dai risultati definitivi dell’Ufficio federale di statistica (UST).</lead>
      <text link="no">Il presente comunicato stampa e ulteriori informazioni sul tema sono reperibili sulla pagina Internet dell'UST (link sotto)</text>
      <contact>Vincenzo Carelli, UST, Sezione Turismo, tel.: +41 58 463 62 80, e-mail: Info-Tour@bfs.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="212374">
        <title>Testo integrale e dossier per i media</title>
        <uri>https://www.bfs.admin.ch/news/it/2021-0290</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Neuchâtel</city>
      <title>Record drop in overnight hotel stays in Switzerland in 2020</title>
      <lead>In 2020, the Swiss hotel sector registered 23.7 million overnight stays. This represents a fall of 40.0% (-15.8 million overnight stays) compared with 2019. The exceptional context of COVID–19 explains this unprecedented fall at a level not seen since the end of the 1950s. Foreign demand registered 7.3 million overnight stays, i.e. a decline of 66.1% (–14.3 million). Swiss demand fell less drastically (–8.6%/–1.5 million) to 16.4 million overnight stays. These are the final results from the Federal Statistical Office (FSO).</lead>
      <text link="no">This press release and further information on this topic can be found on the FSO website (see link below)</text>
      <contact>Vincenzo Carelli, FSO, Tourism section, tel.: +41 58 463 62 80, email: Info-Tour@bfs.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="212375">
        <title>Complete text and press kit</title>
        <uri>https://www.bfs.admin.ch/news/en/2021-0290</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <keywords>
      <keyword id="317.11" org-id="318">
        <name lang="de">Tourismus</name>
        <name lang="fr">Tourisme</name>
        <name lang="it">Turismo</name>
        <name lang="en">Tourism</name>
      </keyword>
    </keywords>
    <topics>
      <topic id="27">
        <name lang="de">Reisen und Tourismus</name>
        <name lang="fr">Voyages et tourisme</name>
        <name lang="it">Viaggi e turismo</name>
        <name lang="en">Travel and Tourism</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="43">
        <name lang="de">Statistik</name>
        <name lang="fr">Statistiques</name>
        <name lang="it">Statistica</name>
        <name lang="en">Statistics</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
