<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="82225" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2021-02-04</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="703" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>701</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Staatssekretariat für Wirtschaft</name>
      <name lang="fr">Secrétariat d'Etat à l'économie</name>
      <name lang="it">Segreteria di Stato dell'economia</name>
      <name lang="en">State Secretariat for Economic Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.seco.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.seco.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.seco.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.seco.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@seco.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@seco.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@seco.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@seco.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="701">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Wirtschaft, Bildung und Forschung</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'économie, de la formation et de la recherche</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'economia, della formazione e della ricerca</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Economic Affairs, Education and Research</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Konsumentenstimmung verschlechtert sich leicht</title>
      <lead>Die Stimmung der Schweizer Haushalte bleibt im Januar eingetrübt. Gegenüber Oktober haben sich insbesondere ihre Erwartungen etwas verschlechtert. Sämtliche Teilindizes liegen weiterhin deutlich unter dem langfristigen Mittelwert. </lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Der Index der Konsumentenstimmung liegt im Januar 2021 bei −15 Punkten und verharrt damit deutlich unter seinem langjährigen Mittelwert (−5 Punkte). Im Vergleich zur Umfrage von Oktober (−13 Punkte) hat sich die Stimmung leicht verschlechtert.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Spürbar pessimistischer im Vergleich zur Erhebung von Oktober fielen insbesondere die Erwartungen für die allgemeine Wirtschaftsentwicklung aus. Nach einer leichten Erholung im Oktober (−14 Punkte) sank der entsprechende Teilindex auf −19 Punkte. Dies steht im Einklang mit der fortdauernd negativen Arbeitsmarkteinschätzung der Konsumentinnen und Konsumenten: Auf bereits ausserordentlich hohem Niveau stieg der Index zur erwarteten Entwicklung der Arbeitslosigkeit abermals leicht an (115 Punkte), und die Sicherheit der Arbeitsplätze wird ähnlich schlecht eingeschätzt wie in der vorangegangenen Erhebung (−123 Punkte). Insgesamt deuten diese Ergebnisse auf eine schwache Entwicklung der Konjunktur in naher Zukunft hin. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Angespannt bleibt auch die Budgetsituation der Befragten. Während der Index zur finanziellen Lage in den vergangenen zwölf Monaten etwas anstieg (−12 Punkte), verschlechterten sich die Erwartungen für die eigene finanzielle Lage (−7 Punkte) erneut leicht. Wenig überraschend bleibt daher auch die Neigung zu grösseren Anschaffungen auf einem unterdurchschnittlichen Niveau. Der entsprechende Teilindex liegt bei −20 Punkten. Dies lässt eine schwache Entwicklung der privaten Konsumausgaben erwarten.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Staatssekretariat für Wirtschaft SECO Holzikofenweg 36 CH-3003 Bern Tel. +41 58 462 56 56 Fax +41 58 462 56 00</contact>
      <attachment id="211848">
        <title>Medienmitteilung und Grafiken</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>345</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/65153.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Le climat de consommation se dégrade légèrement</title>
      <lead>Le moral des ménages suisses est resté en berne en janvier. Leurs attentes, en particulier, se sont quelque peu détériorées par rapport au mois d’octobre. Tous les sous-indices demeurent bien en deçà de leur moyenne à long terme.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;L’indice du climat de consommation s’inscrit à −15 points en janvier 2021, un résultat nettement en dessous de sa moyenne pluriannuelle (−5 points). Le moral des consommateurs est un peu moins bon que lors de l’enquête d’octobre (−13 points).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Les attentes concernant l’évolution de l’économie dans son ensemble, en particulier, étaient nettement plus pessimistes que dans l’enquête d’octobre. Après une légère embellie en octobre (−14 points), le sous-indice en question a reculé à −19 points. Ceci est en accord avec l’évaluation toujours négative que les consommateurs font du marché du travail : partant d’un niveau déjà très élevé, l’indice de l’évolution attendue du chômage a de nouveau légèrement augmenté (115 points), et l’appréciation de la sécurité de l’emploi est restée autant mauvaise que dans l’enquête précédente (−123 points). Dans l’ensemble, ces résultats indiquent une faible évolution de la conjoncture dans un futur proche.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;La situation financière des personnes interrogées reste elle aussi tendue. Alors que le sous-indice relatif à la situation financière au cours des douze derniers mois a quelque peu progressé (−12 points), les attentes des ménages concernant l’évolution future de leur propre situation financière se sont à nouveau légèrement détériorées (−7 points). Sans surprise, la propension aux grandes acquisitions demeure inférieure à la moyenne, le sous-indice en question s’établissant à −20 points. Tous ces éléments laissent augurer une évolution peu sou-tenue des dépenses de consommation privées.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Secrétariat d'Etat à l'économie SECO Holzikofenweg 36 CH-3003 Berne tél. +41 58 462 56 56 fax +41 58 462 56 00</contact>
      <attachment id="211849">
        <title>Communiqué de presse et graphiques</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>342</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/65154.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Lieve peggioramento della fiducia dei consumatori</title>
      <lead>Il clima di fiducia delle economie domestiche svizzere resta cupo a gennaio. Rispetto a ottobre si nota un lieve peggioramento, soprattutto delle loro aspettative. Tutti i sottoindici rimangono ben al di sotto della media a lungo termine. </lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Nel primo mese del 2021 il clima di fiducia dei consumatori registra -15 punti e rimane quindi ben al di sotto della sua media a lungo termine (-5 punti). Rispetto al sondaggio di ottobre (−13 punti) il clima di fiducia è leggermente peggiorato.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sono risultate molto più pessimistiche rispetto al rilevamento di ottobre soprattutto le aspettative riguardo all’andamento economico generale. Dopo una lieve ripresa a ottobre (−14 punti), il sottoindice in questione è sceso a −19 punti. Ciò è in linea con la valutazione tuttora negativa del mercato del lavoro da parte dei consumatori: a un livello già straordinariamente alto, l’indice per l’andamento previsto della disoccupazione ha registrato un ulteriore incremento, anche se lieve (115 punti), e la sicurezza degli impieghi è valutata in modo negativo come nel sondaggio precedente (-123 punti). Nel complesso questi dati indicano un debole sviluppo congiunturale per l’immediato futuro.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Permane tensione anche per quanto riguarda le finanze degli intervistati. Mentre l’indice relativo alla situazione finanziaria è aumentato di poco negli ultimi dodici mesi (-12 punti), le aspettative per la propria situazione finanziaria (-7 punti) sono di nuovo leggermente peggiorate. Non stupisce pertanto che anche la propensione a effettuare acquisti importanti rimanga al di sotto della media. Il sottoindice corrispondente indica -20 punti, un valore che lascia presupporre uno scarso sviluppo dei consumi privati.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Segreteria di Stato dell'economia SECO Holzikofenweg 36 CH-3003 Berna tel. +41 58 462 56 56 fax +41 58 462 56 00</contact>
      <attachment id="211850">
        <title>Comunicato stampa e grafici</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>334</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/65155.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Consumer sentiment deteriorates slightly</title>
      <lead>Figures for January show that the sentiment remains gloomy among Swiss households. Their expectations have taken a particular downturn when compared to October. All sub-indices are still well below their long-term average. </lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;As of January 2021, the consumer sentiment index stands at –15 points, remaining far below its long-term average (−5 points). Sentiment has worsened slightly in comparison with October’s survey (–13 points).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Expectations regarding general economic development, in particular, were decidedly more pessimistic than in October’s survey. The relevant sub-index has fallen to –19 points, which contrasts with the slight recovery it enjoyed in October (–14 points). This is in line with consumers’ enduring negative assessment of the labour market; having already reached an extraordinarily high level, the index on the expected development of unemployment has once again risen slightly (115 points), while the respondents’ assessment of job security remains at a similar negative level to the previous survey (–123 points). Overall, these results point to weak economic development in the near future. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The budget situation of those surveyed also remains troubled. While the index on the financial situation in the last twelve months has increased somewhat (–12 points), the surveyed households’ expectations regarding their own financial situation has once again decreased slightly (–7 points). It should therefore be unsurprising that the likelihood of consumers making major purchases also remains below average, with the relevant sub-index standing at –20 points. A weak level of development in private consumption is to be expected as a result.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>State Secretariat for Economic Affairs SECO Holzikofenweg 36 CH-3003 Bern Tel. +41 58 462 56 56 Fax +41 58 462 56 00</contact>
      <attachment id="211851">
        <title>Press release and graphs</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>254</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/65156.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <offers>
      <offer id="156" org-id="703">
        <name lang="de">BIP-Quartalsdaten und Konjunkturtendenzen</name>
        <name lang="fr">Données trimestrielles PIB et tendances conjoncturelles</name>
        <name lang="it">Tendenze congiunturali</name>
        <name lang="en">Quarterly data on GDP and economic trends</name>
      </offer>
    </offers>
    <topics>
      <topic id="37">
        <name lang="de">Konsum</name>
        <name lang="fr">Consommation</name>
        <name lang="it">Consumo</name>
        <name lang="en">Consumer Affairs</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="43">
        <name lang="de">Statistik</name>
        <name lang="fr">Statistiques</name>
        <name lang="it">Statistica</name>
        <name lang="en">Statistics</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="47">
        <name lang="de">Wirtschaft</name>
        <name lang="fr">Économie</name>
        <name lang="it">Economia</name>
        <name lang="en">Economic Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
