<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="82445" revoked="no">
    <version>4</version>
    <pubdate>2021-02-26</pubdate>
    <blocking-period>2021-02-26</blocking-period>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="318" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>301</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Bundesamt für Statistik</name>
      <name lang="fr">Office fédéral de la statistique</name>
      <name lang="it">Ufficio federale di statistica</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Statistical Office</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.statistik.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.statistique.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.statistica.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.statistics.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@bfs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@bfs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@bfs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@bfs.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="301">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement des Innern</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'intérieur</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'interno</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Home Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Neuchâtel</city>
      <title>Beschäftigung in der Schweiz sinkt im 4. Quartal 2020 zum dritten Mal in Folge</title>
      <lead>Im 4. Quartal 2020 ist die Gesamtbeschäftigung (Anzahl Stellen) im Vergleich zum Vorjahresquartal um 0,3% gefallen (+0,2% zum Vorquartal). Bei den Frauen betrug der Rückgang 0,4% während die Beschäftigung bei den Männern um 0,3% zurückging. In Vollzeitäquivalenten sank die Beschäftigung im selben Zeitraum ebenfalls um 0,3%. In der gesamten Wirtschaft wurden 12 600 offene Stellen weniger gezählt als im entsprechenden Vorjahresquartal (–16,1%) und der Indikator der Beschäftigungsaussichten zeigt nach unten (–2,4%). Dies geht aus den neuesten Zahlen des Bundesamtes für Statistik (BFS) hervor.</lead>
      <text link="no">Diese Medienmitteilung und weitere Informationen zum Thema finden Sie auf der Website des BFS (siehe Link unten).</text>
      <contact>Francis Saucy, BFS, Sektion Konjunkturerhebungen, Tel.: +41 58 463 63 63, E-Mail: diffusion.besta@bfs.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="213256">
        <title>Kompletter Text und Mediendossier</title>
        <uri>https://www.bfs.admin.ch/news/de/2021-0060</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions>
        <revision date="2021-02-26 08:30" type="I"/>
        <revision date="2021-02-26 08:30" type="I"/>
        <revision date="2021-02-26 08:30" type="I"/>
      </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Neuchâtel</city>
      <title>Troisième baisse consécutive de l’emploi en Suisse au 4e trimestre 2020</title>
      <lead>Au 4e trimestre 2020, l’emploi total (nombre de postes occupés) a diminué de 0,3% par rapport au trimestre correspondant de l’année précédente (+0,2% par rapport au trimestre précédent). Le recul était de 0,4% chez les femmes et de 0,3% chez les hommes. En équivalents plein temps, l'emploi a diminué de 0,3% pendant la période sous revue. L’économie totale offrait 12 600 places vacantes de moins qu’au 4e trimestre 2019 (–16,1%) et l’indicateur des prévisions d’évolution de l’emploi était en baisse (–2,4%). Tels sont les derniers chiffres établis par l’Office fédéral de la statistique (OFS).</lead>
      <text link="no">Vous trouverez ce communiqué de presse et d'autres informations sur ce thème sur le site web de l'OFS (cf. lien ci-dessous).</text>
      <contact>Francis Saucy, OFS, section Enquêtes conjoncturelles, tél.: +41 58 463 63 63, e-mail: diffusion.besta@bfs.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="213257">
        <title>Texte intégral et dossier de presse</title>
        <uri>https://www.bfs.admin.ch/news/fr/2021-0060</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions>
        <revision date="2021-02-26 08:30" type="I"/>
        <revision date="2021-02-26 08:30" type="I"/>
        <revision date="2021-02-26 08:30" type="I"/>
      </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Neuchâtel</city>
      <title>Occupazione in calo per la terza volta consecutiva nel quarto trimestre 2020</title>
      <lead>Nel quarto trimestre 2020 l’occupazione complessiva (numero di posti) è calata dello 0,3% rispetto allo stesso trimestre dell’anno precedente (+0,2% rispetto al trimestre precedente). L’occupazione femminile ha segnato una flessione dello 0,4%, mentre quella maschile dello 0,3%. Nello stesso periodo, anche le cifre occupazionali convertite in equivalenti a tempo pieno sono diminuite dello 0,3%. Sulla piazza economica svizzera sono stati contati 12 600 posti liberi in meno rispetto allo stesso trimestre dell’anno precedente (–16,1%), e l’indicatore delle prospettive d’impiego tende al ribasso (–2,4%). Questo è quanto emerge dagli ultimi risultati dell’Ufficio federale di statistica (UST).</lead>
      <text link="no">Il presente comunicato stampa e ulteriori informazioni sul tema sono reperibili sulla pagina Internet dell'UST (link sotto).</text>
      <contact>Francis Saucy, UST, sezione Indagini congiunturali, tel.: +41 58 463 63 63, e-mail: diffusion.besta@bfs.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="213258">
        <title>Testo integrale e dossier per i media</title>
        <uri>https://www.bfs.admin.ch/news/it/2021-0060</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions>
        <revision date="2021-02-26 08:30" type="I"/>
        <revision date="2021-02-26 08:30" type="I"/>
        <revision date="2021-02-26 08:30" type="I"/>
      </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Neuchâtel</city>
      <title>Employment in Switzerland fell in 4th quarter 2020 for the third consecutive time</title>
      <lead>In the 4th quarter 2020, the total employment (number of jobs) fell by 0.3% in comparison with the same quarter a year earlier (+0.2% with previous quarter). Among women, the decrease was 0.4%, while employment among men fell by 0.3%. In full-time equivalents, employment in the same period declined also by 0.3%. The Swiss economy counted 12 600 fewer vacancies than in the corresponding quarter of the previous year (-16.1%) with the employment outlook indicator indicating a downward trend (-2.4%). These are some of the latest findings from the Federal Statistical Office (FSO).</lead>
      <text link="no">This press release and further information on this topic can be found on the FSO website (see link below).</text>
      <contact>Francis Saucy, FSO, Economic Surveys section, tel: +41 58 463 63 63, email: diffusion.besta@bfs.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="213259">
        <title>Complete text and press kit - Please note that the English version only includes the release's lead</title>
        <uri>https://www.bfs.admin.ch/news/en/2021-0060</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions>
        <revision date="2021-02-26 08:30" type="I"/>
        <revision date="2021-02-26 08:30" type="I"/>
        <revision date="2021-02-26 08:30" type="I"/>
      </revisions>
    </content>
    <keywords>
      <keyword id="317.7" org-id="318">
        <name lang="de">Industrie und Dienstleistungen</name>
        <name lang="fr">Industrie et services</name>
        <name lang="it">Industria e servizi</name>
        <name lang="en">Industry and services</name>
      </keyword>
    </keywords>
    <topics>
      <topic id="2">
        <name lang="de">Arbeit</name>
        <name lang="fr">Travail</name>
        <name lang="it">Lavoro</name>
        <name lang="en">Labour</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="43">
        <name lang="de">Statistik</name>
        <name lang="fr">Statistiques</name>
        <name lang="it">Statistica</name>
        <name lang="en">Statistics</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="47">
        <name lang="de">Wirtschaft</name>
        <name lang="fr">Économie</name>
        <name lang="it">Economia</name>
        <name lang="en">Economic Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
