<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="39359" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2011-05-27</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="201" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>201</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="201">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Bundespräsidentin Micheline Calmy-Rey in Georgien</title>
      <lead>Bundespräsidentin Micheline Calmy-Rey, Vorsteherin des Eidgenössischen Departements für auswärtige Angelegenheiten EDA, wird sich am 29. und 30. Mai 2011 zu einem offiziellen Besuch in Georgien aufhalten.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Auf Einladung Georgiens wird Bundespräsidentin Micheline Calmy-Rey dieses Wochenende zu einem offiziellen Besuch in Tiflis eintreffen. Auf dem Programm stehen unter anderem Gespräche mit dem georgischen Präsidenten Mikheil Saakasvihili und Aussenminister Grigol Vashadze. Zudem sind Treffen mit Premierminister Nika Gilauri und David Bakradze, dem Vorsitzenden des georgischen Parlaments, vorgesehen.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Vor genau zehn Jahren eröffnete die Schweiz ihre Botschaft in Georgien, das sich 1991 unabhängig erklärte. Die Schweiz unterhält in Georgien verschiedene Projekte der technischen und wirtschaftlichen Zusammenarbeit, namentlich im Bereich der ländlichen Entwicklung.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Seit 2009 vertritt die Schweiz die diplomatischen Interessen von Georgien in Moskau sowie die diplomatischen Interessen der Russischen Föderation in Tiflis. Die Schweiz hat diese Schutzmachtmandate auf Anfrage der beiden Staaten übernommen.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Information EDA Bundeshaus West CH-3003 Bern Tel.: +41 (0)31 322 31 53 Fax: +41 (0)31 324 90 47 E-Mail: info@eda.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="83937">
        <title>Informationen zu den bilateralen Beziehungen Schweiz-Georgien</title>
        <uri>http://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home/reps/eur/vgeo/bilgeo.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="83938">
        <title>Informationen zur Transitionshilfe der Schweiz im Südkaukasus</title>
        <uri>http://www.deza.admin.ch/de/Home/Laender/Gemeinschaft_Unabhaengiger_Staaten_GUS/Suedkaukasus_Georgien_Armenien_Aserbeidschan</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Visite de Madame Micheline Calmy-Rey, présidente de la Confédération, en Géorgie</title>
      <lead>La présidente de la Confédération Micheline Calmy-Rey, cheffe du Département fédéral des affaires étrangères DFAE, sera en Géorgie les 29 et 30 mai pour une visite officielle.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Sur invitation de la Géorgie, la présidente de la Confédération Micheline Calmy-Rey se rendra à Tiflis ce week-end dans le cadre d'une visite officielle. Elle y rencontrera le président géorgien Mikheïl Saakachvili ainsi que le ministre des affaires étrangères&amp;nbsp;Grigol Vashadze, avec lesquels des entretiens sont prévus. Deux autres rencontres, respectivement avec le premier ministre Nika Gilauri et avec le président du Parlement géorgien David Bakradze, figurent au programme de cette visite.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;En 1991, il y a tout juste dix ans, la Suisse ouvrait une ambassade en Géorgie, alors que cet Etat proclamait son indépendance. Elle gère sur place différents projets de coopération technique et économique, notamment dans le domaine du développement rural.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Depuis 2009, la Suisse défend les intérêts diplomatiques de la Géorgie à Moscou ainsi que les intérêts diplomatiques de la Fédération de Russie à&amp;nbsp;Tiflis. Elle exerce ces mandats de puissance protectrice à la demande des deux pays.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Information DFAE Palais fédéral ouest CH-3003 Berne Tél.: (+41) 031 322 31 53 Fax: (+41) 031 324 90 47 E-Mail: info@eda.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="83939">
        <title>Informations sur les relations bilatérales entre la Suisse et la Géorgie</title>
        <uri>http://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/home/reps/eur/vgeo/bilgeo.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="83940">
        <title>Informations relatives à l'aide à la transition apportée par la Suisse dans le Caucase du Sud</title>
        <uri>http://www.deza.admin.ch/fr/Accueil/Pays/Communaute_des_Etats_independants_CEI/Caucase_du_Sud_Georgie_Armenie_Azerbaidjan</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>La presidente della Confederazione Micheline Calmy-Rey in Georgia</title>
      <lead>La presidente della Confederazione Micheline Calmy-Rey, capo del Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri DFAE, si recherà in visita ufficiale in Georgia dal 29 al 30 maggio 2011.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Su invito della Georgia, la presidente della Confederazione Micheline Calmy-Rey si recherà questo fine settimana in visita ufficiale a Tbilisi. In programma vi sono tra l'altro colloqui con il presidente georgiano Mikheil Saakasvihili e il ministro degli esteri Grigol Vashadze. Inoltre, sono previsti incontri con il primo ministro Nika Gilauri e con il presidente del Parlamento georgiano David Bakradze.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Proprio dieci anni fa la Svizzera ha aperto la sua ambasciata in Georgia, diventata indipendente nel 1991. La Svizzera sostiene in Georgia diversi progetti della cooperazione tecnica ed economica, in particolare nell’ambito dello sviluppo rurale.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Dal 2009 la Svizzera rappresenta gli interessi diplomatici della Georgia a Mosca e gli interessi diplomatici della Federazione russa a Tbilisi. La Svizzera si assume questo mandato in qualità di potenza protettrice su richiesta di entrambi gli Stati.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Informazione DFAE Palazzo federale ovest CH-3003 Berna Tel.: (+41) 031 322 31 53 Fax: (+41) 031 324 90 47 E-Mail: info@eda.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="83941">
        <title>Informazioni sulle relazioni bilaterali tra la Svizzera e la Georgia</title>
        <uri>http://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/home/reps/eur/vgeo/bilgeo.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="83942">
        <title>Informazioni sull'aiuto alla transizione della Svizzera nel Caucaso meridionale</title>
        <uri>http://www.deza.admin.ch/it/Pagina_iniziale/Paesi/Comunita_di_Stati_Indipendenti_CSI/Caucaso_meridionale_Georgia_Armenia_Azerbaigian</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Official visit to Georgia by President of the Confederation Micheline Calmy-Rey</title>
      <lead>President of the Swiss Confederation Micheline Calmy-Rey, head of the Federal Department of Foreign Affairs (FDFA), will pay an official visit to Georgia on 29 and 30 May 2011.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;President of the Swiss Confederation Micheline Calmy-Rey will pay an offical visit to the Georgian capital Tbilisi this weekend. She will hold talks with Georgian President Mikheil Saakasvihili and Foreign Minister Grigol Vashadze. Meetings are also planned with Prime Minister Nika Gilauri and with David Bakradze, the Speaker of the Georgian Parliament.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Ten years ago Switzerland opened its embassy in Georgia, which declared its independence in 1991. Switzerland runs a number of technical and economic cooperation projects in Georgia, notably in the area of agrarian development.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Since 2009 Switzerland has represented Georgia‘s diplomatic interests in Moscow and the diplomatic interests of the Russian Federation in Tbilisi. Switzerland accepted these protecting power mandates at the request of both states.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Information FDFA Bundeshaus West CH-3003 Bern Tel.: (+41) 031 322 31 53 Fax: (+41) 031 324 90 47 E-Mail: info@eda.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="83943">
        <title>Information on bilateral relations between Switzerland and Georgia</title>
        <uri>http://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home/reps/eur/vgeo/bilgeo.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="83944">
        <title>Information on Switzerland‘s transition aid in the South Caucasus</title>
        <uri>http://www.deza.admin.ch/en/Home/Countries/Commonwealth_of_Independent_States_CIS/Southern_Caucasus_Georgia_Armenia_Azerbaijan</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
