<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="39403" revoked="no">
    <version>2</version>
    <pubdate>2011-05-31</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="703" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>701</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Staatssekretariat für Wirtschaft</name>
      <name lang="fr">Secrétariat d'Etat à l'économie</name>
      <name lang="it">Segreteria di Stato dell'economia</name>
      <name lang="en">State Secretariat for Economic Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.seco.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.seco.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.seco.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.seco.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@seco.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@seco.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@seco.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@seco.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="701">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Wirtschaft, Bildung und Forschung</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'économie, de la formation et de la recherche</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'economia, della formazione e della ricerca</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Economic Affairs, Education and Research</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Das Bruttoinlandprodukt im 1. Quartal 2011</title>
      <lead>Das reale Bruttoinlandprodukt der Schweiz (BIP) hat im 1. Quartal 2011 gegenüber dem 4. Quartal 2010 um 0,3% zugenommen*. Positive Wachstumsimpulse gingen von der Handelsbilanz, den Bauinvestitionen sowie - wenn auch nur in bescheidenem Masse - vom privaten Konsum aus. Auf der Produktionsseite trugen insbesondere die Industrie und das Baugewerbe zum Wachstum bei. Verglichen mit dem 1. Quartal des Vorjahres resultierte ein BIP-Wachstum von 2,4%.</lead>
      <text link="no">Der private Konsum hat im 1. Quartal gegenüber dem Vorquartal um 0,2% zugenommen. Das Konsumwachstum war in erster Linie auf die Bereiche Wohnen und Gesundheit sowie auf die Rubrik "Sonstige Waren und Dienstleistungen" (in erster Linie Bankdienstleistungen und Versicherungen) zurückzuführen. Abgenommen hat der Konsum von Nahrungsmitteln und Kleidung. Der Staatskonsum reduzierte sich im 1. Quartal gegenüber dem Vorquartal um 0,3%.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Die Bruttoanlageinvestitionen sind im 1. Quartal gegenüber dem Vorquartal leicht gesunken (-0,3%). Innerhalb dieses Aggregats verlief die Entwicklung sehr unterschiedlich. Die Bauinvestitionen stiegen im Vergleich zum Vorquartal kräftig um 2,7% an. Demgegenüber bildeten sich die Ausrüstungsinvestitionen, nach einem ausserordentlich starken 4. Quartal, im 1. Quartal wieder zurück (-2,7%). Negative Wachstumsbeträge lieferten hier insbesondere die Rubriken Fahrzeugbau und Software.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Wie im 4. Quartal 2010 sind die Warenexporte (ohne Edelmetalle, Edel- und Schmucksteine sowie Kunstgegenstände und Antiquitäten) auch im 1. Quartal 2011 deutlich gewachsen; gegenüber dem Vorquartal stiegen sie um 3,1%. Positive Wachstumsbeiträge lieferten insbesondere die Rubriken Maschinen, Apparate und Elektronik sowie Präzisionsinstrumente, Uhren und Bijouterie. Die Dienstleistungsexporte stiegen gegenüber dem Vorquartal um 10,8%. Für diese sehr ausgeprägte Zunahme waren dabei ausschliesslich die höheren Erträge aus dem Transithandel (u.a. Rohwarenhandel) verantwortlich. Die Warenimporte (ohne Edelmetalle, Edel- und Schmucksteine sowie Kunstgegenstände und Antiquitäten) haben um 0,7% zugenommen. Die Rubriken Metalle, Maschinen, Apparate, Elektronik und Fahrzeuge trugen wesentlich zum Anstieg der Warenimporte bei. Die Dienstleistungsimporte wuchsen um 1,1%.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Die Produktionsseite zeigt ein nuanciertes Bild hinter dem BIP-Wachstum im 1. Quartal 2011. Zum einen konnten die Bereiche Landwirtschaft (+3,8%), Baugewerbe (+1,2%) sowie der durch die Industrie dominierte Sektor (+0,6%) ihre Wertschöpfung im Vorquartalsvergleich deutlich steigern. Demgegenüber verlief die Wertschöpfungsentwicklung im durch Finanzmarktdienstleistungen geprägten Sektor sowie im durch öffentliche Dienstleistungen geprägten Bereich mit Zunahmen von je 0,2% eher bescheiden. Im Bereich Handel, Gastgewerbe, Verkehr und Nachrichtendienste war die Wertschöpfung sogar rückläufig (-0,5%).&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Nach sechs Quartalen negativer Entwicklung erhöhte sich der Deflator des Bruttoinlandprodukts im 1. Quartal 2011 gegenüber dem entsprechenden Quartal des Vorjahres erstmals wieder leicht (+0,4%). Auch der Konsumdeflator verzeichnete ein leichtes Wachstum um 0,3%, derjenige der Bauinvestitionen legte sogar deutlich um 2,1% zu. Dagegen gingen die Preise für Ausrüstungsgüter erneut zurück (-2,7%). Die seit Frühjahr 2009 anhaltende negative Tendenz der Exportpreise setzte sich auch im 1. Quartal mit einem Rückgang um 1,4% fort. Die Importpreise sanken um 1,0%, womit auch hier ein seit Herbst 2008 anhaltender negativer Trend seine Fortsetzung fand.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; *Ohne gegenteilige Anmerkung werden die hier aufgeführten Veränderungsraten gegenüber dem Vorquartal (ohne Hochrechnung auf Jahresbasis) aus saison- und preisbereinigten Reihen berechnet. «Real» steht dabei als Abkürzung für die Formulierung «zu Preisen des Vorjahres, verkettete Werte, Referenzjahr 2000».</text>
      <contact>Staatssekretariat für Wirtschaft SECO Holzikofenweg 36 CH-3003 Bern Tel. +41 58 462 56 56 Fax +41 58 462 56 00</contact>
      <attachment id="156892">
        <title>Entwicklung des Bruttoinlandprodukts (Tabellen)</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>31</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/23186.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="156893">
        <title>Entwicklung des Bruttoinlandproduktes (Grafik)</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>75</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/23188.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <link id="156894">
        <title>BIP Quartalsschätzungen</title>
        <uri>https://www.seco.admin.ch/seco/de/home/wirtschaftslage---wirtschaftspolitik/Wirtschaftslage/bip-quartalsschaetzungen-.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="156895">
        <title>Konjunkturtendenzen</title>
        <uri>https://www.seco.admin.ch/seco/de/home/wirtschaftslage---wirtschaftspolitik/Wirtschaftslage/konjunkkturprognosen.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions>
        <revision date="2016-08-16 11:42" type="R"/>
      </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Le produit intérieur brut au 1er trimestre 2011</title>
      <lead>Le produit intérieur brut (PIB) de la Suisse exprimé en termes réels a progressé de 0,3 % au 1er trimestre 2011 par rapport au trimestre précédent*. Il a bénéficié des impulsions positives de la balance commerciale, des investissements dans la construction et – dans une moindre mesure – de la consommation privée. Côté production, ce sont surtout l’industrie et le secteur de la construction qui ont contribué à la croissance. En comparaison avec le 1er trimestre 2010, le PIB a augmenté de 2,4 %.</lead>
      <text link="no">La consommation des ménages a progressé de 0,2 % au 1er trimestre 2011. Cette croissance est due en premier lieu aux domaines du logement, de la santé et à la rubrique "biens et services divers" (qui comprend notamment les services bancaires et d’assurance). Par contre, la consommation a diminué dans le domaine des produits alimentaires et de l’habillement. La consommation publique, elle, s’est réduite de 0,3 % au cours de la même période.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; La formation brute de capital fixe a légèrement baissé par rapport au trimestre précédent (-0,3 %). L’évolution a été très hétérogène au sein de cet agrégat. Si les investissements dans la construction ont connu une vigoureuse expansion de 2,7 %, les investissements en biens d’équipement ont affiché une baisse de -2,7 %. Cette évolution contraste avec la très vive augmentation des investissements en bien d’équipement du 4e trimestre 2010. Au 1er trimestre ce sont essentiellement les rubriques des investissements en véhicules et moyens de transports et les logiciels qui ont connu une évolution négative.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Comme au 4e trimestre 2010, les exportations de marchandises (hors métaux précieux, pierres gemmes, œuvres d’art et antiquités) ont nettement augmenté au 1er trimestre 2011, à savoir de 3,1 %. Les rubriques des machines, des appareils et de l’électronique, ainsi que des instruments de précision, de l’horlogerie et de la bijouterie ont, en particulier, contribué à cette évolution positive. Les exportations de services ont bondi de 10,8 %, toutefois uniquement sous l’effet de la hausse marquée des revenus du commerce de transit (essentiellement les revenus du négoce de matières premières). Les importations de marchandises (hors métaux précieux, pierres gemmes, œuvres d’art et antiquités) ont affiché une hausse de 0,7 %, en grande partie grâce aux rubriques des métaux, des machines, des appareils, de l’électronique et des véhicules. Quant aux importations de services, celles-ci ont augmenté de 1,1 %.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Côté production, la croissance du PIB au 1er trimestre 2011 illustre une évolution très contrastée selon les secteurs. D’une part, les secteurs de l’agriculture (+3,8 %), de la construction (+1,2 %) et celui dominé par l’industrie (+0,6 %) ont vu leur valeur ajoutée progresser nettement par rapport au trimestre précédent. D’autre part, les secteurs dominés par les services financiers et les services publics ont accusé une hausse très modeste (respectivement +0,2 %). Dans le domaine du commerce, de l’hôtellerie-restauration et des transports et communications, la valeur ajoutée a diminué (-0,5 %).&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Après six trimestres d’évolution négative, le déflateur du PIB s’est inscrit légèrement à la hausse (+0,4 %) au 1er trimestre 2011 par rapport au même trimestre de l’année précédente. Le déflateur de la consommation privée a lui aussi connu une modeste progression (+0,3 %). Celui des investissements dans la construction a affiché une hausse plus marquée (+2,1 %). Par contre, les prix des biens d’équipement ont une nouvelle fois reculé (-2,7 %). En matière de prix à l’exportation, la tendance négative qui perdure depuis le printemps 2009 s’est poursuivie au 1er trimestre 2011, la baisse des prix a été de 1,4 %. Egalement les prix à l‘importation ont baissé, de 1,0 %, et prolongent ainsi également une tendance au repli ininterrompue observée depuis l’automne 2008.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; *Sauf mention contraire, les taux de variation indiqués ici se réfèrent aux variations par rapport au trimestre précédent. Les variations sont calculées à partir des données corrigées des variations saisonnières et de l’évolution des prix (les variations d’un trimestre à l’autre ne sont pas annualisées). L’adjectif «réel» est utilisé en lieu et place de la formulation plus technique «aux prix de l’année précédente, séries chaînées, année de référence 2000».</text>
      <contact>Secrétariat d'Etat à l'économie SECO Holzikofenweg 36 CH-3003 Berne tél. +41 58 462 56 56 fax +41 58 462 56 00</contact>
      <attachment id="156896">
        <title>Evolution du produit intérieur (tableaux)</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>31</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/23190.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="156897">
        <title>Evolution du produit intérieur (graphique)</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>75</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/23191.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <link id="156898">
        <title>PIB estimations trimestrielles</title>
        <uri>https://www.seco.admin.ch/seco/fr/home/wirtschaftslage---wirtschaftspolitik/Wirtschaftslage/bip-quartalsschaetzungen-.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="156899">
        <title>Tendances conjoncturelles</title>
        <uri>https://www.seco.admin.ch/seco/fr/home/wirtschaftslage---wirtschaftspolitik/Wirtschaftslage/konjunkkturprognosen.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions>
        <revision date="2016-08-16 11:42" type="R"/>
      </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Prodotto interno lordo del 1° trimestre 2011</title>
      <lead>Nel 1° trimestre 2011 il prodotto interno lordo reale della Svizzera (PIL) è aumentato dello 0,3% rispetto al 4° trimestre 2010*. Impulsi alla crescita sono giunti dalla bilancia commerciale, dagli investimenti nelle costruzioni nonché – pur se in misura limitata – dai consumi privati. Sotto il profilo della produzione hanno contribuito alla crescita soprattutto il settore industriale e quello edilizio. Da un raffronto con il 1° trimestre dell'anno precedente risulta un aumento del PIL del 2,4%.</lead>
      <text link="no">Nel 1° trimestre 2011 i consumi privati sono cresciuti dello 0,2% rispetto al trimestre precedente. L’aumento dei consumi è dovuto soprattutto alle spese più alte per l'abitazione e per i servizi sanitari; un aumento è stato registrato anche per le spese della rubrica "altri beni e servizi", formata principalmente dai servizi bancari e assicurativi. Sono invece calati i consumi di derrate alimentari e di abbigliamento. Rispetto al trimestre precedente, nel 1° trimestre i consumi pubblici sono calati dello 0,3%.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Dal confronto con i dati del trimestre precedente risulta una leggera diminuzione degli investimenti fissi lordi (-0,3%). Le componenti di questo aggregato fanno tuttavia registrare un andamento fortemente differenziato. Rispetto al trimestre precedente gli investimenti nella costruzione sono aumentati in misura considerevole (+2,7%). Invece gli investimenti per impianti e attrezzature ‒ dopo l’andamento eccezionalmente positivo del 4o trimestre 2010 ‒ nel 1o trimestre di quest’anno hanno subito un calo (-2,7%). A ciò hanno contribuito soprattutto le categorie dei investimenti in mezzi di trasporto e in software.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Come nel 4o trimestre 2010, anche nel 1o trimestre 2011 le esportazioni di merci (esclusi i metalli preziosi, le pietre preziose e semipreziose, nonché gli oggetti d’arte e di antichità) sono nettamente cresciute; rispetto al trimestre precedente l’aumento è stato del 3,1%. Alla crescita hanno contribuito soprattutto le categorie seguenti: macchine, apparecchi, prodotti dell’elettronica, strumenti di precisione, orologi e articoli di gioielleria. Rispetto al trimestre precedente le esportazioni di servizi sono aumentate del 10,8%. Questo aumento molto marcato è dovuto esclusivamente alle maggiori entrate nel settore del commercio di transito (in particolare commercio di materie prime). Le importazioni di merci (esclusi i metalli preziosi, le pietre preziose e semipreziose, nonché gli oggetti d’arte e di antichità) sono cresciute dello 0,7%. Le categorie metalli, macchine, apparecchi, prodotti dell’elettronica e veicoli hanno contribuito in misura importante a questa crescita. Le importazioni di servizi sono aumentate dell’1,1%.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Sotto il profilo della produzione, dall’analisi dei dati relativi alla crescita del PIL nel 1° trimestre 2011 emerge un quadro composito: da un lato, nell’agricoltura (+3,8%), nell’edilizia (+1,2%) e nel settore caratterizzato soprattutto da attività industriali (+0,6%) la creazione di valore aggiunto è sensibilmente aumentata. D’altra parte, nei settori in cui i servizi finanziari e i servizi pubblici hanno un peso importante la creazione di valore aggiunto è stata piuttosto contenuta (+0,2%). Nel commercio, nell’industria alberghiera, nei trasporti e nelle telecomunicazioni è addirittura calata (-0,5%).&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Dopo sei trimestri di andamento negativo, per la prima volta nel 1o trimestre 2011 si è registrato un leggero aumento del deflatore del prodotto interno lordo (+0,4%) rispetto allo stesso trimestre dell’anno precedente. Anche il deflatore dei consumi è leggermente cresciuto (+0,3%). Per ciò che concerne gli investimenti nelle costruzioni, l’incremento è stato addirittura del 2,1%. I prezzi dei beni d’equipaggiamento sono invece scesi nuovamente (-2,7%). La tendenza negativa che caratterizza l’andamento dei prezzi all’esportazione dalla primavera del 2009 è proseguita anche nel 1o trimestre 2011, con un calo dell’1.4%. I prezzi all’importazione hanno subito una riduzione dell’1,0%: in questo caso il trend si mantiene negativo dall’autunno 2008.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; *Salvo diversa indicazione, i tassi di variazione riportati sono calcolati rispetto al trimestre precedente (senza una proiezione su base annua) a partire da serie destagionalizzate e depurate dalle variazioni di prezzo. Per «reale« si intende «rispetto ai prezzi dell'anno precedente, valori concatenati, anno di riferimento 2000».</text>
      <contact>Segreteria di Stato dell'economia SECO Holzikofenweg 36 CH-3003 Berna tel. +41 58 462 56 56 fax +41 58 462 56 00</contact>
      <attachment id="156900">
        <title>Evoluzione dell'prodotto interno lordo (tabelle)</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>31</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/23192.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="156901">
        <title>Evoluzione dell'prodotto interno lordo (grafico)</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>75</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/23193.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <link id="156902">
        <title>Il prodotto interno lordo - Stime trimestrali</title>
        <uri>https://www.seco.admin.ch/seco/it/home/wirtschaftslage---wirtschaftspolitik/Wirtschaftslage/bip-quartalsschaetzungen-.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="156903">
        <title>Previsioni congiunturali</title>
        <uri>https://www.seco.admin.ch/seco/it/home/wirtschaftslage---wirtschaftspolitik/Wirtschaftslage/konjunkkturprognosen.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions>
        <revision date="2016-08-16 11:42" type="R"/>
      </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Gross Domestic Product in First Quarter 2011</title>
      <lead>The real gross domestic product (GDP) for Switzerland grew in the first quarter of 2011 by 0.3% compared to the fourth quarter of 2010*. Positive growth was generated by the trade balance, construction investment, and to a lesser extent by private consumption. On the production side, industrial and the construction sectors contributed to growth. GDP growth was 2.4% compared to the first quarter of the previous year.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Private consumption expanded by 0.2% in the first quarter over the previous quarter. The growth in consumption was primarily the result of expansion in the housing and healthcare sectors along with the “other” category (mainly banking services and insurance). Consump-tion expenditures in the components food and clothing fell however. Government consump-tion increased in the first quarter by 0.3% over the previous quarter.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Gross fixed capital formation fell by a slight -0.3% in the first quarter. Development varied greatly within this aggregate. Construction investment grew sharply by 2.7%. In comparison, capital spending declined by -2.7%, after having registered a strong increase during the last quarter of 2010. Negative growth could be observed in particular in vehicle investments and software categories.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; As in the fourth quarter of 2010, the export of goods (excluding precious metals, gemstones, as well as object of art and antiques) also expanded markedly in the first quarter of 2011 by 3.1%. In particular the machinery and electronics categories along with precision and optical instruments, clocks, watches and jewellery contributed positively to this growth. Service exports grew by 10.8% over the previous quarter. This remarkable increase was exclusively the product of higher earnings from the transit trade (“merchandising” or trade with raw ma-terial). Goods imports (excluding precious metals, gemstones, as well as object of art and antiques) increased by 0.7%. The metal working, machinery, appliance, electronics and vehicle categories all made significant contributions to the increase in imported goods. Services imports expanded by 1.1%.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; The production side was more nuanced in terms of growth in the first quarter of 2011. There was a significant increase in the value added in the areas of agriculture (+3.8%), construction (+1.2%), as well as the industry-dominated sector (+0.6%). By contrast, the value added increases in the sector dominated by financial services as well as the sector dominated by public services were rather modest at a mere 0.2% each. In the trade, hotel and transport services value added even declined (-0.5%).&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; After six quarters of negative development, the deflator for gross domestic product increased for the first time slightly compared to the corresponding quarter in the previous year (+0.4%). The consumption deflator also recorded slight growth of 0.3%. The construction deflator booked a significant increase of 2.1%. By contrast the prices for investment goods declined once again (-2.7%). The negative trend observed in export prices since early 2009 continued in the first quarter of 2011 with a decline of 1.4%. Import prices sank by 1.0%; the negative trend in import prices is observed since fall 2008.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; *Unless otherwise stated the percentage changes listed here refer to the previous quarter from seasonally and price adjusted figures (not annualized). «Real» is used to describe the formulation «data at previous year prices, quarterly chained series with reference year 2000».&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>State Secretariat for Economic Affairs SECO Holzikofenweg 36 CH-3003 Bern Tel. +41 58 462 56 56 Fax +41 58 462 56 00</contact>
      <attachment id="156904">
        <title>Evolution of the Gross Domestic Product (tables)</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>31</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/23194.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="156905">
        <title>Evolution of the Gross Domestic Product (graphic)</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>76</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/23196.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <link id="156895">
        <title>Konjunkturtendenzen</title>
        <uri>https://www.seco.admin.ch/seco/de/home/wirtschaftslage---wirtschaftspolitik/Wirtschaftslage/konjunkkturprognosen.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="156906">
        <title>GDP - quarterly estimates</title>
        <uri>https://www.seco.admin.ch/seco/en/home/wirtschaftslage---wirtschaftspolitik/Wirtschaftslage/bip-quartalsschaetzungen-.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="156907">
        <title>Economic forecasts</title>
        <uri>https://www.seco.admin.ch/seco/en/home/wirtschaftslage---wirtschaftspolitik/Wirtschaftslage/konjunkkturprognosen.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions>
        <revision date="2016-08-16 11:42" type="R"/>
      </revisions>
    </content>
    <offers>
      <offer id="156" org-id="703">
        <name lang="de">BIP-Quartalsdaten und Konjunkturtendenzen</name>
        <name lang="fr">Données trimestrielles PIB et tendances conjoncturelles</name>
        <name lang="it">Tendenze congiunturali</name>
        <name lang="en">Quarterly data on GDP and economic trends</name>
      </offer>
    </offers>
    <topics>
      <topic id="37">
        <name lang="de">Konsum</name>
        <name lang="fr">Consommation</name>
        <name lang="it">Consumo</name>
        <name lang="en">Consumer Affairs</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="47">
        <name lang="de">Wirtschaft</name>
        <name lang="fr">Économie</name>
        <name lang="it">Economia</name>
        <name lang="en">Economic Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
