<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="2634" revoked="no">
    <version>4</version>
    <pubdate>1999-12-16</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="815" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>801</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössische Kommunikationskommission ComCom</name>
      <name lang="fr">Commission fédérale de la communication ComCom</name>
      <name lang="it">Commissione federale delle comunicazioni ComCom</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Communications Commission ComCom</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.comcom.admin.ch/</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.comcom.admin.ch/</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.comcom.admin.ch/</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.comcom.admin.ch/</www>
      <email lang="de">comcom@comcom.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">comcom@comcom.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">comcom@comcom.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">comcom@comcom.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="801">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Umwelt, Verkehr, Energie und Kommunikation</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'environnement, des transports, de l'énergie et de la communication</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'ambiente, dei trasporti, dell'energia e delle comunicazioni</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of the Environment, Transport, Energy and Communications</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.uvek.admin.ch/uvek/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.uvek.admin.ch/uvek/fr/home.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.uvek.admin.ch/uvek/it/home.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.uvek.admin.ch/uvek/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-uvek.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-uvek.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-uvek.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-uvek.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Nummernportabilität: Inkrafttreten um zwei Monate verschoben</title>
      <teaser>Drahtloser Teilnehmeranschluss (Wireless Local Loop, WLL): 19 Kandidaten wurden zur Teilnahme an der Auktion der 48 Konzessionen zugelassen.</teaser>
      <lead>Drahtloser Teilnehmeranschluss (Wireless Local Loop, WLL): 19 Kandidaten wurden zur Teilnahme an der Auktion der 48 Konzessionen zugelassen.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Nach der Evaluation der bis zum 1. November 1999 beim Bundesamt für Kommunikation (BAKOM) eingegangenen Bewerbungen hat die Eidgenössische Kommunikationskommission (ComCom) die folgenden 19 Kandidaten zur Teilnahme an der Auktion der Funkkonzessionen für den drahtlosen Teilnehmeranschluss (WLL) zugelassen: BroadNet, Callino, Commcare, Diax, EUnet/KPNQwest, Europe i Switzerland, FirstMark, Mannesmann ipulsys, MCI Worldcom, Multilink, Primus, Star-One, Sunrise, Telcom Ventures, Tele2, Télésonique, United Pan-Europe, VTX Services und WinStar. Zwei der anfänglich 21 Kandidaten zogen ihre Bewerbung während der Evaluationsphase zurück. Die Versteigerung der 48 Konzessionen wird mit Hilfe einer vom Schweizer Unternehmen Marvel Communications AG entwickelten Software im Internet durchgeführt werden. Die Versteigerung wird vom 9. Februar bis Mitte April 2000 unter der Leitung des BAKOM stattfinden. Somit wird die ComCom die Konzessionen gegen Ende April vergeben können. Zeitplan und weitere Informationen bezüglich der Auktion werden in Kürze auf der Website www.ofcomauction.ch verfügbar sein. Dort werden die Auktionen auch live mitverfolgt werden können.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2&gt;Nummernportabilität&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;Gemäss der Verordnung der ComCom vom 17. November 1997 müssen die Fernmeldedienstanbieter die Nummernportabilität auf den 1. Januar 2000 einführen. Die Nummernportabilität ermöglicht den Abonnenten, beim Wechsel des Anbieters ihre Telefonnummer zu behalten. Dies gilt sowohl für das Festnetz als auch für die Mobiltelefonie.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Wegen Schwierigkeiten bei der Implementierung der zur Bereitstellung der Nummernportabilität erforderlichen Informatiksysteme – vor allem bei den Mobilfunkanbietern – und um mögliche Kollisionen mit dem Jahr-2000-Problem zu vermeiden, hat die Kommission beschlossen, die Einführung der Nummernportabilität um zwei Monate auf den 1. März 2000 zu verschieben.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Entscheidend ist für die Kommission, dass die Nummernportabilität, die ein wichtiger Faktor für die Belebung des Wettbewerbs unter den Betreibern darstellt, von allem Anfang an einwandfrei funktioniert.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact/>
      <revisions>
        <revision date="2006-03-13 16:29" type="R"/>
        <revision date="2006-03-09 12:42" type="R"/>
      </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Portabilité des numéros: entrée en vigueur reportée de deux mois</title>
      <teaser>Boucle locale sans fil (Wireless Local Loop): la ComCom autorise 19 candidats à participer à la mise aux enchères des 48 concessions.</teaser>
      <lead>Boucle locale sans fil (Wireless Local Loop): la ComCom autorise 19 candidats à participer à la mise aux enchères des 48 concessions.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Suite à l'évaluation des dossiers de candidature déposés auprès de l'Office fédéral de la communication (OFCOM) le 1er novembre 1999, la Commission fédérale de la communication a décidé d'admettre 19 candidats (BroadNet, Callino, Commcare, Diax, EUnet/KPNQwest, Europe i Switzerland, FirstMark, Mannesmann ipulsys, MCI Worldcom, Multilink, Primus, Star-One, Sunrise, Telcom Ventures, Tele2, Télésonique, United Pan-Europe, VTX Services et WinStar) à la vente aux enchères des concessions de radiocommunication pour la boucle locale radio (WLL). Parmi les 21 candidats, deux ont retiré leur demande en cours d'évaluation. La vente aux enchères des 48 concessions se déroulera sur Internet au moyen d'un logiciel élaboré par l'entreprise suisse Marvel Communications SA. La vente aux enchères conduite par l'OFCOM commencera le 9 février et se terminera à la mi-avril 2000, de sorte que la commission puisse attribuer les concessions vers la fin du mois d'avril. Le calendrier et les informations concernant la vente aux enchères seront disponibles prochainement sur le site Internet www.ofcomauction.ch. Les intéressés pourront suivre en direct le déroulement des enchères sur ce même site.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2&gt;Portabilité des numéros&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;La commission a fixé, dans son ordonnance du 17 novembre 1997, l'obligation pour les fournisseurs de services de télécommunication d'introduire la portabilité des numéros au 1er janvier 2000. Cette mesure permet aux abonnés de changer d'opérateurs sans devoir changer de numéros de téléphone, ceci aussi bien pour le réseau fixe que pour la téléphonie mobile.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Devant les problèmes rencontrés par les opérateurs, en particulier ceux de téléphonie mobile, pour implémenter les systèmes informatiques chargés de gérer ces modifications et pour éviter les problèmes de collision qui pourraient se produire avec la problématique de l'an 2000, la commission a décidé de reporter son entrée en vigueur de deux mois, à savoir au 1er mars 2000.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;La commission motive sa décision en particulier par le fait que la portabilité des numéros est un élément important pour stimuler la concurrence et qu'il est capital de garantir son parfait fonctionnement dès son introduction.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact/>
      <revisions>
        <revision date="2006-03-13 16:29" type="R"/>
        <revision date="2006-03-09 12:42" type="R"/>
      </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Portabilità dei numeri: entrata in vigore rinviata di due mesi</title>
      <teaser>Rete locale senza filo (Wireless Local Loop): la ComCom autorizza 19 candidati a partecipare all'asta pubblica per le 48 concessioni.</teaser>
      <lead>Rete locale senza filo (Wireless Local Loop): la ComCom autorizza 19 candidati a partecipare all'asta pubblica per le 48 concessioni.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;In seguito alla valutazione dei dossier di candidatura inoltrati all'Ufficio federale delle comunicazioni (UFCOM), il 1° novembre 1999, la Commissione federale delle comunicazioni ha deciso di ammettere 19 candidati (BroadNet, Callino, Commcare, Diax, EUnet/KPNQwest, Europe i Switzerland, FirstMark, WinStar, Mannesmann ipulsys, MCI Worldcom, Multilink, Primus, Star-One, Sunrise, Telcom Ventures, Tele2, Télésonique, United Pan-Europe, et VTX Services ) all'asta pubblica, con la quale saranno attribuite le concessioni di radiocomunicazione per la rete locale senza filo (WLL). Delle 21 candidature presentate, due sono state ritirate nel corso della valutazione. L'asta pubblica per le 48 concessioni si svolgerà su internet con l'ausilio di un software elaborato dalla ditta svizzera Marvel Communications SA e sarà condotta dall'UFCOM. Essa avrà inizio il 9 febbraio e terminerà a metà aprile 2000; la ComCom potrà pertanto attribuire le concessioni verso la fine del mese di aprile. Il calendario e le informazioni relative all'asta saranno prossimamente pubblicati su internet, al seguente indirizzo: www.ofcomauction.ch. Sempre allo stesso indirizzo, gli interessati potranno seguire in diretta lo svolgimento dell'asta.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2&gt;Portabilità dei numeri&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;Nella sua ordinanza del 17 novembre 1997 la ComCom ha sancito l'obbligo per i fornitori di servizi di telecomunicazione d'introdurre la portabilità dei numeri a partire dal 1° gennaio 2000. Tale provvedimento permette agli abbonati di cambiare operatore senza però dovere cambiare il numero telefonico; ciò vale sia per la rete fissa che per la telefonia mobile.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Considerati i problemi ai quali devono far fronte gli operatori, in particolari quelli attivi nella telefonia mobile, nell'implementare i sistemi informatici che permetteranno di attuare le modifiche summenzionate e per evitare che tale problema venga ad aggiungersi a quello del "millenium bug", alla fine di quest'anno, la ComCom ha deciso di rinviare l'entrata in vigore di due mesi, ovvero al 1° marzo 2000.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;La commissione ha motivato la sua decisione illustrando l'importanza che la portabilità dei numeri riveste nella concorrenza tra gli operatori e sottolineando la necessità di garantire sin dall'inizio il perfetto funzionamento di questo nuovo sistema.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact/>
      <revisions>
        <revision date="2006-03-09 12:42" type="R"/>
      </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Wireless Local Loop: ComCom authorises 19 candidates to take part in the auction for 48 licences</title>
      <lead/>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Following the evaluation of the applications submitted to Federal Office for Communications (OFCOM) on 1 November 1999, the Federal Communications Commission (ComCom) has decided to admit 19 candidates (BroadNet, Callino, Commcare, Diax, EUnet/KPNQwest, Europe i Switzerland, FirstMark, Mannesmann ipulsys, MCI Worldcom, Multilink, Primus, Star-One, Sunrise, Telcom Ventures, Tele2, Télésonique, United Pan-Europe, VTX Services, and WinStar) to the auction for the radiocommunication licences for the Wireless Local Loop (WLL). Of the 21 candidates, two withdrew their application during the evaluation. The auction for the 48 licences will take place on the Internet using software developed by the Swiss company Marvel Communications SA. The auction, conducted by OFCOM, will begin on 9 February and will end in mid-April 2000, so that the Commission can grant the licences towards the end of April. The timetable and information on the auction will be soon available on the following Internet site: www.ofcomauction.ch. Interested parties will be able to follow the auction proceedings live on the same site.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2&gt;Number portability&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;The Commission's decree dated 17 November 1997 obliges telecoms service providers to introduce number portability by 1 January 2000. This measure allows subscribers to change operator without having to change telephone numbers, on both fixed and mobile networks.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;In view of the problems encountered by the operators, in particular by the mobile telephone companies, in introducing the computer systems which have to manage these changes and in order to avoid Y2K problems, the Commission has decided to defer the entry into force of the number portability by two months, i.e. until 1 March 2000.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The Commission’s decision is motivated in particular by the fact that number portability is a major component for stimulating competition between operators and that it is important to guarantee that number portability works perfectly as soon as it is introduced.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact/>
      <revisions>
        <revision date="2006-03-13 16:29" type="R"/>
      </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="28">
        <name lang="de">Telekommunikation</name>
        <name lang="fr">Télécommunications</name>
        <name lang="it">Telecomunicazione</name>
        <name lang="en">Telecommunications</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
