<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="23306" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2008-11-25</pubdate>
    <blocking-period>2008-11-25</blocking-period>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="201" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>201</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="201">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>48. Internationale Bildungskonferenz, Genf</title>
      <lead>Bildung ist ein Menschenrecht. Daran erinnerte Micheline Calmy-Rey am Dienstag Abend vor etwa hundert Ministern und tausend Delegierten, die diese Woche in Genf an der Internationalen Bildungskonferenz zum Thema «Inclusive Education: the Way of the Future» teilnahmen.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Die Schweiz ist vom 25. bis 28.&amp;nbsp;November 2008 Tagungsort der 48.&amp;nbsp;Internationalen Bildungskonferenz der UNESCO. Sie ist eines der wichtigsten Treffen für Bildungsminister, die zahlreich erschienen: Über hundert Minister kamen aus allen Kontinenten zusammen, um Möglichkeiten zur Förderung der Bildung für alle zu erörtern.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;In Ihrer Begrüssungsrede betonte die Vorsteherin des Eidgenössischen Departements für auswärtige Angelegenheiten (EDA) vor den Teilnehmerinnen und Teilnehmern, wie wichtig Bildung als Mittel zur Bekämpfung der Ungleichheit in einer von kultureller Vielfalt, aber auch von Ausgrenzung geprägten Welt für unsere gesellschaftliche Entwicklung ist. Mit Blick auf die Feiern zum 60.&amp;nbsp;Jahrestag der Allgemeinen Erklärung der Menschenrechte bekräftigte sie, dass alle Menschen lebenslang Zugang zu hochstehenden Bildungsangeboten haben sollten. Gleichzeitig wies sie auf die Notwendigkeit hin, das Wissen über die Menschenrechte zu fördern.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Bundesrätin Calmy-Rey begrüsste die Bemühungen der UNESCO zur Umsetzung dieser Ziele. Sie unterstrich insbesondere, wie wichtig die Präsenz des Internationalen Bildungsamts (IBE) in der Schweiz, im Herzen des internationalen Genf ist, namentlich, „um die Menschenrechte voranzubringen, zu denen unter anderem das Recht auf Bildung gehört“.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Weitere Informationen zur&amp;nbsp;Internationalen Bildungskonferenz&amp;nbsp;unter:&lt;br /&gt; http://www.ibe.unesco.org/en/ice/48th-session-2008.html&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;u&gt;Auskünfte:&lt;br /&gt; &lt;/u&gt;Information EDA, Jean-Philippe Jutzi, 079 292 08 49&lt;br /&gt; Nicolas MATHIEU, Chef UNESCO-Koordination, 031 323 41 34&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Presse- und Informationsdienst Bundeshaus West CH-3003 Bern Tel.: +41 (0)31 322 31 53 Fax: +41 (0)31 324 90 47 E-Mail: info@eda.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>48 ème session de la Conférence internationale de l’éducation, Genève</title>
      <lead>L’éducation est un droit humain. C’est ce qu’a rappelé mardi soir Micheline Calmy-Rey devant la centaine de Ministres et le millier de délégués présents cette semaine à Genève pour la Conférence internationale de l’éducation sur le thème de l’inclusion.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;La Suisse accueille du 25 au 28 novembre 2008 la 48ème session de la Conférence internationale de l’éducation de l’UNESCO. C’est l’un des plus importants rendez-vous pour les Ministres concernés qui y assistent en nombre&amp;nbsp;: ils sont plus d’une centaine venus de tous les continents à être réunis pour partager des orientations afin de progresser dans la voie d’une éducation pour tous.&lt;b&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Lors d’une réception de bienvenue, la Cheffe du Département fédéral des affaires étrangères s’est adressée aux participants en soulignant le rôle majeur de l’éducation dans nos choix de société, comme moyen de vaincre les inégalités dans un monde à la fois empreint de diversité culturelle mais aussi de marginalisation. A l’heure de la célébration du 60ème anniversaire de la Déclaration universelle des droits de l’homme, elle a rappelé que toute personne, à tout moment de sa vie, devrait pouvoir accéder à une éducation de qualité, en même temps qu’elle a mentionné la nécessité de promouvoir la formation aux droits de l’homme.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Madame Calmy-Rey s’est félicitée des efforts de l’UNESCO pour la réalisation de ces objectifs. Elle a souligné l’importance de la présence du Bureau international de l’éducation en Suisse, au cœur de la Genève internationale, «&amp;nbsp;pour faire avancer la cause des droits humains dont fait partie, entre autre, le droit à l’éducation&amp;nbsp;».&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Plus d’information sur la Conférence internationale de l’éducation sous&amp;nbsp;:&lt;br /&gt; http://www.ibe.unesco.org/fr/ice/48th-session-2008.html&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;u&gt;Renseignements&amp;nbsp;:&lt;br /&gt; &lt;/u&gt;Information DFAE, Jean-Philippe Jutzi, 079 292 08 49&lt;br /&gt; Nicolas MATHIEU, Chef coordination UNESCO, 031 323 41 34&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Service de presse et d'information Palais fédéral ouest CH-3003 Berne Tél.: (+41) 031 322 31 53 Fax: (+41) 031 324 90 47 E-Mail: info@eda.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>48ma sessione della Conferenza internazionale sull’educazione, Ginevra</title>
      <lead>L'educazione è un diritto umano. È quanto ha ricordato martedì sera Micheline Calmy-Rey di fronte a un centinaio di ministri e a un migliaio di delegati presenti questa settimana a Ginevra per la Conferenza internazionale sull'educazione il cui tema è l'inclusione.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Dal 25 al 28 novembre 2008, la Svizzera ospita la 48ma sessione della Conferenza internazionale sull'educazione dell'UNESCO, uno dei più importanti appuntamenti per i ministri interessati che vi assistono numerosi: sono più di cento e provengono da tutti i continenti per condividere i vari orientamenti al fine di progredire sulla via di una educazione per tutti.&lt;b&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;In occasione del suo benvenuto, la responsabile del Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri si è rivolta ai partecipanti sottolineando il ruolo principale dell'educazione nelle nostre scelte di società, come strumento per superare le disparità in un mondo caratterizzato dalla diversità culturale e nel contempo dall'emarginazione. Nel momento in cui si celebra il 60mo anniversario della Dichiarazione universale dei diritti dell'uomo, ha ricordato che ogni persona dovrebbe poter accedere, in qualsiasi momento della propria vita, a un'educazione di qualità, e ha sostenuto la necessità di promuovere la formazione dei diritti umani.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Micheline Calmy-Rey si è rallegrata per gli sforzi che l’UNESCO ha profuso per conseguire questi obiettivi. Ha sottolineato l'importanza della presenza dell'Ufficio internazionale dell'educazione in Svizzera, nel cuore della Ginevra internazionale, luogo privilegiato «per far progredire la causa dei diritti umani fra i quali rientra anche il diritto all'educazione».&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Per saperne di più sulla Conferenza internazionale sull'educazione:&lt;br /&gt; http://www.ibe.unesco.org/fr/ice/48th-session-2008.html&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;u&gt;Per ulteriori informazioni:&lt;/u&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;br /&gt; Informazione DFAE, Jean-Philippe Jutzi, 079 292 08 49&lt;br /&gt; Nicolas MATHIEU, Capo coordinamento UNESCO, 031 323 41 34&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Servizio stampa e informazione Palazzo federale ovest CH-3003 Berna Tel.: (+41) 031 322 31 53 Fax: (+41) 031 324 90 47 E-Mail: info@eda.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>48th session of the International Conference on Education, Geneva</title>
      <lead>Education is a human right. This was the message of Micheline Calmy-Rey on Tuesday evening to some hundred ministers and thousand delegates who have gathered this week in Geneva for the International Conference on Education. The theme of this year’s conference is “Inclusive Education: the Way of the Future”.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;From 25 to 28 November 2008, Switzerland will host the 48th session of the UNESCO International Conference on Education. The International Conference on Education is one of the most important meetings for ministers concerned. More than 100 education ministers from all continents have come to the conference to discuss ways to advance the goal of education for all.&lt;b&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;In her speech at the opening reception, the head of the Swiss Federal Department of Foreign Affairs underlined the crucial importance of education for all in&amp;nbsp; enabling our societies to make informed decisions on how to overcome inequalities in a world characterised both by cultural diversity and marginalisation. As we celebrate the 60th anniversary of the Universal Declaration of Human Rights, Micheline Calmy-Rey pointed out that every individual should have access to good quality education at all times in their lives. At the same time, she mentioned the need to promote education in human rights.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Mrs Calmy-Rey congratulated UNESCO on its efforts to achieve these goals. She stressed the importance of the presence of the International Bureau of Education for International Geneva in its efforts “to advance the cause of human rights, which include&amp;nbsp; among other rights, the right to education.”&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;For further information of the International Conference on Education:&lt;br /&gt; http://www.ibe.unesco.org/fr/ice/48th-session-2008.html&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;u&gt;Contacts:&lt;br /&gt; &lt;/u&gt;Jean-Philippe Jutzi, FDFA Information,&amp;nbsp; 079 292 08 49&lt;br /&gt; Nicolas MATHIEU, Head of UNESCO Coordination, 031 323 41 34&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Press and Information Service Bundeshaus West CH-3003 Bern Tel.: (+41) 031 322 31 53 Fax: (+41) 031 324 90 47 E-Mail: info@eda.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
