<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="67997" revoked="no">
    <version>3</version>
    <pubdate>2017-09-06</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="1070" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>1070</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Der Bundesrat</name>
      <name lang="fr">Conseil fédéral</name>
      <name lang="it">Il Consiglio federale</name>
      <name lang="en">The Federal Council</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.admin.ch/gov/de/start.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.admin.ch/gov/fr/accueil.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.admin.ch/gov/it/pagina-iniziale.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.admin.ch/gov/en/start.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="201" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>201</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="1070">
      <name lang="de">Der Bundesrat</name>
      <name lang="fr">Conseil fédéral</name>
      <name lang="it">Il Consiglio federale</name>
      <name lang="en">The Federal Council</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.admin.ch/gov/de/start.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.admin.ch/gov/fr/accueil.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.admin.ch/gov/it/pagina-iniziale.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.admin.ch/gov/en/start.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <department id="201">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Die Prioritäten der Schweiz an der 72. UNO-Generalversammlung</title>
      <lead>Die Förderung von Frieden und Sicherheit, insbesondere durch eine Stärkung von Konfliktprävention und Mediationskapazitäten, sowie die Stärkung der Rolle der Menschenrechte gehören zu den aussenpolitischen Schwerpunkten, die die Schweiz im Rahmen der 72. UNO-Generalversammlung umsetzen will. In der Ministerwoche zur Eröffnung der UNO-Generalversammlung ab 18. September 2017 in New York werden Bundespräsidentin Doris Leuthard, Bundesrat Didier Burkhalter und EDA-Staatssekretärin Pascale Baeriswyl die Schweiz vertreten.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Nach der Konsultation der Aussenpolitischen Kommissionen des Nationalrats und des Ständerats wurde der Bundesrat am 6. September 2017 über die Prioritäten der Schweiz bei der 72. UNO-Generalversammlung informiert. Die Prioritäten orientieren sich an den zwei strategischen Hauptachsen des Schweizer UNO-Engagements für den Zeitraum 2012-2022: Frieden und Sicherheit sowie Reform der UNO. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Konkrete Schwerpunkte sind unter anderem die Förderung von Frieden und Sicherheit, insbesondere durch eine Stärkung von Konfliktprävention und Mediationskapazitäten, sowie eine Stärkung der Rolle der Menschenrechte. Weiter unterstützt die Schweiz die Reformbestrebungen des neuen UNO-Generalsekretärs António Guterres in allen Belangen, damit die UNO ihrer wichtigen Rolle weiterhin effizient und effektiv gerecht werden kann. Ausserdem engagiert sich die Schweiz für eine wirkungsvolle Umsetzung der Agenda 2030 für eine nachhaltige Entwicklung, für die Ausarbeitung des Global Compact zu Migration, für humanitäre Themen und für die Stärkung des internationalen Genf.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Die Generaldebatte der 72. Generalversammlung beginnt am 19. September 2017 und dauert bis September nächsten Jahres. Bundespräsidentin Doris Leuthard wird bei der Eröffnung der Generaldebatte im Namen der Schweiz sprechen und dabei unter anderem die Wichtigkeit einer starken UNO betonen, um gemeinsame Lösungen für globale Herausforderungen wie Klimawandel, Armut, Konflikte und Migration zu finden. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Während ihres Aufenthalts in New York wird Bundespräsidentin Leuthard ausserdem am UN Private Sector Forum teilnehmen, an welchem hochrangige Vertreterinnen und Vertreter aus Politik und Wirtschaft über neue Finanzierungsformen diskutieren, damit die Ziele der Agenda 2030 erreicht werden können. Ausserdem wird sie an der Columbia Universität eine Rede halten. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Bundesrat Didier Burkhalter wird während der Ministerwoche als Gastgeber an einem von der Schweiz mitorganisierten Anlass zum Zusammenhang von Wasserkooperation und Konfliktprävention teilnehmen. Darüber hinaus wird er an der Lancierung einer Initiative anwesend sein, welche Staaten dabei unterstützen will, den Handel von Waren zu regulieren, die für die Umsetzung der Todesstrafe oder für Folter verwendet werden können. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Staatssekretärin Baeriswyl wird unter anderem Co-Gastgeberin einer Veranstaltung zur Lancierung der „Roadmap for Peaceful, Just and Inclusive Societies“ sein, an welcher nationale Umsetzungsstrategien für das nachhaltige Entwicklungsziel “Frieden, Gerechtigkeit und starke Institutionen“ diskutiert werden. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Bundespräsidentin Leuthard und Bundesrat Burkhalter werden ihre Präsenz während der hochrangigen Woche in New York ausserdem zu bilateralen Treffen nutzen. Beide werden am 20. September 2017 wieder in Bern sein, wenn die Vereinigte Bundesversammlung die Ersatzwahl für Bundesrat Burkhalter vornimmt. &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Information EDA Tel. +41 58 462 31 53 info@eda.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="170408">
        <title>Eröffnung der 72. UNO-Generalversammlung</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/content/eda/de/meta/agenda/2017/9/uno-generalversammlung-new-york.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="170409">
        <title>Prioritäten der Schweiz für die 72. Tagung der UNO-Generalversammlung</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/content/dam/eda/de/documents/aktuell/agenda/72-uno-gv-prio-4pager_DE.pdf</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="170410">
        <title>Bericht über die Umsetzung der Prioritäten der Schweiz für die 71. Tagung der UNO Generalversammlung</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/content/dam/eda/de/documents/aktuell/agenda/umsetzung-prios-uno-gv-71_DE.pdf</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Les priorités de la Suisse à la 72e Assemblée générale des Nations Unies</title>
      <lead>La promotion de la paix et de la sécurité, en particulier par le renforcement de la prévention des conflits, le développement des capacités de médiation et la consolidation du rôle des droits de l’homme, sont quelques-unes des priorités de politique extérieure que la Suisse entend présenter lors de la 72e Assemblée générale des Nations Unies. Lors de la semaine ministérielle qui se tiendra à l’occasion de l’ouverture de l’Assemblée générale des Nations Unies, à partir du 18 septembre 2017 à New York, la Suisse sera représentée par la présidente de la Confédération Doris Leuthard, le conseiller fédéral Didier Burkhalter et la secrétaire d'État du DFAE Pascale Baeriswyl.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Après consultation des commissions de politique extérieure du Conseil national et du Conseil des États, le Conseil fédéral a été informé, le 6 septembre 2017, des priorités de la Suisse pour la 72e Assemblée générale. Celles-ci s'articulent le long des deux grands axes stratégiques de l'engagement suisse au sein des Nations Unies pour la période 2012-2022 : la paix et la sécurité, ainsi que la réforme des Nations Unies. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;L’accent sera mis concrètement sur la promotion de la paix et de la sécurité, notamment par le renforcement de la prévention des conflits et des capacités de médiation, ainsi que sur la consolidation du rôle des droits de l’homme. Par ailleurs, la Suisse soutient l'ensemble des efforts de réforme du nouveau secrétaire général de l’ONU António Guterres, afin que l’ONU puisse continuer à jouer son rôle de manière efficace et efficiente. La Suisse se mobilise pour la réalisation efficace de l’Agenda 2030 de développement durable, l’élaboration du pacte mondial sur la migration et le renforcement de la Genève internationale. Elle est également active sur le front humanitaire.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Le débat général de la 72e Assemblée générale commencera le 19 septembre 2017 et se prolongera jusqu'en septembre de l'année suivante. Lors de son ouverture, la présidente de la Confédération Doris Leuthard prononcera une allocution au nom de la Suisse et soulignera notamment l'importance d’une ONU forte, capable de trouver des solutions communes face aux défis mondiaux tels que le changement climatique, la pauvreté, les conflits et la migration. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Pendant son séjour à New York, la présidente de la Confédération participera par ailleurs au forum du secteur privé organisé par les Nations Unies, au cours duquel des personnalités politiques et économiques discuteront de nouvelles formes de financement permettant de réaliser les objectifs de l’Agenda 2030. Elle prononcera également un discours à l’Université Columbia. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Pendant la semaine ministérielle, le conseiller fédéral Didier Burkhalter assistera à une manifestation co-organisée par la Suisse sur le lien entre la coopération dans le domaine de l'eau et la prévention des conflits. Il participera en outre au lancement d’une initiative dont le but est de soutenir les États souhaitant réglementer le commerce des marchandises susceptibles d’être utilisées pour l'exécution de peines capitales ou la pratique de la torture. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;La secrétaire d'État Pascale Baeriswyl accueillera un événement consacré au lancement de la feuille de route pour des sociétés pacifiques, justes et inclusives, au cours duquel seront discutées les stratégies nationales pour la concrétisation de l’objectif de développement «Paix, justice et institutions efficaces». &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;La présidente de la Confédération Doris Leuthard et le conseiller fédéral Didier Burkhalter profiteront de leur présence pendant la semaine de haut niveau à New York pour participer à des rencontres bilatérales. Tous deux seront de retour à Berne le 20 septembre 2017, lorsque les chambres réunies de l’Assemblée fédérale éliront la personne qui succèdera à Didier Burkhalter au Conseil fédéral. &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Information DFAE Tél. +41 58 462 31 53 info@eda.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="170411">
        <title>Ouverture de la 72e Assemblée générale de l’ONU</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/content/eda/fr/meta/agenda/2017/9/uno-generalversammlung-new-york.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="170412">
        <title>Priorités de la Suisse pour la 72e session de l’Assemblée générale de l’ONU</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/content/dam/eda/fr/documents/aktuell/agenda/72-uno-gv-prio-4pager_FR.pdf</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="170413">
        <title>Rapport sur la mise en oeuvre des priorités de la Suisse pour la 71e session de l’Assemblée générale de l’ONU</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/content/dam/eda/fr/documents/aktuell/agenda/umsetzung-prios-uno-gv-71_FR.pdf</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions>
        <revision date="2017-09-06 13:44" type="R"/>
      </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Le priorità della Svizzera alla 72a Assemblea generale dell’ONU</title>
      <lead>Promozione della pace e della sicurezza, in particolare tramite il rafforzamento della prevenzione dei conflitti e delle capacità di mediazione, e consolidamento del ruolo dei diritti umani sono alcune delle priorità di politica estera della Svizzera per la 72a Assemblea generale delle Nazioni Unite, che si aprirà il 18 settembre 2017 a New York. Durante la settimana ministeriale in apertura dell’Assemblea generale, la Svizzera sarà rappresentata dalla presidente della Confederazione Doris Leuthard, dal consigliere federale Didier Burkhalter e dalla segretaria di Stato Pascale Baeriswyl.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Dopo la consultazione delle Commissioni di politica estera del Consiglio nazionale e del Consiglio degli Stati, il 6 settembre 2017 il Consiglio federale è stato informato sulle priorità della Svizzera per la 72a Assemblea generale dell’ONU. Le priorità fanno riferimento ai due assi strategici dell’impegno della Svizzera in seno all’ONU per il decennio 2012-2022: pace e sicurezza da un lato, riforme dell’ONU dall’altro. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Altre priorità specifiche sono la promozione della pace e della sicurezza, in particolare tramite il rafforzamento della prevenzione dei conflitti e delle capacità di mediazione, e il consolidamento del ruolo dei diritti umani. La Svizzera sostiene inoltre il processo di riforma avviato dal nuovo segretario generale dell’ONU António Guterres in tutti i suoi aspetti, affinché l’ONU possa continuare a svolgere il suo importante ruolo in modo efficiente ed efficace. La Svizzera si adopera anche a favore di un’attuazione risoluta dell’Agenda 2030 per uno sviluppo sostenibile, dell’elaborazione del patto globale sulla migrazione, delle questioni umanitarie e del rafforzamento della Ginevra internazionale.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Il dibattito della 72a Assemblea generale avrà inizio il 19 settembre 2017 e durerà fino a settembre del prossimo anno. In apertura del dibattito, la presidente della Confederazione Doris Leuthard pronuncerà un discorso a nome della Svizzera, sottolineando, tra le altre cose, l’importanza di un’ONU forte allo scopo di trovare soluzioni comuni alle sfide globali, come il cambiamento climatico, la povertà, i conflitti e la migrazione. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Durante il suo soggiorno a New York, la presidente Leuthard parteciperà anche al Forum delle Nazioni Unite sul settore privato (UN Private Sector Forum), dove esponenti di primo piano del mondo della politica e dell’economia discuteranno su nuove forme di finanziamento che consentano di raggiungere gli obiettivi dell’Agenda 2030. Doris Leuthard terrà inoltre un discorso alla Columbia University. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Durante la settimana ministeriale, il consigliere federale Didier Burkhalter parteciperà, in qualità di ospite, a un evento co-organizzato dalla Svizzera sul rapporto tra la cooperazione nel settore dell'acqua e la prevenzione dei conflitti. Assisterà inoltre alla presentazione di un’iniziativa volta a sostenere gli Stati nella regolamentazione degli scambi di merci che potrebbero essere utilizzate per l’applicazione della pena di morte o a scopi di tortura. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;La segretaria di Stato Baeriswyl sarà presente a un altro evento co-organizzato dalla Svizzera sul lancio della «Roadmap per società pacifiche, giuste e inclusive» («Roadmap for Peaceful, Just and Inclusive Societies»). In questo frangente si discuterà sulle strategie nazionali per l’attuazione dell’obiettivo di sviluppo sostenibile «Pace, giustizia e istituzioni forti». &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A New York la presidente della Confederazione Doris Leuthard e il consigliere federale Didier Burkhalter avranno anche alcuni incontri bilaterali. Entrambi faranno ritorno a Berna il 20 settembre 2017, data in cui l’Assemblea federale plenaria si pronuncerà sull’elezione del nuovo consigliere federale che subentrerà a Didier Burkhalter. &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Informazione DFAE Tel. +41 58 462 31 53 info@eda.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="170414">
        <title>Apertura della 72a Assemblea generale dell’ONU</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/content/eda/it/meta/agenda/2017/9/uno-generalversammlung-new-york.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="170415">
        <title>Priorità della Svizzera per la 72a Assemblea generale dell’ONU (fr)</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/content/dam/eda/fr/documents/aktuell/agenda/72-uno-gv-prio-4pager_FR.pdf</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="170416">
        <title>Rapporto sull’attuazione delle priorità della Svizzera per la 71a Assemblea generale dell’ONU (fr)</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/content/dam/eda/fr/documents/aktuell/agenda/umsetzung-prios-uno-gv-71_FR.pdf</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions>
        <revision date="2017-09-07 13:38" type="R"/>
      </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Switzerland's priorities at the 72nd UN General Assembly</title>
      <lead>Building peace and security, especially by stepping up mediation capacity and conflict prevention, and strengthening the role of human rights are just two of the foreign policy priorities that Switzerland aims to implement during the 72nd session of the UN General Assembly. President of the Swiss Confederation Doris Leuthard, Federal Councillor Didier Burkhalter and FDFA State Secretary Pascale Baeriswyl will represent Switzerland in New York from 18 September 2017 during the high-level week that coincides with the opening of the UN General Assembly.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;On 6 September, after consulting with the parliamentary Foreign Affairs Committees, the Federal Council was informed about Switzerland's priorities for the 72nd session of the UN General Assembly, which are based on the two main strategic areas of Switzerland’s engagement at the United Nations for the 2012-22 period – peace and security, and reform of the UN. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Specific priorities include building peace and security, especially by stepping up mediation capacity and conflict prevention, and strengthening the role of human rights. In addition, Switzerland thoroughly supports the reform efforts proposed by the new UN Secretary-General António Guterres, which are vital in ensuring that the UN can continue to fulfil its important role efficiently and effectively. Switzerland is also committed to effective implementation of the 2030 Agenda for Sustainable Development, the drafting of the Global Compact for Migration, humanitarian topics and strengthening International Geneva.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The general debate of the 72nd General Assembly session begins on 19 September this year and runs until September next year. President of the Swiss Confederation Doris Leuthard will speak on behalf of Switzerland at the opening of the General Debate, where she will emphasise the importance of a strong UN in arriving at joint solutions to global challenges such as climate change, poverty, conflicts and migration. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;During her stay in New York, Leuthard will also take part in the UN Private Sector Forum at which high-level representatives from the world of politics and business meet to discuss new forms of financing towards achieving the 2030 Agenda goals. She will also give a speech at Columbia University. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;During the same week, Federal Councillor Didier Burkhalter will host an event on water cooperation and conflict prevention that has been co-organised by Switzerland. He will also take part at the launch of an initiative that aims to help states regulate the trade in goods which could be used for capital punishment and torture. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;State Secretary Baeriswyl will co-host an event launching the Roadmap for Peaceful, Just and Inclusive Societies at which national strategies for achieving the sustainable development goal of “peace, justice and strong institutions” will be discussed. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Leuthard and Burkhalter will additionally take the opportunity to conduct a number of bilateral meetings during their visit to the high-level week in New York. Both will be back in Bern on 20 September 2017, when the United Federal Assembly votes on Didier Burkhalter’s successor as federal councillor. &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>FDFA Information Tel. +41 58 462 31 53 info@eda.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="170417">
        <title>Opening of the 72nd UN General Assembly</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/content/eda/en/meta/agenda/2017/9/uno-generalversammlung-new-york.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="170418">
        <title>Switzerland's priorities for the 72nd session of the UN General Assembly (fr)</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/content/dam/eda/fr/documents/aktuell/agenda/72-uno-gv-prio-4pager_FR.pdf</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="170419">
        <title>Report on the implementation of Switzerland’s priorities for the 71th session of the UN General Assembly (fr)</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/content/dam/eda/fr/documents/aktuell/agenda/umsetzung-prios-uno-gv-71_FR.pdf</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
