<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="81865" revoked="no">
    <version>2</version>
    <pubdate>2021-01-05</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="506" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>501</department-id>
      <name lang="de">armasuisse</name>
      <name lang="fr">Armasuisse</name>
      <name lang="it">Armasuisse</name>
      <name lang="en">Armasuisse</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.ar.admin.ch/</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.ar.admin.ch/</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.ar.admin.ch/</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.ar.admin.ch/</www>
      <email lang="de">info@armasuisse.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@armasuisse.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@armasuisse.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@armasuisse.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="502" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>501</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Generalsekretariat VBS</name>
      <name lang="fr">Secrétariat général du DDPS</name>
      <name lang="it">Segreteria generale del DDPS</name>
      <name lang="en">General Secretariat DDPS</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.vbs.admin.ch/</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.vbs.admin.ch/</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.vbs.admin.ch/</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.vbs.admin.ch/</www>
      <email lang="de">postmaster.vbs@gs-vbs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">postmaster.vbs@gs-vbs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">postmaster.vbs@gs-vbs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">postmaster.vbs@gs-vbs.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="505" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>501</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Gruppe Verteidigung</name>
      <name lang="fr">Groupement de la Défense</name>
      <name lang="it">Aggruppamento Difesa</name>
      <name lang="en">Defence</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.vtg.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.vtg.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.vtg.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.vtg.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@vtg.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@vtg.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@vtg.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@vtg.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="501">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Verteidigung, Bevölkerungsschutz und Sport</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de la défense, de la protection de la population et des sports</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale della difesa, della protezione della popolazione e dello sport</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Defence, Civil Protection and Sports DDPS</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.vbs.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.vbs.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.vbs.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.vbs.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@gs-vbs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@gs-vbs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@gs-vbs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@gs-vbs.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Air2030: Bilaterale Rüstungstreffen mit Behörden und Industrieunternehmen in den Herstellerländern</title>
      <lead>Eine Delegation des VBS unter der Leitung von Rüstungschef Martin Sonderegger besucht im Januar 2021 in Paris, Berlin und Washington Vertreterinnen und Vertreter der Behörden und Industrieunternehmen, die ins Programm Air2030 involviert sind.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Grund der Besuche in Frankreich, Deutschland und den USA ist eine Besprechung zum Programm Air2030 mit Blick auf die Beschaffungen eines neuen Kampfflugzeugs (NKF) und eines neuen bodengestützten Luftverteidigungssystems grösserer Reichweite (Bodluv GR). Die Besuche sind am 5. Januar 2021 in Paris, am 21. Januar in Berlin sowie vom 25. bis 28. Januar in Washington vorgesehen. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In der Delegation von armasuisse vertreten sind nebst dem Rüstungschef Martin Sonderegger der Leiter Kompetenzbereich Luftfahrtsysteme, Peter Winter, der Projektleiter NKF, Darko Savic, sowie in Frankreich und den USA auch der Projektleiter Bodluv GR, Markus Graf.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Arbeiten an den Evaluationsberichten&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Parallel zu diesen Gesprächen laufen die Arbeiten an den Evaluationsberichten NKF und Bodluv GR. Die Evaluationsberichte sollen im 1. Quartal 2021 abgeschlossen werden. Der Typenentscheid durch den Bundesrat ist für beide Systeme im 2. Quartal 2021 vorgesehen.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Kaj-Gunnar Sievert Leiter Kommunikation armasuisse +41 58 464 62 47</contact>
      <link id="210677">
        <title>Dossier Air2030 – Schutz des Luftraumes</title>
        <uri>https://www.vbs.admin.ch/de/verteidigung/schutz-des-luftraumes.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Air2030 : réunions bilatérales sur l’armement avec les autorités et les entreprises industrielles des pays producteurs</title>
      <lead>En janvier 2021, une délégation du DDPS conduite par Martin Sonderegger, directeur général de l’armement, se rendra à Paris, Berlin et Washington pour rencontrer des représentants des autorités et des entreprises industrielles impliquées dans le programme Air2030. </lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;La raison de ces visites en France, en Allemagne et aux États-Unis est une discussion sur le programme Air2030 en vue de l’acquisition d’un nouvel avion de combat (NAC) et d’un nouveau système de défense sol-air longue portée (DSA LP). Les visites sont prévues le 5 janvier 2021 à Paris, le 21 janvier à Berlin et du 25 au 28 janvier à Washington. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Outre le directeur général de l’armement, Martin Sonderegger, le chef du domaine de compétences Systèmes aéronautiques, Peter Winter, le chef de projet NAC, Darko Savic, ainsi que le chef de projet DSA LP, Markus Graf, feront partie de la délégation d’armasuisse en France et aux États-Unis.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Travaux sur les rapports d’évaluation&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Parallèlement à ces discussions, des travaux sont en cours sur les rapports d’évaluation NAC et DSA LP. Les rapports d’évaluation doivent être finalisés au 1er trimestre 2021. La décision quant aux types retenus pour chacun des deux systèmes doit être prise par le Conseil fédéral au 2e trimestre 2021.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Kaj-Gunnar Sievert Chef de la communication d’armasuisse +41 58 464 62 47</contact>
      <link id="210678">
        <title>Dossier Air2030 – Protection de l’espace aérien</title>
        <uri>https://www.vbs.admin.ch/fr/defense/protection-espace-aerien.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Air2030: incontri bilaterali in materia di armamenti con le autorità e le imprese dell’industria dei paesi produttori</title>
      <lead>Nel gennaio 2021 una delegazione del DDPS guidata da Martin Sonderegger, capo dell’armamento, visiterà a Parigi, Berlino e Washington i rappresentanti delle autorità e delle imprese dell’industria coinvolte nel programma Air2030.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Il motivo delle visite in Francia, Germania e negli USA è una discussione sul programma Air2030 in vista dell’acquisto di un nuovo aviogetto da combattimento (NAC) e di un nuovo sistema di difesa terra-aria a lunga gittata (DTA LG). Le visite sono previste il 5 gennaio 2021 a Parigi, il 21 gennaio a Berlino e dal 25 al 28 gennaio a Washington. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Faranno parte della delegazione di armasuisse oltre al capo dell’armamento, Martin Sonderegger, il responsabile del settore di competenza Sistemi aeronautici, Peter Winter, il capoprogetto NAC, Darko Savic, nonché in Francia e negli USA il capoprogetto DTA LG, Markus Graf.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Lavori sui rapporti di valutazione&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Parallelamente a questi colloqui, sono in corso i lavori sui rapporti di valutazione NAC e DTA LG. I rapporti di valutazione verranno conclusi nel 1° trimestre del 2021. La scelta del modello da parte del Consiglio federale è prevista per entrambi i sistemi per il 2° trimestre 2021.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt; &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Kaj-Gunnar Sievert Responsabile comunicazione armasuisse +41 58 464 62 47</contact>
      <link id="210679">
        <title>Dossier Air2030 – Difesa dello spazio aereo</title>
        <uri>https://www.vbs.admin.ch/it/difesa/protezione-spazio-aereo.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Air2030: Bilateral armaments meetings with authorities and industrial companies in the manufacturer countries</title>
      <lead>A delegation from the DDPS led by National Armaments Director Martin Sonderegger will visit representatives from the authorities and industrial companies who are in-volved in the Air2030 programme in January 2021 in Paris, Berlin and Washington.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;The reason for the visits in France, Germany and the USA is to discuss the Air2030 programme, with a view to procuring a new fighter jet (NKF) and a new enhanced range ground-based air defence system (Bodluv GR). The visits are scheduled on January 5, 2021 in Paris, on January 21 in Berlin and from January 25 to 28 in Washington. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Apart from National Armaments Director Martin Sonderegger, the armasuisse delegation will also include the head of the aeronautical systems competence sector Peter Winter, the NKF project manager Darko Savic, as well as in France and the USA the Bodluv GR project manager Markus Graf.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Work on the evaluation reports&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Work on the evaluation reports NKF and Bodluv GR (new fighter aircraft and enhanced range ground-based air defence systems) will continue in parallel to these meetings. The evaluation reports should be concluded in the 1st quarter of 2021. The type decision by the Federal Council is planned for both systems in the 2nd quarter of 2021.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Kaj-Gunnar Sievert Head of Communications armasuisse +41 58 464 62 47</contact>
      <link id="210680">
        <title>Air2030 dossier – Protecting the airspace</title>
        <uri>https://www.vbs.admin.ch/de/verteidigung/schutz-des-luftraumes.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <keywords>
      <keyword id="530" org-id="505">
        <name lang="de">Luftraumsicherung</name>
        <name lang="fr">Sécurité de l'espace aérien</name>
        <name lang="it">Sicurezza dello spazio aereo</name>
        <name lang="en">Air Policing</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="5160" org-id="505">
        <name lang="de">Verteidigung</name>
        <name lang="fr">Défense</name>
        <name lang="it">Difesa</name>
        <name lang="en">defence</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="5180" org-id="505">
        <name lang="de">Armee</name>
        <name lang="fr">Armée</name>
        <name lang="it">Esercito</name>
        <name lang="en">armed forces</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="5300" org-id="505">
        <name lang="de">Unterstützung aus der Luft / Lufttransport</name>
        <name lang="fr">Appui aérien / Transport aérien</name>
        <name lang="it">Sostegno aero / Trasporto aereo</name>
        <name lang="en">aerial support / air transport</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="5310" org-id="505">
        <name lang="de">Rüstung / Beschaffung</name>
        <name lang="fr">Armement / Acquisition d'armement</name>
        <name lang="it">Armamento / Acquisto d'armamenti</name>
        <name lang="en">Armament / Procurement</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="5560" org-id="505">
        <name lang="de">Auslandsbesuch</name>
        <name lang="fr">Visite à l'étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Visita all'estero</name>
        <name lang="en">visit abroad</name>
      </keyword>
    </keywords>
    <topics>
      <topic id="3">
        <name lang="de">Armee</name>
        <name lang="fr">Armée</name>
        <name lang="it">Esercito</name>
        <name lang="en">Armed Forces</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="40">
        <name lang="de">Sicherheit</name>
        <name lang="fr">Sécurité</name>
        <name lang="it">Sicurezza</name>
        <name lang="en">Security</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
