<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="82012" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2021-01-25</pubdate>
    <blocking-period>2021-01-25</blocking-period>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="318" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>301</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Bundesamt für Statistik</name>
      <name lang="fr">Office fédéral de la statistique</name>
      <name lang="it">Ufficio federale di statistica</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Statistical Office</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.statistik.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.statistique.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.statistica.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.statistics.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@bfs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@bfs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@bfs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@bfs.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="301">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement des Innern</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'intérieur</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'interno</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Home Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Neuchâtel</city>
      <title>Zunahme der Mehrsprachigkeit in der Schweiz: 68% verwenden regelmässig mehr als eine Sprache</title>
      <lead>Mehr als zwei Drittel der Bevölkerung ab 15 Jahren in der Schweiz verwenden regelmässig mehr als eine Sprache. Damit hat der Anteil Mehrsprachiger 2019 im Vergleich zu 2014 leicht zugenommen. Englisch ist die am stärksten verbreitete Nichtlandessprache wie auch die am häufigsten gelernte Sprache in der Schweiz. Jede fünfte Person ab 25 Jahren lernt eine oder mehrere Sprachen oder vertieft ihre Sprachkenntnisse, wobei berufliche Gründe Hauptmotivation dafür sind. Das zeigen erste Ergebnisse der Erhebung zur Sprache, Religion und Kultur des Bundesamts für Statistik (BFS), die 2019 zum zweiten Mal durchgeführt wurde.</lead>
      <text link="no">Diese Medienmitteilung und weitere Informationen zum Thema finden Sie auf der Website des BFS (siehe Link unten).</text>
      <contact>Fiona Müller, BFS, Sektion Demografie und Migration, Tel.: +41 58 480 39 75, E-Mail: fiona.mueller@bfs.admin.ch Informationszentrum Sektion Demografie und Migration, Tel. +41 58 463 67 11, E-Mail: info.dem@bfs.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="211164">
        <title>Kompletter Text und Mediendossier</title>
        <uri>https://www.bfs.admin.ch/news/de/2020-0199</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Neuchâtel</city>
      <title>Le plurilinguisme gagne du terrain en Suisse: 68% de la population utilisent régulièrement plus d’une langue</title>
      <lead>En Suisse, plus de deux tiers de la population âgée de 15 ans ou plus utilisent régulièrement plus d’une langue. Entre 2014 et 2019, la part des personnes plurilingues a donc légèrement augmenté. L’anglais est la langue non nationale la plus répandue et que les gens apprennent le plus souvent en Suisse. Parmi les personnes de 25 ans ou plus, une sur cinq apprend une ou plusieurs langues ou perfectionne ses connaissances linguistiques, la principale motivation étant d’ordre professionnel. C’est ce qui ressort des premiers résultats de l’Enquête sur la langue, la religion et la culture, réalisée en 2019 pour la deuxième fois par l’Office fédéral de la statistique (OFS).</lead>
      <text link="no">Vous trouverez ce communiqué de presse et d'autres informations sur ce thème sur le site web de l'OFS (cf. lien ci-dessous).</text>
      <contact>Fiona Müller, OFS, section Démographie et migration, tél.: +41 58 480 39 75, e-mail: fiona.mueller@bfs.admin.ch Centre d’information, Section Démographie et migration, OFS, tél.: +41 58 463 67 11, e-mail: info.dem@bfs.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="211165">
        <title>Texte intégral et dossier de presse</title>
        <uri>https://www.bfs.admin.ch/news/fr/2020-0199</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Neuchâtel</city>
      <title>Aumento del plurilinguismo in Svizzera: il 68% della popolazione usa regolarmente più di una lingua</title>
      <lead>In Svizzera, oltre i due terzi della popolazione dai 15 anni in su usano regolarmente più di una lingua. Nel 2019 la quota delle persone plurilingue è lievemente aumentata rispetto al 2014. L’inglese è la lingua extranazionale più diffusa, oltre a essere quella maggiormente studiata. Una persona su cinque sopra i 25 anni impara una o più lingue o ne sta approfondendo le conoscenze, spinta prevalentemente da motivi professionali. È quanto si evince dai primi risultati dell’indagine sulla lingua, la religione e la cultura realizzata dall’Ufficio federale di statistica (UST) e che nel 2019 è giunta alla sua seconda edizione.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Il presente comunicato stampa e ulteriori informazioni sul tema sono reperibili sulla pagina Internet dell'UST (link sotto).&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Fiona Müller, UST, sezione Demografia e migrazione, tel.: +41 58 480 39 75 e-mail: fiona.mueller@bfs.admin.ch Centro informazioni, sezione Demografia e migrazione, tel.: +41 58 463 67 11, e-mail: info.dem@bfs.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="211166">
        <title>Testo integrale e dossier per i media</title>
        <uri>https://www.bfs.admin.ch/news/it/2020-0199</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Neuchâtel</city>
      <title>Increase in multilingualism in Switzerland: 68% regularly use more than one language</title>
      <lead>Over two-thirds of the population aged 15 or over in Switzerland regularly use more than one language. The percentage of multilingual persons rose slightly in 2019 compared with 2014. English is the most widely used non-national language and the language most frequently learned in Switzerland. One person in five aged 25 or over learns one or more languages or is improving their language skills with professional reasons being the main motivation. These are some of the first findings from the Federal Statistical Office’s language, religion and culture survey, which was carried out for the second time in 2019.</lead>
      <text link="no">This press release and further information on this topic can be found on the FSO website (see link below).</text>
      <contact>Fiona Müller, FSO, Demography and migration, tel.: +41 58 480 39 75, e-mail: fiona.mueller@bfs.admin.ch Information centre, Demography and migration, OFS, tel.: +41 58 463 67 11, e-mail: info.dem@bfs.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="211167">
        <title>Complete text and press kit - Please note that the English version only includes the release's lead</title>
        <uri>https://www.bfs.admin.ch/news/en/2020-0199</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="43">
        <name lang="de">Statistik</name>
        <name lang="fr">Statistiques</name>
        <name lang="it">Statistica</name>
        <name lang="en">Statistics</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
