<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="82314" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2021-02-12</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="201" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>201</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="201">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Ernennung der Schweizer Delegation beim Kongress der Gemeinden und Regionen des Europarates</title>
      <lead>Bundesrat Ignazio Cassis hat am 22. Januar 2021 die 12 Mitglieder der Schweizer Delegation beim Kongress der Gemeinden und Regionen des Europarates (KGRE) für die Amtsperiode 2021–2026 ernannt. Die Wahlvorschläge waren von der Konferenz der Kantonsregierungen (KdK), dem Schweizerischen Städteverband (SSV) und dem Schweizerischen Gemeindeverband (SGV) eingereicht worden. Nach der formellen Bestätigung durch das Kongressbüro am 12. Februar 2021 kann die neue Delegation nun ihre Arbeit im Hinblick auf die Erneuerungssession vom 23. bis 25. März 2021 aufnehmen.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Der Kongress der Gemeinden und Regionen des Europarates (KGRE) wurde in seiner heutigen Form 1994 ins Leben gerufen und hat zum Ziel, die Lokal- und Regionaldemokratie in den 47 Mitgliedsstaaten des Europarates zu stärken. Der Kongress, ein beratendes Organ, dient als Sprachrohr der regionalen und lokalen Gebietskörperschaften Europas. Er besteht aus zwei Kammern, der Kammer der Gemeinden und der Kammer der Regionen. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Zu den Aktivitäten des Kongresses gehören die Überwachung der Umsetzung der Europäischen Charta der kommunalen Selbstverwaltung (die am 17. Februar 2005 von der Schweiz ratifiziert wurde), die Beobachtung von Kommunal- und Regionalwahlen sowie weitere, thematisch breit gefächerte Tätigkeitsfelder. Die 324 ordentlichen Mitglieder des KGRE, denen ebenso viele Stellvertreterinnen und Stellvertreter zur Seite stehen, treffen sich zweimal im Jahr zu den Plenarsessionen am Sitz des Europarates in Strassburg. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Die Schweiz verfügt im Kongress über sechs ordentliche Mitglieder und sechs Stellvertreterinnen und Stellvertreter, die jeweils zur Hälfte die Kantone sowie die Gemeinden und Städte vertreten. Entsprechend dem offiziellen Nominationsverfahren waren die Konferenz der Kantonsregierungen (KdK), der Schweizerische Städteverband (SSV) und der Schweizerische Gemeindeverband (SGV) dafür zuständig, Nominationen für die neue Amtsperiode 2021–2026 vorzuschlagen. Die Schweizer Delegation wurde anschliessend vom Vorsteher des Eidgenössischen Departements für auswärtige Angelegenheiten (EDA) ernannt. Am 12. Februar 2021 hat das Kongressbüro die Zusammensetzung der neuen Delegation formell bestätigt. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Der Schweizer Delegation für die Amtsperiode 2021–2026 gehören folgende Vertreterinnen und Vertreter an: &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Für die Kantone:&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;- Herr David Eray, Minister, Staatsrat des Kantons Jura, Leiter der Delegation (Vollmitglied) &lt;br /&gt;- Frau Cornelia Komposch, Regierungsrätin des Kantons Thurgau (Vollmitglied) &lt;br /&gt;- Herr Paul Winiker, Regierungsrat des Kantons Luzern (Vollmitglied)&lt;br /&gt;- Frau Jacqueline Fehr, Regierungsrätin des Kantons Zürich (Stellvertreterin) &lt;br /&gt;- Herr Philippe Leuba, Staatsrat des Kantons Waadt (Stellvertreter) &lt;br /&gt;- Herr Didier Castella, Staatsrat des Kantons Freiburg (Stellvertreter) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Für die Gemeinden und Städte:&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;- Frau Franziska Stadelmann-Meyer, Gemeindepräsidentin von Muttenz BL (Vollmitglied) &lt;br /&gt;- Herr Laurent Wehrli, Gemeindepräsident von Montreux VD und Nationalrat (Vollmitglied) &lt;br /&gt;- Herr Beat Hirs, Gemeindepräsident von Rorschacherberg SG (Vollmitglied) &lt;br /&gt;- Herr Erich Fehr, Stadtpräsident von Biel BE (Stellvertreter)&lt;br /&gt;- Frau Christine Chevalley, Gemeindepräsidentin von Veytaux VD (Stellvertreterin) &lt;br /&gt;- Herr Matthias Gysin, Gemeinderat der Gemeinde Duggingen BL (Stellvertreter)&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Kommunikation EDA Bundeshaus West CH-3003 Bern Tel. Kommunikationsservice: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Medienstelle: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <link id="212174">
        <title>Diplomatie der Schweizer Kantone, Gemeinden und Städte in Strassburg</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home/das-eda/aktuell/newsuebersicht/2021/02/kongress-europarat.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="212123">
        <title>Kongress der Gemeinden und Regionen des Europarates (EN)</title>
        <uri>https://www.coe.int/en/web/congress/home</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="212139">
        <title>Charta Kongress der Gemeinden und Regionen des Europarates (FR)</title>
        <uri>https://rm.coe.int/CoERMPublicCommonSearchServices/DisplayDCTMContent?documentId=090000168099817e</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="212143">
        <title>Schweizer Delegation 2016-2020 - Kongress der Gemeinden und Regionen des Europarates (EN)</title>
        <uri>https://www.congressdatabase.coe.int/WebForms/Public/Country.aspx?id=11</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="212147">
        <title>Europarat</title>
        <uri>https://www.coe.int/de/web/portal/home</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="212151">
        <title>EDA Wesbseite - Europarat</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home/aussenpolitik/internationale-organisationen/europarat.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Nomination de la délégation suisse au Congrès des pouvoirs locaux et régionaux du Conseil de l’Europe</title>
      <lead>Le 22 janvier 2021, le Conseiller fédéral Ignazio Cassis a nommé les 12 membres de la délégation suisse au Congrès des pouvoirs locaux et régionaux du Conseil de l’Europe (CPLRE) pour la période 2021-2026. Les candidatures avaient été proposées par la Conférence des gouvernements cantonaux (CdC), l’Union des villes suisses (UVS) et l’Association des communes suisses (ACS). Suite à la validation formelle par le Bureau du Congrès le 12 février 2021, la nouvelle délégation peut maintenant entamer son travail en vue de la session de renouvellement du 23 au 25 mars.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Créé dans sa forme actuelle en 1994, le Congrès des pouvoirs locaux et régionaux du Conseil de l’Europe (CPLRE) est l’instance chargée de renforcer la démocratie locale et régionale dans les 47 États membres du Conseil de l’Europe. Organe consultatif, il fait office de porte-parole des régions et communes d’Europe. Il est composé de deux chambres : la Chambre des pouvoirs locaux et la Chambre des pouvoirs régionaux. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Parmi les activités du Congrès, on recense le suivi de l’application de la Charte européenne de l’autonomie locale (ratifiée par la Suisse le 17 février 2005), l’observation d’élections locales et régionales et des activités thématiques variées. Les 324 membres titulaires du CPLRE, auxquels s’ajoutent autant de suppléants, se réunissent en sessions deux fois par an au siège du Conseil de l’Europe, à Strasbourg. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;La Suisse est représentée au Congrès par six membres et autant de suppléants : six élus cantonaux et six représentants des communes et des villes. Pour la nouvelle législature 2021-2026, conformément à la procédure officielle de nomination, la Conférence des gouvernements cantonaux (CdC), l’Union des villes suisses (UVS) et l’Association des communes suisses (ACS) étaient habilitées à proposer des candidatures. La délégation suisse a ensuite été nommée par le Chef du Département fédéral des affaires étrangères (DFAE). Aujourd’hui 12 février, le Bureau du Congrès a validé aussi formellement la composition de la nouvelle délégation. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;La délégation suisse pour la période 2021-2026 est composée des représentants suivants : &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pour les cantons :&lt;br /&gt;- &lt;/strong&gt;M. David Eray, Ministre, Conseiller d’État du canton du Jura, Président de la délégation (titulaire) ; &lt;br /&gt;- Mme Cornelia Komposch, Conseillère d’État du canton de Thurgovie (titulaire) ; &lt;br /&gt;- M. Paul Winiker, Conseiller d’État du canton de Lucerne (titulaire) ;&lt;br /&gt;- Mme Jacqueline Fehr, Conseillère d’État du canton de Zurich (suppléante) ; &lt;br /&gt;- M. Philippe Leuba, Conseiller d’État du canton de Vaud (suppléant) ; &lt;br /&gt;- M. Didier Castella, Conseiller d’État du canton de Fribourg (suppléant). &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pour les communes et les villes :&lt;br /&gt;- &lt;/strong&gt;Mme Franziska Stadelmann-Meyer, Syndique de la commune de Muttenz BL (titulaire) ; &lt;br /&gt;- M. Laurent Wehrli, Syndic de la commune de Montreux VD et Conseiller national (titulaire) ; &lt;br /&gt;- M. Beat Hirs, Syndic de la commune de Rorschacherberg SG (titulaire) ; &lt;br /&gt;- M. Erich Fehr, Maire de la ville de Bienne BE (suppléant) ;&lt;br /&gt;- Mme Christine Chevalley, Syndique de la commune de Veytaux VD (suppléante) ; &lt;br /&gt;- M. Matthias Gysin, Conseiller communal de la commune de Duggingen BL (suppléant).&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Communication DFAE Palais fédéral ouest CH-3003 Berne Tél. Service de communication: +41 58 462 31 53 Tél. Service de presse: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <link id="212175">
        <title>Diplomatie des cantons, communes et villes suisses à Strasbourg</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae/dfae/aktuell/newsuebersicht/2021/02/kongress-europarat.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="212124">
        <title>Congrès des pouvoirs locaux et régionaux du Conseil de l’Europe</title>
        <uri>https://www.coe.int/fr/web/congress/home</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="212140">
        <title>Charte du Congrès des pouvoirs locaux et régionaux du Conseil de l’Europe</title>
        <uri>https://rm.coe.int/CoERMPublicCommonSearchServices/DisplayDCTMContent?documentId=090000168099817e</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="212144">
        <title>Délégation suisse 2016-2020 - Congrès des pouvoirs locaux et régionaux au Conseil de l’Europe (EN)</title>
        <uri>https://www.congressdatabase.coe.int/WebForms/Public/Country.aspx?id=11</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="212148">
        <title>Conseil de l'Europe</title>
        <uri>https://www.coe.int/fr/web/portal/home</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="212152">
        <title>Site du DFAE - Conseil de l'Europe</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae/politique-exterieure/organisations-internationales/conseil-europe.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Nomina della delegazione svizzera al Congresso dei poteri locali e regionali del Consiglio d’Europa</title>
      <lead>Il 22 gennaio 2021 il consigliere federale Ignazio Cassis ha nominato i 12 membri della delegazione svizzera al Congresso dei poteri locali e regionali del Consiglio d’Europa (CPLRE) per il periodo 2021-2026. Le candidature sono state proposte dalla Conferenza dei Governi cantonali (CdC), dall’Unione delle città svizzere (UCS) e dall’Associazione dei Comuni Svizzeri (ACS). Dopo la convalida formale da parte dell’Ufficio del Congresso il 12 febbraio 2021, la nuova delegazione può ora iniziare il suo lavoro in vista della sessione di rinnovo che si terrà dal 23 al 25 marzo prossimi.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Creato nella sua forma attuale nel 1994, il Congresso dei poteri locali e regionali del Consiglio d’Europa (CPLRE) è l’organo incaricato di rafforzare la democrazia locale e regionale nei 47 Stati membri del Consiglio d’Europa. In quanto organo consultivo, si fa portavoce delle regioni e dei Comuni europei. Il Congresso è composto da due camere: la Camera dei poteri locali e la Camera delle regioni. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Il lavoro del Congresso comprende il monitoraggio dell’applicazione della Carta europea dell’autonomia locale (ratificata dalla Svizzera il 17 febbraio 2005), l’osservazione delle elezioni locali e regionali e varie attività tematiche. I 324 membri titolari del CPLRE, a cui si aggiungono altrettanti supplenti, si riuniscono in sessioni due volte l’anno nella sede del Consiglio d’Europa a Strasburgo. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;La Svizzera è rappresentata al Congresso da sei membri e da altrettanti supplenti: sei rappresentanti cantonali e sei rappresentanti dei Comuni e delle città. Conformemente alla procedura ufficiale di nomina, per la nuova legislatura 2021-2026 la Conferenza dei Governi cantonali (CdC), l’Unione delle città svizzere (UCS) e l’Associazione dei Comuni Svizzeri (ACS) avevano la facoltà di proporre delle candidature. La delegazione svizzera è stata poi nominata dal capo del Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri (DFAE). Oggi, 12 febbraio 2021, l’Ufficio del Congresso ha convalidato formalmente la composizione della nuova delegazione. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;La delegazione svizzera per il periodo 2021-2026 è composta dai rappresentanti elencati qui di seguito. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Per i Cantoni:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;- David Eray, ministro, consigliere di Stato del Cantone del Giura, presidente della delegazione (membro titolare); &lt;br /&gt;- Cornelia Komposch, consigliera di Stato del Cantone di Turgovia (membro titolare); &lt;br /&gt;- Paul Winiker, consigliere di Stato del Cantone di Lucerna (membro titolare);&lt;br /&gt;- Jacqueline Fehr, consigliera di Stato del Cantone di Zurigo (supplente); &lt;br /&gt;- Philippe Leuba, consigliere di Stato del Cantone di Vaud (supplente); &lt;br /&gt;- Didier Castella, consigliere di Stato del Cantone di Friburgo (supplente). &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Per i Comuni e le città:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;- Franziska Stadelmann-Meyer, sindaca del Comune di Muttenz BL (membro titolare); &lt;br /&gt;- Laurent Wehrli, sindaco del Comune di Montreux VD e consigliere nazionale (membro titolare); &lt;br /&gt;- Beat Hirs, sindaco del Comune di Rorschacherberg SG (membro titolare); &lt;br /&gt;- Erich Fehr, sindaco della città di Bienne BE (supplente);&lt;br /&gt;- Christine Chevalley, sindaca del Comune di Veytaux VD (supplente); &lt;br /&gt;- Matthias Gysin, consigliere del Comune di Duggingen BL (supplente).&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Comunicazione DFAE Palazzo federale ovest CH-3003 Berna Tel. Servizio di comunicazione: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Servizio stampa: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <link id="212176">
        <title>I rappresentanti dei Cantoni, dei Comuni e delle città svizzere a Strasburgo</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae/dfae/aktuell/newsuebersicht/2021/02/kongress-europarat.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="212125">
        <title>Congresso dei poteri locali e regionali del Consiglio d’Europa (FR)</title>
        <uri>https://www.coe.int/fr/web/congress/home</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="212141">
        <title>Statuto del Congresso dei poteri locali e regionali del Consiglio d’Europa (FR)</title>
        <uri>https://rm.coe.int/CoERMPublicCommonSearchServices/DisplayDCTMContent?documentId=090000168099817e</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="212145">
        <title>Delegazione svizzera 2016-2020 - Congresso dei poteri locali e regionali del Consiglio d’Europa (EN)</title>
        <uri>https://www.congressdatabase.coe.int/WebForms/Public/Country.aspx?id=11</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="212149">
        <title>Consiglio d'Europa</title>
        <uri>https://www.coe.int/it/web/portal/home</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="212153">
        <title>Sito web del DFAE - Consiglio d'Europa</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae/politica-estera/organizzazioni-internazionali/consiglio-europa.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Appointment of the Swiss delegation to the Congress of Local and Regional Authorities of the Council of Europe</title>
      <lead>On 22 January 2021, Federal Councillor Ignazio Cassis appointed the 12 members of the Swiss delegation to the Congress of Local and Regional Authorities of the Council of Europe (hereafter the Congress) for the period 2021–26. The candidatures were proposed by the Conference of Cantonal Governments, the Swiss Union of Cities and the Association of Swiss Communes. Following formal validation by the Congress Bureau on 12 February 2021, the new delegation can now begin its work in preparation for the renewal session from 23 to 25 March.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Created in its present form in 1994, the Congress is the body responsible for strengthening local and regional democracy in the 47 member states of the Council of Europe. As a consultative body, it acts as the voice of Europe's regions and municipalities. It is composed of two chambers: the Chamber of Local Authorities and the Chamber of Regions. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Congress's activities include monitoring the application of the European Charter of Local Self-Government (ratified by Switzerland on 17 February 2005), observation of local and regional elections and various thematic activities. The Congress's 324 members and 324 substitutes meet in sessions twice a year at the Council of Europe's headquarters in Strasbourg. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Switzerland is represented at the Congress by six members and six substitutes, six of whom are elected cantonal representatives and six are elected representatives of communes and cities. For the new legislative period of 2021–26, in accordance with the official appointment procedure, the Conference of Cantonal Governments, the Swiss Union of Cities and the Association of Swiss Communes were entitled to nominate candidates. The Swiss delegation was then appointed by the head of the Federal Department of Foreign Affairs. Today, 12 February, the Congress Bureau formally validated the composition of the new delegation. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Swiss delegation for the period 2021–26 is composed of the following representatives: &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;For the cantons:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;- Mr David Eray, Minister, State Councillor of the Canton of Jura, head of delegation (representative) &lt;br /&gt;- Ms Cornelia Komposch, State Councillor of the Canton of Thurgau (representative) &lt;br /&gt;- Mr Paul Winiker, State Councillor of the Canton of Lucerne (representative)&lt;br /&gt;- Ms Jacqueline Fehr, Councillor of State of the Canton of Zurich (substitute) &lt;br /&gt;- Mr Philippe Leuba, State Councillor of the Canton of Vaud (substitute) &lt;br /&gt;- Mr Didier Castella, State Councillor of the Canton of Fribourg (substitute) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;For the communes and cities:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;- Mrs Franziska Stadelmann-Meyer, Communal President of Muttenz BL (representative) &lt;br /&gt;- Mr Laurent Wehrli, Communal President of Montreux VD and National Councillor (representative) &lt;br /&gt;- Mr Beat Hirs, Communal President of Rorschacherberg SG (representative) &lt;br /&gt;- Mr Erich Fehr, Mayor of the City of Biel-Bienne BE (substitute)&lt;br /&gt;- Ms Christine Chevalley, Communal President of Veytaux VD (substitute) &lt;br /&gt;- Mr Matthias Gysin, Member of the Communal Parliament of Duggingen BL (substitute)&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>FDFA Communication Federal Palace West Wing CH-3003 Bern, Switzerland Tel. Communication service: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Press service: +41 58 460 55 55 E-mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @SwissMFA</contact>
      <link id="212177">
        <title>Swiss cantonal, communal and city diplomacy in Strasbourg</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/fdfa/fdfa/aktuell/newsuebersicht/2021/02/kongress-europarat.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="212126">
        <title>Congress of Local and Regional Authorities of the Council of Europe</title>
        <uri>https://www.coe.int/en/web/congress/home</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="212142">
        <title>Charter of the Congress of Local and Regional Authorities of the Council of Europe (FR)</title>
        <uri>https://rm.coe.int/CoERMPublicCommonSearchServices/DisplayDCTMContent?documentId=090000168099817e</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="212146">
        <title>Swiss Delegation 2016-2020 - Congress of Local and Regional Authorities of the Council of Europe</title>
        <uri>https://www.congressdatabase.coe.int/WebForms/Public/Country.aspx?id=11</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="212150">
        <title>Council of Europe</title>
        <uri>https://www.coe.int/en/web/portal/home</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="212154">
        <title>FDFA website - Council of Europe</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/fdfa/foreign-policy/international-organizations/council-europe.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
