<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="82857" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2021-03-27</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="201" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>201</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="302" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>301</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Generalsekretariat EDI</name>
      <name lang="fr">Secrétariat général DFI</name>
      <name lang="it">Segreteria generale DFI</name>
      <name lang="en">General Secretariat FDHA</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="201">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <department id="301">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement des Innern</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'intérieur</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'interno</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Home Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Schweiz setzt sich für wirksame Rechte und echte Teilhabe von Frauen ein</title>
      <lead>Gestern Abend ging in New York die 65. Sitzung der UNO-Kommission für die Stellung der Frau (CSW) zu Ende. Die Schweiz ist erfreut, dass eine gemeinsame Schlusserklärung zustande gekommen ist und engagiert sich für die weitere Stärkung der Geschlechtergleichstellung und der Frauenrechte.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Im Rahmen der Generaldebatte äusserte Bundesrat Alain Berset seine Besorgnis darüber, dass nach Schätzungen der UNO 47 Millionen Frauen weltweit aufgrund der COVID-19-Pandemie in die extreme Armut zu rutschen drohen. «Die Fortschritte der letzten Jahrzehnte im Bereich der Geschlechtergleichstellung und der Frauenrechte sind durch die gegenwärtige Krise gefährdet», sagt Berset. «Um das zu verhindern, sind wir auf das Engagement der internationalen Gemeinschaft angewiesen». &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Die Verhandlungen über die Schlusserklärung der CSW gestalteten sich dieses Jahr besonders anspruchsvoll. Insbesondere zu den Themen sexuelle und reproduktive Gesundheit und Rechte, geschlechtsspezifische Gewalt, den Menschenrechten, Familienformen und Sexualaufklärung gingen die Meinungen weit auseinander. Umso mehr ist es als Erfolg zu werten, dass die UNO-Mitgliedstaaten eine gemeinsame Schlusserklärung verabschiedeten.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Derzeit sind in der internationalen Frauenrechtspolitik mehrere gegenläufige Tendenzen zu beobachten. So findet einerseits eine weltweite Bewegung von Zivilgesellschafts- und Jugendorganisationen zugunsten der Geschlechtergleichstellung und der Frauenrechte statt, in Form des «Generation Equality Forums». Das Forum wird von UN Women und einer grossen Zahl von Staaten mitgetragen und von Mexiko Ende März 2021 sowie von Frankreich im Juli 2021 ausgerichtet. Die Schweiz wird an beiden Anlässen teilnehmen.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Andererseits verhärten sich die Positionen von Staaten, welche der Geschlechtergleichstellung und den Frauenrechten kritisch gegenüberstehen und Fortschritte mitunter systematisch blockieren. In diesem Zusammenhang bedauert die Schweiz den während der CSW verkündeten Austritt der Türkei aus dem Übereinkommen des Europarats zur Verhütung und Bekämpfung von Gewalt gegen Frauen und häuslicher Gewalt («Istanbul-Konvention»). Die Schweiz war aktiv an der Ausarbeitung dieser Konvention beteiligt, hat diese ratifiziert und misst ihr einen hohen Stellenwert bei.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In Zukunft bleibt die Rolle der Schweiz als pragmatische Brückenbauerin von grosser Wichtigkeit. Sie wird sich weiterhin mit grossem Engagement gegen geschlechtsspezifische Gewalt, für die wirtschaftliche Stärkung der Frauen, insbesondere für Lohngleichheit, und für die gleichberechtigte und wirksame Teilhabe von Frauen am öffentlichen Leben und an Entscheidungsprozessen einsetzen. So bildet auch die Stärkung der Rolle der Frauen in der Friedens- und Sicherheitspolitik einen Schwerpunkt der Aussenpolitischen Strategie der Schweiz 2020–2023.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ein zentraler Beitrag der Schweiz an der diesjährigen CSW war die Women’s Human Rights App (W’sHR). Diese wurde im Vorfeld der CSW vollständig erneuert und neu lanciert. Die Applikation ermöglichte es den Verhandlungsteilnehmenden bereits bei der diesjährigen Ausgabe, rasch auf die wichtigsten Rechts- und Grundlagentexte in verschiedenen für die Frauenrechte und Geschlechtergleichstellung relevanten Bereichen zuzugreifen. «Die Schweiz leistet mit diesem innovativen Tool einen wichtigen Beitrag an eine effiziente UNO und stärkt damit indirekt auch deren Reformbemühungen, was ein Ziel unserer Aussenpolitik darstellt», so Markus Seiler, EDA-Generalsekretär.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Kommunikation EDA Bundeshaus West CH-3003 Bern Tel. Kommunikationsservice: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Medienstelle: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <link id="213989">
        <title>CSW65 UN Women (en und fr)</title>
        <uri>https://www.unwomen.org/en/csw/csw65-2021</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="213990">
        <title>Generation Equality Forum (en)</title>
        <uri>https://forum.generationequality.org/</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="213991">
        <title>EDA-Strategie zu Geschlechtergleichstellung und Frauenrechten</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/dam/deza/de/documents/themen/gender/strategie-gender-2017_DE.pdf</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="213995">
        <title>Women’s Human Rights App (en)</title>
        <uri>https://womenshumanrights.ch</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="213996">
        <title>Gleichstellung von Frau und Mann (DEZA)</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/deza/de/home/themen/gleichstellung_vonfrauundmann.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="214000">
        <title>Eidgenössisches Büro für die Gleichstellung von Frau und Mann EBG</title>
        <uri>https://www.ebg.admin.ch/ebg/de/home.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>La Suisse se mobilise pour la pleine participation des femmes et l’effectivité de leurs droits</title>
      <lead>La 65e session de la Commission de la condition de la femme (CSW) s'est terminée hier soir à New York. La Suisse se félicite qu’une déclaration finale conjointe ait pu être adoptée et poursuivra ses efforts pour renforcer l’égalité des genres et les droits des femmes.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Lors du débat général, le conseiller fédéral Alain Berset a exprimé son inquiétude concernant les 47 millions de femmes dans le monde qui, selon les estimations de l’ONU, risquent de basculer dans l’extrême pauvreté à cause de la pandémie de COVID 19. «Les progrès réalisés ces dernières décennies en matière d’égalité des sexes et de droits des femmes sont menacés par la crise actuelle», a déclaré Alain Berset. Il en a appelé à un engagement accru de la communauté internationale pour éviter qu’une telle situation ne se produise.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Les négociations sur la déclaration finale de la CSW se sont révélées particulièrement difficiles cette année. D’importantes divergences de vues ont notamment été enregistrées dans les domaines de la santé et des droits sexuels et reproductifs, de la violence fondée sur le genre, des droits de l’homme, des structures familiales et de l’éducation sexuelle. Le fait que les États membres de l’ONU soient parvenus à s’entendre sur une déclaration finale conjointe est donc déjà un succès en soi. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Plusieurs tendances contradictoires se dessinent aujourd’hui dans la politique internationale en matière de droits des femmes. D’un côté, nous assistons à l’émergence d’un mouvement mondial d’organisations de la société civile et de la jeunesse en faveur de l’égalité des genres et des droits des femmes qui se sont regroupées sous le nom de «Forum Génération Égalité». Ce forum, qui bénéficie du soutien d’ONU Femmes et d’un grand nombre d’États, sera lancé au Mexique fin mars 2021 et culminera à Paris en juillet 2021. La Suisse participera à ces deux événements. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;De l’autre côté, les positions des États critiques à l’égard de l’égalité des genres et des droits des femmes se durcissent et tendent à bloquer tout progrès. Dans ce registre, la Suisse regrette que la Turquie ait annoncé pendant la 65e session de la CSW son intention de se retirer de la Convention du Conseil de l’Europe sur la prévention et la lutte contre la violence à l’égard des femmes et la violence domestique («Convention d’Istanbul»). La Suisse a participé activement à l’élaboration de cet instrument, l’a ratifié et lui accorde une grande importance. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;À l’avenir, son rôle de médiatrice pragmatique restera capital. La Suisse continuera à se mobiliser avec détermination contre la violence fondée sur le genre. Elle s’attachera également à renforcer la situation économique des femmes, en particulier l’égalité salariale, et à donner aux femmes la possibilité de participer de manière effective et sur un pied d’égalité à la vie publique et aux processus décisionnels. Dans ce même esprit, le renforcement du rôle des femmes dans la politique de paix et de sécurité constitue une priorité de la stratégie de politique extérieure 2020-2023 de la Suisse. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;L’application mobile pour le renforcement des droits des femmes (Women’s Human Rights App, W’sHR) a été une contribution essentielle de la Suisse à la CSW de cette année. Lancée juste avant la session, elle aura permis aux négociateurs d’accéder rapidement aux textes juridiques et fondamentaux les plus importants dans divers domaines relatifs aux droits des femmes et à l’égalité des genres. «Avec cet outil innovant, la Suisse contribue de manière significative à l’efficacité de l’ONU et renforce ainsi indirectement ses efforts de réforme, ce qui constitue l’un des objectifs de notre politique étrangère», a déclaré Markus Seiler, secrétaire général du DFAE.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Communication DFAE Palais fédéral ouest CH-3003 Berne Tél. Service de communication: +41 58 462 31 53 Tél. Service de presse: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <link id="213989">
        <title>CSW65 UN Women (en und fr)</title>
        <uri>https://www.unwomen.org/en/csw/csw65-2021</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="213990">
        <title>Generation Equality Forum (en)</title>
        <uri>https://forum.generationequality.org/</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="213992">
        <title>Stratégie Égalité des genres et droits des femmes du DFAE</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/dam/deza/fr/documents/themen/gender/strategie-gender-2017_FR.pdf</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="213995">
        <title>Women’s Human Rights App (en)</title>
        <uri>https://womenshumanrights.ch</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="213997">
        <title>Égalité entre femmes et hommes (DDC)</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/deza/fr/home/themes-ddc/egalite-femmes-hommes.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="214001">
        <title>Bureau fédéral de l’égalité entre femmes et hommes (BFEG)</title>
        <uri>https://www.ebg.admin.ch/ebg/fr/home.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="214004">
        <title>Forum Génération Égalité</title>
        <uri>https://forum.generationequality.org/fr</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>La Svizzera si impegna per il rispetto dei diritti e la partecipazione reale delle donne</title>
      <lead>Ieri sera si è conclusa a New York la 65a sessione della Commissione delle Nazioni Unite sulla condizione delle donne (CSW). La Svizzera accoglie favorevolmente il fatto che sia stato possibile raggiungere una dichiarazione finale congiunta e si impegna a rafforzare ulteriormente l’uguaglianza di genere e i diritti delle donne.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Durante il dibattito generale il consigliere federale Alain Berset ha espresso la sua preoccupazione sul fatto che, secondo stime dell’ONU, 47 milioni di donne nel mondo rischiano di scivolare nella povertà estrema a causa della pandemia di COVID-19. «I progressi fatti negli ultimi decenni nell’ambito dell’uguaglianza di genere e dei diritti delle donne sono messi in pericolo dall’attuale crisi», ha dichiarato Berset. «Per impedirlo, dobbiamo fare affidamento sull’impegno della comunità internazionale».&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Quest’anno i negoziati sulla dichiarazione finale della CSW sono stati particolarmente impegnativi. Le opinioni erano molto contrastanti soprattutto su temi come la salute sessuale e riproduttiva e il rispetto dei diritti connessi, la violenza di genere, i diritti umani, le forme di famiglia e l’educazione sessuale. È quindi da considerare come un grande successo il fatto che gli Stati membri dell’ONU abbiano adottato una dichiarazione finale congiunta. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Attualmente, nella politica internazionale in materia dei diritti delle donne si osservano tendenze contrastanti. Da un lato è nato un movimento mondiale delle organizzazioni della società civile e dei giovani a favore dell’uguaglianza di genere e dei diritti delle donne, nella forma del «Generation Equality Forums». Il forum, finanziato da UN Women e da numerosi Stati, sarà organizzato dal Messico a fine marzo 2021 e dalla Francia a luglio 2021. La Svizzera parteciperà a entrambi gli eventi. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Dall’altro lato, si inaspriscono le posizioni degli Stati critici nei confronti dell’uguaglianza di genere e dei diritti delle donne e che bloccano sistematicamente i progressi fatti. In questo contesto la Svizzera deplora il ritiro della Turchia dalla Convenzione del Consiglio d’Europa sulla prevenzione e la lotta contro la violenza nei confronti delle donne e la violenza domestica (Convenzione di Istanbul), annunciato durante la CSW. La Svizzera ha partecipato attivamente all’elaborazione della Convenzione, che ha ratificato e alla quale attribuisce una grande importanza. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In futuro, il ruolo della Svizzera come «costruttrice di ponti» pragmatica rimarrà fondamentale. Il nostro Paese continuerà a lavorare assiduamente contro la violenza di genere, per il rafforzamento economico delle donne, in particolare per la parità salariale, e per la partecipazione paritaria ed efficace delle donne alla vita pubblica e ai processi decisionali. Il rafforzamento del ruolo delle donne nella politica di pace e di sicurezza è quindi anche una priorità della Strategia di politica estera della Svizzera 2020–2023. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Un contributo chiave della Svizzera alla CSW di quest’anno è stata l’applicazione Women’s Human Rights (W’sHR App), completamente rinnovata e rilanciata in vista della CSW. Già durante l’edizione di quest’anno, l’applicazione ha consentito ai negoziatori e alle negoziatrici di accedere rapidamente ai più importanti testi giuridici e di base in vari settori rilevanti per i diritti delle donne e l’uguaglianza di genere. «Con questo strumento innovativo la Svizzera fornisce un importante contributo all’efficienza dell’ONU e, indirettamente, rafforza anche i suoi sforzi di riforma, che è uno degli obiettivi della nostra politica estera», ha dichiarato Markus Seiler, segretario generale del Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri (DFAE). &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Comunicazione DFAE Palazzo federale ovest CH-3003 Berna Tel. Servizio di comunicazione: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Servizio stampa: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <link id="213989">
        <title>CSW65 UN Women (en und fr)</title>
        <uri>https://www.unwomen.org/en/csw/csw65-2021</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="213990">
        <title>Generation Equality Forum (en)</title>
        <uri>https://forum.generationequality.org/</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="213993">
        <title>Strategia del DFAE Uguaglianza di genere e Diritti delle donne</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/dam/deza/it/documents/themen/gender/strategie-gender-2017_IT.pdf</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="213995">
        <title>Women’s Human Rights App (en)</title>
        <uri>https://womenshumanrights.ch</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="213998">
        <title>Uguaglianza tra donne e uomini</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/deza/it/home/temi-dsc/uguaglianza-donna-uomo.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="214002">
        <title>Ufficio federale per l'uguaglianza fra donna e uomo</title>
        <uri>https://www.ebg.admin.ch/ebg/it/home.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="214005">
        <title>Generation Equality Forum (fr)</title>
        <uri>https://forum.generationequality.org/fr</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Switzerland calls for full, equal and meaningful participation and rights of women</title>
      <lead>Yesterday marked the final sitting of the 65th session of the UN Commission on the Status of Women (CSW) in New York. Switzerland is pleased that agreed conclusions were adopted, and reiterates its commitment to further advancing gender equality and women's rights.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;During the general debate, Federal Councillor Alain Berset expressed his concern about the number of women at risk of being driven into extreme poverty as a result of the COVID-19 pandemic. The UN estimates that 47 million women worldwide are affected. "This crisis threatens to undo the progress made in gender equality in recent decades," he stated. "Stemming this backward trend will require a determined commitment from the international community."&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Negotiating this year's agreed conclusions proved to be particularly challenging. Opinions diverged widely, particularly on such issues as sexual and reproductive health and rights, gender-based violence, human rights, family structures and sexual education. This makes the adoption of agreed conclusions by the UN member states even more of an achievement. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Women's rights policy at global level is currently experiencing several opposing trends. At one end of the spectrum is a global movement driven by civil society and youth organisations working for gender equality and women's rights, the Generation Equality Forum. It is being co-sponsored by UN Women and a large number of states, and will be hosted by Mexico in late March 2021 and France in July 2021. Switzerland is also taking part in both events. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;At the other end, states with a critical stance on gender equality and women's rights are hardening their positions and often systematically blocking progress. Switzerland regrets Turkey's decision to withdraw from the Council of Europe Convention on preventing and combating violence against women and domestic violence (Istanbul Convention), announced during the CSW. Switzerland played an active role in drafting the Convention, which it has ratified and attaches great importance to. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Switzerland's pragmatic approach as a bridge builder will continue to play an important role in this area. Switzerland remains strongly committed to combating gender-based violence and to promoting women's economic empowerment, particularly equal pay. It will also continue to strive for full, equal and meaningful participation of women in the public sphere and in decision-making processes. To this end, the empowerment of women in peace and security policy is one of the priorities set out in Switzerland's Foreign Policy Strategy 2020–23. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Switzerland made a key contribution to this year's CSW in the form of the Women's Human Rights App (W'sHR), which was revamped and relaunched in the run-up to the session. The current edition of the app gives negotiators quick access to key legal texts and basic documents covering various areas relating to women's rights and gender equality. "The innovative app is an important contribution for the efficient functioning of the UN, so adds indirectly to its reform efforts. This is also one of Switzerland's foreign policy goals", explained FDFA Secretary General Markus Seiler.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>FDFA Communication Federal Palace West Wing CH-3003 Bern, Switzerland Tel. Communication service: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Press service: +41 58 460 55 55 E-mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @SwissMFA</contact>
      <link id="213989">
        <title>CSW65 UN Women (en und fr)</title>
        <uri>https://www.unwomen.org/en/csw/csw65-2021</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="213990">
        <title>Generation Equality Forum (en)</title>
        <uri>https://forum.generationequality.org/</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="213994">
        <title>FDFA Strategy on Gender equality and Women's rights</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/dam/deza/en/documents/themen/gender/strategie-gender-2017_EN.pdf</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="213995">
        <title>Women’s Human Rights App (en)</title>
        <uri>https://womenshumanrights.ch</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="213999">
        <title>Gender equality</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/deza/en/home/themes-sdc/gender-equality.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="214003">
        <title>Federal Office for Gender Equality</title>
        <uri>https://www.ebg.admin.ch/ebg/en/home.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="5">
        <name lang="de">Behörden</name>
        <name lang="fr">Autorités</name>
        <name lang="it">Autorità</name>
        <name lang="en">Authorities</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="10">
        <name lang="de">Bundesrat</name>
        <name lang="fr">Conseil fédéral</name>
        <name lang="it">Consiglio federale</name>
        <name lang="en">Federal Council</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
