<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="83223" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2021-04-22</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="1063" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>701</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Paul Scherrer Institut</name>
      <name lang="fr">Institut Paul Scherrer</name>
      <name lang="it">Istituto Paul Scherrer</name>
      <name lang="en">Paul Scherrer Institut</name>
      <www lang="de"/>
      <www lang="fr"/>
      <www lang="it"/>
      <www lang="en"/>
      <email lang="de">info@psi.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@psi.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@psi.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@psi.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="701">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Wirtschaft, Bildung und Forschung</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'économie, de la formation et de la recherche</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'economia, della formazione e della ricerca</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Economic Affairs, Education and Research</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Villigen</city>
      <title>Einmalig scharfer Röntgenblick</title>
      <lead>Forschenden des Paul Scherrer Instituts PSI ist es erstmals gelungen, mit der Methode des Transient Grating Spectroscopy ins Innere von Stoffen zu blicken. Dazu nutzten sie die Röntgenstrahlen des SwissFEL. Das Experiment am PSI ist ein Meilenstein, um Vorgänge in der Welt der Atome zu beobachten. Ihre Forschungsergebnisse veröffentlichen die Forschenden heute im Fachblatt Nature Photonics.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Die Strukturen auf Mikrochips werden immer winziger, Festplatten schreiben ganze Enzyklopädien auf fingernagelgrosse magnetische Scheiben: Viele Technologien durchbrechen derzeit die Grenzen der klassischen Physik. Doch in der Nanowelt gelten andere Gesetze – die der Quantenphysik. Und dort sind noch viele Fragen offen: Wie wandert eigentlich Wärme durch ein Halbleitermaterial? Was passiert genau, wenn einzelne Bits in eine Computerfestplatte magnetisiert werden? Auf viele dieser und vieler anderer Fragen gibt es noch keine Antworten, hauptsächlich weil die üblichen experimentellen Methoden nicht tief und genau genug in die Werkstoffe schauen können und weil manche Vorgänge viel zu schnell für herkömmliche Experimentierverfahren ablaufen. Wenn man aber die technische Miniaturisierung weitertreiben will, muss man solche Phänomene auf atomarer Ebene verstehen. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Der Methodenmix macht's &lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Frischen Wind in die Sache bringt nun eine neue Methode, die sich Cristian Svetina vom PSI ausgedacht hat, gemeinsam mit Jeremy Rouxel und Majed Chergui an der EPFL in Lausanne, Keith Nelson am MIT in den USA, Claudio Masciovecchio am Fermi-FEL in Italien sowie weiteren internationalen Partnern. „Obwohl, neu ist die Methode eigentlich nicht, sie wird seit Jahrzehnten im optischen Bereich mit grossen Erfolgen eingesetzt“, sagt Svetina, der am PSI derzeit die neue Experimentierstation Furka an der Strahllinie Athos am SwissFEL aufbaut. Das Besondere sei die Kombination und Erweiterung bekannter Methoden aus der nichtlinearen Laserphysik, aber eben mit dem Röntgenlicht aus dem neuen Freie-Elektronen-Röntgenlaser SwissFEL. In dieser Kombination ist das sowohl neu als auch überraschend. Zahlreiche andere Forscherteams weltweit haben Versuche unternommen, allerdings ohne Erfolg. Zuletzt wurden sogar Zweifel laut, ob diese neuen Experimente bei den hohen Energien von Röntgenstrahlung überhaupt erfolgreich sein können. Das Team am PSI hat bewiesen: Ja, es geht. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Im Kern handelt es sich um ein Verfahren, das sich im Englischen Transient Grating Spectroscopy nennt, was übersetzt so viel wie Übergangsgitter-Spektroskopie bedeutet. Unter Spektroskopie fassen die Physiker einen bewährten Strauss an Methoden zusammen, um Informationen über ein Material zu gewinnen, etwa aus welchen chemischen Elementen und Verbindungen es besteht, welche magnetischen Eigenschaften es besitzt oder wie sich die Atome darin bewegen. Bei der speziellen Variante der Transient Grating Spectroscopy wird die Probe mit zwei Laserstrahlen beschossen, die ein Interferenzmuster erzeugen. Ein dritter Laserstrahl wird an diesem Muster gebeugt, wodurch ein vierter Strahl entsteht, der die Informationen über die Eigenschaften der Probe enthält. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Unter die Oberfläche schauen&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Mit dem Begriff Laser wird dabei immer Licht im sichtbaren oder im infraroten Bereich des Wellenlängenspektrums bezeichnet. Laser können in eine Probe nur mit einer begrenzten Auflösung von Hunderten Nanometern hineinschauen. Deshalb benötigt man Röntgenstrahlen. Den Forschern am PSI ist es nun erstmals gelungen, die Transient Grating Spectroscopy auch für einen Röntgenlaser zugänglich zu machen und das gleich mit sehr harten Röntgenstrahlen mit einer Energie von 7,1 Kiloelektronenvolt, was einer Wellenlänge von 0,17 Nanometern, also etwa dem Durchmesser mittelgrosser Atome entspricht. Der Vorteil: Erstmals ist es möglich, in Werkstoffe hineinzuschauen, mit einer Auflösung bis hinunter zu einzelnen Atomen, mit ultrakurzen Belichtungszeiten von Bruchteilen von Femtosekunden (eine millionstel Milliardstelsekunde). Das erlaubt es sogar, Videos von atomaren Vorgängen aufzunehmen. Ausserdem ist die Methode elementselektiv, das heisst, man kann gezielt bestimmte chemische Elemente in einem Gemisch aus Stoffen vermessen. Die Methode ergänzt andere Techniken wie die inelastische Streuung mit Röntgenstrahlung und Neutronen um eine bessere Auflösung bei Zeit und Energie. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Konkret sieht der Versuchsaufbau so aus: Der SwissFEL schickt einen Strahl mit einem Durchmesser von 0,2 Millimetern aus ultrakurzen Röntgenpulsen auf ein Gitter aus Diamant, das unter dem Mikroskop wie ein feiner Kamm aussieht. Diamant deshalb, weil er auch von energiereichen Röntgenstrahlen nicht zerstört wird. Das Gitter wurde eigens von Christian David vom Labor für Mikro- und Nanotechnologie am PSI hergestellt. Die Zinken des Kamms haben einen Abstand von zwei Mikrometern. Sie zerlegen den Röntgenstrahl in feine Teilstrahlen, die sich hinter dem Gitter überlagern und so das Beugungsmuster des Transient Grating erzeugen. Hinter dem Gitter kann man Eins-zu-eins-Abbildungen des Gitters beobachten, die sich in regelmässigen Abständen – den sogenannten Talbot-Ebenen – wiederholen. Platziert man eine Probe in einer dieser Ebenen, werden einige Atome darin angeregt, gerade so, als würde sie an der Stelle des Gitters sitzen. Dabei werden nur die Atome angeregt, die die Röntgenstrahlen in dieser periodischen Modulation "sehen", während die Nachbaratome, die die Bestrahlung nicht erfahren, im Grundzustand bleiben. Das ist der Clou der Methode, denn so können die Forscher charakteristische Bereiche selektiv anregen.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Kamera mit Blitzlicht&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Die Anregung der Atome allein liefert aber noch keine Informationen. Dazu braucht es eine Art Kamera mit einem Blitz, der die Probe kurz belichtet. Das übernimmt bei der Transient Grating Spectroscopy ein Laser, der schräg auf die Probe zielt und minimal zeitverzögert zu dem Röntgenstrahl aus dem SwissFEL Bilder schiesst. Die Information kommt hinten aus der Probe heraus und trifft auf einen Detektor, der das Bild aufnimmt. In den ersten Experimenten hat sich ein Vorteil der Methode gezeigt: Sie erzeugt kein unerwünschtes Hintergrundsignal. „Wenn die Atome angeregt sind, sieht man ein Signal, sind sie nicht angeregt, sieht man nichts“, erläutert Svetina. Das ist äusserst wertvoll bei Messungen an Proben, die nur schwache Signale aussenden. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Dass Cristian Svetina und sein Team geschafft haben, was anderen Forschenden nicht gelungen ist, liegt an der Kreativität und Geduld der Protagonisten. „Wir sind schrittweise vorgegangen und wollten nicht alles auf einmal versuchen“, sagt der Physiker. Vor fünf Jahren haben die Forschenden ihre Experimente mit sichtbarem Licht begonnen und auf extremes ultraviolettes Licht ausgedehnt, bevor sie am PSI zu Röntgenlicht übergingen. Hier, anstatt gleich „echte“ Proben zu untersuchen, haben sie mit Goldfolien getestet, ob die Energie ausreicht, um Atome anzuregen. Dabei gelang es, das Gittermuster aus einer Talbot-Ebene in die Folie zu brennen. Svetina: „Da wussten wir: Wenn wir sogar Strukturen drucken können, können wir mit geringerer Intensität auch Atome anregen.“ Der Weg war damit frei für das mittlerweile gelungene Experiment. An einer Probe aus Bismut-Germanat konnten die Forschenden zeigen, dass die Methode alle Hoffnungen bezüglich Auflösung, Messtempo und Elementselektivität erfüllt. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Nächstes Ziel: Alles mit Röntgenstrahlen&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Der letzte Schritt steht allerdings noch aus. Bisher handelt es sich nur bei dem Strahl, der die Probe anregt, um einen Röntgenstrahl. Der Blitz der Kamera kommt nach wie vor aus einem Laser, ist also sichtbares Licht. Der Gipfel wäre erreicht, wenn auch das ein Röntgenstrahl wäre. Svetina: „Diesen finalen Schritt wollen wir im Lauf des Jahres machen.“ Dabei bekommen sie weitere Unterstützung: Die Institute LCLS-SLAC und PULSE, beide in Stanford, Kalifornien, SPRING8-RIKEN in Japan und FLASH-DESY in Deutschland haben sich dem Team angeschlossen.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Ihre Ergebnisse veröffentlichen die Forschenden heute im Fachmagazin &lt;i&gt;Nature Photonics&lt;/i&gt;. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Text: Bernd Müller&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Über das PSI&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; Das Paul Scherrer Institut PSI entwickelt, baut und betreibt grosse und komplexe Forschungsanlagen und stellt sie der nationalen und internationalen Forschungsgemeinde zur Verfügung. Eigene Forschungsschwerpunkte sind Materie und Material, Energie und Umwelt sowie Mensch und Gesundheit. Die Ausbildung von jungen Menschen ist ein zentrales Anliegen des PSI. Deshalb sind etwa ein Viertel unserer Mitarbeitenden Postdoktorierende, Doktorierende oder Lernende. Insgesamt beschäftigt das PSI 2100 Mitarbeitende, das damit das grösste Forschungsinstitut der Schweiz ist. Das Jahresbudget beträgt rund CHF 400 Mio. Das PSI ist Teil des ETH-Bereichs, dem auch die ETH Zürich und die ETH Lausanne angehören sowie die Forschungsinstitute Eawag, Empa und WSL.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Originalveröffentlichung&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Hard X-ray Transient Grating Spectroscopy on Bismuth Germanate&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt; Jeremy R. Rouxel, Danny Fainozzi, Roman Mankowsky, Benedikt Rosner, Gediminas Seniutinas, Riccardo Mincigrucci, Sara Catalini, Laura Foglia, Riccardo Cucini, Florian Doring, Adam Kubec, Frieder Koch, Filippo Bencivenga, Andre Al Haddad, Alessandro Gessini, Alexei A. Maznev, Claudio Cirelli, Simon Gerber, Bill Pedrini, Giulia F. Mancini, Elia Razzoli, Max Burian, Hiroki Ueda, Georgios Pamfilidis,Eugenio Ferrari, Yunpei Deng, Aldo Mozzanica, Philip Johnson, Dmitry Ozerov, Maria Grazia Izzo,Cettina Bottari, Christopher Arrell, Edwin James Divall, Serhane Zerdane, Mathias Sander, Gregor Knopp,Paul Beaud, Henrik Till Lemke, Chris J. Milne, Christian David, Renato Torre, Majed Chergui, Keith A.Nelson, Claudio Masciovecchio, Urs Staub, Luc Patthey and Cristian Svetina&lt;br /&gt;&lt;i&gt;Nature Photonics, &lt;/i&gt;22.04.2021&lt;br /&gt;DOI: https://dx.doi.org/10.1038/s41566-021-00797-9&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Dr. Mirjam van Daalen Verantwortliche für Kommunikation Paul Scherrer Institut 5232 Villigen PSI Telefon: +41 56 310 56 74 mirjam.vandaalen@psi.ch</contact>
      <link id="215035">
        <title>Bilder und weitere Informationen</title>
        <uri>http://psi.ch/de/node/44815</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Villigen</city>
      <title>Une vision par rayons X d’une netteté unique</title>
      <lead>Des chercheurs de l’Institut Paul Scherrer PSI ont réussi pour la première fois à regarder à l’intérieur de substances au moyen de la méthode de la transient grating spectroscopy. Pour ce faire, ils ont utilisé les rayons X du Swissfel. L’expérience réalisée au PSI est une étape importante pour observer des processus dans le monde des atomes. Les scientifiques publient aujourd’hui leurs résultats dans la revue spécialisée Nature Photonics.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Les structures sur les puces électroniques deviennent de plus en plus minuscules. Les disques durs enregistrent des encyclopédies entières sur des disques magnétiques de la taille d'un ongle. De nombreuses technologies franchissent actuellement les limites de la physique classique. D’autres lois s’appliquent toutefois dans le nanomonde, celles de la physique quantique. Et beaucoup de questions y sont encore ouvertes. Comment la chaleur se déplace-t-elle à travers un matériau semi-conducteur? Que se passe-t-il exactement quand différents bits sont magnétisés sur le disque dur d’un ordinateur? De nombreuses questions n’ont pas encore trouvé de réponse parce que les méthodes expérimentales habituelles ne permettent pas de visualiser les matériaux de manière suffisamment profonde et exacte et parce que certains processus se déroulent beaucoup trop rapidement pour les procédés expérimentaux conventionnels. Si l’on veut poursuivre la miniaturisation technique, il faut toutefois comprendre ces phénomènes à l’échelle atomique. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Le mélange des méthodes est efficace&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Une nouvelle méthode imaginée par Cristian Svetina du PSI, en collaboration avec avec Jeremy Rouxel et Majed Chergui de l’EPFL à Lausanne, Keith Nelson du MIT aux USA, Claudio Masciovecchio au Fermi FEL en Italie ainsi que d’autres partenaires internationaux, apporte une bouffée d’air frais dans ce domaine. «Dans les faits, la méthode n’est pas vraiment nouvelle. Elle est utilisée depuis des décennies et avec beaucoup de succès dans le secteur de l’optique», souligne Cristian Svetina, qui met actuellement en place au PSI la station expérimentale Furka à la ligne de faisceaux Athos du SwissFEL. Ce qui est particulier, selon le chercheur, c’est la combinaison et l’extension de méthodes connues de la physique des lasers, mais grâce justement aux rayons X du laser à rayons X à électrons libres SwissFEL. Dans cette combinaison, c’est à la fois nouveau et surprenant. De nombreuses autres équipes dans le monde entier ont fait des essais, mais sans succès. Au point que le doute est né sur la possibilité de réussite de ces nouvelles expériences avec les hautes énergies du rayonnement X. L’équipe du PSI l’a prouvé: oui, c’est possible. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Il s’agit pour l’essentiel d’un procédé appelé &lt;i&gt;transient grating spectroscopy&lt;/i&gt; en anglais, ce que l’on peut traduire par spectroscopie de réseau transitoire. Sous le terme de spectroscopie, les physiciens rassemblent une palette éprouvée de méthodes, afin d’obtenir des informations sur un matériau, par exemple de quels éléments chimiques et liaisons il est composé, quelles propriétés magnétiques il possède ou comment les atomes s’y meuvent. Avec la &lt;i&gt;transient grating spectroscopy&lt;/i&gt;, l’échantillon est bombardé par deux faisceaux laser qui produisent un motif d’interférence. Un troisième faisceau laser est diffracté sur ce motif, ce qui crée un quatrième faisceau qui contient les informations sur les caractéristiques de l’échantillon. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Regarder sous la surface&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Le terme de laser décrit toujours une lumière dans le domaine visible ou infrarouge du spectre des longueurs d’onde. Les lasers ne permettent de regarder à l’intérieur d’un échantillon qu’avec une résolution limitée de quelques centaines de nanomètres. C’est pourquoi il est nécessaire d’avoir recours à des rayons X. Les chercheurs du PSI ont maintenant pour la première fois réussi à rendre la &lt;i&gt;transient grating spectroscopy&lt;/i&gt; également accessible pour un laser à rayons X et cela avec des rayons X très durs ayant une énergie de 7,1 kilo-électronvolts, ce qui correspond à une longueur d’onde de 0,17 nanomètre, soit environ le diamètre d’un atome de taille moyenne. L’avantage, c’est qu’il est ainsi pour la première fois possible de regarder à l’intérieur de matériaux avec une résolution atteignant l’échelle de l’atome, avec des temps d’exposition ultracourts de l’ordre de fractions de femtosecondes (un millionième de milliardième de seconde). Cela permet même de réaliser des vidéos de processus atomiques. La méthode est par ailleurs sélective, ce qui signifie que l’on peut mesurer de manière ciblée certains éléments chimiques dans un mélange de substances. La méthode complète des techniques comme la diffusion inélastique de rayons X et de neutrons pour une meilleure résolution en temps et en énergie. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Concrètement, l’installation d’essai est la suivante: SwissFEL envoie un faisceau d’un diamètre de 0,2 millimètre constitué d’impulsions de rayons X ultra-courtes sur une grille en diamant qui ressemble sous le microscope à un peigne fin. On utilise du diamant car celui-ci n’est pas détruit même par des rayons X riches en énergie. La grille a été fabriquée par Christian David du Laboratoire de micro- et nanotechnologie du PSI. Les dents du peigne ont un espace de deux micromètres entre elles. Elles découpent le faisceau de rayons X en de fins faisceaux qui se superposent derrière la grille, créant ainsi le motif de diffraction du &lt;i&gt;transient grating. &lt;/i&gt;Derrière la grille, il est possible d’observer des images exactes de la grille qui se répètent à des distances régulières – ce qu’on appelle les plans Talbot. Si l’on place un échantillon sur un de ces plans, quelques-uns des atomes sont excités de la même manière que s’ils se trouvaient au même emplacement que la grille. Seuls les atomes qui «voient» les rayons X dans cette modulation périodique sont excités, alors que les atomes voisins qui ne sont pas soumis au rayonnement restent dans leur état initial. Il s’agit là du clou de la méthode, car les chercheurs peuvent ainsi exciter des secteurs caractéristiques de manière sélective.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Caméra avec flash&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;A elle seule, l’excitation des atomes ne fournit pas encore d’informations. Pour cela, il est nécessaire d’avoir recours à une sorte de caméra avec flash qui éclaire brièvement l’échantillon. Dans le cadre de la &lt;i&gt;transient grating spectroscopy&lt;/i&gt;, cette mission est assumée par un laser qui vise l’échantillon de manière oblique et prend des images dans un délai minimal par rapport au faisceau de rayons X du SwissFEL. L’information vient de l’arrière de l’échantillon et arrive sur un détecteur qui enregistre l’image. Lors des premières expériences, un des avantages de la méthode s’est manifesté: elle ne produit pas de signal de fond indésirable. «Lorsque les atomes sont excités, on voit un signal, s’ils ne le sont pas, on ne voit rien», explique Cristian Svetina. Cela est extrêmement précieux lors de mesures sur des échantillons qui n’émettent que de faibles signaux. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Le fait que Cristian Svetina et son équipe aient réussi là où d’autres ont échoué tient à la créativité et à la patience des protagonistes. «Nous avons procédé par étapes et nous n’avons pas voulu tout essayer en même temps», note le physicien. Il y a cinq ans, les chercheurs ont commencé leurs expériences avec de la lumière visible et les ont ensuite étendues à de la lumière ultraviolette avant de passer à la lumière des rayons X. Et au lieu d’analyser tout de suite de «vrais» échantillons, ils ont d’abord cherché, au moyen de feuilles d’or, à savoir si l’énergie suffisait à exciter des atomes. Il a ainsi été possible de brûler dans la feuille un motif de grille d’un plan Talbot. «Nous avons alors su que si nous pouvions imprimer des structures, nous pouvions aussi exciter des atomes avec une intensité plus faible», précise le scientifique. La voie était ainsi libre pour l’expérience qui a entre-temps réussi. En utilisant un échantillon de germanate de bismuth, les chercheurs ont pu montrer que la méthode répondait à tous les espoirs en matière de résolution, de rythme des mesures et de sélection des éléments.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Prochain objectif: tout au moyen des rayons X&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;La prochaine étape doit toutefois encore être réalisée. Pour l’instant, seul le faisceau qui excite l’échantillon est un faisceau de rayons X. Le flash de la caméra est toujours issu d’un laser, c’est donc de la lumière visible. Le sommet serait atteint s’il s’agissait ici aussi d’un faisceau de rayons X. «Nous voulons franchir cette étape finale au cours de cette année», affirme Cristian Svetina. Pour cela, les chercheurs bénéficieront d’un soutien supplémentaire. Les instituts LCLS-SLAC et PULSE, tous les deux à Stanford en Californie, SPRING8-RIKEN au Japon et FLASH-DESY en Allemagne ont rejoint l’équipe.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Les chercheurs publient aujourd’hui leurs résultats dans la revue spécialisée &lt;i&gt;Nature Photonics&lt;/i&gt;. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Texte: Bernd Müller&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;À propos du PSI&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; L'Institut Paul Scherrer PSI développe, construit et exploite des grandes installations de recherche complexes et les met à la disposition de la communauté scientifique nationale et internationale. Les domaines de recherche de l'institut sont centrés sur la matière et les matériaux, l'énergie et l'environnement ainsi que la santé humaine. La formation des générations futures est un souci central du PSI. Pour cette raison, environ un quart de nos collaborateurs sont des postdocs, des doctorants ou des apprentis. Au total, le PSI emploie 2100 personnes, étant ainsi le plus grand institut de recherche de Suisse. Le budget annuel est d'environ CHF 400 millions. Le PSI fait partie du domaine des EPF, les autres membres étant l'ETH Zurich, l'EPF Lausanne, l'Eawag (Institut de Recherche de l'Eau), l'Empa (Laboratoire fédéral d'essai des matériaux et de recherche) et le WSL (Institut fédéral de recherches sur la forêt, la neige et le paysage).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Publication originale&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Hard X-ray Transient Grating Spectroscopy on Bismuth Germanate&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt; Jeremy R. Rouxel, Danny Fainozzi, Roman Mankowsky, Benedikt Rosner, Gediminas Seniutinas, Riccardo Mincigrucci, Sara Catalini, Laura Foglia, Riccardo Cucini, Florian Doring, Adam Kubec, Frieder Koch, Filippo Bencivenga, Andre Al Haddad, Alessandro Gessini, Alexei A. Maznev, Claudio Cirelli, Simon Gerber, Bill Pedrini, Giulia F. Mancini, Elia Razzoli, Max Burian, Hiroki Ueda, Georgios Pamfilidis,Eugenio Ferrari, Yunpei Deng2, Aldo Mozzanica, Philip Johnson, Dmitry Ozerov, Maria Grazia Izzo,Cettina Bottari, Christopher Arrell, Edwin James Divall, Serhane Zerdane, Mathias Sander, Gregor Knopp,Paul Beaud, Henrik Till Lemke, Chris J. Milne, Christian David, Renato Torre, Majed Chergui, Keith A.Nelson, Claudio Masciovecchio, Urs Staub, Luc Patthey and Cristian Svetina&lt;br /&gt;&lt;i&gt;Nature Photonics, &lt;/i&gt;22.04.2021&lt;br /&gt; DOI: https://dx.doi.org/10.1038/s41566-021-00797-9&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Dr. Mirjam van Daalen Responsable de la communication Paul Scherrer Institut CH-5232 Villigen PSI Téléphone: +41 56 310 56 74 mirjam.vandaalen@psi.ch</contact>
      <link id="215036">
        <title>Images et informations supplémentaires</title>
        <uri>http://psi.ch/fr/node/44815</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Villigen</city>
      <title>Uniquely sharp X-ray view</title>
      <lead>Researchers at the Paul Scherrer Institute PSI have succeeded for the first time in looking inside materials using the method of transient grating spectroscopy with ultrafast X-rays at SwissFEL. The experiment at PSI is a milestone in observing processes in the world of atoms. The researchers are publishing their research results today in the journal Nature Photonics.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;The structures on microchips are becoming ever tinier; hard disks write entire encyclopedias on magnetic disks the size of a fingernail. Many technologies are currently breaking through the boundaries of classical physics. But in the nanoworld, other laws apply – those of quantum physics. And there are still many unanswered questions: How does heat actually travel through a semiconductor material at the nanoscale? What exactly happens when individual bits are magnetised in a computer hard disk, and how fast can we write? There are still no answers to these and many more questions mainly because current experimental techniques cannot look deeply and precisely enough into the materials and because some processes take place far too quickly for conventional experimental methods. But if we want to push ahead with technical miniaturisation, we need to understand such phenomena at the atomic level. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;The mix of methods makes the difference &lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Fresh impetus is now being brought to the matter thanks to a new method devised by PSI researcher Cristian Svetina, together with Jeremy Rouxel and Majed Chergui at EPFL in Lausanne, Keith Nelson at MIT in the USA, Claudio Masciovecchio at Fermi FEL in Italy, and other international partners. "The method is actually not new, though, and it has been used for decades in the optical regime with exceptional results," says Svetina, who is currently setting up the new Furka experiment station on the SwissFEL beamline Athos at PSI. What is special, he says, is the combination and extension of known methods from nonlinear laser physics, but using X-ray light from the new X-ray free-electron laser SwissFEL. This combination is both new and surprising. Several attempts have been made in the past by many groups around the world but without success. It has even been questioned whether such novel experiments could be successfully conducted at all at the high energies of X-rays. The team at PSI has proven: Yes, it can be done. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;At its core, this is a method called transient grating spectroscopy. Spectroscopy is a proven set of methods used by physicists to obtain information about a material, such as the chemical elements and compounds it consists of, its magnetic properties, and how atoms move within it. In the particular variant called transient grating spectroscopy, the sample is bombarded with two laser beams that create an interference pattern. A third laser beam is diffracted at this pattern, creating a fourth beam that contains the information about the sample's properties. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Looking beneath the surface&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The term laser is always used to describe light in the visible or infrared range of the wavelength spectrum. Therefore lasers can look inside a sample only with resolution limited to hundreds of nanometres. To go beyond this, X-rays are needed. Researchers at PSI have now succeeded for the first time in making transient grating spectroscopy accessible to an X-ray laser, using very hard X-rays with an energy of 7.1 kiloelectronvolts, which corresponds to a wavelength of 0.17 nanometres, or about the diameter of medium-sized atoms. The advantage: For the first time, it is possible to look inside materials with a resolution down to individual atoms as well as with ultrashort exposure times of fractions of femtoseconds (one millionth of a billionth of a second), which even allows videos of atomic processes to be recorded. In addition, the method is element-selective, meaning that one can selectively measure specific chemical elements in a mixture of substances. The method complements well established techniques such as inelastic neutron and X-ray scattering, adding better resolution in terms of both time and energy. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;In practice, the experimental setup looks like this: SwissFEL sends a beam with a diameter of 0.2 millimetres, consisting of ultrashort X-ray pulses, onto a transmission phase grating made of diamond, which looks like a fine comb under the microscope. Diamond is used because it is not destroyed even by high-energy X-rays. It was made especially for this experiment by Christian David of the Laboratory for Micro and Nanotechnology at PSI. The spacing between the teeth of the comb is two micrometres, but this can go down to nanometres if needed. They break the X-ray beam into fine partial beams that overlap behind the grating, thus creating the transient grating diffraction pattern. Behind the grating, one-to-one images of the grating can be observed, repeated at regular intervals – so-called Talbot planes. If you place a sample in one of these planes, some atoms within it become excited, just as if it was sitting at the location of the grating. Only the atoms that "see" the X-rays in this periodic modulation are excited, while the neighbours that don’t experience the irradiation remain in the ground state. This is the chief attraction of the method, since it enables researchers to selectively excite characteristic domains of interest. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Camera with flash&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Excitation of the atoms alone, however, does not provide any information. For this, a kind of camera with a flash is needed to briefly expose the sample. In transient grating spectroscopy, this is done by a laser that targets the sample at an angle and shoots images with a minimal time delay to the X-ray beam from SwissFEL. The information comes out of the back of the sample and hits a detector that records the image. Initial experiments have shown one advantage of the method: It does not produce any unwanted background signal. "If the atoms are excited, you see a signal; if they are not excited, you see nothing," Svetina explains. This is extremely valuable when measuring samples that emit only weak signals and that cannot be seen with other techniques where a background obscures the signal.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The fact that Cristian Svetina and his team have managed to do what other researchers have not is due to the creativity and patience of the protagonists. "We proceeded step by step and did not want to try everything at once," says the physicist. Five years ago the researchers started experimenting at FERMI FEL with optical light and extended it to extreme ultraviolet light before moving on to X-rays at PSI. Here, instead of examining "real" samples right away, they used gold foils to test whether the energy was sufficient to excite atoms. They succeeded in burning the lattice pattern from a Talbot plane into the foil. Svetina: "That's when we knew: If we can even print structures, we can excite atoms with lower intensity." With this the way was clear for the now successful experiment. Using a sample of bismuth germanate, the researchers were able to show that the method fulfilled all their hopes in terms of spatial and temporal resolution, measurement speed, and element selectivity. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Next goal: everything with X-rays&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;However, the researchers have not yet taken the final step. So far, only the beam that excites the sample is an X-ray beam. The flash of the camera still comes from a laser, so it is visible light. The pinnacle would be reached if that too were an X-ray beam. Svetina: "We want to take this final step in the course of the year." And they have additional support: SLAC's LCLS and the PULSE Institute, both at Stanford in California, the RIKEN SPring-8 centre in Japan, and DESY's FLASH in Germany have joined the collaboration team.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The researchers are publishing their results today in the journal &lt;i&gt;Nature Photonics&lt;/i&gt;. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Text: Bernd Müller&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;About PSI&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; The Paul Scherrer Institute PSI develops, builds and operates large, complex research facilities and makes them available to the national and international research community. The institute's own key research priorities are in the fields of matter and materials, energy and environment and human health. PSI is committed to the training of future generations. Therefore about one quarter of our staff are post-docs, post-graduates or apprentices. Altogether PSI employs 2100 people, thus being the largest research institute in Switzerland. The annual budget amounts to approximately CHF 400 million. PSI is part of the ETH Domain, with the other members being the two Swiss Federal Institutes of Technology, ETH Zurich and EPFL Lausanne, as well as Eawag (Swiss Federal Institute of Aquatic Science and Technology), Empa (Swiss Federal Laboratories for Materials Science and Technology) and WSL (Swiss Federal Institute for Forest, Snow and Landscape Research).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Original publication&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Hard X-ray Transient Grating Spectroscopy on Bismuth Germanate&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt; Jeremy R. Rouxel, Danny Fainozzi, Roman Mankowsky, Benedikt Rosner, Gediminas Seniutinas, Riccardo Mincigrucci, Sara Catalini, Laura Foglia, Riccardo Cucini, Florian Doring, Adam Kubec, Frieder Koch, Filippo Bencivenga, Andre Al Haddad, Alessandro Gessini, Alexei A. Maznev, Claudio Cirelli, Simon Gerber, Bill Pedrini, Giulia F. Mancini, Elia Razzoli, Max Burian, Hiroki Ueda, Georgios Pamfilidis,Eugenio Ferrari, Yunpei Deng, Aldo Mozzanica, Philip Johnson, Dmitry Ozerov, Maria Grazia Izzo,Cettina Bottari, Christopher Arrell, Edwin James Divall, Serhane Zerdane, Mathias Sander, Gregor Knopp,Paul Beaud, Henrik Till Lemke, Chris J. Milne, Christian David, Renato Torre, Majed Chergui, Keith A.Nelson, Claudio Masciovecchio, Urs Staub, Luc Patthey and Cristian Svetina&lt;br /&gt;&lt;i&gt;Nature Photonics, &lt;/i&gt;22.04.2021&lt;br /&gt; DOI: https://dx.doi.org/10.1038/s41566-021-00797-9&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Dr. Mirjam van Daalen Head of Communications Paul Scherrer Institute CH-5232 Villigen PSI Phone: +41 56 310 56 74 mirjam.vandaalen@psi.ch</contact>
      <link id="215037">
        <title>Images and additional information</title>
        <uri>http://psi.ch/en/node/44815</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="19">
        <name lang="de">Medien</name>
        <name lang="fr">Médias</name>
        <name lang="it">Media</name>
        <name lang="en">Media</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
