<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="83346" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2021-05-10</pubdate>
    <blocking-period>2021-05-10</blocking-period>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="318" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>301</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Bundesamt für Statistik</name>
      <name lang="fr">Office fédéral de la statistique</name>
      <name lang="it">Ufficio federale di statistica</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Statistical Office</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.statistik.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.statistique.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.statistica.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.statistics.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@bfs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@bfs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@bfs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@bfs.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="301">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement des Innern</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'intérieur</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'interno</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Home Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Neuchâtel</city>
      <title>Medizinisch unterstützte Fortpflanzung im Jahr 2019 - Anteil der Mehrlingsgeburten nach In-vitro-Behandlungen geht zurück</title>
      <lead>Im Jahr 2019 wurden in der Schweiz 5993 Paare im Rahmen der medizinisch unterstützten Fortpflanzung mit In-vitro-Methoden behandelt. In der Folge gab es 2080 Geburten. Der Anteil der Mehrlingsgeburten nach In-vitro-Behandlungen lag 2016 noch bei 16% und ist 2019 auf 6% zurückgegangen. Die Zahl der Lebendgeborenen ist im Verhältnis zur Anzahl behandelter Frauen des Kalenderjahres in den letzten zehn Jahren von 30% im Jahr 2009 auf 37% im Jahr 2019 angestiegen. Soweit die wichtigsten Ergebnisse des Bundesamtes für Statistik (BFS) zur medizinisch unterstützten Fortpflanzung im Jahr 2019.</lead>
      <text link="no">Diese Medienmitteilung und weitere Informationen zum Thema finden Sie auf der Website des BFS (siehe Link unten).</text>
      <contact>Tonia Rihs, BFS, Sektion Gesundheit der Bevölkerung, Tel.: +41 58 460 59 50, E-Mail: tonia.rihs@bfs.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="215302">
        <title>Kompletter Text und Mediendossier</title>
        <uri>https://www.bfs.admin.ch/news/de/2021-0241</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Neuchâtel</city>
      <title>Procréation médicalement assistée en 2019 - Diminution des naissances multiples après fécondation in vitro</title>
      <lead>En 2019, 5993 couples ont suivi un traitement de procréation médicalement assistée par fécondation in vitro en Suisse. Ces traitements ont abouti à 2080 naissances. La part des naissances multiples après fécondation in vitro, qui était encore de 16% en 2016, est descendue à 6% en 2019. Quant au nombre de naissances vivantes par rapport au nombre de femmes traitées durant l’année civile considérée, il est passé de 30% en 2009 à 37% en 2019. Ce sont-là les principaux résultats publiés par l’Office fédéral de la statistique (OFS) sur la procréation médicalement assistée en 2019. </lead>
      <text link="no">Vous trouverez ce communiqué de presse et d'autres informations sur ce thème sur le site web de l'OFS (cf. lien ci-dessous).</text>
      <contact>Tonia Rihs, OFS, section Santé de la population, tel.: +41 58 460 59 50, e-mail: tonia.rihs@bfs.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="215303">
        <title>Texte intégral et dossier de presse</title>
        <uri>https://www.bfs.admin.ch/news/fr/2021-0241</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Neuchâtel</city>
      <title>Procreazione medicalmente assistita nel 2019 - Calo della quota di parti gemellari in seguito a trattamenti di procreazione assistita in vitro</title>
      <lead>Nel 2019, in Svizzera, 5993 coppie si sono sottoposte a trattamenti che prevedevano metodi di procreazione medicalmente assistita in vitro. Tali trattamenti hanno dato luogo a 2080 parti. La quota di parti gemellari in seguito a trattamenti in vitro, ancora pari al 16% nel 2016, nel 2019 si attestava al 6%. Rispetto al numero di donne sottoposte a trattamento nell’arco dell’anno civile, negli ultimi dieci anni il numero di nati vivi è aumentato, passando dal 30% nel 2009 al 37% nel 2019. Questi sono i più importanti risultati dell’Ufficio federale di statistica (UST) sulla procreazione medicalmente assistita nel 2019. </lead>
      <text link="no">Il presente comunicato stampa e ulteriori informazioni sul tema sono reperibili sulla pagina Internet dell'UST (link sotto).</text>
      <contact>Tonia Rihs, UST, sezione Salute della popolazione, tel.: +41 58 460 59 50, e-mail: tonia.rihs@bfs.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="215304">
        <title>Testo integrale e dossier per i media</title>
        <uri>https://www.bfs.admin.ch/news/it/2021-0241</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Neuchâtel</city>
      <title>Assisted reproductive technology in 2019 - Percentage of multiple births following in vitro treatments declines</title>
      <lead>In 2019, 5993 couples wishing to have children were treated using medically assisted reproduction with in vitro methods. These treatments resulted in 2080 births. The percentage of multiple births following in vitro treatments was 16% in 2016; in 2019 this had fallen to 6%. The number of live births in proportion to the number of women treated in the calendar year has increased in the past ten years from 30% in 2009 to 37% in 2019. These are the main findings of the Federal Statistical Office (FSO) on assisted reproductive technology in 2019.</lead>
      <text link="no">This press release and further information on this topic can be found on the FSO website (see link below).</text>
      <contact>Tonia Rihs, FSO, Population Health, tel.: +41 58 460 59 50, e-mail: tonia.rihs@bfs.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="215305">
        <title>Complete text and press kit - Please note that the English version only includes the release's lead</title>
        <uri>https://www.bfs.admin.ch/news/en/2021-0241</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="15">
        <name lang="de">Gesundheit</name>
        <name lang="fr">Santé</name>
        <name lang="it">sanità</name>
        <name lang="en">Health</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="41">
        <name lang="de">Soziales</name>
        <name lang="fr">Social</name>
        <name lang="it">Opere sociali</name>
        <name lang="en">Social Affairs</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="43">
        <name lang="de">Statistik</name>
        <name lang="fr">Statistiques</name>
        <name lang="it">Statistica</name>
        <name lang="en">Statistics</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
