<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="84416" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2021-07-12</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="201" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>201</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="502" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>501</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Generalsekretariat VBS</name>
      <name lang="fr">Secrétariat général du DDPS</name>
      <name lang="it">Segreteria generale del DDPS</name>
      <name lang="en">General Secretariat DDPS</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.vbs.admin.ch/</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.vbs.admin.ch/</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.vbs.admin.ch/</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.vbs.admin.ch/</www>
      <email lang="de">postmaster.vbs@gs-vbs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">postmaster.vbs@gs-vbs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">postmaster.vbs@gs-vbs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">postmaster.vbs@gs-vbs.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="505" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>501</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Gruppe Verteidigung</name>
      <name lang="fr">Groupement de la Défense</name>
      <name lang="it">Aggruppamento Difesa</name>
      <name lang="en">Defence</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.vtg.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.vtg.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.vtg.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.vtg.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@vtg.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@vtg.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@vtg.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@vtg.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="201">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <department id="501">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Verteidigung, Bevölkerungsschutz und Sport</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de la défense, de la protection de la population et des sports</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale della difesa, della protezione della popolazione e dello sport</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Defence, Civil Protection and Sports DDPS</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.vbs.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.vbs.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.vbs.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.vbs.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@gs-vbs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@gs-vbs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@gs-vbs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@gs-vbs.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Covid-19: Schweiz schickt medizinische Hilfsgüter für über 850'000 Franken in die Mongolei</title>
      <lead>Die Schweiz hilft der Mongolei im Kampf gegen die Covid-19-Pandemie. Die Humanitäre Hilfe des Bundes hat am Montag, 12. Juli 2021, 40 Beatmungsgeräte und 45 Sauerstoffkonzentratoren im Wert von rund 850'000 Franken nach Ulaanbaatar geschickt.</lead>
      <text link="no">In Anbetracht der gravierenden Gesundheitssituation in der Mongolei und als Antwort auf das Hilfsersuchen der mongolischen Behörden hat die Humanitäre Hilfe des Bundes beschlossen, die Mongolei im Kampf gegen die Covid-19-Pandemie zu unterstützen.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Ein Flugzeug des Lufttransportdiensts des Bundes ist am Montag von Dübendorf nach Ulaanbaatar gestartet. Zur Hilfslieferung gehören neben 40 Beatmungsgeräten, die kostenlos von der Armeeapotheke zur Verfügung gestellt wurden, auch 45 Sauerstoffkonzentratoren.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Das Material wird in Ulaanbaatar von den örtlichen Behörden in Empfang genommen und anschliessend auf die verschiedenen Standorte verteilt, insbesondere an Spitäler, die auf die Versorgung von Frauen und Kindern spezialisiert sind. Die Schweizer Vertretung in der Mongolei steht in engem Kontakt mit den lokalen Behörden, um eine bedarfsgerechte und faire Verteilung der Hilfsgüter nach humanitären Prinzipien sicherzustellen.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Die Mongolei gehört zu den Schwerpunktländern der Schweizer Direktion für Entwicklung und Zusammenarbeit (DEZA). Zusätzlich zu dieser Hilfsgüterlieferung stellt die DEZA 150'000 Franken für den Kauf von drei Röntgengeräten für das Gesundheitsministerium bereit.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Grosse Unterstützung der Schweiz für Asien zur Bekämpfung von Covid-19&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Bei der heutigen Lieferung in die Mongolei handelt es sich um die vierte Hilfsgüterlieferung der Schweiz nach Asien innerhalb weniger Wochen. Die beim EDA angegliederte Humanitäre Hilfe des Bundes hat bereits 13 Tonnen Hilfsgüter nach Indien (06.05.2021), 30 Tonnen Hilfsgüter nach Nepal (21.05.2021) und 16 Tonnen Hilfsgüter nach Sri Lanka (07.06.2021) geschickt. Die Schweiz verfolgt die Entwicklung der Gesundheitssituation in der Welt im Zusammenhang mit der Covid-19-Pandemie laufend und ist bereit, im Rahmen des Möglichen und auf entsprechende Ersuchen Unterstützung zu leisten.</text>
      <contact>Kommunikation EDA Bundeshaus West CH-3003 Bern Tel. Kommunikationsservice: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Medienstelle: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>COVID-19 en Mongolie – La Suisse envoie du matériel sanitaire pour un montant de plus de 850'000 francs</title>
      <lead>La Suisse aide la Mongolie dans la lutte contre la pandémie de COVID-19. L’Aide humanitaire de la Confédération a envoyé à Oulan Bator, ce lundi 12 juillet, 40 respirateurs et 45 concentrateurs d’oxygène pour une valeur totale avoisinant les 850'000 francs.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Face à la situation sanitaire qui prévaut en Mongolie, et en réponse à la demande d’aide faite par les autorités mongoles, l’Aide humanitaire de la Confédération a décidé d’apporter son soutien à ce pays dans la lutte contre la pandémie de Covid-19.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Un avion du Service de transport aérien de la Confédération a décollé ce lundi de Dübendorf en direction de Oulan Bator. Outre les 40 respirateurs mis à disposition gratuitement par la Pharmacie de l’Armée, la cargaison comprend également 45 concentrateurs d’oxygène.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Ce matériel sera réceptionné à Oulan Bator par les autorités locales, puis acheminé sur les différents sites, en particulier dans les hôpitaux spécialisés dans les soins pour femmes et enfants. La représentation suisse en Mongolie est en contact étroit avec les autorités afin de garantir que les biens humanitaires soient distribués de manière équitable et selon les besoins, conformément aux principes humanitaires.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;La Mongolie fait partie des pays prioritaires de la Direction du développement et de la coopération (DDC). En plus de cette livraison de matériel, la DDC a également octroyé un montant de 150'000 francs pour l’acquisition de trois appareils de radiographie pour le compte du Ministère de la santé.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fort soutien de la Suisse en Asie pour lutter contre le COVID-19&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;La cargaison envoyée ce lundi en Mongolie représente la quatrième livraison de matériel humanitaire de la Suisse à destination de l’Asie en l’espace de quelques semaines. L’Aide humanitaire de la Confédération, qui est rattachée au DFAE, a ainsi déjà envoyé 13 tonnes de matériel de secours en Inde (06.05.2021), 30 tonnes au Népal (21.05.2021) ainsi que 16 tonnes au Sri Lanka (07.06.2021). La Suisse suit en permanence l’évolution de la situation sanitaire dans le monde, dans le contexte de la pandémie de Covid-19. Elle se tient prête à apporter son soutien dans la mesure du possible et en fonction des demandes qui lui sont adressées.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Communication DFAE Palais fédéral ouest CH-3003 Berne Tél. Service de communication: +41 58 462 31 53 Tél. Service de presse: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>COVID-19 in Mongolia: la Svizzera invia materiale medico-sanitario per oltre 850 000 franchi</title>
      <lead>Per aiutare la Mongolia a lottare contro la pandemia di COVID-19, oggi, lunedì 12 luglio 2021, l’Aiuto umanitario della Confederazione ha inviato a Ulan Bator 40 respiratori e 45 concentratori di ossigeno per un valore complessivo di circa 850 000 franchi.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Alla luce della situazione medico-sanitaria in Mongolia e per rispondere all’appello lanciato dalle autorità mongole, l’Aiuto umanitario della Confederazione ha deciso di sostenere questo Paese nella lotta contro la pandemia di COVID-19.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Un velivolo del Servizio di trasporto aereo della Confederazione è decollato oggi da Dübendorf con destinazione Ulan Bator. Oltre a 40 respiratori messi a disposizione gratuitamente dalla Farmacia dell’esercito, la spedizione comprende anche 45 concentratori di ossigeno.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Questo materiale sarà preso in consegna a Ulan Bator dalle autorità locali e poi trasportato verso varie località, in particolare negli ospedali specializzati per le cure delle donne e dei bambini. La rappresentanza svizzera in Mongolia è in stretto contatto con le autorità del Paese per garantire che gli aiuti umanitari siano distribuiti in modo equo e secondo i bisogni, conformemente ai principi umanitari.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;La Mongolia è un Paese prioritario della Direzione dello sviluppo e della cooperazione (DSC). Oltre a questa fornitura di materiale, la DSC ha inoltre stanziato un importo di 150 000 franchi destinato all’acquisto di tre apparecchi per radiografie per conto del Ministero della sanità mongolo.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Grande sostegno della Svizzera in Asia per lottare contro la COVID-19&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Il materiale inviato questo lunedì in Mongolia è la quarta fornitura di beni umanitari della Svizzera inviata in Asia nello spazio di poche settimane. L’Aiuto umanitario della Confederazione, che fa parte del DFAE, ha infatti già destinato 13 tonnellate di materiale di soccorso in India (6.5.2021), 30 tonnellate in Nepal (21.5.2021) e 16 tonnellate in Sri Lanka (7.6.2021). La Svizzera segue con attenzione l’evolversi della situazione sanitaria mondiale legata alla pandemia di COVID-19 ed è pronta a fornire il suo sostegno per quanto possibile e in funzione delle richieste.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Comunicazione DFAE Palazzo federale ovest CH-3003 Berna Tel. Servizio di comunicazione: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Servizio stampa: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>COVID-19 in Mongolia – Switzerland sends medical assistance worth CHF 850,000</title>
      <lead>Switzerland is helping Mongolia to fight the COVID-19 pandemic. On Monday 12 July, Swiss Humanitarian Aid sent 40 respirators and 45 oxygen concentrators to Ulaanbaatar with a total value of around CHF 850,000.</lead>
      <text link="no">In view of the public health situation in Mongolia and in response to a request for assistance from the Mongolian authorities, Swiss Humanitarian Aid has decided to support the country in its efforts to combat the COVID-19 pandemic.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;A Federal Air Transport Service plane left Dübendorf on Monday for Ulaanbaatar. In addition to the 40 respirators provided by the Swiss Armed Forces Pharmacy, the shipment also includes 45 oxygen concentrators.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The equipment will be received in Ulaanbaatar by the local authorities and then transported to various sites, in particular to hospitals specialising in care for women and children. The Swiss representation in Mongolia is in close contact with the authorities to ensure that humanitarian goods are distributed fairly based on need, in accordance with humanitarian principles.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Mongolia is a priority country of the Swiss Agency for Development and Cooperation (SDC). In addition to this equipment, the SDC has also donated CHF 150,000 to the Mongolian Ministry of Health for the purchase of three X-ray machines.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Strong Swiss support to combat COVID-19 in Asia&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The shipment sent to Mongolia on Monday is the fourth delivery of humanitarian goods from Switzerland to Asia in the past few weeks. Swiss Humanitarian Aid, which is part of the FDFA, has already sent 13 tonnes of relief supplies to India (06.05.2021), 30 tonnes to Nepal (21.05.2021) and 16 tonnes to Sri Lanka (07.06.2021). Switzerland is constantly monitoring the health situation worldwide in the context of the COVID-19 pandemic. It stands ready to respond to requests for support wherever possible.</text>
      <contact>FDFA Communication Federal Palace West Wing CH-3003 Bern, Switzerland Tel. Communication service: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Press service: +41 58 460 55 55 E-mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @SwissMFA</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
