<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="85823" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2021-11-11</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="201" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>201</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="201">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Verzicht auf das House of Switzerland 2022 in China</title>
      <lead>Vom 4. Februar bis zum 13. März 2022 finden in China die 24. Olympischen und Paralympischen Winterspiele statt. Angesichts der Unsicherheiten rund um die Austragungsform und der zu erwartenden Massnahmen im Zusammenhang mit der Bekämpfung der Covid-19-Pandemie in China, hat das Eidgenössische Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten (EDA) entschieden auf eine Präsenz vor Ort in Form des House of Switzerland zu verzichten. </lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Die Schweiz wird an den kommenden Winterspielen in China kein House of Switzerland betreiben. Aufgrund der Gesundheitsmassnahmen und Einschränkungen im Rahmen der Bekämpfung der Covid-19-Pandemie sieht sich das EDA gezwungen, auf das House of Switzerland zu verzichten. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Das von Präsenz Schweiz normalerweise organisierte House of Switzerland fördert als Kommunikations- und Netzwerkplattform während der Dauer der Spiele traditionell die Kenntnisse über die Schweiz in den Bereichen Wirtschaft, Wissenschaft und Tourismus und ist Ort des Austausches zwischen unterschiedlichen Besuchergruppen. In Zusammenarbeit mit Swiss Olympic und Swiss Paralympic finden im House of Switzerland jeweils die Medaillenfeiern der Schweizer Athletinnen und Athleten mit anschliessenden Pressekonferenzen statt. Durch die zu erwartenden Massnahmen wie Bewegungseinschränkung und Ausschluss von internationalem Publikum, wird eine erfolgreiche Durchführung des House of Switzerland im ursprünglichen Sinn in Peking nicht möglich sein. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Dies ist die zweite pandemiebedingte Absage eines House of Switzerland bei Olympischen und Paralympischen Spielen, nach dem Verzicht in Tokio im Sommer 2021. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Durch den jetzigen Projektstopp wird der finanzielle Aufwand von 4,7 Millionen Franken auf 1,3 Millionen Franken reduziert. Somit wird die Wahrung der finanziellen Interessen des Bundes bestmöglich sichergestellt. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Für Rückfragen:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Botschafter Nicolas Bideau&lt;br /&gt;Chef Präsenz Schweiz&lt;br /&gt;Tel. +41 79 667 69 15&lt;br /&gt;nicolas.bideau@eda.admin.ch &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Kommunikation EDA Bundeshaus West CH-3003 Bern Tel. Kommunikationsservice: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Medienstelle: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Annulation de la House of Switzerland en Chine en 2022</title>
      <lead>La 24e édition des Jeux olympiques et paralympiques d’hiver se déroulera en Chine du 4 février au 13 mars 2022. Compte tenu des incertitudes entourant l’organisation de la manifestation et des mesures attendues dans le cadre de la lutte contre la pandémie de COVID-19 en Chine, le Département fédéral des affaires étrangères (DFAE) a renoncé au déploiement d’une House of Switzerland en Chine. </lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;La Suisse n’organisera pas de House of Switzerland lors des prochains Jeux olympiques d’hiver en Chine. Les mesures sanitaires et les restrictions imposées dans le cadre de la lutte contre la pandémie de COVID-19 ont contraint le DFAE à renoncer à la mise en place d’une House of Switzerland. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;La House of Switzerland, une plateforme de communication et de réseautage habituellement mise sur pied par Présence Suisse pendant la durée des Jeux, a pour objectif de renforcer l’image de la Suisse sur les plans économique, scientifique et touristique, et constitue un lieu d’échange pour les différents groupes de visiteurs. Elle accueille également les conférences de presse et les cérémonies organisées en l’honneur des médaillés suisses, en collaboration avec Swiss Olympic et Swiss Paralympic. Compte tenu des mesures attendues, telles que la restriction des déplacements et l’exclusion du public international, il ne sera pas possible de mettre en place à Pékin une House of Switzerland assumant correctement sa mission. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Après l’annulation de Tokyo en été 2021, c’est la deuxième fois que le DFAE doit renoncer, pour cause de pandémie, à déployer une House of Switzerland dans le cadre des Jeux olympiques et paralympiques. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;L’interruption du projet à ce stade permettra de ramener à 1,3 million de francs les dépenses fixées initialement à 4,7 millions de francs. Cette décision permet de protéger au mieux les intérêts financiers de la Confédération. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pour tout renseignement, veuillez vous adresser à:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Nicolas Bideau, ambassadeur&lt;br /&gt;Chef Présence Suisse&lt;br /&gt;Tél. +41 79 667 69 15&lt;br /&gt;nicolas.bideau@eda.admin.ch &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Communication DFAE Palais fédéral ouest CH-3003 Berne Tél. Service de communication: +41 58 462 31 53 Tél. Service de presse: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Annullata la House of Switzerland in Cina nel 2022</title>
      <lead>Dal 4 febbraio al 13 marzo 2022 si terrà in Cina la 24a edizione dei Giochi olimpici e paralimpici invernali. Considerate le incertezze riguardo alla modalità di svolgimento della manifestazione e le possibili misure per contrastare la pandemia di COVID-19, il Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri (DFAE) ha deciso di rinunciare alla propria presenza in loco con la House of Switzerland. </lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;In occasione dei prossimi Giochi olimpici invernali in Cina, la Svizzera rinuncerà alla House of Switzerland. Il DFAE si vede costretto a prendere questa decisione a causa delle misure sanitarie e delle restrizioni imposte dalla lotta contro la pandemia di COVID-19. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;La House of Switzerland, generalmente organizzata da Presenza Svizzera, è una piattaforma di comunicazione e networking che, durante i Giochi, punta a far conoscere la Svizzera sotto diversi aspetti – dall’economia alla scienza e al turismo – e a promuovere il dialogo tra diversi gruppi di visitatori. In collaborazione con Swiss Olympic e Swiss Paralympic, la House of Switzerland ospita tradizionalmente i festeggiamenti per le medaglie delle atlete e degli atleti svizzeri, seguiti da conferenze stampa. A causa delle misure previste, come le restrizioni alla mobilità e l’esclusione del pubblico internazionale, una presenza della House of Switzerland a Pechino secondo i piani originari non sarà possibile. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Si tratta della seconda cancellazione di una House of Switzerland durante i Giochi olimpici e paralimpici dopo quella di Tokyo nell’estate del 2021. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Con l’annullamento del progetto in questa fase, le spese diminuiranno da 4,7 milioni a 1,3 milioni di franchi. Gli interessi finanziari della Confederazione saranno così salvaguardati nel miglior modo possibile. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Per maggiori informazioni:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ambasciatore Nicolas Bideau&lt;br /&gt;Capo Presenza Svizzera&lt;br /&gt;Tel. +41 79 667 69 15&lt;br /&gt;nicolas.bideau@eda.admin.ch &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Comunicazione DFAE Palazzo federale ovest CH-3003 Berna Tel. Servizio di comunicazione: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Servizio stampa: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Cancellation of House of Switzerland 2022 in China</title>
      <lead>From 4 February to 13 March 2022, China will host the 24th Winter Olympic and Paralympic Games. In view of the uncertainties surrounding the format of the event in China and anticipated measures in connection with the COVID-19 pandemic, the FDFA has decided to forgo a physical presence in the form of the House of Switzerland. </lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Switzerland will not have a House of Switzerland at the upcoming Winter Olympic Games in China. Owing to the public health measures and restrictions to combat the COVID-19 pandemic, the FDFA has seen itself obliged to forgo the House of Switzerland. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The House of Switzerland is a communication and networking platform normally organised by Presence Switzerland for the duration of the Olympics to raise awareness of Swiss business, science and tourism, and a place where various groups of visitors can meet and network. In cooperation with Swiss Olympic and Swiss Paralympic, the medal ceremonies for Swiss athletes are held at the House of Switzerland followed by a press conference. Owing to anticipated public health measures such as restricted movement and the exclusion of international spectators, it will not be possible for the House of Switzerland project in Beijing to go ahead as originally planned.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is the second time that a House of Switzerland at the Olympic and Paralympic Games has been cancelled, after Switzerland decided not to proceed with its planned presence in summer 2021 in Tokyo.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Stopping the current project will reduce Switzerland's spending from CHF 4.7 million to CHF 1.3 million and is therefore fully in keeping with the financial interests of the Confederation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;For further information:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ambassador Nicolas Bideau&lt;br /&gt;Head of Presence Switzerland&lt;br /&gt;Tel. +41 79 667 69 15&lt;br /&gt;nicolas.bideau@eda.admin.ch&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>FDFA Communication Federal Palace West Wing CH-3003 Bern, Switzerland Tel. Communication service: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Press service: +41 58 460 55 55 E-mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @SwissMFA</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
