<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="85832" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2021-11-11</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="1047" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>701</department-id>
      <name lang="de">AGROSCOPE</name>
      <name lang="fr">AGROSCOPE</name>
      <name lang="it">AGROSCOPE</name>
      <name lang="en">AGROSCOPE</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.agroscope.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.agroscope.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.agroscope.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.agroscope.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de"/>
      <email lang="fr"/>
      <email lang="it"/>
      <email lang="en"/>
    </originator>
    <department id="701">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Wirtschaft, Bildung und Forschung</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'économie, de la formation et de la recherche</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'economia, della formazione e della ricerca</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Economic Affairs, Education and Research</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Thomas Gentil wird stellvertretender Leiter von Agroscope</title>
      <lead>Neues Mitglied der Geschäftsleitung von Agroscope: Thomas Gentil wird ab 1. März 2022 stellvertretender Leiter Agroscope und Leiter der Einheit Ressourcen. Zuletzt war er beim Bundesamt für Polizei fedpol verantwortlich für die Unternehmensentwicklung. </lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Thomas Gentil wird als Leiter Ressourcen mit rund 130 Mitarbeitenden die Fachbereiche Informatik, Infrastruktur, Finanzen, Human Resources und Recht führen. Zudem wird der 37-jährige Jurassier Stellvertreter von Leiterin Eva Reinhard und Mitglied der Geschäftsleitung von Agroscope. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Parlamentsdienste, BAG und fedpol &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Thomas Gentil hat an den Universitäten Lausanne und Bern Politikwissenschaften studiert. Nach seinem beruflichen Einstieg in die Bundesverwaltung bei den Parlamentsdiensten war er beim Bundesamt für Gesundheit zunächst als wissenschaftlicher Mitarbeiter und nach einem Abschluss als Master of Advanced Studies in Public Administration (MPA) als Sektionschef tätig. 2014 wechselte er ins fedpol. Dort war er zuletzt als Leiter der Unternehmensentwicklung, in enger Zusammenarbeit mit der Geschäftsleitung, verantwortlich für die Strategieentwicklung und die Steuerung des Projektportfolios.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Die neue Standortstrategie von Agroscope mit dem Campus in Posieux, zwei Forschungszentren in Zürich-Reckenholz und Changins sowie verschiedenen Versuchsstationen führt auch innerhalb der Einheit Ressourcen zu Veränderungen. Agroscope ist überzeugt, dass Thomas Gentil diese mit seiner bisherigen Erfahrung, seinen vielfältigen Kompetenzen und seiner Motivation für Weiterentwicklungen erfolgreich angehen wird. Er übernimmt seine Aufgaben am 1. März 2022. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Thomas Gentil wohnt mit seiner Familie im Kanton Freiburg. &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Marc Andrey Leiter Kommunikation Agroscope, Schwarzenburgstrasse 161, 3003 Bern marc.andrey@agroscope.admin.ch, +41 79 335 92 75 Mediendienst Agroscope media@agroscope.admin.ch +41 58 466 88 62 www.agroscope.ch | gutes Essen, gesunde Umwelt</contact>
      <attachment id="223073">
        <title>Thomas Gentil (Photo: Martine Wolhauser)</title>
        <format>jpg</format>
        <size-kb>2169</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/68909.jpg</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Thomas Gentil nommé responsable suppléant d’Agroscope</title>
      <lead>Nouveau membre du comité de direction d’Agroscope: À partir du 1er mars 2022, Thomas Gentil sera responsable suppléant d’Agroscope et responsable de l’Unité Ressources. Avant cela, il était chargé du développement de l’entreprise à l'Office fédéral de la police (fedpol).</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;En qualité de responsable de l’Unité Ressources, qui ne comprend pas moins de 130 collaboratrices et collaborateurs, Thomas Gentil dirigera les divisions de l’informatique, de l’infrastructure, des finances, des ressources humaines ainsi que le service juridique. Le jurassien de 37 ans sera par ailleurs suppléant de la responsable d’Agroscope, Eva Reinhard, et membre du comité de direction d’Agroscope. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Services du Parlement, OFSP et fedpol&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Thomas Gentil a étudié les sciences politiques aux universités de Lausanne et de Berne. Après avoir débuté sa carrière dans l'administration fédérale auprès des services du Parlement, il a travaillé à l'Office fédéral de la santé publique, d'abord comme collaborateur scientifique puis, après avoir obtenu un Master of Advanced Studies in Public Administration (MPA), comme chef de section. En 2014, il quitte l’OFSP pour rejoindre fedpol où, en tant que chef de la division «Développement de l'entreprise», il a notamment été responsable du développement de la stratégie et de la gestion du portefeuille de projets, en étroite collaboration avec le comité de direction.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;La nouvelle stratégie d’implantation des sites d’Agroscope avec le Campus de &lt;br /&gt; Posieux, deux centres de recherche, l’un à Zürich-Reckenholz et l’autre à Changins, ainsi que diverses stations d’essais entraîne des changements également au sein de l’Unité Ressources. Agroscope est convaincu que Thomas Gentil saura les aborder avec succès grâce à son expérience, à ses diverses compétences et sa motivation pour de nouveaux développements. Il prendra ses fonctions le 1er mars 2022.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Thomas Gentil habite avec sa famille dans le canton de Fribourg.&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Marc Andrey Responsable de la communication Agroscope, Schwarzenburgstrasse 161, 3003 Berne marc.andrey@agroscope.admin.ch, +41 79 335 92 75 Service des médias d’Agroscope media@agroscope.admin.ch +41 58 466 88 62 www.agroscope.ch | Une bonne alimentation, un environnement sain</contact>
      <attachment id="223073">
        <title>Thomas Gentil (Photo: Martine Wolhauser)</title>
        <format>jpg</format>
        <size-kb>2169</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/68909.jpg</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Thomas Gentil capo supplente di Agroscope</title>
      <lead>Nuovo membro del Consiglio di direzione di Agroscope: il 1° marzo 2022 Thomas Gentil diventerà capo supplente di Agroscope e capo dell’unità Risorse. In passato è stato responsabile dello sviluppo aziendale presso l’Ufficio federale di polizia fedpol.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;In veste di capo dell’unità Risorse, che conta circa 130 collaboratori, Thomas Gentil dirigerà i settori Informatica, Infrastruttura e sicurezza, Finanze, Risorse umane e Servizio giuridico. Il 37enne giurassiano sarà inoltre supplente della responsabile Eva Reinhard e membro del Consiglio di direzione di Agroscope. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Servizi del Parlamento, UFSP e fedpol&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Thomas Gentil ha studiato scienze politiche presso le università di Losanna e di Berna. Il suo percorso professionale è iniziato presso i Servizi del Parlamento dell’Amministrazione federale, per poi continuare all’Ufficio federale della sanità pubblica, prima come collaboratore scientifico e in seguito, dopo aver conseguito il Master of Advanced Studies in Public Administration (MPA), come caposezione. Nel 2014 ha proseguito la sua carriera a fedpol e, in veste di capo della divisione Sviluppo aziendale, in stretta collaborazione con la Direzione ha assunto la funzione di responsabile dello sviluppo della strategia e della gestione del portafoglio dei progetti.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;La nuova strategia di ubicazione di Agroscope con il campus di Posieux, due centri di ricerca a Zurigo-Reckenholz e Changins e varie stazioni sperimentali comporta cambiamenti anche all’interno dell’unità Risorse. Agroscope è convinto che, grazie alle esperienze maturate, alle molteplici competenze acquisite e alla sua passione per il perfezionamento continuo, Thomas Gentil saprà affrontare proficuamente tali novità. Il nuovo capo supplente entrerà in servizio il 1° marzo 2022.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Thomas Gentil vive insieme alla sua famiglia nel Cantone di Friburgo. &lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Marc Andrey Responsabile Comunicazione Agroscope, Schwarzenburgstrasse 161, 3003 Berna marc.andrey@agroscope.admin.ch, +41 79 335 92 75 Servizio media Agroscope media@agroscope.admin.ch +41 58 466 88 62 www.agroscope.ch | alimenti buoni, ambiente sano</contact>
      <attachment id="223073">
        <title>Thomas Gentil (Photo: Martine Wolhauser)</title>
        <format>jpg</format>
        <size-kb>2169</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/68909.jpg</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Thomas Gentil to Be New Deputy Head of Agroscope</title>
      <lead>New Agroscope Executive Board member: From 1 March 2022, Thomas Gentil will be the Deputy Head of Agroscope and Head of the Resources Unit. Most recently he was responsible for corporate development at the Swiss Federal Office of Police (fedpol). </lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;As Head of Resources with around 130 staff members, Thomas Gentil will run the IT, Infrastructure, Finances, Human Resources and Legal Service divisions. In addition, the 37-year-old native of Jura will be Head of Agroscope Eva Reinhard’s Deputy and an Agroscope Executive Board member. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Parliamentary Services, FOPH and fedpol &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Thomas Gentil studied Political Science at the Universities of Lausanne and Bern. After starting his career in the Federal Administration at Parliamentary Services, he worked at the Federal Office for Public Health, initially as a staff research scientist, then later, after completing his Master of Advanced Studies in Public Administration (MPA), as head of section. In 2014 he moved to fedpol, where as head of the Corporate Development department he was most recently responsible for strategy development and project portfolio management, in close cooperation with the Executive Board.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Agroscope’s new site strategy, with the Posieux Campus and two research centres (one in Zurich-Reckenholz, one in Changins) as well as various experimental stations, is also leading to changes within the Resources Unit. Agroscope is convinced that Thomas Gentil’s experience to date, broad skillset and appetite for progress will enable him to tackle these challenges successfully. He will take up his new post on 1 March 2022. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Thomas Gentil lives with his family in the canton of Fribourg. &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Marc Andrey Head of Communication Agroscope, Schwarzenburgstrasse 161, 3003 Bern marc.andrey@agroscope.admin.ch, +41 79 335 92 75 Agroscope Media Service media@agroscope.admin.ch +41 58 466 88 62 www.agroscope.ch | Good food, healthy environment</contact>
      <attachment id="223073">
        <title>Thomas Gentil (Photo: Martine Wolhauser)</title>
        <format>jpg</format>
        <size-kb>2169</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/68909.jpg</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="29">
        <name lang="de">Umwelt und Natur</name>
        <name lang="fr">Environnement et nature</name>
        <name lang="it">Ambiente e natura</name>
        <name lang="en">Environment and Nature</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="38">
        <name lang="de">Landwirtschaft</name>
        <name lang="fr">Agriculture</name>
        <name lang="it">Agricoltura</name>
        <name lang="en">Agriculture</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
