<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="85917" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2021-11-16</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="323" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>701</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidg. Materialprüfungs- und Forschungsanstalt</name>
      <name lang="fr">Laboratoire fédéral d'essai des matériaux et de recherche</name>
      <name lang="it">Laboratorio federale di prova dei materiali e di ricerca</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Laboratory for Materials Testing and Research</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.empa.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.empa.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.empa.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.empa.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">contact@empa.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">contact@empa.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">contact@empa.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">contact@empa.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="701">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Wirtschaft, Bildung und Forschung</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'économie, de la formation et de la recherche</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'economia, della formazione e della ricerca</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Economic Affairs, Education and Research</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Dübendorf, St. Gallen und Thun</city>
      <title>Drei Empa-Forscher als «Influencer» ausgezeichnet</title>
      <lead>Jedes Jahr werden die meist zitierten Wissenschaftler und Wissenschaftlerinnen gekürt. Sie gelten für ihren Fachbereich jeweils als besonders einflussreich. Die Empa stellt dieses Jahr gleich drei dieser Ausnahme-Forscher – zwei alte Bekannte und ein Neuzugang.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;«Influencer» gibt es nicht nur in den Sozialen Medien, sondern auch in der Forschung. Gemessen wird der Einfluss von Forscherinnen und Forschern aber nicht anhand von «Followern» oder «Likes», sondern daran, wie oft ihre Arbeiten von anderen Wissenschaftlerinnen und Wissenschaftlern zitiert werden. Nur die Autoren von dem einen Prozent der meist zitierten wissenschaftlichen Arbeiten in verschiedenen Fachbereichen erhalten das Prädikat «Highly Cited Researcher» des Analyse-Unternehmens «Clarivate».&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Dieses Jahr sind erstmals gleich drei Empa-Forscher auf dieser wissenschaftlichen «Who-is-who»-Liste: 2021 werden die Empa-Forscher Bernd Nowack, Maksym Kovalenko und Roman Fasel als «Highly Cited Researcher» ausgezeichnet. Der Umweltwissenschaftler Nowack leitet eine Forschungsgruppe in der Empa-Abteilung «Technologie und Gesellschaft», die unter anderem die Umweltauswirkungen verschiedener Nanomaterialien untersucht. «Man muss einfach vor den Anderen eine Idee haben, und dann etwas Umfassendes daraus machen, dann wird man viel zitiert», sagt Nowack. «Und an der Empa haben wir eine Umgebung, die uns die nötige Freiheit gibt, den eigenen Forschungs-Interessen nachzugehen – auch wenn Andere vielleicht noch gar nicht daran denken, dass man da forschen könnte.» Seine vielbeachteten Arbeiten über Mikroplastik und die Verbreitung von Nanomaterialien in der Umwelt sichern Nowack bereits zum achten Mal in Folge einen Platz auf der Rangliste.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h3&gt;&lt;b&gt;Nanostrukturen als beliebtes Thema&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/h3&gt; &lt;p&gt;Nowack's Kollege Maksym Kovalenko, der auch eine Professur an der ETH Zürich hat, erforscht neuartige Materialien für Anwendungen in der Optoelektronik und im Energiebereich. Er schaffte es alleine dieses Jahr auf fast 5'000 Verweise von anderen Forscherinnen und Forschern. Zwei seiner Arbeiten sind je über 3'000 Mal zitiert worden, was eine Ausnahme ist. Kovalenko ist zum vierten Mal unter den «Highly Cited Researchers».&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Als Neuzugang konnte sich dieses Jahr auch Roman Fasel einen Platz auf der exklusiven Liste sichern. Der Empa-Forscher und Professor für Chemie, Biochemie und Pharmazie an der Universität Bern gehört mit seinem Team zu den Wegbereitern auf dem neuartigen Gebiet der sogenannten On-Surface-Synthese von kohlenstoffbasierten Nanomaterialien. Seine Arbeiten haben bereits zu mehreren Patenten geführt.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Die Auszeichnung wird jedes Jahr von dem Analyse-Unternehmen «Clarivate» herausgegeben. Um das Ranking zu erstellen, werden rund 160'000 Publikationen weltweit aus 21 Feldern der Natur- und Sozialwissenschaften herangezogen. Die Häufigkeit der Zitationen gibt Aufschluss über den Einfluss, den Forschende auf ihrem Gebiet haben. Unter den nominierten sind 24 Nobelpreisträger, fünf davon aus diesem Jahr. Nur etwa 0,05 Prozent aller wissenschaftlicher Arbeiten im Datensatz wurden mehr als 1000 Mal zitiert. Von den rund 8 Millionen Forschenden weltweit – gemäss UN-Schätzungen – gehören nur gerade 6'602 zu den «Highly Cited Researchers».&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h3&gt;&lt;b&gt;Die Schweiz auf Rang 10&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/h3&gt; &lt;p&gt;2021 sind insgesamt 102 Schweizer Forschende auf der Clarivate-Liste vertreten, das sind 1,5 Prozent aller meistzitierten Wissenschaftlerinnen und Wissenschaftler. Die Schweiz liegt im Ländervergleich auf dem zehnten Platz, eine Position schlechter als noch im Vorjahr. An der Spitze der Rangliste sind schon seit Jahren die USA mit 2'622 Forschenden, oder 39,7 Prozent der ausgezeichneten Forscher. China belegt Rang zwei, mit 935 Wissenschaftlern (14,2 Prozent) gefolgt von Grossbritannien, Australien und Deutschland.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Auf die Bevölkerung angepasst verschiebt sich das Ganze ein wenig; hier führt Australien mit knapp 13 besonders einflussreichen Wissenschaftlern pro eine Million Einwohner, gefolgt von den Niederlanden (Rang 6) mit 11,87 und (ganz knapp dahinter) der Schweiz mit 11,81. Die USA kommen auf knapp 8, China wegen seiner immensen Bevölkerung nur auf 0,67 ausgezeichnete Forschende pro Million Einwohner.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Prof. Dr. Roman Fasel nanotech@surfaces Tel: +41 58 765 43 48 roman.fasel@empa.ch Prof. Dr. Maksym Kovalenko Thin Films and Photovoltaics Tel: +41 58 765 45 57 maksym.kovalenko@empa.ch Prof. Dr. Bernd Nowack Technology and Society Tel: +41 58 765 76 92 bernd.nowack@empa.ch Redaktion / Medienkontakt Noé Waldmann Komunikation Tel.+41 58 765 60 59 redaktion@empa.ch</contact>
      <attachment id="223441">
        <title>Roman Fasel ist Leiter der Empa-Abteilung «nanotech@surfaces». Seine Pionierarbeit bei der Synthese von Graphen-Nanobändern ermöglicht abstimmbare, atomar präzise eindimensionale Halbleiterstrukturen. Bild: Gian Vaitl / Empa</title>
        <format>jpg</format>
        <size-kb>4439</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/68975.jpg</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <link id="223442">
        <title>Empa Medienmitteilung DE EN FR</title>
        <uri>https://www.empa.ch/web/s604/highly-cited-researchers2021</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Dübendorf, St. Gallen und Thun</city>
      <title>Ces chercheurs de l'Empa sont des «influenceurs» dans leur domaine</title>
      <lead>Chaque année, les scientifiques les plus cités sont sélectionnés. Ils sont considérés comme particulièrement influents dans leur domaine. Cette année, l'Empa compte trois de ces chercheurs exceptionnels - deux anciennes connaissances et un nouveau venu.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;"Les influenceurs" n'existent pas seulement sur les réseaux sociaux, mais aussi dans la recherche. Cependant, l'influence des chercheurs ne se mesure pas par les "followers" ou les "likes", mais par la fréquence à laquelle leurs travaux sont cités par d'autres chercheurs. Seuls les auteurs du 1% des articles scientifiques les plus cités dans diverses disciplines reçoivent le titre de "Highly Cited Researcher" de la société d'analyse "Clarivate".&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Cette année, pour la première fois, trois chercheurs de l'Empa figurent dans ce "who's who" scientifique : en 2021, les chercheurs de l'Empa Bernd Nowack, Maksym Kovalenko et Roman Fasel seront distingués comme "Highly Cited Researchers". Bernd Nowack, spécialiste de l'environnement, dirige un groupe de recherche du département "Technologie et société" de l'Empa qui étudie notamment l'impact environnemental de différents nanomatériaux. "Il suffit d'avoir une idée avant les autres et d'en faire quelque chose de complet, alors on vous cite beaucoup", dit Bernd Nowack. "Et à l'Empa, nous disposons d'un environnement qui nous donne la liberté nécessaire pour poursuivre nos propres intérêts de recherche - même si d'autres ne pensent pas encore à y faire de la recherche." Ses travaux très appréciés sur les microplastiques et la propagation des nanomatériaux dans l'environnement ont permis à Bernd Nowack de figurer sur la liste du classement pour la huitième fois consécutive.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h3&gt;&lt;b&gt;Les nanostructures, un sujet populaire&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/h3&gt; &lt;p&gt;Le collègue de Bernd Nowack, Maksym Kovalenko, qui est également professeur à l'ETH Zurich, recherche de nouveaux matériaux pour des applications en optoélectronique et en énergie. Il a réussi à obtenir près de 5 000 citations d'autres chercheurs rien que cette année. Deux de ses articles ont été cités plus de 3 000 fois chacun, ce qui est exceptionnel. Maksym Kovalenko figure pour la quatrième fois parmi les "Highly Cited Researchers".&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;En tant que nouveau venu cette année, Roman Fasel a également pu obtenir une place sur la liste exclusive. Le chercheur de l'Empa et professeur de chimie, de biochimie et de pharmacie à l'Université de Berne est l'un des pionniers, avec son équipe, dans le domaine nouveau de la synthèse dite "on-surface" de composés carbonés tels que les nanomatériaux à base de carbone graphénique..&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Ce prix est publié chaque année par la société d'analyse "Clarivate". Environ 160 000 publications du monde entier dans 21 domaines des sciences naturelles et sociales sont utilisées pour établir le classement. La fréquence des citations fournit des informations sur l'influence des chercheurs dans leur domaine. Parmi les nominés figurent 24 lauréats du prix Nobel, dont cinq de cette année. Seuls environ 0,05 % de tous les articles scientifiques de l'ensemble de données ont été cités plus de 1000 fois. Sur les quelque 8 millions de chercheurs dans le monde - selon les estimations de l'ONU - seuls 6 602 font partie des "chercheurs les plus cités".&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h3&gt;&lt;b&gt;La Suisse en 10ème position&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/h3&gt; &lt;p&gt;En 2021, un total de 102 chercheurs suisses figurent sur la liste de Clarivate, ce qui représente 1,5 % de l'ensemble des scientifiques les plus cités. La Suisse occupe la dixième place dans la comparaison par pays, soit une position de moins que l'année précédente. Les États-Unis sont en tête du classement depuis des années, avec 2 622 chercheurs, soit 39,7 % de l'ensemble des chercheurs récompensés. La Chine occupe la deuxième place avec 935 chercheurs (14,2 %), suivie par la Grande-Bretagne, l'Australie et l'Allemagne.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Ajusté à la population, le classement change un peu ; ici, l'Australie est en tête avec un peu moins de 13 chercheurs particulièrement influents par million d'habitants, suivie par les Pays-Bas (rang 6) avec 11,87 et (très près derrière) la Suisse avec 11,81. Les États-Unis arrivent juste en dessous de 8, et la Chine, en raison de son immense population, seulement 0,67 excellent chercheur par million d'habitants.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Prof. Dr. Roman Fasel nanotech@surfaces Tél: +41 58 765 43 48 roman.fasel@empa.ch Prof. Dr. Maksym Kovalenko Thin Films and Photovoltaics Tél: +41 58 765 45 57 maksym.kovalenko@empa.ch Prof. Dr. Bernd Nowack Technology and Society Tél: +41 58 765 76 92 bernd.nowack@empa.ch Rédaction / contact médias Noé Waldmann Communications Tél. +41 58 765 60 59 redaktion@empa.ch</contact>
      <attachment id="223441">
        <title>Roman Fasel ist Leiter der Empa-Abteilung «nanotech@surfaces». Seine Pionierarbeit bei der Synthese von Graphen-Nanobändern ermöglicht abstimmbare, atomar präzise eindimensionale Halbleiterstrukturen. Bild: Gian Vaitl / Empa</title>
        <format>jpg</format>
        <size-kb>4439</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/68975.jpg</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <link id="223442">
        <title>Empa Medienmitteilung DE EN FR</title>
        <uri>https://www.empa.ch/web/s604/highly-cited-researchers2021</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Dübendorf, St. Gallen und Thun</city>
      <title>Three Empa Scientists honored as "Influencers"</title>
      <lead>Every year, the most cited scientists are selected. They are each considered to be particularly influential in their field. This year, Empa has three of these exceptional researchers - two old acquaintances and one newcomer.</lead>
      <text link="no">"Influencers" do not only exist in social media, but also in research. However, the influence of researchers is not measured by "followers" or "likes," but by how often their work is cited by other scientists. Only the authors of the one percent of the most cited scientific papers in various disciplines are awarded the title of "Highly Cited Researcher" by the analysis company "Clarivate". This year, for the first time, three Empa researchers are on this scientific "Who's Who" list: in 2021, Empa researchers Bernd Nowack, Maksym Kovalenko and Roman Fasel will be honored as "Highly Cited Researchers". Nowack, an environmental scientist, heads a research group in Empa's "Technology and Society" laboratory that studies, among other things, the environmental impact of various nanomaterials. "You just have to have an idea before others, and then make something comprehensive out of it, then you get cited a lot," Nowack says. "And at Empa, we have an environment that gives us the freedom we need to pursue our own research interests - even if others might not even think of doing research there yet." His high-profile work on microplastics and the spread of nanomaterials in the environment secured Nowack a spot on the ranking list for the eighth year in a row. -----Nanostructures are a popular topic----- Nowack's colleague Maksym Kovalenko, who also holds a professorship at ETH Zurich, researches novel materials for applications in optoelectronics and energy. He made it to nearly 5,000 referrals from other researchers this year alone. Two of his papers have been cited more than 3,000 times each, which is exceptional. This is the fourth time Kovalenko has been among the "Highly Cited Researchers." As a newcomer this year, Roman Fasel was also able to secure a place on the exclusive list. The Empa researcher and Professor of Chemistry, Biochemistry and Pharmacy at the University of Bern is one of the pioneers with his team in the novel field of so-called on-surface synthesis of carbon-based nanomaterials. His work has already led to several patents. The award is published every year by the analysis company "Clarivate". Around 160,000 publications worldwide from 21 fields of the natural and social sciences are used to compile the ranking. The frequency of citations provides an indication of the influence researchers have in their field. Among those nominated are 24 Nobel Prize winners, five of them from this year. Only about 0.05 percent of all scientific papers in the dataset were cited more than 1000 times. Of the approximately 8 million researchers worldwide - according to UN estimates - only just 6,602 are among the "Highly Cited Researchers." -----Switzerland in 10th place----- In 2021, a total of 102 Swiss researchers are represented on the Clarivate list, or 1.5 percent of all most-cited scientists. Switzerland is in tenth place in the country comparison, one position worse than in the previous year. The USA has been at the top of the ranking for years, with 2,622 researchers, or 39.7 percent of the researchers honored. China takes second place with 935 researchers (14.2 percent), followed by the UK, Australia and Germany. Adjusted to the population, the whole thing shifts a little; here Australia leads with just under 13 particularly influential scientists per million inhabitants, followed by the Netherlands (rank 6) with 11.87 and (very close behind) Switzerland with 11.81. The USA comes in at just under 8, and China, because of its immense population, only 0.67 excellent researchers per million inhabitants. </text>
      <contact>Prof. Dr. Roman Fasel nanotech@surfaces Phone: +41 58 765 43 48 roman.fasel@empa.ch Prof. Dr. Maksym Kovalenko Thin Films and Photovoltaics Phone: +41 58 765 45 57 maksym.kovalenko@empa.ch Prof. Dr. Bernd Nowack Technology and Society Phone: +41 58 765 76 92 bernd.nowack@empa.ch Editor / Media contact Noé Waldmann Communications Phone +41 58 765 60 59 redaktion@empa.ch</contact>
      <attachment id="223441">
        <title>Roman Fasel ist Leiter der Empa-Abteilung «nanotech@surfaces». Seine Pionierarbeit bei der Synthese von Graphen-Nanobändern ermöglicht abstimmbare, atomar präzise eindimensionale Halbleiterstrukturen. Bild: Gian Vaitl / Empa</title>
        <format>jpg</format>
        <size-kb>4439</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/68975.jpg</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <link id="223442">
        <title>Empa Medienmitteilung DE EN FR</title>
        <uri>https://www.empa.ch/web/s604/highly-cited-researchers2021</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="8">
        <name lang="de">Bildung und Forschung</name>
        <name lang="fr">Formation et recherche</name>
        <name lang="it">Formazione e ricerca</name>
        <name lang="en">Education and Research</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
