<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="16552" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2008-01-04</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="206" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>201</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Direktion für Entwicklung und Zusammenarbeit</name>
      <name lang="fr">Direction du développement et de la coopération</name>
      <name lang="it">Direzione dello sviluppo e della cooperazione</name>
      <name lang="en">Swiss Agency for Development and Cooperation</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.deza.admin.ch/index.php?langID=6</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.deza.admin.ch/index.php?langID=2</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.deza.admin.ch/index.php?langID=7</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.deza.admin.ch/index.php?langID=1</www>
      <email lang="de">info@deza.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@deza.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@deza.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@deza.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="201">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Schweizer Hilfe für Kenia</title>
      <lead>Die Schweiz unterstützt via das IKRK das kenianische Rote Kreuz in ihren Nothilfebemühungen zugunsten der Opfer der Unruhen in Kenia mit einem sofortigen Beitrag von 200'000 Franken. Damit folgt sie einem Aufruf des Internationalen Komitees vom Roten Kreuz (IKRK). Ein Schweizer Experte für humanitäre Hilfe ist bereits vor Ort.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Aufgrund eines Aufrufs des IKRK, zusätzliche 15 Millionen Franken zur Verfügung zu stellen, leistet die humanitäre Hilfe des Bundes einen Beitrag von 200&amp;nbsp;000&amp;nbsp;Franken für die Opfer der gewaltsamen Unruhen in Kenia. Damit soll die logistische Unterstützung und Materialversorgung verbessert werden, die das IKRK dem kenianischen Roten Kreuz und seinen Partnern der Internationalen Föderation der Rotkreuz- und Rothalbmondgesellschaften (IFRC) leistet.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Bereits am Mittwoch, dem 2. Januar, wurde ein Experte der humanitären Hilfe zur Verstärkung der Schweizer Botschaft nach Nairobi geschickt. Dieser wird neben Aufgaben des konsularischen Schutzes Abklärungen der dringendsten Bedürfnisse vornehmen und Sofortmassnahmen in die Wege leiten.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Das IKRK wird in enger Zusammenarbeit mit dem kenianischen Gesundheits­ministerium, dem kenianischen Roten Kreuz und der IFRC Hilfsmaterial, Medikamente und lebenswichtige Güter verteilen. Die gewaltsamen Unruhen haben in einer Woche zu mehreren Hundert Toten und Tausenden Verletzten geführt und rund Hunderttausend Menschen in die Flucht getrieben.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Weitere Auskünfte&lt;/b&gt;:&lt;br /&gt; Jean-Philippe Jutzi, Sprecher der DEZA. Tel. +41 (0)79 292 08 49; E-Mail jean-philippe.jutzi@deza.admin.ch&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>DEZA Abteilung Medien und Kommunikation Freiburgstrasse 130 CH-3003 Bern Tel. +41 31 322 44 12 Fax +41 31 324 13 48</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Aide suisse en faveur du Kenya</title>
      <lead>La Suisse apporte son soutien à la Croix-Rouge kenyane en lui accordant, via le CICR, une aide d’urgence immédiate de 200'000 francs en faveur des victimes des violences. Ce montant est versé en réponse à un appel de fonds lancé par le Comité international de la Croix-Rouge. Un expert suisse de l’aide humanitaire est déjà sur place.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;En réponse à un appel de fonds supplémentaires du CICR de 15 millions de francs, l’Aide humanitaire de la Confédération octroie une somme de 200'000 francs en faveur des victimes des violences au Kenya. Cet argent servira à augmenter le soutien logistique et en matériel que le CICR fournit à la Croix-Rouge kenyane et à ses partenaires de la Fédération internationale des sociétés de la Croix-Rouge et du Croissant-Rouge (FICR).&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Mercredi 2 janvier déjà, un expert de l’Aide humanitaire avait été envoyé à Nairobi, en renfort auprès de l’ambassade de Suisse au Kenya. En plus de tâches de protection consulaire, il a pour mission de procéder à l’évaluation des besoins les plus urgents et de prendre les premières mesures d’aide concrète.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;En étroite collaboration avec le ministère kenyan de la Santé, la Croix-Rouge kenyane et la FICR, le CICR procède à des distributions de matériel de secours, de médicaments et de biens de première nécessité. En une semaine, ces violences ont fait plusieurs centaines de morts, des milliers de blessés et ont contraint quelque 100'000 personnes à fuir leur domicile.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Renseignements supplémentaires&lt;/b&gt;&amp;nbsp;:&lt;br /&gt; Jean-Philippe Jutzi, porte-parole de la DDC. Tél +41 (0)79 292 08 49&amp;nbsp;; e-mail jean-philippe.jutzi@deza.admin.ch&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact/>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Aiuto svizzero a favore del Kenya</title>
      <lead>Attraverso il CICR, la Svizzera sostiene la Croce Rossa keniana nei suoi sforzi di aiuto urgente a favore delle vittime delle violenze in Kenya con un importo di 200'000 franchi. Risponde così a un appello del Comitato Internazionale della Croce Rossa (CICR). Un esperto svizzero di aiuto umanitario si trova già sul posto.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;In risposta a un appello di raccolta di fondi supplementari pari a 15 milioni di franchi lanciato dal CICR, l’Aiuto umanitario della Confederazione versa un importo immediato di 200'000 franchi a favore delle vittime delle violenze in Kenya. I fondi servono ad aumentare il sostegno logistico e materiale che il CICR fornisce alla Croce Rossa keniana e ai suoi partner della Federazione Internazionale delle Società della Croce Rossa e della Mezzaluna Rossa (FICR).&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Già mercoledì 2 gennaio, un esperto dell’Aiuto umanitario è stato inviato a Nairobi come rinforzo presso l’Ambasciata di Svizzera in Kenya. Oltre a svolgere compiti di protezione consolare, deve procedere alla valutazione dei bisogni più urgenti e prendere immediatamente i provvedimenti necessari.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Il CICR distribuisce materiale di soccorso, medicamenti e beni di prima necessità in stretta collaborazione con il Ministero keniano della sanità, la Croce Rossa keniana e la FICR. In una settimana le violenze hanno provocato diverse centinaia di morti, migliaia di feriti e hanno costretto circa 100'000 persone a lasciare il loro domicilio.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Informazioni supplementari&lt;/b&gt;:&lt;br /&gt; Jean-Philippe Jutzi, portavoce della DSC; tel. +41 (0)79 292 08 49; e-mail jean-philippe.jutzi@deza.admin.ch&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact/>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Swiss aid for Kenya</title>
      <lead>Switzerland is to provide immediately 200,000 CHF in emergency aid for the victims of the violence now sweeping Kenya. This payment in favour of the Kenyan Red Cross is in response to an appeal for funds launched by the International Committee of the Red Cross (ICRC). A Swiss humanitarian aid expert is already in Kenya.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;In response to an appeal for additional aid of 15 million francs, Swiss humanitarian aid has granted the sum of 200,000 francs for victims of violence in Kenya. The money will be used to increase the logistical and material support that the ICRC provides to the Kenyan Red Cross and to its partners in the International Federation of Red Cross and Red Crescent Societies. (IFRC).&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;On Wednesday 2 January, a humanitarian aid expert was sent to Nairobi to provide support for the Swiss embassy in Kenya. In addition to consular protection responsibilities, his task will be to evaluate the most pressing needs and to implement the first emergency actions.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Working in close collaboration with the Kenyan Ministry of Health, the Kenyan Red Cross and the IFRC, the ICRC will distribute aid material, medicine and items to satisfy immediate needs. In one week, the violence in the country has led to the deaths of several hundred people. Thousands have been injured and an estimated &amp;nbsp;100,000 people have fled their homes.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;For further information please contact&lt;/b&gt;:&lt;br /&gt; Jean-Philippe Jutzi, SDC spokesman. Tel +41 (0)79 292 08 49&amp;nbsp;; e-mail jean-philippe.jutzi@deza.admin.ch&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact/>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
