<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="17694" revoked="no">
    <version>2</version>
    <pubdate>2008-03-07</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="yes" id="703" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>701</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Staatssekretariat für Wirtschaft</name>
      <name lang="fr">Secrétariat d'Etat à l'économie</name>
      <name lang="it">Segreteria di Stato dell'economia</name>
      <name lang="en">State Secretariat for Economic Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.seco.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.seco.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.seco.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.seco.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@seco.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@seco.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@seco.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@seco.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="701">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Wirtschaft, Bildung und Forschung</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'économie, de la formation et de la recherche</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'economia, della formazione e della ricerca</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Economic Affairs, Education and Research</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Kredit für wirtschafts- und handelspolitische Massnahmen in Entwicklungsländern</title>
      <teaser>Der Bundesrat hat am 7. März 2008 den Rahmenkredit für die Weiterführung der wirtschafts- und handelspolitischen Massnahmen im Rahmen der Entwicklungszusammenarbeit genehmigt. Mit diesem Rahmenkredit im Umfang von 800 Millionen Franken über vier Jahre soll die Tätigkeit des Staatssekretariats für Wirtschaft (SECO) zugunsten von Entwicklungsländern weitergeführt werden. Die Hauptziele dieser Massnahmen sind der Einbezug der Partnerländer in die Weltwirtschaft und die Förderung ihres nachhaltigen Wirtschaftswachstums. Damit soll zur dauerhaften Verminderung der Armut beigetragen werden.</teaser>
      <lead>Der Bundesrat hat am 7. März 2008 den Rahmenkredit für die Weiterführung der wirtschafts- und handelspolitischen Massnahmen im Rahmen der Entwicklungszusammenarbeit genehmigt. Mit diesem Rahmenkredit im Umfang von 800 Millionen Franken über vier Jahre soll die Tätigkeit des Staatssekretariats für Wirtschaft (SECO) zugunsten von Entwicklungsländern weitergeführt werden. Die Hauptziele dieser Massnahmen sind der Einbezug der Partnerländer in die Weltwirtschaft und die Förderung ihres nachhaltigen Wirtschaftswachstums. Damit soll zur dauerhaften Verminderung der Armut beigetragen werden.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Der Bundesrat hat den Rahmenkredit für die Weiterführung der wirtschafts- und handelspolitischen Massnahmen im Rahmen der Entwicklungszusammenarbeit genehmigt und an das Parlament überwiesen. In der Botschaft wird beantragt, für diese Massnahmen einen siebten Rahmenkredit über 800 Millionen Franken über eine Laufzeit von vier Jahren (2008-2012) zur Verfügung zu stellen. Die wirtschafts- und handelspolitischen Massnahmen sind Teil der entwicklungspolitischen Strategie der Schweiz, wie sie in der parallel vorgelegten Botschaft für die Massnahmen der Direktion für Entwicklung und Zusammenarbeit (DEZA) dargelegt wird, und leisten einen wichtigen Beitrag zu den entwicklungspolitischen, aussenpolitischen und aussenwirtschaftspolitischen Zielen des Bundesrates.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Das SECO will sich verstärkt auf seine Kernkompetenzen konzentrieren, um die schweizerische Entwicklungszusammenarbeit wirksamer und effizienter zu gestalten. Die Aktivitäten sollen noch mehr auf Massnahmen ausgerichtet werden, die es den Partnerländern ermöglichen, ein nachhaltiges Wirtschaftwachstum zu erzielen und vom zunehmenden internationalen Wirtschaftsaustausch zu profitieren. Die Prioritäten liegen auf der Stärkung der Wettbewerbsfähigkeit und der Diversifizierung des Handels der Entwicklungsländer, der Mobilisierung von in- und ausländischen Investitionen, der Verbesserung der Basisinfrastruktur sowie der Förderung stabiler wirtschaftlicher Rahmenbedingungen. Ein besonderer Schwerpunkt kommt Energie-, Umwelt- und Klimafragen zu. Die Mobilisierung von privatem Kapital und Know-how vor Ort und in der Schweiz ist ein wichtiger Grundsatz der Entwicklungszusammenarbeit des SECO.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Das SECO wird seine bilaterale Zusammenarbeit zudem auf deutlich weniger Schwerpunktländer beschränken (Reduktion von zwölf auf sieben Länder): Ägypten, Ghana, Indonesien, Kolumbien, Peru, Südafrika und Vietnam. Alle sieben Länder weisen momentan ein rasches Wirtschaftswachstum auf, streben eine verstärkte Integration in die Weltwirtschaft an und haben eine grosse wirtschaftliche Bedeutung in ihrer Region.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Sie sind jedoch gleichzeitig auch mit grossen Armuts- und Entwicklungsproblemen konfrontiert. Viele Massnahmen im wirtschafts- und handelspolitischen Bereich, etwa die Förderung internationaler Regelwerke oder die Verbreitung von Produktestandards, haben eine internationale Ausrichtung. Davon profitieren alle Entwicklungsländer, wobei den Herausforderungen der ärmsten Länder besonders Rechnung getragen wird.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;In den Aufgabenbereich des SECO fällt zudem die Betreuung der multilateralen Entwicklungsbanken. In diesem Bereich strebt es insbesondere eine weitere Stärkung der Effizienz und Wirksamkeit dieser Institutionen an.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Mit der starken thematischen und geographischen Fokussierung trägt das SECO den Empfehlungen sowohl des schweizerischen Parlaments als auch internationaler Organisationen wie der Organisation für Zusammenarbeit und Entwicklung (OECD) Rechnung, die zur Steigerung der Effizienz und Wirksamkeit der Entwicklungszusammenarbeit eine stärkere Fokussierung und verbesserte Arbeitsteilung zwischen den verschiedenen Entwicklungsakteuren fordern.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Markus Spörndli, SECO, Informationsbeauftragter Wirtschaftliche Zusammenarbeit und Entwicklung, Tel. +41 (0)31 324 09 10, E-mail: markus.spoerndli@seco.admin.ch</contact>
      <attachment id="37656">
        <title>Medienrohstoff</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>29</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/11354.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Crédit pour des mesures de politique économique et commerciale dans les pays en développement</title>
      <teaser>Le 7 mars 2008, le Conseil fédéral a approuvé le crédit de programme pour la poursuite des mesures de politique économique et commerciale déployées au titre de la coopération au développement. Ce crédit, d’un montant de 800 millions de francs répartis sur quatre ans, doit permettre au Secrétariat d’Etat à l’économie (SECO) de poursuivre ses activités en faveur de pays en développement. Ces mesures, qui visent avant tout à soutenir l’intégration des pays partenaires dans l’économie mondiale et à encourager leur croissance économique durable, contribueront à la réduction à long terme de la pauvreté dans ces pays.</teaser>
      <lead>Le 7 mars 2008, le Conseil fédéral a approuvé le crédit de programme pour la poursuite des mesures de politique économique et commerciale déployées au titre de la coopération au développement. Ce crédit, d’un montant de 800 millions de francs répartis sur quatre ans, doit permettre au Secrétariat d’Etat à l’économie (SECO) de poursuivre ses activités en faveur de pays en développement. Ces mesures, qui visent avant tout à soutenir l’intégration des pays partenaires dans l’économie mondiale et à encourager leur croissance économique durable, contribueront à la réduction à long terme de la pauvreté dans ces pays.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Le Conseil fédéral a approuvé le crédit de programme concernant la poursuite des mesures de politique économique et commerciale déployées au titre de la coopération au développement et transmis le dossier au Parlement. Le message propose de mettre à disposition un septième crédit de programme de 800 millions de francs pour la période de 2008 à 2012. Les mesures de politique économique et commerciale font partie intégrante de la stratégie suisse de développement, à l'instar de celles déployées par la Direction du développement et de la coopération (DDC) et exposées dans le message présenté en parallèle. Elles fournissent une contribution importante à la réalisation des objectifs du Conseil fédéral en matière de politique de développement, de politique étrangère et de politique économique extérieure.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Le SECO entend se concentrer davantage sur ses compétences-clés afin de mettre en place une coopération suisse au développement plus efficace et plus efficiente. Ses activités devront être orientées davantage sur des mesures qui permettront aux pays partenaires d'atteindre une croissance économique durable et de profiter de l'accroissement des échanges économiques internationaux. Il s'agit essentiellement d'accroître la compétitivité et d'assurer la diversification du commerce des pays en développement, de mobiliser les investissements domestiques et étrangers, d'améliorer l'infrastructure de base et de favoriser la stabilité des conditions cadre économiques. Une attention particulière est portée aux questions touchant à l'énergie, à l'environnement et au climat. Mobiliser les capitaux privés et le savoir-faire, aussi bien sur place qu'en Suisse, est un principe essentiel de la coopération au développement du SECO.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Le SECO va par ailleurs limiter sa coopération bilatérale et réduire de douze à sept le nombre des pays prioritaires, à savoir l'Egypte, le Ghana, l'Indonésie, la Colombie, le Pérou, l'Afrique du Sud et le Vietnam. Ces sept pays présentent une forte croissante économique, visent une meilleure intégration dans l'économie mondiale et jouent un rôle économique clé au niveau régional, mais ils sont également confrontés à d'importants problèmes de pauvreté et de développement. Bon nombre des mesures de politique économique et commerciale pévues, telles que la promotion de cadres réglementaires internationaux ou la diffusion de standards, ont une dimension internationale. Elles profitent à tous les pays en développement et font notamment cas des défis que doivent relever les moins avancés d'entre eux.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Le suivi des politiques des banques multilaterales de dévelopement relève également du domaine de compétences du SECO, qui s'efforce notamment d'améliorer l'efficience et l'efficacité de ces institutions.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;En concentrant ses efforts sur les plans thématique et géographique, le SECO tient compte des recommandations à la fois du Parlement suisse et d'organisations internationales comme l'Organisation de coopération et de développement économiques (OCDE), qui préconisent de mieux cibler les actions et de mieux répartir les tâches entre les différents acteurs du développement.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Markus Spörndli, SECO, Coopération et développement économiques, chargé de l’information, tél. +41 (0) 31 324 09 10, courriel : markus.spoerndli@seco.admin.ch</contact>
      <attachment id="37657">
        <title>Dossier de presse</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>29</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/11357.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Credito per provvedimenti economici e di politica commerciale nei Paesi in sviluppo</title>
      <teaser>Il 7 marzo 2008, il Consiglio federale ha approvato il credito quadro per la prosecuzione dei provvedimenti economici e di politica commerciale nell’ambito della collaborazione allo sviluppo. Questo credito quadro – 800 milioni di franchi nell’arco di quattro anni – è finalizzato alla continuazione delle attività svolte dalla Segreteria di Stato dell’economia (SECO) in favore dei Paesi in sviluppo. Gli obiettivi principali di questi provvedimenti consistono nell’integrazione dei Paesi partner nell’economia mondiale e nella promozione della loro crescita economica sostenibile, per contribuire a ridurre durevolmente la povertà.</teaser>
      <lead>Il 7 marzo 2008, il Consiglio federale ha approvato il credito quadro per la prosecuzione dei provvedimenti economici e di politica commerciale nell’ambito della collaborazione allo sviluppo. Questo credito quadro – 800 milioni di franchi nell’arco di quattro anni – è finalizzato alla continuazione delle attività svolte dalla Segreteria di Stato dell’economia (SECO) in favore dei Paesi in sviluppo. Gli obiettivi principali di questi provvedimenti consistono nell’integrazione dei Paesi partner nell’economia mondiale e nella promozione della loro crescita economica sostenibile, per contribuire a ridurre durevolmente la povertà.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Il Consiglio federale ha approvato il credito quadro per la prosecuzione dei provvedimenti economici e di politica commerciale nell'ambito della collaborazione allo sviluppo e lo ha trasmesso al Parlamento. Il messaggio chiede, per i provvedimenti suddetti, un settimo credito quadro di più di 800 milioni di franchi da mettere a disposizione nell'arco di quattro anni (dal 2008 al 2012). I provvedimenti economici e di politica commerciale fanno parte della strategia svizzera in materia di politica dello sviluppo - come risulta dal messaggio concernente le misure attuate dalla Direzione dello sviluppo e della cooperazione (DSC), presentato in concomitanza con quello in questione - e contribuiscono in misura importante al raggiungimento degli obiettivi del Consiglio federale per ciò che concerne la politica dello sviluppo, la politica estera e la politica economica estera.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;La SECO intende focalizzare maggiormente le proprie attività, alla luce delle sue competenze cardine, allo scopo di rendere più efficace l'operato della Svizzera nell'ambito della collaborazione allo sviluppo. Le attività devono soprattutto essere indirizzate all'attuazione di provvedimenti che consentano ai Paesi partner di raggiungere una crescita economica sostenibile e di beneficiare dell'intensificazione degli scambi economici internazionali. Il rafforzamento della competitività, la diversificazione del commercio dei Paesi in sviluppo, la mobilizzazione degli investimenti nazionali ed esteri, il miglioramento delle infrastrutture di base e la promozione di un solido quadro di condizioni economiche sono gli obiettivi principali. Particolare attenzione viene prestata alle questioni legate all'energia, all'ambiente e al clima. La mobilizzazione di capitali privati e di competenze, sul posto e in Svizzera, costituisce un principio importante delle attività di collaborazione allo sviluppo svolte dalla SECO.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Inoltre, l'ambito della collaborazione bilaterale della SECO verrà considerevolmente limitato riducendo il numero di Paesi prioritari da dodici a sette: Egitto, Ghana, Indonesia, Colombia, Perù, Sudafrica e Vietnam. Attualmente, questi sette Paesi sono caratterizzati da una crescita economica rapida, mirano ad una maggiore integrazione nell'economia mondiale e rivestono un ruolo economicamente importante nella loro regione.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Tuttavia essi sono confrontati anche con grossi problemi in relazione alla povertà e allo sviluppo. Molti provvedimenti attuati nel settore economico e in quello della politica commerciale - come ad esempio la promozione di dispositivi normativi internazionali o la diffusione di standard produttivi - sono di orientamento internazionale. Ciò va a beneficio di tutti i Paesi in sviluppo: i problemi dei Paesi più poveri sono però tenuti particolarmente in considerazione.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Tra i compiti della SECO rientra anche l'assistenza alle banche multilaterali di sviluppo. In questo settore viene perseguito, in particolare, il miglioramento di queste istituzioni sotto il profilo dell'efficienza.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;La focalizzazione, tematica e geografica, delle attività della SECO corrisponde alle raccomandazioni formulate sia dal Parlamento svizzero, sia da organizzazioni internazionali - come l'Organizzazione per la cooperazione e lo sviluppo economici (OCSE) - secondo le quali per accrescere&amp;nbsp; l'efficacia della collaborazione allo sviluppo sono necessarie una maggiore concentrazione degli sforzi e una migliore suddivisione dei compiti tra i diversi attori dello sviluppo.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Markus Spörndli, SECO, incaricato dell'informazione, Cooperazione economica e sviluppo, tel. +41 31 324 09 10, markus.spoerndli@seco.admin.ch</contact>
      <attachment id="37657">
        <title>Dossier de presse</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>29</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/11357.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Credit for economic and trade policy measures in developing countries</title>
      <teaser>On 7 March 2008, the Federal Council approved the credit line to continue financing the economic and trade policy measures in the context of development cooperation. This credit line amounting to CHF 800 million over a period of four years will allow the State Secretariat for Economic Affairs (SECO) to continue its activities in developing countries. The primary aims of the measures are to integrate partner countries into the global economy and to promote the sustainable economic growth of these countries, thereby making an effective contribution to long-term poverty reduction.</teaser>
      <lead>On 7 March 2008, the Federal Council approved the credit line to continue financing the economic and trade policy measures in the context of development cooperation. This credit line amounting to CHF 800 million over a period of four years will allow the State Secretariat for Economic Affairs (SECO) to continue its activities in developing countries. The primary aims of the measures are to integrate partner countries into the global economy and to promote the sustainable economic growth of these countries, thereby making an effective contribution to long-term poverty reduction.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;The Federal Council approved the credit line to continue financing the economic and trade policy measures in the context of development cooperation. It has submitted a corresponding dispatch to parliament in which it applies for the appropriation of a seventh credit line of CHF 800 million over a period of four years (2008-2012) to finance these measures. The economic and trade policy measures are part of Switzerland's development policy strategy, as set out in concurrently submitted dispatch on the measures of the Swiss Agency for Development and Cooperation (SDC). They significantly contribute to the Federal Council's development policy, foreign policy and foreign trade policy goals.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;SECO intends to focus increasingly on its core competencies in an effort to improve the effectiveness and efficiency of Swiss development cooperation. Activities should be more oriented towards measures that enable partner countries to attain sustainable economic growth and benefit from increased international economic exchange. The priorities lie in strengthening competitiveness and trade diversification of developing countries, in mobilising domestic and foreign investment, in improving basic infrastructure and promoting stable basic economic conditions. Particular emphasis is placed on the issues of climate change, energy and the environment. The mobilisation of private capital and know-how on-site and in Switzerland is an important principle of SECO's development cooperation.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Furthermore, SECO plans to concentrate its bilateral cooperation on considerably fewer priority countries (reduction from twelve to seven countries): Egypt, Ghana, Indonesia, Colombia, Peru, South Africa and Vietnam. All seven countries are currently experiencing rapid economic growth, are striving towards greater integration into the world economy and are of significant economic importance in their region.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;However, these countries still face huge problems in terms of poverty and development. Many measures in the field of economic and trade policy, such as the promotion of international rules or&amp;nbsp;of product standards, have an international focus. These measures benefit all developing countries, but specifically take into account the challenges of the poorest countries.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;SECO's scope of activities also includes overseeing the multilateral development banks. In this area, it is particularly aiming to further improve the efficiency and effectiveness of these institutions.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;With its strong thematic and geographical focus, SECO takes into account the recommendations of the Swiss parliament and of international organisations such as the OECD which promote a greater focus and improved division of labour between the various actors to increase the efficiency and effectiveness of development cooperation.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Markus Spörndli, SECO, Economic Cooperation and Development, Communications Officer, Tel. +41 (0)31 324 09 10, e-mail: markus.spoerndli@seco.admin.ch</contact>
      <attachment id="37658">
        <title>Media material</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>29</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/11360.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <revisions>
        <revision date="2008-03-07 11:25" type="I"/>
      </revisions>
    </content>
    <keywords>
      <keyword id="703001" org-id="703">
        <name lang="de">SECO Cooperation</name>
        <name lang="fr">SECO Cooperation</name>
        <name lang="it">SECO Cooperation</name>
        <name lang="en">SECO Cooperation</name>
      </keyword>
    </keywords>
    <topics>
      <topic id="10">
        <name lang="de">Bundesrat</name>
        <name lang="fr">Conseil fédéral</name>
        <name lang="it">Consiglio federale</name>
        <name lang="en">Federal Council</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="47">
        <name lang="de">Wirtschaft</name>
        <name lang="fr">Économie</name>
        <name lang="it">Economia</name>
        <name lang="en">Economic Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
