<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="18242" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2008-04-10</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="1032" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>701</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eawag: Wasserforschungsinstitut des ETH-Bereichs</name>
      <name lang="fr">Eawag: L'Institut de Recherche de l'Eau du Domaine des EPF</name>
      <name lang="it">Eawag: L'Istituto per la Ricerca sulle Acque nel Settore dei Politecnici Federali</name>
      <name lang="en">Eawag: Swiss Federal Institute of Aquatic Science and Technology</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.eawag.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.eawag.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.eawag.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.eawag.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@eawag.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@eawag.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@eawag.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@eawag.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="701">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Wirtschaft, Bildung und Forschung</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'économie, de la formation et de la recherche</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'economia, della formazione e della ricerca</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Economic Affairs, Education and Research</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Dübendorf</city>
      <title>Erlös des Carla Bruni Fotos für SODIS</title>
      <teaser>Das Carla Bruni Bild des Schweizer Starfotografen Michel Comte wurde heute Donnerstag, 10. April 2008, in New York versteigert. Der Erlös kommt dem Projekt SODIS des Schweizer Wasserforschungsinstituts Eawag zugute.</teaser>
      <lead>Das Carla Bruni Bild des Schweizer Starfotografen Michel Comte wurde heute Donnerstag, 10. April 2008, in New York versteigert. Der Erlös kommt dem Projekt SODIS des Schweizer Wasserforschungsinstituts Eawag zugute.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Das Auktionshaus Christie’s hat heute in New York auf einer der wichtigsten Fotoauktionen dieses Jahres 135 Fotos der Sammlung Gert Elfering versteigert. Darunter ist auch ein berühmtes Aktfoto von Carla Bruni, welches der Schweizer Starfotograf Michel Comte 1993 für eine Anti-Aids-Kampagne aufgenommen hat. Dieses Bild wurde für 91'000 US Dollar versteigert. Der Erlös dieses Bildes geht an das Projekt Sodis des Schweizer Wasserforschungsinstituts Eawag. Der vormalige Besitzer, Gert Elfering, ist von Sodis derart überzeugt, dass er den Auktionspreis durch einen persönlichen Beitrag grosszügig aufrunden will.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Sodis (Solar Water Disinfection) ist eine einfache Methode, um verkeimtes Wasser zu Trinkwasser aufzubereiten. Dabei wird die UV-Strahlung des Sonnenlichts genutzt. Sie tötet Durchfallerreger und andere Krankheitskeime ab, welche sich im Wasser befinden, das zuvor in PET-Flaschen abgefüllt wurde. Sodis wurde – vorangetrieben durch Martin Wegelin – von der Eawag in der Schweiz erforscht, und das Wasserforschungsinstitut unterstützt nun auch die Verbreitung der Methode in Entwicklungsländern. Heute wird Sodis in rund 30 Ländern von mehr als zwei Millionen Menschen benutzt und auch von der WHO empfohlen. Denn nach wie vor hat über ein Drittel der Bevölkerung in Entwicklungsländern keinen Zugang zu sicherem Trinkwasser und täglich sterben rund 6000 Kinder an den Folgen von Durchfallerkrankungen – in den meisten Fällen zurückzuführen auf verkeimtes Trinkwasser.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Der stellvertretende Eawag-Direktor Rik Eggen freut sich: „Diese Unterstützung ist grossartig. Sie hilft uns, Sodis weiter zu verbreiten, die Trinkwasserqualität zu verbessern, Krankheiten zu reduzieren und sogar mehr Leben zu retten.“&amp;nbsp; Sodis ist auf Sponsoren angewiesen und wird bereits seit längerem von der Michel Comte Water Foundation unterstützt. Zurzeit ist Michel Comte in Kambodscha unterwegs und fotografiert unter anderem auch für Sodis.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Weitere Auskünfte: Rik Eggen, stellvertretender Direktor Eawag, 044 823 53 20 www.sodis.ch</contact>
      <attachment id="39432">
        <title>Sodis research at Eawag</title>
        <format>jpg</format>
        <size-kb>264</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/11744.jpg</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Dubendorf</city>
      <title>Bénéfices de la photo de Carla Bruni pour SODIS</title>
      <teaser>La photo de Carla Bruni prise par le célèbre photographe Michel Comte a été vendue aux enchères le 10 avril 2008 à New York. Les bénéfices de la vente sont destinés au Projet SODIS de l’Institut suisse de Recherche de L’Eau (Eawag).</teaser>
      <lead>La photo de Carla Bruni prise par le célèbre photographe Michel Comte a été vendue aux enchères le 10 avril 2008 à New York. Les bénéfices de la vente sont destinés au Projet SODIS de l’Institut suisse de Recherche de L’Eau (Eawag).</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Le 10 avril 2008, lors d’une campagne photographique des plus importante de l’année, 135 photos de la collection Gert Elfering ont été vendues aux enchères à New York. La photo de Carla Bruni réalisée par le célèbre photographe Michel Comte figurait parmi les enchères. Elle a été vendue pour un montant de 91'000 dollars. Les bénéfices de la vente iront au projet Sodis de l’Institut suisse de Recherche de L’Eau (Eawag). Gert Elfering est profondément convaincu par le projet Sodis et envisage de compléter encore la recette de la vente par une contribution financière personnelle.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Sodis (pour SOlar water DISinfection) est une méthode simple pour transformer l’eau contaminée en eau potable. Sodis utilise la lumière solaire et des bouteilles en plastique pour détruire les germes pathogènes responsables de la diarrhée dans l’eau. Sous la direction de Martin Wegelin, l’Eawag a mis au point Sodis et s’est occupé de sa dissémination dans les pays en voie de développement. A l’heure actuelle, plus de deux millions de personnes utilisent Sodis dans quelques 30 pays. Sodis est aussi recommandé&amp;nbsp; par l’OMS. En effet plus d’un tiers de la population des pays en voie de développement n’ont pas accès à une eau potable sûre, 6000 enfants meurent chaque jour de diarrhées principalement causées par la consommation d’une eau contaminée.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Rik Eggen, directeur adjoint de l’Eawag se réjouit : “cette contribution financière est formidable, elle nous permet d’élargir la dissémination de la méthode, d’améliorer la qualité de l’eau, de réduire les maladies et de sauver des vies.”&amp;nbsp; Sodis repose sur le sponsoring et est soutenue par la Fondation Michel Comte pour l’Eau depuis de nombreuses années. Actuellement Michel Comte voyage au Cambodge pour photographier Sodis, entre autre.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Pour plus d’information : Rik Eggen, directeur adjoint de l’Eawag, +41 44 823 53 20 www.sodis.ch</contact>
      <attachment id="39432">
        <title>Sodis research at Eawag</title>
        <format>jpg</format>
        <size-kb>264</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/11744.jpg</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Dübendorf</city>
      <title>Proceeds of Carla Bruni’s photograph for SODIS</title>
      <teaser>Carla Bruni’s photo by the star photographer Michel Comte was auctioned in New York today, April 10, 2008. The proceeds will be donated to the SODIS project of the Swiss Federal Institute of Aquatic Science and Technology, Eawag.</teaser>
      <lead>Carla Bruni’s photo by the star photographer Michel Comte was auctioned in New York today, April 10, 2008. The proceeds will be donated to the SODIS project of the Swiss Federal Institute of Aquatic Science and Technology, Eawag.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;On 10 April 2008 during one of the most important photo campaigns of the year, Christie’s auctioned 135 photographs of Gert Elfering’s collection in New York. The photograph of Carla Bruni taken by the star photographer Michel Comte was among the photos auctioned. This photograph was sold for USD 91'000. The proceeds of this photo will go to the Sodis project of the Swiss Federal Institute of Aquatic Science and Technology, Eawag. Gert Elfering is convinced by the Sodis project and proposes to increase the amount fetched at the auction by an own personal contribution.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Sodis (Solar Water Disinfection) is a simple method to turn contaminated raw water into drinking water. Sodis uses sunlight and plastic bottles to eliminate the diarrhoeal pathogens in the water. Under Martin Wegelin’s leadership, Eawag has investigated Sodis and endorsed the dissemination of the method in developing countries. More than two million people in some 30 countries currently use Sodis. Sodis is also recommended by the WHO since still more than one third of the population in the developing world lacks access to safe drinking water. Each day approximately 6,000 children die from diarrhea caused – in most cases – by contaminated drinking water.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Rik Eggen, Deputy Director of Eawag, is pleased: “This support is capital, as it helps us to further disseminate the method, improve water quality, reduce illness and even save lives.” Sodis relies on sponsoring and has been supported by the Michel Comte Water Foundation for several years. Currently Michel Comte travels in Cambodia, photographing for Sodis, amongst others.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Further information: Rik Eggen, Deputy Director Eawag, +41 44 823 53 20 www.sodis.ch</contact>
      <attachment id="39432">
        <title>Sodis research at Eawag</title>
        <format>jpg</format>
        <size-kb>264</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/11744.jpg</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="8">
        <name lang="de">Bildung und Forschung</name>
        <name lang="fr">Formation et recherche</name>
        <name lang="it">Formazione e ricerca</name>
        <name lang="en">Education and Research</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="15">
        <name lang="de">Gesundheit</name>
        <name lang="fr">Santé</name>
        <name lang="it">sanità</name>
        <name lang="en">Health</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="18">
        <name lang="de">Kultur</name>
        <name lang="fr">Culture</name>
        <name lang="it">Cultura</name>
        <name lang="en">Culture</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="29">
        <name lang="de">Umwelt und Natur</name>
        <name lang="fr">Environnement et nature</name>
        <name lang="it">Ambiente e natura</name>
        <name lang="en">Environment and Nature</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
