<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="19292" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2008-06-12</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="yes" id="508" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>501</department-id>
      <name lang="de">BASPO - Bundesamt für Sport</name>
      <name lang="fr">OFSPO - Office fédéral du sport</name>
      <name lang="it">UFSPO - Ufficio federale dello sport</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Office of Sports</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.baspo.admin.ch/</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.baspo.admin.ch/</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.baspo.admin.ch/</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.baspo.admin.ch/</www>
      <email lang="de">info@baspo.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@baspo.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@baspo.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@baspo.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="501">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Verteidigung, Bevölkerungsschutz und Sport</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de la défense, de la protection de la population et des sports</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale della difesa, della protezione della popolazione e dello sport</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Defence, Civil Protection and Sports DDPS</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.vbs.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.vbs.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.vbs.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.vbs.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@gs-vbs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@gs-vbs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@gs-vbs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@gs-vbs.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Magglingen</city>
      <title>Das Fussballfest geht weiter</title>
      <lead>Die Enttäuschung ist gross: Die Schweizer Fussballnationalmannschaft ist an der UEFA EURO 08 ausgeschieden. Doch für die Schweiz als Gastgeberin und alle Fans geht die Europameisterschaft weiter. Sie erleben einen einmaligen Anlass mit einer begeisternden Stimmung.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;b&gt;Verkehr&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt; Erneut wurden die Angebote des Öffentlichen Verkehrs gut genutzt und der Verkehr lief insgesamt reibungslos. Im Bahnhof Basel mussten zusätzliche Extrazüge eingesetzt werden, um die die grosse Masse von Fans und Besuchern bewältigen zu können.&lt;br /&gt; Die Anreise der gemeldeten Reisecars erfolgt tendenziell immer früher, erste Busse aus Tschechien trafen gestern bereits um 8 Uhr morgens in Genf ein. Die Busregistrierung liefert bereits im Vorfeld der Anreise verlässliche Zahlen, so dass das Parkplatzmanagement erneut problemlos verlief.&lt;br /&gt; Sehr gut genutzt werden auch die Angebote im Bereich Langsamverkehr. In Genf nutzen ca. 4'000 Matchbesucher die Fusswege und gelangten nach einem einstündigen Marsch ins Stadion.&lt;br /&gt; Gesamtschweizerisch wurde gestern ein ÖV-Anteil von ca. 85 Prozent erreicht. &lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; &lt;b&gt;Besondere Vorkommnisse&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt; Die Polizei verzeichnete ausser einzelnen Schlägereien nach dem Spiel keine nennenswerten Vorkommnisse.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; &lt;b&gt;Public Viewing&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt; Erwartungsgemäss waren die Fanzonen und UBS-Arenen am Mittwochabend voll. In vielen Städten waren die Sitzplätze auf den Tribünen ausverkauft und die Stimmung gut. Je nach Verlauf der UEFA EURO 2008 werden die Fangemeinden in der Schweiz diese Plätze erneut füllen.&lt;br /&gt; &amp;nbsp;&lt;br /&gt; &lt;b&gt;Besuchereinlass im Stadion St. Jakob-Park&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt; Die Verbesserungen der Anreise und des Einlasses ins Stadion in Basel wurden durch die Organisatoren umgesetzt. Es gab mehr und grössere Hinweisschilder und das Warten auf die Kontrolle durch die Stewards dauerte rund 20 Minuten, also weniger lang als beim Eröffnungsspiel.</text>
      <contact>Barbara Meier Kommunikationschefin EURO 2008 des Bundes Tel. +41 31 325 88 41 Mobile: +41 79 244 66 65 E-Mail: media.euro2008@baspo.admin.ch www.switzerland.com</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Macolin</city>
      <title>La fête du ballon rond continue</title>
      <lead>La déception est de taille: l’équipe suisse de football est éliminée de l’UEFA EURO 2008. Il n’empêche que pour la Suisse, pays hôte, et tous les supporters, le Championnat d’Europe continue. Ils vivent avec beaucoup d’enthousiasme un événement unique.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;b&gt;Transports&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt; Une fois de plus, les offres de transport public ont été très sollicitées et le trafic s’est écoulé dans l’ensemble sans difficultés. À la gare de Bâle, il a fallu mettre en service des trains supplémentaires pour pouvoir absorber l’énorme masse des supporters et des visiteurs.&lt;br /&gt; Les autocars annoncés ont tendance à arriver toujours plus tôt. C’est ainsi que les bus en provenance de République tchèque sont arrivés hier à Genève dès 8h00 du matin. Leur enregistrement au départ fournit des chiffres fiables, de sorte que la gestion des places de parking, une fois encore, n’a posé aucun problème.&lt;br /&gt; Les offres de locomotion dite lente (voies piétonnes, entre autres) sont très appréciées également. À Genève, quelque 4 000 personnes ont emprunté les voies piétonnes, parvenant au stade après une heure de marche.&lt;br /&gt; Sur l’ensemble du territoire suisse, la part des transports publics a atteint hier 85 pour cent. &lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; &lt;b&gt;Incidents notables&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt; En dehors de rixes isolées, la police n’a eu connaissance d’aucun incident notable après les matches.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; &lt;b&gt;Projections publiques&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt; Comme c’était prévisible, les fanzones et les UBS ARENA étaient combles mercredi soir. Bon nombre de villes ont affiché complet pour les places assises de tribune, le tout dans une bonne ambiance. Suivant la physionomie que prendra l’UEFA EURO 2008, les communautés de supporters feront à nouveau le plein de ces places en Suisse.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; &lt;b&gt;Accès des spectateurs au stade St-Jacques&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt; Les organisateurs ont apporté les améliorations souhaitées sur le trajet menant au Parc St-Jacques et pour l’accès au stade de Bâle. Ils ont fait installer des panneaux indicateurs plus grands et plus nombreux, et l’attente aux postes de contrôle surveillés par les stadiers a duré une vingtaine de minutes, soit moins longtemps que lors du match d’ouverture.</text>
      <contact>Barbara Meier Responsable de la communication EURO 2008 de la Confédération Tél. +41 31 325 88 41 Portable: +41 79 244 66 65 Adresse courriel: media.euro2008@baspo.admin.ch www.switzerland.com</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Macolin</city>
      <title>La grande festa del calcio continua</title>
      <lead>La delusione è grande: la nazionale di calcio rossocrociata è stata eliminata. Tuttavia per la Svizzera in qualità di nazione ospitante del campionato UEFA EURO 2008 e per i tutti i tifosi del pallone la festa continua e vivono l’eccezionale evento con entusiasmo.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;b&gt;Trasporti&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt; Ancora una volta si è fatto ampio ricorso alle offerte di trasporto pubblico e, nel complesso, il traffico è stato scorrevole. Per poter far fronte all’enorme afflusso di tifosi e visitatori nella stazione di Basilea si sono dovute potenziare le corse con treni speciali. &lt;br /&gt; L’arrivo dei pullman annunciati avviene di solito con un certo anticipo e ieri i primi veicoli provenienti dalla Repubblica Ceca hanno fatto il loro ingresso a Ginevra già alle 8 del mattino. La registrazione dei bus con-sente di ottenere delle cifre attendibili già prima del loro arrivo, agevolando la gestione dei parcheggi che – anche ieri – è proceduta senza intoppi.&lt;br /&gt; Si fa anche ampio uso delle offerte nel settore del traffico lento. A Ginevra all’incirca 4'000 spettatori si sono recati allo stadio a piedi e sono giunti a destinazione dopo aver camminato per un’ora.&lt;br /&gt; Ieri in tutta la Svizzera la percentuale di utilizzo dei mezzi pubblici è stata all’incirca dell’85 per cento.&lt;br /&gt; &amp;nbsp;&lt;br /&gt; &lt;b&gt;Avvenimenti particolari&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt; Ad eccezione di qualche rissa isolata, la polizia non ha segnalato avvenimenti significativi dopo la partita.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; &lt;b&gt;Public viewing&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt; Come da previsioni, mercoledì sera, le zone per i tifosi e le Arene UBS hanno registrato il pienone. In molte città i posti a sedere in tribuna erano esauriti. L’atmosfera era gioiosa e serena. A seconda di come procederà UEFA EURO 2008 le cerchie dei tifosi in Svizzera torneranno a riempire questi posti.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; &lt;b&gt;Ingresso dei visitatori allo stadio St. Jakob-Park&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt; Sono stati messi in campo dagli organizzatori miglioramenti per l’arrivo e l’ingresso nello stadio di Basilea. Le dimensioni e il numero dei cartelli segnaletici sono state incrementate e l’attesa per il controllo da parte degli stewards è durata all’incirca 20 minuti, un tempo inferiore rispetto alla partita di esordio.</text>
      <contact>Barbara Meier Responsabile della comunicazione EURO 2008 della Confederazione Tel. +41 31 325 88 41 Cellulare: +41 79 244 66 65 E-mail: media.euro2008@baspo.admin.ch www.switzerland.com</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Magglingen</city>
      <title>The football festival continues</title>
      <lead>The disappointment is huge: the Swiss national football team has been eliminated from the UEFA EURO 2008. However, for Switzerland as host and all the fans, the European Championship goes on. They are enjoying a unique occasion full of enthusiasm.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;b&gt;Traffic&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt; Once again the public transport facilities were well used and traffic generally circulated smoothly. At Basle station, extra trains had to be laid on, to cope with the large crowds of fans and visitors.&lt;br /&gt; The arrival of the announced coaches is happening progressively earlier, and yesterday the first buses from the Czech Republic reached Geneva already by 08:00 am. The registration of buses on the outskirts of the destination provides reliable numbers, so that the handling of the parking areas went off again without difficulty.&lt;br /&gt; The non-motorized traffic facilities also proved very popular. In Geneva, around 4,000 match visitors used the pedestrian ways and reached the stadium after about an hour’s walk.&lt;br /&gt; Yesterday, throughout Switzerland an 85 percent public transport share of traffic was achieved. &lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; &lt;b&gt;Special incidents&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt; Apart from a few isolated fights after the match, the police announced no unusual incidents.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; &lt;b&gt;Public Viewing&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt; As expected, the fan zones and UBS arenas were full on Wednesday evening. In many towns the seats in the stands were sold out and the atmosphere was great. This seating will fill up again with the various fan groups as the UEFA EURO 2008 proceeds.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; &lt;b&gt;Visitor access at the St. Jakob-Park stadium&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt; The improvements to the approaches and entrance areas of the stadium in Basel were put in place. There were more and bigger signboards and waiting during control by the stewards lasted around 20 minutes, so less than during the opening match.</text>
      <contact>Barbara Meier Head of Communications EURO 2008 for the Confederation Tel. +41 31 325 88 41 Mobile: +41 79 244 66 65 E-Mail: media.euro2008@baspo.admin.ch www.switzerland.com</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <offers>
      <offer id="189" org-id="508">
        <name lang="de">UEFA Euro 2008</name>
        <name lang="fr">UEFA Euro 2008</name>
        <name lang="it">UEFA Euro 2008</name>
        <name lang="en">UEFA Euro 2008</name>
      </offer>
    </offers>
    <keywords>
      <keyword id="560" org-id="508">
        <name lang="de">Logistik</name>
        <name lang="fr">logistique</name>
        <name lang="it">logistica</name>
        <name lang="en">Logistics</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="5390" org-id="508">
        <name lang="de">Sport</name>
        <name lang="fr">Sport</name>
        <name lang="it">Sport</name>
        <name lang="en">sport</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="5470" org-id="508">
        <name lang="de">UEFA Euro 2008</name>
        <name lang="fr">Championnat d'Europe de football Euro 2008</name>
        <name lang="it">UEFA Euro 2008</name>
        <name lang="en">UEFA Euro 2008</name>
      </keyword>
    </keywords>
    <topics>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="40">
        <name lang="de">Sicherheit</name>
        <name lang="fr">Sécurité</name>
        <name lang="it">Sicurezza</name>
        <name lang="en">Security</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="42">
        <name lang="de">Sport</name>
        <name lang="fr">Sport</name>
        <name lang="it">Sport</name>
        <name lang="en">Sport</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="46">
        <name lang="de">Verkehr</name>
        <name lang="fr">Transports</name>
        <name lang="it">Trasporti</name>
        <name lang="en">Transport</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
    <catalogueElements>
      <catalogueElement id="66">
        <name lang="de">Euro 08</name>
        <name lang="fr">Euro 08</name>
        <name lang="it">Euro 08</name>
        <name lang="en">Euro 08</name>
      </catalogueElement>
    </catalogueElements>
  </message>
</messages>
