<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="20220" revoked="no">
    <version>3</version>
    <pubdate>2008-07-19</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="201" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>201</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="201">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Geneva Talks: Position der Schweiz</title>
      <lead>Der Hohe Vertreter der EU für die Gemeinsame Aussen- und Sicherheitspolitik, Javier Solana, hat sich im Namen der sechs Länder der Gruppe EU3+3 mit dem iranischen Chefunterhändler für Nuklearfragen, Saed Jalili, in Genf getroffen. Beide Parteien hatten die Schweiz gebeten, diese Gespräche zu organisieren. Die Schweiz begrüsst, dass die Parteien vereinbart haben, den Dialog weiter zu führen.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Bundesrätin Micheline Calmy-Rey empfing nach dem Treffen Solana und Jalili zu separaten Gesprächen und wiederholte die Position der Schweiz, welche sich stets für eine diplomatische Lösung in der iranischen Nuklearfrage eingesetzt hat. Die Schweiz begrüsst und unterstützt die EU3+3-Initiative und insbesondere das Konzept des so genannten „freeze for freeze“.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Frau Calmy-Rey gab ihrer Genugtuung Ausdruck, dass die Schweizer Diplomatie mit diesem Treffen in Genf einen Beitrag zum Dialog leisten konnte. Dies ist ein Zeichen des Vertrauens in die Schweizer Diplomatie. Solana und Jalili dankten der Schweiz und Genf für die Vorbereitung und Durchführung des Treffens.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Die Schweiz hat in der Vergangenheit verschiedene Ideen entwickelt, welche die Rückkehr der beteiligten Parteien an den Verhandlungstisch ermöglichen sollten.&amp;nbsp;Die Geneva Talks unterstreichen auch die Bedeutung der Schweiz als Ort der Begegnung und Gespräche für die Lösung von internationalen Problemen.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Presse- und Informationsdienst Bundeshaus West CH-3003 Bern Tel.: +41 (0)31 322 31 53 Fax: +41 (0)31 324 90 47 E-Mail: info@eda.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions>
        <revision date="2008-07-21 14:21" type="R"/>
      </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Geneva Talks : position de la Suisse</title>
      <lead>Javier Solana, Haut représentant de l’Union européenne pour la politique étrangère et de sécurité commune, a rencontré samedi à Genève, au nom du groupe des six pays UE3+3, Saïd Jalili, négociateur en chef pour les questions nucléaires de la République Islamique d’Iran. Les deux parties avaient demandé à la Suisse d’accueillir ces entretiens. La Suisse salue le fait que les parties ont convenu de poursuivre le dialogue.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;La conseillère fédérale Micheline Calmy-Rey, cheffe du Département fédéral des affaires étrangères (DFAE), a reçu séparément en fin de journée les deux chefs de délégation. Elle a répété la position de la Suisse, qui s’est toujours engagée en faveur d’une solution diplomatique de la question nucléaire iranienne. La Suisse salue et soutient l’initiative du groupe des six pays UE3+3 et, en particulier, le concept désigné par l’appellation «freeze for freeze».&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Madame Calmy-Rey a également souligné que la diplomatie suisse avait apporté une contribution au dialogue en accueillant cette rencontre à Genève. C’est un signe de la confiance placée dans la diplomatie suisse. Messieurs Solana et Jalili ont exprimé leur reconnaissance à la Suisse et à Genève pour la préparation et l’accueil de cette rencontre.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Par le passé, la Suisse a développé diverses idées, qui devaient rendre possible le retour des parties concernées à la table de négociations. Les Geneva Talks soulignent le rôle significatif de la Suisse comme lieu de rencontre et de dialogue en vue de trouver des solutions à des problèmes internationaux.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Service de presse et d'information Palais fédéral ouest CH-3003 Berne Tél.: (+41) 031 322 31 53 Fax: (+41) 031 324 90 47 E-Mail: info@eda.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions>
        <revision date="2008-07-21 11:47" type="R"/>
      </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Geneva Talks: posizione della Svizzera</title>
      <lead>L’Alto rappresentante dell’Unione europea per la politica estera e di sicurezza comune, Javier Solana, ha incontrato sabato a Ginevra, in nome del gruppo dei sei Paesi UE3+3, Saïd Jalili, capo negoziatore per le questioni nucleari della Repubblica islamica d’Iran. Le due parti avevano chiesto alla Svizzera di accogliere questi colloqui. La Svizzera saluta il fatto che le parti abbiano convenuto di proseguire il dialogo.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;In fine giornata, la consigliera federale e capo del Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri (DFAE), Micheline Calmy-Rey, ha ricevuto separatamente i due capi delegazione, reiterando la posizione della Svizzera che si è sempre adoperata a favore di una soluzione diplomatica della questione nucleare iraniana. La Svizzera sostiene l’iniziativa del gruppo dei sei Paesi UE3+3 e, in particolare, il concetto denominato «freeze for freeze».&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Micheline Calmy-Rey ha rilevato che, accogliendo questo incontro a Ginevra, la diplomazia svizzera ha potuto dare il suo contributo al dialogo, a dimostrazione del fatto che essa gode della fiducia degli interessati. Solana e Jalili hanno espresso la loro riconoscenza alla Svizzera e a Ginevra per l’organizzazione di questo incontro.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;In passato, la Svizzera aveva sviluppato diverse idee nell’intento di rendere possibile il ritorno delle parti in causa al tavolo dei negoziati. I Geneva Talks evidenziano il ruolo significativo della Svizzera quale luogo di incontro e di dialogo per trovare una soluzione ai problemi internazionali.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Servizio stampa e informazione Palazzo federale ovest CH-3003 Berna Tel.: (+41) 031 322 31 53 Fax: (+41) 031 324 90 47 E-Mail: info@eda.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Geneva Talks: Switzerland's position</title>
      <lead>The EU High Representative for the Common Foreign and Security Policy Javier Solana has met the Iranian chief negotiator for nuclear questions Saeed Jalili in Geneva on behalf of the six countries of the EU3+3. Switzerland welcomes the fact that the parties have agreed to continue the dialogue.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;After the meeting, federal councillor Micheline Calmy-Rey, head of the Federal Department of Foreign Affairs, received Solana and Jalili for separate talks. She repeated the position of Switzerland, which has always advocated a diplomatic solution to the Iranian nuclear issue. Switzerland welcomes and supports the EU3+3 initiative, in particular the "freeze for freeze“ concept. &amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Micheline Calmy-Rey expressed her satisfaction that Swiss diplomacy was able to make a contribution to the dialogue by organising this meeting in Geneva. This a sign of trust in Swiss diplomacy. Solana and Jalili thanked Switzerland and Geneva for the preparation and hosting of the meeting. &amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;In the past, Switzerland has presented a variety of ideas to enable the parties involved to return to the negotiating table. The Geneva Talks also underlined the importance of Switzerland as a place of meeting and talks to solve international problems.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Press and Information Service Bundeshaus West CH-3003 Bern Tel.: (+41) 031 322 31 53 Fax: (+41) 031 324 90 47 E-Mail: info@eda.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="34">
        <name lang="de">Europa</name>
        <name lang="fr">Europe</name>
        <name lang="it">Europa</name>
        <name lang="en">Europe</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
