<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="22016" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2008-10-15</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="201" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>201</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="201">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Den Terrorismus mit den Mitteln des Rechts noch effizienter bekämpfen</title>
      <lead>Am 15. Oktober 2008 haben Vertreter der Schweiz in New York, Wien und London die Ratifikations- bzw. Beitrittsurkunden für vier internationale Abkommen der UNO und ihrer Sonderorganisationen zur Bekämpfung des nuklearen und maritimen Terrorismus hinterlegt. Die Schweiz gehört somit zu den ersten drei Staaten, welche alle 16 universellen UNO-Übereinkommen und -Protokolle zur Bekämpfung des Terrorismus ratifiziert haben.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Die vier Abkommen, welche die internationale Zusammenarbeit bei der Terrorismusbekämpfung verstärken sollen, wurden von den Eidgenössischen Räten im vergangenen Juni einstimmig genehmigt. Eine Anpassung des Landesrechts war nicht erforderlich, da die Schweiz die zur Umsetzung der Abkommen notwendigen Regelungen bereits im innerstaatlichen Recht verankert hat.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Die Bekämpfung des Terrorismus ist für die Schweiz seit langem ein wichtiges Anliegen. Sie setzt sich dabei insbesondere dafür ein, dass der Terrorismus auf der Basis völkerrechtlicher Übereinkommen bekämpft wird. Nur mit den Mitteln des Rechts kann ein längerfristiges und allgemein akzeptiertes Fundament für die zwischenstaatliche Zusammenarbeit geschaffen werden.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;u&gt;Auskunft:&lt;/u&gt; Botschafterin Christine Schraner Burgener, Stellvertretende Direktorin der Direktion für Völkerrecht (DV), Tel. 031 322 30 87</text>
      <contact>Presse- und Informationsdienst Bundeshaus West CH-3003 Bern Tel.: +41 (0)31 322 31 53 Fax: +41 (0)31 324 90 47 E-Mail: info@eda.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Renforcer l’efficacité de la lutte contre le terrorisme par le droit</title>
      <lead>Le 15 octobre 2008, des représentants de la Suisse à New York, Vienne et Londres ont déposé les instruments de ratification et d’adhésion concernant quatre conventions et protocoles internationaux de l’ONU et de ses institutions spécialisées dans le domaine de la lutte contre le terrorisme nucléaire et maritime. La Suisse est ainsi l’un des trois premiers pays à avoir ratifié les 16 conventions et protocoles universels des Nations Unies en matière de lutte contre le terrorisme.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Les quatre conventions, qui visent à renforcer la coopération internationale en matière de lutte contre le terrorisme, ont été approuvées à l’unanimité par les Chambres fédérales en juin dernier. Une adaptation de la législation nationale n’était pas nécessaire, les dispositions requises pour la mise en œuvre des conventions ayant déjà été intégrées dans le droit suisse. &amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Pour la Suisse, la lutte contre le terrorisme constitue depuis longtemps une préoccupation majeure. La Suisse œuvre en particulier en faveur d’une lutte antiterroriste basée sur des accords internationaux. Seul le recours au droit permettra de créer un cadre pour la coopération entre les Etats qui soit durable et accepté par le plus grand nombre.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;u&gt;Renseignements:&lt;/u&gt; Christine Schraner Burgener, Ambassadeur, Directrice adjointe de la Direction du droit international public (DDIP), tél. 031 322 30 87&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Service de presse et d'information Palais fédéral ouest CH-3003 Berne Tél.: (+41) 031 322 31 53 Fax: (+41) 031 324 90 47 E-Mail: info@eda.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Combattere ancora più efficacemente il terrorismo con gli strumenti del diritto</title>
      <lead>Rappresentanti della Svizzera a New York, Vienna e Londra hanno depositato il 15 ottobre 2008 i documenti di ratifica e di adesione di quattro convenzioni e protocolli internazionali dell’ONU e delle sue organizzazioni speciali concernenti la lotta al terrorismo nucleare e marittimo. La Svizzera figura quindi fra i primi tre Stati che hanno ratificato tutti e 16 gli accordi universali e i protocolli dell’ONU sulla lotta contro il terrorismo.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Destinati a rafforzare la collaborazione internazionale nell’ambito della lotta contro il terrorismo, le quattro convenzioni sono stati approvati all’unanimità lo scorso giugno dalle Camere federali. Un adeguamento del diritto interno non si è rivelato necessario avendo la Svizzera già integrato nella legislazione interna i disciplinamenti necessari all’attuazione degli accordi.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;La lotta al terrorismo è da tempo un tema prioritario per la Svizzera, la quale s’impegna affinché il terrorismo sia combattuto sulla base di accordi internazionali. &amp;nbsp;Un fondamento generalmente riconosciuto e di lunga durata per una collaborazione interstatale può essere posto unicamente con gli strumenti del diritto.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;u&gt;Informazioni:&lt;/u&gt; Ambasciatrice Christine Schraner Burgener, Vicedirettrice della Direzione del diritto internazionale pubblico (DIP), tel. 031 322 30 87&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Servizio stampa e informazione Palazzo federale ovest CH-3003 Berna Tel.: (+41) 031 322 31 53 Fax: (+41) 031 324 90 47 E-Mail: info@eda.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Combating terrorism more effectively by legal means</title>
      <lead>On 15 October 2008, representatives of Switzerland in New York, Vienna and London deposited the instruments of ratification and accession for four international conventions and protocols of the United Nations (UN) regarding combating nuclear and maritime terrorism. Switzerland is thus one of the first three States to have ratified all 16 universal UN conventions and protocols on combating terrorism.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;The four international legal instruments, which are intended to strengthen international cooperation on combating terrorism, were approved unanimously by the two houses of the federal parliament last June. No amendment of national law was necessary, since Switzerland has already anchored the regulations required to implement the agreement in its national law.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;For Switzerland, the fight against terrorism has long been an important concern. In particular, it is committed to combating terrorism on the basis of international legal conventions. It is only with a legal based approach that a long-term and generally acceptable foundation for cooperation between States can be created.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;u&gt;Information:&lt;/u&gt; Ambassador Christine Schraner Burgener, Deputy Director of the Directorate of Public International Law (DPIL), Tel. 031 322 30 87&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Press and Information Service Bundeshaus West CH-3003 Bern Tel.: (+41) 031 322 31 53 Fax: (+41) 031 324 90 47 E-Mail: info@eda.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
