<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="22977" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2008-11-18</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="703" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>701</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Staatssekretariat für Wirtschaft</name>
      <name lang="fr">Secrétariat d'Etat à l'économie</name>
      <name lang="it">Segreteria di Stato dell'economia</name>
      <name lang="en">State Secretariat for Economic Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.seco.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.seco.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.seco.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.seco.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@seco.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@seco.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@seco.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@seco.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="201" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>201</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="701">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Wirtschaft, Bildung und Forschung</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'économie, de la formation et de la recherche</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'economia, della formazione e della ricerca</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Economic Affairs, Education and Research</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <department id="201">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Unterzeichnung eines bilateralen Rahmenabkommens mit Venezuela</title>
      <lead>Jean-Daniel Gerber, Direktor des Staatssekretariats für Wirtschaft SECO, hat am 18. November 2008 den venezolanischen Vize-Aussenminister für Europa, Alejandro Fleming, zu einem Arbeitstreffen in Bern empfangen. Im Anschluss an das Treffen hat der Staatssekretär gemeinsam mit seinem Gesprächspartner ein Rahmenabkommen zur Zusammenarbeit zwischen der Schweiz und Venezuela unterzeichnet.</lead>
      <text link="no">Das Rahmenabkommen bildet die Grundlage für die weitere Entwicklung der bilateralen Wirtschaftsbeziehungen und die Beteiligung von Schweizer Firmen an Projekten in Venezuela. Es beinhaltet die Schaffung einer Gemischten Kommission, welche eine Plattform für den bilateralen Wirtschaftsdialog bilden soll. Ziel dieser Kommission ist, die Zusammenarbeit beider Länder in wirtschaftsrelevanten Gebieten zu fördern und allfällige Handels- und Investitionshemmnisse unter Einbezug der Privatwirtschaft gemeinsam besprechen und angehen zu können.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Anlässlich seines Besuchs in der Schweiz hat Vize-Aussenminister Fleming am 18. November 2008 zudem Botschafter Pierre Helg, stellvertretender Politischer Direktor im Eidgenössischen Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten EDA, zu politischen Konsultationen getroffen.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; In den ersten neun Monaten des laufenden Jahres exportierte die Schweiz Güter im Wert von gut CHF 200 Millionen nach Venezuela und importierte Waren aus Venezuela im Wert von CHF 53 Millionen. Der Bestand der Schweizer Investitionen in Venezuela belief sich Ende 2006 auf CHF 888 Millionen. Schweizer Firmen beschäftigen in Venezuela 10'625 Personen.</text>
      <contact>Philippe Nell, SECO, Leiter Ressort Amerika, Tel. +41 (0)31 322 23 27 Information EDA, Tel. +41 (0)31 322 31 53</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Signature d’un accord-cadre bilatéral avec le Venezuela</title>
      <lead>Jean-Daniel Gerber, directeur du Secrétariat d'Etat à l'économie SECO, a reçu Alejandro Fleming, vice-ministre vénézuélien des affaires étrangères affecté à l’Europe, lors d’une visite de travail à Berne le 18 novembre 2008. A la suite de cette rencontre, le Secrétaire d’Etat et son interlocuteur ont signé un accord-cadre portant sur la collaboration entre la Suisse et le Venezuela.</lead>
      <text link="no">L’accord-cadre constitue la base pour continuer de développer les relations économiques bilatérales avec le Venezuela et pour favoriser la participation d'entreprises suisses à des projets au Venezuela. Il prévoit la création d’une commission mixte qui servira de plate-forme pour le dialogue économique bilatéral. La commission devra par ailleurs promouvoir la collaboration des deux pays dans des dossiers économiques et examiner les potentielles entraves au commerce et aux investissements en intégrant l'économie privée à la discussion.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Lors de sa visite en Suisse, Alejandro Fleming, vice-ministre des affaires étrangères, a rencontré par ailleurs le 18 novembre 2008 l'ambassadeur Pierre Helg, suppléant du directeur de la Direction politique au Département fédéral des affaires étrangères DFAE, pour des consultations politiques.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Au cours des neuf premiers mois de l’année, les exportations de la Suisse au Venezuela ont dépassé les 200 millions de francs et ses importations depuis ce pays se sont élevées à 53 millions de francs. Fin 2006, les investissements suisses au Venezuela s’élevaient à 888 millions de francs et les sociétés suisses y employaient quelque 10'625 personnes.</text>
      <contact>Philippe Nell, SECO, Chef du secteur Amériques, tél. +41 (0)31 322 23 27 Information DFAE, tél. +41 (0)31 322 31 53</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Firma di un accordo quadro bilaterale con il Venezuela</title>
      <lead>Il 18 novembre 2008, il direttore della Segreteria di Stato dell’economia SECO Jean-Daniel Gerber ha ricevuto il viceministro degli Affari esteri venezuelano per l'Europa, Alejandro Fleming, per un incontro di lavoro a Berna. Dopo l’incontro, il segretario di Stato e il suo interlocutore hanno firmato un accordo quadro per la collaborazione tra la Svizzera e il Venezuela.</lead>
      <text link="no">L’accordo quadro costituisce la base per un ulteriore sviluppo delle relazioni economiche bilaterali e la partecipazione di imprese svizzere alla realizzazione di progetti in Venezuela. Esso prevede la creazione di una commissione mista che dovrebbe costituire una piattaforma per il dialogo bilaterale in ambito economico. La commissione ha il compito di promuovere la collaborazione dei due Paesi in settori rilevanti dal punto di vista economico e di consentire loro di discutere e affrontare insieme eventuali ostacoli al commercio e agli investimenti, coinvolgendo l’economia privata.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Inoltre, in occasione della sua visita in Svizzera, il 18 novembre 2008, il viceministro degli Affari esteri Fleming ha incontrato per una consultazione politica l’ambasciatore Pierre Helg, direttore politico sostituto del Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri (DFAE).&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Nei primi nove mesi dell’anno in corso, la Svizzera ha esportato in Venezuela merci per un valore di oltre 200 milioni di franchi e ha importato prodotti dal Paese sudamericano per 53 milioni di franchi. In Venezuela, gli investimenti svizzeri registrati alla fine del 2006 ammontavano a 888 milioni di franchi, mentre le imprese svizzere occupano attualmente circa 10'625 persone.</text>
      <contact>Philippe Nell, SECO, Capo del settore Americhe, tel. +41 (0)31 322 23 27 Informazione DFAE, tel. +41 (0)31 322 31 53</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Signing of a bilateral framework agreement with Venezuela</title>
      <lead>On 18 November 2008, Jean-Daniel Gerber, Director of the State Secretariat for Economic Affairs SECO, received Venezuela’s Vice Foreign Minister for Europe, Alejandro Fleming, for a working visit in Bern. Following the meeting, the State Secretary and the Vice Foreign Minister signed a framework agreement on cooperation between Switzerland and Venezuela.</lead>
      <text link="no">The framework agreement will form the basis for the further development of bilateral economic relations and for the participation of Swiss firms in projects in Venezuela. It proposes the creation of a mixed committee to serve as a platform for bilateral dialogue on economic affairs. The aim of this committee is to promote cooperation between the two countries in areas relevant to business and to discuss and tackle jointly possible barriers to trade and investment with the involvement of the private sector.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; During his visit to Switzerland on 18 November 2008, Vice Foreign Minister Fleming has also met with Ambassador Pierre Helg, Deputy Political Director at Federal Department of Foreign Affairs (FDFA) for political consultations.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; During the first nine months of this year Switzerland exported goods to Venezuela valued at over CHF 200 million and imported goods from Venezuela to the value of CHF 53 million. At the end of 2006 the level of Swiss investment in Venezuela amounted to CHF 888 million. Swiss firms employ roughly 10,625 people in Venezuela.</text>
      <contact>Philippe Nell, SECO, Head of the section America, tel. +41 (0)31 322 23 27 Information FDFA, tel. +41 (0)31 322 31 53</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
