<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="23333" revoked="no">
    <version>2</version>
    <pubdate>2008-11-26</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="yes" id="302" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>301</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Generalsekretariat EDI</name>
      <name lang="fr">Secrétariat général DFI</name>
      <name lang="it">Segreteria generale DFI</name>
      <name lang="en">General Secretariat FDHA</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="202" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>201</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Generalsekretariat EDA</name>
      <name lang="fr">Secrétariat général DFAE</name>
      <name lang="it">Segreteria generale DFAE</name>
      <name lang="en">General Secretary DFA</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.eda.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/home.html</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/home.html</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de"/>
      <email lang="fr"/>
      <email lang="it"/>
      <email lang="en"/>
    </originator>
    <department id="301">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement des Innern</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'intérieur</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'interno</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Home Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <department id="201">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Offizieller Arbeitsbesuch des französischen Premierministers François Fillon</title>
      <lead>Bundespräsident Pascal Couchepin empfängt am 28. November 2008 den französischen Premierminister François Fillon im Château de Lucens zu einem offiziellen Arbeitsbesuch. Er wird dabei von Aussenministerin Micheline Calmy-Rey und Bundesrat Moritz Leuenberger, Vorsteher des Eidgenössischen Departements für Umwelt, Verkehr, Energie und Kommunikation, begleitet.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Gesprächsthemen bei diesem ersten offiziellen Besuch eines französischen Premierministers seit dem Besuch von Michel Rocard am 26. März 1991 sind neben den bilateralen Beziehungen vor allem die wirtschaftliche Situation in Europa, die neue Finanzarchitektur nach dem G20-Gipfel sowie die Beziehungen zwischen der Schweiz und der Europäischen Union. Dabei werden insbesondere Fragen im Bereich Steuern, Forschung, Agrar-Freihandelsabkommen sowie Energie besprochen.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Der Schweizer Regierungsdelegation gehört unter anderem Jean-Daniel Gerber, Staatssekretär für Wirtschaft, an.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Der Besuch bietet zudem Gelegenheit, den Premierminister des Landes zu treffen, das den Vorsitz der Europäischen Union innehat. Es ist üblich, dass ein Bundesratsmitglied einen Regierungsvertreter des EU-Vorsitzes trifft. In der ersten Jahreshälfte hatte Bundespräsident Pascal Couchepin seinen slowenischen Amtskollegen, Präsident Danilo Turk, getroffen.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Jean-Marc Crevoisier, Kommunikationschef EDI, +41 79 763 84 10</contact>
      <attachment id="48031">
        <title>Medienprogramm</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>28</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/13754.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <link id="48034">
        <title>Weitere Informationen:</title>
        <uri>http://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home/dfa/head/event/2008/france.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Visite officielle de travail du Premier ministre français François Fillon</title>
      <lead>Le Président de la Confédération Pascal Couchepin, accompagné de la cheffe du Département fédéral des affaires étrangères Micheline Calmy-Rey et du chef du Département de l’environnement, des transports, de l’énergie et de la communication, Moritz Leuenberger, recevra, le 28 novembre au Château de Lucens, le Premier ministre français François Fillon.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Au programme des entretiens de cette première visite officielle d’un Premier ministre français en Suisse depuis celle de Michel Rocard le 26 mars 1991 figurent notamment la situation économique en Europe, la nouvelle architecture financière mondiale après le Sommet du G 20 et les relations entre la Suisse et l’Union Européenne. Les dossiers de la fiscalité, de la recherche, de l’accord de libre-échange agricole et de l’énergie seront notamment évoqués.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Jean-Daniel Gerber, secrétaire d’Etat à l’économie complètera notamment la délégation gouvernementale suisse.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Cette visite permet également de rencontrer le Premier ministre du pays qui préside l’Union européenne. Une rencontre entre un membre du Gouvernement suisse et du Gouvernement assurant la présidence de l’UE est traditionnellement agendée. Au premier semestre 2008, Pascal Couchepin avait rencontre son homologue slovène, le Président Danilo Turk.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Jean-Marc Crevoisier, Chef du service de la communication DFI, +41 79 763 84 10</contact>
      <attachment id="48032">
        <title>Programme pour les médias</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>28</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/13755.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <link id="48035">
        <title>Informations supplémentaires:</title>
        <uri>http://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/home/dfa/head/event/2008/france.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Visita di lavoro ufficiale del Primo ministro francese François Fillon</title>
      <lead>Il 28 novembre 2008, il Presidente della Confederazione, Pascal Couchepin, il Capo del Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri, Micheline Calmy-Rey, e il Capo del Dipartimento federale dell’ambiente, dei trasporti, dell’energia e delle comunicazioni, Moritz Leuenberger, riceveranno al Castello di Lucens il Primo ministro francese François Fillon.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Nell’agenda dei colloqui di questa visita ufficiale di un Primo ministro francese in Svizzera, la prima da quella di Michel Rocard del 26 marzo 1991, figurano in particolare la situazione economica in Europa, la nuova architettura finanziaria mondiale dopo il Vertice del G-20 e le relazioni tra la Svizzera e l’Unione Europea. Saranno affrontati anche i dossier della fiscalità, della ricerca, dell’accordo di libero scambio agricolo e dell’energia.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Completerà la delegazione governativa svizzera Jean-Daniel Gerber, Segretario di Stato dell’economia.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;La visita permette altresì di incontrare il Primo ministro del Paese che presiede l’Unione europea. L’incontro fra un membro del Governo svizzero e del Governo che assicura la presidenza dell’UE è divenuto un appuntamento tradizionale: nel primo semestre del 2008, Pascal Couchepin aveva incontrato il suo omologo sloveno, il Presidente Danilo Turk.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Jean-Marc Crevoisier, Responsabile comunicazione DFI, +41 79 763 84 10</contact>
      <attachment id="48033">
        <title>Programme pour les médias</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>28</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/13756.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <link id="48036">
        <title>Informations supplémentaires:</title>
        <uri>http://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/home/dfa/head/event/2008/france.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Official working visit by French Prime Minister François Fillon</title>
      <lead>On 28 November 2008 President of the Confederation Pascal Couchepin will receive French Prime Minister François Fillon in the Château de Lucens for an official working visit. He will be accompanied by Foreign Minister Micheline Calmy-Rey and Federal Councillor Moritz Leuenberger, Head of the Federal Department of Environment, Transport, Energy and Communication.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;The topics for discussion at this first official visit by a French prime minster since that of Michel Rocard on 26 March 1991 will include bilateral relations and above all the economic situation in Europe, the new financial architecture following the G20 summit and relations between Switzerland and the European Union. In this area questions relating to taxation, research, the free trade agreement on agriculture and energy will top the agenda.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Jean-Daniel Gerber, State Secretary for Economics, will be one of the members of the Swiss delegation.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;This visit also provides an opportunity to meet the prime minister of the country that currently holds the presidency of the European Union. It is customary for a member of the Federal Council to meet a member of the government of the country holding the EU presidency. In the first half of this year, President of the Confederation Pascal Couchepin met his Slovenian counterpart President Danilo Turk.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Jean-Marc Crevoisier, Head of Communication, FDHA, +41 79 763 84 10</contact>
      <attachment id="48038">
        <title>Media program</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>28</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/13762.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <link id="48037">
        <title>More informations</title>
        <uri>http://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home/dfa/head/event/2008/france.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="8">
        <name lang="de">Bildung und Forschung</name>
        <name lang="fr">Formation et recherche</name>
        <name lang="it">Formazione e ricerca</name>
        <name lang="en">Education and Research</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="10">
        <name lang="de">Bundesrat</name>
        <name lang="fr">Conseil fédéral</name>
        <name lang="it">Consiglio federale</name>
        <name lang="en">Federal Council</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="33">
        <name lang="de">Bundespräsident/-in</name>
        <name lang="fr">Président/e de la Confédération</name>
        <name lang="it">Presidente della Confederazione</name>
        <name lang="en">President of the Swiss Confederation</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="34">
        <name lang="de">Europa</name>
        <name lang="fr">Europe</name>
        <name lang="it">Europa</name>
        <name lang="en">Europe</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
