<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="55624" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2014-12-10</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="201" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>201</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="201">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Syrienkrise : Die Schweiz stellt zusätzliche 4 Millionen Franken für das UNO Welternährungsprogramm frei</title>
      <lead>Die Schweiz engagiert sich weiterhin für die Opfer der Syrienkrise. Die Humanitäre Hilfe des Bundes unterstützt das UNO Welternährungsprogramm mit zusätzlichen 4 Millionen Franken. Dieser Beitrag ist Teil eines vom Bundesrat gesprochenen Zusatzkredits von 20 Millionen Franken, womit sich die Humanitäre Hilfe der Schweiz für die Opfer der Syrienkrise auf insgesamt 122 Millionen Schweizer Franken beläuft.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Angesichts der weiterhin dramatischen Umstände und den anstehenden Wintermonaten hatte der Bundesrat am 29. Oktober entschieden, den humanitären Hilfsbeitrag für die Syrien- und Irakkrisen um weitere 20 Mio. Franken zu erhöhen. Dies wurde in der Wintersession vom Parlament genehmigt. Aufgrund der Bewertung der Bedürfnisse der Opfer der Syrienkrise werden von diesen 20 Mio. Franken weitere 4 Mio. Franken an das UNO Welternährungsprogramm bereitgestellt. Damit beläuft sich die Unterstützung der Schweiz an das UNO Welternährungsprogramm im Rahmen der Syrienkrise dieses Jahr auf insgesamt 8.8 Millionen Franken. Das UNO Welternährungsprogramm ist einer der wichtigsten Partner der Schweiz bei der Unterstützung der Opfer der Syrienkrise und hatte am 1. Dezember angekündigt, seine Hilfsleistungen für 1.7 Millionen Syrische Flüchtlinge in den Nachbarländern Syriens aufgrund von fehlenden Geldern einzustellen. Dank dem zusätzlichen Beitrag der Schweiz sowie anderer Geberstaaten ist die Weiterführung der Programme nun bis in den Januar hinein gesichert. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Der Finanzierungsengpass betrifft jedoch nicht nur das UNO Welternährungsprogramm, sondern auch zahlreiche andere Hilfswerke. Die für das Jahr 2014 veranschlagten Kosten für die Hilfsleistungen im Rahmen der Syrienkrise belaufen sich auf rund 6 Milliarden Franken, sind jedoch erst zur Hälfte finanziert. Deshalb unterstützt die Schweiz im Rahmen der zusätzlichen 20 Mio Franken auch andere UNO-Hilfswerke und das IKRK. Die Schweiz hat somit seit Ausbruch der Syrienkrise im März 2011 122 Mio. Franken für Hilfsleistungen via Partner oder via eigens durchgeführte Projekte bereitgestellt. Etwas mehr als die Hälfte des Budgets (52%) wird für die Hilfe an die notbedürftige Bevölkerung in Syrien eingesetzt, der Rest (48%) für die Unterstützung der über 3.2 Mio. Flüchtlinge aus Syrien in den Nachbarländern Libanon, Jordanien, Irak und der Türkei. Die Schweiz unterstützt jedoch nicht nur finanziell, sondern auch mit Expertise, indem sie Experten des Schweizerischen Korps für Humanitäre Hilfe an UNO-Partnerorganisationen zur Verfügung stellt. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Die Schweiz wird die bedürftige Bevölkerung in und um Syrien im Jahr 2015 weiterhin unterstützen, auch via das UNO-Welternährungsprogramm. Die Zuteilung der Mittel erfolgt bedarfsbezogen und in enger Koordination mit den Partnern. Die Humanitäre Hilfe des Bundes verfolgt deshalb die Situation und die Bedürfnisse vor Ort laufend und kann Hilfswerke wie das UNO-Welternährungsprogramm bei Bedarf Anfang 2015 rasch mit weiteren Mitteln unterstützen. Angesichts der riesigen Ausmasse der Syrienkrise mit nunmehr über 15 Mio. Menschen, welche Unterstützung brauchen, setzt sich die Schweiz jedoch auch dafür ein, neben humanitärer Nothilfe mittelfristige Programme zur Stärkung der Widerstandsfähigkeit der lokalen Bevölkerung zu finanzieren. So unterstützt die Humanitäre Hilfe des Bundes beispielsweise auch die Food and Agriculture Organisation der UNO (FAO) in Syrien, um nebst der Nahrungsmittelnothilfe via das UNO-Welternährungsprogramm auch die Produktion von Nahrungsmitteln und die Einkommensgrundlagen der Bevölkerung aufrechtzuerhalten.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Kommunikation EDA Bundeshaus West CH-3003 Bern Tel. Kommunikationsservice: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Medienstelle: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <link id="131340">
        <title>Das Engagement der Schweiz in Syrien und der Region</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/deza/de/home/laender/mittlerer-osten/syrien.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Crise syrienne: la Suisse débloque un montant supplémentaire de 4 millions de francs pour le Programme alimentaire mondial de l’ONU</title>
      <lead>La Suisse continue à s’engager en faveur des victimes de la crise syrienne. L’Aide humanitaire de la Confédération soutient le Programme alimentaire mondial de l’ONU par l’octroi d’un montant supplémentaire de 4 millions de francs. Cette contribution fait partie du crédit additionnel de 20 millions de francs accordé par le Conseil fédéral, portant ainsi à 122 millions de francs le montant total de l’aide humanitaire fournie par la Suisse aux victimes de la crise syrienne.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Face à une situation toujours dramatique alors que l’hiver approche, le Conseil fédéral a décidé, le 29 octobre, d’augmenter de 20 millions de francs le montant de l’aide humanitaire apportée aux populations touchées par les crises syrienne et irakienne. L’octroi de ce montant supplémentaire a été approuvé par le Parlement à sa session d’hiver. Compte tenu de l’évaluation des besoins des victimes de la crise syrienne, une enveloppe supplémentaire de 4 millions de francs est consacrée, sur ce montant, au Programme alimentaire mondial, ce qui porte à 8,8 millions de francs l’aide fournie cette année par la Suisse à cette institution spécialisée dans le cadre de la crise syrienne. Le Programme alimentaire mondial est l’un des principaux partenaires de la Suisse en matière d’aide aux victimes de la crise syrienne. Le 1er décembre, il avait annoncé qu’il suspendrait son aide aux 1,7 million de réfugiés syriens dans les pays voisins de la Syrie faute de financement. Grâce aux fonds supplémentaires octroyés par la Suisse et d’autres pays donateurs, la poursuite des programmes est maintenant assurée jusqu’en janvier. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mais le Programme alimentaire mondial n’est pas seul à connaître des difficultés de financement, de nombreux autres organismes d’aide sont dans le même cas. Le coût estimé de l’aide fournie en 2014 dans le cadre de la crise syrienne s’élève à quelque 6 milliards de francs, dont à peine la moitié est financée pour l’instant. C’est pourquoi la Suisse utilise ce montant supplémentaire de 20 millions de francs pour soutenir également d’autres organismes d’aide de l’ONU ainsi que le CICR. Depuis le début de la crise syrienne en mars 2011, l’aide fournie par la Suisse par l’intermédiaire de partenaires ou à travers ses propres projets s’élève à 122 millions de francs. Un peu plus de la moitié de ce budget (52 %) est affectée à l’aide aux populations dans le besoin en Syrie, le reste (48 %) au soutien des plus de 3,2 millions de réfugiés syriens se trouvant dans les pays voisins, au Liban, en Jordanie, en Irak et en Turquie. Outre son concours financier, la Suisse apporte aussi son expertise en mettant des spécialistes du Corps suisse d’aide humanitaire à la disposition de partenaires onusiens. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;La Suisse continuera à venir en aide aux populations dans le besoin en Syrie et dans les pays voisins en 2015, notamment par l’intermédiaire du Programme alimentaire mondial. L’attribution des moyens se fait en fonction des besoins et en coordination étroite avec les partenaires. L’Aide humanitaire de la Confédération suit donc en permanence l’évolution de la situation et des besoins sur place et pourra si nécessaire fournir rapidement, début 2015, des moyens supplémentaires à des organismes d’aide comme le Programme alimentaire mondial. Vu l’ampleur énorme de la crise syrienne qui a plongé dans le besoin plus de 15 millions de personnes, la Suisse apporte une aide humanitaire d’urgence, mais s’emploie aussi à financer des programmes à moyen terme de renforcement de la résilience de la population locale. L’Aide humanitaire de la Confédération soutient ainsi l’Organisation des Nations Unies pour l’alimentation et l’agriculture (FAO) en Syrie, afin de maintenir la production alimentaire et d’assurer des revenus à la population, et ce parallèlement à l’aide humanitaire d’urgence fournie par l’intermédiaire du Programme alimentaire mondial.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Communication DFAE Palais fédéral ouest CH-3003 Berne Tél. Service de communication: +41 58 462 31 53 Tél. Service de presse: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <link id="131341">
        <title>Engagement de la Suisse en Syrie et dans la région</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/deza/fr/home/laender/mittlerer-osten/syrien.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Crisi in Siria: altri 4 milioni di franchi destinati al Programma alimentare mondiale delle Nazioni Unite</title>
      <lead>La Svizzera continua a sostenere le vittime della crisi in Siria. L'Aiuto umanitario della Confederazione decide di stanziare altri 4 milioni di franchi per il Programma alimentare mondiale (PAM) delle Nazioni Unite. Questo importo fa parte del credito supplementare di 20 milioni di franchi approvato dal Consiglio federale: l'aiuto umanitario della Svizzera per le vittime della crisi siriana ha così raggiunto complessivamente 122 milioni di franchi svizzeri.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Nell'ottica della drammatica situazione in Siria e dell'imminenza dell'inverno, il 29 ottobre 2014 il Consiglio federale ha deciso di incrementare di altri 20 milioni di franchi il proprio contributo umanitario per la crisi in Siria e Iraq. La decisione è stata approvata dal Parlamento durante la sessione invernale. Dopo aver analizzato le esigenze delle vittime, è stato stabilito di destinare altri 4 milioni di franchi (dei 20 approvati) al Programma alimentare mondiale delle Nazioni Unite. Nel 2014, il sostegno finanziario della Svizzera al PAM nel quadro della crisi siriana ammonta complessivamente a 8,8 milioni di franchi. Il Programma alimentare mondiale delle Nazioni Unite è uno dei partner principali della Svizzera per il sostegno alle vittime della crisi siriana e il 1° dicembre aveva annunciato che, per mancanza di fondi, intendeva interrompere il proprio aiuto a circa 1,7 milioni di profughi siriani nei Paesi limitrofi. Grazie al contributo della Svizzera e di altri Paesi donatori, è ora possibile garantire il proseguimento del programma fino a gennaio. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Le ristrettezze finanziarie non concernono solo il PAM bensì numerose altre organizzazioni umanitarie. I costi preventivati per fornire aiuto nell'ambito della crisi siriana nel 2014 ammontano a quasi sei miliardi di franchi, importo di cui finora è stata finanziata solo la metà. La Svizzera aiuta pertanto con i 20 milioni di franchi aggiuntivi anche altre agenzie dell'ONU e il CICR. Dall'inizio della crisi in Siria nel marzo del 2011, la Svizzera ha già messo a disposizione 122 milioni di franchi per prestazioni di aiuto offerte da partner o attraverso progetti propri. Poco più della metà del budget (52 %) viene impiegato per aiutare la popolazione bisognosa in Siria, mentre il rimanente 48 per cento viene impiegato per gli oltre 3,2 milioni di siriani rifugiatisi nei Paesi limitrofi (Libano, Giordania, Iraq e Turchia). Il sostegno della Svizzera non si limita all'aspetto finanziario: viene infatti promosso anche l’aiuto «tecnico», mettendo a disposizione delle agenzie dell'ONU l'esperienza dei membri del Corpo svizzero di aiuto umanitario. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;La Svizzera continuerà a offrire aiuto alla popolazione bisognosa in Siria e nelle regioni confinanti nel 2015, anche attraverso il Programma alimentare mondiale delle Nazioni Unite. L'attribuzione dei mezzi avverrà in base alle necessità e in stretta cooperazione con i partner. L'Aiuto umanitario della Confederazione segue costantemente l'evolversi della situazione e delle esigenze in loco e, all'occorrenza, può intervenire rapidamente e destinare ulteriori mezzi a organizzazioni di aiuto come il PAM. A fronte dell'allarmante entità della crisi siriana, che ha ormai colpito oltre 15 milioni di persone bisognose di aiuto, la Svizzera interviene non solo offrendo aiuto umanitario bensì anche finanziando programmi per rafforzare la capacità di resistenza della popolazione locale. L'Aiuto umanitario della Confederazione sostiene per esempio anche l'Organizzazione delle Nazioni Unite per l'alimentazione e l'agricoltura (FAO) in Siria per salvaguardare non solo gli aiuti alimentari attraverso il Programma alimentare mondiale dell'ONU, bensì anche la produzione di generi alimentari e le basi di reddito della popolazione.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Comunicazione DFAE Palazzo federale ovest CH-3003 Berna Tel. Servizio di comunicazione: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Servizio stampa: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <link id="131342">
        <title>L'impegno della Svizzera in Siria e nella regione</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/deza/it/home/laender/mittlerer-osten/syrien.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Syria crisis: Switzerland to make a further CHF 4 million available to the UN World Food Programme</title>
      <lead>Switzerland continues its commitment to the victims of the crisis in Syria. The Confederation’s Humanitarian Aid is to support the UN World Food Programme with a further CHF 4 million. This amount is part of an additional credit line of CHF 20 million pledged by the Federal Council, bringing Switzerland’s humanitarian aid to the victims of the crisis in Syria to a total of CHF 122 million.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Given the dramatic situation and the approaching winter months, the Federal Council decided on 29 October to increase the humanitarian aid contribution to the crises in Syria and Iraq by a further CHF 20 million. This was approved by Parliament during its winter session. On the basis of the assessment of the needs of the victims of the crisis in Syria, a further CHF 4 million of the CHF 20 million has been made available to the UN World Food Programme (WFP). This brings Switzerland’s support this year to the WFP in the context of the Syrian crisis to a total of CHF 8.8 million. The WFP is one of Switzerland's most important partners in its support for the victims of the Syrian crisis, and on 1 December 2014 announced that it would stop its support activities for the 1.7 million Syrian refugees in Syria’s neighbouring countries owing to a lack of funds. The additional contribution from Switzerland and other donor countries ensures the continuation of the programme into January. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This shortage of financial support however is not only affecting the WFP but other relief agencies as well. The estimated cost of the aid in 2014 in the context of the Syrian crisis is approximately CHF 6 billion – of which only half has been financed so far. For this reason, the CHF 20 million Switzerland is providing will also go to other UN relief agencies and the ICRC. Since the outbreak of the Syrian crisis in March 2011, Switzerland has provided a total of CHF 122 million for aid via partners or its own projects. A little more than half of the budget (52%) will be used for aid to the population in need in Syria; the remainder (48%) for support to the more than 3.2 million refugees from Syria in the neighbouring countries, Lebanon, Jordan, Iraq and Turkey. Switzerland is however not only providing financial support but also expertise in the form of specialists from the Swiss Humanitarian Aid Unit to UN partner organisations. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Switzerland will continue to support the vulnerable population in and around Syria in 2015, also through the WFP. The funds are allocated on the basis of needs and in close coordination with its partners. The Confederation's Humanitarian Aid is continually monitoring the situation and needs on the ground and will be able to provide further rapid aid to agencies such as the WFP at the beginning of 2015 if required. In view of the massive spread of the Syrian crisis, now with more than 15 million people in need of support, Switzerland is aiming to finance medium-term programmes to strengthen the resilience of the local population in addition to its humanitarian emergency aid. For example, the Confederation's Humanitarian Aid is also supporting the UN Food and Agriculture Organisation in Syria in order to maintain the production of food and the livelihoods of the population, in addition to the emergency food aid it provides through the WFP.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>FDFA Communication Federal Palace West Wing CH-3003 Bern, Switzerland Tel. Communication service: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Press service: +41 58 460 55 55 E-mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @SwissMFA</contact>
      <link id="131343">
        <title>Switzerland’s commitment in Syria and the Region</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/deza/en/home/laender/mittlerer-osten/syrien.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
