<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="76681" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2019-10-10</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="323" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>701</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidg. Materialprüfungs- und Forschungsanstalt</name>
      <name lang="fr">Laboratoire fédéral d'essai des matériaux et de recherche</name>
      <name lang="it">Laboratorio federale di prova dei materiali e di ricerca</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Laboratory for Materials Testing and Research</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.empa.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.empa.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.empa.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.empa.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">contact@empa.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">contact@empa.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">contact@empa.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">contact@empa.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="701">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Wirtschaft, Bildung und Forschung</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'économie, de la formation et de la recherche</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'economia, della formazione e della ricerca</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Economic Affairs, Education and Research</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Dübendorf, St. Gallen und Thun</city>
      <title>Babys im Mutterleib von Umweltöstrogenen belastet</title>
      <lead>Das frühkindliche Leben im Mutterleib ist besonders empfindlich für die Wirkung von Umweltschadstoffen. Ein Team der Empa und der Universität Wien konnte nun erstmals nachweisen, wie sich ein Schadstoff aus Lebensmitteln - das Umweltöstrogen Zearalenon - im Mutterleib verbreitet und zu bedenklichen Stoffwechselprodukten umgewandelt wird. </lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Fremdöstrogene werden über die Umwelt, insbesondere über die Nahrung, aufgenommen. Sie können als östrogenartige Substanzen den körpereigenen Hormonhaushalt tiefgreifend beeinflussen. Das weit verbreitete Lebensmittelöstrogen Zearalenon wird von Schimmelpilzen der Gattung Fusarium gebildet und gelangt vor allem über den Speiseplan mit Brot oder Müsli in unseren Körper.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;«Die Plazentaschranke bietet dem ungeborenen Kind einen gewissen Schutz gegenüber Bakterien, Viren und manchen Fremdstoffen wie zum Beispiel bestimmten Medikamenten oder vom Körper aufgenommene Umweltgifte. Doch Zearalenon wandert, wie wir nun erstmals zeigen konnten, durch die Plazenta hindurch», sagt Benedikt Warth vom Institut für Lebensmittelchemie und Toxikologie der Universität Wien.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h3&gt;Einzigartiger Mutterkuchen&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Der Weg von Zearalenon durch den Mutterleib konnte bei Analysen ermittelt werden, für die voll funktionierende Plazenten, die nach geplanten Kaiserschnitten zur Verfügung standen, genutzt wurden. «Es ist entscheidend, menschliche Plazenten zu verwenden, um aussagekräftige Resultate zum Transport und Stoffwechsel von Zearalenon zu erhalten», sagt Empa-Forscherin Tina Bürki vom Particles-Biology Interactions-Labor in St. Gallen. «Der Grund sind die Eigenschaften des menschlichen Mutterkuchens, weil Struktur, Funktion und metabolische Kapazität einzigartig und spezifisch sind."&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Die Forschenden ermittelten nicht nur die Konzentrationen von Zearalenon im Gewebe der Plazenta selbst. Sie simulierten mittels einer Nährlösung vor Eintritt und nach Austritt aus der Plazenta auch den Bereich des Stofftransports, dem der Fötus ausgesetzt ist. Gleichzeitig konnten sie die verschiedenen Stoffwechselprodukte untersuchen, die durch Enzyme in der Plazenta gebildet werden.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h3&gt;70-fach erhöhte Aktivität&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;«Sobald wir Umweltstoffe aufnehmen, werden diese im Körper über unseren Stoffwechsel in der Regel entgiftet und ausgeschieden. Es gibt aber auch Enzyme, die diese Substanzen noch stärker aktivieren», sagt Bürki. So auch in diesem Fall: Die Plazenta bildet aus Zearalenon ein neues Stoffwechselprodukt mit einer etwa 70-fach höheren Östrogenaktivität. Selbst geringe Konzentrationen könnten damit schon einen grösseren Effekt auf das Kind im Mutterleib haben als bisher angenommen. «Diese Erkenntnis sollte in künftigen Risikobewertungen berücksichtigt werden – auch wenn die Grenzwerte schon jetzt in Kindernahrung und Muttermilchersatzprodukten strenger geregelt sind als für normale Produkte und die EU die weltweit niedrigsten Grenzwerte eingeführt hat», so Benedikt Warth.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Das körpereigene Gleichgewicht der Hormone ist sehr sensibel. Man geht davon aus, dass sich eine frühe Exposition mit Fremdöstrogenen viele Jahrzehnte später auf verschiedene Erkrankungen wie Brust- oder Gebärmutterhalskrebs, aber auch auf andere Symptome wie eine verfrühte Pubertät oder Unfruchtbarkeit auswirken könnte. «Bis weitere Forschungsergebnisse vorliegen, kann man lediglich zu einer abwechslungsreichen Ernährung raten, um die Belastung mit den Giftstoffen zu reduzieren», so das Autorenteam.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mit der Analysemethode können über 50 verschiedene Fremdöstrogene in biologischen Proben simultan nachgewiesen werden. «Unsere Methode umfasst praktisch alle wichtigen Fremdstoffe, die auf das östrogene System wirken. Das beinhaltet auch zahlreiche andere Substanzen, über die aktuell viel diskutiert wird, wie Bisphenol A oder Pestizide», so Warth. Mit der neuen analytischen Methode erhoffen sich die Forschenden, künftig die Exposition und kombinatorischen Wirkungen von Umweltschadstoffen im menschlichen Körper besser untersuchen zu können.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Dr. Tina Bürki Laboratory for Particles-Biology Interactions Empa Tel. +41 58 765 7696 tina.buerki@empa.ch Assoz. Prof. Dr. Benedikt Warth Institut für Lebensmittelchemie und Toxikologie Universität Wien Tel. +43 664 60277 70806 benedikt.warth@univie.ac.at https://exposomics.univie.ac.at/ https://lmc.univie.ac.at/ Redaktion / Medienkontakte Dr. Andrea Six Kommunikation Empa Tel. +41 58 765 61 33 redaktion@empa.ch Dipl.-Geogr. Lena Yadlapalli Wissenschaftskommunikation Universität Wien Tel. +43 1 4277 52012 lena.yadlapalli@univie.ac.at https://chemie.univie.ac.at/</contact>
      <attachment id="193933">
        <title>The xenoestrogen zearalenone migrates through the placenta, as researchers have now been able to show for the first time. (Image: University of Vienna)</title>
        <format>jpg</format>
        <size-kb>2300</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/58655.jpg</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="193934">
        <title>Empa researcher Tina Bürki at the placenta lab in St.Gallen. Image: Empa</title>
        <format>jpg</format>
        <size-kb>344</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/58656.jpg</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <link id="193936">
        <title>Empa Medienmitteilung</title>
        <uri>https://www.empa.ch/web/s604/schwangerschaft</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Dübendorf, St. Gallen und Thun</city>
      <title>Bébés contaminés par des œstrogènes environnementaux</title>
      <lead>La petite enfance dans l'utérus est particulièrement sensible aux effets des polluants environnementaux. Une équipe de l'Empa et de l'Université de Vienne a pu montrer pour la première fois comment un polluant provenant d'aliments contaminés, la zéaralénone environnementale, se répand dans l'utérus et se transforme en métabolites nocifs. </lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Les œstrogènes étrangers sont absorbés par l'environnement, en particulier par les aliments. En tant que substances oestrogéniques, elles peuvent avoir un effet profond sur l'équilibre hormonal de l'organisme. La zéaralénone, l'oestrogène alimentaire très répandu, est formée par les moisissures du genre Fusarium et pénètre dans notre corps principalement par notre alimentation, par des aliments comme le pain ou le muesli.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"La barrière placentaire offre à l'enfant à naître une certaine protection contre les bactéries, les virus et certaines substances étrangères telles que certains médicaments ou toxines environnementales absorbés par l'organisme. Mais la zéaralénone migre à travers le placenta, comme nous avons pu le montrer pour la première fois ", explique Benedikt Warth de l'Institut de chimie et de toxicologie alimentaire de l'Université de Vienne.&lt;/p&gt; Placenta particulier&lt;p&gt;Le cheminement de la zéaralénone dans l'utérus a pu être déterminé dans des analyses utilisant des placentas entièrement fonctionnels disponibles après des césariennes programmées. "Il est essentiel d'utiliser des placentas humains pour obtenir des résultats significatifs sur le transport et le métabolisme de la zéaralénone", explique Tina Bürki, chercheuse à l'Empa au Laboratoire d'interactions particules-biologie de St-Gall. "La raison en est les caractéristiques du placenta humain, car la structure, la fonction et la capacité métabolique sont uniques et spécifiques.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Les chercheurs n'ont pas seulement déterminé les concentrations de zéaralénone dans les tissus du placenta lui-même. À l'aide d'une solution nutritive avant et après l'entrée du placenta, ils ont également simulé la zone de transport de masse à laquelle le foetus est exposé. En même temps, ils ont pu étudier les différents produits métaboliques produits par les enzymes du placenta.&lt;/p&gt; 70 fois plus d'activité&lt;p&gt;"Dès que nous ingérons des substances environnementales, elles sont généralement détoxifiées et excrétées dans l'organisme par notre métabolisme. Cependant, il existe également des enzymes qui activent ces substances encore plus fortement ", a déclaré M. Bürki. Dans ce cas également, le placenta forme un nouveau produit métabolique à partir de la zéaralénone avec une activité œstrogénique environ 70 fois supérieure. Même de faibles concentrations pourraient avoir un effet plus important sur l'enfant à naître qu'on ne le croyait auparavant. "Ce résultat devrait être pris en compte dans les futures évaluations des risques, même si les valeurs limites dans les aliments pour bébés et les substituts du lait maternel sont déjà plus strictement réglementées que pour les produits normaux et que l'UE a introduit les valeurs limites les plus faibles du monde", déclare Benedikt Warth.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;L'équilibre hormonal du corps est très sensible. On suppose qu'une exposition précoce à des œstrogènes étrangers pourrait avoir un effet sur diverses maladies comme le cancer du sein ou du col de l'utérus, mais aussi sur d'autres symptômes comme la puberté prématurée ou l'infertilité et cela plusieurs décennies plus tard. "Jusqu'à ce que d'autres résultats de recherche soient disponibles, on ne peut que recommander une alimentation variée afin de réduire l'exposition aux toxines", a déclaré l'équipe des auteurs.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;La méthode d'analyse permet la détection simultanée de plus de 50 œstrogènes étrangers différents dans des échantillons biologiques. "Notre méthode inclut pratiquement toutes les substances étrangères importantes qui affectent le système oestrogénique. Cela comprend également de nombreuses autres substances qui font actuellement l'objet de nombreuses discussions, comme le bisphénol A ou les pesticides ", dit Warth. Grâce à cette nouvelle méthode d'analyse, les chercheurs espèrent être en mesure de mieux étudier l'exposition et les effets combinatoires des polluants environnementaux dans le corps humain à l'avenir.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Dr. Tina Bürki Laboratory for Particles-Biology Interactions Empa Tél. +41 58 765 7696 tina.buerki@empa.ch Assoz. Prof. Dr. Benedikt Warth Institut für Lebensmittelchemie und Toxikologie Universität Wien Tél. +43 664 60277 70806 benedikt.warth@univie.ac.at https://exposomics.univie.ac.at/ https://lmc.univie.ac.at/ Rédaction / Contacts Médias Dr. Andrea Six Communication Empa Tél. +41 58 765 61 33 redaktion@empa.ch Dipl.-Geogr. Lena Yadlapalli Universität Wien Tél. +43 1 4277 52012 lena.yadlapalli@univie.ac.at https://chemie.univie.ac.at/</contact>
      <attachment id="193933">
        <title>The xenoestrogen zearalenone migrates through the placenta, as researchers have now been able to show for the first time. (Image: University of Vienna)</title>
        <format>jpg</format>
        <size-kb>2300</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/58655.jpg</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="193934">
        <title>Empa researcher Tina Bürki at the placenta lab in St.Gallen. Image: Empa</title>
        <format>jpg</format>
        <size-kb>344</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/58656.jpg</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <link id="193936">
        <title>Empa Medienmitteilung</title>
        <uri>https://www.empa.ch/web/s604/schwangerschaft</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Dübendorf, St. Gallen und Thun</city>
      <title>Babies burdened by environmental estrogens in mothers' wombs</title>
      <lead>Early childhood life in the womb is particularly sensitive to the effects of environmental pollutants. A team from Empa and the University of Vienna has now for the first time been able to show how a pollutant from contaminated food - the environmental estrogen zearalenone - spreads in the womb and is metabolized into harmful metabolites</lead>
      <text link="no">Xenoestrogens are absorbed through the environment, especially through food. As oestrogen-like substances, they can have a profound effect on the body's hormonal balance. Zearalenone, the widespread food estrogen, is formed by fungi of the Fusarium genus and enters our body mainly via our diet through bread or muesli. "The placental barrier offers the unborn child a certain protection against bacteria, viruses and some substances such as some medications or environmental toxins absorbed by the body. But zearalenone migrates through the placenta, as we have now been able to show for the first time," says Benedikt Warth from the Institute of Food Chemistry and Toxicology at the University of Vienna. The xenoestrogen zearalenone migrates through the placenta, as researchers have now been able to show for the first time. (Image: University of Vienna) Unique human placenta The path of zearalenone through the womb could be determined in analyses using fully functional placentas available after planned Caesarean sections. "It is crucial to use human placentas to obtain significant results concerning the transport and metabolism of zearalenone," says Empa researcher Tina Bürki from the Particles-Biology Interactions Laboratory in St. Gallen. "The reasons are the properties of the human placenta, because structure, function and metabolic capacity are unique and specific." The researchers not only determined the concentrations of zearalenone in the tissue of the placenta itself. Using a nutrient solution before and after entry from the placenta, they also simulated the area of mass transport to which the fetus is exposed. At the same time, they were able to investigate the various metabolic products produced by enzymes in the placenta. 70-fold increased activity "As soon as we ingest environmental substances, these are usually detoxified and excreted by our metabolism. However, there are also enzymes that activate these substances even more strongly," said Bürki. In this case, too, the placenta forms a new metabolic product from zearalenone with about 70 times higher estrogen activity. Even low concentrations could have a greater effect on the unborn child than previously assumed. " These findings should be taken into account in future risk assessments - even if the limits for baby food and breast milk substitutes are already more strictly regulated than for other products and the EU has introduced the world's lowest thresholds," says Benedikt Warth. The body's hormonal balance is highly sensitive. It is assumed that exposure early in life to foreign estrogens many decades later could have an effect on various diseases such as breast or cervical cancer, but also on other manifestations such as premature puberty or infertility. "Until further research results are available, one can only recommend a balanced diet in order to reduce the exposure to toxins," said the team of authors. The analytical method allows the simultaneous detection of more than 50 different foreign estrogens in biological samples. "Our method includes practically all important foreign substances that affect the estrogen system. This also includes numerous other substances that are currently the subject of much discussion, such as bisphenol A or pesticides," says Warth. With the new analytical method, researchers hope to be able to better investigate the exposure and combinatorial effects of environmental pollutants in the human body in the future.</text>
      <contact>Dr. Tina Bürki Laboratory for Particles-Biology Interactions Empa Phone +41 58 765 7696 tina.buerki@empa.ch Assoz. Prof. Dr. Benedikt Warth Institut für Lebensmittelchemie und Toxikologie Universität Wien Phone +43 664 60277 70806 benedikt.warth@univie.ac.at https://exposomics.univie.ac.at/ https://lmc.univie.ac.at/ Editor / Media Contacts Dr. Andrea Six Communication Empa Phone +41 58 765 61 33 redaktion@empa.ch Dipl.-Geogr. Lena Yadlapalli Universität Wien Phone +43 1 4277 52012 lena.yadlapalli@univie.ac.at https://chemie.univie.ac.at/</contact>
      <attachment id="193933">
        <title>The xenoestrogen zearalenone migrates through the placenta, as researchers have now been able to show for the first time. (Image: University of Vienna)</title>
        <format>jpg</format>
        <size-kb>2300</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/58655.jpg</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="193934">
        <title>Empa researcher Tina Bürki at the placenta lab in St.Gallen. Image: Empa</title>
        <format>jpg</format>
        <size-kb>344</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/58656.jpg</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <link id="193936">
        <title>Empa Medienmitteilung</title>
        <uri>https://www.empa.ch/web/s604/schwangerschaft</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="8">
        <name lang="de">Bildung und Forschung</name>
        <name lang="fr">Formation et recherche</name>
        <name lang="it">Formazione e ricerca</name>
        <name lang="en">Education and Research</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
