<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="54795" revoked="no">
    <version>3</version>
    <pubdate>2014-10-12</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="201" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>201</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="201">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Die Schweiz bestätigt ihr Engagement zugunsten des Besetzten Palästinensischen Gebiets</title>
      <lead>Im Rahmen der « Kairo-Konferenz für Palästina – Wiederaufbau von Gaza» bestätigte der Delegierte für humanitäre Hilfe, Manuel Bessler, heute den Beitrag der Schweiz zugunsten des Besetzten Palästinensischen Gebiets von durchschnittlich 30 Millionen Franken jährlich im Zeitraum 2014 bis 2017. Er erwähnte auch die Rolle der Schweiz als Fazilitatorin im Prozess der palästinensischen Wiedervereinigung.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Manuel Bessler war am 30. September 2014 nach Gaza gereist, um Einblicke in die humanitäre Lage vor Ort nach 51 Konflikttagen zu erhalten. Anlässlich der Konferenz von Kairo äusserte Manuel Bessler seine Sorge angesichts der wiederholten Konflikte, von denen die Region gebeutelt wird, und sprach den Familien der zahlreichen Opfer sein Beileid aus. Die Schweiz appelliert an alle involvierten Parteien, den Teufelskreis der Gewalt zu durchbrechen, damit die palästinensische und die israelische Bevölkerung in Sicherheit und Würde leben können.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Nach Auffassung der Schweiz müssen die Friedensverhandlungen gemäss klaren Vorgaben wieder aufgenommen werden, damit eine Zwei-Staaten-Lösung erzielt werden kann. Der Wiederaufbau von Gaza und die Hilfe für die Palästinenser, die in den besetzten Gebieten oder im Exil leben, müssen in einem nachhaltigen politischen Rahmen erfolgen. Die Schweiz betont, dass dazu das zwischen den Parteien geschlossene Waffenstillstandsabkommen unbedingt gefestigt und die Blockade von Gaza aufgehoben werden müssen. Die Schweiz erinnert auch daran, dass die Parteien unter allen Umständen das humanitäre Völkerrecht beachten müssen.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Im Zeitraum 2014-2017 wird die Schweiz durchschnittlich 30 Millionen Franken jährlich für die humanitäre Hilfe, die Entwicklungsprogramme sowie Projekte zur Friedensförderung im Besetzten Palästinensischen Gebiet einsetzen. Schwerpunktbereiche bei der Fortsetzung des aktuellen Programms sind die lokale Regierungsführung, die Förderung des Rechtsstaats, die Wirtschaftsentwicklung und die Unterstützung von humanitären Organisationen wie die UNRWA, das IKRK oder das Welternährungsprogramm. 2014 hat die Schweiz ausserdem als Reaktion auf die humanitären Bedürfnisse wegen des Gaza-Konflikts zusätzlich über 4 Millionen Franken gewährt.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Die Schweiz begrüsst auch das am 25. September 2014 zwischen der Fatah und der Hamas geschlossene Abkommen. Gestützt auf das Mandat der nationalen palästinensischen Konsensregierung und im Einvernehmen mit allen betroffenen Parteien begleitet die Schweiz den Prozess der palästinensischen Wiedervereinigung als Fazilitatorin. Der Einsatz einer Fazilitatorin soll kurzfristig die Lohnkrise der Bediensteten der Zivilverwaltung in Gaza entschärfen und mittelfristig auf die Konsolidierung und Reform des öffentlichen Sektors und Gaza und im ganzen Besetzten Palästinensischen Gebiet hin arbeiten. &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Kommunikation EDA Bundeshaus West CH-3003 Bern Tel. Kommunikationsservice: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Medienstelle: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <attachment id="128814">
        <title>Rede von Manuel Bessler (en)</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>87</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/36857.pdf</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </attachment>
      <link id="128810">
        <title>Naher Osten (Besetztes Palästinensisches Gebiet, Syrien, Libanon, Jordanien, Irak)</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/deza/de/home/laender/mittlerer-osten.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions>
        <revision date="2014-10-13 18:33" type="R"/>
      </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>La Suisse réaffirme son engagement en faveur du Territoire palestinien occupé</title>
      <lead>Dans le cadre de la « Conférence du Caire pour la Palestine - reconstruire Gaza », le délégué à l’Aide humanitaire Manuel Bessler a confirmé aujourd’hui l’engagement de la Suisse en faveur du Territoire palestinien occupé à raison de 30 millions de francs par an en moyenne pour la période 2014-2017. Il a également évoqué le rôle de facilitateur de la Suisse concernant le processus de réunification palestinienne.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;M. Bessler s’était rendu à Gaza le 30 septembre dernier afin de constater la situation humanitaire sur le terrain après 51 jours de conflit. Lors de la conférence du Caire, M. Bessler a fait part de sa préoccupation face aux conflits répétés qui affectent la région et a transmis ses condoléances aux familles des nombreuses victimes. La Suisse appelle toutes les parties impliquées à sortir du cercle vicieux de la violence afin de permettre aux populations palestiniennes et israéliennes de vivre en sécurité et dans la dignité.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Pour la Suisse, les négociations de paix doivent être relancées selon des paramètres clairs afin de parvenir à une solution à deux Etats. La reconstruction de Gaza et le soutien aux Palestiniens vivant dans les territoires occupés ou en exil doivent s’inscrire dans un cadre politique durable. A ce titre, la Suisse souligne que l’accord de cessez-le-feu conclu entre les parties doit impérativement être consolidé et que le blocus de Gaza doit être levé. La Suisse rappelle également que le droit international humanitaire doit être respecté par les parties en toutes circonstances.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Pour la période 2014-2017, la Suisse prévoit d’allouer en moyenne 30 millions de francs par an à l’aide humanitaire et aux programmes de développement dans le Territoire palestinien occupé, ainsi qu’à des projets de promotion de la paix. Dans la continuation de son programme actuel, les domaines d’intervention principaux seront la gouvernance locale, la promotion de l’Etat de droit, le développement économique, ainsi que le soutien aux organisations humanitaires telles que l’UNRWA, le CICR ou le programme alimentaire mondial. En 2014, la Suisse a également alloué plus de 4 millions de francs supplémentaires en réponse aux besoins humanitaires crées par le conflit à Gaza.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;La Suisse salue par ailleurs la conclusion, le 25 septembre dernier, d’un accord entre le Fatah et Hamas. La Suisse accompagne le processus de réunification palestinienne en tant que facilitatrice sur la base d'un mandat du Gouvernement National de Consensus palestinien et en concertation avec toutes les parties concernées. Cette facilitation vise à court terme à désamorcer la crise des salaires des employés civils à Gaza et sur le moyen et long terme à œuvrer à la consolidation et à la réforme du secteur public à Gaza et dans l’ensemble du Territoire palestinien occupé.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Communication DFAE Palais fédéral ouest CH-3003 Berne Tél. Service de communication: +41 58 462 31 53 Tél. Service de presse: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <attachment id="128815">
        <title>Discours de Manuel Bessler (en)</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>87</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/36858.pdf</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </attachment>
      <link id="128811">
        <title>Proche Orient (Territoire palestinien occupé, Syrie, Liban, Jordanie, Irak)</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/deza/fr/home/laender/mittlerer-osten.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions>
        <revision date="2014-10-13 18:33" type="I"/>
      </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>La Svizzera riafferma il proprio impegno a favore dei Territori palestinesi occupati</title>
      <lead>Nel quadro della «Conferenza del Cairo per la Palestina : ricostruire Gaza », il delegato all’Aiuto umanitario Manuel Bessler ha confermato oggi l’impegno della Svizzera a favore dei Territori palestinesi occupati con uno stanziamento di 30 milioni di franchi in media per il periodo 2014-2017. Ha inoltre menzionato il ruolo di facilitatore della Svizzera nel processo di riunificazione palestinese.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Bessler si è recato a Gaza lo scorso 30 settembre per verificare la situazione umanitaria sul campo dopo 51 giorni di conflitto. In occasione della conferenza del Cairo, ha espresso preoccupazione per i ripetuti conflitti che interessano la regione e ha trasmesso le proprie condoglianze alle famiglie delle numerose vittime. La Svizzera invita tutte le parti in causa a uscire da questo circolo vizioso per consentire alle popolazioni palestinesi e israeliane di vivere in sicurezza e con dignità.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Secondo la Svizzera, i negoziati di pace devono essere rilanciati sulla base di parametri chiari per arrivare a una soluzione a due Stati. La ricostruzione di Gaza e il sostegno ai Palestinesi che vivono nei Territori occupati o in esilio deve iscriversi in un contesto politico stabile. A questo titolo, la Svizzera sottolinea la necessità di consolidare imperativamente l’accordo di cessate il fuoco concluso tra le parti e di togliere il blocco di Gaza, ricordando inoltre che il diritto internazionale umanitario deve essere rispettato da tutte le parti in qualsiasi circostanza.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Per il periodo 2014-2017, la Svizzera prevede di stanziare in media 30 milioni di franchi all’anno per aiuto umanitario, programmi di sviluppo dei Territori palestinesi occupati e progetti per promuovere la pace. Nell’ambito del suo programma attuale, i principali settori d’intervento saranno la governance locale, la promozione dello Stato di diritto, lo sviluppo economico e il sostegno alle organizzazioni umanitarie come l’UNRWA, il CICR o il Programma alimentare mondiale. Nel 2014, la Svizzera ha anche destinato oltre 4 milioni di franchi supplementari alle emergenze umanitarie sorte in seguito al conflitto di Gaza.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;La Svizzera saluta infine con soddisfazione la firma, lo scorso 25 settembre, di un accordo tra Fatah e Hamas. La Svizzera accompagna il processo di riunificazione palestinese sulla base di un mandato del Governo di consenso nazionale palestinese e d’intesa con tutte le parti interessate. La sua opera punta, a breve termine, a disinnescare la crisi dei salari dei dipendenti civili a Gaza e a medio e lungo termine a favorire il consolidamento e la riforma del settore pubblico a Gaza e nell’insieme dei Territori palestinesi occupati.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Comunicazione DFAE Palazzo federale ovest CH-3003 Berna Tel. Servizio di comunicazione: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Servizio stampa: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <attachment id="128816">
        <title>Allocuzione di Manuel Bessler (en)</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>87</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/36859.pdf</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </attachment>
      <link id="128812">
        <title>Vicino Oriente (Territori palestinesi occupati, Siria, Libano, Giordania, Iraq)</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/deza/it/home/laender/mittlerer-osten.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions>
        <revision date="2014-10-13 18:33" type="R"/>
      </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Switzerland reaffirms its pledge to the Occupied Palestinian Territory</title>
      <lead>At the Cairo Conference for Palestine on rebuilding the Gaza Strip the Federal Delegate for Humanitarian Aid, Manuel Bessler, today confirmed Switzerland's pledge to donate an average of 30 million francs per annum to the Occupied Palestinian Territory between 2014 and 2017. He also spoke of Switzerland's role as a facilitator in the Palestinian reunification process.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Mr Bessler travelled to Gaza on 30 September to ascertain the humanitarian situation on the ground there after 51 days of conflict. At the Cairo conference Mr Bessler voiced concerns about the repeated conflicts in the region and offered his condolences to the families of its many victims. Switzerland is calling on all the parties involved to break this vicious circle of violence so that the Palestinian and Israeli populations can live in security and dignity.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;According to Switzerland, the resumption of peace talks based on clear parameters is a prerequisite for any two-state solution. The reconstruction of Gaza and support for Palestinians living in the occupied territories or in exile must take place within a sustainable policy framework. To this end, Switzerland stressed how essential it is to consolidate the ceasefire agreement concluded between the parties and insisted that the blockade of Gaza must be lifted. Switzerland also reiterated that the parties to the conflict must comply with international humanitarian law in all circumstances.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Between 2014 and 2017, Switzerland plans to allocate an average of 30 million francs per annum to humanitarian aid and development programmes in the Occupied Palestinian Territory, as well as to peacebuilding projects. Continuing its current programme, the main areas of intervention will be local governance, promotion of the rule of law, economic development and support for humanitarian organisations like UNRWA, the ICRC or the World Food Programme. In 2014, Switzerland also allocated an additional sum of more than 4 million francs to meet humanitarian needs caused by the conflict in Gaza.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Switzerland also welcomed the conclusion on 25 September of an agreement between Fatah and Hamas. Switzerland is monitoring the process of Palestinian reunification as a facilitator based on a mandate from the Palestinian National Consensus Government (PNCG) and in consultation with all the parties concerned. The short-term aim of this facilitation is to defuse the crisis concerning civil-sector salaries in Gaza, but its medium and long-term objective is to work towards the consolidation and reform of the public sector in Gaza and throughout the entire Occupied Palestinian Territory.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>FDFA Communication Federal Palace West Wing CH-3003 Bern, Switzerland Tel. Communication service: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Press service: +41 58 460 55 55 E-mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @SwissMFA</contact>
      <attachment id="128817">
        <title>Speech by Manuel Bessler</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>87</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/36860.pdf</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </attachment>
      <link id="128813">
        <title>Near East (Occupied Palestinian Territory, Syria, Lebanon, Jordan, Iraq)</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/deza/en/home/laender/mittlerer-osten.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions>
        <revision date="2014-10-13 18:33" type="R"/>
      </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
