<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="54964" revoked="no">
    <version>2</version>
    <pubdate>2014-10-28</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="324" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>301</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Swissmedic, Schweizerisches Heilmittelinstitut</name>
      <name lang="fr">Swissmedic, Institut suisse des produits thérapeutiques</name>
      <name lang="it">Swissmedic, Istituto svizzero per gli agenti terapeutici</name>
      <name lang="en">Swiss Agency for Therapeutic Products</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.swissmedic.ch/</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.swissmedic.ch/?lang=3</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.swissmedic.ch/?lang=4</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.swissmedic.ch/?lang=2</www>
      <email lang="de"/>
      <email lang="fr"/>
      <email lang="it"/>
      <email lang="en"/>
    </originator>
    <department id="301">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement des Innern</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'intérieur</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'interno</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Home Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Swissmedic bewilligt Ebola-Impfstudie an der Universitätsklinik CHUV in Lausanne</title>
      <lead>Swissmedic hat am 27. Oktober 2014 das Gesuch für eine Studie mit einem experimentellen Ebola-Impfstoff am Centre hospitalier universitaire vaudois (CHUV) bewilligt. Die Studie wird 120 Freiwillige einschliessen. Sie wird von der Weltgesundheitsorganisation WHO massgeblich unterstützt und führt die Serie der in den USA, England und Mali begonnenen klinischen Versuche weiter.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Der Impfstoff, der auf einem gentechnisch veränderten Schimpansen-Adenovirus (Zaire Ebola Chimpanzee Adenovirus, cAd3-EBO-Z) beruht, wird im Rahmen dieser Studie primär gesunden Freiwilligen verabreicht, die als medizinisches Personal bei der Bekämpfung der Ebola-Epidemie in Westafrika zum Einsatz kommen. Geprüft werden die Sicherheit des Impfstoffs sowie seine Fähigkeit, eine Immunantwort zu produzieren.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Die Studienresultate am CHUV bilden – zusammen mit den Ergebnissen der anderen in die klinischen Versuche involvierten Zentren – die Grundlage, um die nachfolgenden Studien mit mehreren Tausend Probanden optimal zu planen und sicher durchzuführen.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Der Impfstoff besteht aus nicht vermehrungsfähigen Viren, die mit der genetischen Bauanleitung eines bestimmten Ebola-Proteins bestückt sind. Weil es sich beim eingesetzten Impfstoff um einen genetisch veränderten Organismus handelt, hat Swissmedic – wie gesetzlich vorgeschrieben – zusätzlich das Bundesamt für Gesundheit, das Bundesamt für Umwelt und die Eidgenössische Fachkommission für biologische Sicherheit konsultiert. Das Ende September 2014 eingereichte Gesuch wurde angesichts der Dimension der Ebola-Epidemie prioritär behandelt.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class="nsbtextkasten"&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Klinische Versuche dienen der systematischen Sammlung von Informationen über Arzneimittel bei ihrer Anwendung am Menschen. Klinische Versuche mit Heilmitteln dürfen in der Schweiz nur mit Bewilligung von Swissmedic und der zuständigen Ethikkommission durchgeführt werden.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Als Vollzugsbehörde prüft Swissmedic anhand der eingereichten Unterlagen, ob Qualität und Sicherheit des Produkts ausreichend sind, um eine Anwendung am Menschen zu erlauben. Die Ethikkommission prüft die ethischen Aspekte der Versuche und Aspekte des Schutzes der Studienteilnehmenden. Mit dem Versuch darf erst begonnen werden, wenn beide Behörden die Bewilligung erteilt haben.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Während der Durchführung der Versuche sind unerwünschte Nebenwirkungen und Änderungen jeweils den Ethikkommissionen und/oder Swissmedic zu melden. 2013 wurden Swissmedic 212 Gesuche zu klinischen Versuchen mit Arzneimitteln eingereicht. Davon konnten 205 bewilligt werden.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Swissmedic, Schweizerisches Heilmittelinstitut Peter Balzli, Mediensprecher +41 58 462 02 76 media@swissmedic.ch</contact>
      <link id="129258">
        <title>World Health Organization (WHO) - Statement (en)</title>
        <uri>http://www.who.int/mediacentre/news/statements/2014/swissmedic-ebola-vaccine/en/</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions>
        <revision date="2014-10-29 13:13" type="I"/>
      </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Swissmedic approuve un essai portant sur un vaccin contre Ebola au CHUV</title>
      <lead>Swissmedic a approuvé la demande relative à un essai portant sur un vaccin expérimental contre Ebola au Centre hospitalier universitaire vaudois (CHUV) le 27 octobre 2014. L’essai concernera 120 volontaires. Largement soutenu par l'Organisation mondiale de la santé (OMS), cet essai s'inscrit dans le prolongement d'une série d'essais cliniques qui ont débuté aux États-Unis, en Angleterre et au Mali.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Dans le cadre de cet essai, le vaccin, qui est basé sur un adénovirus de chimpanzé génétiquement modifié (Zaire Ebola Chimpanzee Adenovirus, cAd3-EBO-Z), sera administré dans un premier temps à des volontaires sains impliqués en tant que membres du corps médical dans la lutte contre l'épidémie de fièvre Ebola en Afrique occidentale. Cet essai permettra d'analyser la sécurité d'emploi du vaccin et de voir dans quelle mesure il déclenche une réaction immunitaire.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Avec ceux des autres centres qui prennent part aux essais cliniques, les résultats de l'essai conduit au CHUV constituent la base pour planifier de manière optimale et pour mener à bien en toute sécurité les essais ultérieurs qui incluront plusieurs milliers de sujets de recherche.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Le vaccin en question est fabriqué à partir de virus ne pouvant se multiplier, qui ont été chargés avec les instructions génétiques d’une certaine protéine du virus Ebola. Dans la mesure où le vaccin utilisé est un organisme génétiquement modifié, Swissmedic a également consulté – conformément aux dispositions légales – l'Office fédéral de la santé publique, l'Office fédéral de l’environnement, et la Commission fédérale d’experts pour la sécurité biologique. Compte tenu de l'ampleur de l'épidémie d'Ebola, la demande déposée fin septembre 2014 a été traitée en priorité.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class="nsbtextkasten"&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Les essais cliniques ont pour but de colliger de manière systématique des informations sur les médicaments utilisés chez l'être humain. En Suisse, les essais cliniques de produits thérapeutiques ne peuvent être effectués qu'après avoir été autorisés par Swissmedic et par la commission d’éthique compétente.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;En sa qualité d'autorité chargée de l'exécution, Swissmedic vérifie à l'aune des documents qui lui sont transmis si la qualité et la sécurité du produit sont suffisantes pour permettre une utilisation chez l'être humain. La commission d’éthique quant à elle analyse les aspects éthiques des essais ainsi que ceux relatifs à la protection des sujets de recherche. L'essai ne pourra débuter que lorsque les deux autorités auront donné leur feu vert.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Pendant le déroulement des essais, tout effet indésirable et toute modification doivent être annoncés aux commissions d’éthique et/ou à Swissmedic. En 2013, 212 demandes d'essais cliniques de médicaments ont été soumises à Swissmedic, et 205 ont été approuvées.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Swissmedic, Institut suisse des produits thérapeutiques Peter Balzli, porte-parole +41 58 462 02 76 media@swissmedic.ch</contact>
      <link id="129258">
        <title>World Health Organization (WHO) - Statement (en)</title>
        <uri>http://www.who.int/mediacentre/news/statements/2014/swissmedic-ebola-vaccine/en/</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions>
        <revision date="2014-10-29 13:13" type="I"/>
      </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Swissmedic approva la sperimentazione del vaccino anti-Ebola presso l'ospedale universitario CHUV</title>
      <lead>Il 27 ottobre 2014 Swissmedic ha approvato la domanda di uno studio con un vaccino sperimentale anti-Ebola presso il Centre Hospitalier Universitaire Vaudois (CHUV). Lo studio sarà condotto con 120 partecipanti volontari. È fortemente sostenuto dall'Organizzazione Mondiale della Sanità e prosegue la serie di studi clinici iniziati iniziati negli Stati Uniti, in Inghilterra e in Mali.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Nel quadro di questo studio, il vaccino basato su un adenovirus geneticamente modificato degli scimpanzé (Zaire Ebola Chimpanzee Adenovirus, cAd3-EBO-Z) sarà somministrato principalmente a volontari sani impiegati come personale medico nella lotta contro l'epidemia dell'Ebola in Africa occidentale. Saranno testate sia la sicurezza del vaccino che la sua capacità di produrre una risposta immunitaria.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I risultati dello studio presso il CHUV, insieme con i risultati degli altri centri coinvolti nelle sperimentazioni cliniche, costituiscono la base per pianificare in modo ottimale ed eseguire in modo sicuro gli studi successivi con diverse migliaia di soggetti.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Il vaccino è costituito da virus incapaci di replicazione dotati delle istruzioni genetiche per produrre una determinata proteina dell'Ebola. Poiché per il vaccino impiegato viene usato un organismo geneticamente modificato, Swissmedic – come previsto dalla legge – ha consultato l'Ufficio federale della sanità pubblica, l'Ufficio federale dell'ambiente e la Commissione federale per la sicurezza biologica. Considerate le dimensioni dell'epidemia di Ebola, la domanda inoltrata a fine settembre 2014 ha subito un trattamento prioritario.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class="nsbtextkasten"&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Le sperimentazioni cliniche sono utilizzate per la raccolta sistematica di informazioni sugli agenti terapeutici per il loro uso negli esseri umani. Le sperimentazioni cliniche con medicamenti possono essere effettuate in Svizzera solo con l'approvazione di Swissmedic e la competente Commissione di etica.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;In qualità di autorità di esecuzione, Swissmedic controlla, sulla base dei documenti presentati, se la qualità e la sicurezza del prodotto sono sufficienti per consentire un'applicazione sull'uomo. La Commissione di etica esamina gli aspetti etici delle sperimentazioni e gli aspetti della tutela dei partecipanti allo studio. Lo studio può essere avviato solo quando entrambe le autorità hanno rilasciato l'autorizzazione.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Durante l'esecuzione degli esperimenti, a Swissmedic e alla Commissione di etica vanno notificati gli effetti collaterali indesiderati ed eventuali cambiamenti. Nel 2013 a Swissmedic sono state inoltrate 212 domande di sperimentazioni cliniche con medicamenti, 205 delle quali sono state approvate.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Swissmedic, Istituto svizzero per gli agenti terapeutici Peter Balzli, portavoce +41 58 462 02 76 media@swissmedic.ch</contact>
      <link id="129258">
        <title>World Health Organization (WHO) - Statement (en)</title>
        <uri>http://www.who.int/mediacentre/news/statements/2014/swissmedic-ebola-vaccine/en/</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions>
        <revision date="2014-10-29 13:13" type="I"/>
      </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Swissmedic approves an Ebola vaccine trial at the CHUV in Lausanne</title>
      <lead>On 27 October 2014, Swissmedic approved the application for a trial with an experimental Ebola vaccine at the Lausanne University Hospital (CHUV). It will be conducted on 120 volunteer participants. The trial, which is receiving considerable support from the World Health Organization (WHO), continues the series that began in the USA, the UK and Mali.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;The vaccine, based on a genetically modified chimpanzee adenovirus (Zaire Ebola Chimpanzee Adenovirus, cAd3-EBO-Z), will initially be administered to healthy volunteers who will be deployed as medical staff in the fight against the Ebola epidemic in West Africa.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The trial will test the safety of the vaccine and its capacity to provide an immune response. The results from the CHUV trial will – together with the results of other centres involved – provide the basis for optimising the planning of subsequent trials involving several thousand participants and for conducting them safely.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The vaccine consists of viruses that cannot replicate, which are populated by the genetic blueprint of a defined Ebola protein. Since this vaccine is a genetically modified organism, Swissmedic – as required by its legal mandate – has also consulted the Federal Office of Public Health, the Federal Office for the Environment and the Swiss Expert Committee for Biosafety. The application, submitted at the end of September 2014, was handled as a priority given the dimensions of the Ebola epidemic.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class="nsbtextkasten"&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Clinical trials are used for the systematic gathering of information on medicinal products when used on humans. Clinical trials with medicinal products in Switzerland may only be carried out with the approval of Swissmedic and the competent Ethics Committee.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;As the enforcement authority, Swissmedic examines the documentation submitted with regard to whether the quality and safety of the trial product is sufficient in order to permit its use on humans. The Ethics Committee examines the ethical aspects of the trial and issues related to the safety of the trial participants. The trial may only begin when both authorities have approved it. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;During the trials, adverse reactions and amendments must always be reported to the Ethics Committees and/or to Swissmedic. In 2013, 212 applications for clinical trials with medicinal products were submitted, and 205 of them were approved.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Swissmedic, Swiss Agency for Therapeutic Products Peter Balzli, Acting spokesman +41 58 462 02 76 media@swissmedic.ch</contact>
      <link id="129258">
        <title>World Health Organization (WHO) - Statement (en)</title>
        <uri>http://www.who.int/mediacentre/news/statements/2014/swissmedic-ebola-vaccine/en/</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions>
        <revision date="2014-10-29 13:13" type="I"/>
      </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="15">
        <name lang="de">Gesundheit</name>
        <name lang="fr">Santé</name>
        <name lang="it">sanità</name>
        <name lang="en">Health</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="45">
        <name lang="de">Technologie</name>
        <name lang="fr">Technologie</name>
        <name lang="it">Tecnologia</name>
        <name lang="en">Technology</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
    <catalogueElements>
      <catalogueElement id="100">
        <name lang="de">Ebola</name>
        <name lang="fr">Ebola</name>
        <name lang="it">Ebola</name>
        <name lang="en">Ebola</name>
      </catalogueElement>
    </catalogueElements>
  </message>
</messages>
