<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="54930" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2014-10-23</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="201" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>201</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="201">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Schweiz unterstützt freie Wahlen in Tunesien</title>
      <lead>Die Schweiz engagiert sich für das Gelingen der bevorstehenden Wahlen in Tunesien. Sie ist ein wichtiger Akteur mit vielfältigen Projekten und unterstützt das UN-Entwicklungsprogramms (UNDP), welches sich im Namen der internationalen Gemeinschaft für die Wahlen einsetzt, massgeblich. Die Schweiz fördert ausserdem den Mehrparteiendialog und entsendet Wahlbeobachter.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Tunesien steht im Herbst vor wichtigen politischen Entscheidungen: Am 26. Oktober finden Parlamentswahlen statt und am 23. November Präsidentschaftswahlen. Mehr als fünf Millionen Tunesierinnen und Tunesier haben sich in die Wählerregister eingeschrieben, um zum zweiten Mal nach dem Fall des Regimes Ben Ali an die Urnen zu gehen. Die Schweiz ist ein wichtiger Partner Tunesiens und der internationalen Gemeinschaft im Vorfeld der Wahlen. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;So leistet die Schweiz über internationale Partnerorganisationen wie UNDP, das Zentrum für humanitären Dialog (CDH) und IFES, eine auf Wahlen spezialisierte internationale Organisation, finanzielle und technische Hilfe bei der Vorbereitung des Urnengangs. Sie unterstützt Zivilgesellschaft und Medien und setzt sich mit einem Mehrparteiendialog für ein positives politisches Klima im Vorfeld der Wahlen ein. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ausserdem finanziert die Schweiz Material wie zusätzliche 18‘000 Wahlurnen und unterstützt die unparteiische mediale Abdeckung der Wahlen durch regionale Radiostationen. Mehrere Schweizer Wahlbeobachterinnen und –beobachter werden an den Wahltagen im Einsatz sein. &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Kommunikation EDA Bundeshaus West CH-3003 Bern Tel. Kommunikationsservice: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Medienstelle: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>La Suisse soutient des élections libres en Tunisie</title>
      <lead>La Suisse s’engage afin de faciliter le bon déroulement des élections qui auront lieu en Tunisie. Elle est un acteur clé dans le pays, où elle mène divers projets, et apporte un soutien substantiel au Programme des Nations unies pour le développement (PNUD), qui se mobilise pour les élections au nom de la communauté internationale. La Suisse encourage en outre le dialogue multipartite et détache des observateurs électoraux sur place.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Cet automne, des décisions politiques de taille seront prises en Tunisie: les élections parlementaires auront lieu le 26 octobre, tandis que les élections présidentielles se tiendront le 23 novembre. Plus de cinq millions de Tunisiens et de Tunisiennes sont appelés aux urnes pour la deuxième fois depuis la chute du régime Ben Ali. En amont de ces élections, la Suisse constitue un partenaire important de la Tunisie et de la communauté internationale. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Par l'intermédiaire d'organisations partenaires telles que le PNUD, le Centre pour le dialogue humanitaire (CDH) et la Fondation internationale pour les systèmes électoraux (FISE), la Suisse apporte une aide financière et technique dans le cadre de la préparation des élections. Elle soutient la société civile et les médias, et se mobilise, grâce à un dialogue multipartite, pour créer un climat politique positif avant les scrutins. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Par ailleurs, la Suisse finance du matériel, notamment 18'000 urnes supplémentaires, et aide les stations de radio régionales à couvrir l’événement de manière impartiale. Enfin, plusieurs observatrices et observateurs électoraux suisses seront présents lors de ces élections. &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Communication DFAE Palais fédéral ouest CH-3003 Berne Tél. Service de communication: +41 58 462 31 53 Tél. Service de presse: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>La Svizzera sostiene le libere elezioni in Tunisia</title>
      <lead>La Svizzera si adopera per il buon esito delle imminenti elezioni in Tunisia. Partecipando con molteplici progetti, la Svizzera è un attore importante e sostiene in misura consistente il Programma di sviluppo dell’ONU (UNDP), che interviene nell’ambito delle elezioni a nome della comunità internazionale. Il nostro Paese promuove inoltre il dialogo multipartenariale e invierà osservatori elettorali.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Questo autunno la Tunisia dovrà prendere importanti decisioni politiche. Il 26 ottobre si svolgeranno le elezioni parlamentari e il 23 novembre quelle presidenziali. Più di cinque milioni di Tunisine e Tunisini sono chiamati alle urne per la seconda volta dalla caduta del regime di Ben Ali. La Svizzera è un partner importante del Paese e della comunità internazionale nelle fasi preparatorie delle elezioni. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Attraverso organizzazioni partner internazionali come l’UNDP, il Centro per il dialogo umanitario e il Fondo internazionale per i sistemi elettorali (FISE), la Svizzera fornisce aiuto finanziario e tecnico per la preparazione del voto, sostiene la società civile e i media e lavora, mediante il dialogo multipartenariale, per mantenere un clima politico positivo alla vigilia delle elezioni. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;La Svizzera finanzia inoltre l’acquisto di materiali, per esempio 18’000 urne elettorali aggiuntive, e sostiene la copertura mediatica apartitica dell’appuntamento elettorale ad opera di stazioni radio regionali. Vari osservatori elettorali svizzeri saranno presenti nei giorni delle elezioni.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Comunicazione DFAE Palazzo federale ovest CH-3003 Berna Tel. Servizio di comunicazione: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Servizio stampa: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Switzerland supports free elections in Tunisia</title>
      <lead>Switzerland is committed to ensuring the success of the upcoming elections in Tunisia. Switzerland is a major stakeholder with a wide variety of programmes in Tunisia and is providing significant assistance to the UN Development Programme (UNDP), which is supporting the elections on behalf of the international community. In addition, Switzerland is promoting dialogue between the different parties and is sending election observers.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Tunisia is to make important political decisions this autumn: Parliamentary elections will be held on 26 October and presidential elections on 23 November. More than five million Tunisians are being called to cast their votes for a second time since the fall of the Ben Ali regime. Switzerland is an important partner both for Tunisia and the international community in the run-up to these elections. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;It is providing financial and technical support for the preparation of the elections via international partner organisations such as UNDP, the Centre for Humanitarian Dialogue (CHD) and the International Foundation for Electoral Systems (IFES). It is supporting civil society and the media and is actively working to ensure a positive political climate in the run-up to the elections by organising a dialogue between the different parties. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, Switzerland is financing the procurement of material such as an additional 18,000 ballot boxes, and is supporting unbiased media coverage of the elections by regional radio stations. A number of Swiss experts will be deployed to monitor the elections. &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>FDFA Communication Federal Palace West Wing CH-3003 Bern, Switzerland Tel. Communication service: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Press service: +41 58 460 55 55 E-mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @SwissMFA</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
