<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="55025" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2014-10-31</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="201" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>201</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="201">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Schweizer Rettungskette ist fit für den Ernstfall</title>
      <lead>Rund 110 Angehörige der Rettungskette und zwölf Hunde wurden zwischen dem 28. und dem 31. Oktober 2014 im Raum Genf von einem internationalen Evaluationsteam beübt. Das Resultat: Die Rettungskette ist fit für den Ernstfall und wird von UN INSARAG (UN International Search and Rescue Advisory Group) reklassifiziert. Sie bleibt also in der Liga der weltweit professionellsten Such- und Rettungsteams. </lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Insgesamt waren rund 170 Spezialistinnen und Spezialisten der Humanitären Hilfe des Bundes, des Schweizerischen Korps für Humanitäre Hilfe (SKH), des Eidgenössischen Departements für Verteidigung, Bevölkerungsschutz und Sport (VBS) sowie der Rettungshundeorganisation REDOG im Einsatz. Das Szenario sah ein schweres Erdbeben der Stärke 6,9 im fiktiven Land Léma-Jura mit rund 4700 Todesopfern und 17‘400 Verletzten vor. Die Rettungsstaffel hatte den Auftrag, im Übungsdorf der Armee bei Epeisses Verschüttete zu orten, zu retten und die medizinische Notversorgung sicher zu stellen.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Die Rettungsstaffel arbeitete während mehrerer Tage rund um die Uhr. Geprüft wurde sie von acht internationalen INSARAG-Spezialisten. Beübt wurden alle Elemente und Phasen eines Einsatzes der Rettungskette von der Alarmierung bis zur Demobilisierung am 31. Oktober. Mit dem Diplom verfügt die Rettungskette für fünf Jahre über ein INSARAG-klassifiziertes „Heavy Such- und Rettungsteam“. Es ist dementsprechend in der Lage, während zehn Tagen auf zwei Schadensplätzen gleichzeitig Such- und Rettungsarbeiten sowie medizinische Erstversorgung zu leisten. Zudem verlangt INSARAG eine aktive Koordination mit den lokalen Behörden und anderen Rettungsteams (an dieser Übung das marokkanische).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Parallel zur Reklassifizierung der Schweizer Rettungskette wurde die neue marokkanische Rettungsstaffel als „Heavy Such- und Rettungsteam“ in Epeisses klassifiziert. Sie war in den letzten Jahren von der schweizerischen Humanitären Hilfe in Partnerschaft mit dem VBS sowie der REDOG (Schweiz. Verein für Such- und Rettungshunde) ausgebildet worden.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Kommunikation EDA Bundeshaus West CH-3003 Bern Tel. Kommunikationsservice: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Medienstelle: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <link id="129297">
        <title>Rettungskette Schweiz</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/deza/de/home/aktivitaeten_projekte/aktivitaeten/humanitaere_hilfe/einsatzmittel/rettungskette.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>La Chaîne suisse de sauvetage est prête à intervenir en cas de catastrophe</title>
      <lead>Une équipe internationale d’experts a évalué quelque 110 membres de la Chaîne suisse de sauvetage ainsi que douze chiens de recherche lors d’un exercice organisé du 28 au 31 octobre 2014 dans la région de Genève. La Chaîne de sauvetage a obtenu une nouvelle fois la certification du Groupe consultatif international de recherche et de sauvetage chapeauté par l’ONU (INSARAG), qui confirme sa capacité à intervenir en cas de catastrophe. Elle reste ainsi l’une des équipes de recherche et de sauvetage les plus professionnelles au monde. </lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Près de 170 spécialistes de l’Aide humanitaire de la Confédération, du Corps suisse d’aide humanitaire (CSA), du Département fédéral de la défense, de la protection de la population et des sports (DDPS) et de la Société suisse pour chiens de recherche et de sauvetage (REDOG) ont participé à l’opération, qui s’est déroulée selon le scénario suivant: un pays fictif, le Léma-Jura, a été frappé par un séisme de magnitude 6,9, qui a fait plus de 4’700 morts et 17’400 blessés. La patrouille de sauvetage détachée à Epeisses, un village d’exercice de l’armée, avait pour mission de rechercher des victimes, d’assurer leur sauvetage et de leur dispenser les premiers secours.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A l’œuvre 24 h sur 24 pendant plusieurs jours, l’équipe de sauvetage a été évaluée par huit experts internationaux de l’INSARAG. Tous les paramètres et étapes d’une intervention de la Chaîne de sauvetage ont été passés en revue, depuis le déclenchement de l’alerte jusqu’à la démobilisation le 31 octobre. A l’issue de cette évaluation, la Chaîne de sauvetage a obtenu la certification INSARAG « équipe de recherche et de sauvetage à l’aide d’équipement lourd » pour une nouvelle période de cinq ans. Cela signifie qu’elle est en mesure d’intervenir dans deux zones sinistrées simultanément, pendant dix jours, pour y mener des opérations de recherche et de sauvetage et dispenser les premiers secours. La certification INSARAG suppose en outre que l’équipe assure une coordination étroite avec les autorités locales et les autres équipes de sauvetage (dans le cas présent, l’équipe marocaine). &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Parallèlement à la recertification de la Chaîne suisse de sauvetage, la nouvelle patrouille de sauvetage marocaine a quant à elle reçu à Epeisses la certification « équipe de recherche et de sauvetage à l’aide d’équipement lourd ». Elle a été formée ces dernières années par l’Aide humanitaire de la Suisse, en partenariat avec le DDPS et REDOG.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Communication DFAE Palais fédéral ouest CH-3003 Berne Tél. Service de communication: +41 58 462 31 53 Tél. Service de presse: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <link id="129298">
        <title>Chaîne suisse de sauvetage</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/deza/fr/home/aktivitaeten_projekte/aktivitaeten/humanitaere_hilfe/einsatzmittel/rettungskette.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>La Catena svizzera di salvataggio è pronta ad affrontare le emergenze</title>
      <lead>Circa 110 membri della Catena di salvataggio e 12 cani sono stati messi alla prova nei dintorni di Ginevra, tra il 28 e il 31 ottobre 2014, da un gruppo di esperti internazionali. Il risultato: la Catena di salvataggio è pronta ad affrontare le emergenze ed è stata ricertificata dal Gruppo consultivo di ricerca e salvataggio dell’ONU (International Search and Rescue Advisory Group INSARAG). Continuerà così a far parte dei migliori gruppi di ricerca e salvataggio del mondo.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Le specialiste e gli specialisti dell’Aiuto umanitario della Confederazione, del Corpo svizzero di aiuto umanitario (CSA), del Dipartimento federale della difesa, della protezione della popolazione e dello sport (DDPS) e della REDOG (l’associazione che addestra cani da salvataggio) erano circa 170; lo scenario prevedeva un forte terremoto di magnitudo 6,9 in una regione fittizia (chiamata Lema-Giura) con circa 4700 morti e 17 400 feriti. La squadra di salvataggio, in azione sul terreno di addestramento dell’esercito a Epeisses, aveva il compito di localizzare, salvare e fornire le prime cure mediche alle persone rimaste sepolte.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;La squadra ha lavorato per diversi giorni senza sosta e il suo operato è stato verificato da otto specialisti internazionali dell’INSARAG. Sono stati messi alla prova tutti gli elementi e le fasi di un intervento della Catena di salvataggio, dal momento dell’allarme fino alla smobilitazione, avvenuta il 31 ottobre. Con l’ottenimento del diploma, anche per i prossimi cinque anni la Catena svizzera di salvataggio sarà classificata dall’INSARAG come "heavy search and rescue team", e farà parte dei gruppi in grado di intervenire contemporaneamente su due teatri di catastrofe per dieci giorni consecutivi, provvedendo alla ricerca e al salvataggio delle vittime e fornendo loro le prime cure mediche. L’INSARAG richiede inoltre una capacità di coordinamento attivo con le autorità locali e altri team di salvataggio (ruolo svolto in questa esercitazione da colleghi marocchini). &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Contemporaneamente all’esame di ricertificazione della Catena svizzera di salvataggio, a Epeisses anche il nuovo gruppo marocchino di ricerca e salvataggio, addestrato negli anni scorsi dall’Aiuto umanitario svizzero in collaborazione con il DDPS e la REDOG, ha ottenuto la classificazione come "heavy search and rescue team".&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Comunicazione DFAE Palazzo federale ovest CH-3003 Berna Tel. Servizio di comunicazione: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Servizio stampa: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <link id="129299">
        <title>Catena svizzera di salvataggio</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/deza/it/home/aktivitaeten_projekte/aktivitaeten/humanitaere_hilfe/einsatzmittel/rettungskette.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Swiss Rescue is equipped for any emergency</title>
      <lead>Between 28 and 31 October 2014 around 110 members of Swiss Rescue and twelve of their dogs were put through their paces by an international assessment team near Geneva. Swiss Rescue proved itself to be equipped for any emergency, requalifying as one of the world's most professional search and rescue teams in the eyes of the UN International Search and Rescue Advisory Group (INSARAG). </lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Altogether some 170 specialists from Swiss Humanitarian Aid, the Swiss Humanitarian Aid Unit, the Federal Department of Defence, Civil Protection and Sport (DDPS) and the Swiss Disaster Dog Association (REDOG) were involved. The exercise was based on a severe earthquake measuring 6.9 on the Richter scale in a fictitious country called "Léma-Jura", with around 4,700 dead and 17,400 injured. In the military training village facilities near Epeisses, the rescue team's task was to locate and rescue victims, providing initial emergency medical care.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The team worked round the clock for several days, their performance being assessed by eight international INSARAG specialists. All components and phases involved in a Swiss Rescue operation were tested, from the first alarm right up to the moment demobilisation took place on 31 October. With this diploma, Swiss Rescue remains an INSARAG-approved "heavy search and rescue team" for another five years. This means it is capable of providing search and rescue operations and initial emergency medical care in two crisis situations simultaneously for a period of ten days. INSARAG qualification also requires active coordination with local authorities and other rescue teams (in this exercise the Moroccan team). &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;At the same time as Swiss Rescue requalified, the new Moroccan search and rescue team also qualified as a "heavy search and rescue team" in Epeisses. The Moroccan team had been trained over the past few years by Swiss Humanitarian Aid in partnership with the DDPS and REDOG.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>FDFA Communication Federal Palace West Wing CH-3003 Bern, Switzerland Tel. Communication service: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Press service: +41 58 460 55 55 E-mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @SwissMFA</contact>
      <link id="129300">
        <title>Swiss Rescue</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/deza/en/home/aktivitaeten_projekte/aktivitaeten/humanitaere_hilfe/einsatzmittel/rettungskette.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
