<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="54851" revoked="no">
    <version>2</version>
    <pubdate>2014-10-15</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="201" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>201</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="201">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Offizieller Besuch des mazedonischen Präsidenten Gjorge Ivanov in Bern</title>
      <lead>Am 15. Oktober 2014 hat Bundespräsident Didier Burkhalter den mazedonischen Präsidenten Gjorge Ivanov in Bern zu einem offiziellen Besuch empfangen. Im Zentrum der Gespräche standen das Engagement der Schweiz im Rahmen ihres OSZE-Vorsitzes, die politischen Entwicklungen auf dem Westbalkan und in der Ukraine sowie die bilateralen Beziehungen.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Anlässlich ihres Treffens würdigten Bundespräsident Didier Burkhalter, Vorsteher des eidgenössischen Departements für auswärtige Angelegenheiten EDA, und der mazedonische Präsident Gjorge Ivanov die intensiven bilateralen Beziehungen zwischen den beiden Ländern, die nicht zuletzt auf einem engen Geflecht persönlicher Beziehungen beruhen. So leben in der Schweiz gegen 90‘000 Personen mit mazedonischen Wurzeln.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Im Gespräch wies Bundespräsident Burkhalter auf die langjährige Unterstützung der Schweiz für den Übergang Mazedoniens zu einem demokratischen Staat mit nachhaltiger Marktwirtschaft sowie im Rahmen der laufenden Annäherung an die EU hin. Die Schweiz unterhält seit 1994 diplomatische Beziehungen mit Mazedonien. Seit über zwei Jahrzehnten beteiligt sie sich an bilateralen Kooperationsprojekten und leistet Beiträge an regionale und internationale Programme. Seit 1996 ist Mazedonien ein Schwerpunktland der Schweizer Ostzusammenarbeit. Im Rahmen der aktuellen Kooperationsstrategie für die Jahre 2013-2016 mit einem Gesamtvolumen von 85 Mio. CHF konzentriert sich die Schweizer Unterstützung auf die Reformprozesse in den Bereichen Dezentralisierung, Wirtschaft, Wasserversorgung und Naturschutz. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ein weiteres Gesprächsthema war die politische Situation auf dem Westbalkan, wo sich die Schweiz im Rahmen ihres diesjährigen Vorsitzes der Organisation für Sicherheit und Zusammenarbeit in Europa (OSZE) prioritär für stabile Verhältnisse, Versöhnung und Zusammenarbeit einsetzt. In diesem Zusammenhang wies Bundespräsident Burkhalter auf die positiven Entwicklungen in der Region hin und betonte zugleich, dass das Engagement der bestehenden OSZE-Feldoperationen zur Gewährleistung langfristiger Stabilität nach wie vor unabdingbar sei.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Schliesslich erörterten die beiden Gesprächspartner die Entwicklung der Lage in der Ukraine seit dem Waffenstillstandsabkommen vom 5. September 2014 und würdigten dabei namentlich die wichtige Rolle der OSZE-Beobachtermission (Special Monitoring Mission, SMM). Bundespräsident Burkhalter bedankte sich bei seinem mazedonischen Amtskollegen für die Unterstützung der SMM durch Mazedonien. Gleichzeitig betonte er, dass die Mission im Hinblick auf ihre laufende Vergrösserung auf weitere personelle und materielle Unterstützung durch die beteiligten Staaten angewiesen bleibe.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Kommunikation EDA Bundeshaus West CH-3003 Bern Tel. Kommunikationsservice: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Medienstelle: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <link id="145196">
        <title>Bilaterale Beziehungen Schweiz – Mazedonien</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home/vertretungen-und-reisehinweise/mazedonien/bilatereale-beziehungenschweizmazedonien.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="145197">
        <title>DEZA – Mazedonien</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/deza/de/home/laender/mazedonien.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="145198">
        <title>Schweizer OSZE-Vorsitz 2014</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home/aktuell/dossiers/osze-vorsitz-2014.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Visite officielle du président macédonien Gjorge Ivanov à Berne</title>
      <lead>Le président de la Confédération Didier Burkhalter a reçu le président macédonien Gjorge Ivanov à Berne, le 15 octobre 2014, pour une visite officielle. Les entretiens ont essentiellement porté sur l’engagement de la Suisse dans le cadre de sa présidence de l’OSCE, sur les évolutions politiques dans les Balkans occidentaux et en Ukraine ainsi que sur les relations bilatérales.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;A l’occasion de leur rencontre, le président de la Confédération Didier Burkhalter, chef du Département fédéral des affaires étrangères (DFAE), et le président macédonien Gjorge Ivanov ont salué l’intensité des relations bilatérales entre les deux pays, qui reposent aussi sur un tissu dense de relations interpersonnelles. Par exemple, la Suisse compte sur son territoire quelque 90’000 personnes ayant des racines macédoniennes.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Au cours des entretiens, le président de la Confédération Didier Burkhalter a mentionné le soutien que la Suisse apporte de longue date à la Macédoine dans sa transition vers un Etat démocratique doté d’une économie de marché durable ainsi que dans le cadre du rapprochement en cours avec l’UE. La Suisse entretient des relations diplomatiques avec la Macédoine depuis 1994. Elle participe à des projets de coopération bilatérale et soutient des programmes régionaux et internationaux depuis plus de deux décennies. Depuis 1996, la Macédoine est un pays prioritaire de la coopération suisse avec l’Europe de l’Est. Dans le cadre de la stratégie de coopération pour les années 2013 à 2016, l’aide de la Suisse, dont le montant total s’élève à 85 millions de francs, se concentre sur les processus de réforme engagés dans les domaines de la décentralisation, de l’économie, de l’approvisionnement en eau et de la protection de la nature. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Il a également été question de la situation politique dans les Balkans occidentaux, où la Suisse œuvre en priorité en faveur de la stabilité, de la réconciliation et de la coopération, dans le cadre de sa présidence de l’Organisation pour la sécurité et la coopération en Europe (OSCE). Dans ce contexte, M. Burkhalter a relevé les évolutions positives survenues dans la région tout en soulignant que l’action menée actuellement par l’OSCE à travers ses missions de terrain reste indispensable pour assurer une stabilité durable.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Enfin, les deux interlocuteurs ont évoqué l’évolution de la situation en Ukraine depuis l’accord de cessez-le-feu conclu le 5 septembre 2014, saluant notamment le rôle essentiel de la mission d’observation de l’OSCE en Ukraine (Special Monitoring Mission, SMM). Le président de la Confédération Didier Burkhalter a remercié son homologue macédonien du soutien apporté à la SMM par la Macédoine. Il a également souligné que cette mission en pleine expansion restera tributaire du soutien en ressources humaines et matérielles des Etats participants.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Communication DFAE Palais fédéral ouest CH-3003 Berne Tél. Service de communication: +41 58 462 31 53 Tél. Service de presse: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <link id="145199">
        <title>Relations bilatérales Suisse – Macédoine</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae/representations-et-conseils-aux-voyageurs/macedoine/suisse-macedoine.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="145200">
        <title>DDC – Macédoine</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/deza/fr/home/laender/mazedonien.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="145201">
        <title>La Suisse préside l’OSCE en 2014</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/home/aktuell/dossiers/osze-vorsitz-2014.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Visita ufficiale del presidente macedone Gjorge Ivanov a Berna</title>
      <lead>Il 15 ottobre 2014 il presidente della Confederazione Didier Burkhalter ha ricevuto in visita ufficiale a Berna il presidente macedone Gjorge Ivanov. Al centro dei colloqui, l’impegno della Svizzera nell’ambito della presidenza dell’OSCE, gli sviluppi politici nei Balcani occidentali e in Ucraina e le relazioni bilaterali.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;In occasione dell’incontro, il presidente della Confederazione, Didier Burkhalter, capo del Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri DFAE, e il presidente macedone Gjorge Ivanov hanno elogiato le relazioni bilaterali intense tra i due Paesi, che poggiano anche su una fitta rete di rapporti personali. In Svizzera vivono infatti circa 90 000 persone con radici macedoni.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Nel corso dei colloqui, il presidente della Confederazione Burkhalter ha ricordato il sostegno pluriennale della Svizzera durante la transizione della Macedonia verso uno Stato democratico con un’economia di mercato sostenibile e nell’attuale fase di avvicinamento all’UE. La Svizzera intrattiene relazioni diplomatiche con la Macedonia dal 1994 e da oltre vent’anni partecipa a progetti di cooperazione bilaterale e contribuisce alla realizzazione di programmi regionali e internazionali. Dal 1996, la Macedonia è un Paese prioritario della cooperazione svizzera con l’Europa dell’Est. Nel quadro dell’attuale strategia di cooperazione per il periodo 2013-2016, che prevede finanziamenti per 85 milioni di franchi, la Svizzera concentra il suo appoggio su processi di riforma nei settori della decentralizzazione, dell’economia, dell’approvvigionamento idrico e della protezione della natura. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I due presidenti si sono soffermati anche sulla situazione politica nei Balcani occidentali. Nell’ambito della presidenza dell’Organizzazione per la sicurezza e la cooperazione in Europa (OSCE), la Svizzera si impegna a favore della stabilità, della riconciliazione e della cooperazione. In questo contesto, il presidente della Confederazione Burkhalter ha fatto riferimento agli sviluppi positivi nella regione sottolineando nel contempo l’assoluta necessità, ora come in futuro, delle attuali operazioni sul terreno condotte dall’OSCE a garanzia di una stabilità a lungo termine.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Burkhalter e il suo omologo macedone hanno infine affrontato il tema della situazione in Ucraina e della sua evoluzione, dopo l’accordo di cessate il fuoco in vigore dal 5 settembre 2014, elogiando il ruolo importante della missione di osservatori dell’OSCE (Special Monitoring Mission, SMM). Il presidente della Confederazione Burkhalter ha ringraziato il presidente Gjorge Ivanov per il sostegno dato alla SMM da parte della Macedonia, sottolineando che, in vista del suo costante ampliamento, la missione dovrà continuare a poter contare sull’appoggio, a livello di risorse umane e di materiale, degli Stati partecipanti.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Comunicazione DFAE Palazzo federale ovest CH-3003 Berna Tel. Servizio di comunicazione: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Servizio stampa: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <link id="145202">
        <title>Relazioni bilaterali Svizzera – Macedonia</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae/rappresentanze-e-consigli-di-viaggio/macedonia/svizzera-macedonia.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="145203">
        <title>DSC: Macedonia</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/deza/it/home/laender/mazedonien.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="145204">
        <title>Presidenza svizzera dell’OSCE 2014</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/home/aktuell/dossiers/osze-vorsitz-2014.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Macedonian President Gjorge Ivanov pays official visit to Bern</title>
      <lead>On 15 October 2014 the President of the Swiss Confederation, Didier Burkhalter, received Macedonian President Gjorge Ivanov in Bern for an official visit. Talks centred on Switzerland's activities within the framework of its current OSCE Chairmanship, political developments in the Western Balkans and Ukraine, and bilateral relations.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;During their meeting, President Burkhalter – who is also head of the Federal Department of Foreign Affairs – and President Ivanov paid tribute to the close bilateral relations enjoyed by their countries which exist in no small way thanks to a broad network of close personal relations. Around 90,000 people with Macedonian roots live in Switzerland today.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;During their talks Mr Burkhalter underscored the long-standing support Switzerland has given Macedonia in its transition to a democracy with a sustainable market economy and as part of its rapprochement with the EU. Switzerland established diplomatic relations with Macedonia in 1994. For more than two decades it has been running bilateral cooperation projects there and contributing to regional and international programmes. Since 1996 Macedonia has been a priority country for Swiss cooperation with Eastern Europe. As part of its current cooperation strategy for 2013–2016, worth a total of CHF 85 million, Switzerland is concentrating its support on reform processes in the areas of decentralisation, the economy, water supply and environmental protection. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Another topic for discussion was the political situation in the Western Balkans, where Switzerland, within the framework of its current chairmanship of the Organisation for Security and Cooperation in Europe (OSCE), advocates stable relations, reconciliation and cooperation as priorities. In this regard, Mr Burkhalter drew attention to positive developments in the region, emphasising that a commitment to the existing OSCE field operations to ensure long-term stability remained as crucial as ever.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Finally the two men discussed the evolution of the situation in Ukraine since the ceasefire agreement of 5 September 2014, acknowledging the important role played by the OSCE's Special Monitoring Mission (SMM). Mr Burkhalter thanked his Macedonian counterpart for the support his country had given to the SMM, stressing that the mission was constantly growing and hence relied on further support from the participating States in terms of personnel and material resources.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>FDFA Communication Federal Palace West Wing CH-3003 Bern, Switzerland Tel. Communication service: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Press service: +41 58 460 55 55 E-mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @SwissMFA</contact>
      <link id="145205">
        <title>Bilateral relations between Switzerland and Macedonia</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/fdfa/representations-and-travel-advice/macedonia/switzerland-macedonia.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="145206">
        <title>SDC – Macedonia</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/deza/en/home/laender/mazedonien.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="145207">
        <title>Swiss OSCE Chairmanship in 2014</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home/aktuell/dossiers/osze-vorsitz-2014.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
