<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="46213" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2012-10-04</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="201" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>201</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="601" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>601</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Finanzdepartement</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des finances</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale delle finanze</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Finance</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.efd.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.dff.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.efd.admin.ch/efd/it/home.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.efd.admin.ch/efd/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="201">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <department id="601">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Finanzdepartement</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des finances</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale delle finanze</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Finance</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.efd.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.dff.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.efd.admin.ch/efd/it/home.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.efd.admin.ch/efd/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Staatsbesuch des polnischen Präsidenten</title>
      <lead>Der Bundesrat hat am 4. Oktober 2012 den polnischen Staatspräsidenten Bronislaw Komorowski und seine Ehefrau zu einem Staatsbesuch in der Schweiz empfangen. Nach den militärischen Ehren auf dem Bundesplatz und den Ansprachen in der Wandelhalle des Parlaments folgten offizielle Gespräche zwischen der Schweizer Delegation unter der Leitung von Bundespräsidentin Eveline Widmer-Schlumpf und der polnischen Delegation. Am zweiten Tag des Staatsbesuchs steht ein Ausflug in die Kantone Freiburg und Waadt auf dem Programm.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Zwischen der Schweiz und Polen bestehen seit Jahrhunderten enge Verbindungen, die auf gegenseitiger Freundschaft und Sympathie beruhen. In den letzten Jahren haben die beiden Länder ihre Beziehungen erheblich ausgebaut und vertieft. So haben zahlreiche hochrangige Treffen stattgefunden. Als aufstrebender Mitgliedstaat in der Europäischen Union ist Polen ein zunehmend wichtiger wirtschaftlicher und politischer Partner für die Schweiz. Ebenso ist das Land ein bedeutender Partner der Schweiz in der IWF/Weltbank-Stimmrechtsgruppe. Vom Beitrag, den die Schweiz zur Verminderung der wirtschaftlichen und sozialen Ungleichheiten in der erweiterten EU leistet, geht der Hauptanteil an Polen&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Im Anschluss an die Ansprachen der beiden Staatsoberhäupter führten die schweizerische und die polnische Delegation bilaterale Gespräche unter der Leitung von Bundespräsidentin Eveline Widmer-Schlumpf und des polnischen Staatspräsidenten Bronislaw Komorowski. Daran nahmen auch die Bundesräte Ueli Maurer, Vorsteher des Eidgenössischen Departements für Verteidigung, Bevölkerungsschutz und Sport (VBS), Didier Burkhalter, Vorsteher des Eidgenössischen Departements für auswärtige Angelegenheiten (EDA), und Johann Schneider-Ammann, Vorsteher des Eidgenössischen Volkwirtschaftsdepartements (EVD), teil. Im Zentrum der Gespräche stand nebst den bilateralen Beziehungen die Europapolitik der Schweiz. Ferner wurde die Zusammenarbeit in internationalen Organisationen wie der UNO und der Organisation für Sicherheit und Zusammenarbeit in Europa (OSZE) angesprochen, deren Vorsitz die Schweiz im Jahr 2014 innehaben wird. Die Schweiz kündigte zudem ihre Unterstützung des „European Endowment for Democracy“ an, einer von Polen lancierten Initiative zur Demokratieförderung.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In ihren Gesprächen befassten sich die beiden Delegationen auch mit der Zusammenarbeit im wirtschaftlichen Bereich. Zuvor hatten die beiden Staatsoberhäupter am Vormittag des 4. Oktober gemeinsam das polnische Investitionsforum in Zürich-Kloten eröffnet. In den letzten Jahren hat der Handel zwischen der Schweiz und Polen stetig zugenommen. 2011 beliefen sich die Exporte von der Schweiz nach Polen auf rund 2 Mrd. CHF, während die Importe knapp 1.4 Mrd. CHF erreichten. Die Schweizer Botschaft in Warschau beherbergt seit 2003 einen Swiss Business Hub, der kleine und mittlere Unternehmen bezüglich Export, Kontaktvermittlung und Markterschliessung berät und unterstützt.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Zum Abschluss des ersten Tages des Staatsbesuchs findet auf Einladung des Bundesrats ein Galadiner statt. Am Freitag laden Bundespräsidentin Widmer-Schlumpf und ihr Ehemann Christoph Widmer den polnischen Präsidenten und seine Frau Anna Komorowska zu einem Ausflug in die Kantone Freiburg und Waadt ein. In Broc (FR) besuchen die Staatsgäste das „Chocolate Centre of Excellence“ und begeben sich anschliessend ins Städtchen Greyerz, wo die Gäste von einer Delegation der Freiburger Kantonsregierung willkommen geheissen werden. Das Mittagessen nehmen die Delegationen gemeinsam auf einem Dampfschiff auf dem Genfersee ein und besichtigen zum Abschluss des Staatsbesuchs das Paderewski Museum in Morges (VD). &lt;/p&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Weitere Informationen&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/b&gt;Vizekanzler André Simonazzi, Bundesratssprecher, Tel. +41 79 597 64 49 &lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Kommunikation EDA Bundeshaus West CH-3003 Bern Tel. Kommunikationsservice: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Medienstelle: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <link id="102158">
        <title>Staatsbesuch des polnischen Präsidenten</title>
        <uri>http://www.eda.admin.ch/polen</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Visite d’Etat du président polonais</title>
      <lead>Le 4 octobre, le Conseil fédéral a accueilli en Suisse le président de la Pologne Bronislaw Komorowski et son épouse pour une visite d’Etat. A l’issue des honneurs militaires sur la Place fédérale et des allocutions dans la salle des pas perdus du Parlement, des discussions officielles entre la délégation polonaise et la délégation suisse ont eu lieu sous l’égide de la présidente de la Confédération, Eveline Widmer-Schlumpf. Le programme de la deuxième journée de la visite d’Etat prévoit une excursion dans les cantons de Fribourg et de Vaud. </lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;La Suisse et la Pologne sont unies depuis plusieurs siècles par des liens étroits fondés sur une amitié et une sympathie réciproque. Ces dernières années, les deux pays ont considérablement intensifié et approfondi leurs relations ; de nombreuses rencontres de haut niveau ont ainsi eu lieu. Pays en plein développement au sein de l’Union européenne (UE), la Pologne est un partenaire commercial et politique d’une importance croissante pour la Suisse. En outre, elle est un partenaire majeur dans le groupe de vote au FMI et à la Banque mondiale. Par ailleurs, la contribution de la Suisse visant à réduire les disparités économiques et sociales dans l’UE élargie est versée en grande partie à la Pologne.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A l’issue des allocutions des deux chefs d’Etats, la délégation polonaise et la délégation suisse ont mené des discussions bilatérales sous la direction de la présidente de la Confédération Eveline Widmer-Schlumpf et du président polonais Bronisław Komorowski, auxquelles ont également participé les conseillers fédéraux Ueli Maurer, chef du Département fédéral de la défense, de la protection de la population et des sports (DDPS), Didier Burkhalter, chef du Département fédéral des affaires étrangères (DFAE) ainsi que Johann Schneider-Ammann, chef du Département fédéral de l’Economie (DFE). Outre les relations bilatérales, les échanges ont porté principalement sur la politique européenne de la Suisse. La coopération au sein d’organisations internationales telles que l’ONU et l’Organisation pour la sécurité et la coopération en Europe (OSCE), dont la Suisse assurera la présidence en 2014, a également été évoquée. Par ailleurs, la Suisse a annoncé son soutien au Fonds européen pour la démocratie (Europejski Fundusz na rzecz Demokracji), une initiative de promotion de la démocratie lancée par la Pologne.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Les deux délégations se sont également penchées sur la coopération économique entre les deux pays. Dans la matinée du 4 octobre, les deux chefs d’Etat avaient auparavant inauguré conjointement le Forum d’investissements polonais à l’aéroport de Zurich-Kloten. Ces dernières années, le volume des échanges entre la Suisse et la Pologne a connu une croissance constante. En 2011, les exportations suisses à destination de la Pologne atteignaient environ 2 milliards de francs, contre 1,4 milliard pour les importations. Depuis 2003, l’ambassade de Suisse à Varsovie héberge un Swiss Business Hub (Pôle d’affaires suisse), qui offre ses conseils et son soutien aux PME en matière d’exportations, de contacts et d’accès au marché.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;En clôture de la première journée, le Conseil fédéral devait recevoir ses hôtes pour un dîner de gala. Vendredi, la présidente de la Confédération, la conseillère fédérale Eveline Widmer-Schlumpf et son mari Christoph Widmer ainsi que le président polonais et son épouse Anna Komorowska entreprendront une excursion dans les cantons de Fribourg et de Vaud. A Broc (FR), le couple présidentiel visitera le Centre d’excellence du chocolat, avant de se rendre dans le village de Gruyères, où il sera accueilli par une délégation du gouvernement du canton de Fribourg. Les délégations suisse et polonaise déjeuneront ensuite sur un bateau à vapeur lors d’une croisière sur le lac Léman, pour finalement terminer cette visite d’Etat au musée Paderewski à Morges (VD). &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Informations complémentaires&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;André Simonazzi, vice-chancelier, porte-parole du Conseil fédéral, tél. : +41 79 597 64 49&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Communication DFAE Palais fédéral ouest CH-3003 Berne Tél. Service de communication: +41 58 462 31 53 Tél. Service de presse: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <link id="102159">
        <title>Visite d’Etat du président polonais</title>
        <uri>http://www.dfae.admin.ch/pologne</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Visita di Stato del presidente polacco</title>
      <lead>Il 4 ottobre 2012, il Consiglio federale ha ricevuto in visita ufficiale in Svizzera il presidente polacco Bronislaw Komorowski e la sua consorte. Agli onori militari sulla Piazza federale e ai discorsi nella Sala dei passi perduti del Parlamento hanno fatto seguito colloqui ufficiali tra la delegazione svizzera, diretta dalla presidente della Confederazione Eveline Widmer-Schlumpf, e la delegazione polacca. Per il secondo giorno della visita di Stato, il programma prevede un'escursione nei Cantoni di Friburgo e di Vaud.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Tra la Svizzera e la Polonia esistono strette relazioni secolari basate su amicizie reciproche e simpatie. Negli ultimi anni i due Paesi hanno approfondito e intensificato in modo considerevole le loro relazioni, tenendo numerosi incontri di alto rango. In quanto Stato membro emergente dell'Unione europea, la Polonia è un partner economico e politico sempre più importante per la Svizzera. È inoltre un partner eminente della Svizzera nel gruppo di voto del FMI e della Banca mondiale. La parte principale del contributo della Svizzera volto a diminuire le disparità economiche e sociali nell'UE allargata va alla Polonia.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Dopo i discorsi dei due capi di Stato, la delegazione svizzera e quella polacca hanno condotto colloqui bilaterali sotto la direzione della presidente della Confederazione Eveline Widmer-Schlumpf e del presidente polacco Bronislaw Komorowski, a cui hanno partecipato anche i consiglieri federali Ueli Maurer, capo del Dipartimento federale della difesa, della protezione della popolazione e dello sport (DDPS), Didier Burkhalter, capo del Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri (DFAE), e Johann Schneider-Ammann, capo del Dipartimento federale dell'economia (DFE). Oltre alle relazioni bilaterali, al centro dei colloqui vi era la politica europea della Svizzera. Si è discusso inoltre della cooperazione nelle organizzazioni internazionali come l'ONU e l'Organizzazione per la sicurezza e la cooperazione in Europa (OSCE), di cui la Svizzera assumerà la presidenza nel 2014. La Svizzera sostiene inoltre l'«European Endowment for Democracy», un'iniziativa lanciata dalla Polonia per promuovere la democrazia.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Durante i colloqui le delegazioni si sono occupate anche della cooperazione in ambito economico. La mattina del 4 ottobre i due capi di Stato hanno aperto insieme il forum polacco per gli investimenti a Zurigo-Kloten. Negli ultimi anni il commercio tra la Svizzera e la Polonia ha continuato ad aumentare. Nel 2011 le esportazioni della Svizzera in Polonia ammontavano a circa 2 miliardi di franchi, mentre le importazioni a quasi 1,4 miliardi. L'Ambasciata di Svizzera a Varsavia ospita dal 2003 uno Swiss Business Hub che consiglia e sostiene piccole e medie imprese in materia di esportazioni, mediazione di contatti e sfruttamento dei mercati.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Alla conclusione del primo giorno della visita di Stato, avrà luogo una cena di gala su invito del Consiglio federale. Venerdì, la presidente della Confederazione Eveline Widmer-Schlumpf e il consorte Christoph Widmer inviteranno il presidente polacco e la moglie Anna Komorowska a un'escursione nei Cantoni di Friburgo e di Vaud. A Broc (FR) gli ospiti visiteranno il «Chocolate Centre of Excellence» e si recheranno in seguito nella cittadina della Gruyères, dove saranno accolti da una delegazione del Governo cantonale di Friburgo. Le delegazioni pranzeranno insieme su un battello a vapore sul lago di Ginevra e alla fine della visita di Stato visiteranno il Museo Paderewski a Morges (VD). &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Ulteriori informazioni&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;Vicecancelliere André Simonazzi, portavoce del Consiglio federale, tel. +41 79 597 64 49&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Comunicazione DFAE Palazzo federale ovest CH-3003 Berna Tel. Servizio di comunicazione: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Servizio stampa: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <link id="102160">
        <title>Visita di Stato del presidente polacco</title>
        <uri>http://www.dfae.admin.ch/polonia</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>State visit of the President of Poland</title>
      <lead>On 4 October 2012, the Federal Council received the Polish President Bronislaw Komorowski and his wife on the occasion of a state visit to Switzerland. Military honours at the Bundesplatz and speeches in the Wandelhalle in the House of Parliament were followed by official talks between the Swiss delegation headed by the President of the Confederation, Eveline Widmer-Schlumpf, and the Polish delegation. An excursion to the cantons of Fribourg and Vaud is scheduled for the second day of the state visit.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Close ties based on mutual friendship and sympathy have existed between Switzerland and Poland for centuries. In recent years, the two countries have developed and deepened their relations considerably, and have held numerous high-level meetings. As an up-and-coming member State of the European Union, Poland is an increasingly important economic and political partner for Switzerland. In addition, Poland is a key partner of Switzerland in the IMF/World Bank voting constituency. The bulk of Switzerland's contribution to the reduction of economic and social disparities in the enlarged EU goes to Poland.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;After the speeches by the two heads of state, the Swiss and Polish delegations held bilateral talks led by the President of the Swiss Confederation and the Polish President. The talks were also attended by Federal Councillors Ueli Maurer, head of the Federal Department of Defence, Civil Protection and Sport (DDPS), Didier Burkhalter, head of the Federal Department of Foreign Affairs (FDFA), and Johann Schneider-Ammann, head of the Federal Department of Economic Affairs (FDEA). Besides bilateral relations, the talks focused on Switzerland's European policy. Another topic of discussion was cooperation in international organisations such as the UN and the Organization for Security and Co-operation in Europe (OSCE), whose chairmanship-in-office will be held by Switzerland in 2014. Switzerland has also declared its support for the European Endowment for Democracy, an initiative launched by Poland to promote democracy.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The two delegations also discussed economic cooperation. Earlier that day, on the morning of 4 October, the two heads of state had jointly opened the Polish Investment Forum in Zurich-Kloten. Trade between Switzerland and Poland has increased steadily in recent years. In 2011, exports from Switzerland to Poland amounted to approximately CHF 2 billion, while imports reached nearly CHF 1.4 billion. Since 2003, the Swiss Embassy in Warsaw has housed a Swiss Business Hub that provides advice and support to small and medium-sized enterprises regarding exports, establishing contacts and market development.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The first day of the state visit will be concluded with a gala dinner hosted by the Federal Council. On Friday, President Widmer-Schlumpf and her husband Christoph Widmer will invite the Polish President and his wife Anna Komorowska to join them in an excursion to the cantons of Fribourg and Vaud. The guests of state will visit the Chocolate Centre of Excellence in Broc (FR) and then proceed to the town of Gruyères, where they will be greeted by a delegation from the Fribourg cantonal government. The delegations will have lunch together on a steamboat on Lake Geneva and will then conclude the state visit with a tour of the Paderewski Museum in Morges (VD). &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Additional information&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;Vice Chancellor André Simonazzi, Spokesperson for the Federal Council, tel. +41 79 597 64 49&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>FDFA Communication Federal Palace West Wing CH-3003 Bern, Switzerland Tel. Communication service: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Press service: +41 58 460 55 55 E-mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @SwissMFA</contact>
      <link id="102161">
        <title>State visit of the Polish President</title>
        <uri>http://www.fdfa.admin.ch/poland</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <keywords>
      <keyword id="204" org-id="601">
        <name lang="de">Verschiedenes Diverses</name>
        <name lang="fr">Autres: divers</name>
        <name lang="it">Diversi: altro</name>
        <name lang="en">Misc.</name>
      </keyword>
    </keywords>
    <topics>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
