<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="46447" revoked="no">
    <version>3</version>
    <pubdate>2012-10-24</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="201" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>201</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="201">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Einsatz von Streumunition in Syrien – Stellungnahme des EDA</title>
      <lead>Die Schweiz verurteilt den Einsatz von Streumunition durch die syrischen Regierungskräfte in aller Schärfe.</lead>
      <text link="no">Gemäss den jüngsten Berichten von Human Rights Watch (der letzte wurde am 23. Oktober 2012 veröffentlicht) setzen die syrischen Regierungskräfte seit mehreren Wochen Streumunition ein. Verschiedene Städte und Dörfer in fünf Provinzen des Landes wurden von Streubomben getroffen. Die Schweiz verurteilt in aller Schärfe den Einsatz dieser Bomben im Rahmen der syrischen Krise, da sie schwerwiegende und dauerhafte humanitäre Folgen für die Zivilbevölkerung haben. Die Schweiz appelliert an die syrischen Behörden, unverzüglich auf den Einsatz von Streumunition zu verzichten.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Die Schweiz ist äusserst besorgt über die zahlreichen Berichte über schwere Verstösse gegen das humanitäre Völkerrecht und ruft alle Konfliktparteien dazu auf, ihre Verpflichtungen vollumfänglich einzuhalten. Die Gewalt und die Verstösse müssen unbedingt eingestellt werden, und die humanitären Akteure müssen Zugang zur Zivilbevölkerung erhalten, die von den Folgen dieses anhaltenden Konflikts direkt betroffen ist.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Die Schweiz setzt sich seit mehreren Jahren für eine Beschränkung bzw. ein Verbot von Waffen mit schweren humanitären Konsequenzen ein. Unter anderem hat der Bundesrat am 17. Juli 2012 das Übereinkommen über Streumunition (Convention on Cluster Munitions, CCM) ratifiziert, das den Grundsatz eines vollständigen Verbots von Streumunition enthält.</text>
      <contact>Kommunikation EDA Bundeshaus West CH-3003 Bern Tel. Kommunikationsservice: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Medienstelle: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <revisions>
        <revision date="2012-10-25 16:44" type="R"/>
      </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Usage de bombes à sous-munitions en Syrie – Prise de position du DFAE</title>
      <lead>La Suisse condamne avec la plus grande fermeté l’usage de bombes à sous-munitions par les forces gouvernementales syriennes.</lead>
      <text link="no">Selon les derniers rapports de Human Rights Watch dont le dernier a été publié le 23 octobre 2012, les forces gouvernementales syriennes font usage depuis plusieurs semaines de bombes à sous-munitions. Plusieurs villes et villages, se trouvant dans cinq gouvernorats du pays, ont été frappés par des bombes à sous-munitions. La Suisse condamne avec la plus grande fermeté l’usage de ces bombes dans le cadre de la crise syrienne qui provoque de graves et durables conséquences humanitaires pour la population civile. La Suisse appelle les autorités syriennes à cesser immédiatement le recours à celles-ci. &lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;La Suisse est extrêmement préoccupée par les nombreuses allégations graves de violations du droit international humanitaire et appelle toutes les parties au conflit au plein respect de leurs obligations. Il est urgent que les violences et les violations cessent et que les acteurs humanitaires puissent avoir accès à la population civile qui subit de plein fouet les conséquences de ce conflit armé qui se prolonge.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;La Suisse s’engage depuis plusieurs années à restreindre ou interdire l’utilisation d’armes aux effets humanitaires graves. Dans cette optique le Conseil fédéral a ratifié le 17 juillet 2012 la Convention sur les armes à sous-munitions (Convention on Cluster Munitions, CCM). Cette Convention établit le principe d’une interdiction complète des armes à sous-munitions.</text>
      <contact>Communication DFAE Palais fédéral ouest CH-3003 Berne Tél. Service de communication: +41 58 462 31 53 Tél. Service de presse: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <revisions>
        <revision date="2012-10-25 16:44" type="R"/>
      </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Impiego delle munizioni a grappolo in Siria – Presa di posizione del DFAE</title>
      <lead>La Svizzera condanna con fermezza l'impiego di munizioni a grappolo da parte delle forze governative siriane</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;econdo gli ultimi rapporti di Human Rights Watch, di cui l'ultimo pubblicato il 23 ottobre 2012, le forze governative siriane utilizzano munizioni a grappolo da alcune settimane. Parecchi villaggi e città, situati in cinque province del Paese, sono stati colpiti da munizioni a grappolo. La Svizzera condanna con fermezza l'impiego di queste armi nell'ambito della crisi siriana, che provocano conseguenze umanitarie gravi e durature per la popolazione civile. La Svizzera lancia un appello alle autorità siriane affinché cessino immediatamente di utilizzare tali armi. &lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;La Svizzera è estremamente preoccupata per le numerose gravi asserzioni di violazioni del diritto internazionale umanitario e chiede a tutte le parti in conflitto il pieno rispetto dei loro obblighi. Le violenze e le violazioni devono assolutamente cessare e gli attori umanitari devono poter accedere alla popolazione civile direttamente toccata dalle conseguenze di questo conflitto armato che si prolunga.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;La Svizzera s'impegna da vari anni per diminuire o vietare l'impiego di armi con conseguenze umanitarie gravi. In questa ottica, il Consiglio federale ha ratificato il 17 giuglio 2012 la Convenzione sulle munizioni a grappolo (Convention on Cluster Munitions, CCM), che contiene il principio di un divieto completo delle armi a grappolo.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Comunicazione DFAE Palazzo federale ovest CH-3003 Berna Tel. Servizio di comunicazione: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Servizio stampa: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <revisions>
        <revision date="2012-10-25 16:44" type="R"/>
      </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>The use of cluster munitions in Syria - FDFA Statement</title>
      <lead>Switzerland condemns the use of cluster munitions by Syrian government forces in the strongest possible terms. </lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;According to the latest reports by Human Rights Watch, the most recent of which was published on 23 October 2012, Syrian governmental forces have been using cluster bombs against a number of towns and villages in five governorates in the country for several weeks. Switzerland condemns in the strongest possible terms the use of these weapons which are having serious and long-lasting humanitarian consequences for the civilian population in the current crisis. Switzerland calls on the Syrian authorities to stop the use of cluster munitions immediately. &lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;Switzerland is extremely concerned about the many allegations of serious violations of international humanitarian law (IHL), and appeals to all parties in the conflict to ensure full compliance with their obligations. It is a matter of urgency that acts of violence and violations of IHL cease, and that humanitarian actors can gain access to the civilian population, which is exposed to the full impact of this prolonged armed conflict.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;Switzerland has been committed to efforts to restrict or ban the use of weapons with serious humanitarian effects for several years. On 17 July 2012, the Federal Council ratified the Convention on Cluster Munitions (CCM) which establishes as a principle the complete ban on the use of cluster munitions.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>FDFA Communication Federal Palace West Wing CH-3003 Bern, Switzerland Tel. Communication service: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Press service: +41 58 460 55 55 E-mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @SwissMFA</contact>
      <revisions>
        <revision date="2012-10-25 16:44" type="R"/>
      </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
