<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="46434" revoked="no">
    <version>2</version>
    <pubdate>2012-10-24</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="1070" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>1070</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Der Bundesrat</name>
      <name lang="fr">Conseil fédéral</name>
      <name lang="it">Il Consiglio federale</name>
      <name lang="en">The Federal Council</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.admin.ch/gov/de/start.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.admin.ch/gov/fr/accueil.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.admin.ch/gov/it/pagina-iniziale.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.admin.ch/gov/en/start.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="201" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>201</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="501" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>501</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Verteidigung, Bevölkerungsschutz und Sport</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de la défense, de la protection de la population et des sports</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale della difesa, della protezione della popolazione e dello sport</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Defence, Civil Protection and Sports DDPS</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.vbs.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.vbs.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.vbs.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.vbs.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@gs-vbs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@gs-vbs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@gs-vbs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@gs-vbs.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="1070">
      <name lang="de">Der Bundesrat</name>
      <name lang="fr">Conseil fédéral</name>
      <name lang="it">Il Consiglio federale</name>
      <name lang="en">The Federal Council</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.admin.ch/gov/de/start.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.admin.ch/gov/fr/accueil.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.admin.ch/gov/it/pagina-iniziale.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.admin.ch/gov/en/start.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <department id="201">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <department id="501">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Verteidigung, Bevölkerungsschutz und Sport</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de la défense, de la protection de la population et des sports</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale della difesa, della protezione della popolazione e dello sport</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Defence, Civil Protection and Sports DDPS</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.vbs.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.vbs.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.vbs.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.vbs.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@gs-vbs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@gs-vbs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@gs-vbs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@gs-vbs.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Armeeschutz für die Schweizer Botschaft in Tripolis – Der Bundesrat will das Mandat verlängern – Botschaft an das Parlament</title>
      <lead>Der Bundesrat hat am Mittwoch, dem 24. Oktober 2012, die Botschaft zur Weiterführung des Armeeeinsatzes zum Schutz der Schweizer Botschaft in Tripolis zuhanden der eidgenössischen Räte verabschiedet. Er ist der Auffassung, dass für das Personal der diplomatischen Vertretung gegenwärtig und auch in nächster Zeit reale Risiken bestehen.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Die Bundesversammlung hatte den Antrag des Bundesrats, ein Armeedetachement mit dem Schutz der Schweizer Botschaft in Tripolis zu betrauen, mit Bundesbeschluss vom 15. März 2012 genehmigt. Das Personal für das Schutzdetachement wird vom Kommando Spezialkräfte der Armee gestellt, d.h. dem Armee-Aufklärungsdetachement 10 und dem Spezialdetachement der Militärpolizei.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Gemäss Artikel 1 Absatz 2 des Bundesbeschlusses ist der Armeeeinsatz auf sechs Monate befristet. Falls die Situation vor Ort es erfordert, kann der Bundesrat das Mandat jedoch um weitere sechs Monate verlängern, ohne dass das Parlament erneut dazu Stellung nehmen muss. Dies hat er im Juli 2012 mit der sechsmonatigen Verlängerung des Einsatzes der Spezialkräfte der Armee (August 2012 bis Januar 2013) getan. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Der Bundesrat ist aufgrund der Analyse der bisherigen Entwicklungen zur Auffassung gelangt, dass für das Personal der Botschaft in Tripolis auch in den nächsten Monaten noch reale Risiken bestehen. Er erachtet es daher für notwendig, das Mandat der Spezialkräfte der Armee weitere sechs Monate (Februar 2013 bis Juli 2013) weiterzuführen, wobei der Einsatz vom Bundesrat verlängert werden kann, falls die Situation dies erfordert. Mit seiner Botschaft an das Parlament ersucht der Bundesrat um dessen erneute Zustimmung. Sollte der Bundesrat im Verlauf der ersten sechs Monate bzw. während des darauffolgenden halben Jahres feststellen, dass der Einsatz nicht mehr nötig ist, kann er ihn jederzeit unterbrechen oder beenden. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Das bestehende Schutzdispositiv hat sich bewährt. Es wurde aufgrund der Lageentwicklung laufend angepasst. Der Einsatz der Armee für den Schutz der Botschaft stellt eine zweckmässige und wirtschaftliche Lösung dar. Es ist deshalb nicht notwendig, auf die Dienste eines privaten Sicherheitsunternehmens zurückzugreifen. Andere Staaten, die ähnlich exponiert sind wie die Schweiz, werden von eigenen Sicherheitskräften beschützt, deren Grösse in etwa jener des Schweizer Detachements entspricht. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Die Einsatzkosten gehen mit Ausnahme der Löhne (für die das VBS aufkommt) zu Lasten des EDA. Sie belaufen sich für das erste Einsatzjahr auf rund 990 000 Franken. Für die neue verlängerbare Einsatzphase ist ebenfalls mit Kosten in der Höhe von rund einer Million Franken zu rechnen, sofern die Zahl der eingesetzten Personen ungefähr gleich bleibt und keine grösseren unvorhersehbaren Ausgaben getätigt werden müssen.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Für Rückfragen: &lt;br /&gt;Jean-Marc Crevoisier&lt;br /&gt;Chef Information EDA&lt;br /&gt;Tel.: +41 79 763 84 10&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;Silvia Steidle&lt;br /&gt;Mediensprecherin VBS&lt;br /&gt;Tel.: +41 79 211 61 05&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Information EDA +41 31 322 31 53</contact>
      <attachment id="102835">
        <title>Botschaft</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>125</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/28379.pdf</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </attachment>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Protection de l’ambassade suisse à Tripoli par l’armée – Le Conseil fédéral veut prolonger le mandat – Message au Parlement</title>
      <lead>Le Conseil fédéral a approuvé le mercredi 24 octobre 2012 le Message au Parlement portant sur l’approbation de la poursuite de l’engagement de l’armée pour la protection de l’ambassade de Suisse à Tripoli. Selon le gouvernement, le personnel de la représentation diplomatique est et continuera d’être, dans un avenir proche, confronté à des risques qui justifient le maintien du dispositif spécial mis en place.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;L’Assemblée fédérale a approuvé par Arrêté fédéral du 15 mars 2012 la proposition du Conseil fédéral de mandater un détachement de l’armée pour la protection de l’ambassade suisse à Tripoli. Le personnel provient du commandement des forces spéciales de l’armée, en l’occurrence du détachement de reconnaissance de l’armée 10 et du détachement spécial de la police militaire.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Selon l’article premier, 2e alinéa, de l’arrêté, le déploiement de l’armée est limité à une période de six mois. Le Conseil fédéral est cependant autorisé à prolonger le mandat de six autres mois si la situation sur place l’exige sans que l’Assemblée fédérale doive à nouveau se prononcer. C’est ce qu’il a fait en juillet dernier en prolongeant de six mois (août 2012 – janvier 2013) l’engagement des forces spéciales de l’armée. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sur la base de l’analyse de l’évolution de la situation, le Conseil fédéral est d’avis qu’il existe toujours des risques réels auxquels le personnel de l’ambassade à Tripoli sera confronté dans les prochains mois. Il considère par conséquent qu’il est nécessaire de renouveler le mandat des forces spéciales de l’armée pour une période ultérieure de six mois (février 2013 – juillet 2013), renouvelables par le gouvernement si la situation l’exige. Par ce Message, le Conseil fédéral demande une nouvelle autorisation à l’Assemblée fédérale. Si au courant des six premiers mois ou des six mois suivants, il constate que l’engagement n’est plus nécessaire, le gouvernement pourra l’interrompre ou y mettre fin. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Le dispositif de protection actuellement en place a fait ses preuves. Il a été régulièrement adapté à l’évolution de la situation. L’engagement de l’armée pour la protection de l’ambassade représente une solution appropriée et aussi économique. Il n’y a donc pas lieu de recourir aux services d’une société de sécurité privée. D’autres pays dont le degré d’exposition est semblable à celui de la Suisse sont protégés par leurs unités de protection dont la taille est semblable à celle du détachement suisse.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Si l’on exclut le coût des salaires (à la charge du DDPS), les dépenses liées à l’engagement sont à la charge du DFAE ; pour la première année d’engagement elles correspondent à environ 990'000 francs. Pour la nouvelle période de douze mois (six mois renouvelables), le montant prévu – pour autant que le nombre de personnes engagées reste constant et qu’il n’y ait pas de dépenses imprévues importantes – devrait également correspondre à environ un million de francs.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Renseignements: &lt;br /&gt;Jean-Marc Crevoisier&lt;br /&gt;Chef Information DFAE&lt;br /&gt;Tél. : +41 79 763 84 10&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;Silvia Steidle&lt;br /&gt;Porte-parole DDPS&lt;br /&gt;Tél. : +41 79 211 61 05&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Information DFAE +41 31 322 31 53</contact>
      <attachment id="102836">
        <title>Message</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>169</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/28380.pdf</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </attachment>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Protezione dell'Ambasciata di Svizzera a Tripoli da parte dell'esercito – Il Consiglio federale vuole prolungare il mandato – Messaggio al Parlamento</title>
      <lead>Mercoledì 24 ottobre 2012, il Consiglio federale ha approvato il Messaggio al Parlamento concernente l’approvazione della proroga dell’impiego dell’esercito in servizio d’appoggio all’estero per la protezione dell’Ambasciata di Svizzera a Tripoli. Secondo il Governo, il personale della rappresentanza diplomatica è e sarà confrontato, in un prossimo futuro, con rischi che giustificano il mantenimento del contingente speciale.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;L'Assemblea federale ha approvato mediante decreto federale del 15 marzo 2012 la proposta del Consiglio federale di incaricare un distaccamento dell'esercito di proteggere l'Ambasciata di Svizzera a Tripoli. Il personale proviene dal comando delle forze speciali dell'esercito e, più precisamente, dal distaccamento d’esplorazione dell’esercito 10 e dal distaccamento speciale della polizia militare.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Secondo l'articolo 1 capoverso 2 del decreto federale, la durata dell'impiego è limitata a sei mesi. Se la situazione in loco lo esige, il Consiglio federale è autorizzato a prorogare il mandato di altri sei mesi senza che l'Assemblea federale debba di nuovo pronunciarsi al riguardo. Ed è quello che ha fatto lo scorso luglio prolungando di sei mesi (da agosto 2012 a gennaio 2013) l'impiego delle forze speciali dell'esercito. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sulla base dell'analisi dell'evoluzione della situazione, il Consiglio federale reputa che esistono ancora rischi reali con cui il personale dell'Ambasciata a Tripoli sarà confrontato nei prossimi mesi. Considera quindi necessario prolungare il mandato delle forze speciali dell'esercito per un ulteriore periodo di sei mesi (da febbraio 2013 a luglio 2013), rinnovabile se la situazione lo esige. Con il messaggio il Consiglio federale chiede una nuova autorizzazione all'Assemblea federale. Se nel corso dei primi sei mesi o dei sei mesi successivi constata che l’impiego non è più necessario, il Governo potrà interromperlo o porvi fine. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;L'attuale dispositivo di protezione ha dato ottimi risultati ed è stato regolarmente adeguato all’evoluzione della situazione. L’impegno dell’esercito per la protezione dell'Ambasciata rappresenta una soluzione appropriata ed economica che non rende necessario il ricorso a una società di sicurezza privata. Altri Paesi con un grado di esposizione simile a quello della Svizzera sono tutelati da unità di protezione proprie di dimensioni analoghe a quelle del distaccamento svizzero.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Se si esclude il costo dei salari (a carico del DDPS), le spese legate all'impiego, che per il primo anno corrispondono a circa 990 000 franchi, sono a carico del DFAE. Per il nuovo periodo di dodici mesi (rinnovabile di sei mesi), l'importo previsto dovrebbe essere nuovamente di circa un milione di franchi, a condizione che il numero delle persone impiegate resti costante e che non vi siano importanti spese impreviste.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Informazioni: &lt;br /&gt;Jean-Marc Crevoisier&lt;br /&gt;Capo Informazione DFAE&lt;br /&gt;Tel.: +41 79 763 84 10&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;Silvia Steidle&lt;br /&gt;Portavoce DDPS&lt;br /&gt;Tel.: +41 / 79.211 61 05&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Informazione DFAE +41 31 322 31 53</contact>
      <attachment id="102837">
        <title>Messaggio</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>215</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/28391.pdf</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </attachment>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Protection of the Swiss embassy in Tripoli by the army – The Federal Council wishes to prolong the mandate – Dispatch to Parliament</title>
      <lead>On Wednesday, 24 October 2012 the Federal Council approved the dispatch to Parliament on approval of the continued activity of the army to protect the Swiss embassy in Tripoli. The government believes that there are still real risks to which the staff of the diplomatic representation will be exposed in the coming months and that this justifies the prolongation of the provisions currently in place.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;In a Federal Decree of 15 March 2012, the Federal Assembly approved the proposal by the Federal Council to mandate a detachment of the Army to protect the Swiss embassy in Tripoli. The troops concerned are members of the special forces - a reconnaissance detachment from the Army 10 and a special detachment of military police.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;According to the second paragraph of the first article of the decree, the deployment of the army is limited to a six-month period. However the Federal Council is authorised to prolong the mandate without needing to request approval from the Federal Assembly by a further six months if the situation on the ground requires it. In fact it did this in July 2012 by prolonging the activity of the army's special forces from August 2012 to January 2013. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;After analysing developments of the situation, the Federal Council believes that the staff of the embassy in Tripoli is exposed to real risks and that this is likely to continue for several months. It therefore believes that it is necessary to renew the mandate of the army special forces for a further period of six months from February 2013 to July 2013, renewable by the government if the situation requires. In its dispatch, the Federal Council requests a further authorisation by the Federal Assembly. If in the course of the first six months or the following six months it finds that the activity is no longer necessary, the government can interrupt it or end it. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The system of protection currently in the place has proved effective. It is regularly adapted to take account of changes of the situation. The activity of the army to protect the embassy is an appropriate and also an economical solution, as it means that there is no need to use the services of a private security company. Other countries that are exposed to a similar degree of risk to that of Switzerland are protected by their protection units, the size of which is similar to that of the Swiss detachment.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;If the costs of salaries, which are paid by the defence ministry, are excluded, the expenditure connected with this activity will be the responsibility of the FDFA. For the first year of activity, this expenditure amounted to about CHF 990,000. For the new 12-month period (six-month periods that can be prolonged), the costs should also amount to about CHF1 million, provided that the number of people involved remains constant and there is no substantial unforeseen expenditure.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Information: &lt;br /&gt;Jean-Marc Crevoisier&lt;br /&gt;Head of FDFA Information&lt;br /&gt;Tel. : +41 79 763 84 10&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;Silvia Steidle&lt;br /&gt;DDPS spokesperson&lt;br /&gt;Tel. : +41 79 211 61 05&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Information FDFA +41 31 322 31 53</contact>
      <attachment id="102838">
        <title>Message (DE)</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>125</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/28382.pdf</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </attachment>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <keywords>
      <keyword id="505" org-id="501">
        <name lang="de">Sicherheitspolitik</name>
        <name lang="fr">Politique de sécurité</name>
        <name lang="it">Politica di sicurezza</name>
        <name lang="en">Security Policy</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="590" org-id="501">
        <name lang="de">Auslandeinsätze</name>
        <name lang="fr">Engagements à l'étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Impieghi all'estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Foreign Operations</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="5160" org-id="501">
        <name lang="de">Verteidigung</name>
        <name lang="fr">Défense</name>
        <name lang="it">Difesa</name>
        <name lang="en">defence</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="5180" org-id="501">
        <name lang="de">Armee</name>
        <name lang="fr">Armée</name>
        <name lang="it">Esercito</name>
        <name lang="en">armed forces</name>
      </keyword>
    </keywords>
    <topics>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
