<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="44079" revoked="no">
    <version>6</version>
    <pubdate>2012-04-09</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="201" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>201</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="201">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Bund entsendet Spezialisten für Lawinenunglück nach Pakistan</title>
      <lead>Stellungnahme</lead>
      <text link="no">Eine Schneelawine hatte am Samstag im Norden Pakistans in der Nähe des Siachen-Gletschers auf über 4570 Meter Höhe einen pakistanischen Militärstützpunkt unter sich begraben. 124 Soldaten und 11 Zivilisten wurden nach Angaben der pakistanischen Armee verschüttet. Auf Anfrage der pakistanischen Regierung hat der Bund am Montag drei Rettungsexperten an den Unfallort entsendet. Die Schweiz verfügt über international anerkannt hohe Expertise in der hochalpinen Bergrettung. Die Humanitäre Hilfe des Bundes koordiniert den Einsatz. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Das Schweizer Team besteht aus dem Chef Bergrettung Zermatt, einem Bergführer und Paramedic sowie einem Hundeführer mit Lawinenhund. Diese werden am Dienstag ihre Arbeit aufnehmen und die Suchanstrengungen vor Ort unterstützen können. Das Büro der Direktion für Entwicklung und Zusammenarbeit DEZA in Islamabad steht in engem Kontakt mit den pakistanischen Einsatzkräften.Sonntag und Montag wurde die Suche nach den Opfern des Lawinenunglücks mit hoher Intensität fortgesetzt. Mit schwerem Gerät gruben sich die Helfer durch die rund 25 Meter Schnee, Felsen und Schlamm, unter denen der Stützpunkt begraben wurde. Die Hoffnung, noch Überlebende zu finden, ist sehr klein. Bis jetzt konnten keine Opfer geortet werden.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Die Schweiz ist seit über 40 Jahren im Rahmen ihrer Entwicklungszusammenarbeit in Pakistan aktiv. Der Schwerpunkt ihres Engagements liegt in der Armutsbekämpfung und Unterstützung besonders benachteiligter Bevölkerungsgruppen in der Grenzregion zu Afghanistan.</text>
      <contact>Kommunikation EDA Bundeshaus West CH-3003 Bern Tel. Kommunikationsservice: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Medienstelle: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Avalanche au Pakistan : la Confédération envoie des spécialistes</title>
      <lead>Prise de position</lead>
      <text link="no">Une avalanche a déferlé le samedi 7 avril 2012 sur une base militaire pakistanaise située à 4570 mètres d’altitude près du glacier himalayen de Siachen, au nord du Pakistan. Selon les autorités pakistanaises, 124 soldats et onze civils ont été ensevelis. A la demande du gouvernement pakistanais, la Confédération a envoyé sur place lundi une équipe d’experts pour aider les secouristes. La Suisse bénéficie d’une expérience internationalement reconnue dans le domaine du secours en haute montagne. L’Aide humanitaire de la Confédération coordonne cet engagement. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;L’équipe dépêchée par la Suisse se compose du chef des sauveteurs en montagne de Zermatt, d’un guide de montagne bénéficiant d’une expérience médicale ainsi que d’un maître-chien accompagné d’un chien d’avalanche. Ces experts doivent commencer leur travail ce mardi 10 avril 2012 afin de soutenir les recherches menées par les autorités pakistanaises. Le Bureau de la Direction du développement et de la coopération (DDC) à Islamabad est en étroit contact avec les forces pakistanaises engagées sur le terrain. Les recherches en vue de porter secours aux victimes de l’avalanche se sont poursuivies avec plus d’intensité dimanche et lundi. Munis d’équipement lourd, les secouristes pakistanais doivent creuser une couche d’environ 25 mètres constituée de neige, de rochers et de boue qui recouvre la base militaire. L’espoir de retrouver des survivants est minime. Jusqu’ici, aucune victime n’a pu être localisée.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;La Suisse est présente depuis plus de 40 ans au Pakistan par l’intermédiaire de l’aide à la coopération. Le point fort de cet engagement est la lutte contre la pauvreté ainsi que le soutien en faveur des groupes de populations particulièrement vulnérables dans la région frontalière avec l’Afghanistan.</text>
      <contact>Communication DFAE Palais fédéral ouest CH-3003 Berne Tél. Service de communication: +41 58 462 31 53 Tél. Service de presse: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>La Confederazione invia alcuni esperti dopo la valanga in Pakistan</title>
      <lead>Presa di posizone</lead>
      <text link="no">Sabato scorso una valanga si è abbattuta nel nord del Pakistan, nei pressi del ghiacciaio di Siachen a oltre 4570 metri di altezza, travolgendo un campo di soldati. Secondo le stime dell'esercito pakistano, 124 militari e 11 civili sono rimasti sepolti sotto la neve. Su richiesta del Governo pakistano, la Confederazione ha inviato lunedì tre esperti di salvataggio sul luogo del disastro. La Svizzera dispone di un'esperienza internazionalmente riconosciuta nel campo delle operazioni di soccorso in alta montagna. L'intervento è coordinato dall'Aiuto umanitario della Confederazione. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;La squadra svizzera, composta dal capo del soccorso alpino di Zermatt, da una guida di montagna e paramedico e da un conducente di cani con un cane da valanga, sarà operativa a partire da martedì e contribuirà alle ricerche sul posto. L'Ufficio della Direzione dello sviluppo e della cooperazione DSC a Islamabad si mantiene in stretto contatto con le unità di intervento pakistane. Domenica e lunedì le ricerche delle vittime della valanga si sono intensificate. I soccorritori, muniti di pesanti apparecchiature, si sono fatti largo tra una coltre di circa 25 metri di neve, roccia e fango, sotto alla quale è sepolto il campo dei soldati. Le speranze di trovare in vita dei superstiti sono minime. Sinora le vittime non sono state individuate.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;La Svizzera è attiva da oltre 40 anni in Pakistan nel campo della cooperazione allo sviluppo, in particolare nella lotta alla povertà e nel sostegno alle fasce di popolazione più svantaggiate che vivono nella regione al confine con l'Afghanistan.</text>
      <contact>Comunicazione DFAE Palazzo federale ovest CH-3003 Berna Tel. Servizio di comunicazione: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Servizio stampa: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <revisions>
        <revision date="2012-04-10 16:18" type="R"/>
        <revision date="2012-04-10 16:14" type="R"/>
      </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Switzerland sends search and rescue specialists to Pakistan</title>
      <lead>Position</lead>
      <text link="no">Last Saturday, an avalanche buried a Pakistani military camp situated at an altitude of above 4570 metres near the Siachen glacier in the north of the country. According to Pakistani army sources, 124 soldiers and 11 civilians have been trapped under the avalanche. At the request of the Government of Pakistan, Switzerland sent three rescue experts to the scene of the accident on Monday. Switzerland has an international reputation for its search and rescue expertise in high mountains. The Humanitarian Aid of the Swiss Confederation is co-ordinating the mission. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The Swiss team is made up of the head of mountain rescue in Zermatt, a mountain guide and paramedic, and a dog-handler with an avalanche dog. They will begin work on Tuesday to reinforce the search efforts. The office of the Swiss Agency for Development and Cooperation (SDC) in Islamabad is in close contact with the Pakistani rescue teams.On Sunday and Monday, the search for victims of the avalanche disaster was continued with high intensity. The searchers used heavy equipment to dig through the approximately 25 metres of snow, rocks and mud under which the camp has been buried. Hope of finding survivors is very slight and so far no victims have been located.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Switzerland has been actively involved in development cooperation in Pakistan for more than 40 years. Its activities are focused on combating poverty and supporting especially disadvantaged population groups in the border region with Afghanistan.</text>
      <contact>FDFA Communication Federal Palace West Wing CH-3003 Bern, Switzerland Tel. Communication service: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Press service: +41 58 460 55 55 E-mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @SwissMFA</contact>
      <revisions>
        <revision date="2012-04-10 16:36" type="R"/>
      </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
