<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="47431" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2013-01-14</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="201" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>201</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="201">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Schweiz verlangt vom UNO-Sicherheitsrat, die schweren Verbrechen in Syrien dem Internationalen Strafgerichtshof zur Beurteilung zu überweisen</title>
      <lead>Die zahlreichen Vorwürfe wegen Verbrechen gegen die Menschlichkeit und Kriegsverbrechen in Syrien müssen untersucht und die Verantwortlichen aller Konfliktparteien vor Gericht gebracht werden. Diese Forderung hat die Schweiz, unterstützt von 56 Staaten, mit einem Brief vom 14. Januar 2013 beim UNO-Sicherheitsrat deponiert. Das beste Mittel, um Gerechtigkeit zu schaffen, wäre eine Überweisung der Situation in Syrien an den Internationalen Strafgerichtshof (ICC). Die Schweiz ist überzeugt, dass ohne konsequentes Vorgehen gegen die Straflosigkeit in Syrien kein nachhaltiger Frieden möglich ist.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Nach bald zwei Jahren blutiger Kämpfe verschärft sich die humanitäre Situation in Syrien immer weiter. Der Konflikt hat bereits rund 60‘000 Todesopfer gefordert, mehrheitlich zivile Personen. Eine politische Lösung ist weiterhin nicht in Sicht. Angesichts dieser dramatischen Lage und mangels irgendwelcher Anzeichen einer Verbesserung will die Schweiz mit diesem Brief ein Zeichen für die Einhaltung fundamentaler humanitärer Grundwerte und für Gerechtigkeit setzen. Der Appell ist sowohl ein Signal an die syrischen Opfer, dass sie nicht vergessen sind, als auch eine Warnung an die Konfliktparteien, dass sie die Gewalt einstellen und die Menschenrechte sowie das humanitäre Völkerrecht respektieren sollen. 56 Staaten haben sich diesem Aufruf an den Sicherheitsrat angeschlossen.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;Die Schweizer Initiative hat ausschliesslich humanitären Charakter und ist unparteiisch. Sie nimmt einzig Partei für die Gerechtigkeit. Die Verantwortlichen aller Konfliktparteien sollen zur Rechenschaft gezogen werden. Die Verantwortung für die Strafverfolgung liegt zwar primär bei den syrischen Behörden. Diese haben aber trotz zahlreicher internationaler Appelle keine Anstalten getroffen, die Vorwürfe wegen Verbrechen gegen die Menschlichkeit und Kriegsverbrechen in fairen und unabhängigen Gerichtsverfahren zu untersuchen. Gerechtigkeit kann folglich nur vom Internationalen Strafgerichtshof erwartet werden. Weil Syrien kein Vertragsstaat des ICC-Gründungsvertrags ist, braucht es für die Überweisung an den Strafgerichtshof einen Beschluss des Sicherheitsrats. &lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;Der Brief ist eine Petition, da der Sicherheitsrat in alleiniger Kompetenz über eine solche Überweisung entscheidet. In jedem Fall setzt der Brief aber ein starkes Signal gegen die Straflosigkeit und zeigt, dass eine bedeutende Zahl von Staaten nicht gewillt ist, Verbrechen gegen die Menschlichkeit sowie Kriegsverbrechen zu tolerieren.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;u&gt;Für Rückfragen:&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/u&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;Jean-Marc Crevoisier&lt;br /&gt;Chef Information EDA&lt;br /&gt;+41 (0)79 763 84 10&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Adrian Sollberger&lt;br /&gt;Sprecher der Schweizer UNO-Mission in New York&lt;br /&gt;+1 (917) 757 3389&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Kommunikation EDA Bundeshaus West CH-3003 Bern Tel. Kommunikationsservice: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Medienstelle: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <attachment id="105451">
        <title>Letter to the Security Council (en)</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>22</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/29290.pdf</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </attachment>
      <link id="105443">
        <title>Engagement der Schweiz in Syrien</title>
        <uri>http://www.deza.admin.ch/de/Home/Laender/Naher_und_Mittlerer_Osten/Irak_Jordanien_Syrien_Libanon</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="105444">
        <title>Internationale Justiz</title>
        <uri>http://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home/topics/intla/intjus.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>La Suisse demande au Conseil de sécurité de déférer les graves crimes perpétrés en Syrie à la Cour pénale internationale</title>
      <lead>Les nombreuses accusations de crimes contre l’humanité et de crimes de guerre en Syrie doivent faire l’objet d’une enquête et les belligérants responsables être traduits en justice. Telle est la revendication exprimée par la Suisse, soutenue par 56 Etats, dans une lettre du 14 janvier 2013 adressée au Conseil de sécurité des Nations Unies. Le meilleur moyen de faire triompher la justice est de déférer la situation syrienne à la Cour pénale internationale (CPI). La Suisse est convaincue que si rien n’est fait contre l’impunité en Syrie, aucune paix durable n’est possible.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Après bientôt deux ans de combats sanglants en Syrie, la situation humanitaire est de plus en plus alarmante. Le conflit a déjà tué plus de 60 000 personnes, principalement des civils, et aucune solution politique se profile à l’horizon. Face à cette situation dramatique et en l’absence de toute perspective d’amélioration, la Suisse entend témoigner avec cette lettre de son attachement aux valeurs humanitaires fondamentales et à la justice. La Suisse lance également un signal aux victimes syriennes, leur montrant qu’elles n’ont pas été oubliées, et somme les belligérants de cesser les hostilités et de respecter les droits de l’homme et le droit international humanitaire. 56 Etats se sont ralliés à cet appel au Conseil de sécurité.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;L’initiative suisse se veut impartiale et à caractère strictement humanitaire. Son seul objectif est de défendre la justice. Les responsables de toutes les parties belligérantes doivent être amenés à rendre des comptes. La poursuite pénale incombe en premier lieu aux autorités syriennes. Pourtant, malgré les nombreux appels de la communauté internationale, aucune mesure n’a été prise du côté syrien pour instruire les allégations de crimes contre l’humanité de manière équitable et impartiale. La justice ne saurait donc venir que de la Cour pénale internationale. La Syrie n’ayant pas signé l’acte de fondation de la Cour, le défèrement à cette autorité exige une décision du Conseil de sécurité. &lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;Cette lettre ne constitue qu’une pétition, le Conseil de sécurité étant la seule instance habilitée à statuer sur cette question. Toutefois, quelle que soit la décision du Conseil, ce document représente une prise de position forte contre l’impunité et témoigne du refus d’un grand nombre d’Etats de tolérer les crimes contre l’humanité et les crimes de guerre.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;u&gt;Pour plus d’informations:&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/u&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;Jean-Marc Crevoisier&lt;br /&gt;Chef Information DFAE&lt;br /&gt;+41 (0)79 763 84 10&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Adrian Sollberger&lt;br /&gt;Porte-parole de la Mission Suisse à New York&lt;br /&gt;+1 (917) 757 3389&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Communication DFAE Palais fédéral ouest CH-3003 Berne Tél. Service de communication: +41 58 462 31 53 Tél. Service de presse: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <attachment id="105452">
        <title>Letter to the Security Council (en)</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>22</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/29291.pdf</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </attachment>
      <link id="105445">
        <title>L’engagement de la Suisse en Syrie</title>
        <uri>http://www.deza.admin.ch/fr/Accueil/Pays/Proche_et_Moyen_Orient/Irak_Jordanie_Syrie_Liban</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="105446">
        <title>Justice internationale</title>
        <uri>http://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/home/topics/intla/intjus.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>La Svizzera chiede al Consiglio di sicurezza dell’ONU di perseguire i gravi crimini in Siria davanti alla Corte penale internazionale</title>
      <lead>Le numerose accuse di crimini contro l’umanità e crimini di guerra in Siria devono essere sottoposte a un’inchiesta e i responsabili di tutte le parti in conflitto tradotti davanti a un tribunale. Con una lettera datata 14 gennaio 2013, la Svizzera, sostenuta da 56 altri Stati, ha inoltrato questa richiesta al Consiglio di sicurezza dell’ONU. Lo strumento migliore per ottenere giustizia sarebbe la traduzione dei fatti siriani davanti alla Corte penale internazionale (CPI). La Svizzera è convinta che in Siria, senza l’avvio di una procedura coerente contro l’impunità, non sia possibile giungere a una pace duratura.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Dopo quasi due anni di sanguinose lotte, la situazione umanitaria in Siria si sta ulteriormente aggravando. Il conflitto ha già causato circa 60 000 morti, per lo più civili, e attualmente non è ipotizzabile alcuna soluzione politica. Alla luce di questa drammatica situazione e in assenza di qualsiasi segnale di miglioramento, con questa lettera la Svizzera vuole lanciare un segnale in favore del rispetto dei valori umanitari fondamentali e della giustizia. L’appello è rivolto sia alle vittime siriane affinché sappiano di non essere state dimenticate, sia alle parti in conflitto affinché pongano fine alla violenza e rispettino i diritti dell’uomo e il diritto internazionale umanitario. A questo appello rivolto al Consiglio di sicurezza hanno aderito 56 altri Stati.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;L’iniziativa svizzera riveste un carattere puramente umanitario e si pone al di sopra delle parti, schierandosi unicamente in favore della giustizia. I responsabili di tutte le parti in lotta saranno chiamati in causa per le loro azioni. Il perseguimento penale rientra primariamente nella responsabilità delle autorità siriane che, nonostante i ripetuti appelli della comunità internazionale, non hanno ancora dimostrato la volontà di aprire un’inchiesta equa e indipendente contro le accuse di crimini contro l’umanità e crimini di guerra. Di conseguenza, la giustizia può essere espressa solo dalla Corte penale internazionale (CPI). La Siria non rientra fra gli Stati parti del trattato costitutivo della CPI, per cui un suo perseguimento davanti alla Corte penale richiede una decisione del Consiglio di sicurezza. &lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;La lettera è in pratica una petizione, in quanto la decisione in merito a tale perseguimento compete esclusivamente al Consiglio di sicurezza. La lettera rappresenta comunque un segnale forte contro l’impunità e dimostra che un numero significativo di Stati non è disposto a tollerare né i crimini contro l’umanità, né i crimini di guerra.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;u&gt;Per informazioni:&lt;/u&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Jean-Marc Crevoisier&lt;br /&gt;Capo Informazione DFAE&lt;br /&gt;+41 (0)79 763 84 10&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Adrian Sollberger&lt;br /&gt;Portavoce della Missione svizzera a New York&lt;br /&gt;+1 (917) 757 3389&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Comunicazione DFAE Palazzo federale ovest CH-3003 Berna Tel. Servizio di comunicazione: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Servizio stampa: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <attachment id="105453">
        <title>Letter to the Security Council (en)</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>22</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/29292.pdf</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </attachment>
      <link id="105447">
        <title>L’impegno della Svizzera in Siria</title>
        <uri>http://www.deza.admin.ch/it/Pagina_iniziale/Paesi/Vicino_e_Medio_Oriente/Iraq_Giordania_Siria_Libano</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="105448">
        <title>Giustizia internazionale</title>
        <uri>http://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/home/topics/intla/intjus.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Switzerland asks the UN Security Council to refer the serious crimes committed in Syria to the International Criminal Court</title>
      <lead>The numerous allegations of crimes against humanity and war crimes in Syria need to be investigated and those responsible on all sides of the conflict brought before court. Switzerland, supported by 56 other countries, lodged this request with the UN Security Council in a letter on 14 January 2013. The best means of ensuring justice would be to refer the situation in Syria to the International Criminal Court (ICC). Switzerland is convinced that no lasting peace is possible in Syria without taking consistent action against impunity.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;After almost two years of bitter and bloody fighting the humanitarian situation in Syria continues to deteriorate further. The conflict has already claimed around 60,000 lives, predominantly civilians, and there is still no political solution in sight. In view of this dramatic situation and the lack of any signs of an improvement, Switzerland wishes this letter to send a clear signal that basic humanitarian values should be respected and justice upheld. The appeal is intended both to remind the victims of the conflict that they have not been forgotten and as a warning to the warring parties that they should put a stop to the violence and respect human rights and international humanitarian law. 56 countries have joined this appeal to the Security Council.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;The Swiss initiative is of an exclusively humanitarian nature and is impartial. It espouses only the cause of justice. Those responsible on all sides of the conflict should be brought to justice. Although prime responsibility for bringing alleged perpetrators to justice lies with the Syrian authorities, they have made no efforts to investigate the allegations of crimes against humanity and war crimes in fair and independent legal proceedings. Consequently, justice can only be expected from the International Criminal Court. As Syria is not a state party to the ICC founding statute, referral to the Criminal Court requires a decision of the Security Council. &lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;The letter is a petition as the sole authority to decide on such a referral lies with the Security Council. Nonetheless, regardless of the outcome, the letter sends a strong signal against impunity and shows that a significant number of countries are not willing to tolerate crimes against humanity and war crimes.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;u&gt;For further details: &lt;br /&gt;&lt;/u&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;Jean-Marc Crevoisier&lt;br /&gt;Head of FDFA Information&lt;br /&gt;+41 (0)79 763 84 10&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Adrian Sollberger&lt;br /&gt;Spokesperson of the Mission of Switzerland to the United Nations, New York&lt;br /&gt;+1 (917) 757 3389&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>FDFA Communication Federal Palace West Wing CH-3003 Bern, Switzerland Tel. Communication service: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Press service: +41 58 460 55 55 E-mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @SwissMFA</contact>
      <attachment id="105454">
        <title>Letter to the Security Council</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>22</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/29293.pdf</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </attachment>
      <link id="105449">
        <title>Switzerland’s commitment in Syria</title>
        <uri>http://www.deza.admin.ch/en/Home/Countries/Near_and_Middle_East/Iraq_Jordan_Syria_Lebanon</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="105450">
        <title>International justice</title>
        <uri>http://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home/topics/intla/intjus.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
