<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="28121" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2009-07-15</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="yes" id="606" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>601</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössische Zollverwaltung</name>
      <name lang="fr">Administration fédérale des douanes</name>
      <name lang="it">Amministrazione federale delle dogane</name>
      <name lang="en">The Federal Customs Administration</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.ezv.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.ezv.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.ezv.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.ezv.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">ozd.zentrale@ezv.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">ozd.zentrale@ezv.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">ozd.zentrale@ezv.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">ozd.zentrale@ezv.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="1007" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>701</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Integrationsbüro EDA/EVD (IB) - ab 1.1.2013 im EDA</name>
      <name lang="fr">Bureau de l'intégration DFAE/DFE (BI) - dès le 1.1.2013 au DFAE</name>
      <name lang="it">Ufficio dell'integrazione DFAE/DFE (UI) - a partire dal 1.1.2013 nel DFAE</name>
      <name lang="en">Integration Office FDFA/FDEA (IO) - as of 1.1.2013 in the FDFA</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.europa.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.europa.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.europa.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.europa.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">europa@ib.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">europa@ib.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">europa@ib.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">europa@ib.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="601">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Finanzdepartement</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des finances</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale delle finanze</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Finance</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.efd.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.dff.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.efd.admin.ch/efd/it/home.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.efd.admin.ch/efd/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <department id="701">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Wirtschaft, Bildung und Forschung</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'économie, de la formation et de la recherche</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'economia, della formazione e della ricerca</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Economic Affairs, Education and Research</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Geändertes Güterverkehrsabkommen; erste Sitzung des gemischten Ausschusses</title>
      <lead>Der gemischte Ausschuss im Rahmen des geänderten Güterverkehrsabkommens hat zum ersten Mal getagt. Es wurden offene Fragen der gegenseitigen Koordination diskutiert.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Heute fand die erste Sitzung des gemischten Ausschusses im Rahmen des geänderten Güterverkehrsabkommens in Brüssel statt.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Ziel der Sitzung war es, offene Fragen zu beantworten, um die diesbezüglichen Bestimmungen auf beiden Seiten korrekt, fristgerecht und sofern nötig zeitgleich umsetzen zu können. So wurden insbesondere Detailfragen über die summarische Eingangs- und Ausgangsanmeldung (besser bekannt unter den Begriff Vorabanmeldung) und den Austausch der Sicherheitsdaten, den AEO (Authorised Economic Operator) und die Risikoanalyse im Bereich der Sicherheit erörtert.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Die geänderte Vereinbarung (Abkommen zwischen der Schweizerischen Eidgenossenschaft und der Europäischen Gemeinschaft über die Erleichterung der Kontrollen und Formalitäten im Güterverkehr und über zollrechtliche Sicherheitsmassnahmen) wurde am 25. Juni 2009 unterzeichnet und wird seit 1. Juli 2009 vorläufig angewendet.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Sabrina Dallafior, Mission der Schweiz bei der EU, Tel.: +32 2 28 61304 oder +32 473 98 34 20 H. Kästli, Vizedirektor, Chef Hauptabteilung Recht und Abgaben, erreichbar über Kai-Bernhard Trachsel, Kommunikation und Medien EZV, Tel +41 31 32 26572</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Accord sur le transport des marchandises modifié; première séance du comité mixte</title>
      <lead>Le comité mixte créé dans le cadre de l'accord sur le transport des marchandises modifié s'est réuni pour la première fois. Des questions relatives à la coordination réciproque ont été abordées.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;La première séance du comité mixte créé dans le cadre de l'accord sur le transport des marchandises modifié a eu lieu aujourd'hui à Bruxelles.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Le but de cette séance était de répondre à des questions en suspens afin de pouvoir mettre en œuvre les dispositions applicables aux deux parties de façon correcte, dans les délais et si nécessaire simultanément. Les discussions ont porté en particulier sur des questions de détail concernant la déclaration sommaire d'entrée ou de sortie (mieux connue sous le nom de déclaration préalable), l'échange de données de sécurité, l'AEO (Authorized Economic Operator) et l'analyse des risques dans le domaine de la sécurité.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;L'accord modifié (accord entre la Suisse et la Communauté européenne relatif à la facilitation des contrôles et des formalités lors du transport des marchandises ainsi qu'aux mesures douanières de sécurité) a été signé le 25 juin 2009 et est appliqué provisoirement depuis le 1er juillet 2009.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Sabrina Dallafior, Mission suisse auprès de l'UE, tél. +32 2 286 13 04 ou +32 473 98 34 20 Hermann Kästli, vice-directeur, chef de la division principale Droit et redevances, joignable par l'intermédiaire de Kai-Bernhard Trachsel, Communication et médias AFD, tél. +41 31 322 65 72</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Modifica dell'accordo sui trasporti di merci: prima seduta del comitato misto</title>
      <lead>Il comitato misto che si occupa della modifica dell'accordo sui trasporti di merci si è riunito per la prima volta. Durante la seduta sono state affrontate questioni in sospeso inerenti al coordinamento tra le Parti.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;In data odierna ha avuto luogo a Bruxelles la prima seduta del comitato misto, istituito nell'ambito della modifica dell'accordo sui trasporti di merci.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;L'obiettivo dell'incontro era trattare le questioni in sospeso, affinché le relative disposizioni possano essere applicate in modo corretto da entrambe le Parti entro i termini e, se necessario, contemporaneamente. In particolare, il suddetto comitato ha esaminato dettagli riguardanti la dichiarazione sommaria di entrata e di uscita (meglio nota come "predichiarazione"), lo scambio di dati e l'analisi dei rischi in materia di sicurezza nonché la qualifica di "operatore economico autorizzato" (Authorized Economic Operator, AEO).&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Il nuovo "Accordo tra la Comunità europea e la Confederazione Svizzera riguardante l'agevolazione dei controlli e delle formalità nei trasporti di merci e le misure doganali di sicurezza", sottoscritto il 25 giugno 2009, è applicato provvisoriamente dal 1°&amp;nbsp;luglio 2009.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Sabrina Dallafior, Missione della Svizzera presso l'UE, tel. +32 2 28 61304 oppure +32 473 98 34 20 Hermann Kästli, vicedirettore, capo della divisione principale Diritto e tributi, Direzione generale delle dogane, raggiungibile tramite Kai-Bernhard Trachsel, Comunicazione/Media, Direzione generale delle dogane, tel. +41 31 32 26572</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Amended Agreement on the Carriage of Goods; first meeting of the Mixed Committee</title>
      <lead>The Mixed Committee on the Amended Agreement on the Carriage of Goods has held its first meeting. Unresolved questions to do with joint coordination were discussed.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Today the first meeting of the Mixed Committee on the Amended Agreement on the Carriage of Goods took place in Brussels.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The objective of the meeting was to answer unresolved questions, to be able to implement the provisions in this regard on both sides correctly, within the stipulated period and as far as it is necessary, at the same time. Detailed questions in particular on entry and exit summary declarations (better known as prior notification) and the exchange of security data, the Authorised Economic Operator (AEO) and risk analysis in the area of security were discussed.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The amended agreement (Agreement between the EU and the Swiss Confederation on the Waiving of Checks and Formalities in Goods Transport and on Customs Security Measures) was signed on 25 June 2009 and has been applied provisionally since 1 July 2009.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Sabrina Dallafior, Swiss Mission to the EU, tel.: + 32 2 28 61304 or +32 473 98 34 20 H. Kästli, Vice-Director, Head of Legal and Duties Division, can be reached via Kai-Bernhard Trachsel, FCA Communications and Media, tel. +41 31 32 26572</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <offers>
      <offer id="16" org-id="606">
        <name lang="de">Zolltarif</name>
        <name lang="fr">Tarif douanier</name>
        <name lang="it">Tariffa doganale</name>
        <name lang="en">Customs tariff</name>
      </offer>
    </offers>
    <keywords>
      <keyword id="184" org-id="606">
        <name lang="de">Zollverfahren</name>
        <name lang="fr">Procédure douanière</name>
        <name lang="it">Operazioni doganali</name>
        <name lang="en">Customs procedure</name>
      </keyword>
    </keywords>
    <topics>
      <topic id="34">
        <name lang="de">Europa</name>
        <name lang="fr">Europe</name>
        <name lang="it">Europa</name>
        <name lang="en">Europe</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="46">
        <name lang="de">Verkehr</name>
        <name lang="fr">Transports</name>
        <name lang="it">Trasporti</name>
        <name lang="en">Transport</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="48">
        <name lang="de">Zoll</name>
        <name lang="fr">Douanes</name>
        <name lang="it">Dogane</name>
        <name lang="en">Customs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
