<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="81422" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2020-12-07</pubdate>
    <blocking-period>2020-12-07</blocking-period>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="318" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>301</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Bundesamt für Statistik</name>
      <name lang="fr">Office fédéral de la statistique</name>
      <name lang="it">Ufficio federale di statistica</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Statistical Office</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.statistik.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.statistique.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.statistica.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.statistics.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@bfs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@bfs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@bfs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@bfs.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="301">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement des Innern</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'intérieur</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'interno</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Home Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Neuchâtel</city>
      <title>2019 investierten die Unternehmen 15,5 Milliarden Franken in die Forschung</title>
      <lead>2019 wendeten die Privatunternehmen in der Schweiz 15,5 Milliarden Franken für Forschung und Entwicklung (F+E) auf, das sind 9% mehr als der revidierte Betrag von 2017. Die Pharmaindustrie investierte mit 5,2 Milliarden Franken am meisten in die F+E in der Schweiz. Knapp 58 700 Personen gingen in einem Privatunternehmen Forschungsaktivitäten nach, ein Viertel davon waren Frauen. Soweit die wichtigsten Ergebnisse der Erhebung des Bundesamtes für Statistik (BFS) in Zusammenarbeit mit economiesuisse.</lead>
      <text link="no">Diese Medienmitteilung und weitere Informationen zum Thema finden Sie auf der Website des BFS (siehe Link unten).</text>
      <contact>Sandra Plaza Chardon, BFS, Sektion Wirtschaftsstruktur und -analysen, Tel.: +41 58 463 63 48, E-Mail: Sandra.PlazaChardon@bfs.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="208970">
        <title>Kompletter Text und Mediendossier</title>
        <uri>https://www.bfs.admin.ch/news/de/2020-0298</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Neuchâtel</city>
      <title>Les entreprises ont investi 15,5 milliards de francs dans la recherche en 2019</title>
      <lead>En 2019, les entreprises privées ont consacré 15,5 milliards de francs en Suisse pour leurs activités de recherche et développement (R-D), soit une augmentation de 9% par rapport au montant révisé de 2017. Avec 5,2 milliards de francs, la «Pharmacie» est la branche qui investit le plus dans la R-D en Suisse. Les activités de recherche des entreprises privées ont été effectuées par près de 58 700 personnes dont un quart sont des femmes. Tels sont les principaux résultats de l’enquête réalisée par l’Office fédéral de la statistique (OFS) en partenariat avec economiesuisse.</lead>
      <text link="no">Vous trouverez ce communiqué de presse et d'autres informations sur ce thème sur le site web de l'OFS (cf. lien ci-dessous).</text>
      <contact>Sandra Plaza Chardon, OFS, Section Structure et analyses économiques, tél.: +41 58 463 63 48, e-mail: Sandra.PlazaChardon@bfs.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="208971">
        <title>Texte intégral et dossier de presse</title>
        <uri>https://www.bfs.admin.ch/news/fr/2020-0298</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Neuchâtel</city>
      <title>Nel 2019 le imprese hanno investito 15,5 miliardi di franchi nella ricerca</title>
      <lead>Nel 2019, le imprese private hanno destinato 15,5 miliardi di franchi alle loro attività di ricerca e sviluppo (R+S) in Svizzera, il che corrisponde a un aumento del 9% rispetto all’importo rivisto per il 2017. Con 5,2 miliardi di franchi il ramo «Farmacia» è quello che investe di più in R+S in Svizzera. Le attività di ricerca delle imprese private sono state effettuate da circa 58 700 persone, un quarto delle quali erano donne. Sono questi i principali risultati emersi dalla rilevazione realizzata dall’Ufficio federale di statistica (UST) in collaborazione con economiesuisse.</lead>
      <text link="no">Il presente comunicato stampa e ulteriori informazioni sul tema sono reperibili sulla pagina Internet dell'UST (link sotto).</text>
      <contact>Sandra Plaza Chardon, UST, sezione Struttura e analisi economiche, tel.: +41 58 463 63 48, e-mail: Sandra.PlazaChardon@bfs.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="208972">
        <title>Testo integrale e dossier per i media</title>
        <uri>https://www.bfs.admin.ch/news/it/2020-0298</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Neuchâtel</city>
      <title>Enterprises spent CHF 15.5 billion on research in 2019</title>
      <lead>In 2019, private enterprises dedicated CHF 15.5 billion in Switzerland to their research and development (R&amp;D) activities, i.e. an increase of 9% compared with the revised figure for 2017. With CHF 5.2 billion, the pharmaceutical sector invested the most in R&amp;D in Switzerland. Research activities in private enterprises were carried out by almost 58 700 persons, a quarter of whom were women. These are the main results of a study carried out by the Federal Statistical Office (FSO) in partnership with economiesuisse.</lead>
      <text link="no">This press release and further information on this topic can be found on the FSO website (see link below).</text>
      <contact>Sandra Plaza Chardon, FSO, Economic Structure and Analyses, tel.: +41 58 463 63 48, e-mail: Sandra.PlazaChardon@bfs.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="208973">
        <title>Complete text and press kit - Please note that the English version only includes the release's lead</title>
        <uri>https://www.bfs.admin.ch/news/en/2020-0298</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="43">
        <name lang="de">Statistik</name>
        <name lang="fr">Statistiques</name>
        <name lang="it">Statistica</name>
        <name lang="en">Statistics</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="47">
        <name lang="de">Wirtschaft</name>
        <name lang="fr">Économie</name>
        <name lang="it">Economia</name>
        <name lang="en">Economic Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
