<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="81856" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2020-12-30</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="324" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>301</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Swissmedic, Schweizerisches Heilmittelinstitut</name>
      <name lang="fr">Swissmedic, Institut suisse des produits thérapeutiques</name>
      <name lang="it">Swissmedic, Istituto svizzero per gli agenti terapeutici</name>
      <name lang="en">Swiss Agency for Therapeutic Products</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.swissmedic.ch/</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.swissmedic.ch/?lang=3</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.swissmedic.ch/?lang=4</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.swissmedic.ch/?lang=2</www>
      <email lang="de"/>
      <email lang="fr"/>
      <email lang="it"/>
      <email lang="en"/>
    </originator>
    <department id="301">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement des Innern</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'intérieur</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'interno</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Home Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Medienberichte zu Todesfall nach Covid-19-Impfung in der Schweiz: Kein Zusammenhang mit der Impfung ersichtlich</title>
      <lead>Auf Social-Media-Kanälen und Informationsplattformen kursiert die Meldung über den Tod einer 91-jährigen Person im Kanton Luzern, nachdem sie sich gegen Covid-19 impfen liess. Abklärungen der kantonalen Gesundheitsbehörden und von Swissmedic haben ergeben, dass aufgrund der Krankengeschichte und des Krankheitsverlaufs ein Zusammenhang zwischen dem Tod und der Covid-19 Impfung höchst unwahrscheinlich ist.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Einige Tage nach einer Covid-19-Impfung ist in einem Alters- und Pflegeheim im Kanton Luzern eine 91-jährige Person, die an mehreren schweren Vorerkrankungen litt, verstorben. Weder die Krankengeschichte noch der akute Krankheitsverlauf legen einen direkten kausalen Zusammenhang zwischen der Covid-19-Impfung und dem Tod nahe. Die zur Verfügung stehenden, umfassenden Angaben weisen auf eine natürliche Todesursache hin. Dies wurde auch so auf dem Totenschein vermerkt. Dies wurde auch so auf dem Totenschein vermerkt.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Bisher sind bei Impfungen gegen das neuartige Coronavirus keine unbekannten Nebenwirkungen aufgetreten. Es gibt zum jetzigen Zeitpunkt keine Anhaltspunkte für eine Veränderung des Nutzen-Risiko-Profils des eingesetzten Impfstoffs.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Swissmedic Medienstelle +41 58 462 02 76 media@swissmedic.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Articles faisant état d’un décès en Suisse après une vaccination contre le COVID-19 : la vaccination a priori hors de cause</title>
      <lead>Les médias sociaux et plateformes d’information rapportent qu’une personne de 91 ans est décédée dans le canton de Lucerne après s’être fait vacciner contre le COVID-19. Les investigations des autorités sanitaires cantonales et de Swissmedic ont révélé qu’il est hautement improbable qu’il existe un lien entre le décès et la vaccination, vu les antécédents médicaux de la personne et l’évolution de la maladie.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Quelques jours après s’être fait vacciner contre le COVID-19, une personne de 91 ans souffrant de plusieurs maladies préexistantes graves est décédée dans un établissement médico-social du canton de Lucerne. Ni ses antécédents médicaux ni l’évolution aiguë de la maladie ne suggèrent un lien de causalité direct entre la vaccination contre le COVID-19 et le décès. Les informations complètes disponibles pointent une cause naturelle du décès, mention d’ailleurs portée sur le certificat de décès.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;À ce jour, aucun effet secondaire inconnu n’a été relevé concernant les vaccinations contre le nouveau coronavirus et rien n’indique pour l’heure une modification du profil bénéfice/risque du vaccin utilisé.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Swissmedic Service de presse +41 58 462 02 76 media@swissmedic.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Caso di decesso avvenuto in Svizzera dopo la vaccinazione contro il Covid-19: nessun nesso evidente con la vaccinazione nel caso riportato dai media</title>
      <lead>I social media e altre piattaforme di informazione riportano la notizia della morte di una persona di 91 anni, nel cantone di Lucerna, che era stata vaccinata contro il Covid-19. Le indagini condotte dalle autorità sanitarie cantonali e da Swissmedic hanno dimostrato che, in base all’anamnesi e al decorso della malattia della vittima, l’esistenza di un nesso tra la morte e la vaccinazione contro il Covid-19 è altamente improbabile.</lead>
      <text link="no">Una persona di 91 anni, affetta da gravi patologie pregresse, è morta in una casa di cura nel cantone di Lucerna, pochi giorni dopo essersi sottoposta alla vaccinazione contro il Covid-19. Né l’anamnesi né il decorso acuto della malattia della vittima fanno pensare a una relazione causale diretta tra la vaccinazione contro il Covid-19 e il decesso. Secondo le informazioni dettagliate disponibili la causa naturale del decesso risiederebbe nelle patologie della vittima, come attestato anche dal certificato di morte. Finora non si sono manifestati effetti collaterali sconosciuti in relazione con le vaccinazioni contro il nuovo coronavirus. Al momento non vi è alcun indizio che il profilo rischio-beneficio del vaccino utilizzato si sia alterato.</text>
      <contact>Swissmedic Ufficio stampa +41 58 462 02 76 media@swissmedic.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Media reports about a fatality following a COVID-19 vaccination in Switzerland: no apparent correlation with the vaccination</title>
      <lead>Reports are circulating on social media channels and information platforms of the death of a 91-year-old person in Canton Lucerne who had been vaccinated against COVID-19. Investigations by the cantonal health authorities and Swissmedic have shown that, due to the person’s medical history and the course of their illness, it is highly unlikely that there is a connection between the death and the COVID-19 vaccination.</lead>
      <text link="no">A few days after receiving a vaccination against COVID-19, a 91-year-old person with multiple serious pre-existing health conditions died at a retirement home in Canton Lucerne. Neither the person’s medical history nor the acute course of their illness suggests a direct causal link between the COVID-19 vaccination and their death. The detailed information available indicates that the person died of natural causes. This was also noted on the death certificate. To date, no unknown side effects have occurred as a result of vaccinations against the novel coronavirus. At present, there are no indications that the benefit-risk profile of the vaccine in question should be updated. </text>
      <contact>Swissmedic Media Unit +41 58 462 02 76 media@swissmedic.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="15">
        <name lang="de">Gesundheit</name>
        <name lang="fr">Santé</name>
        <name lang="it">sanità</name>
        <name lang="en">Health</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
