<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="80035" revoked="no">
    <version>2</version>
    <pubdate>2020-08-24</pubdate>
    <blocking-period>2020-08-24</blocking-period>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="318" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>301</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Bundesamt für Statistik</name>
      <name lang="fr">Office fédéral de la statistique</name>
      <name lang="it">Ufficio federale di statistica</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Statistical Office</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.statistik.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.statistique.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.statistica.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.statistics.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@bfs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@bfs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@bfs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@bfs.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="301">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement des Innern</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'intérieur</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'interno</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Home Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Neuchâtel</city>
      <title>Viele Personen mit EFZ absolvieren eine Tertiärausbildung an einer höheren Fachschule</title>
      <lead>Höhere Fachschulen (HF) bieten Personen mit einer beruflichen Grundbildung die Möglichkeit, eine Tertiärausbildung zu absolvieren. Nahezu 80% der HF-Eintretenden besitzen ein eidgenössisches Fähigkeitszeugnis (EFZ) und 10% eine Berufsmaturität. Die HF bieten zudem die Möglichkeit, bereits erworbene Bildungsleistungen anrechnen zu lassen, um die Ausbildungsdauer an der HF zu verkürzen. 14% der HF-Eintretenden nutzen dieses Verfahren. Die Erfolgsquoten an HF sind hoch: 80% der Eintretenden erwerben einen Abschluss. Dies geht aus den Ergebnissen einer Studie des Bundesamtes für Statistik (BFS) hervor.</lead>
      <text link="no">Diese Medienmitteilung und weitere Informationen zum Thema finden Sie auf der Website des BFS (siehe Link unten).</text>
      <contact>Julie Falcon, BFS, Sektion Bildungssystem, Tel.: +41 58 460 51 82, E-Mail: julie.falcon@bfs.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="205034">
        <title>Kompletter Text und Mediendossier</title>
        <uri>https://www.bfs.admin.ch/news/de/2019-0064</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Neuchâtel</city>
      <title>Les écoles supérieures représentent une voie importante d’accès au degré tertiaire pour les titulaires d’un CFC</title>
      <lead>Les écoles supérieures (ES) constituent une voie importante de certification du degré tertiaire pour les titulaires d’un certificat fédéral de capacité (CFC). Près de 80% des entrants en ES détiennent un CFC et 10% une maturité professionnelle. Ces écoles offrent aussi la possibilité de faire reconnaître des compétences acquises précédemment, ce qui permet d’effectuer la formation plus rapidement. Cette opportunité est utilisée par 14% des entrants en ES. Les taux de réussite y sont élevés, avec plus de 80% des entrants qui obtiennent un diplôme, selon une étude réalisée par l’Office fédéral de la statistique (OFS).</lead>
      <text link="no">Vous trouverez ce communiqué de presse et d'autres informations sur ce thème sur le site web de l'OFS (cf. lien ci-dessous).</text>
      <contact>Julie Falcon, BFS, Section Système de formation, tél.: +41 58 460 51 82, e-mail: julie.falcon@bfs.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="205035">
        <title>Texte intégral et dossier de presse</title>
        <uri>https://www.bfs.admin.ch/news/fr/2019-0064</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Neuchâtel</city>
      <title>Le scuole specializzate superiori rappresentano un’importante via d’accesso al grado terziario per le persone titolari di un AFC</title>
      <lead>Le scuole specializzate superiori (SSS) costituiscono un’importante via di certificazione di grado terziario per le persone titolari di un attestato federale di capacità (AFC). Quasi l’80% degli studenti che si iscrivono a una SSS ha conseguito un AFC e il 10% una maturità professionale. Queste scuole offrono inoltre la possibilità di far riconoscere competenze acquisite in precedenza, fatto che permette di portare a termine la formazione più rapidamente. Il 14% delle persone che si iscrivono a una SSS approfittano di tale opportunità. Queste scuole vantano alti tassi di successo, considerando che oltre l’80% degli iscritti si diploma; è quanto emerge da uno studio realizzato dall’Ufficio federale di statistica (UST).</lead>
      <text link="no">Il presente comunicato stampa e ulteriori informazioni sul tema sono reperibili sulla pagina Internet dell'UST (link sotto).</text>
      <contact>Julie Falcon, UST, Sezione Sistema di formazione, tel.: +41 58 460 51 82, e-mail: julie.falcon@bfs.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="205036">
        <title>Testo integrale e dossier per i media</title>
        <uri>https://www.bfs.admin.ch/news/it/2019-0064</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Neuchâtel</city>
      <title>Professional education institutions (PEIs) are an important pathway to a tertiary-level qualification for holders of a federal diploma of vocational education and training</title>
      <lead>Professional education institutions (PEIs) are an important pathway to a tertiary level certification for holders of a federal VET diploma. Nearly 80% of newly enrolled students at Swiss PEIs were holders of a federal diploma of vocational education and training and 10% were also holders of a federal vocational baccalaureate. Swiss PEIs also offer the possibility of obtaining advanced placement in their study programmes through the recognition of non-formal and informal learning (RNIL). 14% of newly enrolled students have benefitted from this option. Moreover, graduation rates at Swiss PEIs are high. According to a study conducted by the Federal Statistical Office (FSO), over 80% of newly enrolled students obtain their professional qualification.</lead>
      <text link="no">This press release and further information on this topic can be found on the FSO website (see link below).</text>
      <contact>Julie Falcon, FSO, Education System section, tel.: +41 58 460 51 82, email: julie.falcon@bfs.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="205037">
        <title>Complete text and press kit - Please note that the English version only includes the release's lead</title>
        <uri>https://www.bfs.admin.ch/news/en/2019-0064</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions>
        <revision date="2020-08-24 08:30" type="I"/>
      </revisions>
    </content>
    <keywords>
      <keyword id="317.16" org-id="318">
        <name lang="de">Bildung und Wissenschaft</name>
        <name lang="fr">Education et science</name>
        <name lang="it">Formazione e scienza</name>
        <name lang="en">Education and science</name>
      </keyword>
    </keywords>
    <topics>
      <topic id="8">
        <name lang="de">Bildung und Forschung</name>
        <name lang="fr">Formation et recherche</name>
        <name lang="it">Formazione e ricerca</name>
        <name lang="en">Education and Research</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="43">
        <name lang="de">Statistik</name>
        <name lang="fr">Statistiques</name>
        <name lang="it">Statistica</name>
        <name lang="en">Statistics</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
