<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="28699" revoked="no">
    <version>2</version>
    <pubdate>2009-08-26</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="yes" id="602" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>601</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Generalsekretariat EFD</name>
      <name lang="fr">Secrétariat général DFF</name>
      <name lang="it">Segreteria generale DFF</name>
      <name lang="en">Secretariat-General FDF</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.efd.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.efd.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.efd.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.efd.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="601">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Finanzdepartement</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des finances</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale delle finanze</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Finance</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.efd.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.dff.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.efd.admin.ch/efd/it/home.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.efd.admin.ch/efd/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Bundesrat nimmt die Umsetzung des Vertrages mit Libyen an die Hand</title>
      <lead>Der Bundespräsident orientierte an der heutigen Sitzung des Bundesrates über die in Libyen zurückgehaltenen Schweizer Geschäftsleute. Der Bundesrat nimmt die Umsetzung des am 20. August 2009 von Bundespräsident Hans-Rudolf Merz und dem libyschen Premierminister Al Baghdadi A. El-Mahmudi in Tripoli unterzeichneten Abkommens an die Hand.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Am Dienstag, den 25. August um 15.30 Uhr ist die "Falcon" der Swiss Air Force nach problemloser Überflugerlaubnis auf dem Militärflugplatz Tripoli gelandet. Nach längerer Wartezeit erhielt die Schweizer Delegation die Einreise-Bewilligung.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Anschliessend fand die Kontaktaufnahme mit den beiden in Libyen zurückgehaltenen Schweizer Bürgern statt. Im Verlaufe des Abends wurde den beiden in Libyen Zurückgehaltenen Pass und Ausreise-Visum übergeben. Als letzten Akt gilt es, die Zustimmung der Justizbehörde für die Ausreise zu erhalten.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Der libysche Premierminister teilte dem Bundespräsidenten heute Morgen schriftlich mit, dass es sich beim Abschluss der in Libyen erforderlichen administrativen Verfahren nur um eine Frage der Zeit handelt.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Das EFD ist in regelmässigem Kontakt mit der Delegation des Bundespräsidenten, den Familienangehörigen der in Libyen Zurückgehaltenen sowie einem Vertreter der ABB (Arbeitgeber einer der in Libyen Zurückgehaltenen).&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Der Bundesrat nahm von der Orientierung durch den Bundespräsidenten und der Vorsteherin des EDA über den aktuellen Stand der bilateralen Beziehungen zwischen der Schweiz und Libyen Kenntnis.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Vizekanzler André Simonazzi, Bundesratssprecher, 031 322 37 03</contact>
      <revisions>
        <revision date="2009-08-26 17:51" type="R"/>
      </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Le Conseil fédéral se charge de la mise en œuvre de l'accord passé avec la Libye</title>
      <lead>Lors de la séance du Conseil fédéral d'aujourd'hui, le président de la Confédération a donné des informations sur les hommes d'affaire suisses retenus en Libye. Le Conseil fédéral se charge de la mise en œuvre de l'accord signé le 20 août 2009 à Tripoli par le président de la Confédération Hans-Rudolf Merz et par le premier ministre libyen Al Baghdadi A. El-Mahmudi.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Mardi 25&amp;nbsp;août, le "Falcon" de la Swiss Air Force s'est posé vers 15&amp;nbsp;h&amp;nbsp;30 sur l'aérodrome militaire de Tripoli après avoir obtenu sans problème l'autorisation de survoler la Libye. Après une longue attente, la délégation suisse a reçu son autorisation d'entrée.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;La délégation a ensuite pu rencontrer les deux citoyens suisses retenus en Libye. Ces deux personnes ont reçu leur passeport et un visa de sortie au cours de la soirée. Il importait en dernier lieu d'obtenir l'autorisation de sortie de la part des autorités judiciaires.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Ce matin, le premier ministre libyen a informé par écrit le président de la Confédération qu'il ne s'agit que d'une question de temps pour que la procédure administrative nécessaire en Libye prenne fin.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Le DFF a des contacts réguliers avec la délégation du président de la Confédération, avec les membres de la famille des personnes retenues en Libye ainsi qu'avec un représentant d'ABB (employeur d'un des deux Suisses retenus en Libye).&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Le Conseil fédéral a pris acte des informations sur l'état actuel des relations bilatérales entre la Suisse et la Libye qui lui ont été fournies par le président de la Confédération et la cheffe du Département fédéral des affaires étrangères.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>André Simonazzi, vice-chancelier, porte-parole du Conseil fédéral, tél. 031 322 37 03</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Il Consiglio federale si occupa dell'attuazione dell'accordo con la Libia</title>
      <lead>In occasione dell'odierna seduta del Consiglio federale, il presidente della Confederazione ha dato informazioni sui due uomini d'affari svizzeri trattenuti in Libia. Il Consiglio federale si occuperà dell'attuazione dell'accordo firmato a Tripoli il 20 agosto 2009 dal presidente della Confederazione Hans-Rudolf Merz e dal primo ministro libico Al Baghdadi A. El-Mahmudi.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Martedì 25 agosto alle ore 15.30 il "Falcon" dalla Swiss Air Force è atterrato senza problemi all'aeroporto militare di Tripoli dopo aver ottenuto l'autorizzazione al sorvolo. Dopo lunga attesa la delegazione svizzera ha ricevuto l'autorizzazione all'entrata.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Successivamente è avvenuto l'incontro con i due cittadini svizzeri trattenuti in Libia, ai quali nel corso della serata è stato restituito il passaporto e consegnato il visto di uscita. Per espletare la pratica occorre ancora l'autorizzazione dell'autorità di giustizia a lasciare il Paese.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Stamattina il primo ministro libico ha comunicato per scritto al presidente della Confederazione che il disbrigo del necessario procedimento amministrativo in Libia sarà solo questione di tempo.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Il Dipartimento federale delle finanze DFF è regolarmente in contatto con la delegazione del presidente della Confederazione, i familiari dei cittadini trattenuti in Libia e con un rappresentante di ABB (datore di lavoro di uno dei due uomini d'affari).&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Il Governo ha preso conoscenza delle informazioni date dal presidente della Confederazione e dal capo del Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri DFAE sullo stato attuale delle relazioni bilaterali tra la Svizzera e la Libia.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Vicecancelliere André Simonazzi, portavoce del Consiglio federale, tel. 031 322 37 03</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Federal Council will take charge of implementing the agreement with Libya</title>
      <lead>The President of the Swiss Confederation provided information during today's meeting of the Federal Council about the Swiss business men detained in Libya. The Federal Council will take charge of implementing the agreement signed by President Hans-Rudolf Merz and the Libyan Prime Minister Al Baghdadi A. El-Mahmudi in Tripoli on 20 August 2009.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;On Tuesday, 25 August at 3.30 p.m., the "Falcon" of the Swiss Air Force landed at the military airfield in Tripoli as a result of unproblematic landing approval. After a long wait, the Swiss delegation was granted permission to enter.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Contact with the two Swiss citizens detained in Libya was subsequently made. During the course of the evening, the passports and exit visas were handed over to both of the detainees.&amp;nbsp;The final hurdle is that of obtaining the approval ot the justice authorities for the departure.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The Libyan Prime Minister informed the President in writing this morning that it was only a matter of time before the administrative procedures required in Libya were finalised.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The Federal Department of Finance (FDF) is regularly in touch with the President's delegation and the family members of those detained in Libya, as well as a representative of ABB (the employer of one of the individuals detained in Libya).&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The Federal Council took note of the information provided by the President and the head of the Federal Department of Foreign Affairs (FDFA) on the current status of bilateral relations between Switzerland and Libya.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Vice-Chancellor André Simonazzi, Federal Council Spokesman, tel. 031 322 37 03</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <keywords>
      <keyword id="234" org-id="602">
        <name lang="de">Eveline Widmer-Schlumpf, Bundespräsidentin 2012</name>
        <name lang="fr">Eveline Widmer-Schlumpf, présidente de la Confédération en 2012</name>
        <name lang="it">Eveline Widmer-Schlumpf, presidente della Confederazione 2012</name>
        <name lang="en">Eveline Widmer-Schlumpf, President of the Swiss Confederation 2012</name>
      </keyword>
    </keywords>
    <topics>
      <topic id="30">
        <name lang="de">Ausserordentliche Lagen</name>
        <name lang="fr">Situations extraordinaires</name>
        <name lang="it">Situazioni straordinarie</name>
        <name lang="en">Special Situations</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="33">
        <name lang="de">Bundespräsident/-in</name>
        <name lang="fr">Président/e de la Confédération</name>
        <name lang="it">Presidente della Confederazione</name>
        <name lang="en">President of the Swiss Confederation</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
