<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="2865" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2006-02-06</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="201" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>201</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="201">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Gespräche zwischen srilankischer Regierung und Liberation Tigers of Tamil Eelam 22. und 23. Februar 2006 in der Schweiz</title>
      <lead>Die srilankische Regierung und die Liberation Tigers of Tamil Eelam (LTTE) haben beschlossen, am 22. und 23. Februar 2006 in der Schweiz zu Gesprächen über die Umsetzung des Waffenstillstandes zusammen zu kommen. Die Schweiz begrüsst diesen Entscheid.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Am 25. Januar 2006 haben sich die srilankische Regierung und die LTTE unter der Vermittlung Norwegens darauf geeinigt, Gespräche zur Umsetzung des Waffenstillstandes in der Schweiz durchzuführen. Die Gespräche sollen am 22. und 23. Februar 2006 in der Region Genf stattfinden.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Die Schweiz begrüsst diesen Entscheid und wird alles unternehmen, damit diese Gespräche in einem Rahmen stattfinden könne, der einer einvernehmlichen Lösung förderlich ist.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Die Schweiz begrüsst auch den Rückgang der Waffenstillstandsverletzungen seit dem 25. Januar 2006. In Anbetracht der Vorkommnisse in den letzten Tage ruft die Schweiz die Konfliktparteien jedoch dazu auf, alles daran zu setzen, damit die Gespräche in einer konstruktiven Atmosphäre beginnen können.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Presse- und Informationsdienst Bundeshaus West CH-3003 Bern Tel.: (+41) 031 322 31 53 Fax: (+41) 031 324 90 47 / 48</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Pourparlers entre le gouvernement sri lankais et les Tigres de libération de l’Eelam Tamoul, les 22 et 23 février 2006 en Suisse</title>
      <lead>Le gouvernement sri lankais et les Tigres de libération de l’Eelam Tamoul (LTTE) ont décidé de mener des pourparlers les 22 et 23 février 2006 en Suisse sur la mise en œuvre du cessez-le-feu. La Suisse se félicite de cette décision.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Le 25 janvier 2006, le gouvernement sri lankais et les LTTE sont convenus, grâce aux efforts de facilitation de la Norvège, de mener des pourparlers en Suisse sur la mise en œuvre du cessez-le-feu. Les pourparlers doivent avoir lieu les 22 et 23 février 2006 dans la région de Genève.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;La Suisse salue cette décision et fera tout son possible pour que les pourparlers puissent se dérouler dans un cadre qui soit propice à l’adoption d’une solution satisfaisant les deux parties.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;La Suisse se félicite en outre de la réduction des violations du cessez-le-feu depuis le 25 janvier 2006. Au vu des incidents survenus ces derniers jours, la Suisse appelle toutefois les parties au conflit à mettre tout en œuvre pour que les pourparlers commencent dans une atmosphère constructive.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Service de presse et d'information Palais fédéral ouest CH-3003 Berne Tél.: (+41) 031 322 31 53 Fax: (+41) 031 324 90 47 / 48</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Il 22 e 23 febbraio 2006 colloqui in Svizzera tra il Governo di Sri Lanka e le Liberation Tigers of Tamil Eelam</title>
      <lead>Il Governo di Sri Lanka e le Liberation Tigers of Tamil Eelam (LTTE) hanno deciso di incontrarsi il 23 e 16 febbraio 2006 in Svizzera per discutere dell'applicazione della tregua. La Svizzera si rallegra per questa decisione.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Il 25 gennaio 2006 Il Governo di Sri Lanka e le Liberation Tigers of Tamil Eelam hanno convenuto, grazie alla mediazione della Norvegia, di condurre colloqui in Svizzera circa l'applicazione della tregua. I colloqui si terranno nella regione di Ginevra il 22 e 23 febbraio.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;La Svizzera si rallegra per questa decisione e si adopererà in ogni modo affinché questi colloqui si possano svolgere in un quadro che favorisca una soluzione di comune accordo.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;La Svizzera si felicita anche per la diminuzione, a partire dal 25 gennaio 2006, delle violazioni alla tregua. Visti gli avvenimenti degli ultimi giorni, la Svizzera invita le parti in conflitto a fare tutto il possibile affinché i colloqui possano cominciare in un clima costruttivo.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Servizio stampa e informazione Palazzo federale ovest CH-3003 Berna Tel.: (+41) 031 322 31 53 Fax: (+41) 031 324 90 47 / 48</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Talks between the Government of Sri Lanka and the Liberation Tigers of Tamil Eelam on 22 and 23 February 2006 in Switzerland</title>
      <lead>The Government of Sri Lanka and the Liberation Tigers of Tamil Eelam (LTTE) have agreed to meet on 22 and 23 February 2006 in Switzerland for talks on the implementation of the ceasefire agreement. Switzerland welcomes this decision.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;On 25 January 2006, the Government of Sri Lanka and the LTTE with the facilitation of Norway agreed to hold talks in Switzerland on the implementation of the ceasefire agreement. The talks are expected to take place on 22 and 23 February 2006 in the region of Geneva.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Switzerland welcomes this decision and will do its utmost to ensure that the talks take place in an environment that is conducive to reaching a mutually acceptable solution.&lt;br /&gt; &amp;nbsp;&lt;br /&gt; Switzerland also welcomes the reduction in the number of ceasefire violations since 25 January 2006. In view of the events of the last few days, Switzerland calls on the parties to the conflict to do all within their powers to ensure that the talks can start in a constructive atmosphere.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Press and Information Service Bundeshaus West CH-3003 Berne Tel.: (+41) 031 322 31 53 Fax: (+41) 031 324 90 47 / 48</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
