<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="3408" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2006-02-27</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="322" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>301</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Staatssekretariat für Bildung und Forschung (SBF) - ab 1.1.2013 SBFI</name>
      <name lang="fr">Secrétariat d'Etat à l'éducation et à la recherche (SER) - dès le 1.1.2013 SEFRI</name>
      <name lang="it">Segreteria di Stato per l'educazione e la ricerca (SER) - a partire dal 1.1.2013 SEFRI</name>
      <name lang="en">State Secretariat for Education and Research (SER) - as of 1.1.2013 SERI</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.sbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.sbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.sbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.sbf.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@sbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@sbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@sbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@sbf.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="301">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement des Innern</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'intérieur</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'interno</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Home Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Das Ratskomitee der Europäischen Organisation für Astronomie ESO tagt zum ersten Mal in der Schweiz</title>
      <lead>Auf Einladung des Staatssekretariats für Bildung und Forschung SBF findet am 27. und 28. Februar 2006 in Bern die erste offizielle Sitzung der Europäischen Organisation für Astronomie ESO statt. Auf der Tagesordnung der 66. Sitzung des ESO-Ratskomitees stehen laufende und geplante Projekte, finanzielle Langzeit- und Strategiepläne sowie Beitrittsanträge verschiedener europäischer Länder.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Die Schweiz ist seit 1982 Vollmitglied der ESO (European Southern Observatory), welche 1962 gegründet wurde und ihren Hauptsitz in Garching bei München hat. Die Mitgliedstaaten der ESO sind neben der Schweiz: Belgien, Dänemark, Deutschland, Finnland, Frankreich, Grossbritannien, Italien, Niederlande, Portugal, Schweden und Spanien (ab 1.7.2006). Zum Nutzen der Astronomen aus ihren Mitgliedstaaten betreibt die ESO Teleskope an drei Standorten in der chilenischen Atacama-Wüste, namentlich das Very Large Telescope VLT auf Paranal, welches aus vier Teleskopen von je 8,2 Metern Durchmesser besteht.&lt;br /&gt; Während der 23-jährigen Mitgliedschaft der Schweiz bei der ESO haben Schweizer Astronomen mit Forschungsarbeiten über Kosmologie und zu Planeten ausserhalb unseres Sonnensystems wiederholt wissenschaftliche Spitzenleistungen erbracht. Die Schweiz beteiligt sich mit CHF 6,68 Mio. am Haushalt 2006 der ESO von CHF 174 Mio.; verantwortlich für die Beteiligung der Schweiz an der ESO ist das Staatssekretariat für Bildung und Forschung SBF.&lt;br /&gt; Die erste offizielle Sitzung der ESO in der Schweiz vom 27. und 28. Februar 2006 wird vom Präsidenten des ESO-Rats, Prof. Richard Wade, geleitet. Es sind 20 Delegierte aus den 11 Mitgliedstaaten anwesend, für die Schweiz Prof. Michel Mayor vom Observatorium der Universität Genf und Dr. Martin Steinacher vom SBF. Die ESO ist durch die Generaldirektorin Frau Dr. Catherine Cesarsky und ihren Stellvertreter, Dr. Ian Corbett, vertreten.&lt;br /&gt; Auf der Traktandenliste stehen u.a. der Weiterausbau des VLT sowie die globale Zusammenarbeit mit Nordamerika und Japan beim Radioteleskop ALMA (Atacama Large Millimeter Array). Zudem wird das zukünftige Projekt Extremely Large Telescope ELT diskutiert, ein neues 60-Meter-Teleskop, für welches die ESO schon über fortgeschrittene Studien und Umsetzungspläne verfügt.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Staatssekretariat für Bildung und Forschung SBF Ressort Multilaterale Forschungszusammenarbeit Dr. Martin Steinacher, Tel. 031 324 23 82 Dr. Jean Pierre Ruder Tel. 031 322 96 78 Hallwylstrasse 4 3003 Bern</contact>
      <link id="6183">
        <title>mehr Informationen unter www.eso.org</title>
        <uri>http://www.eso.org</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Le comité du conseil de l’Organisation européenne pour la recherche astronomique ESO se réunit pour la première fois en Suisse</title>
      <lead>A l’invitation du Secrétariat d’Etat à l’éducation et à la recherche SER, la première réunion officielle de l’Organisation européenne pour l’astronomie ESO en Suisse a lieu les 27 et 28 février 2006 à Berne. A l’ordre du jour de la 66e réunion du comité du Conseil de l’ESO figurent les projets en cours et nouveaux, la programmation financière à long terme et les plans stratégiques ainsi que les demandes d’adhésion de divers pays européens.</lead>
      <text link="no">La Suisse est membre de l’ESO depuis 1982. L’ESO (Observatoire européen austral) a été créée en 1962 et a son siège à Garching près de Munich. En dehors de la Suisse, les pays membres sont l’Allemagne, la Belgique, le Danemark, la Finlande, la France, la Grande-Bretagne, l’Italie, les Pays-Bas, le Portugal, la Suède et l’Espagne (à partir du 1.7.2006). A l’usage des astronomes des pays membres, l’ESO exploite des télescopes sur trois sites du désert chilien d’Atacama, dont le Very Large Telescope VLT sur le Mont Paranal, qui se compose de quatre télescopes de 8,2 mètres de diamètre chacun.&lt;br /&gt; Au cours des 23 années d’adhésion de la Suisse à l’ESO, des astronomes suisses se sont distingués par leurs travaux de recherche en cosmologie et sur les exoplanètes (planètes situées hors de notre système solaire). La Suisse contribue à raison de 6,68 millions de francs au budget 2006 de l’ESO qui se monte à 174 millions de francs. La participation de la Suisse à l’ESO est gérée par le Secrétariat d’Etat à l’éducation et à la recherche SER.&lt;br /&gt; La première réunion officielle de l’ESO en Suisse a lieu les 27 et 28 février 2006 à Berne sous la présidence du professeur Richard Wade, président du Conseil de l’ESO. Vingt délégués des onze pays membres sont présents, pour la Suisse le professeur Michel Mayor de l’Observatoire de l’Université de Genève et Martin Steinacher du SER. L’ESO est représentée par sa directrice générale Catherine Cesarsky et son suppléant Ian Corbett.&lt;br /&gt; A l’ordre du jour de cette réunion figurent les extensions du VLT et la coopération globale avec l’Amérique du Nord et le Japon pour le radiotélescope ALMA (Atacama Large Millimeter Array). On discutera aussi du futur projet ELT (Extremely Large Telescope), un nouveau télescope de 60 mètres pour lequel l’ESO a déjà développé des études avancées et des plans de réalisation.</text>
      <contact>Secrétariat d’Etat à l’éducation et à la recherche SER Unité Coopération multilatérale de recherche Martin Steinacher, tél. 031 324 23 82 Jean Pierre Ruder, tél. 031 322 96 78 Hallwylstrasse 4 3003 Berne</contact>
      <link id="6184">
        <title>Compléments d’information: www.eso.org</title>
        <uri>http://www.eso.org</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Council of the European Southern Observatory meets for first time in Switzerland</title>
      <lead>The council of the European Southern Observatory, ESO, is meeting for the first time in Switzerland. On the agenda of the two-day conference 27-28 February in Bern is discussion of current and planned projects, the financing of long-term and strategic plans and requests by different European countries to participate in ESO activities as full members. The invitation to hold the 66th meeting of the ESO in Switzerland came from the State Secretariat for Education and Research, SER.</lead>
      <text link="no">Switzerland joined the European Southern Observatory as a full member in 1982, 20 years after the founding of the organization which has its headquarters in Garching, Germany. Other members are Belgium, Denmark, Germany, Finland, France, Britain, Italy, the Netherlands, Portugal and Sweden. Spain will become the organization’s 12th member on 1 July 2006.&amp;nbsp; The ESO operates telescopes at three locations in the Atacama Desert in Chile. The Very Large Telescope, VLT, at Paranal consists of four telescopes each of which are 8.2 metres in diameter. &lt;br /&gt; During Switzerland’s 23 years as an ESO member, Swiss astronomers have repeatedly accomplished top-class research in cosmology and in the search for and study of planets outside the solar system. Switzerland is contributing CHF 6.68 million to the 2006 ESO budget.&amp;nbsp; The State Secretariat for Education and Research represents Switzerland at the ESO.&lt;br /&gt; The ESO’s first official meeting in Switzerland 27-28 February is chaired by the president of the ESO Council Prof. Richard Wade. Twenty delegates from the 11 member states are taking part. Switzerland is repesented by Prof. Michel Mayor of the Geneva University observatory and Dr. Martin Steinacher of the SER. ESO representatives are the director-general Dr. Catherine Cesarsky and her deputy Dr. Ian Corbett.&lt;br /&gt; Included on the agenda are such topics as the further enlargement of the VLT and global cooperation with North America and Japan on ALMA (Atacama Large Millimeter Array) radio telescope. Discussion will also include the Extremely Large Telescope, ELT,&amp;nbsp; project, a new 60-metre telescope for which the ESO has already carried out advanced studies and implementation plans.</text>
      <contact>State Secretariat for Education and Research SER Multilateral research cooperation unit Dr. Martin Steinacher, Tel. 031 324 23 82 Dr. Jean Pierre Ruder Tel. 031 322 96 78 Hallwylstrasse 4 3003 Bern</contact>
      <link id="6185">
        <title>more information at www.eso.org</title>
        <uri>http://www.eso.org</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <keywords>
      <keyword id="325.10" org-id="322">
        <name lang="de">Wissenschaft</name>
        <name lang="fr">Science</name>
        <name lang="it">Scienza</name>
        <name lang="en">Science</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="325.27" org-id="322">
        <name lang="de">Institution</name>
        <name lang="fr">Institution</name>
        <name lang="it">Istituzione</name>
        <name lang="en">Institution</name>
      </keyword>
    </keywords>
    <topics>
      <topic id="5">
        <name lang="de">Behörden</name>
        <name lang="fr">Autorités</name>
        <name lang="it">Autorità</name>
        <name lang="en">Authorities</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="8">
        <name lang="de">Bildung und Forschung</name>
        <name lang="fr">Formation et recherche</name>
        <name lang="it">Formazione e ricerca</name>
        <name lang="en">Education and Research</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="13">
        <name lang="de">Öffentliche Finanzen</name>
        <name lang="fr">Finances publiques</name>
        <name lang="it">Finanze pubbliche</name>
        <name lang="en">Public Finances</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="19">
        <name lang="de">Medien</name>
        <name lang="fr">Médias</name>
        <name lang="it">Media</name>
        <name lang="en">Media</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="31">
        <name lang="de">Bund und Kantone</name>
        <name lang="fr">Confédération et cantons</name>
        <name lang="it">Confederazione e Cantoni</name>
        <name lang="en">Confederation and Cantons</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="34">
        <name lang="de">Europa</name>
        <name lang="fr">Europe</name>
        <name lang="it">Europa</name>
        <name lang="en">Europe</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="45">
        <name lang="de">Technologie</name>
        <name lang="fr">Technologie</name>
        <name lang="it">Tecnologia</name>
        <name lang="en">Technology</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
