<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="34930" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2010-09-02</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="yes" id="702" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>701</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Generalsekretariat WBF</name>
      <name lang="fr">Secrétariat général DEFR</name>
      <name lang="it">Segreteria generale DEFR</name>
      <name lang="en">Secretariat-General EAER</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="701">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Wirtschaft, Bildung und Forschung</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'économie, de la formation et de la recherche</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'economia, della formazione e della ricerca</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Economic Affairs, Education and Research</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Geburtstagsgeschenk für 50 Jahre EFTA</title>
      <teaser>Seit 50 Jahren ist die Europäische Freihandelsassoziation EFTA für die Schweiz eines der wichtigsten handelspolitischen Instrumente. Im Rahmen der EFTA hat unser Land zusammen mit Liechtenstein, Norwegen und Island 23 Freihandelsabkommen abgeschlossen. Mit einer Briefmarke der Schweizerischen Post wird die Jubilarin geehrt.</teaser>
      <lead>Seit 50 Jahren ist die Europäische Freihandelsassoziation EFTA für die Schweiz eines der wichtigsten handelspolitischen Instrumente. Im Rahmen der EFTA hat unser Land zusammen mit Liechtenstein, Norwegen und Island 23 Freihandelsabkommen abgeschlossen. Mit einer Briefmarke der Schweizerischen Post wird die Jubilarin geehrt.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;„Diese „kleine" EFTA ist der siebtgrösste Güter- und der fünftgrösste Dienstleistungshändler der Welt", stellte Bundespräsidentin Doris Leuthard an der Pressekonferenz am Donnerstag fest, an der auch EFTA-Generalsekretär Kare Bryn und Post-Verwaltungsratspräsident Peter Hasler teilnahmen. Gemeinsam enthüllten sie die EFTA-Briefmarke der Schweizerischen Post, die ab dem 3. September gültig ist und eine grenzübergreifende und verbindende EFTA darstellt. „Erst im Ensemble von mehreren Briefmarken, sprich Handelspartnern, wird die verbindende Funktion in der EFTA offenbart", erklärte der VR-Präsident der Post, Peter Hasler.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Die EFTA mit Hauptsitz in Genf wurde vor 50 Jahren mit dem Ziel gegründet, um das wirtschaftliche Wachstum und den Wohlstand der Mitgliedsländer zu fördern. Mit den Freihandelsabkommen, die insbesondere seit den späten Neunzigerjahren rund um den Globus abgeschlossen werden, verfügen die EFTA-Mitglieder heute über einen erleichterten Zutritt zu Märkten mit rund 600 Millionen Konsumenten ausserhalb der EU. Kare Bryn, seit gut drei Jahren EFTA-Generalsekretär, folgerte denn auch vor den Medien: „Von den Anfängen wirtschaftlicher Zusammenarbeit in Europa bis zum gegenwärtigen weltumfassenden Netz von Freihandelsbeziehungen hat die EFTA einen sehr erfolgreichen Weg zurückgelegt. Wir können stolz sein auf das Erreichte."&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Evelyn Kobelt, Pressesprecherin EVD, Tel. 031 322 20 59</contact>
      <attachment id="73709">
        <title>Briefmarke der Schweizerischen Post</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>213</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/20307.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <link id="73713">
        <title>Medienmitteilung der Schweizerischen Post</title>
        <uri>http://www.post.ch/news</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Cadeau pour les 50 ans de l’AELE</title>
      <teaser>L’Association européenne de libre-échange (AELE) est l’un des principaux instruments de la politique commerciale de la Suisse depuis 50 ans. Nous avons, avec le Liechtenstein, la Norvège et l’Islande, conclu sous sa bannière 23 accords de libre-échange. La Poste Suisse émet un timbre en son honneur.</teaser>
      <lead>L’Association européenne de libre-échange (AELE) est l’un des principaux instruments de la politique commerciale de la Suisse depuis 50 ans. Nous avons, avec le Liechtenstein, la Norvège et l’Islande, conclu sous sa bannière 23 accords de libre-échange. La Poste Suisse émet un timbre en son honneur.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;«&amp;nbsp;Cette 'petite' AELE est septième en termes d'échanges de marchandises dans le monde, et cinquième pour les échanges de services&amp;nbsp;», rappelait la présidente de la Confédération Doris Leuthard lors de la conférence de presse de jeudi, à laquelle étaient également présents Kare Bryn, le secrétaire général de l'AELE, et Peter Hasler, le président du conseil d'administration de la Poste. Ensemble, ils ont dévoilé le timbre «&amp;nbsp;50 ans de l'AELE&amp;nbsp;» de La Poste Suisse, qui sera valable à partir du 3 septembre et représente une AELE transfrontalière et fédératrice. «&amp;nbsp;La fonction unificatrice de l'AELE et la coopération entre ses partenaires commerciaux se visualise au travers de la série de timbres » explique Peter Hasler.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;L'AELE, dont le siège est à Genève, a été créée il y a 50 ans dans le but de promouvoir la croissance économique et la prospérité de ses Etats membres. Grâce aux accords de libre-échange conclus dans le monde entier, pour la plupart depuis la fin des années 90, les membres de l'AELE disposent aujourd'hui d'un accès préférentiel à des marchés qui, ensemble, comptent plus de 600 millions de consommateurs en dehors de l'UE. Kare Bryn, secrétaire général de l'AELE depuis plus de trois ans, résumait ainsi les activités de l'AELE devant les médias&amp;nbsp;: «&amp;nbsp;Des débuts de la collaboration économique en Europe au réseau mondial de relations de libre-échange actuel, l'AELE a cumulé les succès. Nous pouvons être fiers de ce que nous avons accompli.&amp;nbsp;»&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Evelyn Kobelt, porte-parole du DFE, tél. 031 322 20 59</contact>
      <attachment id="73710">
        <title>Timbre de la Poste Suisse</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>213</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/20308.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <link id="73714">
        <title>Communiqué de la Poste Suisse</title>
        <uri>http://www.post.ch/news</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Celebrazione del 50° anniversario dell’AELS</title>
      <teaser>Da 50 anni a questa parte l’Associazione europea di libero scambio (AELS o, dall’inglese, EFTA) costituisce uno dei principali strumenti di politica commerciale della Svizzera. Nell’ambito dell’AELS, insieme a Liechtenstein, Norvegia e Islanda, il nostro Paese ha stipulato finora 23 accordi di libero scambio. Per onorare questa ricorrenza la Posta Svizzera emetterà un francobollo celebrativo.</teaser>
      <lead>Da 50 anni a questa parte l’Associazione europea di libero scambio (AELS o, dall’inglese, EFTA) costituisce uno dei principali strumenti di politica commerciale della Svizzera. Nell’ambito dell’AELS, insieme a Liechtenstein, Norvegia e Islanda, il nostro Paese ha stipulato finora 23 accordi di libero scambio. Per onorare questa ricorrenza la Posta Svizzera emetterà un francobollo celebrativo.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;"Quest'associazione, all'apparenza piccola, rappresenta a livello mondiale il settimo fornitore di beni e il quinto fornitore di servizi" - ha dichiarato giovedì la presidente della Confederazione Doris Leuthard nel corso della conferenza stampa alla quale hanno partecipato anche il segretario generale dell'AELS Kare Bryn e il presidente del Consiglio d'amministrazione della Posta Peter Hasler. Insieme mostreranno al pubblico per la prima volta il francobollo dell'AELS, valido a partire dal 3 settembre, che simboleggia il carattere transfrontaliero e di collegamento di questa associazione. "È proprio in mezzo a tanti diversi francobolli, ovvero a tanti diversi partner commerciali, che emerge la funzione di collegamento dell'AELS", ha spiegato il presidente del CdA della Posta, Peter Hasler.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;L'AELS, con sede a Ginevra, è stata fondata 50 anni fa allo scopo di promuovere la crescita economica e il benessere degli Stati membri. Con gli accordi di libero scambio che sono stati conclusi con Paesi di varie parti del mondo, soprattutto a partire dalla fine degli anni Novanta, i membri dell'AELS possono accedere oggi più facilmente a mercati che contano 600 milioni di consumatori al di fuori dell'UE. Kare Bryn, segretario generale dell'AELS da più di tre anni, ha inoltre dichiarato: "Dagli inizi della cooperazione economica in Europa all'attuale rete mondiale di relazioni di libero scambio, l'AELS ha fatto molta strada e possiamo dirci fieri dei traguardi raggiunti."&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Evelyn Kobelt, portavoce DFE, tel. 031 322 20 59</contact>
      <attachment id="73711">
        <title>Francobollo della Posta Svizzera</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>213</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/20309.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <link id="73715">
        <title>Comunicato della Posta Svizzera</title>
        <uri>http://www.post.ch/news</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Anniversary gift to mark 50 years of EFTA</title>
      <teaser>For fifty years the European Free Trade Association EFTA has been one of Switzerland’s most important trade policy instruments. As part of EFTA our country, together with Liechtenstein, Norway and Iceland, has concluded 23 free trade agreements. A commemorative postage stamp is being issued to mark this jubilee year.</teaser>
      <lead>For fifty years the European Free Trade Association EFTA has been one of Switzerland’s most important trade policy instruments. As part of EFTA our country, together with Liechtenstein, Norway and Iceland, has concluded 23 free trade agreements. A commemorative postage stamp is being issued to mark this jubilee year.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;"This ‘small' EFTA is the world's seventh largest trader in goods and the fifth largest trader in services", noted President Doris Leuthard at the press conference on Thursday, which was also attended by EFTA Secretary-General Kare Bryn and the chairman of the Swiss Post board of directors, Peter Hasler. The commemorative stamp issued by SwissPost was jointly unveiled by all three.. The stamp, which is valid from 3 September, depicts an international and uniting EFTA. "The full unifying function of EFTA, with its trading partners, will be revealed though a series of stamps", explained SwissPost chairman, Peter Hasler.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;EFTA, which has its headquarters in Geneva, was established 50 years ago with the aim of encouraging economic growth and the prosperity of its member states. Today, thanks to the free trade agreements that have been concluded with countries around the world, particularly since the late 1990s, the EFTA member states have facilitated access to markets outside the EU with around 600 million consumers. EFTA Secretary-General Kare Bryn, who has now been in office for a little over three years, asserted that "EFTA has come a long way from its origins of economic cooperation in Europe to today's global network of free trade agreements. We can be proud of what has been achieved."&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Evelyn Kobelt, Press Spokesperson FDEA Tel. 031 322 20 59</contact>
      <attachment id="73712">
        <title>Swiss Post stamp</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>213</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/20310.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <link id="73716">
        <title>Swiss Post Communiqué</title>
        <uri>http://www.post.ch/news</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="33">
        <name lang="de">Bundespräsident/-in</name>
        <name lang="fr">Président/e de la Confédération</name>
        <name lang="it">Presidente della Confederazione</name>
        <name lang="en">President of the Swiss Confederation</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="34">
        <name lang="de">Europa</name>
        <name lang="fr">Europe</name>
        <name lang="it">Europa</name>
        <name lang="en">Europe</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="47">
        <name lang="de">Wirtschaft</name>
        <name lang="fr">Économie</name>
        <name lang="it">Economia</name>
        <name lang="en">Economic Affairs</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="48">
        <name lang="de">Zoll</name>
        <name lang="fr">Douanes</name>
        <name lang="it">Dogane</name>
        <name lang="en">Customs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
