<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="47586" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2013-01-29</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="yes" id="1060" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>601</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Staatssekretariat für internationale Finanzfragen</name>
      <name lang="fr">Secrétariat d'Etat aux questions financières internationales</name>
      <name lang="it">Segreteria di Stato per le questioni finanziarie internazionali</name>
      <name lang="en">State Secretariat for International Financial Matters</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.sif.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.sif.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.sif.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.sif.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@sif.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@sif.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@sif.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@sif.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="601">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Finanzdepartement</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des finances</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale delle finanze</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Finance</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.efd.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.dff.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.efd.admin.ch/efd/it/home.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.efd.admin.ch/efd/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Das Financial Stability Board (FSB) stärkt seine Bindung zur Schweiz</title>
      <lead>Das Financial Stability Board (FSB), ein zentrales Gremium für Fragen zur internationalen Finanzmarktregulierung und –aufsicht, hat sich gestern im Rahmen seiner Plenarversammlung als Verein mit Sitz in Basel statuiert. Damit bekräftigt das FSB seine Verankerung in der Schweiz.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Das FSB hat im Nachgang der Finanzkrise zunehmend an Bedeutung als Koordinator internationaler Finanzmarktregulierung gewonnen. Im November 2011 haben die Staats- und Regierungschefs der G20 beschlossen, das FSB in eine Institution mit eigener Rechtspersönlichkeit zu überführen. Dieser Schritt ermöglicht es dem Gremium, geeignete Strukturen und Abläufe aufzubauen und finanziell autonomer zu sein. Die Schweiz hat sich dafür eingesetzt, dass das FSB seinen Sitz in Basel behält.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Die Organisationsstruktur des FSB wird keine Änderung erfahren. Administrativ bleibt das FSB bei der Bank für Internationalen Zahlungsausgleich (BIZ) angesiedelt. Die Interessen der Schweiz im FSB nehmen das Eidgenössische Finanzdepartement (EFD) und die Schweizerische Nationalbank (SNB) wahr. Die Finanzmarktaufsicht (FINMA) unterstützt die Arbeiten durch Einsitznahme in diversen Arbeitsgruppen.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Das FSB ist zuständig für Fragen der internationalen Finanzstabilität und Finanzmarktregulierung. Es treibt - oft basierend auf einem Mandat der G20 - internationale Finanzmarktreformen voran, beispielsweise auf dem Gebiet systemrelevanter Finanzinstitute, der Derivatemärkte oder der Schattenbanken und überwacht die nationale Implementierung. Zu seinen Mitgliedern zählen 54 Behörden aus 24 Ländern (Länder der G20, Schweiz, Niederlande, Spanien, Singapur und Hong Kong) und 10 internationale Organisationen und Standardsetzungsgremien. &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Anne Césard, Kommunikation SIF + 41 31 322 62 91, anne.cesard@sif.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="105877">
        <title>FSB press release</title>
        <uri>http://www.financialstabilityboard.org/press/pr_130128.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Le Conseil de stabilité financière renforce ses liens avec la Suisse</title>
      <lead>Hier, à l'occasion de son assemblée plénière, le Conseil de stabilité financière (CSF) s'est constitué en tant qu'association avec siège à Bâle. Organe central chargé de la réglementation et de la surveillance des marchés financiers au niveau international, le CSF renforce ainsi son ancrage en Suisse.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Suite à la crise financière, le Conseil de stabilité financière (CSF) a pris une importance croissante en tant que coordinateur des travaux concernant la réglementation internationale des marchés financiers. En novembre 2011, les chefs d'Etat et de gouvernement du G20 ont décidé de transformer le CSF en une institution possédant sa propre personnalité juridique. Cette décision permet à cet organe de se doter de structures et de processus adaptés, tout en bénéficiant d'une plus grande autonomie financière. La Suisse s'est engagée dans ce cadre pour que le siège du CSF demeure à Bâle. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;La structure organisationnelle du CSF ne subira pas de modification. Du point de vue administratif, le CSF demeure rattaché à la Banque des règlements internationaux (BRI). Quant aux intérêts de la Suisse, ils sont représentés au sein du CSF par le Département fédéral des finances (DFF) et la Banque nationale suisse (BNS). L'Autorité fédérale de surveillance des marchés financiers (FINMA) participe également aux travaux du CSF dans le cadre de divers groupes de travail. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Le CSF est chargé des questions relevant de la stabilité financière et de la réglementation des marchés financiers au niveau international. Souvent mandaté par le G20, il soutient les réformes internationales touchant les marchés financiers, par exemple dans le domaine des établissements financiers d'importance systémique, des marchés de dérivés ou du système bancaire parallèle («&lt;i&gt;shadow banking&lt;/i&gt;»), tout en surveillant la mise en œuvre de ces réformes dans les différents pays. Parmi ses membres, on trouve 54 autorités de 24 pays (membres du G20, Suisse, Pays-Bas, Espagne, Singapour et Hong Kong) ainsi que 10 organisations internationales et organismes chargés de fixer des normes. &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Anne Césard, Communication SFI, + 41 31 322 62 91, anne.cesard@sif.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="105877">
        <title>FSB press release</title>
        <uri>http://www.financialstabilityboard.org/press/pr_130128.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Il Financial Stability Board (FSB) rafforza il proprio legame con la Svizzera</title>
      <lead>Nel quadro della propria assemblea plenaria, il Financial Stability Board (FSB) – un organismo centrale per le questioni inerenti alla regolamentazione e alla vigilanza dei mercati finanziari – si è costituito ieri sotto forma di associazione con sede a Basilea. In questo modo, il FSB rafforza la propria presenza in Svizzera.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;In seguito alla crisi finanziaria, il FSB ha viepiù assunto importanza quale coordinatore nella regolamentazione internazionale dei mercati finanziari. Nel novembre del 2011 i capi di Stato e di Governo dei Paesi membri del G20 hanno deciso di trasformare il FSB in un'istituzione dotata di personalità giuridica propria. Questo passo ha permesso all'organismo di creare strutture e processi adeguati e di essere autonomo dal punto di vista finanziario. La Svizzera si è adoperata affinché il FSB mantenesse la propria sede a Basilea. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;La struttura organizzativa del FSB non subirà modifiche. Dal punto di vista amministrativo il FSB rimane insediato presso la Banca dei regolamenti internazionali (BRI). Il Dipartimento federale delle finanze (DFF) e la Banca nazionale svizzera (BNS) tutelano gli interessi della Svizzera in seno al FSB. La presenza di rappresentanti in diversi gruppi di lavoro permette all'Autorità federale di vigilanza sui mercati finanziari (FINMA) di sostenerne i lavori.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Il FSB si occupa di questioni concernenti la stabilità finanziaria internazionale e la regolamentazione dei mercati finanziari. Spesso, su mandato del G20, l'organismo promuove riforme internazionali dei mercati finanziari, come ad esempio riguardo agli istituti finanziari di rilevanza sistemica, ai mercati dei derivati o alle banche ombra e ne verifica l'attuazione a livello nazionale. Tra i suoi membri figurano 54 autorità di 24 Paesi (Paesi membri del G20, Svizzera, Paesi Bassi, Spagna, Singapore e Hong Kong) e 10 organizzazioni internazionali e organismi di standardizzazione.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Anne Césard, Comunicazione SFI + 41 31 322 62 91, anne.cesard@sif.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="105877">
        <title>FSB press release</title>
        <uri>http://www.financialstabilityboard.org/press/pr_130128.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Financial Stability Board (FSB) strengthens ties with Switzerland</title>
      <lead>During its plenary meeting yesterday, the Financial Stability Board (FSB), a central body for issues associated with international financial market regulation and supervision, established itself as an association headquartered in Basel, thereby reaffirming its ties with Switzerland.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;In the wake of the financial crisis, the FSB became increasingly important as a coordinator of international financial market regulation. In November 2011, the G20 heads of state and government decided to make the FSB an institution with its own legal personality. This move will enable the body to establish appropriate structures and processes and be more independent financially. Switzerland campaigned for the FSB to keep its headquarters in Basel.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;There will be no changes to the FSB's organisational structure. Administratively, the FSB will remain hosted by the Bank for International Settlements (BIS). The Federal Department of Finance (FDF) and the Swiss National Bank (SNB) represent Switzerland's interests within the FSB. The Swiss Financial Market Supervisory Authority (FINMA) supports this work by participating in various working groups.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The FSB is responsible for international financial stability and financial market regulation. Frequently based on a G20 mandate, it drives international financial market reforms in areas such as systemically important financial institutions, derivatives markets and shadow banks, and monitors national implementation. Its members include 54 authorities from 24 countries (G20 countries, Switzerland, the Netherlands, Spain, Singapore and Hong Kong) and ten international organisations and standard-setting bodies.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Anne Césard, SIF Communications + 41 31 322 62 91, anne.cesard@sif.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="105877">
        <title>FSB press release</title>
        <uri>http://www.financialstabilityboard.org/press/pr_130128.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <keywords>
      <keyword id="118" org-id="1060">
        <name lang="de">Finanzmarktregulierung und -aufsicht</name>
        <name lang="fr">Réglementation et surveillance des marchés financiers</name>
        <name lang="it">Regolamentazione e vigilanza dei mercati finanziari</name>
        <name lang="en">Financial market regulation and supervision</name>
      </keyword>
    </keywords>
    <topics>
      <topic id="35">
        <name lang="de">Finanzplatz</name>
        <name lang="fr">Place financière</name>
        <name lang="it">Piazza finanziaria</name>
        <name lang="en">Financial Centre</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="44">
        <name lang="de">Steuern</name>
        <name lang="fr">Impôts</name>
        <name lang="it">Imposte</name>
        <name lang="en">Taxation</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="47">
        <name lang="de">Wirtschaft</name>
        <name lang="fr">Économie</name>
        <name lang="it">Economia</name>
        <name lang="en">Economic Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
