<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="47761" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2013-02-13</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="1070" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>1070</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Der Bundesrat</name>
      <name lang="fr">Conseil fédéral</name>
      <name lang="it">Il Consiglio federale</name>
      <name lang="en">The Federal Council</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.admin.ch/gov/de/start.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.admin.ch/gov/fr/accueil.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.admin.ch/gov/it/pagina-iniziale.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.admin.ch/gov/en/start.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="yes" id="1080" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>701</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Staatssekretariat für Bildung, Forschung und Innovation</name>
      <name lang="fr">Secrétariat d'Etat à la formation, à la recherche et à l'innovation</name>
      <name lang="it">Segreteria di Stato per la formazione, la ricerca e l'innovazione</name>
      <name lang="en">State Secretariat for Education, Research and Innovation</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.sbfi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.sbfi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.sbfi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.sbfi.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@sbfi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@sbfi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@sbfi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@sbfi.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="1070">
      <name lang="de">Der Bundesrat</name>
      <name lang="fr">Conseil fédéral</name>
      <name lang="it">Il Consiglio federale</name>
      <name lang="en">The Federal Council</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.admin.ch/gov/de/start.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.admin.ch/gov/fr/accueil.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.admin.ch/gov/it/pagina-iniziale.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.admin.ch/gov/en/start.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <department id="701">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Wirtschaft, Bildung und Forschung</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'économie, de la formation et de la recherche</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'economia, della formazione e della ricerca</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Economic Affairs, Education and Research</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Wiederwahl des Empa-Direktors</title>
      <lead>Der Bundesrat hat auf Antrag des ETH-Rats den Direktor der Empa, Gian-Luca Bona, für weitere vier Jahre wiedergewählt. Die zweite Amtszeit beginnt am 1. September 2013.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Unter der Leitung von Gian-Luca Bona hat sich die Empa (Eidg. Materialprüfungs- und Forschungsanstalt) zu einem international führenden Forschungsinstitut für Materialforschung und innovative Technologien entwickelt. Dies wurde u.a. durch eine Analyse der Universität Leiden (NL) bestätigt, welche die Empa in ihren Fachgebieten unter die 25 besten Universitäten weltweit einreiht. Auf dieser Basis bereitet die Empa mit Partnern aus der Industrie Innovationen für den Markt vor. Der Wissens- und Technologietransfer in Wirtschaft und Gesellschaft wird durch zahlreiche Initiativen vorangetrieben; das Netzwerk der Empa umfasst mittlerweile allein in der Schweiz mehr als 500 Partnerfirmen. In Zusammenarbeit mit den beiden ETH, den Schweizer Universitäten und in direkten Kooperationen mit der Schweizer Industrie entwickelt die Empa so genannte Demonstratoren: Mit solchen lassen sich innovative Technologien und Konzepte in die Praxis umsetzen. Aktuelle Beispiele sind das modulare Gebäudelabor für nachhaltiges Bauen „NEST“ sowie „Future Mobility“, eine Demonstrationsplattform für die energieeffiziente und ressourcenschonende Mobilität von morgen.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Gian-Luca Bona studierte Physik an der ETH Zürich, wo er 1987 promovierte. Nach seinem Wechsel zum IT- und Beratungsunternehmen IBM arbeitete er in verschiedenen Bereichen in der Forschung und Entwicklung, sowohl in der Schweiz als auch in den USA. 2009 trat er seine Stelle als Direktor der Empa an und wurde in dieser Funktion auch zum Professor für Photonik an der ETH Zürich und an der EPFL ernannt. Gian-Luca Bona ist Mitglied in verschiedenen Gremien für Wissens- und Technologietransfer u. a. bei der Kommission für Technologie und Innovation, im Technopark Zürich und im Förderzentrum für Jungunternehmen und Innovationsprozesse glaTec.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Rudolf Christen, Informationschef WBF Tel. 031 322 39 60 Markus Bernhard, Leiter Kommunikation ETH-Rat Tel. 044 632 20 03</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Le directeur de l’Empa est reconduit dans ses fonctions</title>
      <lead>Sur proposition du Conseil des EPF, le Conseil fédéral a confirmé Gian-Luca Bona dans ses fonctions de directeur de l’Empa pour un second mandat de quatre ans, qui débutera le 1er septembre 2013.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Sous la direction de Gian-Luca Bona, l’Empa (Laboratoire fédéral d’essai des matériaux et de recherche) a acquis une renommée internationale en tant que leader de la recherche sur les matériaux et les technologies innovantes. Une analyse réalisée par l’Université de Leyde (Pays-Bas) confirme notamment que l’Empa rivalise avec les 25 meilleures universités du monde dans ses domaines de spécialisation. Dans ce contexte, l’Empa développe des innovations adaptées au marché avec l’aide de partenaires industriels. Une multitude d’initiatives permettent d’encourager le transfert de savoir et de technologie dans l’économie et la société; le réseau de l’Empa compte désormais plus de 500 entreprises associées rien qu’en Suisse. En collaboration avec les deux écoles polytechniques fédérales (EPF) et les universités suisses, ainsi que dans le cadre de coopérations directes avec des partenaires industriels suisses, l’Empa met au point des installations de démonstration permettant de transposer dans la pratique des technologies et des concepts novateurs. Il s’agit par exemple de «NEST», un laboratoire modulaire dédié à la construction durable, ou encore de «Future Mobility», une plate-forme de démonstration consacrée à la mobilité efficiente et écologique de demain.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Gian-Luca Bona a suivi des études de physique à l’ETH Zurich et y a passé son doctorat en 1987. Engagé par la société IBM, spécialisée dans l’informatique et le conseil, il a travaillé dans différents secteurs liés à la recherche et au déve­lop­pement, tant en Suisse qu’aux Etats-Unis. Il est devenu directeur de l’Empa en 2009. A ce poste, il a également été nommé professeur de photonique à l’ETH Zurich et à l’EPFL. Gian-Luca Bona est membre de plusieurs comités qui se consacrent au transfert de savoir et de technologie, notamment auprès de la Commission pour la technologie et l’innovation, du Technopark Zurich et du centre technologique glaTec qui encourage les créations d’entreprises et les processus innovants.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Rudolf Christen, chef de l’Information du DEFR tél. 031 322 39 60 Markus Bernhard, Responsable communication Conseil des EPF, Tel. 044 632 20 03</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Nuovo mandato per il direttore dell’Empa</title>
      <lead>Su proposta del Consiglio dei Politecnici federali il Consiglio federale ha riconfermato per altri quattro anni Gian-Luca Bona alla carica di direttore dell’Empa. Il suo secondo mandato inizia il 1° settembre 2013.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;b&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sotto la direzione di Gian-Luca Bona, il Laboratorio federale di prova dei materiali e di ricerca (Empa) è diventato un istituto rinomato a livello internazionale per quanto riguarda la ricerca sui materiali e le tecnologie innovative. Anche uno studio realizzato dall’Università di Leiden, in Olanda, ha inserito l’Empa fra le 25 migliori università al mondo nei suoi ambiti specialistici. Su tali basi, l’Empa prepara innovazioni per il mercato insieme a partner del settore industriale. Le iniziative che incentivano il trasferimento di conoscenze e tecnologia nell’economia e nella società sono numerose; nella sola Svizzera la rete dell’Empa conta oltre 500 imprese partner. In collaborazione con entrambi i Politecnici federali, le università svizzere, e nel contesto di una cooperazione diretta con l’industria svizzera, l’Empa sviluppa dunque impianti di dimostrazione per realizzare sul piano pratico le tecnologie e le idee innovative. Ne sono un esempio «NEST», l’edificio modulare di ricerca per l’edilizia sostenibile, così come «Future Mobility», una piattaforma di dimostrazioni atta a sviluppare la mobilità del futuro nel rispetto dell’efficienza energetica e delle risorse naturali.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Gian-Luca Bona ha studiato fisica al PF di Zurigo, dove ha conseguito il dottorato nel 1987. Dopo aver collaborato con l’azienda di consulenza e servizi informatici IBM, ha lavorato in diversi settori di ricerca e sviluppo sia in Svizzera che negli Stati Uniti. Nel 2009 ha assunto l’incarico di direttore dell’Empa e in questa funzione è stato nominato anche professore di fotonica presso i PF di Zurigo e di Losanna. Gian-Luca Bona è membro di diversi organismi del settore del trasferimento della tecnologia e delle conoscenze, ad esempio presso la Commissione per la tecnologia e l’innovazione, presso Technopark Zurigo e nel centro di ricerca per imprese giovani e processi innovativi glaTec.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Rudolf Christen, capo dell’informazione DEFR, tel. 031 322 39 60 Markus Bernhard, Responsabile comunicazione Consiglio dei PF, tel. 044 632 20 03</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Reappointment of the Empa Director</title>
      <lead>On application of the ETH Board, the Federal Council has reappointed the Director of Empa, Gian-Luca Bona, for another four years. The second term of office will start on 1 September 2013.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;b&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;p&gt;Under Gian-Luca Bona’s leadership, Empa (Swiss Federal Laboratories for Materials Testing and Research) has developed into an internationally leading research institute for materials research and innovative technologies. This has been confirmed by, among other things, an analysis conducted by Leiden University (Netherlands), which places Empa among the world’s 25 best universities in its specialist fields. On this basis, Empa prepares innovations for the market with industrial partners. The transfer of knowledge and technology in trade and industry and in society is driven forward by numerous initiatives; by now, Empa’s network extends to more than 500 partner firms in Switzerland alone. In cooperation with ETH Zurich and EPFL, with the Swiss universities, and in direct contact cooperation ventures with Swiss industry, Empa develops so-called demonstrators, which serve to translate innovative technologies and concepts into practice. Current examples include the modular building laboratory for sustainable construction, NEST, as well as Future Mobility, a demonstration platform for tomorrow’s energy-efficient and resource-conserving mobility.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Gian-Luca Bona studied physics at ETH Zurich, where he obtained his doctor’s degree in 1987. After joining the IT and consultancy firm, IBM, he worked in various fields in research and development, both in Switzerland and in the US. In 2009, he took up the post of Director of Empa, and in this capacity was also appointed Professor of Photonics at ETH Zurich and at EPFL. Gian-Luca Bona is a member of various bodies involved in knowledge and technology transfer, such as the Commission for Technology and Innovation, in Technopark Zurich and in the support centre for start-ups and innovation processes, glaTec.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Rudolf Christen, Head of Information EAER tel. 031 322 39 60 Markus Bernhard, Head of Communications ETH Board, tel. 044 632 20 03</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <keywords>
      <keyword id="325.11" org-id="1080">
        <name lang="de">Eidgenössische Technische Hochschule ETH</name>
        <name lang="fr">Ecole polytechnique fédérale EPF</name>
        <name lang="it">Politecnico federale</name>
        <name lang="en">Federal Institutes of Technology</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="325.10" org-id="1080">
        <name lang="de">Wissenschaft</name>
        <name lang="fr">Science</name>
        <name lang="it">Scienza</name>
        <name lang="en">Science</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="325.21" org-id="1080">
        <name lang="de">Wissenschaftsaussenpolitik</name>
        <name lang="fr">Politique scientifique extérieure</name>
        <name lang="it">Politica scientifica dell'esterno</name>
        <name lang="en">Foreign scientific policy</name>
      </keyword>
    </keywords>
    <topics>
      <topic id="5">
        <name lang="de">Behörden</name>
        <name lang="fr">Autorités</name>
        <name lang="it">Autorità</name>
        <name lang="en">Authorities</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="8">
        <name lang="de">Bildung und Forschung</name>
        <name lang="fr">Formation et recherche</name>
        <name lang="it">Formazione e ricerca</name>
        <name lang="en">Education and Research</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="10">
        <name lang="de">Bundesrat</name>
        <name lang="fr">Conseil fédéral</name>
        <name lang="it">Consiglio federale</name>
        <name lang="en">Federal Council</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="32">
        <name lang="de">Bundespersonal</name>
        <name lang="fr">Personnel de la Confédération</name>
        <name lang="it">Personale della Confederazione</name>
        <name lang="en">Government Employees</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="47">
        <name lang="de">Wirtschaft</name>
        <name lang="fr">Économie</name>
        <name lang="it">Economia</name>
        <name lang="en">Economic Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
