<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="47765" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2013-02-13</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="1070" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>1070</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Der Bundesrat</name>
      <name lang="fr">Conseil fédéral</name>
      <name lang="it">Il Consiglio federale</name>
      <name lang="en">The Federal Council</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.admin.ch/gov/de/start.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.admin.ch/gov/fr/accueil.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.admin.ch/gov/it/pagina-iniziale.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.admin.ch/gov/en/start.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="201" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>201</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="1070">
      <name lang="de">Der Bundesrat</name>
      <name lang="fr">Conseil fédéral</name>
      <name lang="it">Il Consiglio federale</name>
      <name lang="en">The Federal Council</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.admin.ch/gov/de/start.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.admin.ch/gov/fr/accueil.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.admin.ch/gov/it/pagina-iniziale.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.admin.ch/gov/en/start.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <department id="201">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Neuer rechtlicher Status für die Generaldelegation Palästinas in Bern</title>
      <lead>Die UNO-Generalversammlung hat mit der Resolution vom 29. November 2012 dem Nicht-Mitgliedstaat Palästina den Beobachterstatus zuerkannt. Als Folge hat der Bundesrat beschlossen, den rechtlichen Status der Generaldelegation Palästinas in Bern anzupassen. </lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Für die Generaldelegation und ihr Personal kommt künftig das Wiener Übereinkommen vom 18. April 1961 über diplomatische Beziehungen sinngemäss zur Anwendung. Sie erhält damit denselben rechtlichen Status wie die Ständige Beobachtermission Palästinas in Genf, deren Status von der UNO nach der Annahme der Resolution geändert worden war. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Für die beiden Mitglieder der Ständigen Mission in Genf, die auch Funktionen in der Generaldelegation Palästinas in Bern wahrnehmen, gilt somit für beide Funktionen derselbe Status, was eine beträchtliche technische und administrative Vereinfachung bedeutet.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Für Rückfragen:&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;Jean-Marc Crevoisier&lt;br /&gt;Chef Information EDA&lt;br /&gt;+41 (0)79 763 84 10&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Information EDA +41(31) 322 31 53</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Modification du statut juridique de la Délégation générale de Palestine à Berne</title>
      <lead>Suite à la résolution du 29 novembre 2012 de l’Assemblée générale des Nations Unies qui a accordé à la Palestine le statut d’Etat non membre observateur auprès de l’ONU, le Conseil fédéral a décidé d’adapter le statut juridique de la Délégation générale de Palestine à Berne. </lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;La Délégation générale de Palestine à Berne ainsi que les membres de son personnel se verront appliquer par analogie la Convention de Vienne du 18 avril 1961 sur les relations diplomatiques. Elle bénéficiera ainsi du même régime juridique que la Mission permanente d’observation de la Palestine à Genève dont le statut a été modifié par l’ONU suite à l’adoption de la résolution. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Cette décision permet aux deux membres de la mission permanente à Genève qui occupent également des fonctions au sein de la Délégation générale de Palestine à Berne de bénéficier d’un statut identique dans ces deux fonctions, ce qui représente une simplification notable au plan technique et administratif.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Renseignements:&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;Jean-Marc Crevoisier&lt;br /&gt;Chef Information DFAE&lt;br /&gt;079 763 84 10&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Information DFAE +41(31) 322 31 53</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Modifica dello statuto giuridico della Delegazione generale palestinese a Berna</title>
      <lead>Dando seguito alla risoluzione dell’Assemblea generale dell’ONU del 29 novembre 2012, che ha accordato alla Palestina lo statuto di Paese osservatore non membro, il Consiglio federale ha deciso di adattare lo statuto giuridico della Delegazione generale palestinese a Berna. </lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;La Delegazione generale così come tutto il suo personale, sarà assoggettata per analogia alla Convenzione di Vienna del 18 aprile 1961 sulle relazioni diplomatiche e beneficerà dello stesso regime giuridico della Missione permanente di osservazione della Palestina a Ginevra, il cui statuto è stato modificato dall’ONU dopo l’adozione della risoluzione. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Questa decisione permette ai due membri della commissione permanente a Ginevra, che svolgono funzioni in seno alla Delegazione generale palestinese a Berna di beneficiare dello stesso statuto giuridico nello svolgimento di queste due funzioni, una notevole semplificazione sul piano tecnico e amministrativo.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Informazioni: &lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;Jean-Marc Crevoisier&lt;br /&gt;Capo Informazione DFAE &lt;br /&gt;079 763 84 10&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Informazione DFAE +41(31) 322 31 53</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Modification to the legal status of the General Delegation of Palestine in Bern</title>
      <lead>Following the adoption of the resolution on 29 November 2012 of the United Nations General Assembly which grants Palestine non-member observer State status at UN, the Federal Council has accordingly decided to adapt the legal status of the General Delegation of Palestine in Bern. </lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;The General Delegation and the members of its personnel will by analogy be subject to the Convention of Vienna of 18 April 1961 on diplomatic relations. The General Delegation and its staff will therefore benefit from the same legal regime as the Permanent Observer Mission of the State of Palestine to the United Nations Office in Geneva whose status was modified by the UN following the adoption of the resolution. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This decision permits the two members of the Permanent Observer Mission in Geneva who also carry out functions at the General Delegation of Palestine in Bern to enjoy identical status in these two functions. The change brings with it a significant simplification at the technical and administrative levels.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Further information: &lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;Jean-Marc Crevoisier&lt;br /&gt;Head of FDFA Information &lt;br /&gt;079 763 84 10&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Information FDFA +41(31) 322 31 53</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
