<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="48224" revoked="no">
    <version>3</version>
    <pubdate>2013-03-21</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="201" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>201</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="201">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Die DEZA lanciert ein neues Kooperationsprogramm in Kambodscha</title>
      <lead>Die DEZA eröffnet am Donnerstag, 21. März 2013, in Phnom Penh ein neues Kooperationsbüro. Mit dieser Eröffnung wird das neue Kooperationsprogramm der Schweiz in Kambodscha offiziell lanciert. Das Programm konzentriert sich auf die Bereiche Landwirtschaft und Ernährungssicherheit, lokale Gouvernanz und Bürgerpartizipation sowie Beschäftigung und Berufsbildung. Das Engagement erfolgt im Rahmen der neuen Kooperationsstrategie für die Mekong-Region 2013–2017.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Kambodscha wurde in der Botschaft zur internationalen Zusammenarbeit der Schweiz, die 2012 vom Parlament verabschiedet wurde, als neues Tätigkeitsgebiet der Direktion für Entwicklung und Zusammenarbeit (DEZA) definiert. Es ist immer noch eines der ärmsten Länder in Asien. Ungefähr ein Drittel der etwa 14.5 Millionen Einwohnerinnen und Einwohner leben unter der Armutsschwelle. Die Ernährungsunsicherheit ist ein ständiges Problem. 80% der Bevölkerung leben auf dem Land und betreiben im Wesentlichen Subsistenzlandwirtschaft. Diese Menschen profitieren kaum vom Wirtschaftswachstum. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mit dem neuen Programm in Kambodscha, wo die DEZA schon bisher Beiträge an Schweizer Nichtregierungsorganisationen (NGO) leistete, engagiert sich die Schweiz in einem Land, das durch fast vierzig Jahre Unsicherheit und innere Konflikte geprägt ist. Trotz der laufenden Reformen und der Fortschritte, die erzielt werden konnten, sind die Herausforderungen in den Bereichen Armutsbekämpfung, Verbesserung des Gesundheits- und Bildungssystems sowie Rechtsstaatlichkeit immer noch gross. Die Schweizer Zusammenarbeit wird sich auf drei Schwerpunkte konzentrieren: lokale Gouvernanz, Berufsbildung sowie Förderung der Landwirtschaft und Verringerung der Ernährungsunsicherheit. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Die DEZA wird zudem weiterhin mit einem Beitrag an die Kantha-Bopha-Spitäler von Dr. Richner den Gesundheitsbereich unterstützen, um kambodschanischen Kindern kostenlos eine qualitativ hochstehende medizinische Versorgung zu bieten und das kambodschanische Ausbildungssystem für Pflegepersonal zu fördern. Zu diesem Beitrag der Schweiz in der Höhe von 4 Millionen Franken kommen jährlich 10 bis 12 Millionen Franken hinzu, die die Schweizer Zusammenarbeit in den nächsten Jahren in Kambodscha investieren will. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Das neue Programm der DEZA in Kambodscha wird im Rahmen der Aktivitäten der Schweizer Zusammenarbeit in der Mekong-Region durchgeführt. Die neue Kooperationsstrategie für die Mekong-Region 2013–2017 umfasst neben Kambodscha auch Laos und Vietnam, zwei Länder, in denen die DEZA seit vielen Jahren tätig ist. Bei ihrer Tätigkeit in der Region konzentriert sie sich auf die Armen und Benachteiligten in ländlichen Gebieten, um Armut und Ungleichheiten zu bekämpfen und zum sozialen Frieden und zur Stabilität der ganzen Region beizutragen. &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Kommunikation EDA Bundeshaus West CH-3003 Bern Tel. Kommunikationsservice: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Medienstelle: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <link id="108020">
        <title>Aktivitäten der DEZA in der Mekong-Region</title>
        <uri>http://www.deza.admin.ch/de/Home/Laender/Suedostasien/Mekong_Vietnam_Laos_Kambodscha_Myanmar</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="108021">
        <title>Bilaterale Beziehungen Schweiz – Kambodscha</title>
        <uri>http://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home/reps/asia/vkhm/bilkab.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="108022">
        <title>Engagement der DEZA in Kambodscha</title>
        <uri>http://www.deza.admin.ch/de/Home/Aktuell/News_Detailansicht?itemID=220208</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="108023">
        <title>Projektbeispiel im Bereich Governanz in Kambodscha</title>
        <uri>http://www.deza.admin.ch/de/Home/Projekte/Ausgewaehlte_Projekte/Demokratisierungsprozess_in_Kambodscha</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions>
        <revision date="2013-03-21 12:52" type="R"/>
        <revision date="2013-03-22 16:09" type="R"/>
      </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>La DDC lance un nouveau programme de coopération au Cambodge</title>
      <lead>La DDC ouvre un nouveau bureau de coopération ce jeudi 21 mars 2013 à Phnom Penh. Cette inauguration marque le lancement officiel d’un nouveau programme de la coopération suisse dans ce pays. Ce programme porte sur l’agriculture et la sécurité alimentaire, la gouvernance locale et la participation citoyenne, ainsi que sur l’emploi et la formation professionnelle. Cet engagement s’inscrit dans le cadre de la nouvelle Stratégie de coopération régionale au Mékong 2013-2017.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Proposé comme nouveau pays de coopération de la Direction du développement et de la coopération (DDC) dans le Message concernant la coopération internationale de la Suisse, approuvé par le Parlement en 2012, le Cambodge reste l’un des pays les plus pauvres d’Asie. Environ un tiers de ses quelque 14,5 millions d’habitants vivent sous le seuil de pauvreté. L’insécurité alimentaire y est un problème constant et les effets de la croissance économique se font peu ressentir auprès de la population rurale, laquelle représente 80% de la population et dépend essentiellement d’une agriculture de subsistance.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Avec son nouveau programme au Cambodge – où elle était présente jusqu’ici avec des contributions versées à des programmes d’ONG suisses actives sur place - la DDC s’engage dans un pays marqué par presque quarante années d’insécurité et de conflits internes. Malgré les réformes en cours et les progrès réalisés, les défis y sont encore importants en matière de réduction de la pauvreté, d’amélioration des systèmes de santé et d’éducation, ainsi que d’Etat de droit. La coopération suisse axera son travail sur trois priorités: la gouvernance locale, la formation professionnelle ainsi que le développement du secteur agricole et la réduction de l’insécurité alimentaire. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;La DDC continuera par ailleurs à soutenir le secteur de la santé via la contribution aux hôpitaux de Kantha Bopha du Dr. Richner, dont l’objectif est d’apporter aux enfants cambodgiens des soins de santé de qualité et gratuits et de contribuer au système cambodgien de formation du personnel soignant. Cette contribution de la Suisse de 4 millions CHF par an vient s’ajouter aux 10 à 12 millions CHF par an que la coopération suisse prévoit d‘engager au Cambodge ces prochaines années.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Le nouveau programme de la DDC au Cambodge s’inscrit dans le cadre des activités de la coopération suisse dans la zone Mékong. Faisant l’objet d’une nouvelle Stratégie de coopération régionale 2013-2017, celle-ci comprend en plus du Cambodge, le Laos et le Vietnam, deux pays dans lesquels la DDC est active depuis de nombreuses années. Son travail dans cette région se concentre principalement sur les populations pauvres et défavorisées des zones rurales, dans le but de réduire la pauvreté et les inégalités. L’engagement de la Suisse a pour objectif de contribuer à la paix sociale et à la stabilité dans l’ensemble de cette région. &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Communication DFAE Palais fédéral ouest CH-3003 Berne Tél. Service de communication: +41 58 462 31 53 Tél. Service de presse: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <link id="108024">
        <title>Activités de la DDC dans la région du Mékong</title>
        <uri>http://www.deza.admin.ch/fr/Accueil/Pays/Asie_du_Sud_Est/Mekong_Vietnam_Laos_Cambodge_Myanmar</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="108025">
        <title>Relations bilatérales Suisse-Cambodge</title>
        <uri>http://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/home/reps/asia/vkhm/bilkab.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="108026">
        <title>Engagement de la DDC au Cambodge</title>
        <uri>http://www.deza.admin.ch/fr/Home/Aktuell/News_Detailansicht?itemID=220208</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="108027">
        <title>Exemple d’un projet dans le domaine de la gouvernance au Cambodge</title>
        <uri>http://www.deza.admin.ch/fr/Accueil/Projets/Exemples_de_projets/Processus_de_democratisation_au_Cambodge</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions>
        <revision date="2013-03-22 16:09" type="R"/>
      </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>La DSC lancia un nuovo programma di cooperazione in Cambogia</title>
      <lead>Giovedì 21 marzo 2013, la DSC apre un nuovo ufficio di cooperazione a Phnom Penh. L’inaugurazione segna il lancio ufficiale di un nuovo programma della cooperazione svizzera in Cambogia. I temi toccati sono l’agricoltura e la sicurezza alimentare, la governance locale e la partecipazione civile, l’impiego e la formazione professionale. L’impegno si inserisce nel quadro della nuova Strategia di cooperazione regionale nel Mekong 2013-2017.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;La Cambogia, proposta come nuovo Paese di cooperazione della Direzione dello sviluppo e della cooperazione (DSC) nel Messaggio concernente la cooperazione internazionale della Svizzera approvato dal Parlamento nel 2012, rimane uno degli Stati più poveri in Asia. Circa un terzo per cento dei 14,5 milioni di abitanti vive sotto la soglia di povertà. L’insicurezza alimentare è un problema costante e la popolazione rurale, che rappresenta l’80 per cento di tutta la popolazione e vive per lo più di agricoltura di sussistenza, è poco toccata dagli effetti della crescita economica.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Con il suo nuovo programma in Cambogia, dove finora cofinanziava programmi di ONG svizzere attive sul posto, la DSC s'impegna in un Paese segnato da quasi quarant’anni di insicurezza e conflitti interni. Nonostante le riforme in corso e i progressi compiuti, le sfide da affrontare sono ancora importanti in materia di riduzione della povertà, di miglioramento dei sistemi di salute e di educazione e di Stato di diritto. L’operato della cooperazione svizzera sarà incentrato su tre priorità: la governance locale, la formazione professionale e lo sviluppo del settore agricolo con riduzione dell’insicurezza alimentare. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;La DSC continuerà inoltre a sostenere il settore sanitario con il contributo agli ospedali di Kantha Bopha del dott. Richner, il cui obiettivo consiste nell'assicurare all’infanzia cambogiana cure gratuite di buona qualità e nel sostenere il sistema cambogiano di formazione del personale curante. A questo contributo annuale di 4 milioni di franchi si aggiungono 10-12 milioni di franchi l’anno che la cooperazione svizzera intende destinare alla Cambogia nei prossimi anni.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Il nuovo programma della DSC in Cambogia si inserisce nel quadro delle attività della cooperazione svizzera nella regione del Mekong, che rientra in una nuova Strategia di cooperazione regionale 2013-2017 riguardante, oltre alla Cambogia, anche il Laos e il Vietnam, due Paesi nei quali la DSC è attiva da parecchi anni. L’operato si focalizza soprattutto sulle popolazioni povere e sfavorite delle aree rurali allo scopo di ridurre la povertà e le disparità. L’impegno della Svizzera mira a contribuire alla pace sociale e alla stabilità in tutta la regione. &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Comunicazione DFAE Palazzo federale ovest CH-3003 Berna Tel. Servizio di comunicazione: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Servizio stampa: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <link id="108028">
        <title>Attività della DSC nella regione del Mekong</title>
        <uri>http://www.deza.admin.ch/it/Pagina_iniziale/Paesi/Sud_Est_asiatico/Mekong_Vietnam_Laos_Cambodge_Myanmar</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="108029">
        <title>Relazioni bilaterali Svizzera - Cambogia</title>
        <uri>http://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/home/reps/asia/vkhm/bilkab.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="108030">
        <title>Impegno della SDC in Cambogia</title>
        <uri>http://www.deza.admin.ch/it/Pagina_iniziale/Novita/News_dettagli?itemID=220208</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="108031">
        <title>Esempio di progetto sul tema della governance locale in Cambogia</title>
        <uri>http://www.deza.admin.ch/it/Pagina_iniziale/Progetti/Progetti_selezionati/Processo_di_democratizzazione_in_Cambogia</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions>
        <revision date="2013-03-22 16:09" type="R"/>
      </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>The SDC launches a new cooperation programme in Cambodia</title>
      <lead>The SDC opens a new cooperation office on Thursday 21 March 2013 in Phnom Penh. This inauguration marks the official launch of a new Swiss cooperation programme in Cambodia focusing on agriculture and food security, local government and citizens’ participation, and job creation and professional training. This engagement is part of Switzerland’s new regional cooperation strategy for the Mekong region in the period 2013-2017.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;As one of the poorest countries in Asia, Cambodia has been proposed as a new priority country of the Swiss Agency for Development and Cooperation (SDC) in the Federal Council’s Dispatch to Parliament on Switzerland’s international cooperation, which Parliament approved in 2012. About one third of Cambodia’s approximately 14.5 million inhabitants are living below the poverty line. Food insecurity is a constant problem and the effects of economic growth are hardly felt in rural areas where 80% of the country’s population lives, depending essentially on subsistence agriculture.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;With its new programme in Cambodia, Switzerland commits itself to a country that has been marked by almost 40 years of insecurity and internal conflict. Up to now, it has been present in Cambodia through contributions to programmes of Swiss NGOs working in the country. In spite of the reforms under way and progress made to date, there are still major challenges to meet in reducing poverty, improving the health and education systems, and the rule of law. Swiss cooperation efforts will focus on the following three priority areas: local government, professional training, developing the agricultural sector and reducing food insecurity. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, the SDC will continue to support the health sector through its contribution to the Kantha Bopha Hospitals of Dr Beat Richner, whose aim is to provide Cambodian children with high-quality health care free of charge and to contribute to the Cambodian system for training health care personnel. Switzerland’s annual contribution of CHF 4 million is in addition to the CHF 10 to 12 million per year that Swiss international cooperation plans to commit to Cambodia in the coming years.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The new SDC programme in Cambodia is part of Switzerland’s international cooperation activities in the Mekong region and is the object of a new regional cooperation strategy for 2013-2017. The strategy also covers Laos and Vietnam, two countries where the SDC has been active for some years. Its work in this region targets poor and disadvantaged rural populations with the aim of reducing poverty and inequalities. Switzerland’s commitment is intended to contribute to social harmony and stability in the whole region. &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>FDFA Communication Federal Palace West Wing CH-3003 Bern, Switzerland Tel. Communication service: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Press service: +41 58 460 55 55 E-mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @SwissMFA</contact>
      <link id="108032">
        <title>The SDC’s activities in the Mekong region</title>
        <uri>http://www.deza.admin.ch/en/Home/Countries/Southeast_Asia/Mekong_Vietnam_Laos_Cambodia_Myanmar</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="108033">
        <title>Bilateral relations between Switzerland and Cambodia</title>
        <uri>http://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home/reps/asia/vkhm/bilkab.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="108034">
        <title>The SDC’s commitment in Cambodia</title>
        <uri>http://www.deza.admin.ch/en/Home/News/Close_up?itemID=220208</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="108035">
        <title>Example of a project in the domain of local governance in Cambodia</title>
        <uri>http://www.deza.admin.ch/en/Home/Projects/Selected_projects/Democracy_building_in_Cambodia</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions>
        <revision date="2013-03-22 16:09" type="R"/>
      </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
