<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="49067" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2013-05-31</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="201" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>201</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="201">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Offizieller Arbeitsbesuch des tschechischen Aussenministers Karel Schwarzenberg</title>
      <lead>Bundesrat Didier Burkhalter, Vorsteher des Eidgenössischen Departements für auswärtige Angelegenheiten (EDA), hat am 31. Mai 2013 den tschechischen Aussenminister Karel Schwarzenberg zu einem offiziellen Arbeitsbesuch in Bern empfangen. Gesprächsthemen waren die Europapolitik der Schweiz, die Nachbarschaftspolitik der Tschechischen Republik, der Schweizer Beitrag an die Erweiterung der Europäischen Union und die Wirtschaftsbeziehungen zwischen den beiden Ländern. </lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Die Beziehungen zwischen der Schweiz und Tschechien sind ausgezeichnet und wurden in den letzten Jahren stetig ausgebaut. Das Treffen vom 31. Mai 2013 zwischen Bundesrat Didier Burkhalter und seinem tschechischen Amtskollegen Karel Schwarzenberg ist Ausdruck dieser Intensivierung der bilateralen Beziehungen. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Die beiden Aussenminister besprachen die Europapolitik der Schweiz und die Nachbarschaftspolitik der Tschechischen Republik. Bundesrat Didier Burkhalter unterstrich insbesondere die Bedeutung der Beziehungen zwischen der Schweiz und der Europäischen Union für beide Partner und erläuterte die Weiterführung der Ventilklausel für die Mitgliedstaaten der EU. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Weiteres Gesprächsthema war der Schweizer Beitrag an die Erweiterung der Europäischen Union. Der Beitrag für die Tschechische Republik beläuft sich auf 110 Millionen Franken. Bis 2017 werden in Tschechien 38 Projekte zur Verringerung der wirtschaftlichen und sozialen Ungleichheiten realisiert. Bundesrat Burkhalter zeigte sich erfreut über die bisherige erfolgreiche Zusammenarbeit zwischen der Schweiz und Tschechien im Rahmen des Erweiterungsbeitrags. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ausserdem sprachen die beiden Aussenminister über die multilateralen Beziehungen. Im Hinblick auf den Schweizer OSZE-Vorsitz im Jahr 2014 äusserte Aussenminister Schwarzenberg seine Erwartungen bezüglich der Rolle der OSZE in Osteuropa. Die beiden Aussenminister versicherten sich zudem der gegenseitigen Unterstützung für die Kandidaturen der beiden Länder für den Menschenrechtsrat. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mit einem Handelsvolumen von rund 3,7 Milliarden Franken im Jahr 2012 ist die Tschechische Republik der wichtigste Handelspartner der Schweiz in Mitteleuropa. Der offizielle Besuch bot auch Gelegenheit, die Wirtschafts- und Handelsbeziehungen zwischen den beiden Ländern zu würdigen.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Das Treffen vom 31. Mai 2013 fand nach der Jahreskonferenz der Schweizer Ostzusammenarbeit statt, an der beide Aussenminister teilnahmen. In seiner Eröffnungsansprache hatte Bundesrat Didier Burkhalter die Bedeutung des Schweizer Engagements bei der Verringerung der wirtschaftlichen und sozialen Ungleichheiten in der erweiterten EU hervorgehoben. Der tschechische Aussenminister Karl Schwarzenberg hatte in seiner Rede die Sicht eines Partnerlandes des Schweizer Erweiterungsbeitrags erläutert.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Kommunikation EDA Bundeshaus West CH-3003 Bern Tel. Kommunikationsservice: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Medienstelle: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <link id="110507">
        <title>Bilaterale Beziehungen Schweiz – Tschechische Republik</title>
        <uri>http://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home/reps/eur/vcze/biltsc.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="110508">
        <title>Schweizer Beitrag an die Tschechische Republik</title>
        <uri>http://www.erweiterungsbeitrag.admin.ch/de/Home/Laender/Tschechische_Republik</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Visite officielle de travail du ministre des affaires étrangères tchèque, Karel Schwarzenberg</title>
      <lead>Le conseiller fédéral Didier Burkhalter, chef du Département fédéral des affaires étrangères (DFAE), a reçu le ministre des affaires étrangères tchèque, Karel Schwarzenberg, le 31 mai 2013 dans le cadre d’une visite officielle de travail à Berne. Leurs discussions ont porté sur la politique européenne de la Suisse, la politique de voisinage de la République tchèque, la contribution de la Suisse à l’élargissement de l’Union européenne ainsi que les relations économiques entre les deux pays. </lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Les relations entre Ia Suisse et Ia République tchèque sont excellentes; les contacts officiels n’ont cessé de s’intensifier ces dernières années. La rencontre du 31 mai entre le ministre des affaires étrangères Didier Burkhalter et son homologue tchèque Karel Schwarzenberg témoigne du renforcement des relations entre les deux pays. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Les ministres ont échangé des vues sur la politique européenne de la Suisse et la politique de voisinage de la République tchèque. Le conseiller fédéral Didier Burkhalter a notamment présenté l'importance des relations entre la Suisse et l’Union européenne pour les deux partenaires et expliqué la reconduite de la clause de sauvegarde pour les États membres de l’UE. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Les discussions ont également porté sur Ia contribution suisse à l'élargissement de l’Union européenne. Cette contribution, qui s’élève à 110 millions CHF pour la République tchèque, permettra la mise en œuvre d’ici à 2017 de 38 projets dans le but de réduire les inégalités économiques et sociales. Didier Burkhalter s’est réjoui du succès de la collaboration qui s’est faite jusqu’à présent entre la Suisse et la République tchèque dans le cadre de cette contribution. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Les relations multilatérales ont également été abordées au cours de l’entretien. Dans la perspective de la présidence suisse de l’OSCE en 2014, Karel Schwarzenberg a fait part de ses attentes en ce qui concerne le rôle de l’OSCE en Europe de l’Est. Les deux ministres se sont également assurés d’un soutien mutuel pour les candidatures de leurs pays respectifs au Conseil des droits de l’homme. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Avec un niveau d'échanges commerciaux d'environ 3,7 milliards de CHF en 2012, Ia République tchèque est le premier partenaire commercial de la Suisse en Europe centrale. Cette visite officielle a finalement été l’occasion de valoriser les relations économiques et commerciales entre les deux pays.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;La rencontre du 31 mai entre Didier Burkhalter et Karel Schwarzenberg a eu lieu après la participation des deux ministres à Ia Conférence annuelle de la coopération suisse avec I'Europe de I'Est. Dans son discours d’ouverture, le conseiller fédéral Didier Burkhalter a insisté sur l’importance de I’engagement de la Suisse dans la réduction des inégalités économiques et sociales dans l’Union européenne élargie. Le ministre des affaires étrangères tchèque Karel Schwarzenberg y a présenté le point de vue d’un pays partenaire sur la contribution suisse à l'élargissement de l’Union européenne.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Communication DFAE Palais fédéral ouest CH-3003 Berne Tél. Service de communication: +41 58 462 31 53 Tél. Service de presse: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <link id="110511">
        <title>Relations bilatérales Suisse-République tchèque</title>
        <uri>http://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/home/reps/eur/vcze/biltsc.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="110512">
        <title>Contribution suisse à la République tchèque</title>
        <uri>http://www.erweiterungsbeitrag.admin.ch/fr/Home/Pays/Republique_tcheque</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Visita ufficiale del ministro degli affari esteri della Repubblica ceca, Karel Schwarzenberg</title>
      <lead>Il consigliere federale Didier Burkhalter, capo del Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri (DFAE), ha ricevuto il ministro degli affari esteri ceco, Karel Schwarzenberg, il 31 maggio 2013 nel quadro di una visita ufficiale di lavoro a Berna. I colloqui hanno riguardato la politica europea della Svizzera, la politica di vicinato della Repubblica ceca, il contributo della Svizzera all'allargamento dell'Unione europea e le relazioni economiche tra i due Paesi. </lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Le relazioni tra la Svizzera e la Repubblica ceca sono eccellenti; negli ultimi anni, infatti, i contatti ufficiali non hanno fatto che intensificarsi. L'incontro del 31 maggio tra il ministro degli affari esteri Didier Burkhalter e il suo omologo ceco Karel Schwarzenberg testimonia il rafforzamento delle relazioni tra i due Paesi. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I ministri hanno avuto scambi di vedute sulla politica europea della Svizzera e sulla politica di vicinato della Repubblica ceca. Il consigliere federale Didier Burkhalter ha illustrato l'importanza delle relazioni tra la Svizzera e l'Unione europea per i due partner e ha spiegato il prolungamento della clausola di salvaguardia per gli Stati membri dell'UE. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I colloqui hanno anche riguardato il contributo svizzero all'allargamento dell'Unione europea che, pari a 110 milioni CHF per la Repubblica ceca, consentirà di realizzare da qui al 2017 38 progetti volti a ridurre le disparità economiche e sociali. Didier Burkhalter si è rallegrato del successo della collaborazione tra la Svizzera e la Repubblica ceca nell'ambito di questo contributo. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Durante l'incontro è stato affrontato anche il tema degli relazioni multilaterali . Nell'ottica della presidenza svizzera dell'OSCE nel 2014, Karel Schwarzenberg ha espresso le proprie attese per quanto concerne il ruolo dell'OSCE in Europa dell'Est. I due ministri hanno inoltre garantito il loro reciproco sostegno alle candidature dei rispettivi Paesi al Consiglio dei diritti dell'uomo. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Con un volume di scambi commerciali di circa 3,7 miliardi di CHF nel 2012, Ia Repubblica ceca è il primo partner commerciale della Svizzera in Europa centrale. Questa visita ufficiale ha costituito l'opportunità di valorizzare le relazioni economiche e commerciali tra i due Paesi.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;L'incontro del 31 maggio tra Didier Burkhalter e Karel Schwarzenberg ha avuto luogo dopo la partecipazione dei due ministri alla Conferenza annuale della cooperazione svizzera con l'Europa dell'Est. Nel discorso d'apertura, Burkhalter ha insistito sull'importanza dell'impegno della Svizzera nella riduzione delle disparità economiche e sociali in seno all'Unione europea allargata. Il ministro degli affari esteri ceco Karel Schwarzenberg ha illustrato il punto di vista di un Paese partner sul contributo svizzero all'allargamento dell'Unione europea.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Comunicazione DFAE Palazzo federale ovest CH-3003 Berna Tel. Servizio di comunicazione: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Servizio stampa: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <link id="110513">
        <title>Relazioni bilaterali Svizzera - Repubblica ceca</title>
        <uri>http://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/home/reps/eur/vcze/biltsc.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="110514">
        <title>Contributo svizzero alla Repubblica ceca</title>
        <uri>http://www.erweiterungsbeitrag.admin.ch/it/Home/Pays/Republique_tcheque</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Official working visit by the Czech Minister of Foreign Affairs, Karel Schwarzenberg</title>
      <lead>Federal Councillor Didier Burkhalter, Head of the Federal Department of Foreign Affairs (FDFA), received the Minister of Foreign Affairs of the Czech Republic, Karel Schwarzenberg, on 31 May 2013 for an official working visit to Bern. Their discussions focused on Switzerland's European policy, the Czech Republic's European Neighbourhood Policy, the Swiss contribution to the enlargement of the European Union, and economic relations between the two countries.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Relations between Switzerland and the Czech Republic are excellent, and official contacts have steadily intensified in recent years. The meeting of 31 May between FDFA Head Didier Burkhalter and his Czech counterpart Karel Schwarzenberg underscores the strengthening of relations between the two countries. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Ministers exchanged views on Switzerland's European policy and the Czech Republic's European Neighbourhood Policy. Mr Burkhalter emphasised the importance for the two partners of relations between Switzerland and the European Union and the renewal of the safeguard clause for EU Member States. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Discussions also focused on the Swiss contribution to the enlargement of the European Union. This contribution, which amounts to CHF 110 million for the Czech Republic, will allow the implementation by 2017 of 38 projects that aim to reduce economic and social disparities. Mr Burkhalter welcomed the success of the cooperation between Switzerland and the Czech Republic within the framework of this contribution. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Multilateral relations were also discussed during the meeting. As Switzerland is about to assume the chairmanship of the OSCE in 2014, Mr Schwarzenberg also spoke about his expectations for the OSCE's role in Eastern Europe. The two ministers also assured each other of their mutual support for their respective countries' candidatures for the Human Rights Council. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A trade volume of approximately CHF 3.7 billion in 2012 makes the Czech Republic Switzerland's largest trading partner in Central Europe. This official visit was a long-awaited opportunity to showcase trade and economic relations between the two countries.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The meeting of 31 May between Didier Burkhalter and Karel Schwarzenberg took place after the two ministers participated in the Annual Conference on Swiss Cooperation with Eastern Europe. In his opening speech, Mr Burkhalter stressed the importance of Switzerland's commitment to reducing economic and social disparities in the enlarged European Union. Mr Schwarzenberg presented a partner country's point of view on the Swiss contribution to the enlargement of the European Union.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>FDFA Communication Federal Palace West Wing CH-3003 Bern, Switzerland Tel. Communication service: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Press service: +41 58 460 55 55 E-mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @SwissMFA</contact>
      <link id="110515">
        <title>Bilateral relations between Switzerland and Czech Republic</title>
        <uri>http://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home/reps/eur/vcze/biltsc.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="110516">
        <title>Swiss Contribution to the Czech Republic</title>
        <uri>http://www.erweiterungsbeitrag.admin.ch/en/Home/Countries/Czech_Republic</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
