<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="49179" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2013-06-07</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="yes" id="1060" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>601</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Staatssekretariat für internationale Finanzfragen</name>
      <name lang="fr">Secrétariat d'Etat aux questions financières internationales</name>
      <name lang="it">Segreteria di Stato per le questioni finanziarie internazionali</name>
      <name lang="en">State Secretariat for International Financial Matters</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.sif.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.sif.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.sif.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.sif.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@sif.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@sif.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@sif.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@sif.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="601">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Finanzdepartement</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des finances</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale delle finanze</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Finance</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.efd.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.dff.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.efd.admin.ch/efd/it/home.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.efd.admin.ch/efd/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Schweiz und USA unterzeichnen Verständigungsvereinbarung zu FATCA-Abkommen</title>
      <lead>In Washington haben heute die Schweiz und die USA ein Memorandum of Understanding über Auslegungen des FATCA-Abkommens vom 14. Februar 2013 unterzeichnet.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Im Rahmen der Verhandlungen über das am 14. Februar 2013 unterzeichnete FATCA-Abkommen hatten beide Seiten vereinbart, einzelne Auslegungen technischer oder administrativer Art in einer Verständigungsvereinbarung (Memorandum of Understanding) festzuhalten. Diese Verständigungsvereinbarung wurde heute in Washington von Manuel Sager, Schweizer Botschafter in den USA, und Mark Mazur, Assistant Secretary for Tax Policy, unterzeichnet.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Die Vereinbarung fasst die Verpflichtungen der Schweizer Finanzinstitute zusammen, hält das Verhältnis zum Qualified Intermediary System fest und bestätigt für unter dem FATCA-Abkommen befreite schweizerische Nutzungsberechtigte die erleichterte Eigendeklaration. Schliesslich wird festgehalten, dass schweizerische Finanzinstitute grundsätzlich Begriffsbestimmungen aus den Ausführungsbestimmungen des US-Finanzministeriums anwenden können, wenn diese gegenüber den Definitionen im FATCA-Abkommen Erleichterungen bringen.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Mario Tuor, Kommunikation Staatssekretariat für internationale Finanzfragen SIF +41 31 322 46 16, mario.tuor@sif.admin.ch</contact>
      <attachment id="110877">
        <title>Verständigungsvereinbarung</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>21</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/30882.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>La Suisse et les Etats-Unis signent un protocole d'entente concernant l'accord FATCA</title>
      <lead>La Suisse et les Etats-Unis ont signé aujourd'hui à Washington un protocole d'entente sur l'interprétation de l'accord FATCA du 14 février 2013.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Lors des négociations sur l'accord FATCA du 14 février 2013, les deux parties avaient convenu de clarifier certains points techniques et administratifs dans un protocole d'entente. Manuel Sager, ambassadeur de Suisse aux Etats-Unis, et Mark Mazur, secrétaire adjoint au Trésor américain pour la politique fiscale, ont signé aujourd'hui aux Etats-Unis ce protocole d'entente. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Le protocole résume les obligations des établissements financiers suisses, précise le lien avec le système de l'intermédiaire qualifié et confirme l'autodéclaration simplifiée pour les bénéficiaires effectifs exemptés dans le cadre de l'accord FATCA. Enfin, il stipule que les établissements financiers suisses peuvent en principe utiliser les définitions figurant dans les dispositions d'exécution du Trésor américain quand ces définitions apportent des simplifications par rapport à celles contenues dans l'accord FATCA.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Mario Tuor, Communication du Secrétariat d'Etat aux questions financières internationales (SFI) +41 31 322 46 16, mario.tuor@sif.admin.ch</contact>
      <attachment id="110877">
        <title>Verständigungsvereinbarung</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>21</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/30882.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="110878">
        <title>Memorandum of Understanding</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>20</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/30883.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Svizzera e Stati Uniti firmano un Memorandum d'intesa dell'Accordo FATCA</title>
      <lead>In data odierna la Svizzera e gli Stati Uniti hanno firmato un Memorandum d'intesa concernente l'interpretazione dell'Accordo FACTA del 14 febbraio 2013.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Nel quadro dei negoziati dell'Accordo FATCA, firmato il 14 febbraio 2013, entrambe le parti avevano convenuto di accordarsi su singole interpretazioni di tipo tecnico o amministrativo in una convenzione di interpretazione (Memorandum d'intesa). Questo Memorandum è stato firmato in data odierna a Washington da Manuel Sager, ambasciatore svizzero negli Stati Uniti, e da Mark Mazur, Assistant Secretary for Tax Policy.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Il Memorandum riassume gli obblighi degli istituti finanziari svizzeri, definisce il rapporto con il Qualified Intermediary System e conferma l'autodichiarazione agevolata per i beneficiari effettivi svizzeri esonerati secondo l'Accordo FATCA. Viene infine stabilito che gli istituti finanziari svizzeri possono di principio impiegare le definizioni delle pertinenti disposizioni esecutive del Dipartimento del Tesoro statunitense se queste comportano agevolazioni rispetto alle relative definizioni dell'Accordo.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Mario Tuor, Comunicazione Segreteria di Stato per le questioni finanziarie internazionali SFI, +41 31 322 46 16, mario.tuor@sif.admin.ch</contact>
      <attachment id="110877">
        <title>Verständigungsvereinbarung</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>21</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/30882.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="110878">
        <title>Memorandum of Understanding</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>20</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/30883.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Switzerland and United States sign Memorandum of Understanding on FATCA agreement</title>
      <lead>Today in Washington, Switzerland and the United States signed a Memorandum of Understanding on interpretations regarding the FATCA agreement of 14 February 2013.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Within the scope of the negotiations on the FATCA agreement signed on 14 February 2013, both sides agreed to set out individual interpretations of a technical or administrative nature in a Memorandum of Understanding (MoU). This Memorandum of Understanding was signed today in Washington by Manuel Sager, Ambassador of Switzerland to the United States, and Mark Mazur, Assistant Secretary for Tax Policy.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The MoU summarises the obligations of Swiss financial institutions, states the relationship with the qualified intermediary system, and confirms the simplified self-declaration for exempt Swiss beneficial owners under the FATCA agreement. Finally, it is stated that Swiss financial institutions can generally apply definitions from the implementing provisions of the US Department of the Treasury if these simplify matters relative to the definitions in the FATCA agreement.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Mario Tuor, Communications, State Secretariat for International Financial Matters SIF +41 31 322 46 16, mario.tuor@sif.admin.ch</contact>
      <attachment id="110878">
        <title>Memorandum of Understanding</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>20</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/30883.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <offers>
      <offer id="291" org-id="1060">
        <name lang="de">Wirtschaft, Währung, Finanzplatz</name>
        <name lang="fr">Economie, monnaie, place financière</name>
        <name lang="it">Economia, Moneta, Piazza finanziaria</name>
        <name lang="en">Economic, Monetary and Financial Affairs</name>
      </offer>
      <offer id="317" org-id="1060">
        <name lang="de">SIF NEWSLETTER</name>
        <name lang="fr">SFI NEWSLETTER</name>
        <name lang="it">SFI NEWSLETTER</name>
        <name lang="en">SIF NEWSLETTER</name>
      </offer>
    </offers>
    <keywords>
      <keyword id="235" org-id="1060">
        <name lang="de">Internationale Steuerpolitik</name>
        <name lang="fr">Politique fiscale internationale</name>
        <name lang="it">Politica fiscale internazionale</name>
        <name lang="en">International tax policy</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="126" org-id="1060">
        <name lang="de">Finanzplatz Schweiz</name>
        <name lang="fr">Place financière suisse</name>
        <name lang="it">Piazza finanziaria svizzera</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland as a financial centre</name>
      </keyword>
    </keywords>
    <topics>
      <topic id="35">
        <name lang="de">Finanzplatz</name>
        <name lang="fr">Place financière</name>
        <name lang="it">Piazza finanziaria</name>
        <name lang="en">Financial Centre</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="44">
        <name lang="de">Steuern</name>
        <name lang="fr">Impôts</name>
        <name lang="it">Imposte</name>
        <name lang="en">Taxation</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="47">
        <name lang="de">Wirtschaft</name>
        <name lang="fr">Économie</name>
        <name lang="it">Economia</name>
        <name lang="en">Economic Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
