<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="49853" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2013-08-14</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="1070" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>1070</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Der Bundesrat</name>
      <name lang="fr">Conseil fédéral</name>
      <name lang="it">Il Consiglio federale</name>
      <name lang="en">The Federal Council</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.admin.ch/gov/de/start.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.admin.ch/gov/fr/accueil.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.admin.ch/gov/it/pagina-iniziale.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.admin.ch/gov/en/start.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="201" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>201</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="501" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>501</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Verteidigung, Bevölkerungsschutz und Sport</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de la défense, de la protection de la population et des sports</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale della difesa, della protezione della popolazione e dello sport</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Defence, Civil Protection and Sports DDPS</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.vbs.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.vbs.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.vbs.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.vbs.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@gs-vbs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@gs-vbs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@gs-vbs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@gs-vbs.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="1070">
      <name lang="de">Der Bundesrat</name>
      <name lang="fr">Conseil fédéral</name>
      <name lang="it">Il Consiglio federale</name>
      <name lang="en">The Federal Council</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.admin.ch/gov/de/start.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.admin.ch/gov/fr/accueil.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.admin.ch/gov/it/pagina-iniziale.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.admin.ch/gov/en/start.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <department id="201">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <department id="501">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Verteidigung, Bevölkerungsschutz und Sport</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de la défense, de la protection de la population et des sports</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale della difesa, della protezione della popolazione e dello sport</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Defence, Civil Protection and Sports DDPS</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.vbs.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.vbs.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.vbs.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.vbs.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@gs-vbs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@gs-vbs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@gs-vbs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@gs-vbs.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Schweizer Einsatz von unbewaffneten Armeeangehörigen in Mali</title>
      <lead>Der Bundesrat hat am 14. August 2013 beschlossen, sich mit bis zu acht Armeeangehörigen an der Mission der Vereinten Nationen in Mali zu beteiligen. Diese werden als unbewaffnete Militärbeobachter eingesetzt. Damit wird das humanitäre, entwicklungs- und friedenspolitische Engagement der Schweiz in Mali verstärkt. </lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Der Bundesrat hat gestützt auf das Militärgesetz und aufgrund der entsprechenden Resolution des UNO-Sicherheitsrates sowie einer konkreten Anfrage der UNO entschieden, dass sich die Schweiz mit bis zu acht unbewaffneten Armeeangehörigen an der Mission multidimensionnelle intégrée des Nations Unies au Mali (MINUSMA) beteiligt. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Die Stabsoffiziere und Experten der Schweizer Armee werden – gemäss den Bedürfnissen der UNO Mission vor Ort – in den Bereichen humanitäre Minenräumung und Blindgängerbeseitigung, Sicherung von Munitions- und Waffenbeständen, der Sicherheitssektor-Reform oder allenfalls im Bereich Genie- und Logistik eingesetzt werden.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Die Entsendung von unbewaffneten Armeeangehörigen für die MINUSMA entspricht den Entscheiden des Bundesrates und des Parlaments bezüglich des Engagements der Schweizer Armee in Missionen der militärischen Friedensförderung. Die Beteiligung der Schweiz an der MINUSMA ist zudem konform mit den gesetzlichen Grundlagen (Militärgesetz), da die Mission durch ein Mandat des UNO-Sicherheitsrates etabliert wurde.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Die Schweiz engagiert sich damit auch militärisch konkret in der Stabilisierung Malis und der Sahel-Region. In der Tat wird mit der Unterstützung der MINUSMA ein komplementärer Beitrag zu den langjährigen Bemühungen der humanitären Hilfe, der Entwicklungszusammenarbeit sowie der Friedensförderung geleistet. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Für die Programme der Entwicklungszusammenarbeit wurden im Jahre 2012 insgesamt 16,5 Mio. Franken aufgewendet. Die humanitäre Hilfe hat seit 2012 insgesamt 38,7 Mio. Franken für die Hungerhilfe im Sahel und die Krise in Mali ausgegeben. Die Schweiz führt zudem ein Programm der zivilen Friedensförderung in Mali mit dem Ziel, die Konflikttransformation zu unterstützen. Die Schweiz hat sich, zusammen mit der Afrikanischen Union, der Europäischen Union, Frankreich und anderen Staaten, als Fazilitatorin an der Mediation der UNO und von Burkina Faso beteiligt. Dies hat am 18. Juni 2013 zur Unterzeichnung des vorläufigen Abkommens im Hinblick auf die Präsidentschaftswahlen und die alle einschliessenden Friedensgespräche geführt. Die Schweiz ist zudem Mitglied des internationalen Begleit- und Evaluationsausschusses, unter der Ägide der UNO, der mit diesem Abkommen gegründet wurde. Die Aufgabe dieses Ausschusses ist es, die Umsetzung des Abkommens durch die Vertragsparteien zu begleiten und insbesondere, nach den Präsidentschaftswahlen, inklusive Gespräche mit allen relevanten Akteuren über die hängigen Fragen, die zur Krise geführt haben, zu führen.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Die Schweiz hat sich auch an der Beobachtung der kürzlich stattgefundenen Wahlen beteiligt. Die Entsendung von schweizerischem zivilem Personal in die MINUSMA und in die Ausbildungsmission der EU (EUTM) ist ebenfalls vorgesehen.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Die Anfrage der UNO zeigt, dass die Schweiz als unparteiische und kompetente Partnerin auch in ausserordentlichen und komplexen Situationen gefragt ist. Die Schweiz hat nicht nur aus humanitären, sondern auch aus sicherheits- und friedenspolitischen, sowie wirtschaftlichen und migrationspolitischen Gründen ein Interesse daran, dass Mali und die Sahel-Region – unter Einhaltung der Menschenrechte und des Völkerrechts - möglichst rasch und nachhaltig stabilisiert werden kann. Die Schweiz leistet mit der Entsendung der unbewaffneten Armeeangehörigen einen wichtigen Beitrag dazu.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Information EDA Tel. 031 322 31 53 Kommunikation VBS Tel. 031 324 88 75</contact>
      <link id="112858">
        <title>Resolution des Sicherheitsrates 2100 (2013) (fr)</title>
        <uri>http://www.un.org/fr/documents/view_doc.asp?symbol=S/RES/2100(2013)&amp;TYPE=&amp;referer=http://www.un.org/fr/sc/documents/resolutions/2013.shtml&amp;Lang=F</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="112859">
        <title>Mission multidimensionnelle intégrée des Nations Unies au Mali (MINUSMA) (fr)</title>
        <uri>http://www.un.org/fr/peacekeeping/missions/minusma/</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="112860">
        <title>Kompetenzzentrum Friedensfördernde Einsätze SWISSINT des VBS</title>
        <uri>http://www.vtg.admin.ch/internet/vtg/de/home/themen/einsaetze/peace.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="112861">
        <title>Engagement der DEZA in Mali</title>
        <uri>http://www.deza.admin.ch/de/Home/Laender/Westafrika/Mali</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Des militaires non armés suisses en mission au Mali</title>
      <lead>Le 14 août 2013, le Conseil fédéral a décidé de détacher jusqu’à huit militaires pour participer à la Mission des Nations Unies au Mali. Ils seront affectés à celle-ci en tant qu’observateurs militaires non armés. La Suisse renforce ainsi son engagement humanitaire et son action au service de la paix et du développement au Mali. </lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Sur la base de la loi sur l’armée et eu égard à la résolution pertinente du Conseil de sécurité de l’ONU, le Conseil fédéral a décidé, en réponse à une demande concrète de l’ONU, que la Suisse détacherait jusqu’à huit militaires non armés pour participer à la Mission multidimensionnelle intégrée des Nations Unies au Mali (MINUSMA). &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Les officiers d’état-major et les experts détachés par l’armée suisse seront affectés – selon les besoins de la mission de l’ONU sur place – au déminage humanitaire et à l’élimination des ratés, à la sécurisation des stocks d’armes et de munitions, à la réforme du secteur de la sécurité ou éventuellement au domaine du génie et de la logistique.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Le détachement de militaires non armés auprès de la MINUSMA est en accord avec les décisions prises par le Conseil fédéral et le Parlement en ce qui concerne l’engagement de l’armée suisse dans des missions de promotion militaire de la paix. La participation de la Suisse à la MINUSMA est en outre conforme aux bases légales (loi sur l’armée), car cette mission a été établie en vertu d’un mandat du Conseil de sécurité de l’ONU.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Par cet engagement militaire, la Suisse participe concrètement à la stabilisation du Mali et de la région du Sahel. En soutenant la MINUSMA, elle apporte une contribution qui vient compléter les efforts qu’elle déploie de longue date dans les domaines de l’aide humanitaire, de la coopération au développement et de la promotion de la paix. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;En 2012, une enveloppe totale de 16,5 millions de francs a été consacrée aux programmes de la coopération au développement. Depuis 2012, un montant total de 38,7 millions de francs a été affecté à l’aide alimentaire au Sahel et à la crise au Mali, au titre de l’aide humanitaire. La Suisse mène en outre un programme de promotion civile de la paix au Mali en vue de soutenir la transformation du conflit. Elle a participé en qualité de facilitateur, aux côtés de l’Union africaine, de l’Union européenne, de la France et d’autres pays, à la médiation assurée par l’ONU et le Burkina Faso. Ces efforts ont abouti à la signature, le 18 juin 2013, de l’Accord préliminaire à l’élection présidentielle et aux pourparlers de paix inclusifs au Mali. La Suisse est en outre membre du Comité international de suivi et d’évaluation créé par cet accord et qui est placé sous l’égide de l’ONU. Ce comité a pour mission d’accompagner la mise en œuvre de l’accord par les parties contractantes et en particulier de mener, après les élections présidentielles, des discussions inclusives avec tous les acteurs pertinents sur les questions ayant conduit à la crise et qui restent en suspens. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;La Suisse a également participé à une mission d’observation électorale lors des élections récentes. Le détachement de personnel civil suisse auprès de la MINUSMA et de la mission de formation de l’UE (EUTM) est également prévu.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;La demande de l’ONU montre que la Suisse est sollicitée même dans des situations exceptionnelles et complexes, en tant que partenaire compétent et impartial. Pour des raisons d’ordre humanitaire, mais aussi économique et migratoire, ainsi que dans une perspective de politique de paix et de sécurité, il est de l’intérêt de la Suisse que le Mali et la région du Sahel connaissent rapidement une stabilisation durable, dans le respect des droits de l’homme et du droit international. Par l’envoi de militaires non armés, la Suisse apporte une contribution importante à la réalisation de cet objectif.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Information DFAE tél. 031 322 31 53 Communication DDPS tél. 031 324 88 75</contact>
      <link id="112862">
        <title>Résolution du Conseil de sécurité 2100 (2013)</title>
        <uri>http://www.un.org/fr/documents/view_doc.asp?symbol=S/RES/2100(2013)&amp;TYPE=&amp;referer=http://www.un.org/fr/sc/documents/resolutions/2013.shtml&amp;Lang=F</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="112863">
        <title>Mission multidimensionnelle intégrée des Nations Unies au Mali (MINUSMA)</title>
        <uri>http://www.un.org/fr/peacekeeping/missions/minusma/</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="112864">
        <title>Centre de compétences Engagements de promotion de la paix à l’étranger (SWISSINT) du DDPS</title>
        <uri>http://www.vtg.admin.ch/internet/vtg/fr/home/themen/einsaetze/peace.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="112865">
        <title>Action de la DDC au Mali</title>
        <uri>http://www.deza.admin.ch/fr/Accueil/Pays/Afrique_occidentale/Mali</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Impiego di militari svizzeri non armati in Mali</title>
      <lead>Il 14 agosto 2013 il Consiglio federale ha deciso di inviare fino a otto militari, in qualità di osservatori non armati, a sostegno della missione delle Nazioni Unite in Mali. La Svizzera rafforza così il suo impegno in Mali nell'ambito dell'aiuto umanitario nonché della politica di sviluppo e di pace. </lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;In base alla legge militare e alla relativa risoluzione del Consiglio di sicurezza dell'ONU, nonché dietro espressa richiesta delle Nazioni Unite, il Consiglio federale ha deciso che la Svizzera parteciperà alla Missione multidimensionale integrata delle Nazioni Unite in Mali (MINUSMA) inviando fino a otto militari non armati. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A seconda delle esigenze della missione dell'ONU sul posto, gli ufficiali superiori e gli esperti dell'esercito svizzero saranno impiegati nello sminamento umanitario e nell'eliminazione di proiettili inesplosi nonché nell'ambito della riforma del settore della sicurezza o eventualmente nel genio e nella logistica.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;L'invio di militari non armati a sostegno della MINUSMA fa seguito alle decisioni del Consiglio federale e del Parlamento riguardanti l'impegno dell'Esercito svizzero in missioni di promozione militare della pace. La partecipazione della Svizzera alla MINUSMA è inoltre conforme alla legislazione vigente (legge militare), in quanto la missione è stata istituita su mandato del Consiglio di sicurezza dell'ONU.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;La Svizzera promuove la stabilizzazione in Mali e nella regione del Sahel impegnandosi concretamente anche a livello militare. Il sostegno alla missione MINUSMA rappresenta infatti un contributo complementare all'impegno pluriennale del nostro Paese nel campo dell'aiuto umanitario, della cooperazione allo sviluppo e della promozione della pace. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Nel 2012, per i programmi della cooperazione allo sviluppo sono stati investiti complessivamente 16,5 milioni di franchi, mentre nell’ultimo anno l'aiuto umanitario ha stanziato in totale 38,7 milioni di franchi per la lotta alla fame nel Sahel e la crisi in Mali. La Svizzera conduce inoltre un programma di promozione civile della pace in Mali volto a favorire una trasformazione del conflitto. Insieme all'Unione Africana, all'Unione europea, alla Francia e ad altri Stati, la Svizzera ha anche partecipato come Paese facilitatore alla mediazione dell'ONU e del Burkina Faso, sfociata il 18 giugno 2013 nella firma dell'Accordo di pace preliminare alle elezioni presidenziali e a trattative di pace inclusive in Mali. Il nostro Paese è membro del Comitato internazionale di monitoraggio e di valutazione, sotto l'egida dell'ONU, istituito con tale accordo. Questo comitato ha il compito di accompagnare l'attuazione dell'accordo da parte degli Stati contraenti e, in particolare, di condurre con tutti gli attori coinvolti, dopo le elezioni presidenziali, colloqui inclusivi sulle cause della crisi ancora rimaste in sospeso.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;La Svizzera ha inoltre partecipato all'osservazione delle recenti elezioni e prevede anche di inviare personale civile a sostegno della MINUSMA e della missione di formazione dell'UE (EUTM).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;La richiesta dell'ONU mostra come la Svizzera venga apprezzata in veste di partner imparziale e competente anche in situazioni straordinarie e complesse. L'interesse del nostro Paese a una stabilizzazione il più possibile rapida e duratura del Mali e della regione del Sahel, nel rispetto dei diritti dell'uomo e del diritto internazionale, non riguarda soltanto gli aspetti umanitari, ma è dettato anche da motivi legati alla politica di sicurezza e di pace, nonché all'economia e alla politica migratoria. Con l'invio di militari non armati la Svizzera fornisce un importante contributo in tal senso.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Informazione DFAE tel. 031 322 31 53 Comunicazione DDPS tel. 031 324 88 75</contact>
      <link id="112866">
        <title>Risoluzione 2100 (2013) del Consiglio di sicurezza (fr)</title>
        <uri>http://www.un.org/fr/documents/view_doc.asp?symbol=S/RES/2100(2013)&amp;TYPE=&amp;referer=http://www.un.org/fr/sc/documents/resolutions/2013.shtml&amp;Lang=F</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="112867">
        <title>Missione multidimensionale integrata delle Nazioni Unite in Mali (MINUSMA) (fr)</title>
        <uri>http://www.un.org/fr/peacekeeping/missions/minusma/</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="112868">
        <title>Centro di competenza SWISSINT del DDPS</title>
        <uri>http://www.vtg.admin.ch/internet/vtg/it/home/themen/einsaetze/peace.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="112869">
        <title>Impegno della DSC in Mali</title>
        <uri>http://www.deza.admin.ch/it/Pagina_iniziale/Paesi/Africa_Occidentale/Mali</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Swiss mission of unarmed military personnel to Mali</title>
      <lead>On 14 August 2013, the Federal Council decided to second up to eight military personnel to the United Nations Mission in Mali to be deployed as unarmed military observers. The decision strengthens Switzerland’s humanitarian, development and peace policy commitment in Mali. </lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;The Federal Council based its decision on the Swiss Armed Forces Act, the relevant resolution of the UN Security Council, and a specific request by the UN that Switzerland participate with up to eight unarmed military personnel in the United Nations Multidimensional Integrated Stabilisation Mission in Mali (MINUSMA).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The staff officers and experts of the Swiss Armed Forces will – in accordance with the needs of the UN Mission in Mali – be deployed in the areas of humanitarian demining and explosive ordnance disposal, security of munitions and weapons stocks, security sector reform or, if required, military engineering and logistics.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The secondment of unarmed military personnel to MINUSMA is in keeping with the decisions of the Federal Council and Parliament with regard to the involvement of the Swiss Armed Forces in military peacekeeping missions. Moreover, Switzerland’s participation in MINUSMA is also in compliance with the Swiss Armed Forces Act since the mission has been established on the basis of a UN Security Council mandate.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In this way Switzerland is actively involved, also in a military capacity, in the stabilisation of Mali and the Sahel region. Switzerland’s support for MINUSMA complements its long-standing efforts in the areas of humanitarian aid, development cooperation and peace promotion.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In 2012, Switzerland spent a total of CHF15.6 million on development cooperation programmes in the region. Since 2012, Swiss Humanitarian Aid has channelled a total of CHF 38.7m for hunger relief aid into the Sahel and helping to resolve the crisis in Mali. In addition, Switzerland is carrying out a civilian peace promotion programme in Mali to support conflict transformation. Together with the African Union, the European Union, France and other countries, Switzerland has been active as a facilitator in the mediation efforts of the UN and Burkina Faso. This led to the signing, on 18 June 2013, of a preliminary agreement calling for the holding of a presidential election and inclusive peace talks in Mali (“Accord préliminaire à l’élection présidentielle et aux pourparlers de paix inclusifs au Mali”). In addition, Switzerland is a member of the international follow-up and evaluation committee (“Comité international de suivi et d’évaluation”), under the aegis of the UN, that was established under this agreement. The committee’s task is to monitor the implementation of the agreement by the contracting parties and, in particular following the presidential elections, to conduct inclusive talks with all relevant players on the still-unresolved issues that led to the crisis. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Switzerland also participated as an observer in the recently held elections. The secondment of Swiss civilian personnel to MINUSMA and to the EU training mission (EUTM) is also envisaged.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The UN’s request shows that Switzerland is needed as an impartial and competent partner even in extremely complex situations. Switzerland has an interest that Mali and the Sahel region be rapidly and sustainably stabilised - while respecting human rights and international law - not only for humanitarian reasons but also for reasons of security and peace policy and those concerning economic and migration policy. With the secondment of unarmed military personnel, Switzerland is making a significant contribution to achieving this end.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>FDFA Information: Tel. 031 322 31 53 DDPS Communications: Tel. 031 324 88 75</contact>
      <link id="112870">
        <title>Security Council resolution 2100 (2013)</title>
        <uri>http://www.un.org/en/peacekeeping/missions/minusma/documents/mali%20_2100_E_.pdf</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="112871">
        <title>United Nations Multidimensional Integrated Stabilisation Mission in Mali (MINUSMA).</title>
        <uri>http://www.un.org/en/peacekeeping/missions/minusma/</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="112873">
        <title>Armed Forces International Command SWISSINT for peace support operations abroad, of the DDPS</title>
        <uri>http://www.vtg.admin.ch/internet/vtg/en/home/themen/einsaetze/peace.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="112874">
        <title>The SDC’s commitment in Mali</title>
        <uri>http://www.deza.admin.ch/en/Home/Countries/West_Africa/Mali</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <keywords>
      <keyword id="590" org-id="501">
        <name lang="de">Auslandeinsätze</name>
        <name lang="fr">Engagements à l'étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Impieghi all'estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Foreign Operations</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="5180" org-id="501">
        <name lang="de">Armee</name>
        <name lang="fr">Armée</name>
        <name lang="it">Esercito</name>
        <name lang="en">armed forces</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="5530" org-id="501">
        <name lang="de">Bundespolitik / Bundesrat</name>
        <name lang="fr">Politique fédérale</name>
        <name lang="it">Politica federale / Consiglio federale</name>
        <name lang="en">federal policy / Federal Council(lor)</name>
      </keyword>
    </keywords>
    <topics>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
