<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="50150" revoked="no">
    <version>2</version>
    <pubdate>2013-09-05</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="201" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>201</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="201">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Offizieller Arbeitsbesuch von Bundesrat Didier Burkhalter in Marokko</title>
      <lead>Bundesrat Didier Burkhalter wird am Freitag, 6. September 2013, zu einem offiziellen Arbeitsbesuch in Marokko weilen. Es handelt sich um die erste offizielle Reise eines Schweizer Aussenministers in dieses Land. Auf dem Programm stehen Gespräche mit dem marokkanischen Minister für auswärtige Angelegenheiten und Zusammenarbeit, Saad-Eddine El Othmani, sowie mit Regierungschef Abdelilah Benkirane und Innenminister Mohand Laenser.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Die Beziehungen zwischen der Schweiz und Marokko sind sehr gut und vielfältig. Die Aussenministerien beider Länder führen seit 2009 regelmässig politische Konsultationen durch. Die letzte fand im Januar 2013 in Rabat im Beisein des Staatssekretärs des Eidgenössischen Departements (EDA), Yves Rossier, statt. Ziel dieser Gespräche ist es, neue Kooperationsschwerpunkte zu definieren und die Zusammenarbeit in den Bereichen Entwicklung, demokratische Reformen und gute Regierungsführung, menschliche Sicherheit, Menschenrechte und Migrationsdialog zu stärken. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Bundesrat Didier Burkhalter wird im Rahmen dieses offiziellen Arbeitsbesuchs in Rabat seinen marokkanischen Amtskollegen Saad-Eddine El Othmani treffen. Zudem wird er Gespräche mit Regierungschef Abdelilah Benkirane und Innenminister Mohand Laenser führen. Anlässlich dieses Besuchs wird auch ein Rahmenabkommen über die internationale Zusammenarbeit zwischen dem Königreich Marokko und der Schweiz unterzeichnet. Gegenstand dieses Abkommens sind die demokratische Transition, Menschenrechte, die wirtschaftliche Entwicklung und die Schaffung von Arbeitsplätzen sowie Migrationsfragen.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Kommunikation EDA Bundeshaus West CH-3003 Bern Tel. Kommunikationsservice: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Medienstelle: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <link id="114062">
        <title>Reise von Bundesrat Didier Burkhalter nach Marokko (fr)</title>
        <uri>http://www.dfae.admin.ch/eda/fr/home/dfa/head/hoeven/mar.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="114042">
        <title>Bilaterale Beziehungen mit Marokko</title>
        <uri>http://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home/reps/afri/vmar/bilmar.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="114043">
        <title>Erfassung der Kapazitäten des marokkanischen Zivilschutzes</title>
        <uri>http://www.deza.admin.ch/de/Accueil/Projets/Exemples_de_projets/Les_secouristes_volontaires_de_proximite_au_Maroc</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="114044">
        <title>Die DEZA in Marokko</title>
        <uri>http://www.deza.admin.ch/de/Accueil/Pays/Afrique_du_Nord/Maroc</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="114045">
        <title>Strategie für Nordafrika 2011–2016</title>
        <uri>http://www.deza.admin.ch/de/Home/Laender/Nordafrika</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="114046">
        <title>Projekte in Nordafrika</title>
        <uri>http://www.deza.admin.ch/de/Home/Laender/Nordafrika/Projekte_in_Nordafrika</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Visite officielle de travail du conseiller fédéral Didier Burkhalter au Maroc</title>
      <lead>Le conseiller fédéral Didier Burkhalter effectuera une visite officielle de travail au Maroc le vendredi 6 septembre 2013. Il s’agira du premier déplacement officiel d’un chef de la diplomatie suisse dans ce pays. M. Burkhalter rencontrera le ministre marocain des affaires étrangères et de la coopération, Saad-Eddine El Othmani. Il s’entretiendra également avec le chef du gouvernement, Abdelilah Benkirane, ainsi qu’avec le ministre de l’intérieur, Mohand Laenser.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Les relations entre la Suisse et le Maroc sont très bonnes et largement diversifiées. Les ministères des affaires étrangères des deux pays organisent régulièrement des consultations politiques, et ce depuis 2009. Organisées la dernière fois en janvier 2013 à Rabat, en présence du secrétaire d’Etat du Département fédéral des affaires étrangères (DFAE) Yves Rossier, elles visent à identifier de nouveaux axes de coopération et à renforcer cette dernière dans des domaines tels que la coopération au développement, les réformes démocratiques et la bonne gouvernance, la sécurité humaine, les droits de l’homme, et le dialogue migratoire. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A l’occasion de cette visite officielle de travail à Rabat, le conseiller fédéral Didier Bukhalter rencontrera le chef de la diplomatie marocaine, M. El Othmani. Il s’entretiendra par ailleurs avec le chef du gouvernement marocain, M. Benkirane, et le ministre marocain de l’intérieur, M. Laenser. Ce déplacement sera notamment l’occasion de la signature d’un accord cadre pour la coopération internationale entre le Royaume du Maroc et la Suisse. Cet accord traite des questions de transition démocratique et des droits de l’homme, de développement économique et de création d’emplois et de migration.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Communication DFAE Palais fédéral ouest CH-3003 Berne Tél. Service de communication: +41 58 462 31 53 Tél. Service de presse: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <link id="114063">
        <title>Voyage du conseiller fédéral Didier Burkhalter au Maroc</title>
        <uri>http://www.dfae.admin.ch/eda/fr/home/dfa/head/hoeven/mar.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="114047">
        <title>Relations bilatérales avec le Maroc</title>
        <uri>http://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/home/reps/afri/vmar/bilmar.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="114048">
        <title>Recouvrement des capacités de la Protection civile marocaine</title>
        <uri>http://www.deza.admin.ch/fr/Accueil/Projets/Exemples_de_projets/Les_secouristes_volontaires_de_proximite_au_Maroc</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="114049">
        <title>La DDC au Maroc</title>
        <uri>http://www.deza.admin.ch/fr/Accueil/Pays/Afrique_du_Nord/Maroc</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="114050">
        <title>Stratégie pour l’Afrique du Nord 2011-2016</title>
        <uri>http://www.deza.admin.ch/fr/Accueil/Pays/Afrique_du_Nord</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="114051">
        <title>Projets en Afrique du Nord</title>
        <uri>http://www.deza.admin.ch/fr/Home/Laender/Nordafrika/Projekte_in_Nordafrika</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Il consigliere federale Didier Burkhalter in Marocco per una visita ufficiale di lavoro</title>
      <lead>Venerdì 6 settembre 2013 il consigliere federale Didier Burkhalter effettuerà una visita ufficiale di lavoro in Marocco, che sarà il primo viaggio ufficiale di un capo della diplomazia svizzera in questo Paese. Didier Burkhalter incontrerà il ministro marocchino degli affari esteri e della cooperazione Saad-Eddine El Othmani, il capo di Governo Abdelilah Benkirane e il ministro dell'interno Mohand Laenser.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Le relazioni tra la Svizzera e il Marocco sono ottime e molto diversificate. I ministeri degli affari esteri dei due Paesi organizzano regolarmente consultazioni politiche dal 2009. L'ultima volta hanno avuto luogo nel gennaio 2013 a Rabat, in presenza del segretario di Stato del Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri (DFAE) Yves Rossier. Tali consultazioni mirano a identificare i nuovi assi di cooperazione e a rafforzare quest'ultima in ambiti come la cooperazione allo sviluppo, le riforme democratiche e il buon governo, la sicurezza umana, i diritti dell'uomo e il dialogo in materia di migrazione. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In occasione di questa visita ufficiale di lavoro a Rabat, il consigliere federale Didier Burkhalter incontrerà il capo della diplomazia marocchina Saad-Eddine El Othmani, ma anche il capo del Governo marocchino Abdelilah Benkirane e il ministro marocchino dell'interno Mohand Laenser. Questo viaggio sarà in particolare l'occasione per firmare un accordo quadro per la cooperazione internazionale tra il Regno del Marocco e la Svizzera, che tratta questioni come la transizione democratica e i diritti dell’uomo, lo sviluppo economico e la creazione di impieghi nonché la migrazione.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Comunicazione DFAE Palazzo federale ovest CH-3003 Berna Tel. Servizio di comunicazione: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Servizio stampa: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <link id="114064">
        <title>Viaggio del consigliere federale Didier Burkhalter in Marocco (fr)</title>
        <uri>http://www.dfae.admin.ch/eda/fr/home/dfa/head/hoeven/mar.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="114052">
        <title>Relazioni bilaterali con il Marocco</title>
        <uri>http://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/home/reps/afri/vmar/bilmar.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="114053">
        <title>Recupero delle capacità della Protezione civile marocchina</title>
        <uri>http://www.deza.admin.ch/it/Pagina_iniziale/Progetti/Progetti_selezionati/Volontari_di_primo_soccorso_in_Marocco</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="114054">
        <title>La DSC in Marocco</title>
        <uri>http://www.deza.admin.ch/it/Pagina_iniziale/Paesi/Nordafrica/Marocco</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="114055">
        <title>Strategia per il Nord Africa 2011-2016</title>
        <uri>http://www.deza.admin.ch/it/Pagina_iniziale/Paesi/Nordafrica</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="114056">
        <title>Progetti in Nord Africa</title>
        <uri>http://www.deza.admin.ch/it/Pagina_iniziale/Paesi/Nordafrica/Projekte_in_Nordafrika</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Federal Councillor Didier Burkhalter on official working visit to Morocco</title>
      <lead>Federal Councillor Didier Burkhalter will make an official working visit to Morocco on Friday 6 September 2013. It is the first official visit of a head of Swiss diplomacy to the country. Mr Burkhalter will meet with the Moroccan minister for foreign affairs and cooperation, Saad-Eddine El Othmani. He will also talk with the Moroccan head of government, Abdelilah Benkirane, and interior minister, Mohand Laenser.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Relations between Switzerland and Morocco are excellent and very diverse. The foreign ministries of the two countries have regularly held political consultations since 2009. The most recent consultations took place in January 2013 in Rabat, in the presence of the state secretary of the Federal Department of Foreign Affairs (FDFA), Yves Rossier. The aim of these consultations is to identify new avenues for cooperation and to strengthen cooperation in areas such as development, democratic reform and good governance, human security, human rights and dialogue on migration. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;During his official working visit to Rabat, Federal Councillor Didier Burkhalter will meet the head of Moroccan diplomacy, Mr El Othmani. He will also talk with the Moroccan head of government, Mr Benkirane, and the interior minister, Mr Laenser. This trip will in particular be the opportunity to sign a framework agreement on international cooperation with the Kingdom of Morocco. The agreement covers issues of democratic transition and human rights, economic development and job creation, as well as migration.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>FDFA Communication Federal Palace West Wing CH-3003 Bern, Switzerland Tel. Communication service: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Press service: +41 58 460 55 55 E-mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @SwissMFA</contact>
      <link id="114065">
        <title>Visit by Federal Councillor Didier Burkhalter to Morocco (fr)</title>
        <uri>http://www.dfae.admin.ch/eda/fr/home/dfa/head/hoeven/mar.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="114057">
        <title>Bilateral relations with Morocco</title>
        <uri>http://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home/reps/afri/vmar/bilmar.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="114058">
        <title>Building up the capacities of the Moroccan civil protection services</title>
        <uri>http://www.deza.admin.ch/en/Accueil/Projets/Exemples_de_projets/Les_secouristes_volontaires_de_proximite_au_Maroc</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="114059">
        <title>The SDC in Morocco</title>
        <uri>http://www.deza.admin.ch/en/Accueil/Pays/Afrique_du_Nord/Maroc</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="114060">
        <title>North Africa strategy 2011-2016</title>
        <uri>http://www.deza.admin.ch/en/Home/Countries/North_Africa</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="114061">
        <title>Projects in North Africa</title>
        <uri>http://www.deza.admin.ch/en/Home/Countries/North_Africa/Projekte_in_Nordafrika</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
