<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="50664" revoked="no">
    <version>2</version>
    <pubdate>2013-10-23</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="1070" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>1070</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Der Bundesrat</name>
      <name lang="fr">Conseil fédéral</name>
      <name lang="it">Il Consiglio federale</name>
      <name lang="en">The Federal Council</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.admin.ch/gov/de/start.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.admin.ch/gov/fr/accueil.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.admin.ch/gov/it/pagina-iniziale.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.admin.ch/gov/en/start.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="401" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>401</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Justiz- und Polizeidepartement</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de justice et police</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale di giustizia e polizia</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Justice and Police</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.ejpd.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.ejpd.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.ejpd.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.ejpd.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-ejpd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">Info@gs-ejpd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-ejpd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-ejpd.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="405" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>401</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Staatssekretariat für Migration</name>
      <name lang="fr">Secrétariat d’Etat aux migrations</name>
      <name lang="it">Segreteria di Stato della migrazione</name>
      <name lang="en">State Secretariat for Migration</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.sem.admin.ch/sem/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.sem.admin.ch/sem/fr/home.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.sem.admin.ch/sem/it/home.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.sem.admin.ch/sem/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@sem.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@sem.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@sem.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@sem.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="1070">
      <name lang="de">Der Bundesrat</name>
      <name lang="fr">Conseil fédéral</name>
      <name lang="it">Il Consiglio federale</name>
      <name lang="en">The Federal Council</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.admin.ch/gov/de/start.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.admin.ch/gov/fr/accueil.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.admin.ch/gov/it/pagina-iniziale.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.admin.ch/gov/en/start.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <department id="401">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Justiz- und Polizeidepartement</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de justice et police</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale di giustizia e polizia</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Justice and Police</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.ejpd.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.ejpd.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.ejpd.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.ejpd.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-ejpd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">Info@gs-ejpd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-ejpd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-ejpd.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Der Bundesrat lehnt die Ecopop-Initiative ab</title>
      <lead>Der Bundesrat hat am Mittwoch die Botschaft zur Eidgenössischen Volksinitiative "Stopp der Überbevölkerung – zur Sicherung der natürlichen Lebensgrundlagen" verabschiedet. Er beantragt dem Parlament, die Initiative Volk und Ständen ohne Gegenentwurf zu unterbreiten, mit der Empfehlung, sie abzulehnen. Der Bundesrat hatte diesen Beschluss bereits am 29. Mai 2013 gefasst und erläutert. Die Botschaft, die er nun vorlegt, macht noch einmal deutlich, dass Ziele und Inhalt der Initiative weder mit der heutigen Migrationspolitik der Schweiz noch mit der schweizerischen Praxis im Bereich der internationalen Entwicklungszusammenarbeit vereinbar sind.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Die Volksinitiative verlangt eine fixe Obergrenze für die Zuwanderung und damit eine grundsätzlich neue Zuwanderungspolitik. Konkret verlangt sie, dass die ständige Wohnbevölkerung in der Schweiz infolge Zuwanderung nicht um mehr als 0,2 Prozent pro Jahr wachsen darf. Zudem gibt die Initiative vor, dass der Bund mindestens 10 Prozent seiner Mittel für die Entwicklungszusammenarbeit in die Förderung der freiwilligen Familienplanung investieren muss. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Die Limite für Aufenthaltsbewilligungen würde auch für das Asylwesen, die humanitäre Aufnahme sowie den Familiennachzug gelten. In diesen Bereichen ist die Schweiz allerdings an gewisse verfassungs- und völkerrechtliche Verpflichtungen gebunden. Zudem hätten die verschiedenen Branchen der Wirtschaft entsprechend schlechtere Aussichten auf die notwendigen ausländischen Arbeitskräfte.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Bewährte Migrationspolitik im Interesse der Wirtschaft &lt;br /&gt;&lt;/b&gt;Die heutige Migrationspolitik basiert auf der Personenfreizügigkeit mit der EU sowie einer eingeschränkten Zulassung von Drittstaatsangehörigen. Die Zuwanderung aus der EU wird in erster Linie durch den Bedarf der Wirtschaft nach Arbeitskräften beeinflusst. Die Initiative würde es den Branchen durch eine strenge Beschränkung der Zuwanderung in die Schweiz verunmöglichen, die nötigen Arbeitskräfte zu beschaffen. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Würde die Volksinitiative angenommen, müssten für alle Kategorien von Bewilligungen für Aufenthalte von über einem Jahr Kontingente festgelegt werden. Dies wäre aufgrund der Vielzahl unterschiedlicher Aufenthaltskategorien sowie aufgrund der divergierenden Interessen der betroffenen Branchen eine höchst komplexe Aufgabe, die mit grossem administrativem Aufwand verbunden wäre.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Eine Annahme der Initiative könnte dazu führen, dass das Freizügigkeitsabkommen (FZA) gekündigt würde. Aufgrund der Guillotine-Klausel treten bei einer Kündigung des FZA nach sechs Monaten alle anderen betroffenen Abkommen der Bilateralen I ausser Kraft. Dies würde der Schweiz und ihrer Wirtschaft erheblichen Schaden zufügen, ist die EU doch der wichtigste Handelspartner der Schweiz.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Bewährte Praxis der Schweiz im Bereich der Entwicklungszusammenarbeit &lt;br /&gt;&lt;/b&gt;Die Initiative fordert neben einer Obergrenze bei den Aufenthaltsbewilligungen, dass 10 Prozent der Mittel der Entwicklungszusammenarbeit für Massnahmen im Bereich der freiwilligen Familienplanung zu verwenden sind. Die langjährigen Erfahrungen der Schweiz in der Entwicklungszusammenarbeit zeigen, dass isolierte Einzelmassnahmen nicht zielführend sind. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Eine Annahme der Initiative hätte zur Folge, dass die Schweiz Projekte im Bereich der freiwilligen Familienplanung in Entwicklungsländern selbst dann durchführen müsste, wenn deren Wirkung nachweislich beschränkt wäre. Auch müssten für wichtige andere Massnahmen die finanziellen Mittel gekürzt werden, was mit Blick auf die Zielsetzung der Initianten sogar kontraproduktive Folgen haben könnte.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Der Bundesrat beantragt der Bundesversammlung, die Initiative ohne Gegenentwurf Volk und Ständen zu unterbreiten, mit der Empfehlung, sie abzulehnen.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Agnès Schenker, Mediensprecherin EJPD, Tel. +41 31 322 40 05</contact>
      <link id="120866">
        <title>Die Dokumente zu dieser Medienmitteilung finden Sie auf der Website des EJPD</title>
        <uri>http://www.ejpd.admin.ch/content/ejpd/de/home/dokumentation/mi/2013/2013-10-230.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions>
        <revision date="2014-03-31 10:57" type="I"/>
      </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Le Conseil fédéral rejette l'initiative Ecopop</title>
      <lead>Le Conseil fédéral a approuvé mercredi le message relatif à l'initiative fédérale "Halte à la surpopulation – Oui à la préservation durable des ressources naturelles". Il propose au Parlement de soumettre l'initiative au vote du peuple et des cantons sans lui opposer de contre-projet et en leur recommandant de la rejeter. Le Conseil fédéral avait déjà fait connaître sa décision le 29 mai 2013. Le message qu'il présente rappelle une nouvelle fois de manière claire que les objectifs et le contenu de l'initiative ne sont compatibles ni avec l'actuelle politique de la Suisse en matière de migrations ni avec la pratique suisse dans le domaine de la coopération internationale au développement.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;L'initiative vise l'instauration d'un plafond fixe pour l'immigration et donc un changement de cap de la politique menée par la Suisse en matière d'immigration. Concrètement, la part de l'accroissement de la population résidant de manière permanente en Suisse qui est attribuable au solde migratoire ne doit pas excéder 0,2 % par an. L'initiative indique également que la Confédération doit affecter à l'encouragement de la planification familiale volontaire 10 % au moins des moyens qu'elle consacre à la coopération internationale au développement. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;La limite pour les autorisations de séjour s'appliquerait aussi au domaine de l'asile, à l'admission pour raisons humanitaires et au regroupement familial. Dans ces domaines, la Suisse est cependant liée par un certain nombre d'obligations constitutionnelles et de droit international. Qui plus est, les différentes branches de l'économie éprouveraient davantage de difficultés à recruter la main-d'œuvre étrangère nécessaire.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Une politique migratoire éprouvée qui va dans l'intérêt de l'économie&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/b&gt;La politique actuelle en matière de migrations repose sur la libre circulation des personnes avec l'UE et sur une admission limitée de ressortissants d'Etats tiers. L'immigration en provenance de l'UE est déterminée en premier lieu par les besoins de main-d'œuvre de l'économie. En limitant de manière stricte l'immigration en Suisse, l'initiative empêcherait les différents secteurs économiques de recruter les travailleurs dont ils ont besoin. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Si l'initiative était acceptée, il faudrait fixer des contingents pour toutes les catégories d'autorisations délivrées pour des séjours d'une durée supérieure à un an. Cette tâche, particulièrement complexe en raison de la multitude de catégories de séjour et des intérêts divergents des secteurs concernés, engendrerait une charge administrative importante.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Une acceptation de l'initiative pourrait entraîner la dénonciation de l'accord sur la libre circulation des personnes (ALCP). En raison de la "clause guillotine", une dénonciation de l'ALCP rendrait automatiquement caducs, six mois plus tard, tous les autres accords de la première série d'accords bilatéraux. Une telle situation porterait un grave préjudice à la Suisse et à son économie, car l'UE est le principal partenaire commercial du pays.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;La pratique éprouvée de la Suisse dans le domaine de la coopération au développement&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/b&gt;Outre l'instauration d'un plafond pour les autorisations de séjour, l'initiative demande que 10 % des moyens consacrés à la coopération internationale au développement soient affectés à la planification familiale volontaire. L'expérience de longue date de la Suisse en matière de coopération au développement montre que des mesures individuelles isolées ne sont pas adéquates. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;En cas d'acceptation de l'initiative, la Suisse devrait mener des projets de planification familiale volontaire dans des pays en développement même s'il était prouvé que ces projets n'ont qu'un effet limité. Par ailleurs, les moyens financiers consacrés à d'autres mesures importantes devraient être réduits ce qui, au vu des objectifs visés par les auteurs de l'initiative, pourrait avoir des conséquences contre-productives.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Le Conseil fédéral propose à l'Assemblée fédérale de soumettre l'initiative au peuple et aux cantons sans contre-projet, en leur recommandant de la rejeter.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Agnès Schenker, porte-parole du DFJP, tél. +41 31 322 40 05</contact>
      <link id="120867">
        <title>Vous trouverez les documents relatifs à ce communiqué de presse sur le site internet du DFJP</title>
        <uri>http://www.ejpd.admin.ch/content/ejpd/fr/home/dokumentation/mi/2013/2013-10-230.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions>
        <revision date="2014-03-31 10:57" type="I"/>
      </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Il Consiglio federale respinge l’iniziativa Ecopop</title>
      <lead>Mercoledì il Consiglio federale ha adottato il messaggio concernente l’iniziativa popolare "Stop alla sovrappopolazione - sì alla conservazione delle basi naturali della vita". Propone al Parlamento di sottoporla, senza controprogetto, al voto del Popolo e dei Cantoni, con la raccomandazione di respingerla. Il Consiglio federale aveva preso e spiegato questa decisione già il 29 maggio 2013. Il messaggio che ora presenta ribadisce che gli obiettivi e il contenuto dell’iniziativa non sono compatibili né con la politica in materia di migrazione della Svizzera né con la prassi adottata dal nostro Paese nella cooperazione internazionale allo sviluppo.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;L'iniziativa popolare prevede di introdurre un limite massimo fisso all'immigrazione e quindi una politica d'immigrazione radicalmente nuova. Concretamente chiede che la crescita annua della popolazione svizzera residente in seguito all'immigrazione non superi lo 0,2 per cento. Inoltre, impone alla Confederazione di investire nella promozione della pianificazione familiare volontaria il 10 per cento dei fondi previsti per la cooperazione allo sviluppo.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Il limite previsto per i permessi di soggiorno si applicherebbe anche al settore dell'asilo, all'accoglienza per motivi umanitari e al ricongiungimento familiare. In questi settori la Svizzera è tuttavia vincolata da obblighi costituzionali e impegni internazionali. I diversi rami dell'economia avrebbero inoltre difficoltà ad assumere i lavoratori stranieri di cui hanno bisogno.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Politica migratoria consolidata nell'interesse dell'economia&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/b&gt;L'attuale politica migratoria si fonda sulla libera circolazione delle persone con l'UE e su un'ammissione limitata di cittadini di Stati terzi. L'immigrazione proveniente dall'UE è influenzata soprattutto dal bisogno di manodopera dell'economia. Limitando fortemente l'immigrazione verso la Svizzera, l'iniziativa impedirebbe ai diversi rami dell'economia di assumere i lavoratori di cui hanno bisogno.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In caso di accettazione dell'iniziativa popolare, occorrerebbe fissare dei contingenti per tutte le categorie di permessi di soggiorno superiori a un anno. In considerazione dei vari tipi di soggiorno e degli interessi divergenti dei rami economici interessati, tale compito sarebbe estremamente complesso e comporterebbe notevoli oneri amministrativi.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;L'approvazione dell‘iniziativa potrebbe portare alla denuncia dell'Accordo sulla libera circolazione delle persone (ALC). Secondo la clausola ghigliottina, sei mesi dopo la denuncia dell'ALC cessano di essere applicati anche gli altri accordi bilaterali I. Considerato che l'UE rappresenta il partner commerciale più importante della Svizzera, le conseguenze di una simile denuncia sarebbero molto dannose per la Svizzera e la sua economia.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Prassi consolidata della Svizzera nella cooperazione internazionale allo sviluppo &lt;br /&gt;&lt;/b&gt;Oltre a limitare i permessi di soggiorno, l'iniziativa popolare chiede di investire in provvedimenti per la pianificazione familiare volontaria il 10 per cento dei fondi previsti per la cooperazione allo sviluppo. L'esperienza pluriennale della Svizzera nella cooperazione allo sviluppo mostra che singole misure isolate non permettono di raggiungere gli obiettivi. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Con l'accettazione dell'iniziativa, la Svizzera dovrebbe svolgere progetti nel settore della pianificazione familiare volontaria nei Paesi in via di sviluppo anche nel caso in cui la loro efficacia fosse manifestamente limitata. Occorrerebbe inoltre ridurre i mezzi finanziari per altre misure importanti, il che potrebbe essere controproducente anche alla luce degli obiettivi dei promotori dell'iniziativa popolare. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Il Consiglio federale propone all'Assemblea federale di sottoporre l'iniziativa popolare, senza controprogetto, al Popolo e ai Cantoni con la raccomandazione di respingerla.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Agnès Schenker, portavoce DFGP, tel. +41 31 322 40 05</contact>
      <link id="120868">
        <title>I documenti relativi al presente comunicato stampa sono reperibili sul sito del DFGP</title>
        <uri>http://www.ejpd.admin.ch/content/ejpd/it/home/dokumentation/mi/2013/2013-10-230.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions>
        <revision date="2014-03-31 10:57" type="I"/>
      </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Federal Council rejects Ecopop Initiative</title>
      <lead>The Federal Council has issued a dispatch on the federal popular initiative entitled ‘Stop overpopulation – safeguard our natural environment’. Parliament is requested to put the initiative to the vote among the electorate and cantons, with the recommendation to reject the proposal. Furthermore, no direct counter-proposal to the initiative is made. When it presented its discussion paper on 29 May 2013, the Federal Council was already of the opinion that the objectives and content of the initiative could not be reconciled either with Switzerland’s current immigration policy nor with Swiss practice in international development cooperation.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;The popular initiative foresees imposing a cap on immigration, which would represent a fundamentally new approach in immigration policy. It proposes that the permanent population of Switzerland should not increase by more than 0.2 per cent annually as the result of immigration. The initiative also proposes that at least 10 per cent of federal funds earmarked for development cooperation should be spent on promoting voluntary family planning.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The cap on residence permits would also apply to asylum seekers, persons granted entry on humanitarian grounds and those wanting to be reunited with a family member already in Switzerland. In these areas Switzerland is, however, bound by certain requirements under the Constitution and international agreements. Furthermore, the various economic sectors would have less opportunity to recruit the foreign labour they require. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Current immigration policy in the interests of the economy &lt;br /&gt;&lt;/b&gt;Current immigration policy is based on the free movement of persons with the EU and on allowing a restricted number of persons from non-EU states to enter Switzerland. Immigration from the EU is steered primarily by the economy's need for labour. Greatly restricting immigration into Switzerland, as proposed by the initiative, would mean that some sectors of the economy would be unable to recruit the workers they require. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;If the popular initiative is accepted, quotas for residence permits of more than one year would need to be set for all permit categories. As there are so many different categories, and the interests of the various economic sectors are so divergent, this would be an exceedingly complex and expensive administrative task.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Swiss practice in development cooperation tried and tested &lt;br /&gt;&lt;/b&gt;In addition to the cap on residence permits, the initiative requires that 10 per cent of funds earmarked for development cooperation should be spent on measures to promote voluntary family planning. Long-term experience in Switzerland in the field of development cooperation has shown that isolated measures prove to be ineffective. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;If the initiative is accepted, Switzerland would need to carry out projects in voluntary family planning in developing countries even if their effect was shown to be limited. It would also mean a reduction in funding for other important measures, and this could actually be counterproductive to the aims of the initiative.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Federal Council requests the Federal Assembly to present the initiative to the electorate and cantons without a counter-proposal, recommending that it should be rejected. &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Agnès Schenker, media spokesperson FJPD, tel. +41 31 322 40 05</contact>
      <link id="120869">
        <title>Go to the Web site of the FDJP for documents pertinent to this media release</title>
        <uri>http://www.ejpd.admin.ch/content/ejpd/en/home/dokumentation/mi/2013/2013-10-230.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions>
        <revision date="2014-03-31 10:57" type="I"/>
      </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="10">
        <name lang="de">Bundesrat</name>
        <name lang="fr">Conseil fédéral</name>
        <name lang="it">Consiglio federale</name>
        <name lang="en">Federal Council</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="20">
        <name lang="de">Migration</name>
        <name lang="fr">Migrations</name>
        <name lang="it">Migrazione</name>
        <name lang="en">Migration</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
