<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="51077" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2013-11-22</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="yes" id="502" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>501</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Generalsekretariat VBS</name>
      <name lang="fr">Secrétariat général du DDPS</name>
      <name lang="it">Segreteria generale del DDPS</name>
      <name lang="en">General Secretariat DDPS</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.vbs.admin.ch/</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.vbs.admin.ch/</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.vbs.admin.ch/</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.vbs.admin.ch/</www>
      <email lang="de">postmaster.vbs@gs-vbs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">postmaster.vbs@gs-vbs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">postmaster.vbs@gs-vbs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">postmaster.vbs@gs-vbs.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="1016" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>501</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Teilstreitkraft Luftwaffe</name>
      <name lang="fr">Forces aériennes</name>
      <name lang="it">Forze aeree</name>
      <name lang="en">Air Force</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.lw.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.lw.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.lw.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.lw.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info.lw@vtg.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info.lw@vtg.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info.lw@vtg.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info.lw@vtg.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="501">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Verteidigung, Bevölkerungsschutz und Sport</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de la défense, de la protection de la population et des sports</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale della difesa, della protezione della popolazione e dello sport</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Defence, Civil Protection and Sports DDPS</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.vbs.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.vbs.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.vbs.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.vbs.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@gs-vbs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@gs-vbs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@gs-vbs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@gs-vbs.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Vorverkaufsstart AIR14 und Taufe einer Lokomotive</title>
      <lead>Ab Freitag, 22. November, um 12.00 Uhr sind die Eintrittskarten für die AIR14 PAYERNE online und an allen SBB-Bahnhöfen der Schweiz erhältlich. Diese grosse Airshow wird an zwei Wochenenden, 30. und 31. August sowie 6. und 7. September 2014 auf dem Militärflugplatz Payerne (VD) aufgrund eines dreifachen Jubiläums stattfinden: 100 Jahre Luftwaffe, 50 Jahre Patrouille Suisse und 25 Jahre PC-7 TEAM. Eine Lokomotive in den Farben der Veranstaltung wurde zu diesem Anlass getauft. Sie wird bis im September 2014 auf dem SBB-Netz verkehren.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Im Museum «Clin d'Ailes» in Payerne, inmitten von Flugzeugen und Helikoptern, welche die Schweizer Militäraviatik geprägt haben, hat Oberst im Generalstab Ian Logan, Direktor der AIR14, den Billettverkauf für die internationale Airshow, die am 30. und 31. August sowie am 6. und 7. September 2014 in Payerne stattfinden wird, eröffnet. Die Eintrittskarten sind via www.air14.ch erhältlich, aber auch in allen SBB-Bahnhöfen der Schweiz. «Wir wollen, dass die Veranstaltung ein Treffpunkt für die Bevölkerung wird! Deshalb müssen die Tickets erschwinglich sein», betonte der Direktor vor den Medien. So liegt der Preis für einen einzelnen Tag im Vorverkauf bei 22 Franken und wird später 33 Franken betragen. Für eine Familie - zwei Erwachsene und ihre Kinder, egal wie viele es sind - beträgt der Preis im Vorverkauf 60 Franken. Eine Wochenende kostet beispielsweise für einen Erwachsenen anfangs 40 Franken und später 62 Franken. Eine eigens diesem Anlass gewidmete Website sowie eine AIR14-App für Smartphones (iOS und Android), die ein Kartenspiel mit Flugzeugen für Familien beinhaltet, wurden ebenfalls am Freitag lanciert.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Auch der Bahnhof von Payerne war Teil der Veranstaltung. Eine Lokomotive in den Farben der AIR14 wurde auf dem Gleis 5 getauft. Eine Taufe, die nicht ohne einen Wein der Gemeinde Payerne erfolgen konnte, dem offiziellen Wein der Veranstaltung, der ebenfalls deren Logo trägt. Die Lokomotive wird bis zum Anlass auf dem Netz der SBB verkehren. Besonderen Wert wird auf die Erreichbarkeit der Veranstaltung gelegt, dies unter Einbezug von mehreren Bahnhöfen in der Nähe des Flugplatzes.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Die AIR14 ist eine Airshow, die am 30. und 31. August sowie am 6. und 7. September 2014 am Boden und in der Luft ein vorlockendes Angebot präsentieren wird. Jeden Tag wird ein anderes Programm gezeigt - Teams, Flugzeuge und Helikopter, historisch wie modern. Mit der AIR14 werden 100 Jahre Luftwaffe, 50 Jahre Patrouille Suisse und 25 Jahre PC-7 TEAM würdig gefeiert. Die Schweizer Mittel werden jeden Tag fliegen. Auch Geschichte, Würdigungen und Innovation werden auf dem Militärflugplatz nicht zu kurz kommen.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Laurent Savary Kommunikation AIR14 031 323 22 58</contact>
      <link id="116496">
        <title>Air14 - Payerne</title>
        <uri>http://www.air14.ch</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Ouverture de la billetterie d’AIR14 et baptême d’une locomotive</title>
      <lead>Dès le vendredi 22 novembre à 12h00, les billets d’entrée d’AIR14 PAYERNE sont disponibles en ligne et dans toutes les gares CFF de Suisse. Ce grand rendez-vous aérien aura lieu durant deux week-ends, les 30-31 août et 6-7 septembre 2014 sur la base aérienne de Payerne (VD) à l’occasion d’un triple jubilé : les 100 ans des Forces aériennes, les 50 ans de la Patrouille Suisse et les 25 ans du PC-7 TEAM. Une locomotive aux couleurs de l’événement a été baptisée à cette occasion. Elle circulera jusqu’en septembre 2014 sur le réseau des CFF.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;C'est au Musée Clin d'Ailes de Payerne, au milieu des avions et hélicoptères qui ont marqué l'histoire de l'aviation militaire suisse, que le colonel EMG Ian Logan, directeur d'AIR14, a lancé officiellement l'ouverture de la billetterie de ce meeting aérien international qui se déroulera les 30-31 août et 6-7 septembre 2014 à Payerne. Les sésames sont disponibles via internet, www.air14.ch, mais aussi dans toutes les gares CFF de Suisse. «Nous voulons faire de cet événement un rendez-vous populaire ! Raison pour laquelle les prix devaient être abordables», a affirmé devant la presse le directeur d'AIR14. Le prix d'entrée d'une journée est fixé à 22 francs en prévente, avant de passer à 33 francs au tarif plein. Pour une famille - deux adultes et leurs enfants quel que soit leur nombre - le prix est de 60 francs en prévente. Un weekend coûtera par exemple 40 francs pour un adulte dans un premier temps avant de passer à 62 francs. Un site internet spécialement dédié à cet événement ainsi qu'une application AIR14 pour smartphone (IOS et Androïd), avec notamment un jeu des familles de cartes d'avions, ont également été lancés vendredi.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;La gare de Payerne a également participé à la fête. Une locomotive aux couleurs d'AIR14 a été baptisée sur le quai 5 de la gare broyarde. Un baptême que ne pouvait se faire qu'avec un vin de la commune de Payerne, vin officiel aux couleurs de la manifestation. La locomotive circulera sur le réseau des CFF jusqu'à l'événement. Un accent tout particulier sera mis sur l'accès à la manifestation, notamment avec l'aménagement de plusieurs gares à proximité de la base aérienne.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;AIR14 est un meeting aérien qui proposera, les 30-31 août et 6-7 septembre 2014 à Payerne, un plateau aussi alléchant que varié tant dans les airs qu'au sol. Chaque jour présentera un programme différent, incluant des patrouilles, des avions et hélicoptères anciens comme modernes. Il marquera dignement les 100 ans des Forces aériennes, les 50 ans de la Patrouille Suisse et les 25 ans du PC-7 TEAM. Des appareils suisses qui voleront tous les jours. Outre l'histoire, les hommages et l'innovation trouveront également leur place sur la base aérienne.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Laurent Savary Communication AIR14 031 323 22 58</contact>
      <link id="116496">
        <title>Air14 - Payerne</title>
        <uri>http://www.air14.ch</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Apertura della biglietteria dell'AIR 14 e inaugurazione di una locomotiva</title>
      <lead>A partire dalle ore 12:00 di venerdì 22 novembre, i biglietti d'ingresso per l'AIR14 PAYERNE sono disponibili online e presso tutte le stazioni FFS della Svizzera. Questo grande evento nell'ambito dell'aviazione avrà luogo durante due fine settimana, quello del 30 e 31 agosto e quello del 6 e 7 settembre 2014, presso la base aerea di Payerne in occasione di un triplice anniversario: il centenario delle Forze aeree svizzere, i 50 anni della Patrouille Suisse e i 25 anni del PC-7 TEAM. Una locomotiva con i colori della manifestazione è stata inaugurata per l'occasione. Circolerà fino a settembre 2014 sulla rete ferroviaria delle FFS.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Nel Museo Clin d'Ailes di Payerne, in mezzo agli aerei e agli elicotteri che hanno caratterizzato la storia dell'aviazione militare svizzera, il colonnello SMG Ian Logan, direttore dell'AIR14, ha dato ufficialmente il via all'apertura della biglietteria di questo meeting internazionale nel campo dell'aviazione che si svolgerà il 30 e il 31 agosto come pure il 6 e il 7 settembre a Payerne. I biglietti sono disponibili sul sito Internet www.air14.ch come pure in tutte le stazioni delle FFS. «Vogliamo fare di questo evento un meeting popolare! Ragion per cui i prezzi devono essere abbordabili», ha affermato il direttore davanti ai media. Ad esempio, il costo del biglietto d'ingresso per una giornata è fissato a 22 franchi in prevendita prima di passare a 33 franchi a prezzo intero. Per una famiglia (due adulti e i loro bambini, qualunque sia il loro numero) il prezzo è di 60 franchi alla prevendita. In un primo tempo, un fine settimana costerà ad esempio 40 franchi per un adulto prima di passare a 62 franchi. Allo stesso modo venerdì viene aperto un sito Internet dedicato in modo particolare a questo evento e viene lanciata un'applicazione AIR14 per smartphone (iOS e Android), contenente anche un gioco di carte sull'aviazione.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Anche la stazione di Payerne ha partecipato alla festa. Una locomotiva con i colori dell'AIR14 è stata inaugurata sul binario 5 della stazione locale. Un'inaugurazione che non si poteva fare se non con un vino del Comune di Payerne, vino ufficiale con i colori della manifestazione. La locomotiva circolerà sulla rete delle FFS fino ai giorni dell'evento. Un accento particolare sarà posto sull'accesso alla manifestazione, in special modo con la pianificazione di diverse stazioni nelle vicinanze della base aerea.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;L'AIR14 è un meeting aereo che proporrà il 30 e il 31 agosto come pure il 6 e il 7 settembre a Payerne un programma molto avvincente con molteplici attività al suolo e nel cielo. Ogni giorno avrà un programma differente comprendente pattuglie, aerei ed elicotteri d'epoca e moderni. Ciò contrassegnerà degnamente i 100 anni delle Forze aeree, i 50 anni della Patrouille Suisse e i 25 anni del PC-7 TEAM. Mezzi aerei che voleranno in tutti i giorni della manifestazione. Oltre alla storia, anche l'innovazione e i riconoscimenti avranno il loro posto presso la base aerea di Payerne. &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Laurent Savary Comunicazione AIR14 031 323 22 58</contact>
      <link id="116496">
        <title>Air14 - Payerne</title>
        <uri>http://www.air14.ch</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Advance AIR14 ticket sales and inauguration of a locomotive</title>
      <lead>As of today, Friday 22 November 12 noon, tickets for the AIR14 PAYERNE air show are available online and at any SBB railway station in Switzerland. This major air show on the weekends of 30/31 August and 6/7 September 2014 at Payerne airbase (Canton of Vaud) will commemorate the triple jubilee of 100 years of the Swiss Air Force, 50 years of the Patrouille Suisse and 25 years of the PC-7 TEAM. To mark the occasion, a locomotive will be inaugurated in the event’s colour scheme. It will operate on the Swiss Federal Railways SBB network until September 2014.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;At the Clin d' Ailes museum in Payerne, among the aircraft and helicopters that bear testimony to Switzerland's military aviation history, Colonel GS Ian Logan, Director of AIR14, officially launched the ticket sales for the international airshow to be held on the weekends of 30 and 31 August, and 6 and 7 September 2014 in Payerne. Tickets are now available online at www.air14.ch and at any SBB railway station in Switzerland. "We want this to be an event for the general public, so ticket prices must be affordable," emphasized the Director to the media. Proving his point, one-day tickets can currently be purchased for CHF 22 instead of the later regular price of CHF 33. Advance sale tickets for a family - two adults and their children, regardless of how many - cost CHF 60 for one day. Admission for one weekend for an adult, for example, costs CHF 40 during advance sales; later the price will be increased to CHF 62. A website specially dedicated to the occasion and an AIR14 App for smartphones (iOS and Android), featuring a family aircraft card game, was also launched this Friday.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Payerne railway station also played a role in the festivities. Track 5 saw the inauguration of a locomotive in the AIR14 colour scheme. Naturally, the ceremony could not have taken place without a bottle of wine from Payerne, the official wine in the colour scheme of the event. The locomotive will operate on the SBB network until the air show has taken place. Particular attention will be paid to the access routes to the event, with several railway stations near Payerne air base being specially equipped to meet the challenge of coping with the large numbers of spectators expected.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The AIR14 event on 30/31 August and 6/7 September at Payerne will offer an interesting and varied programme on the ground and in the air. The visitors are promised a different but equally thrilling programme every day, featuring displays of airborne teams, and historic and new aircraft and helicopters. The event will be a fitting celebration of 100 years of the Swiss Air Force, 50 years of the Patrouille Suisse and 25 years of the PC-7 TEAM. Swiss Air Force assets will be airborne every day of the show and special emphasis will be given to history, tributes and innovation. &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Laurent Savary Communication AIR14 031 323 22 58</contact>
      <link id="116496">
        <title>Air14 - Payerne</title>
        <uri>http://www.air14.ch</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <keywords>
      <keyword id="5440" org-id="1016">
        <name lang="de">Veranstaltung</name>
        <name lang="fr">Manifestation</name>
        <name lang="it">Manifestazione</name>
        <name lang="en">Event</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="5180" org-id="1016">
        <name lang="de">Armee</name>
        <name lang="fr">Armée</name>
        <name lang="it">Esercito</name>
        <name lang="en">armed forces</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="5510" org-id="1016">
        <name lang="de">Information / Kommunikation</name>
        <name lang="fr">Information / Communication</name>
        <name lang="it">Informazione / Comunicazione</name>
        <name lang="en">information / communication</name>
      </keyword>
    </keywords>
    <topics>
      <topic id="3">
        <name lang="de">Armee</name>
        <name lang="fr">Armée</name>
        <name lang="it">Esercito</name>
        <name lang="en">Armed Forces</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
