<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="51477" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2013-12-18</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="1070" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>1070</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Der Bundesrat</name>
      <name lang="fr">Conseil fédéral</name>
      <name lang="it">Il Consiglio federale</name>
      <name lang="en">The Federal Council</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.admin.ch/gov/de/start.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.admin.ch/gov/fr/accueil.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.admin.ch/gov/it/pagina-iniziale.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.admin.ch/gov/en/start.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="201" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>201</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="1070">
      <name lang="de">Der Bundesrat</name>
      <name lang="fr">Conseil fédéral</name>
      <name lang="it">Il Consiglio federale</name>
      <name lang="en">The Federal Council</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.admin.ch/gov/de/start.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.admin.ch/gov/fr/accueil.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.admin.ch/gov/it/pagina-iniziale.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.admin.ch/gov/en/start.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <department id="201">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Bundesrat verlängert die Vermögenssperren gegen mehrere Personen aus Tunesien und Ägypten</title>
      <lead>Der Bundesrat beschloss an seiner heutigen Sitzung, die Sperre sämtlicher in der Schweiz gelegenen Vermögenswerte der gestürzten Präsidenten Ben Ali (Tunesien) und Mubarak (Ägypten) sowie von politisch exponierten Personen aus deren Umfeld um drei Jahre zu verlängern. Die Verlängerung bezweckt, den strafrechtlichen Ermittlungen in Tunesien und Ägypten zur Herkunft der Gelder mehr Zeit einzuräumen. Der Bundesrat trägt damit der politischen Umbruchsituation in beiden Ländern Rechnung. </lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Anfang 2011 ordnete der Bundesrat die vorsorgliche Sperre sämtlicher in der Schweiz gelegenen Vermögenswerte der gestürzten Präsidenten Ben Ali (Tunesien) und Mubarak (Ägypten) sowie von politisch exponierten Personen aus deren Umfeld an. Die Sperre ist auf drei Jahre befristet. Ziel der Sperre ist, die Rechtshilfezusammenarbeit in Strafsachen mit den betroffenen Staaten zu erleichtern und so die Voraussetzungen für eine richterliche Überprüfung der Herkunft verdächtiger Gelder zu schaffen. Die Sperren stellen sicher, dass möglicherweise unrechtmässig erworbene Vermögenswerte nicht auf anderen Finanzplätzen versteckt und so der gerichtlichen Klärung entzogen werden. Im Falle Tunesiens sind rund 60 Mio., im Falle Ägyptens rund 700 Mio. CHF gesperrt. Diese Beträge umfassen die Sperrungen auf der Basis der Sperrverordnungen des Bundesrates sowie jene im Rahmen der Rechtshilfe und der Strafverfahren.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In den vergangenen drei Jahren bauten die zuständigen Behörden in der Schweiz eine enge Zusammenarbeit mit den Behörden in Tunesien und Ägypten auf. Dadurch gelang es, wichtige Fortschritte im Hinblick auf die Klärung der Herkunft der in der Schweiz gesperrten Vermögen zu erzielen. Weder im Fall Tunesiens noch zu Ägypten sind die Ermittlungen jedoch heute bereits so weit fortgeschritten, dass die vorsorglichen Vermögenssperren ihren Zweck erfüllt hätten. Deshalb beschloss der Bundesrat, die Sperren um weitere drei Jahre zu verlängern. Dadurch soll den Ermittlungen in Tunesien und Ägypten mehr Zeit eingeräumt und der politischen Umbruchsituation in beiden Ländern Rechnung getragen werden. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Information EDA +41 (0)31 322 31 53</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Le Conseil fédéral prolonge le blocage de fonds décidé à l’encontre de plusieurs personnes provenant de Tunisie et d’Egypte</title>
      <lead>Lors de sa séance d’aujourd’hui, le Conseil fédéral a décidé de prolonger de trois ans le blocage de tous les avoirs en Suisse des présidents déchus Ben Ali (Tunisie) et Moubarak (Egypte) ainsi que de personnes politiquement exposées de leur entourage. Cette décision vise à accorder du temps supplémentaire pour les enquêtes pénales en cours et tient compte de la mutation politique qui s’opère dans ces deux pays. </lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Début 2011, le Conseil fédéral avait ordonné à titre préventif le gel de tous les avoirs en Suisse des présidents déchus Ben Ali (Tunisie) et Moubarak (Egypte) et de ceux de personnes politiquement exposées de leur entourage. Arrêtée pour une durée de trois ans, cette mesure doit faciliter l’entraide judiciaire en matière pénale avec les Etats concernés et créer les conditions favorables au contrôle judiciaire sur l’origine de fonds suspects. Elle permet également d’éviter que des avoirs qui auraient été acquis de manière illicite ne soient dissimulés sur d’autres places financières et n’échappent ainsi au contrôle juridictionnel. Dans le dossier tunisien, environ 60 millions de francs ont été bloqués. Ce montant s’élève à quelque 700 millions de francs pour l’Egypte. Ces sommes correspondent aux gels d’avoirs intervenus sur la base des l’ordonnances de blocage du Conseil fédéral ainsi qu’à ceux s’inscrivant dans le cadre de l’entraide judiciaire et de la procédure pénale.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Au cours des trois dernières années, les autorités compétentes en Suisse ont travaillé en étroite collaboration avec les autorités tunisiennes et égyptiennes afin de déterminer l’origine des avoirs bloqués. Si des progrès importants ont été réalisés en la matière, l’état d’avancement des enquêtes ne permet cependant pas de dire aujourd’hui que les blocages des avoirs à titre préventif ont atteint leur objectif. Le Conseil fédéral, tenant compte de la période de mutation politique que traversent ces deux pays, a donc décidé de prolonger le gel de ces avoirs pour une nouvelle période de trois ans, ce qui laisse plus de temps pour mener à bien les enquêtes. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Information DFAE + 41 (0)31 322 31 53</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Il Consiglio federale proroga il blocco dei beni di varie persone originarie della Tunisia ed Egitto</title>
      <lead>In occasione della sua seduta odierna, il Consiglio federale ha deciso di prorogare per un periodo di ulteriori tre anni il blocco di tutti i valori patrimoniali detenuti in Svizzera dai deposti presidenti Ben Ali (Tunisia) e Mubarak (Egitto) nonché da persone politicamente esposte facenti capo alla loro sfera d’influenza. L'obiettivo della proroga è di concedere più tempo alle indagini penali in corso in Tunisia e in Egitto volte ad accertare la provenienza di tali fondi. Con questa decisione, il Consiglio federale tiene conto del mutato clima politico nei due Paesi. </lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;All'inizio del 2011 il Consiglio federale ha ordinato il blocco, in via cautelativa, di tutti i valori patrimoniali detenuti in Svizzera dai deposti presidenti Ben Ali (Tunisia) e Mubarak (Egitto) nonché da persone politicamente esposte facenti capo alla loro sfera d’influenza. L'obiettivo di tale blocco, originariamente previsto per una durata di tre anni, è di facilitare la cooperazione con i Paesi in questione nell’ambito dell’assistenza giudiziaria in materia penale e di creare le condizioni propizie al fine di una verifica in sede giudiziaria della provenienza dei fondi sospetti. Bloccando i valori patrimoniali si impedisce che eventuali patrimoni illeciti vengano trasferiti su altre piazze finanziarie e, di conseguenza, sottratti all'accertamento giudiziario. Nel caso della Tunisia, i valori bloccati ammontano a circa 60 milioni di franchi, mentre per l’Egitto la somma si aggira sui 700 milioni. Tali importi comprendono sia i blocchi disposti in base alle ordinanze di blocco del Consiglio federale sia quelli decisi nell'ambito dell'assistenza giudiziaria e dei procedimenti penali.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Negli ultimi tre anni, la stretta collaborazione avviata dalle competenti autorità svizzere con le autorità tunisine ed egiziane ha permesso di compiere importanti progressi nell'accertamento della provenienza dei valori patrimoniali bloccati in Svizzera. Tuttavia né in Tunisia né in Egitto le indagini hanno finora prodotto risultati tali da far ritenere raggiunto lo scopo dei blocchi cautelativi dei beni. Il Consiglio federale ha pertanto deciso di prorogare tali blocchi per un periodo di ulteriori tre anni in modo da concedere più tempo alle indagini in corso in Tunisia e in Egitto e di tenere conto in tal modo del mutato clima politico nei due Paesi. &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Informazione DFAE + 41 (0)31 322 31 53</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>The Federal Council extends the freezing of assets of several individuals from Tunisia and Egypt</title>
      <lead>The Federal Council decided during today's session to extend by three years the freezing of all assets held in Switzerland by deposed presidents Ben Ali (Tunisia) and Mubarak (Egypt) and by politically exposed persons in their entourage. The aim of this extension is to provide more time for criminal investigations in Tunisia and Egypt into the origin of these assets. The Federal Council is thereby taking account of the political transition in the two countries. </lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;At the beginning of 2011, the Federal Council ordered the preventive freezing of all assets held in Switzerland by deposed presidents Ben Ali (Tunisia) and Mubarak (Egypt) and by politically exposed persons in their entourage. The assets are frozen for a period of three years. The aim of the asset freeze is to facilitate mutual legal assistance on criminal matters with the affected states and thus to create the preconditions for judicial scrutiny into the origin of suspicious assets. The asset freezes ensure that potentially illicitly acquired assets are not hidden in other financial centres and thus evade judicial clarification. In the case of Tunisia, approximately CHF 60 million has been frozen and in that of Egypt approximately CHF 700 million. These amounts have been frozen pursuant to the Federal Council's ordinances on the freezing of assets, mutual legal assistance and criminal proceedings.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Over the past three years, the competent authorities in Switzerland have established close cooperation with the authorities in Tunisia and Egypt. Thanks to this cooperation, significant progress has been made in determining the origin of assets frozen in Switzerland. Nevertheless, neither in the case of Tunisia nor in that of Egypt have investigations made sufficient progress for the preventive freezing of assets to have achieved its purpose. The Federal Council has therefore decided to extend the asset freezes by another three years. The aim is to give investigations in Tunisia and Egypt more time and to take account of the political transition in the two countries. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>FDFA Information +41 (0)31 322 31 53</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
