<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="8879" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2003-06-24</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="811" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>801</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Bundesamt für Umwelt BAFU</name>
      <name lang="fr">Office fédéral de l'environnement OFEV</name>
      <name lang="it">Ufficio federale dell'ambiente UFAM</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Office for the Environment FOEN</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.bafu.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.bafu.admin.ch/fr</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.bafu.admin.ch/it</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.bafu.admin.ch/en</www>
      <email lang="de">info@bafu.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@bafu.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@bafu.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@bafu.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="801">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Umwelt, Verkehr, Energie und Kommunikation</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'environnement, des transports, de l'énergie et de la communication</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'ambiente, dei trasporti, dell'energia e delle comunicazioni</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of the Environment, Transport, Energy and Communications</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.uvek.admin.ch/uvek/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.uvek.admin.ch/uvek/fr/home.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.uvek.admin.ch/uvek/it/home.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.uvek.admin.ch/uvek/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-uvek.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-uvek.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-uvek.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-uvek.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Meeresschutz-Kommissionen tagen gemeinsam</title>
      <lead>Der Nordostatlantik und die Ostsee sollen umfassender geschützt werden. Vom 25. bis am 26. Juni 2003 tagen daher in Bremen die Kommissionen zum Schutz des Nordostatlantiks (OSPAR) und der Ostsee (HELCOM) erstmals gemeinsam. Die Schweiz als Mitglied des OSPAR-Übereinkommens wird an der Ministerkonferenz durch das BUWAL vertreten sein.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Die beiden Kommissionen OSPAR und HELCOM setzen sich für den Schutz des Nordostatlantiks und der Ostsee ein. Ihre Mitgliedstaaten sind unter anderem dazu verpflichtet, die Meeresüberdüngung zu bekämpfen, Einträge von Schadstoffen und radioaktiven Substanzen im Meer zu verringern und die Ökosysteme der Meeresgebiete zu erhalten. Die Schweiz als Oberlieger im Einzugsgebiet der Nordsee ist seit 1998 Mitglied der OSPAR.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Schutz der Meere mit vereinten Kräften vorantreiben&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;An der gemeinsamen Ministerkonferenz von OSPAR und HELCOM sollen Ziele definiert werden für eine nachhaltige Nutzung der beiden Meeresregionen und den Schutz der Meeresökosysteme. Die Kommissionen wollen zudem Vorschläge erarbeiten für die zukünftige «Strategie zum Schutz und zur Erhaltung des Meeresumwelt» der Europäischen Union. Weiter soll bis 2010 ein gemeinsames Netzwerk von Meeresschutzzonen entstehen zum Erhalt der Biodiversität in den Meeren und den Küstengebieten. Der Beeinträchtigung der Meeresumwelt durch Hochseefischerei und -schiffahrt wollen OSPAR und HELCOM durch eine engere Zusammenarbeit mit den betreffenden internationalen Behörden begegnen.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Binnenland Schweiz ist mitverantwortlich für saubere Meere&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Mit der Teilnahme an der Konferenz in Bremen zeigt die Schweiz ihre Bereitschaft, gemeinsame Strategien zur Lösung der aktuellen Umweltprobleme auf europäischer Ebene mitzutragen. Im Wissen um die grosse Bedeutung der Meeresökosysteme als Lebensgrundlage unterstützt sie auch als Binnenland die Massnahmen zur Rettung und Erhaltung der Qualität von Ostsee und Nordostatlantik.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Die beiden Kommissionen wollen sich an ihrer gemeinsamen Konferenz offiziell zum Ökosystemansatz bekennen. Sie übernehmen damit ein Prinzip, das auch in der schweizerischen Umweltzusammenarbeit wichtig ist. Indem die Schweiz die Ökosysteme der hier entspringenden Flüsse nachhaltig schützt, kann sie einen direkten Beitrag zum internationalen Meeresumweltschutz leisten, denn das Wasser gelangt in die europäischen Meere.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Auskünfte Botschafter Beat Nobs Abt. Internationales BUWAL Tel. 031 322 93 23 Ulrich Sieber Abt. Gewässerschutz und Fischerei BUWAL Tel. 031 322 69 69</contact>
      <link id="16437">
        <title>OSPAR: Kommission zum Schutz des Nordostatlantiks (englisch und französisch)</title>
        <uri>http://www.ospar.org/</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="16440">
        <title>HELCOM: Kommission zum Schutz der Ostsee (englisch)</title>
        <uri>http://www.helcom.fi/</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Commissions pour la protection du milieu marin vont siéger ensemble</title>
      <lead>L’Atlantique du Nord-Est et la mer Baltique doivent être mieux protégés. Dans cette optique, la Commission pour la protection du milieu marin de l’Atlantique du Nord-Est (OSPAR) ainsi que celle pour la mer Baltique (HELCOM) vont siéger pour la première fois ensemble, les 25 et 26 juin à Brême. La Suisse, membre de la Convention OSPAR, sera représentée par l’OFEFP à la réunion ministérielle.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Les conventions OSPAR et HELCOM visent à protéger les milieux marins de l’Atlantique du Nord-Est et de la mer Baltique. Les Etats membres de ces deux commissions s’engagent entre autres à lutter contre l’eutrophisation, à limiter les rejets de polluants et de substances radioactives dans la mer ainsi qu’à préserver les écosystèmes des zones maritimes. Depuis 1998, la Suisse est membre de la Convention OSPAR au titre de pays appartenant à la partie supérieure du bassin versant de la mer du Nord.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;S’unir pour mieux protéger les mers&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;La réunion ministérielle commune aux commissions OSPAR et HELCOM doit permettre de fixer des objectifs pour les deux zones maritimes en termes de gestion durable et de protection des écosystèmes marins. Les commissions veulent en outre élaborer des propositions pour la future «stratégie maritime européenne». Un réseau commun de zones maritimes protégées doit être créé d’ici à 2010 dans le but de préserver la biodiversité des mers et des zones côtières. Les commissions OSPAR et HELCOM veulent parer aux nuisances causées à l’environnement marin par la pêche en haute mer et la navigation maritime, grâce à une meilleure collaboration avec les autorités internationales concernées par ce problème.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Le rôle de la Suisse&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;En participant à la réunion ministérielle à Brême, la Suisse montre qu’elle est prête à s’investir dans des stratégies communes pour résoudre les problèmes écologiques à l’échelle européenne. Consciente de la fonction vitale des écosystèmes marins, la Suisse, pays sans littoral, soutient les mesures visant à sauver et à préserver la mer Baltique et l’Atlantique du Nord-Est.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Au cours de leur réunion commune, les deux commissions ont l’intention de se prononcer officiellement pour une approche écosystémique du problème. Ce principe est également adopté par la coopération environnementale de notre pays. La Suisse peut ainsi contribuer directement à la protection des mers en protégeant durablement ses rivières, l’eau de ces dernières atteignant par la suite les mers européennes.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Renseignements Beat Nobs Ambassadeur Chef de la division Affaires internationales, OFEFP Tél. 031 322 93 23 Ulrich Sieber Division Protection des eaux et pêche, OFEFP Tél. 031 322 69 69</contact>
      <link id="16438">
        <title>Commission pour la protection du milieu marin de l’Atlantique du Nord-Est (OSPAR)</title>
        <uri>http://www.ospar.org/fr/html/welcome.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="16441">
        <title>Commission pour la protection de la mer Baltique (HELCOM; en anglais)</title>
        <uri>http://www.helcom.fi/</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Joint meeting between the commissions for the protection of the oceans</title>
      <lead>The North-East Atlantic and the Baltic Sea require more comprehensive protection. The commissions for the protection of the North-East Atlantic (OSPAR) and the Baltic Sea (HELCOM) will hold a joint meeting for the first time in Bremen from 25 to 26 June 2003 to address this issue. Switzerland, as a member of the OSPAR Convention, will be represented at the Joint Ministerial Meeting by the SAEFL.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Both the OSPAR and HELCOM commissions support the protection of the North-East Atlantic and the Baltic Sea. The member states are committed to combating the over-fertilisation of the ocean, reducing the entry hazardous and radioactive substances into the ocean, and the conservation of the ecosystems of the marine environment. Switzerland is an upstream country of the rivers flowing into the North Sea and has been a member of OSPAR since 1998.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Joining forces to promote the protection of the oceans&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;At the joint ministerial meeting, the OSPAR and HELCOM commissions plan to define goals for the sustainable use of both marine environments and for the protection of the marine ecosystems. The commissions also intend to develop proposals for the future European «Strategy for the Protection and Conservation of the Marine Environment». A joint network of marine protection zones should be developed by 2010 for the conservation of ocean and coastal area biodiversity. OSPAR and HELCOM want to work more closely with the relevant international authorities to address damage to the marine environment caused by deep sea fishing and navigation.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Land-locked Switzerland also has responsibility for clean oceans&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Switzerland’s participation in the conference shows its willingness to endorse joint strategies for solving the current environmental problems on a European level. Even though Switzerland is a land-locked country, it is aware of the great importance of marine ecosystems in terms of livelihood and supports the measures to save and conserve the quality of the Baltic Sea and the North-East Atlantic.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;At the joint meeting, the two commissions intend to officially commit themselves to the ecosystem approach. In so doing, they will be adopting a principle that is also important in Swiss environmental cooperation. By sustainably protecting the ecosystems of the source rivers which flow into the European oceans, Switzerland can make a direct contribution to the international protection of the marine environment.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Information Ambassador Beat Nobs International Affairs Division, SAEFL Tel. +41 (0)31 322 93 23 Ulrich Sieber Division of Water Protection and Fisheries, SAEFL Tel. +41 (0)31 322 69 69</contact>
      <link id="16439">
        <title>Commission for the protection of the North-East Atlantic (OSPAR)</title>
        <uri>http://www.ospar.org/eng/html/welcome.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="16442">
        <title>Commissions for the protection of the Baltic Sea (HELCOM)</title>
        <uri>http://www.helcom.fi/</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <keywords>
      <keyword id="1390" org-id="811">
        <name lang="de">Wasser</name>
        <name lang="fr">Eaux</name>
        <name lang="it">Acqua</name>
        <name lang="en">Water</name>
      </keyword>
    </keywords>
    <topics>
      <topic id="29">
        <name lang="de">Umwelt und Natur</name>
        <name lang="fr">Environnement et nature</name>
        <name lang="it">Ambiente e natura</name>
        <name lang="en">Environment and Nature</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
