<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="50425" revoked="no">
    <version>2</version>
    <pubdate>2013-09-30</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="yes" id="502" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>501</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Generalsekretariat VBS</name>
      <name lang="fr">Secrétariat général du DDPS</name>
      <name lang="it">Segreteria generale del DDPS</name>
      <name lang="en">General Secretariat DDPS</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.vbs.admin.ch/</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.vbs.admin.ch/</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.vbs.admin.ch/</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.vbs.admin.ch/</www>
      <email lang="de">postmaster.vbs@gs-vbs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">postmaster.vbs@gs-vbs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">postmaster.vbs@gs-vbs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">postmaster.vbs@gs-vbs.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="201" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>201</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="501">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Verteidigung, Bevölkerungsschutz und Sport</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de la défense, de la protection de la population et des sports</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale della difesa, della protezione della popolazione e dello sport</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Defence, Civil Protection and Sports DDPS</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.vbs.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.vbs.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.vbs.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.vbs.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@gs-vbs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@gs-vbs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@gs-vbs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@gs-vbs.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <department id="201">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Staatsbesuch des finnischen Präsidenten Sauli Niinistö vom 15. - 16.10.2013</title>
      <lead>Auf Einladung des Bundesrats wird der Präsident der Republik Finnland Sauli Niinistö der Schweiz am 15./16.10.2013 einen Staatsbesuch abstatten. An den offiziellen Gesprächen wird neben europapolitischen und wirtschaftlichen Fragen sowie Themen von internationaler Aktualität namentlich die Kooperation im sicherheitspolitischen Bereich im Vordergrund stehen.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Am 15. Oktober 2013 wird der Präsident Finnlands vom Gesamtbundesrat mit militärischen Ehren in Bern empfangen. Traditionsgemäss halten der Bundespräsident und sein Gast anschliessend eine Rede in der Wandelhalle des Parlaments. An den offiziellen Gesprächen unter der Leitung von Bundespräsident Ueli Maurer, Vorsteher des Eidgenössischen Departements für Verteidigung, Bevölkerungsschutz und Sport (VBS), und des finnischen Präsidenten nehmen auch Bundesrat Didier Burkhalter, Vorsteher des Eidgenössischen Departements für auswärtige Angelegenheiten (EDA), Bundesrat Johann Schneider-Ammann, Vorsteher des Eidgenössischen Departements für Wirtschaft, Bildung und Forschung (WBF) und Bundesrätin Doris Leuthard, Vorsteherin des Eidgenössischen Departements für Umwelt, Verkehr, Energie und Kommunikation (UVEK) teil. Am Abend lädt der Bundesrat zu einem Galadiner.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Nach dem ersten Tag in der Bundeshauptstadt wird der Bundespräsident seinen Gast in die Kantone Aargau, Zürich sowie in die Innerschweiz führen. Die Delegation wird eine Katastrophenhilfeeinheit der Schweizer Armee, ein Wasserenergieprojekt und die Abteilung Raumfahrt der RUAG Space besuchen.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Karin Suini Sprecherin VBS 031 324 50 86 karin.suini@gs-vbs.admin.ch Information EDA +41 31 322 31 53 info@eda.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="114880">
        <title>Staatsbesuch des finnischen Präsidenten Sauli Niinistö vom 15.–16.10.2013</title>
        <uri>http://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home/dfa/head/hoeven/finlan.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions>
        <revision date="2013-09-30 15:49" type="R"/>
      </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Visite d’Etat du président finlandais Sauli Niinistö les 15 et 16 octobre 2013</title>
      <lead>Répondant à l’invitation du Conseil fédéral, le président de la République de Finlande Sauli Niinistö effectuera une visite d’Etat en Suisse les 15 et 16 octobre 2013. Les entretiens officiels porteront non seulement sur la politique européenne et sur des questions économiques mais aussi sur des thèmes liés à l’actualité internationale, notamment la coopération en matière de politique de sécurité.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Le 15 octobre 2013, le président de la Finlande sera reçu avec les honneurs militaires par le Conseil fédéral in corpore. Comme le veut la tradition, le président de la Confédération et son hôte prononceront ensuite un discours dans la Salle des pas perdus du Parlement. Les entretiens officiels seront dirigés par le président de la Confédération Ueli Maurer, chef du Département fédéral de la défense, de la protection de la population et des sports (DDPS), et par le président finlandais. Le conseiller fédéral Didier Burkhalter, chef du Département fédéral des affaires étrangères (DFAE), le conseiller fédéral Johann Schneider-Ammann, chef du Département fédéral de l'économie, de la formation et de la recherche (DEFR) et la conseillère fédérale Doris Leuthard, cheffe du Département fédéral de l'environnement, des transports, de l'énergie et de la communication (DETEC) y prendront également part. Le soir, le Conseil fédéral donnera un dîner de gala en l'honneur de ses hôtes.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Après la première journée passée dans la capitale, le président de la Confédération emmènera son homologue finlandais dans les cantons d'Argovie et de Zurich ainsi qu'en Suisse centrale. La délégation visitera une unité d'aide en cas de catastrophe de l'Armée suisse, un projet d'énergie hydraulique et la division aérospatiale de RUAG SPACE.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Karin Suini Porte-parole du DDPS 031 324 50 86 karin.suini@gs-vbs.admin.ch Information DFAE +41 31 322 31 53 info@eda.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="114881">
        <title>Visite d’Etat du président finlandais Sauli Niinistö les 15 et 16 octobre 2013</title>
        <uri>http://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/home/dfa/head/hoeven/finlan.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Visita di Stato del Presidente finlandese Sauli Niinistö dal 15 al 16 ottobre 2013</title>
      <lead>Il Presidente della Repubblica di Finlandia Sauli Niinistö sarà in visita ufficiale in Svizzera dal 15 al 16 ottobre 2013 su invito del Consiglio federale. I colloqui ufficiali verteranno sulla politica europea ed economica, su temi di attualità internazionale e, in particolare, sulla cooperazione nell’ambito della politica di sicurezza.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Il 15 ottobre 2013 il Presidente della Finlandia sarà accolto a Berna con gli onori militari dal Consiglio federale in corpore. Conformemente alla tradizione, il Presidente della Confederazione e il suo ospite terranno successivamente un discorso ufficiale nella Sala dei passi perduti del Parlamento. Ai colloqui ufficiali tra il Presidente finlandese e il Presidente della Confederazione Ueli Maurer, capo del Dipartimento federale della difesa, della protezione della popolazione e dello sport (DDPS), parteciperanno anche il Consigliere federale Didier Burkhalter, capo del Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri (DFAE), il Consigliere federale Johann Schneider-Ammann, capo del Dipartimento federale dell'economia, della formazione e della ricerca (DEFR) e la Consigliera federale Doris Leuthard, capo del Dipartimento federale dell'ambiente, dei trasporti, dell'energia e delle comunicazioni (DATEC). La giornata del 15 si concluderà con una serata di gala organizzata dal Consiglio federale in onore del Presidente finlandese.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Dopo la prima giornata nella capitale federale, il Presidente della Confederazione farà visitare al Presidente Niinistö i Cantoni di Argovia e Zurigo e la Svizzera centrale. La delegazione finlandese visiterà un'unità delle truppe di aiuto in caso di catastrofe dell'Esercito svizzero, un progetto idroelettrico e il reparto «Astronautica» della RUAG Space.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Karin Suini Portavoce DDPS 031 324 50 86 karin.suini@gs-vbs.admin.ch Informazione DFAE +41 31 322 31 53 info@eda.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="114882">
        <title>Visita di Stato del Presidente finlandese Sauli Niinistö dal 15.–16.10.2013</title>
        <uri>http://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/home/dfa/head/hoeven/finlan.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>State visit by Finnish President Sauli Niinistö on 15 and 16 October 2013</title>
      <lead>At the invitation of the Swiss Federal Council, Sauli Niinistö, President of the Republic of Finland, will visit Switzerland on 15 and 16 October 2013. The official talks will focus on European political and economic issues as well as topics of current international importance including cooperation in the field of security policy in particular.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;The entire Federal Council will receive the President of Finland with military honours in Bern on 15 October 2013. According to tradition, the President of the Swiss Confederation and his guest will then deliver addresses in the Wandelhalle of the Swiss Parliament. Federal Councillors Didier Burkhalter, head of the Federal Department of Foreign Affairs (FDFA), Johann Schneider-Ammann, head of the Federal Department of Economic Affairs, Education, and Research (EAER), and Doris Leuthard, head of the Federal Department of the Environment, Transport, Energy, and Communications (DETEC) will also participate in talks with the President of Finland chaired by Swiss President Ueli Maurer, head of the Federal Department of Defence, Civil Protection, and Sport (DDPS). The first day of the state visit to the federal capital will be concluded with a gala dinner hosted by the Federal Council.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;On the second day, the President of the Confederation will take his guest to the Cantons of Aargau and Zurich as well as to central Switzerland. The delegation will visit a Swiss Armed Forces disaster-relief unit, a hydro-energy project site, and RUAG Space Switzerland.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>DDPS Communication Federal Palace East CH-3003 Bern</contact>
      <link id="114883">
        <title>State visit by Finnish President Sauli Niinistö on 15 and 16 October 2013</title>
        <uri>http://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home/dfa/head/hoeven/finlan.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <keywords>
      <keyword id="506" org-id="502">
        <name lang="de">Kooperation</name>
        <name lang="fr">Coopération</name>
        <name lang="it">Cooperazione</name>
        <name lang="en">Cooperation</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="5440" org-id="502">
        <name lang="de">Veranstaltung</name>
        <name lang="fr">Manifestation</name>
        <name lang="it">Manifestazione</name>
        <name lang="en">Event</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="5450" org-id="502">
        <name lang="de">Besuch</name>
        <name lang="fr">Visite</name>
        <name lang="it">Visita</name>
        <name lang="en">Visit</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="5540" org-id="502">
        <name lang="de">Europapolitik</name>
        <name lang="fr">Politique européenne</name>
        <name lang="it">Politica europea</name>
        <name lang="en">European policy / politics</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="5580" org-id="502">
        <name lang="de">Wirtschaft</name>
        <name lang="fr">Économie</name>
        <name lang="it">Economia</name>
        <name lang="en">economy</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="5930" org-id="502">
        <name lang="de">Internationale Beziehungen</name>
        <name lang="fr">Relations internationales</name>
        <name lang="it">Relazioni internazionali</name>
        <name lang="en">international relations</name>
      </keyword>
    </keywords>
    <topics>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
