<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="90180" revoked="no">
    <version>2</version>
    <pubdate>2022-09-01</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="408" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>408</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Bundesanwaltschaft</name>
      <name lang="fr">Ministère public de la Confédération</name>
      <name lang="it">Ministero pubblico della Confederazione</name>
      <name lang="en">Office of the Attorney General of Switzerland</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.ba.admin.ch/ba/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.ba.admin.ch/ba/fr/home.html</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.ba.admin.ch/ba/it/home.html</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.ba.admin.ch/</www>
      <email lang="de">info@ba.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@ba.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@ba.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@ba.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="408">
      <name lang="de">Bundesanwaltschaft</name>
      <name lang="fr">Ministère public de la Confédération</name>
      <name lang="it">Ministero pubblico della Confederazione</name>
      <name lang="en">Office of the Attorney General of Switzerland</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.ba.admin.ch/ba/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.ba.admin.ch/ba/fr/home.html</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.ba.admin.ch/ba/it/home.html</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.ba.admin.ch/</www>
      <email lang="de">info@ba.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@ba.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@ba.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@ba.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Terrorismusbekämpfung: Hausdurchsuchungen und Festnahmen in den Kantonen Genf und Waadt</title>
      <lead>Im Auftrag der Bundesanwaltschaft (BA) haben fedpol und die Kantonspolizeien Genf und Waadt am 1. September 2022 insgesamt vier Hausdurchsuchungen in den Kanton Genf und Waadt durchgeführt und zwei Personen festgenommen. Gegen die festgenommenen Personen führt die BA ein Strafverfahren wegen des Verdachts der Beteiligung an resp. der Unterstützung der verbotenen terroristischen Organisation "Islamischer Staat".</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Die Hausdurchsuchungen fanden im Rahmen eines im Juli 2021 eröffneten Strafverfahrens statt, welches die BA gegen einen schweizerisch-mazedonischen Doppelbürger und einen kosovarischen Staatsbürger führt. Einer der beiden Beschuldigten hat den Wohnsitz im Kanton Genf, der andere im Kanton Waadt. Das betreffende Verfahren wird wegen des Verdachts des Verstosses gegen Art. 2 des Bundesgesetzes über das Verbot der Gruppierungen „Al-Qaïda“ und „Islamischer Staat“ sowie verwandter Organisationen (SR 122) und der Unterstützung bzw. Beteiligung an einer kriminellen Organisation (Art. 260ter StGB) geführt. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Die beiden festgenommenen Personen werden der BA zugeführt und einvernommen. Danach wird die BA über ein allfälliges Gesuch an das zuständige Zwangsmassnahmengericht in Bezug auf Untersuchungshaft entscheiden. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Die BA dankt fedpol, den Kantonspolizeien Genf und Waadt und dem Nachrichtendienst des Bundes NDB für die wertvolle Zusammenarbeit in dieser Angelegenheit. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Aufgrund des Verfahrensstadiums können zurzeit keine weiteren Angaben zu den Vorwürfen gegen die beiden beschuldigten Personen gemacht werden. Die BA wird wieder informieren, sobald der Verfahrensstand dies zulässt. Die BA hält fest, dass wie immer die Unschuldsvermutung gilt.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; &lt;i&gt;Originaltext auf Französisch&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Kommunikationsdienst der Bundesanwaltschaft, info@ba.admin.ch, T +41 58 464 32 40</contact>
      <revisions>
        <revision date="2022-09-07 13:28" type="R"/>
      </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Lutte contre le terrorisme: perquisitions et arrestations dans les cantons de Genève et de Vaud</title>
      <lead>Sur mandat du Ministère public de la Confédération (MPC), fedpol, en collaboration avec la police cantonale genevoise et vaudoise, a effectué, le 1er septembre 2022 au total quatre perquisitions dans les cantons de Genève et de Vaud et a arrêté deux personnes. Le MPC mène une procédure pénale contre les personnes arrêtées pour soupçons de participation ou de soutien à l'organisation terroriste interdite "Etat islamique".</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Les perquisitions ont eu lieu dans le cadre d’une procédure pénale ouverte en juillet 2021 et conduite par le MPC contre un double national suisse-macédonien et un citoyen kosovar. Les deux prévenus sont domiciliés respectivement dans les cantons de Vaud et Genève. La procédure en question est menée pour soupçons de violation de l'art. 2 de la loi fédérale sur l'interdiction des groupes "Al-Qaïda" et "Etat islamique" et des organisations apparentées (RS 122) et de soutien ou de participation à une organisation criminelle (art. 260ter CP). &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Les deux prévenus seront conduits au MPC pour auditions au terme desquelles il décidera de leur éventuelle mise en détention provisoire à requérir auprès du Tribunal des mesures de contrainte compétent.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Le MPC remercie fedpol, les polices cantonales de Genève et Vaud ainsi que le Service de renseignements de la Confédération (SRC) pour leur précieuse collaboration dans cette affaire. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;En raison du stade de la procédure, le MPC ne peut, pour l’heure, donner de plus amples informations sur les faits reprochés aux deux personnes prévenues, il le fera lorsque l’avancement de la procédure le lui permettra. Le MPC tient à préciser que, comme toujours, la présomption d'innocence s'applique. &lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Service de communication du Ministère public de la Confédération, info@ba.admin.ch, T +41 58 464 32 40</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Lotta al terrorismo: perquisizioni e arresti nei Cantoni di Ginevra e Vaud</title>
      <lead>Su incarico del Ministero pubblico della Confederazione (MPC), il primo di settembre 2022 fedpol e le polizie cantonali di Ginevra e Vaud hanno condotto quattro perquisizioni domiciliari nei Cantoni di Ginevra e Vaud e arrestato due persone. Nei confronti delle due persone arrestate il MPC sta conducendo un procedimento penale per sospetto di partecipazione risp. sostegno all’organizzazione terroristica vietata «Stato Islamico».</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Le perquisizioni si sono svolte nell’ambito di un procedimento penale aperto nel luglio 2021, che il MPC conduce contro un cittadino svizzero-macedone e un cittadino kosovaro. Uno dei due imputati è residente nel Cantone di Ginevra, l’altro nel Cantone di Vaud. Il relativo procedimento è condotto per sospetto di violazione dell’art. 2 della legge federale che vieta i gruppi «Al-Qaïda» e «Stato islamico» nonché le organizzazioni associate (RS 122), e sostegno risp. partecipazione a un’organizzazione criminale (art. 260ter CP).&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;I due imputati saranno condotti dinanzi al MPC per gli interrogatori, al termine dei quali si deciderà se chiedere la loro carcerazione preventiva al giudice dei provvedimenti coercitivi competente.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Il MPC ringrazia fedpol, le polizie cantonali di Ginevra e Vaud e il Servizio delle attività informative della Confederazione (SIC) per la preziosa collaborazione in questa vicenda. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Nell’attuale stadio del procedimento non si possono fornire per il momento ulteriori informazioni sui reati contestati ai due imputati. Il MPC fornirà nuove informazioni non appena lo stadio del procedimento lo permetterà. Il MPC ricorda che vale come sempre la presunzione di innocenza. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;testo originale in francese&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Servizio di comunicazione del Ministero pubblico della Confederazione, info@ba.admin.ch, T +41 58 464 32 40</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Combating terrorism: Searches and arrests in the cantons of Geneva and Vaud</title>
      <lead>On the instructions of the Office of the Attorney General of Switzerland (OAG), officers from fedpol and the Geneva and Vaud cantonal police forces searched four houses in the cantons of Geneva and Vaud on 1 September 2022 and arrested two persons. The OAG is conducting criminal proceedings against the persons arrested on suspicion of participating in or supporting the proscribed terrorist organisation "Islamic state".</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;The house searches were carried out as part of criminal proceedings opened by the OAG in July 2021 against a Swiss-Macedonian dual national and a Kosovar national. One of the two suspects is resident in the canton of Geneva, the other in the canton of Vaud. The proceedings relate to suspicions of violation of Article 2 of the Federal Act on the Proscription of the Groups “Al-Qaeda” and “Islamic state” and Associated Organisations (SR 122) and of supporting and/or participating in a criminal organisation (Art. 260ter Swiss Criminal Code). &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The two suspects will be taken to the OAG for questioning, after which the OAG will decide whether or not it will apply to the competent compulsory measures court for them to be placed in pre-trial detention.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The OAG wishes to thank fedpol, the cantonal police forces in Geneva and Vaud and the Federal Intelligence Service for their valuable cooperation in this matter. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;It is not possible to provide any further details on the allegations against the two suspects at this stage in the proceedings. The OAG will issue a further statement as soon as the status of the proceedings permits. As always, the presumption of innocence applies.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt; &lt;/b&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Original text in French&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Communications Service of the Office of the Attorney General of Switzerland, info@ba.admin.ch, T +41 58 464 32 40</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="17">
        <name lang="de">Kriminalität</name>
        <name lang="fr">Criminalité</name>
        <name lang="it">Criminalità</name>
        <name lang="en">Criminality</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
