<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="90229" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2022-09-05</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="yes" id="1060" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>601</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Staatssekretariat für internationale Finanzfragen</name>
      <name lang="fr">Secrétariat d'Etat aux questions financières internationales</name>
      <name lang="it">Segreteria di Stato per le questioni finanziarie internazionali</name>
      <name lang="en">State Secretariat for International Financial Matters</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.sif.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.sif.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.sif.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.sif.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@sif.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@sif.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@sif.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@sif.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="701" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>701</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Wirtschaft, Bildung und Forschung</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'économie, de la formation et de la recherche</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'economia, della formazione e della ricerca</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Economic Affairs, Education and Research</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="601">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Finanzdepartement</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des finances</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale delle finanze</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Finance</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.efd.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.dff.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.efd.admin.ch/efd/it/home.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.efd.admin.ch/efd/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <department id="701">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Wirtschaft, Bildung und Forschung</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'économie, de la formation et de la recherche</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'economia, della formazione e della ricerca</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Economic Affairs, Education and Research</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Bundesrat Ueli Maurer empfängt den Finanzminister von Katar</title>
      <lead>Bundesrat Ueli Maurer, Vorsteher des Eidgenössischen Finanzdepartements EFD, hat am 5. September 2022 in Dübendorf den katarischen Finanzminister Ali bin Ahmed Al Kuwari zu einem Arbeitsbesuch empfangen. Parallel zu diesem Treffen setzten die Schweiz und Katar auf technischer Ebene ihren Austausch zu Finanz- und Wirtschaftsthemen fort und besprachen aktuelle Fragen im Bereich des Energiesektors.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Die Finanzminister tauschten sich über die Rolle von Finanzinstituten in Energiemärkten sowie die aktuelle Energiesituation und allfällige bilaterale Kooperationen aus. Anschliessend besichtigten sie am Ort des Treffens, der Eidgenössischen Materialprüfungs- und Forschungsanstalt EMPA in Dübendorf, verschiedene Vorzeigeprojekte im Bereich der nachhaltigen Infrastruktur und der Mobilität.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Anlässlich einen Austausches zu Finanz- und Wirtschaftsthemen sprachen die Delegationen der beiden Länder über Inflationstendenzen und Zinsentwicklungen sowie Digitalisierung und Nachhaltigkeit im Finanzsektor. Sie diskutierten zudem über die Revision des bestehenden Doppelbesteuerungsabkommens. Besprochen wurden im Weiteren auch Möglichkeiten, wie die Beziehungen zwischen den Wirtschaftsakteuren beider Länder gestärkt werden könnten. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Am Dienstag, 6. September 2022, wird der Finanzminister von Katar auch von Bundesrat Guy Parmelin in Bern zu Gesprächen über die bilateralen Wirtschafts- und Handelsbeziehungen empfangen.&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Kommunikation Eidgenössisches Finanzdepartement EFD Tel.-Nr. +41 58 462 60 33; info@gs-efd.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Le conseiller fédéral Ueli Maurer accueille le ministre qatarien des finances</title>
      <lead>Le 5 septembre 2022, le conseiller fédéral Ueli Maurer, chef du Département fédéral des finances, a reçu à Dübendorf le ministre qatarien des finances, Ali bin Ahmed Al Kuwari, pour une visite de travail. En marge de cette rencontre, les délégations suisse et qatarienne ont poursuivi leurs échanges techniques sur les thématiques financières et économiques et se sont penchés sur les questions d'actualité dans le domaine de l'énergie. </lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Les ministres suisse et qatarien des finances ont discuté du rôle des institutions financières sur les marchés de l'énergie, ainsi que de la situation énergétique actuelle et d'éventuelles possibilités de coopération bilatérale. Sur le lieu de la rencontre, qui se tenait dans les locaux du Laboratoire fédéral d'essai des matériaux et de recherche (EMPA) à Dübendorf, ils ont ensuite pu découvrir différents projets phares menés dans le domaine des infrastructures durables et de la mobilité. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Dans le cadre des échanges sur les thématiques financières et économiques, les délégations suisse et qatarienne se sont intéressées aux tendances inflationnistes et à l'évolution des taux d'intérêt, ainsi qu'à la numérisation et à la durabilité dans le secteur financier. Elles se sont aussi penchées sur la révision de la convention contre les doubles impositions. Les discussions ont en outre porté sur les moyens de renforcer les relations entre les acteurs économiques des deux pays.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Le 6 septembre 2022, le ministre qatarien des finances sera aussi reçu à Berne par le conseiller fédéral Guy Parmelin, avec lequel il s’entretiendra des relations économiques et commerciales entre le Qatar et la Suisse.&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Communication Département fédéral des finances DFF n° tél. 41 58 462 60 33; info@gs-efd.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Il consigliere federale Ueli Maurer riceve il ministro delle finanze del Qatar</title>
      <lead>Il 5 settembre 2022 il consigliere federale Ueli Maurer, capo del Dipartimento federale delle finanze (DFF), ha accolto a Dübendorf il ministro delle finanze del Qatar Ali bin Ahmed al Kuwari per una visita di lavoro. Parallelamente all’incontro, la Svizzera e il Qatar hanno proseguito lo scambio sul piano tecnico in merito a tematiche finanziarie ed economiche e hanno affrontato la questione energetica, ora di grande attualità.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;I ministri delle finanze hanno discusso del ruolo degli istituti finanziari sui mercati dell’energia nonché dell’attuale situazione energetica e di un’eventuale cooperazione bilaterale. In seguito, presso la sede dell’incontro, ossia il Laboratorio federale di prova dei materiali e di ricerca di Dübendorf, sono stati presentati loro diversi progetti rilevanti nel settore delle infrastrutture sostenibili e della mobilità.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;In occasione dei colloqui riguardanti le tematiche finanziarie ed economiche, le delegazioni di entrambi i Paesi si sono soffermate su questioni quali le tendenze inflazionistiche, l’evoluzione dei tassi d’interesse, la digitalizzazione e la sostenibilità nel settore della finanza. Inoltre, al centro dell’incontro vi sono state la revisione della vigente convenzione per evitare le doppie imposizioni e le possibilità di consolidare le relazioni tra gli operatori economici dei due Paesi.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Martedì 6 settembre 2022 il ministro delle finanze del Qatar sarà ricevuto a Berna anche dal consigliere federale Guy Parmelin. I due ministri si intratterranno sulle relazioni bilaterali economiche e commerciali.&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Comunicazione Dipartimento federale delle finanze DFF Tel. +41 58 462 60 33; info@gs-efd.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Federal Councillor Ueli Maurer receives Qatari Minister of Finance</title>
      <lead>On 5 September 2022, Federal Councillor Ueli Maurer, Head of the Federal Department of Finance FDF, received the Qatari Minister of Finance, Ali bin Ahmed Al Kuwari, in Dübendorf for a working visit. In parallel to this meeting, Switzerland and Qatar continued their exchange on financial and economic matters at a technical level and discussed current issues in the energy sector.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;The finance ministers exchanged views on the role of financial institutions in energy markets, the current energy situation and possible bilateral cooperation. They then visited various flagship projects on sustainable infrastructure and mobility being conducted at the meeting venue, the Swiss Federal Laboratories for Materials Science and Technology Empa in Dübendorf.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;During talks on financial and economic issues, the delegations from the two countries addressed inflationary trends and interest rate developments, as well as digitalisation and sustainability in the financial sector. They further discussed the revision of the existing double taxation agreement and ways in which relations between the economic players of both countries could be strengthened.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;On Tuesday, 6 September 2022, the Qatari Minister of Finance will also be received in Bern by Federal Councillor Guy Parmelin for talks on bilateral economic and trade relations.&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Communications Federal Department of Finance FDF Tel. +41 58 462 60 33; info@gs-efd.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <keywords>
      <keyword id="235" org-id="1060">
        <name lang="de">Internationale Steuerpolitik</name>
        <name lang="fr">Politique fiscale internationale</name>
        <name lang="it">Politica fiscale internazionale</name>
        <name lang="en">International tax policy</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="126" org-id="1060">
        <name lang="de">Finanzplatz Schweiz</name>
        <name lang="fr">Place financière suisse</name>
        <name lang="it">Piazza finanziaria svizzera</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland as a financial centre</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="137" org-id="1060">
        <name lang="de">Internationale Doppelbesteuerung</name>
        <name lang="fr">Double imposition internationale</name>
        <name lang="it">Doppia imposizione internazionale</name>
        <name lang="en">International double taxation</name>
      </keyword>
    </keywords>
    <topics>
      <topic id="47">
        <name lang="de">Wirtschaft</name>
        <name lang="fr">Économie</name>
        <name lang="it">Economia</name>
        <name lang="en">Economic Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
