<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="90511" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2022-09-27</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="323" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>701</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidg. Materialprüfungs- und Forschungsanstalt</name>
      <name lang="fr">Laboratoire fédéral d'essai des matériaux et de recherche</name>
      <name lang="it">Laboratorio federale di prova dei materiali e di ricerca</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Laboratory for Materials Testing and Research</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.empa.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.empa.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.empa.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.empa.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">contact@empa.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">contact@empa.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">contact@empa.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">contact@empa.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="701">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Wirtschaft, Bildung und Forschung</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'économie, de la formation et de la recherche</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'economia, della formazione e della ricerca</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Economic Affairs, Education and Research</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Dübendorf, St. Gallen und Thun</city>
      <title>Hightech für leisere Gleise: Schienen-«Polster» gegen Bahnlärm und Vibrationen</title>
      <lead>Um Bahnlärm für Anwohner zu reduzieren, sind nicht nur Lärmschutzwände oder leisere Radsysteme und Bremsen geeignet. Ein unscheinbares Bauteil unter den Gleisen ist für ein Forscherteam mit Beteiligung der Empa ein Hoffnungsträger für leiseren Schienenverkehr – und die Auswertung von Tests an vorbeifahrenden Zügen zeigt eine positive Wirkung.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;br /&gt;Bahnlärm ist für Anwohner von Schienentrassen oft eine grosse Belastung. Um sie zu mindern, haben Forschende der Empa und der Haute École d'Ingénierie et de Gestion du Canton de Vaud unter Federführung der EPFL einen unauffälligen Bestandteil des Schienensystems neu gedacht: «Rail Pads» aus elastischem Kunststoff, die zwischen Schienen und Betonschwellen stecken. Sie dienen dazu, den hochbelasteten Fahrweg aus verdichtetem Schotter und Betonschwellen zu schonen.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;In der Schweiz bestehen diese «Polster» meist aus dem harten Kunststoff Ethylenvinylacetat (EVA). Zwar würde ein weicheres Material den Fahrweg besser schonen – aber zum Preis einer höheren Lärmbelastung. Um dieses verzwickte Problem zu lösen und eine leisere Alternative zu schaffen, hat das Forscherteam in den vergangenen Jahren im Auftrag des Bundesamtes für Umwelt und des Bundesamtes für Verkehr in Zusammenarbeit mit den SBB neuartige Rail Pads entwickelt.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;b&gt;Ein massgeschneiderter Verbundwerkstoff&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Die ursprüngliche Idee der Fachleute: harte Schale, weicher Kern – in Gestalt einer äusseren Hülle aus herkömmlichem EVA mit einem Kern aus einem weichen viskoelastischen Werkstoff. Dessen Dämpfung stimmten sie präzise auf den Frequenzbereich von etwa 500 bis 2'000 Hertz ab, in dem die Schwingungen besonders geräuschintensiv sind.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Nachdem Computerberechnungen und Labormessungen von neu entwickelten Bauteilen nach diesem Prinzip vielversprechend ausgefallen waren, stellten die Forschenden mit dem Kunststoff-Hersteller Semperit erste Prototypen her. Und testeten ihre Rail Pads schliesslich im vergangenen März gemeinsam mit Fachleuten der SBB in der Praxis – auf einem 100 Meter langen Gleisabschnitt nahe Nottwil im Kanton Luzern. Mit Messungen der Schwingungen von Gleisschwellen und Schienen, von Schallpegeln und anderen Daten wurden ihre Auswirkungen bei realen Zugfahrten exakt erfasst.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Wie Empa-Forscher Bart Van Damme zu den Versuchen erläutert, fielen die Resultate erfreulich aus (siehe Video unten). Die Auswertung der Daten zeigte, dass die neuartigen Rail Pads sowohl den Zuglärm als auch Schwingungen spürbar dämpften. Dank dieser Resultate sind die Forschenden nun optimistisch, dass die neuartigen Bauteile in Zukunft in der Praxis zum Einsatz kommen werden.</text>
      <contact>Dr. Bart Van Damme Abteilung Akustik / Lärmminderung Tel. +41 58 765 41 10 bart.vandamme@empa.ch</contact>
      <attachment id="236306">
        <title>Zuglärm im Visier: Empa-Forscher Bart Van Damme mit einem neuartigen Rail Pad, das im Zugverkehr getestet wurde. Bild: Empa</title>
        <format>png</format>
        <size-kb>1385</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/73284.png</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <link id="236299">
        <title>Video</title>
        <uri>https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=8A9SugnG6IQ</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="236301">
        <title>Bericht über aktuelle Fachtagung zu Bahnlärm-Forschung und Rail Pads in Lausanne</title>
        <uri>https://laermforschung-eisenbahn.ch/fokus/#exchange-of-experts-222</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="236302">
        <title>Video mit Fachleuten zum Nutzen und Potenzial von Rail Pads</title>
        <uri>https://laermforschung-eisenbahn.ch/site/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/BAFU_EE02_RAILPADS.mp4</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="236303">
        <title>Empa-Medienmitteilung: Lärmminderung im Schienenverkehr: Leise Geleise; Februar 2022)</title>
        <uri>https://www.empa.ch/web/s604/noise-reduction-of-rail-transport?inheritRedirect=true</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Dübendorf, St. Gallen und Thun</city>
      <title>La haute technologie au service de voies plus silencieuses: Rail "coussin" contre le bruit et les vibrations des trains</title>
      <lead>Pour réduire le bruit des trains pour les riverains, il n'y a pas que les parois antibruit ou les systèmes de roues et de freins plus silencieux. Pour une équipe de chercheurs dont des chercheurs de l'Empa, un élément discret sous les voies est porteur d'espoir pour un trafic ferroviaire plus silencieux - et l'évaluation de tests effectués sur le terrain montre un effet positif.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Le bruit des trains est souvent une nuisance importante pour les riverains des voies ferrées. Pour l'atténuer, des chercheurs de l'Empa et de la Haute École d'Ingénierie et de Gestion du Canton de Vaud, sous la houlette de l'EPFL, ont repensé un élément discret du système ferroviaire : des "Rail Pads" en plastique élastique, insérés entre les rails et les traverses en béton. Ils servent à ménager la voie de circulation très sollicitée, composée de ballast compacté et de traverses en béton.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;En Suisse, ces "coussins" sont généralement constitués d'un plastique dur, l'éthylène-acétate de vinyle (EVA). Certes, un matériau plus souple ménagerait mieux la chaussée - mais au prix d'une pollution sonore plus élevée. Pour résoudre ce problème épineux et créer une alternative plus silencieuse, l'équipe de chercheurs a développé ces dernières années, sur mandat de l'Office fédéral de l'environnement et de l'Office fédéral des transports et en collaboration avec les CFF, des Rail Pads d'un nouveau genre.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;b&gt;Un matériau composite sur mesure&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;L'idée initiale des spécialistes : une coque dure, un noyau souple - sous la forme d'une enveloppe extérieure en EVA traditionnel avec un noyau en matériau viscoélastique souple. L'amortissement de ce dernier a été adapté avec précision à la plage de fréquences d'environ 500 à 2'000 hertz, dans laquelle les vibrations sont particulièrement bruyantes.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Après que les calculs informatiques et les mesures en laboratoire des nouveaux composants développés selon ce principe se sont révélés prometteurs, les chercheurs ont fabriqué les premiers prototypes avec le fabricant de matières plastiques Semperit. En mars dernier, ils ont testé leurs "Rail Pads" dans la pratique avec des spécialistes des CFF, sur un tronçon de voie de 100 mètres près de Nottwil, dans le canton de Lucerne. Des mesures des vibrations des traverses et des rails, des niveaux sonores et d'autres données ont permis de déterminer avec précision leurs effets lors de passages de trains réels.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Comme l'explique le chercheur de l'Empa Bart Van Damme à propos des essais, les résultats ont été réjouissants (voir la vidéo ci-dessous). L'évaluation des données a montré que les nouveaux Rail Pads atténuaient sensiblement le bruit et les vibrations des trains. Grâce à ces résultats, les chercheurs sont optimistes quant à l'utilisation future de ces nouveaux composants dans la pratique.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Dr. Bart Van Damme Laboratory for Acoustics / Noise Control Tél. +41 58 765 41 10 bart.vandamme@empa.ch</contact>
      <attachment id="236308">
        <title>Le bruit des trains en ligne de mire : le chercheur de l'Empa Bart Van Damme avec un nouveau Rail Pad qui a été testé dans le trafic ferroviaire. Image : Empa</title>
        <format>png</format>
        <size-kb>1385</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/73286.png</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <link id="236305">
        <title>Bruit de fond: Rails silencieux; Communiqué de presse février 2022</title>
        <uri>https://www.empa.ch/web/s604/noise-reduction-of-rail-transport?inheritRedirect=true</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Dübendorf, St. Gallen und Thun</city>
      <title>High-tech for quieter tracks: "Cushions" against rail noise and vibrations</title>
      <lead>To reduce rail noise for residents, noise barriers or quieter wheel systems and brakes are not the only options. An inconspicuous component under the railway tracks is a beacon of hope for quieter rail traffic for a team of researchers with Empa involvement – and first tests on passing trains show a positive effect.</lead>
      <text link="no">Railroad noise is often a major nuisance for residents living near railway tracks. To reduce it, researchers at Empa and the Haute École d'Ingénierie et de Gestion du Canton de Vaud, under the leadership of EPFL, have rethought an inconspicuous component of the rail system: rail pads made of elastic polymers, which are inserted between the rails and concrete sleepers. They serve to protect the highly stressed track made of compacted ballast and concrete sleepers.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;In Switzerland, these pads are usually made of hard plastic, ethylene vinyl acetate (EVA). A softer material would protect the tracks even better – but at the price of higher noise pollution. To solve this tricky problem and create a quieter alternative, the research team has developed novel rail pads in recent years on behalf of the Federal Office for the Environment and the Federal Office of Transport in collaboration with SBB, the Swiss national railroad company.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;b&gt;A tailor-made composite material&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The experts' original idea: hard shell, soft core – in the form of an outer shell made of conventional EVA with a core made of a soft viscoelastic material. They precisely tuned the damping of the core to the frequency range from about 500 to 2,000 hertz, in which vibrations are particularly noise-intensive.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;After computer calculations and laboratory measurements of newly developed components based on this principle proved promising, the researchers produced the first prototypes together with the plastics manufacturer Semperit. And finally, last March, they tested their rail pads in practice together with SBB experts – on a 100-meter section of track near Nottwil in the canton of Lucerne. Measurements of the vibrations of track sleepers and rails, sound levels and other data were used to precisely record their effects during real train passings.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;As Empa researcher Bart Van Damme explains, the results of the tests were very encouraging (see video below). The analysis of the data showed that the new rail pads noticeably dampened both train noise and vibrations. Thanks to these results, the researchers are now optimistic that the novel components will be used in practice in the future.&lt;br /&gt;</text>
      <contact>Dr. Bart Van Damme Laboratory for Acoustics / Noise Control Phone +41 58 765 41 10 bart.vandamme@empa.ch</contact>
      <attachment id="236307">
        <title>Train noise in focus: Empa researcher Bart Van Damme with a new type of rail pad that has been tested in train traffic. Image: Empa</title>
        <format>png</format>
        <size-kb>1385</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/73285.png</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <link id="236300">
        <title>Video</title>
        <uri>https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=fh422dNh6c0</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="236304">
        <title>oise reduction of rail transport: Silence on the tracks; Empa Media Release February 2022</title>
        <uri>https://www.empa.ch/web/s604/noise-reduction-of-rail-transport?inheritRedirect=true</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="8">
        <name lang="de">Bildung und Forschung</name>
        <name lang="fr">Formation et recherche</name>
        <name lang="it">Formazione e ricerca</name>
        <name lang="en">Education and Research</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="45">
        <name lang="de">Technologie</name>
        <name lang="fr">Technologie</name>
        <name lang="it">Tecnologia</name>
        <name lang="en">Technology</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="46">
        <name lang="de">Verkehr</name>
        <name lang="fr">Transports</name>
        <name lang="it">Trasporti</name>
        <name lang="en">Transport</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
