<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="65746" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2017-02-22</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="201" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>201</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="1070" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>1070</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Der Bundesrat</name>
      <name lang="fr">Conseil fédéral</name>
      <name lang="it">Il Consiglio federale</name>
      <name lang="en">The Federal Council</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.admin.ch/gov/de/start.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.admin.ch/gov/fr/accueil.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.admin.ch/gov/it/pagina-iniziale.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.admin.ch/gov/en/start.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="201">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <department id="1070">
      <name lang="de">Der Bundesrat</name>
      <name lang="fr">Conseil fédéral</name>
      <name lang="it">Il Consiglio federale</name>
      <name lang="en">The Federal Council</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.admin.ch/gov/de/start.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.admin.ch/gov/fr/accueil.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.admin.ch/gov/it/pagina-iniziale.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.admin.ch/gov/en/start.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Staatssekretärin Pascale Baeriswyl koordiniert ab dem 1. April 2017 die Verhandlungen mit der Europäischen Union</title>
      <lead>Pascale Baeriswyl folgt auf Jacques de Watteville, der die Verhandlungen mit der Europäischen Union (EU) bis anhin koordiniert hat. Der Bundesrat hat an seiner Sitzung vom 22. Februar 2017 die Staatssekretärin des Eidgenössischen Departements für auswärtige Angelegenheiten (EDA) mit dieser Funktion betraut. Sie wird ab 1. April 2017 die Gespräche mit der EU, gemeinsam mit den für die verschiedenen Dossiers zuständigen Unterhändlern, koordinieren.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Pascale Baeriswyl ist seit dem 1. Dezember 2016 Staatssekretärin und Politische Direktorin des Eidgenössischen Departements für auswärtige Angelegenheiten (EDA). Sie verfügt über umfassende, multilaterale Verhandlungserfahrungen sowie über gute Kenntnisse der Europapolitik. So betreute sie zwischen 2005 und 2008 die aussen- und sicherheitspolitischen Fragen an der Mission der Schweiz bei der EU in Brüssel und war ab 2014 als Vizedirektorin der Direktion für Völkerecht für die rechtlichen Aspekte der europäischen Dossiers zuständig.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Der Bundesrat sprach Staatssekretär Jacques de Watteville, der nach 35-jähriger Tätigkeit in verschiedenen Funktionen in der Bundesverwaltung in Pension geht, seinen herzlichen Dank für seine Dienste zugunsten der Schweiz aus.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Information EDA Tel. +41 58 462 31 53 info@eda.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>La secrétaire d’Etat Pascale Baeriswyl coordonnera les négociations avec l’Union européenne dès le 1er avril 2017</title>
      <lead>Pascale Baeriswyl prendra le relais de Jacques de Watteville pour la coordination des négociations avec l’Union européenne (UE). Lors de sa séance du 22 février 2017, le Conseil fédéral a chargé mercredi la secrétaire d’Etat du Département fédéral des affaires étrangères (DFAE) de cette tâche. Elle coordonnera, avec les autres négociateurs en charge des différents dossiers, les discussions avec l’UE dès le 1er avril.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Mme Baeriswyl occupe depuis le 1er décembre 2016 le poste de secrétaire d’Etat et directrice politique du DFAE. Forte d’une large expérience des négociations multilatérales et d’une solide connaissance de la politique européenne, elle a été responsable des questions de sécurité et de politique extérieure au sein de la Mission suisse auprès de l’Union européenne (UE) à Bruxelles entre 2005 et 2008 et, à partir de 2014, a été en charge des aspects juridiques des dossiers européens dans sa fonction de vice-directrice de la Direction du droit international public. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Prenant acte du prochain départ à la retraite du secrétaire d’Etat Jacques de Watteville, le Conseil fédéral lui a par ailleurs adressé ses vifs remerciements pour son engagement au service de l’Etat dans différentes fonctions au cours des trente-cinq dernières années.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Information DFAE Tél. +41 58 462 31 53 info@eda.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>La segretaria di Stato Pascale Baeriswyl coordinerà i negoziati con l’Unione europea dal 1° aprile 2017</title>
      <lead>Pascale Baeriswyl succederà a Jacques de Watteville nel coordinamento dei negoziati con l’Unione europea (UE). Nella sua seduta di mercoledì 22 febbraio 2017 il Consiglio federale ha infatti affidato tale compito alla segretaria di Stato del Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri (DFAE), che dal 1° aprile coordinerà le discussioni con l’UE insieme agli altri negoziatori incaricati dei vari dossier.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Pascale Baeriswyl ricopre le cariche di segretaria di Stato e di direttrice della Direzione politica del DFAE dal 1° dicembre 2016. Ha una vasta esperienza nel campo dei negoziati multilaterali e conoscenze approfondite della politica europea. Dal 2005 al 2008, si è occupata delle questioni di sicurezza e politica estera alla Missione della Svizzera presso l’Unione europea (UE) di Bruxelles e, dal 2014, è stata responsabile degli aspetti giuridici dei dossier europei quale vicedirettrice della Direzione del diritto internazionale pubblico.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Il Consiglio federale ha preso atto dell’imminente pensionamento del segretario di Stato Jacques de Watteville, a cui ha rivolto un sentito ringraziamento per il suo impegno al servizio dello Stato nelle varie funzioni ricoperte nel corso degli ultimi trentacinque anni.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Informazione DFAE Tel. +41 58 462 31 53 info@eda.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>State Secretary Pascale Baeriswyl to coordinate negotiations with EU starting 1 April 2017</title>
      <lead>Pascale Baeriswyl will take over the coordination of Switzerland’s negotiations with the European Union (EU) from Jacques de Watteville. During its session on Wednesday 22 February 2017, the Federal Council tasked the State Secretary of the Federal Department of Foreign Affairs (FDFA) with pursuing the coordination of the discussions with the EU, together with the negotiators in charge of different dossiers, as of 1 April.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Ms Baeriswyl was appointed to the post of state secretary and head of the FDFA's Directorate of Political Affairs on 1 December 2016. She has wide-ranging multilateral negotiation experience and a sound knowledge of European policy. Between 2005 and 2008 she was in charge of foreign and security policy at the Swiss Mission to the European Union in Brussels. Since 2014, Ms Baeriswyl has been responsible for the legal aspects of Switzerland's European dossiers in her capacity as vice director of the Directorate of International Law. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Federal Council also expressed its sincere thanks to former State Secretary for International Financial Matters, Mr de Watteville, for his engagement during 35 years of civil service.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>FDFA Information Tel. +41 58 462 31 53 info@eda.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="32">
        <name lang="de">Bundespersonal</name>
        <name lang="fr">Personnel de la Confédération</name>
        <name lang="it">Personale della Confederazione</name>
        <name lang="en">Government Employees</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="34">
        <name lang="de">Europa</name>
        <name lang="fr">Europe</name>
        <name lang="it">Europa</name>
        <name lang="en">Europe</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
