<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="87456" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2022-03-04</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="1070" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>1070</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Der Bundesrat</name>
      <name lang="fr">Conseil fédéral</name>
      <name lang="it">Il Consiglio federale</name>
      <name lang="en">The Federal Council</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.admin.ch/gov/de/start.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.admin.ch/gov/fr/accueil.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.admin.ch/gov/it/pagina-iniziale.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.admin.ch/gov/en/start.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="yes" id="1080" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>701</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Staatssekretariat für Bildung, Forschung und Innovation</name>
      <name lang="fr">Secrétariat d'Etat à la formation, à la recherche et à l'innovation</name>
      <name lang="it">Segreteria di Stato per la formazione, la ricerca e l'innovazione</name>
      <name lang="en">State Secretariat for Education, Research and Innovation</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.sbfi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.sbfi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.sbfi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.sbfi.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@sbfi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@sbfi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@sbfi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@sbfi.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="1089" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>701</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Innosuisse – Schweizerische Agentur für Innovationsförderung</name>
      <name lang="fr">Innosuisse – Agence suisse pour l’encouragement de l’innovation</name>
      <name lang="it">Innosuisse – Agenzia svizzera per la promozione dell’innovazione</name>
      <name lang="en">Innosuisse – Swiss Innovation Promotion Agency</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.innosuisse.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.innosuisse.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.innosuisse.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.innosuisse.ch</www>
      <email lang="de"/>
      <email lang="fr"/>
      <email lang="it"/>
      <email lang="en"/>
    </originator>
    <department id="1070">
      <name lang="de">Der Bundesrat</name>
      <name lang="fr">Conseil fédéral</name>
      <name lang="it">Il Consiglio federale</name>
      <name lang="en">The Federal Council</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.admin.ch/gov/de/start.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.admin.ch/gov/fr/accueil.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.admin.ch/gov/it/pagina-iniziale.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.admin.ch/gov/en/start.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <department id="701">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Wirtschaft, Bildung und Forschung</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'économie, de la formation et de la recherche</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'economia, della formazione e della ricerca</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Economic Affairs, Education and Research</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>«Horizon Europe»: Bundesrat verabschiedet Übergangsmassnahmen für KMU und Start-ups</title>
      <lead>Der Bundesrat setzt das revidierte Bundesgesetz über die Förderung der Forschung und der Innovation (FIFG) gestaffelt in Kraft: Für die Unterstützung von KMU und Start-ups, die aktuell keinen Zugang zum Förderinstrument «Accelerator» des European Innovation Council (EIC) haben, setzt er eine neue Gesetzesbestimmung bereits auf den 15. April 2022 in Kraft. Ebenso hat der Bundesrat am 4. März 2022 die entsprechenden finanziellen Massnahmen zuhanden des Parlaments verabschiedet. Die übrigen Bestimmungen des revidierten Gesetzes sollen am 1. Januar 2023 in Kraft treten.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Die Schweiz gilt zurzeit als nicht assoziiertes Drittland bei «Horizon Europe», dem EU-Rahmenprogramm für Forschung und Innovation. In diesem Status ist eine Beteiligung am Förderinstrument «Accelerator» des European Innovation Council (EIC), mit dem innovative kleine und mittlere Unternehmen gefördert werden, nicht möglich. Betroffen sind Schweizer KMU und insbesondere Start-ups. Vor diesem Hintergrund hat das Parlament in der Herbstsession 2021 eine Bestimmung in das Bundesgesetz über die Förderung der Forschung und der Innovation (FIFG) aufgenommen, die es der Schweizerischen Agentur für Innovationsförderung Innosuisse ermöglicht, ein eigenes Programm umzusetzen, solange sich Schweizer Unternehmen nicht an Ausschreibungen des «EIC Accelerator» beteiligen können. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Der Bundesrat hat am 4. März 2022 das Inkrafttreten dieser Gesetzesbestimmung auf den 15. April 2022 beschlossen sowie die dazugehörende Änderung der Beitragsverordnung der Innosuisse genehmigt. Zudem hat er die finanziellen Mittel für Übergangsmassnahmen der Innosuisse zu den Ausschreibungen des «EIC Accelerator» 2022 zuhanden des Parlaments verabschiedet. Innosuisse wird die Ausschreibung auf ihrer Website veröffentlichen. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Die übrigen Bestimmungen des revidierten Gesetzes werden am 1. Januar 2023 in Kraft treten. Sie betreffen vorwiegend die Innovationsförderung. Die Gesetzesrevision erhöht den Handlungsspielraum und die Flexibilität von Innosuisse. So können sich Unternehmen als Umsetzungspartner bei der Förderung von Innovationsprojekten durch Innosuisse neu mit 40 bis 60 Prozent an den Gesamtprojektkosten beteiligen. Bis anhin galt grundsätzlich eine hälftige Beteiligung. Im Einzelfall kann Innosuisse künftig eine höhere (über 60%) oder eine tiefere (unter 40%) Beteiligung des Umsetzungspartners festlegen. Ein besonderes Gewicht kommt neu der Förderung von Innovationsprojekten von Start-ups zu: Innosuisse wird Innovationsprojekte von Jungunternehmen zur Vorbereitung ihres erstmaligen Markteintritts direkt fördern können.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Kommunikation WBF info@gs-wbf.admin.ch, +41 58 462 20 07</contact>
      <link id="228226">
        <title>Bundesgesetz über die Förderung der Forschung und der Innovation (FIFG) (Änderungen bei der Innovationsförderung)</title>
        <uri>https://www.fedlex.admin.ch/eli/fga/2021/3003/de</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="228229">
        <title>Innosuisse</title>
        <uri>https://www.innosuisse.ch/</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>« Horizon Europe » : le Conseil fédéral adopte des mesures transitoires pour les PME et les start-up</title>
      <lead>Le Conseil fédéral a décidé d’échelonner l’entrée en vigueur de la révision de la loi fédérale sur l’encouragement de la recherche et de l’innovation (LERI). Pour soutenir les PME et les start-up suisses, qui n’ont actuellement pas accès à l’instrument « Accelerator » du Conseil européen de l’innovation, une nouvelle disposition entrera en force dès le 15 avril. Le Conseil fédéral a également approuvé, le 4 mars 2022, les mesures de financement correspondantes à l’intention du Parlement. L’entrée en vigueur des autres dispositions concernées par la révision est prévue pour le 1er janvier 2023.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;La Suisse est actuellement considérée comme un pays tiers non associé au programme-cadre de recherche et d’innovation de l’UE « Horizon Europe ». Or, ce statut ne permet pas de participer à l’instrument « Accelerator » du Conseil européen de l’innovation (&lt;i&gt;European Innovation Council&lt;/i&gt;, EIC), qui vise à encourager les petites et moyennes entreprises particulièrement innovantes. Les PME suisses, et notamment les start-up, sont donc directement concernées. Dans ce contexte, le Parlement a adopté, lors de sa session d’automne 2021, une disposition de la loi fédérale sur l’encouragement de la recherche et de l’innovation (LERI) qui autorise Innosuisse, l’Agence suisse pour l’encouragement de l’innovation, à déployer son propre programme de soutien aux entreprises suisses tant que celles-ci ne peuvent pas participer aux appels à projets de l’EIC Accelerator. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Le 4 mars 2022, le Conseil fédéral a décidé que cette disposition entrerait en vigueur le 15 avril 2022, en même temps que les modifications correspondantes de l’ordonnance sur les contributions d’Innosuisse. Il a également approuvé, à l’intention du Parlement, l’enveloppe financière pour les mesures transitoires d’Innosuisse pour les appels à projets 2022 de l’EIC Accelerator. Dans le cadre de ces mesures, Innosuisse publiera les appels à propositions sur son site Internet. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Il est prévu que les autres dispositions concernées par la révision, qui relèvent essentiellement de l’encouragement de l’innovation, entrent en vigueur le 1er janvier 2023. La révision de la loi offre davantage de marge de manœuvre et une plus grande souplesse à Innosuisse. Désormais, le soutien apporté par Innosuisse aux entreprises, dans leur position de partenaires chargés de la mise en valeur, se situe dans une fourchette comprise entre 40 et 60 % du coût total d’un projet d’innovation. Auparavant, la règle voulait que les coûts soient partagés à parts égales. Dans certains cas, Innosuisse pourra fixer une participation du partenaire chargé de la mise en valeur plus élevée (&gt; 60 %) ou, à l’inverse, plus basse (&lt; 40 %). L’encouragement de projets innovants émanant de start-up occupe désormais une place plus importante : Innosuisse pourra soutenir directement les projets d’innovation de jeunes entreprises qui préparent leur entrée sur le marché.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Communication DEFR info@gs-wbf.admin.ch, +41 58 462 20 07</contact>
      <link id="228227">
        <title>Loi fédérale sur l’encouragement de la recherche et de l’innovation (LERI) (Adaptations concernant l’encouragement de l’innovation)</title>
        <uri>https://www.fedlex.admin.ch/eli/fga/2021/3003/fr</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="228229">
        <title>Innosuisse</title>
        <uri>https://www.innosuisse.ch/</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>«Orizzonte Europa»: il Consiglio federale adotta misure transitorie per PMI e start-up</title>
      <lead>Per la legge federale riveduta sulla promozione della ricerca e dell’innovazione (LPRI) il Consiglio federale ha previsto un’entrata in vigore scaglionata. Il 15 aprile 2022 entrerà in vigore una nuova disposizione a sostegno di PMI e start-up, che non hanno accesso allo strumento di promozione «Accelerator» del Consiglio europeo dell’innovazione (EIC). Il 4 marzo sono state adottate le apposite misure finanziarie all’attenzione del Parlamento. Le altre disposizioni della legge riveduta entreranno in vigore il 1° gennaio 2023.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Attualmente la Svizzera partecipa al programma quadro dell’UE di ricerca e innovazione «Orizzonte Europa» come Paese terzo non associato. Con questo status non può partecipare allo strumento di promozione «Accelerator» del Consiglio europeo dell’innovazione (EIC), che sostiene le piccole e medie imprese innovative. La situazione tocca le PMI svizzere e in particolare le start-up. Per questo, nella sessione autunnale 2021 il Parlamento ha deciso di introdurre nella legge federale sulla promozione della ricerca e dell’innovazione (LPRI) una disposizione che consente a Innosuisse, l’Agenzia svizzera per la promozione dell’innovazione, di realizzare un proprio programma finché le imprese svizzere non potranno partecipare ai bandi dell’«EIC Accelerator». &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Il 4 marzo 2022 il Consiglio federale ha deciso che la disposizione entrerà in vigore il 15 aprile 2022 e ha autorizzato l’apposita modifica dell’ordinanza sui sussidi di Innosuisse. Ha inoltre stanziato i fondi per le misure transitorie dell’Agenzia riguardanti i bandi 2022 dell’«EIC Accelerator» all’attenzione del Parlamento. Nell’ambito di queste misure, Innosuisse pubblicherà il bando sul proprio sito. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Le altre disposizioni della legge riveduta, che riguardano principalmente la promozione dell’innovazione, entreranno in vigore il 1° gennaio 2023. La revisione incrementa il margine di manovra e la flessibilità di Innosuisse. Pertanto, d’ora in poi nella promozione dei progetti d’innovazione i partner attuatori (le aziende) parteciperanno ai costi complessivi di progetto nella misura del 40 al 60 per cento, mentre finora era prevista una partecipazione al 50 per cento. In casi particolari l'Agenzia potrà stabilire una partecipazione del partner attuatore superiore al 60 per cento o inferiore al 40 per cento. Sarà posta un’enfasi speciale sulla promozione dei progetti d’innovazione delle start-up: Innosuisse potrà infatti promuovere direttamente i progetti d’innovazione di queste ultime in vista del loro primo ingresso sul mercato.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Comunicazione DEFR info@gs-wbf.admin.ch, +41 58 462 20 07</contact>
      <link id="228228">
        <title>Legge federale sulla promozione della ricerca e dell’innovazione (LPRI) (Modifiche in materia di promozione dell’innovazione)</title>
        <uri>https://www.fedlex.admin.ch/eli/fga/2021/3003/it</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="228229">
        <title>Innosuisse</title>
        <uri>https://www.innosuisse.ch/</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Horizon Europe: Federal Council adopts transitional measures for SMEs and start-ups</title>
      <lead>The Federal Council is staggering the entry into force of the revised Federal Act on the Promotion of Research and Innovation (RIPA). A new legislative provision will come into force on 15 April 2022 to support SMEs and start-ups that currently do not have access to the European Innovation Council's Accelerator funding instrument. The Federal Council also approved and submitted to Parliament the related financial measures on 4 March 2022. The remaining provisions of the revised Act are to enter into force on 1 January 2023.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Switzerland is currently a non-associated third country in Horizon Europe, the EU framework programme for research and innovation. This status does not allow participation in the Accelerator funding instrument of the European Innovation Council (EIC), which supports innovative small and medium-sized enterprises. This concerns Swiss SMEs and, in particular, start-ups. In its autumn 2021 session, Parliament therefore included a provision in the Federal Act on the Promotion of Research and Innovation (RIPA) to allow the Swiss Innovation Agency (Innosuisse) to implement its own programme as long as Swiss companies cannot participate in EIC Accelerator calls for proposals. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;On 4 March, the Federal Council decided that this legislative provision would come into force on 15 April 2022 and approved the related amendment to the Innosuisse Funding Ordinance. It also approved and submitted to Parliament the financial resources for Innosuisse's transitional measures for the 2022 EIC Accelerator calls for proposals. Innosuisse will publish the calls implementing these measures on its website. &lt;/p&gt; The remaining provisions of the revised law, which mainly concern the promotion of innovation, are planned to enter into force on 1 January 2023. The revised law increases Innosuisse's room for manoeuvre and flexibility by allowing companies to contribute between 40 and 60% of the total costs of innovation projects as Innosuisse implementation partners. Up to now, a 50% contribution has been the rule. In future, Innosuisse may determine a higher (above 60%) or lower (below 40%) partner contribution in individual cases. Special emphasis will now be placed on funding innovation projects by start-ups. Innosuisse will be able to directly support start-up innovation projects preparing for their market entry.</text>
      <contact>EAER Communications info@gs-wbf.admin.ch, +41 58 462 20 07</contact>
      <link id="228226">
        <title>Bundesgesetz über die Förderung der Forschung und der Innovation (FIFG) (Änderungen bei der Innovationsförderung)</title>
        <uri>https://www.fedlex.admin.ch/eli/fga/2021/3003/de</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="228229">
        <title>Innosuisse</title>
        <uri>https://www.innosuisse.ch/</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="8">
        <name lang="de">Bildung und Forschung</name>
        <name lang="fr">Formation et recherche</name>
        <name lang="it">Formazione e ricerca</name>
        <name lang="en">Education and Research</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="10">
        <name lang="de">Bundesrat</name>
        <name lang="fr">Conseil fédéral</name>
        <name lang="it">Consiglio federale</name>
        <name lang="en">Federal Council</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="34">
        <name lang="de">Europa</name>
        <name lang="fr">Europe</name>
        <name lang="it">Europa</name>
        <name lang="en">Europe</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="45">
        <name lang="de">Technologie</name>
        <name lang="fr">Technologie</name>
        <name lang="it">Tecnologia</name>
        <name lang="en">Technology</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="47">
        <name lang="de">Wirtschaft</name>
        <name lang="fr">Économie</name>
        <name lang="it">Economia</name>
        <name lang="en">Economic Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
