<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="87561" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2022-03-11</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="1070" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>1070</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Der Bundesrat</name>
      <name lang="fr">Conseil fédéral</name>
      <name lang="it">Il Consiglio federale</name>
      <name lang="en">The Federal Council</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.admin.ch/gov/de/start.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.admin.ch/gov/fr/accueil.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.admin.ch/gov/it/pagina-iniziale.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.admin.ch/gov/en/start.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="201" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>201</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="1070">
      <name lang="de">Der Bundesrat</name>
      <name lang="fr">Conseil fédéral</name>
      <name lang="it">Il Consiglio federale</name>
      <name lang="en">The Federal Council</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.admin.ch/gov/de/start.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.admin.ch/gov/fr/accueil.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.admin.ch/gov/it/pagina-iniziale.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.admin.ch/gov/en/start.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <department id="201">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Ukraine: Bundesrat beschliesst 80 Millionen Franken für die humanitäre Hilfe der Schweiz in der Ukraine und der Region</title>
      <lead>Aufgrund der anhaltenden Militärintervention Russlands in der Ukraine sind rund 12 Millionen Menschen auf Nothilfe angewiesen. Der Bundesrat hat an seiner Sitzung vom 11. März entschieden, die humanitäre Hilfe in der Ukraine und der Region auf 80 Millionen Franken aufzustocken. Damit zeigt sich die Schweiz solidarisch mit der notleidenden ukrainischen Bevölkerung.</lead>
      <text link="no">Infolge des russischen Angriffs auf die Ukraine sind aktuell etwa 12 Millionen Menschen auf Nothilfe angewiesen. Viele unter ihnen haben keinen Zugang zu Strom, Wasser, Lebensmitteln und anderen Gütern der Grundversorgung. Millionen von Menschen sind innerhalb der Ukraine auf der Flucht. Zusätzlich sind gemäss Hochkommissariat der Vereinten Nationen für Flüchtlinge (UNHCR) bereits über zwei Millionen Menschen in Nachbarländer geflüchtet, über die Hälfte davon nach Polen. Bei den vertriebenen Personen handelt es sich grösstenteils um Frauen und Kinder, da wehrfähige Männer zur Verteidigung in der Ukraine zurückbleiben müssen. Die UNO sowie die Rotkreuz- und Rothalbmondbewegung beziffern in ihren jüngst lancierten Hilfsaufrufen den Finanzierungsbedarf für die Ukraine und die Nachbarstaaten für die nächsten drei Monate auf knapp 2 Milliarden US-Dollar.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Die Schweiz hat auf den Krieg in der Ukraine durch die rasche Bereitstellung von humanitärer Hilfe reagiert. Das humanitäre Unterstützungspaket der Schweiz besteht zurzeit aus drei Komponenten: Lieferung von Hilfsgütern, Einsatz von Expertinnen und Experten des Schweizerischen Korps für humanitäre Hilfe (SKH) und finanzielle Unterstützung an humanitäre Organisationen. Die Schweiz hat schon mehr als 500 Tonnen Hilfsgüter in die Ukraine sowie nach Polen und Moldawien geschickt. Das Unterstützungspaket der Schweiz beläuft sich in dieser ersten Phase auf 8 Millionen Franken.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;b&gt;Massive Aufstockung der finanziellen Hilfe&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Angesichts der Flüchtlingskrise hat der Bundesrat an seiner Sitzung vom 11. März beschlossen, die humanitäre Hilfe für die Ukraine auf insgesamt 80 Millionen Franken aufzustocken. Dadurch trägt die Schweiz ihrer humanitären Tradition Rechnung und zeigt sich solidarisch mit der notleidenden ukrainischen Bevölkerung. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Ein Viertel dieser 80 Millionen Franken soll zu Gunsten der geflohenen Ukrainerinnen und Ukrainer in den Nachbarländern eingesetzt werden. Drei Viertel sind für die Unterstützung der zurückgebliebenen Bevölkerung in der Ukraine vorgesehen. Die Mittel teilen sich auf zwischen Beiträgen an die Rotkreuz- und Rothalbmondbewegung, an UNO-Agenturen, an internationale und lokale NGOs sowie an Projekte, die von der Direktion für Entwicklung und Zusammenarbeit (DEZA) in der Ukraine umgesetzt werden. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Das EDA trägt 21 Millionen Franken aus bestehenden Krediten bei, das EJPD beteiligt sich mit 6 Millionen Franken. Die restlichen 53 Millionen Franken sind zusätzliche Mittel und werden dem Parlament zur Bewilligung unterbreitet.</text>
      <contact>für weitere Informationen: Kommunikation EDA Tel. +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Medienstelle +41 58 460 55 55 kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Ukraine : Le Conseil fédéral débloque 80 millions de francs pour l’aide humanitaire de la Suisse en Ukraine et dans la région</title>
      <lead>En raison de l’intervention militaire russe qui se poursuit en Ukraine, environ 12 millions de personnes ont besoin de l’aide d’urgence. Lors de sa séance du 11 mars, le Conseil fédéral a décidé d’augmenter à 80 millions de francs l’aide humanitaire en Ukraine et dans la région. La Suisse manifeste ainsi sa solidarité avec la population ukrainienne en détresse.</lead>
      <text link="no">Suite à l’attaque russe contre l’Ukraine, près de 12 millions de personnes dépendent actuellement de l’aide d'urgence. Beaucoup d’entre elles n’ont aucun accès à l’électricité, à l’eau, à la nourriture et aux autres produits de première nécessité. Des millions de personnes sont déplacées à l'intérieur de l’Ukraine. De plus, selon le Haut-Commissariat des Nations Unies pour les réfugiés (HCR), plus de deux millions de personnes se sont déjà réfugiées dans les pays voisins, dont plus de la moitié en Pologne. Les personnes déplacées sont en grande partie des femmes et des enfants, car les hommes en âge de combattre doivent rester en Ukraine pour défendre leur pays. Dans leurs derniers appels d’aide, l’ONU et le Mouvement international de la Croix-Rouge et du Croissant-Rouge estiment les besoins de financement pour l’Ukraine et les pays voisins à près de 2 milliards de dollars.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;La Suisse a rapidement fourni une aide humanitaire en réaction au déclenchement de la guerre en Ukraine. La série de mesures de soutien humanitaire prises actuellement par la Suisse comporte trois volets: livraison de matériel de secours, intervention d’experts du Corps suisse d’aide humanitaire (CSA) et soutien financier à des organisations humanitaires. La Suisse a déjà envoyé plus de 500 tonnes de matériel de secours en Ukraine ainsi qu’en Pologne et en Moldavie. Le montant de cette série de mesures de soutien déployées par la Suisse s’élève pour l’instant à 8 millions de francs. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Augmentation massive de l’aide financière&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Face à la crise des réfugiés, le Conseil fédéral a décidé, lors de sa séance du 11 mars, d’augmenter le montant de l’aide humanitaire pour l’Ukraine à un total de 80 millions de francs. La Suisse perpétue ainsi sa tradition humanitaire et manifeste sa solidarité avec la population ukrainienne en détresse. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Un quart des 80 millions de francs débloqués sera utilisé en faveur des Ukrainiennes et Ukrainiens qui ont fui dans les pays voisins. Les trois quarts restants sont destinés à aider la population ukrainienne restée sur place. Les fonds seront alloués sous forme de contributions au Mouvement de la Croix-Rouge et du Croissant-Rouge, à des agences onusiennes, à des ONG internationales et locales et à des projets mis en œuvre par la Direction du développement et de la coopération (DDC) en Ukraine. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Le DFAE verse une participation de 21 millions de francs prélevés sur des crédits existants et le DFJP participe à hauteur de 6 millions de francs. Les 53 millions de francs restants sont des fonds supplémentaires qui seront soumis au Parlement pour approbation. </text>
      <contact>Pour plus d'informations: Communication DFAE Tél. +41 58 462 31 53 Tél. Service de presse +41 58 460 55 55 kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Ucraina: Il Consiglio federale approva lo stanziamento di 80 milioni di franchi per l’aiuto umanitario della Svizzera in Ucraina e nella regione</title>
      <lead>A causa dell’intervento militare della Russia in Ucraina, ancora in corso, circa 12 milioni di persone necessitano di aiuti di emergenza. Nella sua seduta dell’11 marzo il Consiglio federale ha deciso di aumentare i fondi per l’aiuto umanitario in Ucraina e nella regione a 80 milioni di franchi. La Svizzera si dimostra così solidale con la popolazione ucraina.</lead>
      <text link="no">A causa dell’attacco russo all’Ucraina, circa 12 milioni di persone necessitano attualmente di aiuti di emergenza. Molte di loro non hanno accesso a elettricità, acqua, cibo e altri beni di prima necessità. Milioni di persone sono in fuga all’interno del Paese e secondo l’Alto Commissariato delle Nazioni Unite per i rifugiati (ACNUR), più di due milioni sono già fuggite nei Paesi vicini, oltre la metà in Polonia. La maggior parte degli sfollati sono donne e bambini, poiché gli uomini abili alle armi devono rimanere in Ucraina per difendere il Paese. In alcuni appelli diffusi di recente, l’ONU e il Movimento della Croce Rossa e della Mezzaluna Rossa hanno stimato il fabbisogno di fondi per l’Ucraina e i Paesi confinanti per i prossimi tre mesi in quasi 2 miliardi di dollari.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;La Svizzera ha reagito alla guerra in Ucraina fornendo rapidamente aiuto umanitario. Il pacchetto di aiuti della Svizzera prevede attualmente tre componenti: la consegna di beni di prima necessità, l’invio di esperte ed esperti del Corpo svizzero di aiuto umanitario (CSA) e il sostegno finanziario alle organizzazioni umanitarie. La Svizzera ha già inviato oltre 500 tonnellate di beni di prima necessità in Ucraina, Polonia e Moldova. Il pacchetto di aiuti ammonta in questa prima fase a otto milioni di franchi.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;b&gt;Aumento notevole degli aiuti finanziari&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;In considerazione della crisi dei profughi, nella sua seduta dell’11 marzo il Consiglio federale ha deciso di aumentare l’aiuto umanitario per l’Ucraina e la regione portandolo a un importo complessivo di 80 milioni di franchi. In questo modo la Svizzera tiene fede alla sua tradizione umanitaria e si dimostra solidale con la popolazione ucraina bisognosa. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Un quarto di questi 80 milioni dovrà essere utilizzato per assistere le Ucraine e gli Ucraini fuggiti nei Paesi vicini. Tre quarti sono destinati al sostegno della popolazione rimasta in Ucraina. I fondi sono suddivisi in contributi al Movimento della Croce Rossa e della Mezzaluna Rossa, ad agenzie dell’ONU, a ONG locali e internazionali e a progetti realizzati dalla Direzione dello sviluppo e della cooperazione (DSC) in Ucraina. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Il DFAE contribuisce con 21 milioni di franchi provenienti da crediti esistenti, il DFGP con sei milioni di franchi. I restanti 53 milioni sono fondi aggiuntivi e saranno sottoposti al Parlamento per approvazione. </text>
      <contact>Informazioni: Comunicazione DFAE Tel. +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Servizio stampa +41 58 460 55 55 kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Ukraine: Federal Council approves CHF 80 million for Swiss humanitarian aid in Ukraine and wider region</title>
      <lead>Around 12 million people are dependent on emergency aid because of Russia's ongoing military intervention in Ukraine. At its meeting of 11 March, the Federal Council decided to increase humanitarian aid to Ukraine and the wider region to CHF 80 million. With this contribution, Switzerland is expressing its solidarity with Ukrainians in need.</lead>
      <text link="no">About 12 million people are currently dependent on emergency aid as a result of the Russian attack on Ukraine. Many lack access to electricity, water, food and other basic necessities. Millions have been forced to flee their homes but remain in Ukraine. The United Nations High Commissioner for Refugees (UNHCR) warns that over two million people have already fled to neighbouring countries – more than half of them to Poland. The vast majority of those displaced are women and children, as able-bodied men are obliged to remain behind in Ukraine to defend their country. In their latest appeals for support, the UN and the Red Cross and Red Crescent Movement put the funding needs for Ukraine and neighbouring countries at just under USD 2 billion over the next three months.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Switzerland responded swiftly to the war in Ukraine with humanitarian aid. Switzerland's humanitarian support package currently involves three elements: sending relief supplies, deploying Swiss Humanitarian Aid Unit (SHA) specialists and providing financial support to humanitarian organisations. To date, Switzerland has sent over 500 tonnes of relief supplies to Ukraine, Poland and Moldova. Switzerland's support package for the initial phase of the aid operation amounts to CHF 8 million.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;b&gt;Major increase in financial aid&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;In response to the refugee crisis, the Federal Council decided at its meeting of 11 March to increase humanitarian aid to Ukraine to a total of CHF 80 million. With this contribution, Switzerland is expressing its solidarity with the people of Ukraine in their time of need.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;A quarter of this sum will be used to help Ukrainian refugees in neighbouring countries. Three quarters are earmarked to help those who have remained in Ukraine. The funds will go to the Red Cross and Red Crescent Movement, UN agencies, international and local NGOs and projects implemented by the Swiss Agency for Development and Cooperation (SDC) in Ukraine. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The FDFA is contributing CHF 21 million from existing credits; the Federal Department of Justice and Police CHF 6 million. The remaining CHF 53 million are additional funds and will be submitted to parliamentary approval.</text>
      <contact>For further information: FDFA Communication Tel. +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Press service +41 460 55 55 kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
