<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="87747" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2022-03-25</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="1070" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>1070</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Der Bundesrat</name>
      <name lang="fr">Conseil fédéral</name>
      <name lang="it">Il Consiglio federale</name>
      <name lang="en">The Federal Council</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.admin.ch/gov/de/start.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.admin.ch/gov/fr/accueil.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.admin.ch/gov/it/pagina-iniziale.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.admin.ch/gov/en/start.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="yes" id="703" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>701</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Staatssekretariat für Wirtschaft</name>
      <name lang="fr">Secrétariat d'Etat à l'économie</name>
      <name lang="it">Segreteria di Stato dell'economia</name>
      <name lang="en">State Secretariat for Economic Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.seco.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.seco.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.seco.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.seco.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@seco.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@seco.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@seco.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@seco.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="1070">
      <name lang="de">Der Bundesrat</name>
      <name lang="fr">Conseil fédéral</name>
      <name lang="it">Il Consiglio federale</name>
      <name lang="en">The Federal Council</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.admin.ch/gov/de/start.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.admin.ch/gov/fr/accueil.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.admin.ch/gov/it/pagina-iniziale.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.admin.ch/gov/en/start.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <department id="701">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Wirtschaft, Bildung und Forschung</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'économie, de la formation et de la recherche</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'economia, della formazione e della ricerca</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Economic Affairs, Education and Research</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Ukraine: Weitere EU-Sanktionen umgesetzt</title>
      <lead>Der Bundesrat hat am 25. März 2022 angesichts der anhaltenden Militärinvasion in der Ukraine weitere Sanktionen gegenüber Russland verabschiedet. Damit ist der Entscheid des Bundesrates vom 18. März 2022, auch das neueste Sanktionspaket der EU zu übernehmen, umgesetzt. Die Massnahmen treten am 25. März 2022 um 23 Uhr in Kraft. </lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Mit dem Entscheid vom 25. März 2022 schliesst sich die Schweiz den Massnahmen an, welche die EU am 9. und 15. März 2022 angesichts der anhaltenden Militärinvasion Russlands in der Ukraine beschlossenen hat. Bereits am 16. März 2022 hat die Schweiz die von der EU bis dahin beschlossenen Ausweitungen der Liste der Personen, die von Finanzsanktionen betroffen sind, umgesetzt.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Die Ausfuhr von Gütern für den Energiesektor und damit verbundene Dienstleistungen werden neu untersagt. Ebenfalls verboten sind Beteiligungen und Bereitstellung von Darlehen oder sonstiger Finanzmittel an Unternehmen, die im Energiesektor tätig sind. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Neu wird ein Einfuhrverbot von Eisen- und Stahlerzeugnissen aus oder mit Ursprung in Russland sowie ein Verbot der Ausfuhr von Luxusgütern und Gütern zur maritimen Navigation nach Russland eingeführt. Im Finanzbereich werden Transaktionen mit gewissen staatseigenen Unternehmen und die Bereitstellung von Ratingdienstleistungen verboten.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Weiter hat der Bundesrat gewisse Ausnahmen von den Finanzsanktionen für humanitäre Zwecke beschlossen. Dadurch werden Geschäftsbeziehungen, die für die Arbeit der humanitären Organisationen erforderlich sind, erleichtert. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Damit sind alle Massnahmen zum 4. Sanktionspaket der EU umgesetzt.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Zudem hat der Bundesrat entschieden, die Massnahme der EU vom 1. März 2022 betreffend die Verbreitung von Inhalten bestimmter russischer Sender, namentlich Sputnik und Russia Today, nicht umzusetzen. Auch wenn es sich bei diesen Kanälen um Werkzeuge der gezielten Propaganda und Desinformation durch die Russische Föderation handelt, ist der Bundesrat der Meinung, dass es wirksamer sei, unwahren und schädlichen Äusserungen mit Fakten zu begegnen, anstatt sie zu verbieten.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Rückfragen Medien: Kommunikation WBF, Tel. 058 462 20 07, info@gs-wbf.admin.ch Rückfragen Unternehmen (Sanktionen): sanctions@seco.admin.ch, Tel. 058 464 08 12</contact>
      <link id="229057">
        <title>Massnahmen im Zusammenhang mit der Situation in der Ukraine (admin.ch)</title>
        <uri>https://bit.ly/3wCo8Q5</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Ukraine : le Conseil fédéral met en œuvre d’autres sanctions</title>
      <lead>Le 25 mars 2022, le Conseil fédéral a adopté des sanctions supplémentaires à l’encontre de la Russie en raison de la poursuite de l’agression militaire de ce pays contre l’Ukraine. La décision du Conseil fédéral du 18 mars 2022, qui prévoit la reprise du dernier train de sanctions de l’UE, est ainsi mise en œuvre. Les mesures entrent en vigueur le 25 mars 2022, à 23 heures.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Par la décision du 25 mars 2022, la Suisse s’associe aux mesures que l’UE a arrêtées respectivement le le 9 et le 15 mars 2022 en raison de la poursuite de l’agression militaire de la Russie contre l’Ukraine. Le 16 mars 2022, elle avait déjà repris l’extension de la liste des personnes visées par des sanctions financières arrêtées par l’UE. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;L’exportation de biens destinés au secteur énergétique et les prestations qui y sont liées sont interdites. Sont aussi interdites la fourniture de prêts ou d’autres moyens financiers à des entreprises opérant dans le secteur énergétique ainsi que les participations dans ces entreprises. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;L’importation de produits sidérurgiques originaires ou provenant de Russie et l’exportation à destination de la Russie d’articles de luxe et de biens servant à la navigation maritime sont aussi interdites. Dans le domaine financier, les transactions avec certaines entreprises d’État et la fourniture de services de notation de crédit sont interdites. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Le Conseil fédéral a arrêté certaines dérogations aux sanctions financières à des fins humanitaires, afin de faciliter le travail des organisations humanitaires. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Toutes les mesures du quatrième train de sanctions de l’UE sont ainsi reprises. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Le Conseil fédéral a en revanche décidé de ne pas reprendre la mesure arrêtée par l’UE le 1er mars 2022 concernant la diffusion des contenus de certaines chaînes russes, notamment Sputnik et Russia Today. Même si ces canaux sont des outils de propagande et de désinformation de la Fédération russe, le Conseil fédéral est convaincu qu’il est plus efficace, pour contrer des affirmations inexactes et dommageables, de leur opposer des faits plutôt que de les interdire. &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Renseignements (médias) : Communication DEFR,tél. 058 462 20 07, info@gs-wbf.admin.ch Renseignements (entreprises) : sanctions@seco.admin.ch, tél. 058 464 08 12</contact>
      <link id="229058">
        <title>Mesures en lien avec la situation en Ukraine (admin.ch)</title>
        <uri>https://bit.ly/3NhuZ7L</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Ucraina: attuate ulteriori sanzioni dell'UE</title>
      <lead>Il 25 marzo 2022 il Consiglio federale ha adottato ulteriori sanzioni nei confronti della Russia a seguito del perdurare dell’invasione militare in Ucraina. Viene così attuata la decisione del Consiglio federale del 18 marzo 2022 di riprendere anche il più recente pacchetto di sanzioni dell'UE. I provvedimenti entrano in vigore il 25 marzo 2022, alle ore 23.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Con la decisione del 25 marzo 2022 la Svizzera aderisce ai provvedimenti varati dall'Unione europea (UE) il 9 e il 15 marzo scorsi a seguito del perdurare dell’invasione militare della Russia in Ucraina. La Svizzera ha già attuato, il 16 marzo, l'ampliamento della lista di persone colpite da sanzioni finanziarie, secondo quanto deciso dall'UE a tale data.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ora sono vietate l'esportazione di beni del settore energetico e la fornitura dei relativi servizi, così come è proibito partecipare o mettere a disposizione prestiti o altri mezzi finanziari alle imprese attive nel settore energetico. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;È vietato importare prodotti siderurgici provenienti o originari della Federazione Russa, nonché esportare nella Federazione Russa beni di lusso e beni per la navigazione marittima. In ambito finanziario sono vietate le transazioni con talune imprese statali e la messa disposizione di servizi di rating del credito.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Il Consiglio federale ha inoltre deciso alcune deroghe alle sanzioni finanziarie, se finalizzate ad attività umanitarie. Ciò facilita le relazioni commerciali necessarie per l'operato delle organizzazioni umanitarie.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Con ciò sono stati attuati tutti i provvedimenti del quarto pacchetto di sanzioni dell'UE.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Oltre a ciò il Consiglio federale ha deciso di non attuare il provvedimento UE del 1° marzo relativo alla diffusione dei contenuti di alcuni organi di informazioni russi, segnatamente Sputnik e Russia Today. Pur trattandosi di strumenti di propaganda e disinformazione mirata utilizzati dalla Federazione Russa, il Consiglio federale ritiene più efficace rispondere con i fatti a dichiarazioni fallaci e dannose, anziché vietarle.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Domande (per i giornalisti): Comunicazione DEFR, tel. 058 462 20 07, info@gs-wbf.admin.ch Domande (per le imprese): sanctions@seco.admin.ch, tel. 058 464 08 12</contact>
      <link id="229059">
        <title>Provvedimenti in relazione alla situazione in Ucraina (admin.ch)</title>
        <uri>https://bit.ly/36LMOe4</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Ukraine: Implementation of further EU sanctions</title>
      <lead>In response to Russia’s ongoing invasion of Ukraine, the Federal Council took the decision on 25 March to adopt further sanctions against Russia, thereby implementing the Federal Council decision of 18 March to adopt the latest package of EU sanctions. The measures come into force at 11pm on 25 March.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;The Federal Council decision of 25 March means that Switzerland remains in line with the measures imposed by the EU on 9 and 15 March in response to Russia’s ongoing invasion of Ukraine. On 16 March, Switzerland had already adopted the extended list of persons and entities subject to financial sanctions imposed by the EU.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The export of goods and related services for the Russian energy sector is now prohibited. Also prohibited is the participation in businesses active in the energy sector and the provision of loans or other financial resources to such businesses.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A ban is introduced on the import of iron and steel goods from Russia, or originating in Russia, as well as a ban on the export of luxury goods and maritime navigation goods to Russia. In the financial sector, transactions with certain state-owned companies and the provision of credit rating services are prohibited.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;However, the Federal Council has decided to allow certain exceptions from the financial sanctions for humanitarian purposes. This eases business relationships necessary for the work of humanitarian organisations.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This means that all measures contained in the EU’s fourth package of sanctions have been implemented.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;However, the Federal Council took the decision not to implement the EU measure of 1 March suspending the broadcasting of contents from certain Russian media outlets, namely Sputnik and Russia Today. Despite the fact that these outlets are used to spread targeted propaganda and disinformation by the Russian Federation, the Federal Council is of the opinion that it is more effective to counter untrue and harmful statements with facts instead of preventing them from being broadcast.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Enquiries from the media: EAR Communications, Tel. 058 462 20 07, info@gs-wbf.admin.ch Enquiries from businesses (sanctions): sanctions@seco.admin.ch, Tel. 058 464 08 12</contact>
      <link id="229060">
        <title>Measures in connection with the Situation in Ukraine (admin.ch)</title>
        <uri>https://bit.ly/3uuTcPi</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <offers>
      <offer id="255" org-id="703">
        <name lang="de">Sanktionen / Embargos und Exportkontrollen</name>
        <name lang="fr">sanctions / embargos et contrôles à l‘exportation</name>
        <name lang="it">Sanzioni / embarghi e controlli delle esportazioni</name>
        <name lang="en">sanctions / embargoes and export controls</name>
      </offer>
    </offers>
    <topics>
      <topic id="47">
        <name lang="de">Wirtschaft</name>
        <name lang="fr">Économie</name>
        <name lang="it">Economia</name>
        <name lang="en">Economic Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
