<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="85619" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2021-10-28</pubdate>
    <blocking-period>2021-10-28</blocking-period>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="318" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>301</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Bundesamt für Statistik</name>
      <name lang="fr">Office fédéral de la statistique</name>
      <name lang="it">Ufficio federale di statistica</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Statistical Office</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.statistik.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.statistique.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.statistica.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.statistics.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@bfs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@bfs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@bfs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@bfs.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="301">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement des Innern</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'intérieur</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'interno</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Home Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Neuchâtel</city>
      <title>Die Bevölkerung der Schweiz ist gegenüber Diversität mehrheitlich offen – mit individuellen und regionalen Unterschieden</title>
      <lead>Im Zeitraum 2016 bis 2020 zeigte sich die Bevölkerung der Schweiz in Bezug auf Diversität insgesamt offen. Nur ein geringer Anteil fühlt sich von als «anders» wahrgenommenen Menschen gestört und die Mehrheit lehnt rassistische Einstellungen ab. Vergleichsweise weniger offen sind Personen, die politisch rechtsorientiert sind, keinen Migrationshintergrund haben oder in dünn besiedelten Gebieten leben. Dies sind einige Ergebnisse aus einer vertieften Analyse der vom Bundesamt für Statistik (BFS) in den Jahren 2016, 2018 und 2020 durchgeführten Erhebung zum Zusammenleben in der Schweiz (ZidS).</lead>
      <text link="no">Diese Medienmitteilung und weitere Informationen zum Thema finden Sie auf der Website des BFS (siehe Link unten)</text>
      <contact>Johanna Probst, BFS, Sektion Demografie und Migration, Tel.: +41 58 466 80 93, E-Mail: johanna.probst@bfs.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="222489">
        <title>Kompletter Text und Mediendossier</title>
        <uri>https://www.bfs.admin.ch/news/de/2021-0551</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Neuchâtel</city>
      <title>La population de la Suisse est généralement ouverte envers la diversité, avec des différences individuelles et régionales</title>
      <lead>Sur la période 2016-2020, la population de la Suisse se montre généralement ouverte envers la diversité. Peu de gens déclarent être dérangés par la présence de personnes perçues comme différentes et la majorité rejette les attitudes racistes. L’ouverture est comparativement moins grande parmi les personnes politiquement orientées à droite, celles n’étant pas issues de la migration ou encore celles vivant dans des zones faiblement peuplées. Ce sont là quelques-uns des résultats de l’analyse approfondie de l’enquête sur le vivre ensemble en Suisse (VeS), réalisée par l’Office fédéral de la statistique (OFS) en 2016, 2018 et 2020.</lead>
      <text link="no">Vous trouverez ce communiqué de presse et d'autres informations sur ce thème sur le site web de l'OFS (voir le lien ci-dessous)</text>
      <contact>Marion Aeberli, OFS, Section Démographie et migration, tél.: +41 58 467 24 67, e-mail: marion.aeberli@bfs.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="222490">
        <title>Texte intégral et dossier de presse</title>
        <uri>https://www.bfs.admin.ch/news/fr/2021-0551</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Neuchâtel</city>
      <title>Generalmente la popolazione della Svizzera è aperta nei confronti della diversità, seppure con differenze individuali e regionali</title>
      <lead>Nel periodo dal 2016 al 2020, la popolazione della Svizzera si è generalmente mostrata aperta nei confronti della diversità. Sono poche le persone che dichiaravano di sentirsi infastidite dalla presenza di persone percepite come diverse e la maggior parte ricusava gli atteggiamenti razzisti. L’apertura è minore per le persone con orientamento politico di destra, quelle senza passato migratorio e quelle che vivono in zone scarsamente popolate. Questi sono alcuni dei risultati dell’analisi approfondita dell’indagine sulla convivenza in Svizzera (VeS), realizzata dall’Ufficio federale di statistica (UST) nel 2016, nel 2018 e nel 2020.</lead>
      <text link="no">Il presente comunicato stampa e ulteriori informazioni sul tema sono reperibili sulla pagina Internet dell'UST (link sotto)</text>
      <contact>Marion Aeberli, UST, Sezione Demografia e migrazione, tel.: +41 58 467 24 67, e-mail: marion.aeberli@bfs.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="222491">
        <title>Testo integrale e dossier per i media</title>
        <uri>https://www.bfs.admin.ch/news/it/2021-0551</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Neuchâtel</city>
      <title>Switzerland’s population is generally open to diversity, with individual and regional differences</title>
      <lead>Over the 2016-2020 period, Switzerland’s population was generally open to diversity. A small part of the population stated that they felt uncomfortable about the presence of people perceived to be different and most rejected racist attitudes. An open attitude is comparatively less likely among people politically oriented to the right, as well as among those with no migration background or those living in sparsely populated zones. These are some of the findings from the in-depth analysis of the survey on diversity and coexistence in Switzerland (VeS) conducted by the Federal Statistical Office (FSO) in 2016, 2018 and 2020.</lead>
      <text link="no">This press release and further information on this topic can be found on the FSO website (see link below)</text>
      <contact>Marion Aeberli, FSO, Demography and Migration section, tel.: +41 58 467 24 67, email: marion.aeberli@bfs.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="222492">
        <title>Please note that the English version only includes the release's lead</title>
        <uri>https://www.bfs.admin.ch/news/en/2021-0551</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <keywords>
      <keyword id="317.2" org-id="318">
        <name lang="de">Bevölkerung</name>
        <name lang="fr">Population</name>
        <name lang="it">Popolazione</name>
        <name lang="en">Population</name>
      </keyword>
    </keywords>
    <topics>
      <topic id="20">
        <name lang="de">Migration</name>
        <name lang="fr">Migrations</name>
        <name lang="it">Migrazione</name>
        <name lang="en">Migration</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="43">
        <name lang="de">Statistik</name>
        <name lang="fr">Statistiques</name>
        <name lang="it">Statistica</name>
        <name lang="en">Statistics</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
