<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="85549" revoked="no">
    <version>2</version>
    <pubdate>2021-10-21</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="701" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>701</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Wirtschaft, Bildung und Forschung</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'économie, de la formation et de la recherche</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'economia, della formazione e della ricerca</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Economic Affairs, Education and Research</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="701">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Wirtschaft, Bildung und Forschung</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'économie, de la formation et de la recherche</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'economia, della formazione e della ricerca</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Economic Affairs, Education and Research</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Bundespräsident reist nach Israel, in das besetzte palästinensische Gebiet und zum Schweizer Tag der Expo Dubai in die VAE</title>
      <lead>Bundespräsident Guy Parmelin wird kommende Woche nach Israel und in das besetzte palästinensische Gebiet reisen. Die Gespräche mit den Staats- und Regierungschefs finden am Donnerstag, 28. Oktober 2021, statt. Am Freitag, 29. Oktober, wird der Bundespräsident in Dubai in den Vereinigten Arabischen Emiraten (VAE) am offiziellen Schweizer Tag der Expo 2020 teilnehmen. Am Samstag, 30. Oktober, sind Gespräche mit der Regierung der VAE angesetzt.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Bei den Gesprächen in Israel und im besetzten palästinensischen Gebiet stehen jeweils die bilaterale Zusammenarbeit in wirtschaftlicher und wissenschaftlicher Hinsicht, die Schaffung von Arbeitsplätzen für palästinensische Jugendliche sowie die Friedensförderung der Schweiz im Vordergrund. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;In Israel wird Bundespräsident Parmelin mit Staatspräsident Isaac Herzog und Ministerpräsident Naftali Bennett zusammenkommen. In Ramallah wird der Bundespräsident an einem Anlass mit Vertretern des schweizerisch-palästinensischen Wirtschaftsrates und der Innovationsszene teilnehmen und Gespräche führen mit Präsident Mahmud Abbas, in Anwesenheit des Vize-Premiers Ziad Abu Amr und des Aussenministers Ryiad Al Malki.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Die ursprünglich für das Jahr 2020 geplante Expo in Dubai wurde coronabedingt erst am 1. Oktober 2021 eröffnet. Es handelt sich um die erste Weltausstellung in der Region Mittlerer Osten, Afrika und Südasien (MEASA) und zugleich ist es die erste, die von einem arabischen Land durchgeführt wird; sie steht unter dem Motto «Connecting Minds, Creating the Future». Bundespräsident Parmelin wird am Schweizer Nationentag teilnehmen und den Landespavillon besuchen, der die Schweiz als führenden Innovations-Standort und als Tourismusdestination präsentiert. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Geplant sind auch Treffen mit Regierungsvertretern der Vereinigten Arabischen Emirate. Dabei werden neben dem Schweizer Expo-Auftritt insbesondere die Wirtschafts- und Finanzbeziehungen zwischen der Schweiz und den VAE, die Zusammenarbeit in den Bereichen Bildung, Wissenschaft und Innovation sowie die regionalen politischen Entwicklungen zur Sprache kommen.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Kommunikation GS-WBF Tel. +41 58 462 20 07 info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="222297">
        <title>Bilaterale Beziehungen Schweiz–Israel</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home/vertretungen-und-reisehinweise/israel/bilatereale-beziehungenschweizisrael.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="222298">
        <title>Bilaterale Beziehungen Schweiz–Besetztes Palästinensisches Gebiet</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home/vertretungen-und-reisehinweise/besetztes-palaestinensisches-gebiet/bilatereale-beziehungen-ch-besetztes-palaestinensisches-gebiet.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="222299">
        <title>Bilaterale Beziehungen Schweiz–Vereinigte Arabische Emirate</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home/vertretungen-und-reisehinweise/vereinigte-arabischeemirate/bilatereale-beziehungenschweizvereinigtearabischeemirate.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="222300">
        <title>Schweizer Pavillon an der Expo Dubai</title>
        <uri>https://houseofswitzerland.org/de/events/schweizer-pavillon-der-expo-dubai</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions>
        <revision date="2021-10-21 15:43" type="R"/>
      </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Le président de la Confédération se rend en Israël, dans le Territoire palestinien occupé ainsi qu’aux Émirats arabes unis à l’occasion de la journée suisse à l’Expo 2020</title>
      <lead>Le président de la Confédération Guy Parmelin se rendra en Israël et dans le Territoire palestinien occupé la semaine prochaine. Les entretiens avec les chefs d'État et de gouvernement auront lieu le jeudi 28 octobre 2021. Le vendredi 29 octobre, Guy Parmelin se rendra à Dubaï aux Émirats arabes unis pour assister à la journée officielle de la Suisse à l'Expo 2020. En outre, des entretiens sont prévus avec le gouvernement des Émirats arabes unis.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Les entretiens en Israël et dans le Territoire palestinien occupé porteront principalement sur la coopération bilatérale en matière économique et scientifique, la création d'emplois pour les jeunes Palestiniens et les activités de promotion de la paix menées par la Suisse. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;En Israël, le président Guy Parmelin rencontrera le président Isaac Herzog et le Premier ministre Naftali Bennett. À Ramallah, il participera à un évènement avec des représentants du Conseil d’entreprises commun Suisse-Palestine et du domaine de l'innovation. Il s'entretiendra aussi avec le président Mahmoud Abbas, en présence du Vice-premier ministre Ziad Abu Amr et du ministre des Affaires étrangères Riyad Al-Maliki.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;L’Expo de Dubaï, sur le thème « Connecter les esprits, construire le futur », était initialement prévue pour 2020, mais a finalement ouvert ses portes le 1er octobre 2021 en raison du COVID-19. Il s'agit de la première exposition universelle dans la région du Moyen-Orient, de l’Afrique et de l’Asie du Sud (MEASA) et de la première à être organisée par un pays arabe. Guy Parmelin participera à la journée nationale suisse et visitera le pavillon suisse, où notre pays est présenté comme un haut lieu de l’innovation et comme une destination touristique. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Des rencontres avec des représentants du gouvernement des Émirats arabes unis sont également prévues. Les entretiens porteront sur la présence de la Suisse à l’Expo, sur les relations économiques et financières entre la Suisse et les Émirats arabes unis, sur la coopération dans les domaines de l'éducation, de la science et de l'innovation et sur les développements politiques régionaux.&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Communication SG DEFR tél. +41 58 462 20 07 info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="222301">
        <title>Relations bilatérales Suisse–Israël</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae/representations-et-conseils-aux-voyageurs/israel/suisse-israel.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="222302">
        <title>Relations bilatérales Suisse–Territoire palestinien occupé</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae/representations-et-conseils-aux-voyageurs/territoire-palestinien-occupe/suisse-territoire-palestinien-occupe.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="222303">
        <title>Relations bilatérales Suisse–Émirats arabes unis</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae/representations-et-conseils-aux-voyageurs/emirats-arabes-unis/suisse-emirats-arabes-unis.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="222304">
        <title>Le Pavillon Suisse à l'Expo Dubaï</title>
        <uri>https://houseofswitzerland.org/fr/events/le-pavillon-suisse-lexpo-dubai</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Il Presidente della Confederazione Parmelin visita Israele, il Territorio palestinese occupato e partecipa alla Giornata svizzera dell’Expo di Dubai negli Emirati arabi uniti</title>
      <lead>La prossima settimana il Presidente della Confederazione Guy Parmelin si recherà in Israele e nel Territorio palestinese occupato. I colloqui con i capi di Stato e di Governo si terranno giovedì 28 ottobre 2021. Venerdì 29 ottobre il Presidente della Confederazione parteciperà negli Emirati arabi uniti alla Giornata ufficiale svizzera dell’Expo 2020. Sono inoltre previsti incontri con il Governo degli Emirati arabi uniti.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Nei colloqui in Israele e nel Territorio palestinese occupato i temi verteranno principalmente sulla collaborazione bilaterale in campo economico e scientifico, sulla creazione di posti di lavoro per i giovani palestinesi e sulla promozione della pace da parte della Svizzera. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;In Israele il Presidente della Confederazione incontrerà il Presidente israeliano Isaac Herzog e il Primo ministro Naftali Bennett. A Ramallah, Parmelin parteciperà a un evento con rappresentanti del Consiglio della scienza svizzero-palestinese e del settore dell’innovazione e avrà uno scambio di vedute con il Presidente palestinese Mahmud Abbas, alla presenza del Vice Primo ministro Ziad Abu Amr e del ministro degli esteri Riyad al-Maliki.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Programmata inizialmente per il 2020, l’apertura dell'Esposizione universale di Dubai è stata posticipata a causa del coronavirus al 1° ottobre 2021. Sarà la prima a tenersi nella regione Medio Oriente, Africa e Asia meridionale e a essere organizzata da un Paese arabo. Il tema dell’Expo è «Unire le menti, creare il futuro». Il Presidente Parmelin parteciperà alla Giornata nazionale svizzera e visiterà il padiglione nazionale che presenta la Svizzera come una piazza di punta dell’innovazione e come destinazione turistica.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Il programma prevede anche incontri con rappresentanti del Governo degli Emirati arabi uniti. Oltre che sulla presenza della Svizzera all’Expo, i colloqui verteranno in particolare sulle relazioni economiche e finanziarie tra Svizzera ed Emirati arabi uniti, sulla collaborazione nei settori dell’educazione, della scienza e dell’innovazione e sull’evoluzione politica regionale.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Comunicazione SG-DEFR tel. +41 58 462 20 07 info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="222305">
        <title>Relazioni bilaterali Svizzera–Israele</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae/rappresentanze-e-consigli-di-viaggio/israele/svizzera-israele.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="222306">
        <title>Relazioni bilaterali Svizzera–Territorio palestinese occupato</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae/rappresentanze-e-consigli-di-viaggio/territorio-palestinese-occupato/svizzera-territorio-palestinese-occupato.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="222307">
        <title>Relazioni bilaterali Svizzera–Emirati arabi uniti</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae/rappresentanze-e-consigli-di-viaggio/emirati-arabi-uniti/svizzera-emirati-arabi-uniti.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="222308">
        <title>Il Padiglione svizzero all'Expo Dubai</title>
        <uri>https://houseofswitzerland.org/it/events/il-padiglione-svizzero-allexpo-dubai</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>President Parmelin to travel to Israel, the occupied Palestinian territory and United Arab Emirates for Expo Dubai Swiss Day</title>
      <lead>The President of the Swiss Confederation, Mr Guy Parmelin, will travel to Israel and the occupied Palestinian territory next week. Talks with the heads of state and government will be held on Thursday 28 October. On Friday 29 October, Mr Parmelin will be in Dubai in the United Arab Emirates (UAE) to attend the official Swiss Day at Expo 2020. Talks with the UAE government are also scheduled.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;The talks in Israel and in the occupied Palestinian territory will focus on bilateral cooperation in economic and science matters, the creation of jobs for Palestinian youth and Switzerland's peace promotion efforts. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;In Israel, Mr Parmelin will meet with President Isaac Herzog and Prime Minister Naftali Bennett. While in Ramallah, he will take part in an event with representatives of the Swiss-Palestinian Joint Business Council and the innovation scene and will hold talks with President Mahmoud Abbas, at which Vice-Prime Minister Ziad Abu Amr and Foreign Minister Ryiad Al Malki will also be present.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Dubai Expo, originally scheduled for 2020, did not open until 1 October 2021 due to the coronavirus pandemic. This is the first world exhibition in the Middle East, Africa and South Asia (MEASA) region and also the first to be held by an Arab country. The motto is Connecting Minds, Creating the Future. Mr Parmelin will attend Switzerland's National Day and visit the country's pavilion, which presents Switzerland as a leading location for innovation and as a tourist destination. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Meetings with UAE government representatives are also planned. In addition to Switzerland's presence at Expo Dubai, talks will focus on economic and financial relations between Switzerland and the UAE, cooperation in the fields of education, science and innovation, and regional policy developments.&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>GS-EAER Communication Tel. +41 58 462 20 07 info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="222309">
        <title>Bilateral relations Switzerland–Israel</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/fdfa/representations-and-travel-advice/israel/switzerland-israel.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="222310">
        <title>Bilateral relations Switzerland–the occupied Palestinian territory</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/fdfa/representations-and-travel-advice/palestinian-authority/switzerland-palestinian-authority.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="222311">
        <title>Bilateral relations Switzerland–United Arab Emirates</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/fdfa/representations-and-travel-advice/united-arab-emirates/switzerland-united-arab-emirates.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="222312">
        <title>Swiss Pavilion at Expo Dubai</title>
        <uri>https://houseofswitzerland.org/events/swiss-pavilion-expo-dubai</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <keywords>
      <keyword id="0005" org-id="701">
        <name lang="de">Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Etranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Straniero</name>
        <name lang="en">Foreign</name>
      </keyword>
    </keywords>
    <topics>
      <topic id="10">
        <name lang="de">Bundesrat</name>
        <name lang="fr">Conseil fédéral</name>
        <name lang="it">Consiglio federale</name>
        <name lang="en">Federal Council</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="33">
        <name lang="de">Bundespräsident/-in</name>
        <name lang="fr">Président/e de la Confédération</name>
        <name lang="it">Presidente della Confederazione</name>
        <name lang="en">President of the Swiss Confederation</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="47">
        <name lang="de">Wirtschaft</name>
        <name lang="fr">Économie</name>
        <name lang="it">Economia</name>
        <name lang="en">Economic Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
    <catalogueElements>
      <catalogueElement id="94">
        <name lang="de">Naher Osten</name>
        <name lang="fr">Naher Osten</name>
        <name lang="it">Naher Osten</name>
        <name lang="en">Naher Osten</name>
      </catalogueElement>
      <catalogueElement id="104">
        <name lang="de">Parmelin Guy</name>
        <name lang="fr">Parmelin Guy</name>
        <name lang="it">Parmelin Guy</name>
        <name lang="en">Parmelin Guy</name>
      </catalogueElement>
    </catalogueElements>
  </message>
</messages>
