<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="85471" revoked="no">
    <version>2</version>
    <pubdate>2021-10-15</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="701" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>701</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Wirtschaft, Bildung und Forschung</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'économie, de la formation et de la recherche</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'economia, della formazione e della ricerca</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Economic Affairs, Education and Research</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="201" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>201</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="701">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Wirtschaft, Bildung und Forschung</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'économie, de la formation et de la recherche</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'economia, della formazione e della ricerca</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Economic Affairs, Education and Research</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <department id="201">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Georgien und die Schweiz besprechen Weiterentwicklung ihrer Beziehungen</title>
      <lead>Bundespräsident Guy Parmelin und Bundesrat Ignazio Cassis, Vorsteher des Eidgenössischen Departements für auswärtige Angelegenheiten (EDA), haben am 15. Oktober die georgische Präsidentin Salome Zourabichvili im Landgut Lohn empfangen. Es handelte sich um den ersten präsidialen Besuch aus Georgien in der Schweiz. Im Zentrum des Gesprächs stand die Weiterentwicklung der bilateralen Beziehungen; diese sind von einer engen Zusammenarbeit, einem wachsenden wirtschaftlichen Austausch, den Guten Diensten der Schweiz und dem langjährigen Engagement der Schweiz im Südkaukasus geprägt.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Beide Seiten betonten, dass die politischen, wirtschaftlichen und kulturellen Bande in den vergangenen Jahren gestärkt wurden. Trotz der Pandemie entwickelten sich die bilateralen Wirtschaftsbeziehungen positiv, wobei nach wie vor ein grosses Wachstumspotential besteht. Das Handelsvolumen betrug im vergangenen Jahr 131 Millionen Franken. Bei der Bekämpfung des Klimawandels sind die Schweiz und Georgien bereits enge Partner. Diese Zusammenarbeit wird durch ein bilaterales Abkommen unter dem Übereinkommen von Paris weiter gestärkt werden. Die Delegationen erörterten Themen, bei denen die Beziehungen weiter intensiviert werden können. Zur Sprache kamen ein geplanter Energiedialog sowie eine erweiterte Zusammenarbeit im Bereich der Migration durch den Abschluss einer umfassenden bilateralen Migrationspartnerschaft.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Besprochen wurden zudem die Ziele der Internationalen Zusammenarbeit der Schweiz im Südkaukasus in den kommenden Jahren. Die für 2022 bis 2025 geplante Kooperationsstrategie bestätigt die hohe politische und wirtschaftliche Relevanz der Region aus Schweizer Sicht. Für Georgien ist ein Beitrag in gleichbleibender Höhe von rund 34 Millionen Franken vorgesehen. Das Programm zielt darauf ab, nachhaltiges Wirtschaftswachstum zu fördern, und damit zur Linderung der sozialen und ökonomischen Folgen der Pandemie beizutragen.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Im Zentrum der Schweizer Tätigkeit in der Region steht weiter die Friedensförderung, insbesondere die Verbesserung der Lebensumstände der vom Konflikt betroffenen Bevölkerung. Seit 2009 vertritt die Schweiz im Rahmen des Schutzmachtmandats die diplomatischen Interessen Georgiens in Moskau und die Interessen Russlands in Tiflis. Die Schweizer Delegation bedankte sich für das georgische Vertrauen, welches der Schweiz in diesem Zusammenhang entgegengebracht wird. Die Lage im Südkaukasus und in Osteuropa, die Sicherheitsarchitektur mit der bedeutsamen Rolle der Organisation für Sicherheit und Zusammenarbeit in Europa (OSZE) sowie die Zusammenarbeit zwischen der Schweiz und Georgien auf internationaler Ebene standen ebenfalls auf der Traktandenliste.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Kommunikation GS-WBF Tel. +41 58 462 20 07 info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="222010">
        <title>Bilaterale Beziehungen Schweiz–Georgien</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home/vertretungen-und-reisehinweise/georgien/bilatereale-beziehungenschweizgeorgien.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>La Géorgie et la Suisse discutent du développement de leurs relations</title>
      <lead>Le président de la Confédération Guy Parmelin et le conseiller fédéral Ignazio Cassis, chef du Département fédéral des affaires étrangères (DFAE), ont reçu vendredi 15 octobre la présidente géorgienne Salomé Zourabichvili au manoir du Lohn. Il s’agissait de la première visite officielle d’un président géorgien en Suisse. Les discussions ont principalement porté sur le développement des relations bilatérales. Celles-ci se caractérisent par une étroite collaboration, des échanges économiques croissants, les bons offices de la Suisse et un engagement de longue date de notre pays dans le Caucase du Sud.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Les deux parties ont souligné que les liens politiques, économiques et culturels se sont renforcés ces dernières années. Les relations économiques se sont accrues malgré la pandémie et le potentiel de croissance continue d’être important. L’année passée, le volume des échanges commerciaux s’est élevé à 131 millions de francs. La Suisse et la Géorgie collaborent déjà étroitement dans la lutte contre le changement climatique. Cette collaboration sera encore renforcée par un accord bilatéral en la matière tel que prévu par l’Accord de Paris. Les délégations ont discuté des sujets où les relations pourraient encore être renforcées, notamment du dialogue énergétique qu’il est prévu de mettre en place et d’une collaboration approfondie en matière de migration grâce à la conclusion d’un partenariat migratoire bilatéral complet.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Les objectifs que poursuivra la coopération internationale de la Suisse dans le Caucase du Sud ces prochaines années ont également été abordés. La stratégie en matière de coopération pour les années 2022 à 2025 confirme la haute importance politique et économique que la Suisse accorde à la région. La contribution en faveur de la Géorgie prévue à ce titre est stable et s’élève à quelque 34 millions de francs. Le programme vise à soutenir une croissance durable et contribuer à atténuer les conséquences sociales et économiques de la pandémie.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;La promotion de la paix, notamment l’amélioration des conditions de vie de la population touchée par le conflit, est également au centre des activités de la Suisse dans la région. Depuis 2009, la Suisse y exerce un mandat de puissance protectrice et représente les intérêts diplomatiques de la Géorgie à Moscou et ceux de la Russie à Tbilissi. La délégation suisse a remercié la Géorgie pour la confiance dont elle témoigne à notre pays à cet égard. La situation dans le Caucase du Sud et en Europe de l’Est, l’architecture de sécurité et le rôle déterminant qu’y joue l’Organisation pour la sécurité et la coopération en Europe de même que la collaboration entre la Suisse et la Géorgie sur le plan international ont également fait l’objet de discussions.&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Service de communication du secrétariat général du DEFR tél. +41 58 462 20 07 info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="222011">
        <title>Relations bilatérales Suisse–Géorgie</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae/representations-et-conseils-aux-voyageurs/georgie/suisse-georgie.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions>
        <revision date="2021-10-15 13:42" type="R"/>
      </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>La Georgia e la Svizzera discutono sullo sviluppo delle loro relazioni</title>
      <lead>Il 15 ottobre il presidente della Confederazione Guy Parmelin e il consigliere federale Ignazio Cassis, capo del Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri (DFAE), hanno accolto la presidente georgiana Salome Zourabichvili nella residenza del Lohn. Si è trattato della prima visita ufficiale di un presidente della Georgia in Svizzera. Al centro dei colloqui vi è stato lo sviluppo delle relazioni bilaterali, caratterizzate da una stretta collaborazione, dalla crescita degli scambi economici, dai buoni uffici della Svizzera e dall’impegno pluriennale della Svizzera nel Caucaso meridionale.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Ambedue le parti hanno sottolineato che negli ultimi anni i loro legami politici, economici e culturali si sono rafforzati. Le relazioni economiche bilaterali hanno visto uno sviluppo positivo nonostante la pandemia e il potenziale di crescita permane elevato come in passato. L’anno scorso il volume degli scambi commerciali ammontava a 131 milioni di franchi. Già oggi la Svizzera e la Georgia collaborano strettamente nella lotta contro il cambiamento climatico. Tale collaborazione sarà ulteriormente rafforzata mediante un accordo bilaterale, come previsto dall’Accordo di Parigi. Le delegazioni hanno affrontato tematiche che presentano un potenziale rafforzamento delle relazioni, quali il previsto dialogo sull’energia e una collaborazione allargata nel settore delle migrazioni grazie alla conclusione di un partenariato bilaterale globale in materia di migrazione.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sono stati inoltre discussi gli obiettivi della cooperazione internazionale della Svizzera nel Caucaso meridionale per i prossimi anni. La strategia in materia di cooperazione prevista per gli anni dal 2022 al 2025 conferma l’elevata importanza politica ed economica attribuita dalla Svizzera alla regione. Il contributo previsto in favore della Georgia permane stabile a 34 milioni di franchi. Il programma mira a promuovere una crescita economica sostenibile, contribuendo in tal modo ad attenuare le conseguenze sociali ed economiche della pandemia.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;La promozione della pace, segnatamente il miglioramento delle condizioni di vita della popolazione colpita dal conflitto, figura parimenti al centro delle attività nella Svizzera nella regione. Nell’ambito del suo mandato in qualità di potenza protettrice, la Svizzera rappresenta dal 2009 gli interessi diplomatici della Georgia a Mosca e gli interessi della Russia a Tbilisi. La delegazione svizzera ha ringraziato la Georgia per la fiducia riposta nella Svizzera a tale riguardo. All’ordine del giorno figuravano inoltre la situazione nel Caucaso meridionale e nell’Europa orientale, l’architettura della sicurezza e il ruolo significativo esercitato dall’Organizzazione per la sicurezza e la cooperazione in Europa (OSCE) nonché la cooperazione tra la Svizzera e la Georgia sul piano internazionale. &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Comunicazione SG-DEFR tel. +41 58 462 20 07 info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="222012">
        <title>Relazioni bilaterali Svizzera–Georgia</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae/rappresentanze-e-consigli-di-viaggio/georgia/svizzera-georgia.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Georgia and Switzerland discuss further developing relations</title>
      <lead>On 15 October, President Guy Parmelin and Federal Councillor Ignazio Cassis, head of the Federal Department of Foreign Affairs (FDFA), welcomed Georgian President Salome Zourabichvili at the Lohn Manor. This was the first official visit by a Georgian president to Switzerland. The talks focused on further developing their bilateral relations, which are dominated by close cooperation and expanding economic ties as well as Switzerland's good offices and long-standing engagement in the South Caucasus.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Both sides noted the strengthening of political, economic and cultural ties in recent years. Bilateral economic relations have advanced, despite the pandemic, and there is still much potential for growth. The volume of trade last year was CHF 131 million. Switzerland and Georgia are already close partners in the fight against climate change, and this cooperation will be further consolidated through a bilateral agreement concluded under the Paris Climate Agreement. The delegations also explored areas in which relations could be expanded. They discussed a planned energy dialogue as well as increased cooperation in migration through the signing of a comprehensive bilateral migration partnership.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Switzerland's objectives for international cooperation in the South Caucasus in the coming years were also discussed. The cooperation strategy planned for 2022 to 2025 acknowledges the region's high political and economic relevance for Switzerland. The proposed contribution for Georgia remains unchanged at approximately CHF 34 million. This programme aims to promote sustainable economic growth and thereby help alleviate the social and economic impacts of the pandemic.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Switzerland's activities in the region continue to focus on peacebuilding, and particularly on improving the living conditions of the population affected by the conflict. Since 2009, Switzerland has represented Georgia's diplomatic interests in Moscow and Russia's interests in Tbilisi within the framework of its protecting power mandate. The Swiss delegation expressed their gratitude for the trust that Georgia has placed in Switzerland in this regard. Other topics on the agenda included the situation in the South Caucasus and Eastern Europe, the important role of the Organisation for Security and Cooperation in Europe (OSCE) in the security architecture, and cooperation between Switzerland and Georgia on the international scene.&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>GS-EAER Communication Tel. +41 58 462 20 07 info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="222013">
        <title>Bilateral relations Switzerland–Georgia</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/fdfa/representations-and-travel-advice/georgia/switzerland-georgia.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <keywords>
      <keyword id="0005" org-id="701">
        <name lang="de">Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Etranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Straniero</name>
        <name lang="en">Foreign</name>
      </keyword>
    </keywords>
    <topics>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
