<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="85638" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2021-10-28</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="701" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>701</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Wirtschaft, Bildung und Forschung</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'économie, de la formation et de la recherche</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'economia, della formazione e della ricerca</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Economic Affairs, Education and Research</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="701">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Wirtschaft, Bildung und Forschung</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'économie, de la formation et de la recherche</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'economia, della formazione e della ricerca</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Economic Affairs, Education and Research</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Bundespräsident Parmelin besucht Israel und das besetzte palästinensische Gebiet</title>
      <lead>Bundespräsident Guy Parmelin ist am Donnerstag, 28. Oktober 2021, in Israel und im besetzten palästinensischen Gebiet mit den jeweiligen Präsidenten sowie Regierungsvertretern zusammengekommen. Bei den Gesprächen standen insbesondere die bilaterale Zusammenarbeit in wirtschaftlicher und wissenschaftlicher Hinsicht und die Friedensförderung der Schweiz auf der Traktandenliste. In Israel kam zudem die Kooperation bei der Innovationsförderung zur Sprache, im besetzten palästinensischen Gebiet war die Schaffung von Arbeitsplätzen für Jugendliche ein wichtiges Thema. </lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Bei den Treffen des Bundespräsidenten mit Präsident Isaac Herzog und Ministerpräsident Naftali Bennett würdigten beide Seiten die bilateralen Beziehungen zwischen der Schweiz und Israel, die in jüngerer Vergangenheit insbesondere in den Gebieten Wirtschaft und Wissenschaft ausgeweitet und vertieft werden konnten. Die Strategie der Schweiz für den Mittleren Osten und Nordafrika (MENA) sieht für den Zeitraum 2021 bis 2024 unter anderem noch engere Wirtschaftsbeziehungen mit Israel als Ziel vor, einen Akzent auf Fragen der Innovation und die Unterstützung der Schweiz für Dialog und Frieden. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Bundespräsident Parmelin betonte, dass die im Herbst 2020 geschlossenen Normalisierungsabkommen zwischen Israel und mehreren Golf-Staaten für die ganze Region und für die Zusammenarbeit mit der Schweiz neue Möglichkeiten eröffnen. Mit Blick auf den Nahost-Konflikt bekräftigte der Bundespräsident das Engagement der Schweiz für Dialog und Frieden in der Region. Er begrüsste die Wiederaufnahme des Dialogs zwischen den israelischen und den palästinensischen Behörden im Sommer als einen wichtigen ersten Schritt. Er rief beide Seiten dazu auf, das humanitäre Völkerrecht und die Menschenrechte zu respektieren und die Ursachen des Konflikts zu behandeln. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Auch bei seinem Treffen mit Präsident Mahmud Abbas unterstrich der Bundespräsident die Schweizer Unterstützung für einen Dialog mit dem Ziel, die Zwei-Staaten-Lösung zu verwirklichen. Eine wichtige Grundlage hierfür sei es, die Spaltung zwischen den palästinensischen Gebieten im Gaza-Streifen und in der West Bank zu überwinden. Gemäss MENA-Strategie zählt es zu den Zielen der Schweiz, die Bevölkerung im besetzten palästinensischen Gebiet zu stärken, indem deren Abhängigkeit von humanitärer Hilfe verringert und neue Arbeitsplätze und Zukunftschancen geschaffen werden. Beide Seiten würdigten am Donnerstag die bereits unternommenen Schritte, um die bilateralen Wirtschaftsbeziehungen zu stärken. Erörtert wurde zudem, was die Schweiz beitragen kann, damit sich der Arbeitsmarkt für junge Palästinenserinnen und Palästinenser verbessert. Anschliessend traf der Bundespräsident Vertreter des 2020 gegründeten schweizerisch-palästinensischen Wirtschaftsrates und der Innovationsszene. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Nächste Station der Nahost-Reise des Bundespräsidenten ist die Weltausstellung in Dubai, wo er am Schweizer Nationentag vom Freitag teilnehmen und dabei den Schweizer Pavillon besuchen wird. Ausserdem sind Gespräche mit der Regierung der Emirate angesetzt. &lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Kommunikation GS-WBF Tel. +41 58 462 20 07 info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="222534">
        <title>Zusätzliche Informationen</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home/vertretungen-und-reisehinweise/israel/bilatereale-beziehungenschweizisrael.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="222535">
        <title>Zusätzliche Informationen</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home/vertretungen-und-reisehinweise/besetztes-palaestinensisches-gebiet/bilatereale-beziehungen-ch-besetztes-palaestinensisches-gebiet.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Le président de la Confédération en visite en Israël et dans le territoire palestinien occupé</title>
      <lead>Le président de la Confédération Guy Parmelin a rencontré le jeudi 28 octobre 2021 les présidents et responsables gouvernementaux respectifs d’Israël et du territoire palestinien occupé. Les entretiens ont notamment porté sur la coopération bilatérale en matière économique et scientifique et sur la promotion de la paix de la Suisse. En Israël a également été évoquée la coopération en matière de promotion de l’innovation, tandis que dans le territoire palestinien occupé a notamment été mise en avant la création d’emplois pour les jeunes.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Dans le cadre des entretiens que le président de la Confédération a eus avec le président Isaac Herzog et le premier ministre Naftali Bennett, les deux parties ont fait l’éloge des relations bilatérales entre la Suisse et Israël, qui ont récemment été élargies et approfondies, en particulier dans les domaines économique et scientifique. La stratégie de la Suisse pour le Moyen-Orient et l’Afrique du Nord (stratégie MENA) prévoit notamment pour la période 2021 à 2024 le renforcement accru des relations économiques avec Israël, un accent mis sur les questions touchant l’innovation et le soutien de la Suisse au dialogue et à la paix.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Le président Parmelin a souligné que les accords de normalisation conclus à l’automne 2020 entre Israël et plusieurs pays du Golfe ouvraient des perspectives nouvelles pour toute la région et en termes de coopération avec la Suisse. Évoquant le conflit du Moyen-Orient, le président Parmelin a réaffirmé la volonté de la Suisse de s’engager dans la région en faveur du dialogue et de la paix. Il a salué la reprise à l’été dernier du dialogue entre autorités israéliennes et autorités palestiniennes, y voyant une première étape importante. Il a appelé les deux parties à respecter le droit international humanitaire et les droits de l’homme et à s’attaquer aux causes du conflit.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Lors de sa rencontre avec le président Mahmoud Abbas, le président de la Confédération a à nouveau souligné que la Suisse apportait son soutien à un dialogue visant à mettre en place la solution à deux États. Il a ajouté que cela supposait toutefois que les territoires palestiniens de la bande de Gaza et de la Cisjordanie surmontent leurs divisions. Aux termes de la stratégie MENA, l’un des objectifs de la Suisse est d’accroître la résilience des populations du territoire palestinien occupé en réduisant leur dépendance à l’aide humanitaire et en créant de nouveaux emplois et des opportunités d’avenir. Les deux parties ont salué jeudi les mesures déjà prises pour renforcer les relations économiques bilatérales. Elles se sont également entretenues de ce que la Suisse pouvait faire pour améliorer le marché du travail des jeunes Palestiniens. Le président de la Confédération a ensuite rencontré des représentants du Conseil d’entreprises commun Suisse-Palestine, fondé en 2020, et du domaine de l’innovation.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;La prochaine étape du voyage du président au Moyen-Orient sera l’exposition universelle de Dubaï, où il participera vendredi à la Journée de la Suisse et visitera le pavillon suisse. Pour le reste, des entretiens sont prévus avec le gouvernement des Émirats arabes unis.&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Communication SG-DEFR tél. +41 58 462 20 07 info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="222536">
        <title>Informations supplémentaires</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/countries/israel/fr/home/relations-bilaterales/bilaterale.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="222537">
        <title>Informations supplémentaires</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae/representations-et-conseils-aux-voyageurs/territoire-palestinien-occupe/suisse-territoire-palestinien-occupe.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Il Presidente della Confederazione in visita in Israele e nel Territorio palestinese occupato</title>
      <lead>Il Presidente della Confederazione Guy Parmelin ha incontrato giovedì 28 ottobre 2021 i presidenti e i rappresentanti di Governo rispettivamente di Israele e del Territorio palestinese occupato. I colloqui si sono incentrati sulla cooperazione bilaterale nei settori economico e scientifico e sulla promozione della pace della Svizzera. In Israele si è parlato anche di cooperazione in materia di promozione dellʼinnovazione, mentre nel Territorio palestinese occupato si è posto lʼaccento sulla questione riguardante la creazione di posti di lavoro per i giovani. </lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;In occasione degli incontri che il Presidente della Confederazione ha avuto con il Presidente israeliano Isaac Herzog e il Primo ministro Naftali Bennett, le due parti hanno elogiato le relazioni bilaterali che intercorrono fra la Svizzera e Israele e che sono state recentemente estese e approfondite, in particolare nei settori dellʼeconomia e della scienza. La strategia della Svizzera per il Medio Oriente e il Nord Africa (MENA) per il periodo che va dal 2021 al 2024 prevede, fra lʼaltro, un ulteriore consolidamento delle relazioni economiche con Israele, una particolare considerazione delle questioni legate allʼinnovazione e il sostegno della Svizzera al dialogo e alla pace. Il Presidente della Confederazione Guy Parmelin ha sottolineato che gli accordi di normalizzazione conclusi nellʼautunno del 2020 fra Israele e vari Stati del Golfo hanno aperto nuove prospettive per lʼintera regione e per la cooperazione con la Svizzera. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Riguardo al conflitto in Medio Oriente, il Presidente della Confederazione ha riaffermato la volontà della Svizzera di impegnarsi nella regione in favore del dialogo e della pace. Parmelin ha salutato la ripresa, avvenuta la scorsa estate, del dialogo fra le autorità israeliane e le autorità palestinesi, considerandola un primo passo importante. Il Presidente della Confederazione ha esortato le due parti al rispetto del diritto internazionale umanitario e dei diritti umani e a intervenire su quelle che sono le cause del conflitto. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Anche in occasione dellʼincontro con il Presidente palestinese Mahmud Abbas, il Presidente della Confederazione ha sottolineato il sostegno apportato dalla Svizzera a un dialogo che ha per obiettivo lʼattuazione della soluzione a due Stati. È tuttavia essenziale, ha aggiunto Parmelin, che i territori palestinesi della Striscia di Gaza e della Cisgiordania superino le loro divisioni. In base alla strategia MENA, uno degli obiettivi della Svizzera è di accrescere la resilienza della popolazione del Territorio palestinese occupato al fine di ridurre la sua dipendenza dagli aiuti umanitari e di creare nuovi posti di lavoro e prospettive per il futuro. Giovedì entrambe le parti hanno riconosciuto i passi già intrapresi per rafforzare le relazioni economiche bilaterali. Si è anche discusso di ciò che la Svizzera può fare per migliorare il mercato del lavoro per i giovani palestinesi. Successivamente, il Presidente della Confederazione ha incontrato alcuni rappresentanti del Consiglio commerciale congiunto Svizzera-Palestina, fondato nel 2020, e del settore dellʼinnovazione. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;La prossima tappa del viaggio in Medio Oriente del Presidente della Confederazione è lʼEsposizione universale di Dubai, nellʼambito della quale Guy Parmelin parteciperà alla Giornata nazionale svizzera di venerdì, visitando il padiglione nazionale. Sono previsti colloqui con il Governo degli Emirati Arabi Uniti. &lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Comunicazione SG-DEFR tel. +41 58 462 20 07 info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="222538">
        <title>Ulteriori informazioni</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/countries/israel/it/home/la-svizzera-e/relazioni-bilaterali.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="222539">
        <title>Ulteriori informazioni</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae/rappresentanze-e-consigli-di-viaggio/territorio-palestinese-occupato/svizzera-territorio-palestinese-occupato.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>President Parmelin visits Israel and the occupied Palestinian territory</title>
      <lead>On Thursday, 28 October, President Guy Parmelin met with the respective presidents and government representatives of Israel and the occupied Palestinian territory. The talks focused in particular on bilateral cooperation in economic and science matters, and on Switzerland's peace promotion efforts. Cooperation in innovation promotion was also discussed in Israel, while in the occupied Palestinian territory the creation of jobs for young people was a central topic. </lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;At the meetings between Mr Parmelin and President Isaac Herzog and Prime Minister Naftali Bennett, both sides acknowledged the importance of Switzerland and Israel's bilateral relations, which have recently been expanded and deepened, particularly in the areas of business and science. Switzerland's strategy for the Middle East and North Africa region (MENA Strategy) envisages, among other things, a further strengthening of economic relations with Israel from now until 2024, and places an increased focus on innovation issues and on Switzerland's support for dialogue and peace. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;President Parmelin emphasised that the normalisation agreement concluded in autumn 2020 between Israel and several Gulf states opens up new opportunities for the entire region and for cooperation with Switzerland. With regard to the Middle East conflict, Mr Parmelin reaffirmed Switzerland's commitment to dialogue and peace in the region. He welcomed the resumption of talks between the Israeli and Palestinian authorities in the summer and considers this an important first step. He called on both sides to respect human rights and international humanitarian law, and to address the root causes of the conflict. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;In his meeting with President Mahmoud Abbas, President Parmelin again underlined Switzerland's support for a dialogue aimed at achieving a two-state solution. To make this possible, he said, the divisions between the Palestinian territories in the Gaza Strip and the West Bank will need to be overcome. In terms of the MENA strategy, one of Switzerland's objectives is to strengthen the resilience of the population in the occupied Palestinian territory by reducing their dependence on humanitarian aid and by creating new jobs and opportunities for the future. On Thursday, both sides acknowledged the steps already taken towards strengthening bilateral economic ties. Ways in which Switzerland could help improve the labour market for young Palestinians were also discussed. Mr Parmelin then met with representatives of the innovation scene and of the Swiss-Palestinian Joint Business Council, which was founded in 2020.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The next stop on the President's trip to the Middle East will be the World Expo in Dubai, where he will attend Switzerland's National Day on Friday and visit the Swiss Pavilion. Talks are also scheduled with the government of the United Arab Emirates. &lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>GS-EAER Communications Tel. +41 58 462 20 07 info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="222532">
        <title>Additional information</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/countries/israel/en/home/switzerland-and/bilateral-relations.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="222533">
        <title>Additional information</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/fdfa/representations-and-travel-advice/palestinian-authority/switzerland-palestinian-authority.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="10">
        <name lang="de">Bundesrat</name>
        <name lang="fr">Conseil fédéral</name>
        <name lang="it">Consiglio federale</name>
        <name lang="en">Federal Council</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="33">
        <name lang="de">Bundespräsident/-in</name>
        <name lang="fr">Président/e de la Confédération</name>
        <name lang="it">Presidente della Confederazione</name>
        <name lang="en">President of the Swiss Confederation</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="47">
        <name lang="de">Wirtschaft</name>
        <name lang="fr">Économie</name>
        <name lang="it">Economia</name>
        <name lang="en">Economic Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
