<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="10131" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2007-01-09</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="yes" id="603" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>601</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidg. Finanzverwaltung</name>
      <name lang="fr">Administration fédérale des finances</name>
      <name lang="it">Amministrazione federale delle finanze</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Finance Administration</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.efv.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.efv.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.efv.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.efv.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@efv.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@efv.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@efv.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@efv.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="601">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Finanzdepartement</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des finances</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale delle finanze</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Finance</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.efd.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.dff.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.efd.admin.ch/efd/it/home.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.efd.admin.ch/efd/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Schweiz tritt Financial Stability Forum bei</title>
      <lead>Die Schweiz wird Mitglied des Financial Stability Forum (FSF). Die Zuständigkeit für die Durchführung der Mitgliedschaft im FSF liegt beim Eidg. Finanzdepartement EFD. Als Vertreter der Schweiz wird Jean-Pierre Roth, Präsident des Direktoriums der Schweizerischen Nationalbank, bestimmt.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Das FSF vereinigt hochrangige Vertreter nationaler Behörden und internationaler Finanzinstitutionen. Die Mitgliedschaft im FSF eröffnet der Schweiz die Gelegenheit zur aktiven Teilnahme am internationalen Dialog über die Früherkennung stabilitätsrelevanter Fragen sowie zu Fragen der Finanzmarktregulierung und -aufsicht. Dabei ist insbesondere die Mitwirkung an der Diskussion der Behörden der wichtigsten Finanzplätze zu relevanten internationalen Finanzsystemfragen für die Schweiz von erheblichem Nutzen.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Als neues Mitglied des Financial Stability Forum wird die Schweiz erstmals an der Sitzung vom 29. März 2007 vertreten sein. Als Vertreter der Schweiz wird Jean-Pierre Roth, Präsident des Direktoriums der Schweizerischen Nationalbank, bestimmt.&lt;/p&gt; Das FSF wurde 1999 von den Finanzministern und Zentralbankgouverneuren der G7 im Nachgang zur Asienkrise geschaffen. Es verfolgt die Vertiefung der Zusammenarbeit und die Förderung der Koordination bei der Überwachung des internationalen Finanzsystems und dient der Reduktion des systemischen Risikos. Nebst Finanzministerien, Zentralbanken und Regulatoren der G7-Staaten nehmen die Notenbankgouverneure Australiens, Hong Kongs, der Niederlande, Singapurs und neu der Schweiz Einsitz. Internationale Finanzinstitutionen, internationale Aufsichts- und Regulierungsbehörden und die Europäische Zentralbank sind ebenfalls im FSF vertreten.</text>
      <contact>Alexander Karrer, Leiter der Abteilung internationale Finanzfragen und Währungspolitik, Eidgenössische Finanzverwaltung, Tel. 031 324 95 84. Werner Abegg, Leiter Kommunikation, Schweizerische Nationalbank, Tel. 044 631 32 67</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Adhésion de la Suisse au Forum sur la stabilité financière</title>
      <lead>La Suisse devient membre du Forum sur la stabilité financière (FSF). Le Département fédéral des finances (DFF) est responsable de l’application du statut de membre du FSF. Le président de la direction générale de la Banque nationale suisse, Jean-Pierre Roth, a été nommé représentant de la Suisse.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Le FSF rassemble des représentants haut placés d'autorités nationales et d'institutions financières internationales. En adhérant à cette institution, la Suisse pourra participer activement au dialogue international portant sur la détection précoce de problèmes liés à la stabilité et sur la réglementation et la surveillance des marchés financiers. Elle tirera en particulier un avantage notable de la possibilité de prendre part à la discussion entre les autorités des places financières les plus importantes sur des questions internationales relatives au système financier.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;La Suisse participera pour la première fois à la séance du 29 mars 2007 en tant que nouveau membre du Forum sur la stabilité financière. Le président de la direction générale de la Banque nationale suisse, Jean-Pierre Roth, représentera notre pays.&lt;/p&gt; Le FSF a été créé en 1999 par les ministres des finances et les gouverneurs des banques centrales du G7 à la suite de la crise asiatique. Il a pour but d'approfondir la collaboration et de promouvoir la coordination dans la surveillance du système financier international et de réduire les risques systémiques. En plus des ministères des finances, des banques centrales et des autorités de régulation des pays du G7, les banques nationales d'Australie, de Hong-Kong, des Pays-Bas, de Singapour et désormais de la Suisse sont représentés au sein du FSF. Des institutions financières et des autorités de surveillance et de réglementation internationales ainsi que la Banque centrale européenne y ont également un siège.</text>
      <contact>Alexander Karrer, chef de la division des questions financières internationales et de la politique monétaire, Administration fédérale des finances, tél. 031 324 95 84 Werner Abegg, responsable de la communication, Banque nationale suisse, tél. 044 631 32 67</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Switzerland joins Financial Stability Forum</title>
      <lead>Switzerland is to become a member of the Financial Stability Forum (FSF). The FDF will have responsibility for formal aspects of membership. Jean-Pierre Roth, Chairman of the Governing Board of the Swiss National Bank, will be the Swiss representative.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;The FSF brings together high-ranking representatives of national authorities and international financial institutions. Membership in the FSF affords Switzerland the opportunity to participate actively in the international dialogue on early identification of questions relevant to stability and financial market regulation and oversight. In particular, Switzerland will greatly benefit from taking part in the discussions held by the authorities of the major financial centres on relevant questions regarding international financial systems.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;As a new member of the Financial Stability Forum (FSF), Switzerland will be represented for the first time at the meeting of 29 March 2007. Jean-Pierre Roth, Chairman of the Governing Board of the Swiss National Bank, will be the Swiss representative.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The FSF was established by the Ministers of Finance and central bank governors of the G7 countries in 1999 in the aftermath of the Asian crisis. It seeks to enhance cooperation and to promote coordination in overseeing the international financial system. Moreover, it serves to reduce systemic risk. In addition to ministries of finance, central banks and regulatory bodies of the G7 countries, central bank governors of Australia, Hong Kong, the Netherlands, Singapore and now also Switzerland hold seats in the organisation. International financial institutions, international regulatory and supervisory authorities and the European Central Bank are also represented in the FSF.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Alexander Karrer, Head of "International financial questions and monetary policy" department, Federal Finance Administration, Tel. 031 342 95 84. Werner Abegg, Head of Communications, Swiss National Bank, Tel. 044 631 32 67</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <offers>
      <offer id="3" org-id="603">
        <name lang="de">Wirtschaft, Währung</name>
        <name lang="fr">Economie, monnaie</name>
        <name lang="it">Economia, Moneta</name>
        <name lang="en">Economic, Monetary affairs</name>
      </offer>
      <offer id="4" org-id="603">
        <name lang="de">Internationaler Währungsfonds IWF</name>
        <name lang="fr">Fond monétaire international (FMI)</name>
        <name lang="it">Fondo monetario internazionale</name>
        <name lang="en">International Monetary Fund</name>
      </offer>
    </offers>
    <keywords>
      <keyword id="118" org-id="603">
        <name lang="de">Finanzmarktregulierung und -aufsicht</name>
        <name lang="fr">Réglementation et surveillance des marchés financiers</name>
        <name lang="it">Regolamentazione e vigilanza dei mercati finanziari</name>
        <name lang="en">Financial market regulation and supervision</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="123" org-id="603">
        <name lang="de">IWF und Weltbank</name>
        <name lang="fr">FMI et Banque mondiale</name>
        <name lang="it">FMI e Banca mondiale</name>
        <name lang="en">IMF and World Bank</name>
      </keyword>
    </keywords>
    <topics>
      <topic id="35">
        <name lang="de">Finanzplatz</name>
        <name lang="fr">Place financière</name>
        <name lang="it">Piazza finanziaria</name>
        <name lang="en">Financial Centre</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="47">
        <name lang="de">Wirtschaft</name>
        <name lang="fr">Économie</name>
        <name lang="it">Economia</name>
        <name lang="en">Economic Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
