<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="10906" revoked="no">
    <version>3</version>
    <pubdate>2007-02-20</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="703" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>701</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Staatssekretariat für Wirtschaft</name>
      <name lang="fr">Secrétariat d'Etat à l'économie</name>
      <name lang="it">Segreteria di Stato dell'economia</name>
      <name lang="en">State Secretariat for Economic Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.seco.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.seco.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.seco.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.seco.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@seco.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@seco.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@seco.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@seco.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="701">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Wirtschaft, Bildung und Forschung</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'économie, de la formation et de la recherche</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'economia, della formazione e della ricerca</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Economic Affairs, Education and Research</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Richtig regulieren, damit alle profitieren</title>
      <lead>Nur mit den richtigen Regulierungen kann der wachsende Dienstleistungsbereich mit über 70 Prozent der Schweizer Beschäftigten sein Potential entfalten. Viele Elemente erfolgreicher Reformen im Ausland lassen sich auf die Schweiz übertragen – und am Ende profitieren alle: Unternehmen, Arbeitnehmende und Konsument/innen. Dies ist das Fazit der in Bern durchgeführten SECO-Reformtagung «Reform Works» vom 19. und 20. Februar 2007 mit nationalen und internationalen Experten aus Wissenschaft, Wirtschaft und Politik.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Das SECO hat Erfahrungen mit Reformen im Dienstleistungsbereich in ausgewählten europäischen Ländern auswerten lassen und an der SECO-Reformtagung vorgestellt. Der schwedische Postmarkt zum Beispiel ist seit 1993 vollständig liberalisiert und garantiert – ohne gesetzlichen Auftrag – weiterhin die flächendeckende Grundversorgung auf sehr hohem Niveau und zu Marktpreisen.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Bundesrätin Doris Leuthard betonte in ihrem Referat «Reformen für mehr Lebensqualität» die Bedeutung wettbewerbsfreundlicher Marktregeln. Durch sie kämen die Gewinne der Reformen auch den Konsument/innen zugute, so die EVD-Vorsteherin.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Staatssekretär Jean-Daniel Gerber, Gastgeber der SECO-Reformtagung, plädierte dafür, auch im Inland die Märkte zu öffnen und längerfristig das Wachstum zu sichern.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Er hob hervor, dass die Vorteile der Liberalisierung nicht einigen wenigen, sondern praktisch allen Bevölkerungsschichten zufallen: Die Konsument/innen haben eine grössere Auswahl an Gütern zu gleicher Qualität und günstigeren Preisen; den Unternehmen bieten sich mehr Marktchancen dank erweiterten und günstigeren Beschaffungsmöglichkeiten; die höhere Produktivität beschert den Arbeitnehmenden höhere Löhne und sichert Arbeitsplätze.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Gerber begrüsste die eingeleiteten Neuerungen wie die Personenfreizügigkeit und das Binnenmarktgesetz. Er warnte aber eindringlich davor, jetzt angesichts der guten Konjunkturlage die Hände in den Schoss zu legen, die weiteren notwendigen&amp;nbsp; Reformen zu verschleppen und damit eine schleichende Erosion der Wettbewerbsfähigkeit der Schweiz in Kauf zu nehmen.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Gerade aufgrund der guten Wirtschaftslage sei es ein Gebot der Stunde, die nötigen Anpassungen fortzusetzen. «Mit den richtigen Regulierungen in nur fünf Dienstleistungsbranchen könnte die Schweizer Volkswirtschaft um mindestens 10 Milliarden Franken wachsen. Verpassen wir die Chance nicht!», mahnte der Staatssekretär im Hinblick auf das schwache langfristige Wirtschaftswachstum der Schweiz und den sich abzeichnenden demographischen Wandel.&amp;nbsp;&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; In einer Podiumsdiskussion zur Postmarktöffnung kamen Vertreter aus der Praxis zu Wort. Reto Müllhaupt, Generalsekretär der Schweizerischen Post, sagte: «Die Post ist Willens und in der Lage, auch in Zukunft eine hochstehende Grundversorgung anzubieten.» Er anerkannte, dass im Bereich der Paketpost die sichtbare Konkurrenz die Leistungsfähigkeit der Schweizerischen Post gesteigert hat. Um frei von politischen Unwägbarkeiten die flächendeckende Grundversorgung sicherstellen zu können, sei allerdings der Weiterbestand eines Restmonopols notwendig. Jean Noël Rey, Vizepräsident des Verwaltungsrats von Direct Parcel Distribution (DPD) Schweiz, betonte: «Der Bundesrat muss klipp und klar entscheiden, welchen service public wir wollen und wie wir ihn finanzieren sollen.» In der weiteren Diskussion blieb offen, wie teuer der service public derzeit zu stehen kommt. Rey verwies aber auf Verteilnetze von Zeitungsverlegern, die auch in Randgebieten wie dem Wallis schon heute eine Frühzustellung sichern. Bei einer konsequenten Öffnung des Postmarktes erwartet Rey einen Markteintritt ausländischer Unternehmen wie DHL oder der holländischen TNT. Er stimmte bei, dass die Politik die Versorgung mit Infrastrukturdiensten im Interesse der Randregionen und der Beschäftigten mit Regeln gewährleisten muss.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; In der zweiten Podiumsdiskussion über die Auswirkungen der wirtschaftspolitischen Reformen auf den Detailhandel stand die Einführung des Cassis-de-Dijon-Prinzips im Zentrum. Hansueli Loosli, Vorsitzender der Geschäftleitung von Coop, illustrierte anhand mehrerer, schwer verständlichen Vorschriften in der Schweiz, dass Coop nicht den vollen Nutzen aus der eingegangenen europaweiten Einkaufskooperation ziehen kann. Er plädierte deshalb dafür, die Zahl der Ausnahmen zum Cassis-de-Dijon-Prinzip müsse auf einem A4-Blatt Platz finden. Herbert Bolliger, Präsident der Generaldirektion des Migros-Genossenschafts-Bundes, pflichtete Loosli bei, dass die Schweizer Lebensmittelindustrie sich auf einen europaweiten Markt einzurichten habe, wobei er seine Industriebetriebe, wie auch die Mitgliedfirmen des Markenartikelherstellerverbandes ProMarca, nicht als Zulieferer von Billiglinien sieht. Alexander Jost vom ProMarca verwies auf Erfolge von Schweizer Lebensmittelherstellern bis nach China, machte aber geltend, dass die Einführung des Cassis-de-Dijon-Prinzips mit anderen Reformschritten verbunden werden müsse. Schweizer Zulieferer hätten noch nicht alle Vorteile, die ausländische Konkurrenten aufgrund von Liberalisierungen, beispielsweise des Elektrizitätsmarktes, geniessen würden. Die Diskussionsteilnehmer stimmten denn auch überein, dass sich Reformen in verschiedenen Bereichen gegenseitig stützen und ergänzen müssten.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Reformen voranzutreiben macht indes nicht populär. Dies musste Anfang der neunziger Jahre der Gastredner, Prof. Leszek Balcerowicz, erfahren. Als Finanzminister der ersten nicht-kommunistischen Regierung in Polen nach dem Fall des eisernen Vorhangs sollte er marktwirtschaftliche Strukturen aufbauen. In seiner Präsentation stellte er die beharrenden Kräfte und ihre Argumentationslinien ins Zentrum. Als besonders erfolgversprechenden Weg zu mehr Reformbereitschaft nannte er den Vergleich mit Nachbarn, die mit ihren Reformen Erfolg erzielt hatten.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Peter Balastèr, Ressort Wachstum und Wettbewerbspolitik, SECO, Tel. +41 (31) 322 21 18 Sven Michal, Ressort Wachstum und Wettbewerbspolitik, SECO, Tel. +41 (31) 324 07 92</contact>
      <attachment id="22182">
        <title>Reformen für mehr Lebensqualität: Rede von Doris Leuthard</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>539</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/7039.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="22183">
        <title>ReformWorks: Rede von Jean-Daniel Gerber</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>54</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/7035.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="22184">
        <title>ReformWorks - Zusammenfassungen der am 19.02.2007 vorgestellten Studien</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>59</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/7036.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="22185">
        <title>Sonderdruck «Die Volkswirtschaft»: Erfolgreiche Reformen: Vom Ausland lernen</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>5696</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/7037.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <link id="22186">
        <title>Dokumentation ReformWorks</title>
        <uri>http://www.seco.admin.ch/themen/00374/00459/02061/index.html?lang=de</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Des règles qui profitent au plus grand nombre</title>
      <lead>Pour pouvoir déployer son potentiel, le secteur en croissance des services, qui emploie 70% des travailleurs suisses, a besoin de bonnes règles. Bien des éléments tirés de réformes menées avec succès à l’étranger sont transposables en Suisse, et au bénéfice de tous : entreprises, salariés et consommateurs. Tel est le bilan du séminaire sur les réformes (Reform Works) organisé par le SECO, les 19 et 20 février 2007, à Berne, qui a réuni des experts internationaux issus du monde scientifique, économique et politique.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Le SECO a fait analyser les expériences réalisées dans une série de pays européens en matière de réformes dans le secteur des services et les a présentées lors de son séminaire sur les réformes. A titre d’exemple, le marché postal en Suède, qui est complètement libéralisé depuis 1993, garantit, sans mandat légal, un service de base de qualité au prix du marché.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Dans son allocution intitulée « Des réformes pour améliorer la qualité de la vie », la conseillère fédérale Doris Leuthard a souligné l’importance de règles de marché favorables à la concurrence. La cheffe du Département fédéral de l’économie a relevé que ces règles profitaient également aux consommateurs.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Jean-Daniel Gerber, Secrétaire d’Etat à l’économie et hôte du séminaire du SECO sur les réformes, a plaidé en faveur d’une ouverture des marchés, également en Suisse, afin de garantir la croissance à long terme.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Il a relevé que les avantages de la libéralisation profitaient à presque toutes les couches de la population : les consommateurs disposent d’un choix plus vaste de marchandises de même qualité à des prix plus intéressants ; les entreprises se donnent plus de chances sur les marchés grâce aux possibilités d’achat élargies et plus avantageuses ; une meilleure productivité rejaillit positivement sur les travailleurs, dont les salaires seront plus élevés, et contribue au maintien des emplois.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Monsieur Gerber s’est félicité des nouveautés que sont la libre-circulation des personnes ou la loi sur le marché intérieur. Mais il a fortement mis en garde contre toute velléité, sous l’influence de l’embellie conjoncturelle, de rester les bras croisés et de tarder à engager les autres réformes nécessaires, attitude qui contribuerait à une érosion rampante de la compétitivité de la Suisse.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Son mot d’ordre du moment : poursuivre les adaptations nécessaires, précisément en raison de la bonne conjoncture économique. Opérer des réformes dans seulement cinq branches du secteur des services permettrait de générer une croissance d’au moins dix milliards de francs pour l’économie suisse. « Ne passons pas à côté des améliorations possibles !» a lancé le Secrétaire d’Etat, eu égard à la faiblesse de la croissance économique de la Suisse à long terme et aux mutations démographiques en perspective.&amp;nbsp;&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Dans une table ronde consacrée à l’ouverture du marché postal, des représentants de ce secteur ont pris la parole. Reto Müllhaupt, secrétaire général de La Poste Suisse s’est exprimé en ces termes :&amp;nbsp; « La Poste veut et peut offrir un service universel de qualité, également à l’avenir. » Il a reconnu que la concurrence visible a permis d’accroître la compétitivité de La Poste Suisse dans le secteur des colis. Il a toutefois précisé que pour assurer un service universel à l’abri des impondérables politiques, le maintien d’un monopole restant était nécessaire. Jean-Noël Rey, vice-président du conseil d’administration de Direct Parcel Distribution (DPD) Suisse a précisé :&amp;nbsp; « Le Conseil fédéral doit décider très clairement quel service public nous voulons et comment nous allons le financer ». Dans la suite de la discussion, la question du prix actuel du service public est restée ouverte. Mais Monsieur Rey a mentionné les réseaux de distribution des éditeurs de journaux, qui assurent aujourd’hui déjà une livraison matinale dans des régions périphériques comme le Valais. En cas d’ouverture généralisée du marché postal, il s’attend à ce que des entreprises étrangères comme DHL ou la société néerlandaise TNT entrent sur le marché. Il a reconnu que la politique doit instaurer des règles pour garantir le service universel avec une infrastructure au service des régions périphériques et des employés.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; L’introduction du principe « Cassis de Dijon » a été au cœur de la seconde table ronde dédiée aux effets des réformes économiques sur le commerce de détail. Hansueli Loosli, président de la direction générale de Coop, a relevé que le foisonnement de prescriptions guère compréhensibles en Suisse ne permettait pas à Coop de tirer pleinement profit de la coopération en matière d’achats qui s’est instaurée au niveau européen. Il a demandé que la liste des exceptions au principe « Cassis de Dijon » n’excède pas une page A4. Herbert Bolliger, président de la direction générale de la Fédération des coopératives Migros, partage l’avis de Monsieur Loosli : l’industrie alimentaire suisse doit s’organiser en fonction du marché européen ; il ne voit pas ses exploitations ni les entreprises affiliées de l’association des fabricants d’articles de marque ProMarca comme des fournisseurs de lignes bon marché. Alexander Jost de ProMarca a souligné les succès remportés par les fabricants suisses de denrées alimentaires jusqu’en Chine et fait valoir que l’introduction du principe « Cassis de Dijon » doit s’accompagner d’autres réformes. Les fournisseurs suisses n’auraient pas encore tous les avantages dont bénéficient des concurrents étrangers en raison de libéralisations telles que celle du marché de l’électricité. Les participants aux tables rondes se sont accordés à dire qu’il fallait que les réformes dans les différents domaines se complètent.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Mais introduire des réformes n’est pas gage de popularité. Le professeur Leszek Balcerowicz, l’un des orateurs du séminaire, en a fait l’expérience au début des années 90. Ministre des Finances au sein du premier gouvernement polonais non communiste qui a suivi la chute du Rideau de fer, il lui a fallu mettre en place de nouvelles structures relevant de l’économie de marché. Sa présentation s’est concentrée sur les forces réfractaires aux changements et sur leurs argumentaires. A son sens, la meilleure voie pour les convaincre est de citer en exemple les pays voisins dont les réformes ont été couronnées de succès.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Peter Balastèr, Secteur Croissance et politique de la concurrence, SECO, tél. +41 (31) 322 21 18 Sven Michal, Secteur Croissance et politique de la concurrence, SECO, tél. +41 (31) 324 07 92</contact>
      <attachment id="22187">
        <title>Des réformes pour améliorer la qualité de vie: Discours de Doris Leuthard</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>537</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/7038.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="22188">
        <title>ReformWorks: Discours de Jean-Daniel Gerber</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>49</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/7040.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="22189">
        <title>ReformWorks: Aperçus des études présentées le 19 février 2007</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>64</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/7041.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="22190">
        <title>La vie économique: Apprendre de l'extérieur pour réussir les réformes</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>5914</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/7048.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <link id="22191">
        <title>Documentation ReformWorks</title>
        <uri>http://www.seco.admin.ch/themen/00374/00459/02061/index.html?lang=fr</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Regolamentazioni giuste: vantaggi per tutti</title>
      <lead>Il settore dei servizi è in continua crescita, vi lavora più del 70 per cento delle persone attive in Svizzera e solo una giusta regolamentazione potrà permettere di dipanare il suo potenziale. Molti elementi che all’estero hanno dato vita a riforme di successo possono essere trasposti in Svizzera, con enorme vantaggio per tutti: imprese, lavoratori e consumatori. Questo è la conclusione a cui è giunto il «ReformWorks», il meeting della SECO sul tema delle riforme tenutosi a Berna il 19 e 20 febbraio 2007 alla presenza di esperti internazionali del mondo scientifico, economico e politico.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Durante il «ReformWorks» la SECO ha presentato le valutazioni effettuate su alcune esperienze di riforma nel settore dei servizi di determinati Paesi europei. Il mercato postale svedese, ad esempio, è totalmente liberalizzato dal 1993 e continua a garantire – senza mandato legale – una copertura totale del territorio di qualità e a prezzi di mercato.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Già nella sua relazione «Reformen für mehr Lebensqualität» (riforme per una migliore qualità della vita), la consigliera federale Doris Leuthard aveva evidenziato l’importanza di regole di mercato che lasciano spazio alla concorrenza e aggiunto: «grazie a essa, anche i consumatori possono godere dei successi delle riforme».&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Il Segretario di Stato Jean-Daniel Gerber, ospite al «ReformWorks», si è dichiarato favorevole all’apertura dei mercati anche all’interno e alla garanzia di una crescita più a lungo termine.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Ha ribadito che saranno tutte e non solo alcune categorie sociali a beneficiare dei vantaggi della liberalizzazione: i consumatori accedono a una più vasta gamma di prodotti di pari qualità e a prezzi inferiori; le imprese godono di maggiori opportunità grazie alla presenza di forme di approvvigionamento più economiche e numerose; l’alta produttività crea stipendi più elevati per i lavoratori e assicura i posti di lavoro.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Gerber ha altresì approvato le innovazioni introdotte, ovvero la libera circolazione delle persone e la legge sul mercato interno. Ha però poi messo in guardia dallo starsene con le mani in mano, ora che la situazione congiunturale è favorevole, e ha incitato a portare avanti le altre riforme necessarie, tenendo conto di una lenta erosione della competitività svizzera.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Proprio la situazione economica favorevole rende imperativo proseguire con gli adeguamenti necessari. «Introdurre le giuste regolamentazioni in soli cinque settori di servizi accrescerebbe l’economia svizzera di almeno 10 miliardi di franchi. Non perdiamo quest’occasione!» ha esortato il Segretario di Stato, guardando alla debole crescita economica a lungo termine della Svizzera e al cambiamento demografico che si profila.&amp;nbsp;&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Durante una tavola rotonda sull’apertura dei mercati, sono intervenuti i rappresentanti di alcune imprese. Reto Müllhaupt, Segretario generale della Posta svizzera, ha affermato:«La Posta vuole e può fornire il migliore approvvigionamento di base anche in futuro». Egli ha riconosciuto che nell’ambito della spedizione di pacchi la Posta ha aumentato la propria efficienza in seguito all’aumento della concorrenza ma che, per assicurare una copertura totale del territorio libera da imponderabilità politiche, è necessario mantenere un monopolio minimo. Jean Noël Rey, Vicepresidente del Consiglio di amministrazione di Direct Parcel Distribution (DPD) Schweiz, ha sottolineato: «Il Consiglio federale deve decidere chiaramente quali sono i servizi pubblici di cui vogliamo disporre e come si devono finanziare». Nelle successive discussioni la questione del prezzo del servizio pubblico è rimasta aperta. Rey ha però fatto riferimento alle reti di distribuzione degli editori giornalistici che assicurano un recapito di buon mattino anche in regioni periferiche, come il Vallese. Dall’apertura del mercato postale Rey si aspetta l’entrata sul mercato di imprese straniere, quali DHL o l’olandese TNT. Ha quindi riconosciuto che la politica deve provvedere a creare regole per l’approvvigionamento di servizi infrastrutturali, nell’interesse delle regioni periferiche e degli occupati.&lt;br /&gt; La seconda tavola rotonda, concernente le conseguenze delle riforme di politica economica per il commercio al dettaglio, si è incentrata sull’introduzione del principio Cassis-de-Dijon. Hansueli Loosli, presidente della Direzione generale Coop, ha illustrato, riportando diversi esempi di prescrizioni difficilmente comprensibili vigenti in Svizzera, che Coop non può beneficiare pienamente della cooperazione negli acquisti realizzata a livello europeo. Ha quindi sostenuto che il numero di eccezioni al principio Cassis-de-Dijon debba essere contenuto in un foglio formato A4. Herbert Bolliger, presidente della Direzione generale della Federazione Cooperative Migros, concorda con Loosli che l’industria alimentare svizzera debba orientarsi a un mercato europeo, senza tuttavia considerare né le sue aziende industriali né le aziende affiliate all’Associazione dei produttori di articoli di marca ProMarca, come fornitori di linee di prodotti a basso prezzo. Alexander Jost di ProMarca ha rammentato il successo dei produttori svizzeri di generi alimentari fino in Cina, sostenendo tuttavia l’importanza di introdurre il principio Cassis-de-Dijon in connessione con altre misure di riforma. I fornitori svizzeri non beneficerebbero ancora di tutti i vantaggi di cui i concorrenti stranieri godono grazie alle liberalizzazioni, ad esempio nel mercato dell’elettricità. I partecipanti al dibattito sono stati inoltre concordi nell’affermare che le riforme dovrebbero sostenersi e completarsi reciprocamente nei diversi settori.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; L’introduzione di riforme non apporta certo popolarità. È quanto ha dovuto constatare, all’inizio degli anni novanta, il prof. Leszek Balcerowicz, ministro delle finanze del primo governo polacco non comunista che, dopo la caduta della cortina di ferro, aveva dovuto creare strutture per l’economia di mercato. Fulcro del suo intervento sono state la forza costante e le linee argomentative e ha proclamato il confronto con i vicini, i quali avevano raggiunto risultati positivi grazie all’introduzione di riforme, quale percorso di particolare successo verso la disponibilità alle riforme.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Peter Balastèr, settore Sviluppo economico e politica della concorrenza, SECO, tel. +41 (31) 322 21 18 Sven Michal, settore Sviluppo economico e politica della concorrenza, SECO, tel. +41 (31) 324 07 92</contact>
      <attachment id="22187">
        <title>Des réformes pour améliorer la qualité de vie: Discours de Doris Leuthard</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>537</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/7038.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="22188">
        <title>ReformWorks: Discours de Jean-Daniel Gerber</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>49</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/7040.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="22189">
        <title>ReformWorks: Aperçus des études présentées le 19 février 2007</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>64</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/7041.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="22190">
        <title>La vie économique: Apprendre de l'extérieur pour réussir les réformes</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>5914</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/7048.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <link id="22191">
        <title>Documentation ReformWorks</title>
        <uri>http://www.seco.admin.ch/themen/00374/00459/02061/index.html?lang=fr</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Regulating well so that all can benefit</title>
      <lead>It is only with the right regulation that the growing service sector employing over 70 per cent of the Swiss workforce can attain its full potential. Many elements of successful reforms implemented abroad can be transferred to Switzerland – and ultimately benefit all: businesses, workers and consumers. That is the conclusion of the SECO «Reform Works» conference held in Bern on 19 and 20 February 2007 attended by national and international experts from the academic, business and political world.</lead>
      <text link="no">SECO commissioned a series of evaluations of experiences with reforms in the service sector in selected European countries and presented these findings at its reform conference. The Swedish postal market, for example, has been fully liberalised since 1993 and continues to guarantee high quality basic services throughout the country at market prices – without a legal mandate. &lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; In her speech entitled «Reform for a better quality of life», Federal Councillor Doris Leuthard stressed the importance of market rules conducive to competition. That way the benefits arising from reforms could also be felt by the consumer, said the head of the FDEA. &lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; State Secretary Jean-Daniel Gerber, the host of the SECO reform conference, also advocated the opening up of domestic markets and the safeguarding of long-term growth. &lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; He emphasised that the advantages of liberalisation are not felt by just a few, but by practically all sections of the population: consumers have a greater choice of goods of the same quality and at lower prices; firms have greater market opportunities thanks to an increased ability to source goods more cheaply; higher productivity brings workers higher wages and safeguards jobs. &lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Gerber welcomed the new measures that have already been initiated such as freedom of movement and the Internal Market Act. In view of the buoyant economic situation, however, he expressly warned against sitting back and delaying further necessary reforms, thereby running the risk of a creeping erosion of Switzerland’s competitiveness. &lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; The current good economic situation means that now is precisely the right time to continue making the necessary changes. «With the right kind of regulation in just five service sectors, the Swiss economy could grow by at least CHF 10 billion. Let us not miss that opportunity!», urged the State Secretary in view of Switzerland’s weak long term economic growth forecasts and emerging demographic changes.&amp;nbsp; &lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; In one podium discussion on the opening of the postal market, representatives from the sector voiced their opinions. Reto Müllhaupt, General Secretary of Swiss Post, said: «Swiss Post is willing and able to offer a high quality basic service in the future.» He recognised that in the area of parcel post visible competition had increased the performance capabilities of the Swiss postal service. The continued existence of a residual monopoly was certainly necessary in order to be able to ensure an across-the-board basic service free of political imponderables, he said. Jean Noël Rey, Vice President of the Board of Direct Parcel Distribution (DPD) Switzerland, stressed that «the Federal Council must make a clear decision as to which public service we want and how we are to finance it.» In further discussion it was not clear how expensive the public service currently is. Rey, however, referred to the distribution networks of newspaper publishers who were already ensuring an early delivery even in outlying areas such as the Valais. Given a consistent opening of the postal market, Rey expects the market entry of foreign companies such as DHL or the Netherlands company TNT. He recognised that the policy must ensure the provision of infrastructure services in the interests of outlying regions and employees by laying down rules. &lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; In the second podium discussion on the effects of economic reforms on the retail trade, the focus was on the introduction of the Cassis de Dijon principle. Hansueli Loosli, Chairman of the Executive Board of the Coop, demonstrated with the aid of several, barely comprehensible regulations that apply in Switzerland that the Coop may not be able to enjoy the full benefits of the Europe-wide retail cooperation which has been initiated. He therefore argued that a clear indication should be given of the number of exceptions to the Cassis de Dijon principle. Herbert Bolliger, CEO of the Federation of Migros Cooperatives, agreed with Loosli that the Swiss foodstuffs industry had to adapt itself to a pan-European market, but he did not envisage his manufacturing companies, nor indeed the member companies of the ProMarca association of manufacturers of branded articles, as the suppliers of cut-price product lines. Alexander Jost from ProMarca cited the achievements of Swiss foodstuffs producers that ranged as far afield as China, but argued that the introduction of the Cassis de Dijon principle had to be linked to other reform moves. Swiss suppliers would not have all the advantages that foreign competitors would enjoy due to liberalisation moves, for example in the electricity market. The participants in the debate were also agreed that reforms in various sectors would have to mutually support and complement each other. &lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Pushing through reforms is not especially popular, however, as one of the guest speakers, Prof. Leszek Balcerowicz, found out at the beginning of the 1990s. As finance minister of Poland’s first non-communist government after the fall of the Iron Curtain, it was his task to put in place the structures of a free market economy. In his presentation he focused on those sectors of society most resistant to change and their lines of argument. He cited the com-parison with neighbours who had achieved success with their reforms as a particularly good way of encouraging greater willingness to reform.</text>
      <contact>Peter Balastèr, Growth &amp;amp; Competition Policy, SECO, tel: +41 (31) 322 21 18 Sven Michal, Growth &amp;amp; Competition Policy, SECO, tel: +41 (31) 324 07 92</contact>
      <attachment id="22182">
        <title>Reformen für mehr Lebensqualität: Rede von Doris Leuthard</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>539</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/7039.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="22192">
        <title>ReformWorks: Presentation by Jean-Daniel Gerber</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>48</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/7043.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="22193">
        <title>ReformWorks: Executive summaries of the studies presented on 19 February 2007</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>59</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/7044.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="22185">
        <title>Sonderdruck «Die Volkswirtschaft»: Erfolgreiche Reformen: Vom Ausland lernen</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>5696</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/7037.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <link id="22186">
        <title>Dokumentation ReformWorks</title>
        <uri>http://www.seco.admin.ch/themen/00374/00459/02061/index.html?lang=de</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="47">
        <name lang="de">Wirtschaft</name>
        <name lang="fr">Économie</name>
        <name lang="it">Economia</name>
        <name lang="en">Economic Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
