<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="13811" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2007-07-25</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="201" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>201</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="201">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Ernennung eines Postenchefs in Chicago</title>
      <lead>Das Eidgenössische Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten gibt folgende Ernennung bekannt: Giambattista MONDADA, zum schweizerischen Generalkonsul in Chicago. Er übernimmt die Nachfolge von Generalkonsul Hermann Buff. Herr Mondada wird seine Arbeit in der ersten Hälfte August 2007 aufnehmen.</lead>
      <text link="no">Giambattista MONDADA, 1945 in Küssnacht am Rigi/SZ geboren, ist Bürger von Minusio/TI. Er trat 1969 in den Dienst des Eidgenössischen Departements für auswärtige Angelegenheiten und wurde sukzessive in München, Rotterdam, Buenos Aires, Kuwait, New Orleans, Mexico und New York (UNO) eingesetzt. Ab 1989 leitete er als Geschäftsträger ad interim unsere Vertretung in Luanda und anschliessend in der selben Funktion ab 1993 die Schweizerische Botschaft in Khartum und von 1996 bis 2002 die Schweizerische Botschaft in Dhaka. Seit März 2002 war Herr Mondada als Postenchef beim Schweizerischen Generalkonsulat in São Paulo tätig.</text>
      <contact>Presse- und Informationsdienst Bundeshaus West CH-3003 Bern Tel.: +41 (0)31 322 31 53 Fax: +41 (0)31 324 90 47 E-Mail: info@eda.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Nomination d'un chef de poste à Chicago</title>
      <lead>Le Département fédéral des affaires étrangères donne connaissance de la nomination suivante : M. Giambattista MONDADA, en qualité de Consul général de Suisse à Chicago. Il succède au Consul général Hermann Buff. M. Mondada prendra ses fonctions dans la première moitié d'août 2007.</lead>
      <text link="no">Giambattista MONDADA, né en 1945 à Küssnacht am Rigi/SZ, est originaire de Minusio/TI. Entré en 1969 au service du Département fédéral des affaires étrangères, il fut transféré successivement à Munich, Rotterdam, Buenos Aires, Koweït, New Orléans, Mexico et New York (ONU). Dès 1989, il dirigea en qualité de Chargé d'affaires intérimaire notre Représentation à Luanda et toujours avec cette même fonction, à partir de 1993 l'Ambassade de Suisse à Khartoum et, de 1996 à 2002, l'Ambassade de Suisse à Dhaka. Dès mars 2002, M. Mondada fut Consul général de Suisse à São Paulo.&amp;nbsp;</text>
      <contact>Service de presse et d'information Palais fédéral ouest CH-3003 Berne Tél.: (+41) 031 322 31 53 Fax: (+41) 031 324 90 47 E-Mail: info@eda.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Nomina di un capoposto a Chicago</title>
      <lead>Il Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri comunica la nomina seguente: Giambattista MONDADA è nominato console generale di Svizzera a Chicago. Succede al console generale Hermann Buff. Il signor Mondada assumerà le sue funzioni nella prima metà di agosto 2007.</lead>
      <text link="no">Giambattista MONDADA è nato a Küssnacht am Rigi/SZ nel 1945 ed è attinente di Minusio/TI. Entrato a far parte del Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri nel 1969, ha prestato servizio a Monaco di Baviera, Rotterdam, Buenos Aires, Kuwait, New Orleans, Messico e New York (ONU). A partire dal 1989 ha diretto in qualità di incaricato d'affari ad interim la rappresentanza svizzera a Luanda per poi ricoprire, dal 1993, la stessa carica presso l'Ambasciata svizzera di Khartum e, dal 1996 al 2002, presso l'Ambasciata svizzera a Dhaka. Dal marzo 2002, il signor Mondada ricopriva la carica di capoposto presso il Consolato generale di Svizzera a São Paulo.</text>
      <contact>Servizio stampa e informazione Palazzo federale ovest CH-3003 Berna Tel.: (+41) 031 322 31 53 Fax: (+41) 031 324 90 47 E-Mail: info@eda.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Appointment of head of post in Chicago</title>
      <lead>The Federal Department of Foreign Affairs (DFA) announces the following appointment: Giambattista MONDADA is to be Swiss Consul General in Chicago. He succeeds Consul General Hermann Buff. Mr Mondada will take up his post in the first half of August 2007.</lead>
      <text link="no">Giambattista MONDADA was born in 1945 in Küssnacht am Rigi/SZ and is a citizen of Minusio/TI. He joined the DFA in 1969 and subsequently held posts in Munich, Rotterdam, Buenos Aires, Kuwait, New Orleans, Mexico and New York (UN). In 1989 he headed our representation in Luanda ad interim. He held the same post at the Swiss embassy in Khartoum from 1993 and from 1996 to 2002 in the Swiss embassy in Dhaka. Since March 2000 Mr Mondada has been head of the Swiss Consulate General in São Paulo.</text>
      <contact>Press and Information Service Bundeshaus West CH-3003 Berne Tel.: (+41) 031 322 31 53 Fax: (+41) 031 324 90 47 E-Mail: info@eda.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
