<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="15719" revoked="no">
    <version>2</version>
    <pubdate>2007-11-16</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="yes" id="603" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>601</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidg. Finanzverwaltung</name>
      <name lang="fr">Administration fédérale des finances</name>
      <name lang="it">Amministrazione federale delle finanze</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Finance Administration</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.efv.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.efv.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.efv.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.efv.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@efv.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@efv.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@efv.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@efv.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="601">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Finanzdepartement</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des finances</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale delle finanze</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Finance</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.efd.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.dff.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.efd.admin.ch/efd/it/home.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.efd.admin.ch/efd/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Finanzplatz: Vertiefung des Dialogs zwischen dem EFD und dem Finanzsektor</title>
      <lead>Bundesrat Hans-Rudolf Merz hat heute die Spitzen der Verbände der schweize-rischen Finanzdienstleistungsbranche zu einer Aussprache eingeladen. Es handelte sich um das erste Gespräch zum „Masterplan Finanzplatz Schweiz“, mit dem sich die Verbände den zukünftigen Herausforderungen des Finanzsek-tors stellen wollen. Die private Initiative zugunsten einer branchenübergreifenden, integrierten Strategie zur Weiterentwicklung des schweizerischen Finanzsektors wird von Bundesrat Merz begrüsst. Der Dialog zwischen den Vertretern des Finanzplatzes und dem EFD soll institutionalisiert werden.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Es liegt im volkswirtschaftlichen Interesse der Schweiz, das Potenzial ihres Finanzsektors auszuschöpfen und zusätzliche Wertschöpfung, Steueraufkommen und hochwertige Arbeitsplätze zu generieren. Der Bundesrat und das EFD messen der Forderung nach attraktiven Rahmenbedingungen für den Finanzplatz Schweiz, welchem innerhalb der schweizerischen Volkswirtschaft eine wichtige Rolle zukommt, seit Jahren eine hohe Priorität zu. Zahlreiche Reformprojekte wurden in den letzten Jahren mit Blick auf den Erhalt und die Förderung der Wettbewerbsfähigkeit des schweizerischen Finanzsektors durchgeführt.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Im vergangenen September haben die Schweizerische Bankiervereinigung (SBGg), der Schweizer Versicherungsverband (SVV), der Schweizerische Anlagefondsverband (SFA) sowie die Infrastruktur-Anbieter SWX Group, SIS Group und Telekurs Group den in einem Gemeinschaftsprojekt erarbeiteten „Masterplan Finanzplatz Schweiz" der Öffentlichkeit vorgestellt. Dessen Ziel ist es, die internationale Wettbewerbsfähigkeit des schweizerischen Finanzsektors nachhaltig zu sichern und auszubauen. Bundesrat Hans-Rudolf Merz schlug die Institutionalisierung eines regelmässigen Dialogs auf zwei Ebenen vor. Ein Strategie-Organ unter seiner Leitung mit Spitzenvertretern aus Behörden und Finanzbranche soll sich künftig jährlich treffen. Ein neu eingesetztes Steuerungs- und Koordinationsorgan unter der Leitung von EFV-Direktor Peter Siegenthaler wird diesen Dialog vertiefen. Gestützt auf den Masterplan werden weitere Themen behandelt und Prioritäten festgelegt.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="nsbtextkasten"&gt;Das EFD hat sich auch bisher intensiv mit den strategischen Herausforderungen im Zusammenhang mit dem global ausgerichteten schweizerischen Finanzzentrum. In den „Leitlinien für die Finanzplatzpolitik" formulierte das EFD 2003 erstmals eine explizite Politik zum Finanzplatz Schweiz. Als Basis der Leitlinien dienten die Beratungen der im Jahr 2000 eingesetzten interdepartementalen Strategiegruppe „Groupe de réflexion", welche auch Hearings mit dem Privatsektor durchführte. Die Förderung der internationalen Wettbewerbsfähigkeit wurde als Zielsetzung auf die gleiche Ebene gehoben wie die Sicherstellung der Funktionsfähigkeit, Effizienz und Stabilität sowie die Wahrung der Integrität des Finanzplatzes.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Die Schweiz hatte in den letzten Jahren mit über 30 Reformvorhaben aus verschiedenen Bereichen des Finanzmarktes (Finanzmarktaufsicht, Unternehmensrecht, Kapitalanlagenmarkt, Steuerpolitik, Kriminalitätsbekämpfung etc.) eine intensive Reform- und Regulierungsphase. Zwei Drittel der Projekte davon konnten abgeschlossen werden, verschiedene laufende Gesetzesvorhaben befinden sich auf der Zielgeraden. Nachfolgend eine Auswahl wichtiger Reformvorhaben der letzten Jahre:&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; &lt;strong&gt;Ausgewählte Reformvorhaben mit Bezug zum Finanzplatz&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt; - Bundesgesetz über die Eidgenössische Finanzmarktaufsicht (Finanzmarktaufsichtsgesetz, FINMAG)&lt;br /&gt; - Umsetzung der Basler Eigenmittelvorschriften („Basel II")&lt;br /&gt; - Bundesgesetz über die kollektiven Kapitalanlagen (Kollektivanlagegesetz, KAG)&lt;br /&gt; - Totalrevision des Versicherungsaufsichtsgesetzes (VAG) und der so genannte „Swiss Solvency&amp;nbsp;Test"&lt;br /&gt; - Umsetzung der revidierten Empfehlungen der FATF&lt;br /&gt; - Bilaterale II - Dossier Zinsbesteuerung, Betrugsbekämpfung und Schengen/Dublin&lt;br /&gt; &amp;nbsp; Totalrevision Bundesgesetz über die Schweizerische Nationalbank (Nationalbankgesetz, NBG)&lt;br /&gt; - Revision des Bundesgesetzes über die Börsen und den Effektenhandel betreffend der Amtshilfe in Börsensachen&lt;br /&gt; - Insiderstrafnorm - Streichung von Art. 161 Ziff. 3 StGB&lt;br /&gt; - Haager Trust-Übereinkommen&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Alexander Karrer, Botschafter, Leiter Abteilung Internationale Finanzfragen und Währungspolitik, Tel 031 324 95 84</contact>
      <link id="32911">
        <title>Leitlinien für die Finanzplatzpolitik</title>
        <uri>http://www.efd.admin.ch/dokumentation/grundlagenpapiere/00817/index.html?lang=de</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Place financière: approfondissement du dialogue entre le DFF et le secteur financier</title>
      <lead>Le conseiller fédéral Hans-Rudolf Merz a invité aujourd'hui à un entretien les responsables des associations de la branche des services financiers suisses. Il s'agissait de la première discussion portant sur le «Masterplan pour la place financière suisse», avec lequel les associations entendent faire face aux futurs défis posés au secteur financier. Le conseiller fédéral Hans-Rudolf Merz salue l'initiative privée d'une stratégie intégrée de développement concernant l'ensemble du secteur financier suisse. Il est prévu d’institutionnaliser le dialogue entre les représentants de la place financière et le DFF.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Il est dans l'intérêt de l'économie de notre pays d'utiliser pleinement le potentiel du secteur financier et de générer de la valeur ajoutée, des revenus fiscaux et des emplois de haute qualité. Depuis des années, offrir des conditions attrayantes à la place financière à laquelle un rôle important est dévolu au sein de l'économie suisse, constitue une des priorités du Conseil fédéral et du DFF. De nombreux projets de réforme ont été réalisés au cours de ces dernières années dans le but de maintenir et de renforcer la compétitivité du secteur financier suisse.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;En septembre dernier, l'Association suisse des banquiers (ASB), l'Association Suisse d'Assurance (ASA), l'Association suisse des fonds de placement (SFA) ainsi que les groupes SWX, SIS et Telekurs en tant que fournisseurs d'infrastructures ont présenté au public le «Masterplan pour la place financière suisse» qu'ils ont élaboré ensemble. Le but de ce projet est de développer et d'assurer durablement la compétitivité internationale du secteur financier suisse. Le conseiller fédéral Hans-Rudolf Merz propose d'institutionnaliser un dialogue régulier à deux niveaux: un organe stratégique placé sous sa direction et réunissant des hauts responsables des autorités et du domaine financier se réunira dorénavant chaque année. Un organe de pilotage et de coordination nouvellement créé, dirigé par le directeur de l'AFF Peter Siegenthaler, sera chargé d'approfondir ce dialogue. D'autres thèmes seront abordés et des priorités fixées en se fondant sur le Masterplan.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="nsbtextkasten"&gt;Le DFF s'est déjà occupé par le passé de manière intensive des défis stratégiques qui se posent à la place financière suisse, axée sur le marché international. Il a formulé pour la première fois une politique explicite à l'égard de la place financière suisse en 2003, dans les «Lignes directrices régissant la politique à l'égard de la place financière». Ces dernières se basaient sur les délibérations d'un groupe stratégique interdépartemental institué en l'an 2000, appelé «Groupe de réflexion», qui a également consulté le secteur privé. Le renforcement de la compétitivité internationale a été placé au même niveau que les autres objectifs que sont la garantie du bon fonctionnement, de l'efficacité et de la stabilité ainsi que la sauvegarde de l'intégrité de la place financière.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Ces dernières années, la Suisse a traversé une phase intense de réformes et de réglementations puisqu'elle a lancé plus de 30 projets touchant différents domaines du marché financier (surveillance des marchés financiers, droit des entreprises, politique fiscale, lutte contre la criminalité, etc.). Deux tiers des projets sont arrivés à leur terme et divers projets de loi en cours sont sur le point d'aboutir. Voici quelques uns des projets de réforme importants de ces dernières années:&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; &lt;strong&gt;Quelques projets de réforme ayant trait à la place financière&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt; - Loi fédérale sur l'Autorité fédérale de surveillance des marchés financiers (LFINMA)&lt;br /&gt; - Mise en application des prescriptions relatives aux fonds propres du Comité de Bâle («Bâle II»)&lt;br /&gt; - Loi fédérale sur les placements collectifs de capitaux (loi sur les placements collectifs, LPCC)&lt;br /&gt; - Révision totale de la loi sur la surveillance des assurances (LSA) et du «Swiss Solvency Test»&lt;br /&gt; - Application des recommandations révisées du GAFI&lt;br /&gt; - Deuxième cycle de négociations bilatérales - Dossiers portant sur la fiscalité de l'épargne, la lutte contre la fraude et les accords de Schengen/Dublin&lt;br /&gt; - Révision totale de la loi fédérale sur la Banque nationale suisse (loi sur la Banque nationale, LBN)&lt;br /&gt; - Révision de la loi fédérale sur les bourses et le commerce des valeurs mobilières concernant l'assistance administrative dans le domaine boursier.&lt;br /&gt; - Norme pénale sur le délit d'initié - suppression de l'art. 161, ch. 3, CP&lt;br /&gt; - Convention de La Haye sur les trusts&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Alexander Karrer, ambassadeur, chef de la Division des questions financières internationales et de la politique monétaire, tél. 031 324 95 84</contact>
      <link id="32912">
        <title>Lignes directrices régissant la politique à l'égard de la place financière</title>
        <uri>http://www.efd.admin.ch/dokumentation/grundlagenpapiere/00817/index.html?lang=fr</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Piazza finanziaria: approfondimento del dialogo tra il DFF e il settore finanziario</title>
      <lead>In data odierna, il consigliere federale Hans-Rudolf Merz ha invitato i vertici delle associazioni di categoria del settore finanziario svizzero. È il primo colloquio sul «Masterplan per la piazza finanziaria svizzera», con cui le associazioni intendono affrontare le sfide future del settore finanziario. Il consigliere federale Hans-Rudolf Merz accoglie favorevolmente questa iniziativa privata a favore di una strategia intersettoriale integrata e finalizzata all’ulteriore sviluppo del settore finanziario svizzero. Il dialogo tra i rappresentanti della piazza finanziaria e il DFF dovrà essere istituzionalizzato.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;È nell'interesse dell'economia nazionale sfruttare il potenziale del settore finanziario e generare ulteriore valore aggiunto, gettito fiscale supplementare e creare posti di lavoro di elevato profilo. Il Consiglio federale e il DFF attribuiscono da anni la massima priorità all'esigenza di condizioni quadro attrattive per la piazza finanziaria svizzera, che riveste un ruolo importante all'interno dell'economia del nostro Paese. In vista del mantenimento e della promozione della competitività del settore finanziario svizzero, negli ultimi anni sono stati realizzati diversi progetti di riforma.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Lo scorso settembre, l'Associazione svizzera dei banchieri (ASB), l'Associazione Svizzera d'Assicurazioni (ASA), e la Swiss Fund Association (SFA) come pure i fornitori dell'infrastruttura finanziaria SWX Group, SIS Group e Telekurs Group hanno presentato al pubblico un progetto comune denominato «Masterplan per la piazza finanziaria svizzera». L'obiettivo è garantire in modo sostenibile e rafforzare la competitività del settore finanziario svizzero a livello internazionale. Il consigliere federale Hans-Rudolf Merz ha proposto di istituzionalizzare un dialogo continuo su due piani. Sotto la sua direzione, ogni anno si riunirà un organo strategico costituito dalle autorità e dai massimi esponenti del settore finanziario. Il dialogo sarà approfondito nel quadro di un costituendo organo di coordinamento e di gestione strategica, sotto la direzione di Peter Siegenthaler, direttore dell'Amministrazione federale delle finanze. Il Masterplan costituirà una base per trattare ulteriori temi e definire le priorità.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="nsbtextkasten"&gt;Già da tempo il DFF si confronta con le sfide strategiche legate al ruolo globale di centro finanziario del nostro Paese. Nel 2003, nel quadro delle «Linee direttive della politica della piazza finanziaria», il DFF ha formulato per la prima volta una politica chiara per la piazza finanziaria svizzera. Le linee direttive si sono fondate sulle deliberazioni del «Groupe de réflexion», il gruppo strategico interdipartimentale istituito nel 2000, che ha pure sentito il settore privato. Il promovimento della competitività internazionale ha beneficiato della stessa attenzione riservata alla garanzia della funzionalità, all'efficienza e alla stabilità nonché alla tutela dell'integrità della piazza finanziaria.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Negli ultimi anni la Svizzera ha attraversato un'intensa fase di riforme e regolamentazione, con oltre 30 proposte di modifiche concernenti diversi ambiti del mercato finanziario (vigilanza, diritto della società anonima, investimenti di capitale, politica fiscale, lotta alla criminalità ecc.). Due terzi dei progetti hanno potuto essere conclusi e diversi disegni di legge sono in fase di rifinitura. Di seguito, elenchiamo alcune delle principali riforme proposte negli ultimi anni.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; &lt;strong&gt;Progetti di riforma approvati in relazione con la piazza finanziaria&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt; - Legge federale concernente l'Autorità federale di vigilanza sui mercati finanziari (Legge sulla vigilanza dei mercati finanziari, LAUFIN)&lt;br /&gt; - Attuazione delle prescrizioni di Basilea sul capitale proprio («Basilea II»)&lt;br /&gt; - Legge federale sugli investimenti collettivi di capitale (Legge sugli investimenti collettivi, LICol)&lt;br /&gt; - Revisione totale della Legge federale sulla sorveglianza delle imprese di assicurazione (Legge sulla sorveglianza degli assicuratori, LSA) e del cosiddetto «Swiss Solvency Test»&lt;br /&gt; - Attuazione delle raccomandazioni rivedute del GAFI&lt;br /&gt; - Bilaterali II - Dossier fiscalità del risparmio, lotta alla frode e Schengen/Dublino&lt;br /&gt; - Revisione totale della Legge federale sulla Banca nazionale svizzera (Legge sulla Banca nazionale, LBN)&lt;br /&gt; - Revisione della legge federale sulle borse e il commercio di valori mobiliari concernente l'assistenza amministrativa in questioni di borsa&lt;br /&gt; - Norma sui reati insider - stralcio dell'art.&amp;nbsp;161 n.&amp;nbsp;3 CP&lt;br /&gt; - Convenzione dell'Aia sui trust&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Alexander Karrer, Ambasciatore, Divisione delle questioni finanziarie internazionali e della politica monetaria, tel. 031 324 95 84</contact>
      <link id="32913">
        <title>Linee direttive della politica della piazza finanziaria</title>
        <uri>http://www.efd.admin.ch/dokumentation/grundlagenpapiere/00817/index.html?lang=it</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Financial centre: dialogue between the FDF and the financial sector to be enhanced</title>
      <lead>Federal Councillor Hans-Rudolf Merz today invited the heads of the associations in the Swiss financial services sector for talks. This was the first discussion on the Swiss Financial Centre Master Plan, with which the associations wish to address future challenges facing the financial sector. The private initiative for an integrated, cross-sector strategy on the further development of Switzerland's financial centre has been welcomed by Federal Councillor Merz. The dialogue between representatives of the financial centre and the FDF is to be institutionalised.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;It is in Switzerland's economic interests to tap the full potential of its financial sector and generate additional added value, tax revenue and quality jobs. The Federal Council and the FDF have for years attached a high priority to calls for an attractive framework for the country's financial centre, which plays an important role in the Swiss economy. Numerous reform projects have been implemented in the last few years with a view to maintaining and promoting the competitiveness of the Swiss financial sector.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Last September the Swiss Bankers Association, the Swiss Insurance Association, the Swiss Funds Association and the companies responsible for Switzerland's financial infrastructure, namely the SWX Group, the SIS Group and the Telekurs Group published the Swiss Financial Centre Master Plan, drawn up as part of a joint project. The goal of the plan is to sustainably secure and develop the international competitiveness of the Swiss financial sector. Federal Councillor Hans-Rudolf Merz proposed the institutionalisation of a regular dialogue on two levels. A strategy body under his leadership and consisting of top representatives from the authorities and the financial sector will meet annually. And a newly established steering and coordination body under the leadership of Federal Finance Administration director Peter Siegenthaler will expand on this dialogue. Other topics will be discussed on the basis of the master plan and priorities set accordingly.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="nsbtextkasten"&gt;The FDF has long been dealing intensively with strategic challenges linked to the globally-geared Swiss financial centre. The FDF first formulated in-depth policies on the Swiss financial centre in 2003 in the form of the Swiss Guidelines for Financial Market Policy. The guidelines were drawn up based on the discussions of the interdepartmental strategy group, "Groupe de réflexion", set up in 2000, which also conducted hearings with the private sector. The promotion of international competitiveness was set as a goal on a par with those of assuring the effectiveness, efficiency and stability of the financial centre, and that of guaranteeing its integrity.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Over the last few years, Switzerland has undergone an intensive phase of reform and regulation with over 30 projects in different sectors of the financial market (financial market supervision, company law, investment market, tax policy, combating crime, etc.). Two thirds of these projects have been concluded, and a range of ongoing legislative projects are in their final stages. Below are a selection of important reform projects from the last few years:&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; &lt;strong&gt;Selected reform projects linked to the financial centre&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt; - Federal Act on the Federal Authority for Financial Market Supervision (Financial Market Supervision Act, FINMAG)&lt;br /&gt; - Implementation of the Basel Capital Adequacy Framework (Basel II)&lt;br /&gt; - Federal Act on Collective Investments (Collective Investment Act)&lt;br /&gt; - Complete revision of the Insurance Supervision Act and the Swiss Solvency Test&lt;br /&gt; - Implementation of the FATF Revised Recommendations&lt;br /&gt; - Second series of bilateral negotiations - taxation of savings income dossier, dossier on combating crime and Schengen/Dublin&lt;br /&gt; - Complete revision of the Federal Act on the National Bank (National Bank Act)&lt;br /&gt; - Revision of the Federal Act on Stock Exchanges and Securities Trading concerning administrative assistance in matters relating to the stock exchange&lt;br /&gt; - Insider criminal law provisions - deletion of Art. 161, section 3 of the Criminal Code&lt;br /&gt; - Hague Trust Convention&lt;br /&gt; &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Ambassador Alexander Karrer, Head, Monetary Affairs and International Finance Division, Federal Finance Administration, tel. 031 324 95 84</contact>
      <link id="32914">
        <title>Swiss Guidelines for Financial Market Policy</title>
        <uri>http://www.efd.admin.ch/dokumentation/grundlagenpapiere/00817/index.html?lang=en</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <offers>
      <offer id="3" org-id="603">
        <name lang="de">Wirtschaft, Währung</name>
        <name lang="fr">Economie, monnaie</name>
        <name lang="it">Economia, Moneta</name>
        <name lang="en">Economic, Monetary affairs</name>
      </offer>
    </offers>
    <keywords>
      <keyword id="118" org-id="603">
        <name lang="de">Finanzmarktregulierung und -aufsicht</name>
        <name lang="fr">Réglementation et surveillance des marchés financiers</name>
        <name lang="it">Regolamentazione e vigilanza dei mercati finanziari</name>
        <name lang="en">Financial market regulation and supervision</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="126" org-id="603">
        <name lang="de">Finanzplatz Schweiz</name>
        <name lang="fr">Place financière suisse</name>
        <name lang="it">Piazza finanziaria svizzera</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland as a financial centre</name>
      </keyword>
    </keywords>
    <topics>
      <topic id="10">
        <name lang="de">Bundesrat</name>
        <name lang="fr">Conseil fédéral</name>
        <name lang="it">Consiglio federale</name>
        <name lang="en">Federal Council</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="35">
        <name lang="de">Finanzplatz</name>
        <name lang="fr">Place financière</name>
        <name lang="it">Piazza finanziaria</name>
        <name lang="en">Financial Centre</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="47">
        <name lang="de">Wirtschaft</name>
        <name lang="fr">Économie</name>
        <name lang="it">Economia</name>
        <name lang="en">Economic Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
