<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="15857" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2007-11-23</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="408" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>408</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Bundesanwaltschaft</name>
      <name lang="fr">Ministère public de la Confédération</name>
      <name lang="it">Ministero pubblico della Confederazione</name>
      <name lang="en">Office of the Attorney General of Switzerland</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.ba.admin.ch/ba/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.ba.admin.ch/ba/fr/home.html</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.ba.admin.ch/ba/it/home.html</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.ba.admin.ch/</www>
      <email lang="de">info@ba.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@ba.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@ba.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@ba.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="408">
      <name lang="de">Bundesanwaltschaft</name>
      <name lang="fr">Ministère public de la Confédération</name>
      <name lang="it">Ministero pubblico della Confederazione</name>
      <name lang="en">Office of the Attorney General of Switzerland</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.ba.admin.ch/ba/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.ba.admin.ch/ba/fr/home.html</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.ba.admin.ch/ba/it/home.html</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.ba.admin.ch/</www>
      <email lang="de">info@ba.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@ba.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@ba.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@ba.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Oil-for-Food: Bilanz der Bundesanwaltschaft</title>
      <lead>Die Bundesanwaltschaft BA zieht zwei Jahre nach der Anzeige durch das Staatssekretariats für Wirtschaft, SECO, eine erste Bilanz zu den von ihr geführten Ermittlungen im Öl-für-Nahrung-Skandal der Vereinten Nationen.</lead>
      <text link="no">Ausgehend von einem Übernahmebegehren des für die Ahndung von Zuwiderhandlungen gegen das Embargogesetz primär zuständigen SECO (Art. 14 Abs. 2 Embargogesetz) im November 2005 hat die Bundesanwaltschaft den Volcker-Bericht und die darin enthaltenen Vorwürfe analysiert. Die BA hat in der Folge rund Zweidrittel der im Volcker-Bericht aufgeführten und zu jenem Zeitpunkt noch nicht verjährten Sachverhaltskomplexe – grösstenteils Fälle von erhöhter Komplexität – übernommen und innerhalb der BA verschiedenen Teams zur Bearbeitung zugeteilt. Mit den Fällen waren im Laufe der letzten zwei Jahren mehrere Teams beschäftigt und ein eigens hierfür geschaffenes Kompetenzzentrum hat den Verfahrenskomplex rund um das UNO-Hilfsprogramm Oil-for-Food koordiniert. &lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Insgesamt hat die Bundesanwaltschaft 36 Ermittlungs- und Vorabklärungsverfahren im Zusammenhang mit dem Öl-für-Nahrung-Skandal der Vereinten Nationen eröffnet. Diese Verfahren basieren massgeblich, aber nicht ausschliesslich auf den Erkenntnissen des Volcker-Berichtes vom 27. Oktober 2005 der Unabhängigen Untersuchungskommission der UNO (IIC). Andere schweizerische Ermittlungsverfahren sind originären Ursprungs, d.h. gehen auf MROS-Meldungen zurück oder wurden aufgrund von Informationen aus internationalen Rechtshilfeersuchen, für deren Vollzug die Bundesanwaltschaft zuständig ist, eröffnet. Kriterien für die Eröffnung der entsprechenden Strafuntersuchungen waren ein genügender Anknüpfungspunkt zur Schweiz, der begründete Tatverdacht, die Nachweisbarkeit von illegalen Handlungen und zu guter Letzt die Verjährungsfrage für allfällig begangene Verstösse gegen das Embargogesetz. &lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Im Laufe der letzten zwei Jahre wurden 15 Verfahren nach Delegation an kantonale Strafverfolgungsbehörden durch Strafbefehle oder durch Einstellungsverfügungen der Bundesanwaltschaft erledigt. 1 Verfahren ist im Moment beim Eidgenössischen Untersuchungsrichteramt hängig. &lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Heute sind bei der Bundesanwaltschaft noch 20 Strafuntersuchungen im Gang. Diese 20 Verfahren werden voraussichtlich ebenfalls durch Strafbefehle und Einstellungsverfügungen erledigt werden. In Einzelfällen kann es statt eines Strafbefehls zu einer Anklageerhebung kommen. Allerdings ist aufgrund der Verjährungsproblematik diese Variante eher auszuschliessen, d.h. es ist zurzeit keine Anklageerhebungen geplant. Ausserdem ist von Seiten der BA auch nicht mit weiteren Verfahrenseröffnungen in diesem Zusammenhang zu rechnen. &lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Die Ermittlungen betreffen einerseits Personen und Firmen, die im Zusammenhang mit Ölkäufen illegale Zahlungen geleistet haben sollen, und andererseits Firmen, welche humanitäre Güter an den Irak zu mutmasslich überhöhten Preisen geliefert haben sollen. Die Erkenntnisse aus den einzelnen Verfahren sind je nach Art der Geschäfte sehr unterschiedlich. &lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Die Hauptprobleme im Verfahrenskomplex Oil-for-Food liegen darin, dass die mutmasslich illegalen Zahlungen an den Irak zwischen Sommer 1999 bis kurz vor Ausbruch des Irak-Krieges Anfang 2003 erfolgten. Entsprechend eng wird es bezüglich der drohenden Verjährung bei allfälligen Verletzungen der schweizerischen Embargo-Bestimmungen. &lt;br /&gt; Erschwerend wirkt sich zudem der Umstand aus, dass Beweismittel zum Nachweis allfällig strafbaren Verhaltens auf dem Rechtshilfeweg beigebracht werden müssen. Die Beweismittelerhebung nimmt, sofern sie überhaupt möglich ist, viel Zeit in Anspruch. &lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Mit Rücksicht auf die laufenden Untersuchungen können im jetzigen Zeitpunkt keine weiter gehenden Angaben zu den noch pendenten Strafuntersuchungen gemacht werden. Die Verfahren richten sich gegen Firmen oder Personen, die der schweizerischen Strafverfolgung unterliegen. Die Namen der Firmen und Personen können aufgrund des Untersuchungsgeheimnisses nicht bekannt gegeben werden.</text>
      <contact>Jeannette Balmer, Schweizerische Bundesanwaltschaft, T +41 (0)31 324 32 40</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Pétrole contre nourriture: Bilan du Ministère public de la Confédération</title>
      <lead>Deux ans après la dénonciation déposée par le Secrétariat d’Etat à l’économie SECO, le Ministère public de la Confédération MPC fait un premier bilan des investigations qu’il a menées dans le scandale du Pétrole contre nourriture des Nations Unies.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Le Ministère public de la Confédération a analysé le rapport Volcker et les charges qu’il contient, suite à une demande de délégation présentée, en novembre 2005, par le SECO, organe compétent, en premier lieu, pour la répression des infractions à la loi sur les embargos (art. 14, al. 2 de la loi sur les embargos). Le MPC a repris environ deux tiers des états de fait que cite le rapport Volcker, pour l’essentiel des cas complexes, dans la mesure où ils n’étaient pas prescrits ; il les a répartis entre plusieurs équipes du MPC. Elles se sont penchées sur ces affaires au cours des deux dernières années ; un centre de compétence ad hoc a coordonné les procédures.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Au total, le Ministère public de la Confédération a ouvert 36 enquêtes et recherches préliminaires en relation avec le scandale du Pétrole contre nourriture des Nations Unies. Ces procédures se fondent largement, mais non exclusivement, sur les constatations du rapport Volcker du 27 octobre 2005 de la Commission d’enquête indépendante (CEI) de l’ONU. D’autres enquêtes menées en Suisse ont une origine immédiate ; elles découlent d’annonces du Bureau de communication en matière de blanchiment d’argent MROS ou elles ont été ouvertes sur la base d’informations obtenues dans le cadre de demandes d’entraide judiciaire internationale pour l’exécution desquelles le Ministère public de la Confédération est compétent. Les critères suivants ont présidé à l’ouverture des enquêtes : un lien suffisant avec la Suisse, des soupçons fondés, la possibilité d'apporter la preuve des actes illégaux et, enfin, la prescription d’éventuelles contraventions à la loi sur les embargos.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Au cours des deux dernières années, 15 procédures ont été closes, après délégation aux autorités cantonales de poursuite pénale, par ordonnance pénale ou par ordonnance de suspension du Ministère public de la Confédération. Une procédure est actuellement pendante auprès de l’Office des juges d’instruction fédéraux.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; A l’heure actuelle, 20 procédures pénales sont encore pendantes auprès du Ministère public de la Confédération. Elles seront probablement closes, elles aussi, par ordonnance pénale ou par ordonnance de suspension. Il se peut que certaines aboutissent à une mise en accusation au lieu d’une ordonnance pénale. Toutefois, ceci est peu probable en raison de la prescription ; en d’autres termes, il n’y pas de mise en accusation de prévue pour l’heure. Il ne faut pas s’attendre non plus à ce que le MPC ouvre d’autres procédures dans ce contexte.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Les investigations portent sur des personnes et des sociétés qui auraient effectué des paiements illégaux dans le cadre de ventes de pétrole et sur des sociétés qui auraient livré des biens humanitaires à l’Irak à des prix présumés excessifs. Les constatations faites dans les diverses procédures divergent fortement selon le type des affaires.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Les principales difficultés rencontrées dans les procédures concernant le programme Pétrole contre nourriture sont dues au fait que les payements présumés illégaux à l’Irak sont apparus, en été 1999, pour prendre fin peu avant le commencement de la guerre d’Irak, début 2003. En conséquence, d’éventuelles violations des dispositions suisses en matière d’embargos risquent d’être prescrites.&lt;br /&gt; Les moyens nécessaires pour prouver un comportement punissable doivent être obtenus par la voie de l’entraide judiciaire internationale, ce qui complique les choses. L’administration des preuves exige beaucoup de temps, si tant est qu’elle soit possible.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Les investigations n’étant pas closes, il est impossible de fournir plus de détails sur les procédures en cours. Les procédures sont dirigées contre des sociétés ou des personnes soumises à la législation suisse. Leurs noms ne peuvent être rendus publics en raison du secret de l’instruction.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Jeannette Balmer, Ministère public de la Confédération, T +41 (0)31 324 32 40</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Petrolio contro cibo: bilancio del Ministero pubblico della Confederazione</title>
      <lead>Due anni dopo la denuncia da parte del Segretariato di Stato dell’economia (SECO), il Ministero pubblico della Confederazione (MPC) stila un primo bilancio delle indagini condotte nell’ambito dello scandalo «Petrolio contro cibo» che ha coinvolto le Nazioni Unite.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Partendo da una richiesta di assunzione del procedimento emanante dal SECO, primariamente competente in materia di perseguimento di infrazioni contro la legge sugli embarghi (art. 14 capoverso 2 della legge sugli embarghi), nel novembre 2005 il Ministero pubblico della Confederazione (MPC) ha analizzato il rapporto Volcker e le accuse ivi contenute. Il MPC ha conseguentemente ripreso circa due terzi delle fattispecie – nella maggior parte dei casi assai complesse – riportate dal rapporto Volcker e a quell’epoca non ancora prescritte, assegnandone la trattazione a diversi team all’interno del MPC. Nel corso degli ultimi due anni numerosi team si sono occupati di tali casi e un centro di competenza appositamente creato ha coordinato il complesso delle procedure riguardanti il programma di aiuti dell’ONU «Petrolio contro cibo».&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Il MPC ha avviato complessivamente 36 procedure d’indagine e di accertamento preliminare in relazione allo scandalo «Petrolio contro cibo» delle Nazioni Unite. Tali procedure si fondano sostanzialmente, anche se non esclusivamente, sugli elementi acquisiti grazie al rapporto Volcker del 27 ottobre 2005 della Commissione d’inchiesta indipendente dell’ONU. Le altre indagini elvetiche sono state avviate in seguito a segnalazioni dell’MROS o in base a informazioni provenienti da domande di assistenza giudiziaria internazionale, per la cui esecuzione è competente il MPC. Le inchieste penali sono state avviate sulla base di criteri quali un sufficiente legame con la Svizzera, fondati sospetti di reato, la comprovabilità di atti illeciti e la questione legata alla prescrizione di eventuali infrazioni alla legge sugli embarghi.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Nel corso degli ultimi due anni sono stati liquidati 15 procedimenti, previa delega ad autorità cantonali di perseguimento penale mediante decreto d’accusa o mediante decreto d’abbandono emanato dal MPC. Un procedimento è attualmente pendente presso l’Ufficio dei giudici istruttori federali.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Oggi presso il MPC sono in corso ancora 20 inchieste penali, che presumibilmente termineranno pure con un decreto d’accusa o d’abbandono. In singoli casi, sarà invece possibile procedere alla promozione dell’accusa. Al momento simili ipotesi non sono tuttavia previste: si tende infatti a escludere questa variante a causa del problema legato alla prescrizione. Non si prevede inoltre l’avvio di ulteriori indagini da parte del MPC.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Le indagini riguardano, da un lato, persone e società che avrebbero versato tangenti in relazione all’acquisto di petrolio e, dall’altro, società che avrebbero consegnato beni umanitari all’Iraq a prezzi che si presume eccessivi. Le conclusioni risultanti dai singoli procedimenti divergono considerevolmente a seconda del tipo di affare.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; I principali problemi nei procedimenti riguardanti il programma «Petrolio contro cibo» risiedono nel fatto che le presunte tangenti sarebbero state versate all’Iraq tra l’estate del 1999 fino a poco prima dello scopo della guerra nel 2003. Eventuali infrazioni alle disposizioni svizzere in materia di embargo rischiano dunque di cadere in prescrizione.&lt;br /&gt; Il fatto che i mezzi per comprovare un eventuale comportamento punibile debbano essere acquisiti mediante assistenza giudiziaria rappresenta inoltre un ulteriore ostacolo. La raccolta delle prove, quando è possibile, può esigere molto tempo.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Dato che le indagini sono tuttora in corso, al momento non è possibile fornire ulteriori informazioni in merito alle inchieste penali pendenti. Tali procedimenti riguardano società o persone che sono soggette al perseguimento penale svizzero. Il segreto istruttorio non consente di rivelare i nomi delle società e delle persone coinvolte.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Jeannette Balmer, Ministero pubblico della Confederazione, T +41 (0)31 324 32 40</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Oil-for-Food: Interim Report from the Office of the Attorney General of Switzerland</title>
      <lead>Two years after being handed the task by the State Secretariat for Economic Affairs (SECO), the Office of the Attorney General of Switzerland (OAG) has issued a first interim report on its investigations into the United Nations Oil-for-Food scandal.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Following a request to take over proceedings made in November 2005 by SECO, which is primarily responsible for dealing with infringements of the Embargo Act (Art. 14 para. 2 Embargo Act), the Office of the Attorney General of Switzerland analysed the Volcker Report and the allegations that it contains. The OAG then took responsibility for around two thirds of the cases detailed in the Volcker Report that were not yet time-barred, and allocated those cases, most of them highly complex, to various teams within the OAG for processing. Several teams have been working on the cases over the past two years and a specially set up competence centre has coordinated the procedures relating to the UN Oil-for-Food Aid Programme.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;In total, the Office of the Attorney General of Switzerland has opened 36 investigations and preliminary examination procedures in connection with the United Nations Oil-for-Food scandal. These procedures are based primarily but not exclusively on the findings contained in the Volcker Report issued by the UN Independent Inquiry Committee (IIC) on 27 October 2005. Other Swiss investigation proceedings are of independent origin, i.e. they are based on reports to MROS or have been opened as a result of information obtained from international requests for mutual assistance, for which the Office of the Attorney General of Switzerland is responsible. The criteria for opening related criminal investigations were a sufficient link to Switzerland, the justified suspicion that an offence had been committed, sufficient evidence of illegal acts and the issue of whether any violations of the Embargo Act were time-barred from prosecution.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Over the past two years, 15 cases have been concluded by means of summary penalty orders following delegation to the cantonal prosecution authorities or by “no proceedings” decisions made by the Office of the Attorney General of Switzerland. One case is currently pending at the Office of the Federal Examining Magistrates.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Today there are still 20 criminal investigations underway at the Office of the Attorney General of Switzerland. These 20 cases will probably also result in summary penalty orders being imposed or “no proceedings” decisions being made. Certain cases may result in prosecution rather than a summary penalty order. However, as a result of the time-bar problem, it is unlikely that this option will be taken, i.e. no prosecutions are planned at present. In addition, the OAG does not expect to open further proceedings in this connection.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The investigations relate on the one hand to persons and businesses that are alleged to have made illegal payments in connection with the purchase of oil, and on the other to businesses that are alleged to have supplied humanitarian goods to Iraq at excessive prices. The information obtained in individual cases varies enormously depending on the nature of the transactions.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The main problem in the various Oil-for-Food proceedings is that the suspected illegal payments to Iraq were allegedly made between the summer of 1999 and shortly before the outbreak of the Iraq War in early 2003. This means that prosecution is already time barred or close to being time-barred under the provisions on infringements of the Swiss Embargo Act.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;A further difficulty is that the evidence to prove any criminal conduct must be obtained through international mutual assistance. As a result, gathering evidence, if it is possible at all, is a very time consuming process.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;No additional information can be given at present on the pending criminal investigations. The proceedings are directed against businesses or persons that are liable to prosecution in Switzerland. The names of the businesses or persons are subject to the rules on secrecy in criminal investigations and may not be disclosed.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Jeannette Balmer, OAG Media Spokeswoman, Tel. +41 (0)31 324 32 40</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="26">
        <name lang="de">Recht</name>
        <name lang="fr">Droit</name>
        <name lang="it">Diritto</name>
        <name lang="en">Legal Affairs</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
