<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="63883" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2016-09-23</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="1070" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>1070</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Der Bundesrat</name>
      <name lang="fr">Conseil fédéral</name>
      <name lang="it">Il Consiglio federale</name>
      <name lang="en">The Federal Council</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.admin.ch/gov/de/start.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.admin.ch/gov/fr/accueil.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.admin.ch/gov/it/pagina-iniziale.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.admin.ch/gov/en/start.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="yes" id="605" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>601</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössische Steuerverwaltung</name>
      <name lang="fr">Administration fédérale des contributions</name>
      <name lang="it">Amministrazione federale delle contribuzioni</name>
      <name lang="en">The Federal Tax Administration</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.estv.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.estv.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.estv.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.estv.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de"/>
      <email lang="fr"/>
      <email lang="it"/>
      <email lang="en"/>
    </originator>
    <department id="1070">
      <name lang="de">Der Bundesrat</name>
      <name lang="fr">Conseil fédéral</name>
      <name lang="it">Il Consiglio federale</name>
      <name lang="en">The Federal Council</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.admin.ch/gov/de/start.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.admin.ch/gov/fr/accueil.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.admin.ch/gov/it/pagina-iniziale.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.admin.ch/gov/en/start.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <department id="601">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Finanzdepartement</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des finances</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale delle finanze</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Finance</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.efd.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.dff.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.efd.admin.ch/efd/it/home.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.efd.admin.ch/efd/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Bundesrat will Konzernfinanzierung in der Schweiz erleichtern</title>
      <lead>Der Bundesrat hat heute die Vernehmlassung zu einer Änderung der Verordnung über die Verrechnungssteuer eröffnet. Mit der Vorlage sollen Finanzierungstätigkeiten von Konzernen in der Schweiz gestärkt werden. </lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;In der Schweiz ansässige Konzerne nehmen heute Finanzierungsaktivitäten häufig gezielt im Ausland vor. Sie weichen damit der Verrechnungssteuer aus, die in bestimmten Situationen anfiele, würden sie die Finanzierung über in der Schweiz ansässige Konzerngesellschaften abwickeln. Damit entgeht der Schweizer Volkswirtschaft ein Teil der Wertschöpfung in diesem Bereich.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Um diese Wertschöpfung zurück in die Schweiz zu holen, schlägt der Bundesrat eine Änderung der Verordnung über die Verrechnungssteuer vor. Diese Änderung betrifft diejenigen Konzerne, bei welchen eine inländische Konzerngesellschaft (Garantin) eine Obligation einer zum gleichen Konzern gehörenden ausländischen Konzerngesellschaft (Emittentin) garantiert. Mit den vorgeschlagenen Anpassungen sollen konzerninterne Zinszahlungen der inländischen Garantin nicht mehr in jedem Fall der Verrechnungssteuer unterliegen. Eine Weiterleitung von Mitteln der ausländischen Emittentin an eine in der Schweiz ansässige Konzerngesellschaft soll noch maximal im Umfang des Eigenkapitals der Emittentin möglich sein. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Die vom Bundesrat vorgeschlagene Reform des Verrechnungssteuergesetzes (Wechsel zum Zahlstellenprinzip), wie sie am 18. Dezember 2014 in die Vernehmlassung gegeben wurde, würde die heutigen Probleme grundsätzlich und nachhaltig lösen. Die Reform ist allerdings derzeit sistiert (Abwarten Ausgang der Abstimmung zur Volksinitiatve «Ja zum Schutz der Privatsphäre»), und der weitere Zeitplan ist ungewiss. Vor diesem Hintergrund schlägt der Bundesrat die vorliegende Änderung der Verordnung über die Verrechnungssteuer vor, um die Attraktivität des Standortes Schweiz zu stärken.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Patrick Teuscher, Leiter Kommunikation, Eidgenössische Steuerverwaltung ESTV Tel. 058 464 90 00, media@estv.admin.ch</contact>
      <attachment id="159051">
        <title>Entwurf Verordnung über die Verrechnungssteuer</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>31</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/45468.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="159054">
        <title>Erläuternder Bericht zur Vernehmlassung</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>141</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/45472.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="159057">
        <title>Brief an die Kantone</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>35</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/45475.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="159060">
        <title>Brief an die Organisationen</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>35</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/45478.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="159064">
        <title>Adressatenliste</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>230</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/45481.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Le Conseil fédéral entend faciliter le financement des groupes de sociétés sis en Suisse</title>
      <lead>Le Conseil fédéral a ouvert aujourdʼhui la consultation relative à la modification de lʼordonnance sur lʼimpôt anticipé. Ce projet est destiné à renforcer les activités de financement des groupes de sociétés sis en Suisse. </lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Les groupes de sociétés qui ont leur siège en Suisse exercent aujourdʼhui fréquemment et de manière ciblée leurs activités de financement à lʼétranger. Ils évitent ainsi lʼimpôt anticipé auquel ils seraient soumis dans certaines situations, si une société du groupe sise en Suisse gérait le financement. Une partie de la création de valeur dans ce domaine échappe donc à lʼéconomie suisse.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Afin de rapatrier cette création de valeur en Suisse, le Conseil fédéral propose de modifier lʼordonnance sur lʼimpôt anticipé. La modification proposée concerne les groupes dont une entreprise sise en Suisse garantit une obligation émise par une autre société du groupe sise à lʼétranger. En vertu de cette modification, les intérêts versés par lʼentreprise suisse garante de lʼobligation ne seront plus soumis systématiquement à lʼimpôt anticipé. Pour que les intérêts sur ces fonds soient exonérés de lʼimpôt anticipé, le transfert de fonds de la société émettrice étrangère vers une société du groupe sise en Suisse ne devra pas excéder le montant des fonds propres de la société émettrice.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Telle quʼelle a été soumise à la consultation le 18 décembre 2014, la révision de la loi fédérale sur lʼimpôt anticipé (passage au principe de lʼagent payeur) proposée par le Conseil fédéral, résoudrait fondamentalement et durablement les problèmes actuels. Elle est actuellement suspendue (en attendant lʼissue de la votation sur lʼinitiative populaire «Oui à la protection de la sphère privée») et la suite des événements reste incertaine. Dans ce contexte, le Conseil fédéral propose de modifier lʼordonnance sur lʼimpôt anticipé, afin de renforcer lʼattrait de la place économique suisse.&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Patrick Teuscher, responsable de la communication, Administration fédérale des contributions AFC Tél. +058 464 90 00, media@estv.admin.ch</contact>
      <attachment id="159052">
        <title>Projet dʼordonnance sur lʼimpôt anticipé</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>31</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/45469.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="159055">
        <title>Rapport explicatif sur le projet soumis à consultation</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>202</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/45473.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="159058">
        <title>Lettre adressée aux cantons</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>148</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/45476.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="159061">
        <title>Lettre adressée aux organisations</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>148</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/45479.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="159065">
        <title>Liste des destinataires</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>230</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/45482.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Il Consiglio federale intende agevolare il finanziamento di gruppi in Svizzera</title>
      <lead>In data odierna il Consiglio federale ha indetto la procedura di consultazione concernente la modifica dell’ordinanza sull’imposta preventiva. Il progetto intende potenziare le attività di finanziamento di gruppi in Svizzera.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Oggigiorno i gruppi con sede in Svizzera svolgono spesso le attività di finanziamento deliberatamente all’estero. In tal modo evitano di versare l’imposta preventiva dovuta in determinate situazioni in caso di finanziamento tramite una società del gruppo domiciliata in Svizzera. L’economia elvetica perde dunque una parte del valore aggiunto creato in questo settore.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Per riportare questo valore aggiunto nel nostro Paese, il Consiglio federale propone una modifica dell’ordinanza sull’imposta preventiva (OIPrev). La modifica concerne i gruppi all’interno dei quali una società svizzera del gruppo (garante) garantisce un’obbligazione emessa da una società estera appartenente allo stesso gruppo (emittente). Con l’adeguamento proposto, gli interessi pagati all’interno del gruppo dalla società garante svizzera non saranno più soggetti in tutti i casi all’imposta preventiva. Il trasferimento di fondi da una società emittente estera a una società del gruppo con sede in Svizzera continuerà ad essere possibile al massimo fino a concorrenza dell’ammontare del capitale proprio della società emittente.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;La riforma della legge federale sull’imposta preventiva proposta dal Consiglio federale (passaggio al principio dell’agente pagatore), posta in consultazione il 18 dicembre 2014, risolverebbe definitivamente i problemi attuali. Tuttavia, in attesa dei risultati della votazione sull’iniziativa popolare «Sì alla protezione della sfera privata» prevista attualmente non prima del 2017, al momento il progetto di riforma è sospeso e la relativa tempistica rimane incerta. Alla luce di quanto esposto l’Esecutivo propone la modifica dell’OIPrev qui presentata al fine di rafforzare l’attrattiva della piazza finanziaria svizzera.&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Patrick Teuscher, capo della Comunicazione, Amministrazione federale delle contribuzioni AFC tel. 058 464 90 00, media@estv.admin.ch</contact>
      <attachment id="159053">
        <title>Progetto dell’ordinanza sull’imposta preventiva</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>31</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/45470.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="159056">
        <title>Rapporto esplicativo per la procedura di consultazione</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>206</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/45474.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="159059">
        <title>Lettera ai Cantoni</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>146</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/45477.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="159062">
        <title>Lettera alle organizzazioni</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>146</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/45480.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="159066">
        <title>Elenco dei destinatari</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>230</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/45483.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Federal Council wants to facilitate group financing in Switzerland</title>
      <lead>Today, the Federal Council initiated the consultation procedure on an amendment to the Withholding Tax Ordinance. The proposal should strengthen financing activities of groups in Switzerland. </lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;At present, groups established in Switzerland often carry out targeted financing activities abroad. In this way, they avoid withholding tax, which would be due in certain situations were they to conduct the financing via group companies established in Switzerland. The Swiss economy thereby misses out on some of the added value in this sector. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;For this added value to be retained in Switzerland, the Federal Council is proposing an amendment to the Withholding Tax Ordinance. This amendment concerns those groups in which a Swiss group company (guarantor) provides a guarantee for a bond of a foreign group company (issuer) belonging to the same group. With the proposed amendment, intra-group interest payments of the Swiss guarantor are no longer to be subject to withholding tax in all cases. Forwarding of funds from the foreign issuer to a group company established in Switzerland should still be possible up to the maximum amount of the equity capital of the issuer.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The reform of the Withholding Tax Act proposed by the Federal Council (switchover to the paying agent principle), as indicated on 18 December 2014 in the consultation, would sustainably resolve the current problems in principle. However, the reform has been suspended for the time being (awaiting the outcome of the vote on the popular initiative "Yes to protecting privacy"), and the subsequent timetable is unknown. Against this backdrop, the Federal Council is proposing this amendment of the Withholding Tax Ordinance to enhance the appeal of Switzerland as a business location.&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Patrick Teuscher, Head of Communications, Federal Tax Administration FTA Tel. 058 464 90 00, media@estv.admin.ch</contact>
      <attachment id="159051">
        <title>Entwurf Verordnung über die Verrechnungssteuer</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>31</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/45468.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="159054">
        <title>Erläuternder Bericht zur Vernehmlassung</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>141</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/45472.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="159057">
        <title>Brief an die Kantone</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>35</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/45475.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="159060">
        <title>Brief an die Organisationen</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>35</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/45478.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="159064">
        <title>Adressatenliste</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>230</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/45481.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <offers>
      <offer id="10" org-id="605">
        <name lang="de">Verrechnungssteuer</name>
        <name lang="fr">Impôt anticipé</name>
        <name lang="it">Imposta preventiva</name>
        <name lang="en">Withholding tax</name>
      </offer>
    </offers>
    <keywords>
      <keyword id="132" org-id="605">
        <name lang="de">Verrechnungssteuer</name>
        <name lang="fr">Impôt anticipé</name>
        <name lang="it">Imposta preventiva</name>
        <name lang="en">Swiss withholding tax</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="126" org-id="605">
        <name lang="de">Finanzplatz Schweiz</name>
        <name lang="fr">Place financière suisse</name>
        <name lang="it">Piazza finanziaria svizzera</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland as a financial centre</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="235" org-id="605">
        <name lang="de">Internationale Steuerpolitik</name>
        <name lang="fr">Politique fiscale internationale</name>
        <name lang="it">Politica fiscale internazionale</name>
        <name lang="en">International tax policy</name>
      </keyword>
    </keywords>
    <topics>
      <topic id="5">
        <name lang="de">Behörden</name>
        <name lang="fr">Autorités</name>
        <name lang="it">Autorità</name>
        <name lang="en">Authorities</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="10">
        <name lang="de">Bundesrat</name>
        <name lang="fr">Conseil fédéral</name>
        <name lang="it">Consiglio federale</name>
        <name lang="en">Federal Council</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="44">
        <name lang="de">Steuern</name>
        <name lang="fr">Impôts</name>
        <name lang="it">Imposte</name>
        <name lang="en">Taxation</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
