<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="63901" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2016-09-23</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="201" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>201</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="1080" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>701</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Staatssekretariat für Bildung, Forschung und Innovation</name>
      <name lang="fr">Secrétariat d'Etat à la formation, à la recherche et à l'innovation</name>
      <name lang="it">Segreteria di Stato per la formazione, la ricerca e l'innovazione</name>
      <name lang="en">State Secretariat for Education, Research and Innovation</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.sbfi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.sbfi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.sbfi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.sbfi.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@sbfi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@sbfi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@sbfi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@sbfi.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="201">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <department id="701">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Wirtschaft, Bildung und Forschung</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'économie, de la formation et de la recherche</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'economia, della formazione e della ricerca</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Economic Affairs, Education and Research</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Die Schweizer Vertretung mit ihren Partnern unter einem gemeinsamen Dach in San Francisco</title>
      <lead>Heute wird in San Francisco in einer historischen Lagerhalle am Pier 17 die neue Heimat des Schweizer Generalkonsulats, von swissnex San Francisco, des Swiss Business Hubs USA sowie von Schweiz Tourismus eröffnet. In Zusammenarbeit mit verschiedenen anderen Departementen arbeitet das Eidgenössische Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten EDA daran, am selben Standort jeweils alle Aktivitäten der schweizerischen Aussenpolitik unter einem Dach zusammenzuführen.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Wer in San Francisco künftig den Kontakt zur Schweiz sucht, findet ihn am Hafen. Eine langgezogene ehemalige Lagerhalle im zentral gelegenen Hafengebiet wird den grossen Schweizer Hub an der amerikanischen Westküste beherbergen. Nicht nur das Schweizer Generalkonsulat ist in Zukunft an dieser Adresse vertreten, sondern auch swissnex San Francisco für den wissenschaftlichen und technologischen Austausch, Schweiz Tourismus sowie der Swiss Business Hub USA, der sich im Auftrag von Switzerland Global Enterprise um die Export- und Investitionsförderung kümmert. Von hier ist es auch zum Silicon Valley nicht mehr weit. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Das Pier 17 als diplomatisches Zentrum sowie Innovations- und Wirtschaftshub in San Francisco vereint somit die verschiedenen Akteure der schweizerischen Aussenpolitik unter einem Dach. Das neue Gebäude ermöglicht als Ort der Begegnung eine noch bessere Vernetzung von Schweizer Akteuren aus Wirtschaft, Tourismus, Wissenschaft, Start-ups, Verwaltung, Kunst und Kultur mit jenen der USA. Die Schweiz tritt am Pier 17 innovativ und offen in Erscheinung und bietet Besucherinnen und Besuchern verschiedene Dienstleistungen an. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In Nähe des führenden Innovationszentrums Silicon Valley besteht ein steigendes Interesse von Schweizer Universitäten, Forschungsinstitutionen und innovativen Unternehmen sowie schweizerischen KMUs und Investoren an verstärkten Beziehungen zu dieser Region an der US-Westküste. Mit dem Ausbau namentlich von swissnex San Francisco und dessen Zusammenführung mit dem Swiss Business Hub USA unter einem Dach wird diesem Bedürfnis Rechnung getragen. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In Zusammenarbeit mit verschiedenen Departementen arbeitet das EDA daran, am selben Standort jeweils alle Aktivitäten der schweizerischen Aussenpolitik unter einem Dach zusammenzuführen, so dass in der betroffenen Botschaft bzw. dem Generalkonsulat ein kohärenter Auftritt der Schweiz, eine stärkere Sichtbarkeit unseres Landes und eine höhere betriebliche Effizienz ermöglicht werden. Dies ist ein entscheidender Faktor bei der Vermarktung der Schweiz als Wirtschafts– und Innovationsstandort sowie als Tourismusdestination. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Die Eröffnungsveranstaltungen in San Francisco finden vom 23. bis 25. September am Pier 17 statt und beinhalten Podiumsdiskussionen, Workshops und Ausstellungen zu Themen wie „Living Lab for Diplomacy“ und „Shaping the Future of Hospitality“.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Kommunikation EDA Bundeshaus West CH-3003 Bern Tel. Kommunikationsservice: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Medienstelle: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Regroupement sur un même site de la représentation suisse et de ses partenaires à San Francisco</title>
      <lead>Aujourd'hui a lieu l'inauguration des locaux qui abriteront désormais le consulat général de Suisse, swissnex San Francisco, le Swiss Business Hub USA et Suisse Tourisme dans un ancien entrepôt sis à l'adresse Pier 17, à San Francisco. En collaboration avec différents départements, le Département fédéral des affaires étrangères (DFAE) cherche à réunir sur des sites uniques toutes les activités liées à la politique étrangère de la Suisse.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;A San Francisco, le port constituera dorénavant le centre névralgique pour tisser des contacts avec la Suisse. En plein cœur dela ville, un ancien entrepôt conçu tout en longueur et situé dans la zone portuaire s'apprête à accueillir le grand hub suisse appelé à rayonner sur la côte ouest des États-Unis. Le consulat général de Suisse partagera désormais cette adresse avec swissnex San Francisco, qui se dédie aux échanges scientifiques et technologiques, Suisse Tourisme ainsi que le Swiss Business Hub USA, qui s'emploie à promouvoir les exportations et les investissements sur mandat de Switzerland Global Enterprise. Tout cela à quelques pas seulement de la Silicon Valley. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;En tant que centre diplomatique et pôle économique axé notamment sur l'innovation, Pier 17 regroupe désormais sur un même site les différents intervenants de la politique extérieure de la Suisse. Propice aux échanges, ce nouveau bâtiment facilitera le réseautage des acteurs suisses et américains issus des milieux économiques et scientifiques, du tourisme, de l'administration, de la scène artistique et culturelle ainsi que des start-up. L'image véhiculée par Pier 17 est celle d'une Suisse innovante et ouverte, qui propose de multiples prestations à ses visiteurs. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;La proximité du pôle d'innovation de la Silicon Valley suscite un intérêt croissant de la part des universités, des instituts de recherche et des entreprises innovantes ainsi que des PME et des investisseurs suisses qui souhaitent renforcer leurs relations avec cette région de la côte ouest des États-Unis. C'est précisément ce besoin que visent à combler le développement de swissnex San Francisco et son regroupement avec le Swiss Business Hub USA. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;En collaboration avec différents départements, le DFAE cherche à réunir sur des sites uniques toutes les activités liées à la politique étrangère de la Suisse afin que les ambassades ou les consulats généraux concernés puissent renforcer leur efficience et garantir une présence plus cohérente et une meilleure visibilité de la Suisse. Cette démarche est décisive pour promouvoir la Suisse en tant que site économique, pôle d'innovation et destination touristique. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Les manifestations organisées pour l'inauguration de Pier 17 ont lieu du 23 au 25 septembre et comprennent des débats publics, des ateliers et des expositions sur les thèmes «Living Lab for Diplomacy» et «Shaping the Future of Hospitality».&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Communication DFAE Palais fédéral ouest CH-3003 Berne Tél. Service de communication: +41 58 462 31 53 Tél. Service de presse: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>La rappresentanza svizzera e i suoi partner sotto lo stesso tetto a San Francisco</title>
      <lead>Oggi a San Francisco viene inaugurata in un capannone storico al Pier 17 la nuova sede del consolato generale di Svizzera, di swissnex San Francisco, di Swiss Business Hub USA e di Svizzera Turismo. In collaborazione con vari dipartimenti, il Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri (DFAE) cerca di riunire sotto lo stesso tetto tutte le attività legate alla politica estera della Svizzera in una stessa località.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Chi in futuro cercherà il contatto con la Svizzera a San Francisco lo troverà al porto. Un lungo ex capannone nella centrale zona portuale ospiterà il grande centro svizzero sulla costa occidentale americana. Non solo il consolato generale di Svizzera si troverà a questo indirizzo, ma anche swissnex San Francisco per lo scambio scientifico e tecnologico, Svizzera Turismo e Swiss Business Hub USA che, su mandato di Switzerland Global Enterprise, si occupa della promozione delle esportazioni e degli investimenti. Da qui la Silicon Valley non è più così lontana. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Il Pier 17, in qualità di centro diplomatico, innovativo ed economico a San Francisco, riunisce i vari attori della politica estera della Svizzera sotto lo stesso tetto. Come luogo d'incontro, il nuovo edificio permette un collegamento ancora migliore tra gli attori svizzeri dell'economia, del turismo, della scienza, delle start-up, dell'amministrazione, dell'arte e della cultura con i loro omologhi statunitensi. La Svizzera si presenta in modo innovativo e aperto al Pier 17 e offre alle visitatrici e ai visitatori diversi servizi. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Università, istituti di ricerca, aziende innovative, PMI e investitori svizzeri sono sempre più interessati a potenziare le relazioni con questa regione sulla west coast americana, nelle vicinanze della Silicon Valley, centro di innovazione leader nel mondo. Ampliare swissnex San Francisco e riunirla sotto lo stesso tetto con lo Swiss Business Hub USA risponde a questa esigenza. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In collaborazione con vari dipartimenti, il DFAE cerca di riunire sotto lo stesso tetto tutte le attività legate alla politica estera della Svizzera in una stessa località per permettere all'ambasciata o al consolato generale di presentare in modo coerente la Svizzera, di garantire maggiore visibilità e di ottenere più efficienza aziendale. Si tratta di un fattore decisivo nell'ambito della promozione della Svizzera come piazza economica, centro innovativo e destinazione turistica. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Gli eventi di apertura a San Francisco avranno luogo dal 23 al 25 settembre al Pier 17 e prevedono tavole rotonde, workshop e mostre su temi come «Living Lab for Diplomacy» e «Shaping the Future of Hospitality».&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Comunicazione DFAE Palazzo federale ovest CH-3003 Berna Tel. Servizio di comunicazione: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Servizio stampa: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Swiss representation in San Francisco now under one roof with its partners</title>
      <lead>Today sees the opening of the new home of the consulate general of Switzerland, swissnex San Francisco, the Swiss Business Hub USA and Switzerland Tourism inside a historic warehouse on San Francisco's Pier 17. In cooperation with various federal departments, the Federal Department of Foreign Affairs FDFA is working to bring all the activities of Swiss foreign policy together under a single roof in one location.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;In future, this will be the right address for anyone in San Francisco seeking to make contact with Switzerland. A long, former warehouse in the centrally located port area will accommodate this major Swiss hub on the West Coast of the United States. Not only the consulate general of Switzerland will in future be represented at this location, but also swissnex San Francisco (for science and technology-related exchanges), Switzerland Tourism and the Swiss Business Hub USA, which promotes exports and investments on behalf of Switzerland Global Enterprise. The new location is also not far from Silicon Valley.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Pier 17, as a diplomatic centre and hub for business and innovation in San Francisco, thus unites the different actors in Swiss foreign policy under one shared roof. As a meeting place, the new location helps further improve the networking of Swiss actors in the fields of commerce, tourism, science, start-ups, administration, art and culture with those from the USA. At the innovative address on Pier 17, Switzerland will be welcoming visitors and offering them a range of services. Situated close to Silicon Valley, the world's leading innovation centre, there is an increasing interest being shown by Swiss universities, research institutions and innovative companies, as well as by Swiss SMEs and investors, in enhanced relationships with this region. Establishing swissnex San Francisco and the Swiss Business Hub USA under one roof will serve to meet this need.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;In cooperation with various federal departments, the FDFA is working to bring all the activities of Swiss foreign policy together under a single roof at one location, providing for a coherent image of Switzerland, while increasing the visibility of our country and boosting efficiency at the respective embassy or consulate general. This is a key factor in marketing Switzerland as a hub for business and innovation and as a tourist destination. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The opening events are being held from 23 to 25 September at Pier 17 in San Francisco and include panel discussions, workshops and exhibitions relating to such topics as 'Living Lab for Diplomacy' and 'Shaping the Future of Hospitality'. &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>FDFA Communication Federal Palace West Wing CH-3003 Bern, Switzerland Tel. Communication service: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Press service: +41 58 460 55 55 E-mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @SwissMFA</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
