<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="63714" revoked="no">
    <version>2</version>
    <pubdate>2016-09-09</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="201" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>201</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="201">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Die DEZA präsentiert sich am Comptoir Suisse in Lausanne</title>
      <lead>Die DEZA stellt ihr Engagement am 97. Comptoir Suisse in Lausanne vor. Mit einer Ausstellung lädt sie die Besucherinnen und Besucher ein, ein halbes Dutzend Projekte der Schweizer Entwicklungszusammenarbeit in der Welt zu entdecken und ihr kulturelles Umfeld kennen zu lernen. Die zum ersten Mal in der Westschweiz gezeigte Ausstellung ist dem Thema Ernährungssicherheit gewidmet, wobei das Schwergewicht auf den Produktionsbedingungen der Kleinbauern liegt. Die Ausstellung gibt auch Einblick in Bildungsangebote im ländlichen Raum.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Am Comptoir Suisse, das vom 10. bis 19. September 2016 stattfindet, stellt die Direktion für Entwicklung und Zusammenarbeit (DEZA) auf einer Fläche von 150 m2 ihre Arbeit vor. Die Ausstellung mit dem Titel «Saveurs d’ailleurs. L’engagement de la DDC aux côtés des paysans du monde» (Über den Tellerrand: Einblick in die Schweizer Entwicklungszusammenarbeit) in der Eingangshalle gibt Einblick in das kulturelle Umfeld eines halben Dutzends Länder, in denen die DEZA die Arbeit von Kleinbäuerinnen und Kleinbauern unterstützt. Die interaktive Ausstellung lädt zum Dialog und zur Degustation von Produkten aus lokalem Anbau ein.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;70 Prozent der in Armut lebenden Menschen sind in der Landwirtschaft tätig. Der Agrarsektor beschäftigt weltweit am meisten Menschen. Deshalb ist das tägliche Engagement der DEZA und ihrer Partner, insbesondere im Bereich der Ernährungssicherheit, so wichtig.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Die Ausstellung am Comptoir Suisse zeigt, wie die DEZA durch die Entwicklung einer umweltverträglichen Landwirtschaft Armut und Hunger bekämpft. Je nach Land sind die Probleme rund um die Nahrungsmittelproduktion verschieden: In Benin fördert die DEZA den Schutz der Ernte vor Insektenbefall. In Laos wahrt die DEZA gemeinsam mit Reisbäuerinnen und -bauern sowie den betroffenen Behörden die Artenvielfalt der Anbaukulturen. Im Kosovo werden Gemüsebauern in der Verarbeitung und Lagerung ihrer Erzeugnisse geschult – zwei Aktivitäten, die Arbeitsplätze schaffen. In Peru finanziert die DEZA mehrere Initiativen zur Sensibilisierung von Ackerbauern und Viehzüchtern für den Klimawandel in den Anden und die dadurch erforderlichen Anpassungen.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mit ihrem Stand zeigt die DEZA auch, wie sie möglichst vielen Menschen zu einer hochwertigen Grund- und Berufsbildung verhelfen will. Grundkenntnisse – Lesen, Schreiben, Rechnen und die Beherrschung einer Landessprache – sind von entscheidender Bedeutung für alle Bäuerinnen und Bauern, die ihre Produkte auf dem Markt besser präsentieren und absetzen möchten.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Am Wochenende (einschliesslich Bettagsmontag) gibt es am Stand jeweils ein Podiumsgespräch mit einer Expertin oder einem Experten der DEZA und einem externen Gesprächspartner zu verschiedenen Themen der Entwicklungszusammenarbeit. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Daten und Themen der Podiumsgespräche:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Samstag, 10. September 2016, 11 Uhr: «Le pari des start-ups suisses pour gagner la bataille de l’eau potable»&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sonntag, 11. September 2016, 11 Uhr: «La super-puissance de la Chine à l’œuvre en Asie et en Afrique: une menace pour les petits paysans?»&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Samstag, 17. September 2016, 11 Uhr: «L’éducation contre l’exclusion: pouvoir apprendre à tout âge…»&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sonntag, 18. September 2016, 11 Uhr: «Quels modèles pour une agriculture éco-responsable?»&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Montag, 19. September 2016, 11 Uhr: «Les situations de crise alimentaire en Afrique: une fatalité?»&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Kommunikation EDA Bundeshaus West CH-3003 Bern Tel. Kommunikationsservice: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Medienstelle: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <attachment id="159209">
        <title>Daten und Themen der Podiumsgespräche (fr)</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>54</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/45280.pdf</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </attachment>
      <link id="159210">
        <title>Engagement der DEZA im Bereich Landwirtschaft und Ernährungssicherheit</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/deza/de/home/themen/landwirtschaft_undernaehrungssicherheit.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="159211">
        <title>Grundschul- und Berufsbildung, eine Priorität</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/deza/de/home/themen/grund-_und_berufsbildung.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="159212">
        <title>Comptoir Suisse in Lausanne (fr)</title>
        <uri>http://www.comptoir.ch/fr-CH.aspx</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="159225">
        <title>Fotogallerie</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/deza/de/home/publikationen_undservice/videos_und_bilder.html/publikationen/de/deza/image-galleries/comptoir-suisse-lausanne-2016</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="159226">
        <title>Galería de foto (sp)</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/deza/es/home/publikationen_undservice/videos_und_bilder.html/publikationen/en/deza/image-galleries/comptoir-suisse-lausanne-2016</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>La DDC à la rencontre du public au Comptoir suisse de Lausanne</title>
      <lead>La DDC se présentera sous la forme d’une exposition didactique lors de la 97e édition du Comptoir suisse à Lausanne. Dévoilée pour la première fois en Suisse romande, l’exposition invite les visiteurs à parcourir les univers culturels d’une demi-douzaine de projets de coopération au développement que la DDC met en œuvre à travers le monde. Le thème retenu est celui de la sécurité alimentaire avec un accent mis sur les conditions de production des petits paysans. L’exposition offre également un éclairage sur les offres éducatives proposées en milieu rural.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Au Comptoir suisse, du 10 au 19 septembre, la Direction du développement et de la coopération (DDC) accueillera le public sur un espace de 150 m2 situé dans la halle d’entrée de la manifestation. Intitulé «Saveurs d’ailleurs. L’engagement de la DDC aux côtés des paysans du monde», le stand emmènera les visiteurs découvrir l’univers culturel d’une demi-douzaine de pays où la DDC soutient le travail de petits exploitants agricoles. La visite se veut interactive à tous points de vue: la dégustation de produits cultivés dans les pays concernés servira d’invitation au dialogue.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;L’agriculture regroupe 70% des personnes vivant dans la pauvreté. Et elle reste à ce jour le secteur qui emploie le plus grand nombre de travailleurs à l'échelle planétaire. D’où l’importance du combat mené au quotidien par la DDC et ses partenaires dans le domaine de la sécurité alimentaire, parmi d’autres priorités.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;L’exposition présentée au Comptoir suisse montre comment on peut lutter contre la pauvreté et la faim tout en développant une agriculture respectueuse de l’environnement. Les problématiques liées à la production alimentaire sont diverses: au Bénin, un projet soutenu par la DDC aide les petits paysans à préserver les grains de maïs de l’appétit dévastateur des insectes. Au Laos, la DDC défend la biodiversité des cultures en agissant aux côtés des cultivateurs de riz et des autorités concernées. Au Kosovo, des maraîchers sont formés à la transformation et à la conservation de leurs produits – deux activités génératrices d’emplois. Au Pérou, la DDC finance plusieurs initiatives qui visent à sensibiliser les cultivateurs et les éleveurs des Andes au changement climatique et aux adaptations que ce dernier impose.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Le stand dévoile aussi comment la DDC s’y prend pour offrir une éducation de base et une formation professionnelle de qualité au plus grand nombre. Les compétences de base – savoir lire, écrire, calculer et maîtriser une langue nationale – sont en effet décisives pour tout paysan qui, en plus de nourrir sa famille, souhaite valoriser et écouler ses récoltes sur le marché.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Lors des jours de week-end (lundi du Jeûne inclus), une table ronde publique réunira, sur le stand, un(e) expert(e) de la DDC et un interlocuteur extérieur pour aborder diverses thématiques de la coopération au développement. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dates et thèmes des tables rondes programmées:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Samedi 10 septembre 2016, 11h: «Le pari des start-up suisses pour gagner la bataille de l’eau potable»&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Dimanche 11 septembre 2016, 11h: «La super-puissance de la Chine à l’œuvre en Asie et en Afrique: une menace pour les petits paysans?»&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Samedi 17 septembre 2016, 11h: «L’éducation contre l’exclusion: pouvoir apprendre à tout âge…»&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Dimanche 18 septembre, 11h: «Quels modèles pour une agriculture éco-responsable?»&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Lundi 19 septembre, 11h: «Les situations de crise alimentaire en Afrique: une fatalité?»&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Communication DFAE Palais fédéral ouest CH-3003 Berne Tél. Service de communication: +41 58 462 31 53 Tél. Service de presse: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <attachment id="159213">
        <title>Dates et thèmes des tables rondes programmées</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>54</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/45281.pdf</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </attachment>
      <link id="159214">
        <title>L’engagement de la DDC dans les domaines de l’agriculture et de la sécurité alimentaire</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/deza/fr/home/themes-ddc/agriculture-securite-alimentaire.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="159215">
        <title>L’éducation de base et la formation professionnelle, une priorité</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/deza/fr/home/themes-ddc/education-base-formation-professionnelle.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="159216">
        <title>Comptoir suisse de Lausanne</title>
        <uri>http://www.comptoir.ch/fr-CH.aspx</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="159227">
        <title>Galerie photo</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/deza/fr/home/publikationen_undservice/videos_und_bilder.html/publikationen/fr/deza/image-galleries/comptoir-suisse-lausanne-2016</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="159228">
        <title>Galería de foto (es)</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/deza/es/home/publikationen_undservice/videos_und_bilder.html/publikationen/en/deza/image-galleries/comptoir-suisse-lausanne-2016</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>La DSC incontra il pubblico al Comptoir Suisse di Losanna</title>
      <lead>In occasione della 97a edizione del Comptoir Suisse di Losanna, la DSC si presenterà attraverso un'esposizione didattica. Organizzata per la prima volta in Svizzera romanda, l'esposizione invita i visitatori a percorrere gli universi culturali di una mezza dozzina di progetti di cooperazione allo sviluppo della DSC in tutto il mondo. Il tema affrontato è quello della sicurezza alimentare, con l’accento sulle condizioni di produzione dei piccoli contadini. L'esposizione mette in luce anche le offerte formative in contesti rurali.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Dal 10 al 19 settembre al Comptoir Suisse, la Direzione dello sviluppo e della cooperazione (DSC) accoglierà il pubblico in uno spazio di 150 m2 situato nell’area all'entrata della manifestazione. Con il titolo «Sapori lontani. L'impegno della DSC a favore dei contadini del mondo», lo stand permetterà ai visitatori di scoprire l'universo culturale di una mezza dozzina di Paesi in cui la DSC sostiene il lavoro dei piccoli agricoltori. La visita sarà interattiva sotto ogni punto di vista: la degustazione di prodotti coltivati nei Paesi interessati servirà da invito al dialogo.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Il 70 per cento delle persone attive nel settore agricolo vive in condizioni di povertà; l'agricoltura resta finora il settore che impiega il maggior numero di lavoratori su scala mondiale. Per questo motivo, la DSC e i suoi partner operano ogni giorno nell'ambito della sicurezza alimentare, che è una delle priorità.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;L’esposizione presentata al Comptoir Suisse mostra come sia possibile combattere la povertà e la fame sviluppando un'agricoltura rispettosa dell'ambiente. Le problematiche legate alla produzione alimentare sono diverse: nel Benin, un progetto sostenuto dalla DSC aiuta i piccoli contadini a preservare i chicchi di mais dall'appetito devastante degli insetti. In Laos, la DSC tutela la biodiversità delle colture, offrendo sostegno ai coltivatori di riso e alle autorità. In Kosovo, degli orticoltori vengono formati alla lavorazione e alla conservazione dei loro prodotti, due attività che generano impieghi. In Perù, la DSC finanzia diverse iniziative che puntano a sensibilizzare coltivatori e allevatori delle Ande al cambiamento climatico e agli adattamenti che questo impone.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Lo stand mostra anche come la DSC cerchi di offrire un'istruzione di base e una formazione professionale di qualità al maggior numero possibile di persone. Le competenze di base – leggere, scrivere, calcolare e padroneggiare una lingua nazionale – sono decisive per ogni contadino che, oltre a nutrire la propria famiglia, desidera valorizzare e smerciare i propri raccolti. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Nelle giornate festive (compreso il lunedì del Digiuno federale), durante una tavola rotonda pubblica sullo stand, un esperto della DSC e un interlocutore esterno, affronteranno diverse tematiche della cooperazione allo sviluppo. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Date e temi delle tavole rotonde in programma&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sabato 10 settembre 2016, ore 11.00: «Le pari des start-up suisses pour gagner la bataille de l’eau potable» («La scommessa delle start-up svizzere per vincere la battaglia per l'acqua potabile»)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Domenica 11 settembre 2016, ore 11.00: «La super-puissance de la Chine à l’œuvre en Asie et en Afrique: une menace pour les petits paysans?» («La superpotenza cinese all'opera in Asia e in Africa: una minaccia per i piccoli contadini?»)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sabato 17 settembre 2016, ore 11.00: «L’éducation contre l’exclusion: pouvoir apprendre à tout âge…» («L'educazione contro l'esclusione: poter imparare a ogni età...»)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Domenica 18 settembre, ore 11.00: «Quels modèles pour une agriculture éco-responsable?» («Quali modelli per un'agricoltura eco-responsabile?»)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Lunedì 19 settembre, ore 11.00: «Les situations de crise alimentaire en Afrique: une fatalité?» («Le situazioni di crisi alimentare in Africa: una fatalità?»)&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Comunicazione DFAE Palazzo federale ovest CH-3003 Berna Tel. Servizio di comunicazione: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Servizio stampa: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <attachment id="159217">
        <title>Date e temi delle tavole rotonde in programma (fr)</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>54</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/45282.pdf</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </attachment>
      <link id="159218">
        <title>L'impegno della DSC nel settore dell'agricoltura e della sicurezza alimentare</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/deza/it/home/themen/landwirtschaft_undernaehrungssicherheit.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="159219">
        <title>Istruzione di base e formazione professionale: una priorità</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/deza/it/home/themen/grund-_und_berufsbildung.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="159220">
        <title>Comptoir Suisse di Losanna (fr)</title>
        <uri>http://www.comptoir.ch/fr-CH.aspx</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="159229">
        <title>Galleria fotografica</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/deza/it/home/publikationen_undservice/videos_und_bilder.html/publikationen/it/deza/image-galleries/comptoir-suisse-lausanne-2016</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="159230">
        <title>Galería de foto (sp)</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/deza/es/home/publikationen_undservice/videos_und_bilder.html/publikationen/en/deza/image-galleries/comptoir-suisse-lausanne-2016</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>SDC showcase at Lausanne's Comptoir Suisse</title>
      <lead>This year's 97th edition of the Comptoir Suisse national fair in Lausanne will include an exhibition by the Swiss Agency for Development and Cooperation (SDC). Unveiled for the first time in the French-speaking part of Switzerland, the exhibition invites visitors to tour the cultural universe of six development cooperation projects that the SDC is implementing around the world. The theme is food security with a focus on the conditions for agricultural production for smallholder farmers. The exhibition also highlights education in rural areas.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;From 10 to 19 September, the SDC will welcome the public to its 150 m2 exhibition in the entry hall of the Comptoir Suisse grounds. Under the heading 'Flavours from beyond – how the SDC works with the farmers of the world', the stand will take visitors on a cultural journey through six countries where the SDC is supporting the work of smallholder farmers. The exhibition is designed to be interactive from all angles: visitors will be invited to taste the locally grown produce and discuss topical issues.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Seventy percent of people living in poverty work in the agricultural sector, which remains the single largest employer in the world. That is why the SDC and its partners have committed themselves to increasing food security as one of their top priorities.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The exhibition will demonstrate how environmentally friendly farming can help fight poverty and hunger. There are many factors that affect food production. In Benin, the SDC backs a project that helps smallholders protect their corn from the devastating impact of insect damage. In Laos, the SDC works with rice farmers and the relevant authorities to support crop diversity. In Kosovo, market gardeners are shown how to process and preserve their produce – two activities that generate employment. In Peru, the SDC funds several initiatives among Andean farmers and livestock breeders to raise awareness of climate change and how they will need to adapt to this.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The stand will also show how the SDC is working to provide basic education and quality vocational training to as many people as possible. Basic skills such as reading, writing, arithmetic and the ability to speak a national language are in fact crucial for smallholder farmers who wish to move beyond subsistence farming and sell their crops on the market.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Public round tables will also be hosted at the weekends (incl. on the lundi du Jeûne public holiday in the canton of Vaud), with SDC specialists and guest speakers discussing a variety of topics in the field of development cooperation. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Round-table programme:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Saturday 10 September 2016, 11am: The challenge for Swiss start-up in the battle for drinking water&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sunday11 September 2016, 11am: The Chinese superpower in Asia and Africa – a threat to smallholder farmers?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Saturday 17 September 2016, 11am: Education versus exclusion – a case for lifelong learning...&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sunday 18 September 2016, 11am: What are the models for environmentally sound agriculture?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sunday 18 September 2016, 11am: Are food crises in Africa inevitable?&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>FDFA Communication Federal Palace West Wing CH-3003 Bern, Switzerland Tel. Communication service: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Press service: +41 58 460 55 55 E-mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @SwissMFA</contact>
      <attachment id="159221">
        <title>Round-table programme (fr)</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>54</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/45283.pdf</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </attachment>
      <link id="159222">
        <title>The SDC's activities in agriculture and food security</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/deza/en/home/themen/landwirtschaft_undernaehrungssicherheit.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="159223">
        <title>Prioritising basic education and vocational training</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/deza/en/home/themen/grund-_und_berufsbildung.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="159224">
        <title>Comptoir suisse in Lausanne (fr)</title>
        <uri>http://www.comptoir.ch/fr-CH.aspx</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="159231">
        <title>Photo gallery</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/deza/en/home/publikationen_undservice/videos_und_bilder.html/publikationen/en/deza/image-galleries/comptoir-suisse-lausanne-2016</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="159232">
        <title>Galería de foto (sp)</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/deza/es/home/publikationen_undservice/videos_und_bilder.html/publikationen/en/deza/image-galleries/comptoir-suisse-lausanne-2016</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
