<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="41644" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2011-10-10</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="201" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>201</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="201">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Bundespräsidentin Micheline Calmy-Rey empfängt UNO-Generalsekretär Ban Ki-moon zu einem Arbeitsbesuch</title>
      <lead>Am 17. Oktober 2011 empfängt eine von Bundespräsidentin Micheline Calmy-Rey geleitete Delegation des Bundesrates UNO-Generalsekretär Ban Ki-moon zu einem offiziellen Arbeitsbesuch. Auf dem Programm stehen Gespräche über verschiedene UNO-Themen von gemeinsamem Interesse. Ban Ki-moon nimmt am 16. Oktober an den Eröffnungsfeierlichkeiten der 125. Konferenz der Interparlamentarischen Union IPU teil. </lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;UNO-Generalsekretär Ban Ki-moon weilt am 17. Oktober 2011 für einen offiziellen Arbeitsbesuch in Bern. Er wird von einer von Bundespräsidentin Micheline Calmy-Rey geleiteten Delegation des Bundesrates zu einem offiziellen Arbeitsbesuch empfangen. Ban Ki-moon hat der Schweiz letztmals im April 2007 einen Arbeitsbesuch abgestattet. Im Lichte der Ernennung von Ban Ki-moon für eine zweite Amtszeit als UNO-Generalsekretär am 21. Juni 2011 bietet der Besuch die Gelegenheit, über die Herausforderungen der UNO in den kommenden Jahren zu diskutieren und sich über die Prioritäten des Generalsekretärs und der Schweiz auszutauschen. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ban Ki-moon wird am 16. Oktober 2011 an den Eröffnungsfeierlichkeiten der 125. Konferenz der Interparlamentarischen Union IPU in Bern teilnehmen. Die Schweiz ist Gastgeberin der Jubiläumskonferenz der IPU. Ausserdem trifft er am 16. Oktober mit sechs Jugendlichen aus dem arabischen Raum zusammen, die anlässlich der Jahreskonferenz der Politischen Abteilung IV Menschliche Sicherheit des Eidgenössischen Departements für auswärtige Angelegenheiten vom 18. Oktober in Bern weilen. Die Jugendlichen, die sich im Rahmen des arabischen Frühlings in ihren Heimatländern engagieren, erhalten Gelegenheit, dem UNO-Generalsekretär ihre Situation, ihr Engagement und ihre Erwartungen an die Adresse der Vereinten Nationen zu erläutern.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Kommunikation EDA Bundeshaus West CH-3003 Bern Tel. Kommunikationsservice: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Medienstelle: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Visite de travail du secrétaire général des Nations Unies à Berne</title>
      <lead>Le 17 octobre 2011, la présidente de la Confédération, Madame Micheline Calmy-Rey, accompagnée d’une délégation du Conseil fédéral, recevra le secrétaire général des Nations Unies, Monsieur Ban Ki-moon, pour une visite officielle de travail. Les entretiens porteront sur des thèmes d’intérêt commun relatifs à l’ONU. Le 16 octobre, Monsieur Ban Ki-moon prendra part à l’ouverture de la 125e Conférence de l’Union interparlementaire (UIP). </lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Le secrétaire général des Nations Unies, Monsieur Ban Ki-moon, se rendra à Berne le 17 octobre pour une visite officielle de travail. Il sera reçu par une délégation du Conseil fédéral emmenée par Madame Micheline Calmy-Rey. La dernière visite de travail de Monsieur Ban Ki-moon remonte au mois d’avril 2007. Le mandat de Monsieur Ban Ki-moon en tant que secrétaire général de l’ONU ayant été renouvelé le 21 juin 2011, cette visite est aussi l’occasion pour les participants de se pencher sur les défis auxquels sera confrontée l’ONU ces prochaines années et de s’entretenir des priorités du secrétaire général et de la Suisse. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Le 16 octobre, Monsieur Ban Ki-moon prendra part à l’ouverture de la 125e Conférence de l’Union interparlementaire (UIP), à Berne. La Suisse est l’Etat-hôte de cette Conférence-anniversaire de l’UIP. En outre, Monsieur Ban Ki-moon rencontrera six jeunes originaires du monde arabe qui séjourneront à Berne à l’occasion de la conférence annuelle de la Division politique IV Sécurité humaine du Département fédéral des affaires étrangères, qui aura lieu le 18 octobre. Ces jeunes, qui se mobilisent dans leur pays pour le printemps arabe, auront l’occasion de présenter au secrétaire général des Nations Unies leur situation, leur engagement et leurs attentes vis-à-vis de l’ONU.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Communication DFAE Palais fédéral ouest CH-3003 Berne Tél. Service de communication: +41 58 462 31 53 Tél. Service de presse: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>La presidente della Confederazione Micheline Calmy-Rey riceve il segretario generale dell'ONU Ban Ki-moon per una visita di lavoro</title>
      <lead>Il 17 ottobre 2011 la presidente della Confederazione Micheline Calmy-Rey riceverà insieme con una delegazione il segretario generale dell'ONU Ban Ki-moon per una visita ufficiale di lavoro. Il programma prevede colloqui su vari temi dell'ONU d’interesse comune. Ban Ki-moon prenderà parte il 16 ottobre alla cerimonia di apertura della 125ª Conferenza dell'Unione interparlamentare (UIP). </lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Il segretario generale dell'ONU Ban Ki-moon giungerà a Berna il 17 ottobre 2011 per una visita di lavoro ufficiale. Sarà ricevuto da una delegazione del Consiglio federale guidata dalla presidente della Confederazione Micheline Calmy-Rey. L'ultima visita di lavoro di Ban Ki-moon in Svizzera risale all'aprile 2007. In previsione della rinomina di Ban Ki-moon a segretario generale dell'ONU, prevista per il 21 giugno 2011, la visita sarà l'occasione per discutere delle sfide dell'ONU nei prossimi anni e delle priorità del segretario generale e della Svizzera. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Il 16 ottobre Ban Ki-moon prenderà parte a Berna alla cerimonia di apertura della 125ª Conferenza dell'Unione interparlamentare (UIP), di cui la Svizzera è ospite organizzatore. Lo stesso giorno incontrerà un gruppo di sei giovani provenienti dal mondo arabo che, il 18 ottobre, parteciperanno alla Conferenza annuale della Divisione politica IV della Sicurezza umana del Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri, che si terrà a Berna. Questi sei giovani, protagonisti nei propri Paesi d’origine della cosiddetta «Primavera araba», avranno la possibilità di illustrare al segretario generale dell’ONU la loro situazione e il loro impegno nonché di esporre le loro aspettative nei confronti delle Nazioni Unite.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Comunicazione DFAE Palazzo federale ovest CH-3003 Berna Tel. Servizio di comunicazione: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Servizio stampa: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>The President of the Confederation to receive the UN Secretary-General in Bern for a working visit</title>
      <lead>On 17 October 2011, the President of the Confederation, Micheline Calmy-Rey, together with a delegation of the Federal Council, will receive the UN Secretary-General, Ban Ki-moon, in Bern for an official working visit. The programme will cover a number of UN-related themes of mutual interest. Prior to this, on 16 October, Ban Ki-moon will attend the inaugural ceremony of the 125th Assembly of the Inter-Parliamentary Union IPU. </lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;On 17 October 2011, the UN Secretary-General, Ban Ki-moon, will be in Bern for an official working visit. He will be received by a delegation of the Federal Council led by the President of the Confederation, Micheline Calmy-Rey. Ban Ki-moon last paid a working visit to Switzerland in April 2007. In the light of his nomination for a second term in office as UN Secretary-General on 21 June 2011, the visit offers the opportunity to discuss the challenges facing the UN in the coming years and to exchange views about the priorities of the Secretary-General and Switzerland. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;On 16 October 2011, Ban Ki-moon will attend the inaugural ceremony of the 125th Assembly of the Inter-Parliamentary Union IPU in Bern. Switzerland is hosting the 125th anniversary assembly of the IPU. On the same day, he will also meet six young people from the Arab world here in Bern for the Political Affairs Division IV Annual Conference on 18 October. These people, who are actively involved in the Arab Spring in their home countries, will have the opportunity to discuss with the Secretary-General their situation, their activities and their expectations with regard to the United Nations. &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>FDFA Communication Federal Palace West Wing CH-3003 Bern, Switzerland Tel. Communication service: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Press service: +41 58 460 55 55 E-mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @SwissMFA</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
