<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="17916" revoked="no">
    <version>2</version>
    <pubdate>2008-03-21</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="yes" id="603" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>601</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidg. Finanzverwaltung</name>
      <name lang="fr">Administration fédérale des finances</name>
      <name lang="it">Amministrazione federale delle finanze</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Finance Administration</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.efv.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.efv.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.efv.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.efv.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@efv.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@efv.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@efv.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@efv.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="601">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Finanzdepartement</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des finances</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale delle finanze</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Finance</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.efd.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.dff.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.efd.admin.ch/efd/it/home.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.efd.admin.ch/efd/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Bund erhält 63,67 Millionen Franken für seinen früheren Anteil an der Swiss</title>
      <lead>Die Lufthansa zahlt dem Bund 63,67 Millionen Franken für das Paket an Swiss-Aktien, das dieser vor drei Jahren gegen einen so genannten Besserungsschein abgetreten hat. Die Ausgaben, die der Bund für den Start der Swiss aufgewendet hat, reduzieren sich damit von 600 auf 536,33 Millionen Franken. Der von der Lufthansa überwiesene Barbetrag gilt als ausserordentliche Einnahme und wird darum gemäss Finanzhaushaltgesetz für den Schuldenabbau verwendet.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Im Rahmen der Übernahme der Swiss durch die Lufthansa haben die Grossaktionäre ihre Aktien vor drei Jahren der AirTrust AG abgetreten (Total Aktien Grossaktionäre: 45'339'948; Anteil Bund: 10'714'286 oder 23,6 Prozent). Sie erhielten dafür kein Geld, sondern einen Besserungsschein. Der Wert dieses Besserungsscheins wurde von der Kursentwicklung der Lufthansa-Aktie gegenüber einem Index von Konkurrenzwerten abhängig gemacht. Als Referenzfirmen wurden die British Airways (40 Prozent), die Air France/KLM (40 Prozent) und die Iberia (20 Prozent) bestimmt. Mit den Grossaktionären wurde vertraglich eine Entschädigung vereinbart für den Fall, dass sich der Kurs der Lufthansa-Aktie bis zum 20. März 2008 besser entwickeln sollte als derjenige der Konkurrenzwerte. Die Entschädigung war zu ermitteln aus dem arithmetischen Durchschnittswert der Schlusskurse der Lufthansa-Aktien im Vergleich zu denjenigen der Referenzaktien an den letzten 30 Börsentagen.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Für die Fortführung des Flugbetriebs durch eine neue nationale Fluggesellschaft nach dem Grounding der Swissair hat der Bund im Jahre 2001 Kredite in der Höhe von insgesamt 2'050 Millionen bewilligt. Effektiv hat er für die Aufrechterhaltung des Flugbetriebs von Swissair und Crossair vom bewilligten Kredit von 1'450 Millionen Zahlungen von 1'169 Millionen geleistet. Sodann hat sich der Bund in der vorgesehenen Grössenordnung von 600 Millionen an der neuen nationalen Fluggesellschaft Swiss beteiligt. Insgesamt resultierten also Ausgaben von 1'769 Millionen.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Nach Abgeltung des Besserungsscheins durch die Lufthansa beläuft sich das vorläufige Bundesengagement für die Fortführung des Flugbetriebs der Swissair und den Start der Nachfolgegesellschaft Swiss auf rund 1'705 Millionen. Der definitive Betrag kann erst nach Abschluss des Konkursverfahrens durch den Liquidator beziffert werden. Aus heutiger Sicht ist eine weitere Reduktion durchaus wahrscheinlich (Anerkennung einer allfälligen Liquiditätsreserve im Zusammenhang mit dem gewährten Bundesdarlehen sowie Nachlassdividende).&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Der Bund engagierte sich bei der Swiss, weil für die politische, wirtschaftliche und gesellschaftliche Entwicklung unseres Landes direkte Anschlussverbindungen an die wichtigsten Handels- und Industriezentren der Welt von grosser Bedeutung sind. Die ersatzlose Aufgabe des Flugbetriebs der Swissair und des damit mit hoher Wahrscheinlichkeit verbundenen Zusammenbruchs weiterer Gesellschaften der Swissair-Gruppe hätte sich zudem massiv auf die Beschäftigung ausgewirkt. Eine Massenentlassung wäre insofern zu einem sehr ungünstigen Zeitpunkt gekommen, als sich der Arbeitsmarkt gerade an einem kritischen Wendepunkt befand. In die Überlegungen zu Swissair hat der Bundesrat auch die erhebliche Bedeutung des Zürcher Hubs für die Volkswirtschaft mit einbezogen.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Eine Voraussetzung für das Engagement des Bundes war, dass sich an einer Lösung alle Kreise beteiligen, die an der Existenz einer nationalen Fluggesellschaft mit interkontinentaler Anbindung interessiert sind. Von Beginn an war klar, dass das Engagement des Bundes zeitlich befristet sein würde. In einem liberalisierten Markt - wie es die Luftfahrt ganz ausgeprägt ist - soll der Staat für die Schaffung möglichst optimaler Rahmenbedingungen sorgen. Nicht zu seinen langfristigen Aufgaben gehört das Tragen von unternehmerischen Risiken.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Dieter Leutwyler, Pressesprecher EFD, Tel. 079 459 73 76</contact>
      <revisions>
        <revision date="2008-03-25 10:10" type="R"/>
      </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>La Confédération reçoit 63,67 millions de francs pour sa participation au lancement de Swiss</title>
      <lead>Lufthansa verse 63,67 millions de francs à la Confédération pour le paquet d'actions de Swiss que cette dernière lui a cédé il y a trois ans contre un bon de récupération. Les dépenses consacrées par la Confédération au démarrage de Swiss reculent dès lors de 600 à 536,33 millions de francs. Considéré comme une recette extraordinaire, le montant en espèces versé par Lufthansa sera affecté à la réduction de la dette, conformément à la loi sur les finances de la Confédération.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Lors de la reprise de Swiss par Lufthansa, il y a trois ans, les grands actionnaires ont cédé leurs actions à la société Air Trust AG (nombre total des actions des grands actionnaires: 45&amp;nbsp;339&amp;nbsp;948; part de la Confédération: 10&amp;nbsp;714&amp;nbsp;286 ou 23,6&amp;nbsp;%). Ils n'ont pas reçu d'argent en contrepartie mais un bon de récupération. La valeur de ce bon est liée à l'évolution du cours de l'action Lufthansa par rapport à un indice de valeurs concurrentes. Les entreprises de référence retenues sont British Airways (40&amp;nbsp;%), Air France/KLM (40&amp;nbsp;%) et Iberia (20&amp;nbsp;%). Une indemnisation a été convenue par contrat avec les grands actionnaires pour le cas où le cours de l'action Lufthansa évoluerait plus favorablement que celui des valeurs concurrentes jusqu'au 20 mars 2008. Le montant de l'indemnité se fonde sur la moyenne arithmétique des cours de clôture de Lufthansa comparée à celle des actions de référence durant les 30 derniers jours de Bourse.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Pour assurer l'exploitation du réseau aérien par une nouvelle compagnie nationale après le grounding de Swissair, la Confédération a ouvert des crédits pour un montant total de 2&amp;nbsp;050 millions en 2001. Sur le crédit de 1&amp;nbsp;450 millions ouvert pour le maintien du service aérien de Swissair et de Crossair, elle a utilisé effectivement 1&amp;nbsp;169 millions. De plus, la Confédération a participé à hauteur du montant prévu de quelque 600 millions au démarrage de la nouvelle compagnie aérienne nationale Swiss. Au total, les dépenses se sont donc élevées à 1&amp;nbsp;769 millions.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Suite au remboursement du bon de récupération par Lufthansa, l'engagement de la Confédération pour le maintien du service de vol de Swissair et le démarrage de la nouvelle compagnie Swiss s'élève provisoirement à près de 1 705 millions. Le montant définitif ne pourra toutefois être déterminé que lorsque le liquidateur aura mis fin à la procédure de faillite. Selon les estimations actuelles, une réduction supplémentaire est tout à fait possible (reconnaissance d'une éventuelle réserve de liquidité en relation avec le prêt alloué par la Confédération ainsi que dividende de liquidation).&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Si la Confédération s'est engagée en faveur de Swiss, c'est parce que les liaisons directes avec les principaux centres commerciaux et industriels du monde sont vitales pour le développement politique, économique et social de notre pays. L’abandon pur et simple des vols de Swissair, qui aurait très probablement entraîné la chute d’autres sociétés du groupe, aurait par ailleurs exercé un effet massif sur l’emploi. Des licenciements en masse seraient tombés à un très mauvais moment puisque le marché du travail se trouvait alors à un tournant critique. Dans ses considérations relatives à Swissair, le Conseil fédéral avait également tenu compte de la grande importance de la plate-forme aéroportuaire (hub) de Zurich pour l’économie.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Une des conditions posées par la Confédération pour fournir son aide était que tous les milieux intéressés à l’existence d’une compagnie aérienne nationale assurant des vols intercontinentaux participent à la recherche d’une solution. Il était d’emblée clair que cette aide serait limitée dans le temps. Sur un marché libéralisé – et celui des transports aériens l’est au plus haut point – l’Etat doit veiller à la mise en place de conditions-cadres optimales. Mais supporter les risques auxquels une entreprise est exposée ne fait pas partie de ses tâches à long terme.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Dieter Leutwyler, porte-parole du DFF, tél. 079 459 73 76</contact>
      <revisions>
        <revision date="2008-03-25 10:10" type="R"/>
      </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>La Confederazione riceve 63,67 milioni di franchi per la sua precedente partecipazione a Swiss</title>
      <lead>Lufthansa versa alla Confederazione 63,67 milioni di franchi per il pacchetto di azioni Swiss che quest'ultima aveva ceduto tre anni or sono in cambio di un cosiddetto buono di recupero. Le spese che la Confederazione ha sostenuto per l’avvio di Swiss si riducono pertanto da 600 milioni a 536,33 milioni di franchi. Il versamento in contanti effettuato da Lufthansa è considerato entrata straordinaria ed è pertanto utilizzato per la riduzione del debito conformemente alla legge sulle finanze della Confederazione.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Nel quadro della ripresa di Swiss da parte di Lufthansa, i grandi azionisti hanno ceduto tre anni or sono le loro azioni alla AirTrust AG (totale delle azioni dei grandi azionisti: 45&amp;nbsp;339&amp;nbsp;948; quota della Confederazione: 10&amp;nbsp;714&amp;nbsp;286, ossia il 23,6 %). In cambio non hanno ricevuto denaro, bensì un buono di recupero, il cui valore è stato fatto dipendere dall’evoluzione del corso delle azioni Lufthansa rispetto a un indice di valori concorrenti. Sono state definite come compagnie di riferimento British Airways (40&amp;nbsp;%), Air France/KLM (40&amp;nbsp;%) e Iberia (20&amp;nbsp;%). Con i grandi azionisti è stata convenuta per contratto un’indennità, nell’ipotesi che il corso dell’azione Lufthansa avesse registrato un’evoluzione migliore di quella dei valori concorrenti alla data del 20&amp;nbsp;marzo 2008. L’indennità doveva essere calcolata in funzione del valore medio dei corsi di chiusura dell’azione Lufthansa rispetto ai valori di chiusura delle azioni di riferimento negli ultimi 30 giorni di quotazione in borsa.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Per la continuazione delle attività di volo da parte di una nuova compagnia aerea nazionale dopo il grounding di Swissair, nel 2001 la Confederazione aveva concesso crediti per complessivi 2050 milioni di franchi. Per il mantenimento delle attività di volo di Swissair e di Crossair, la Confederazione ha operato versamenti effettivi di 1169 milioni, attinti dal credito autorizzato di 1450 milioni. La Confederazione ha poi partecipato alla nuova compagnia aerea nazionale Swiss nel volume previsto di 600 milioni. Ne sono quindi risultate uscite complessive pari a 1769 milioni.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Ad avvenuto saldo del buono di recupero da parte di Lufthansa, l’impegno della Confederazione per il mantenimento delle attività di volo della Swissair e per l'avvio della società continuatrice Swiss ammonta a circa 1705 milioni. L'importo definitivo potrà essere quantificato dal liquidatore solo dopo la chiusura della procedura di fallimento. Nell'ottica attuale un'ulteriore riduzione è senz'altro probabile (riconoscimento di un'eventuale riserva di liquidità in relazione al prestito concesso dalla Confederazione nonché dividendo concordatario).&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; La Confederazione si è impegnata in Swiss perché collegamenti diretti con i principali centri commerciali e industriali del mondo sono di somma importanza per lo sviluppo politico, economico e sociale del nostro Paese. La cessazione senza sostituzione delle attività di volo di Swissair e quindi l’elevata probabilità di crollo di altre società del gruppo Swissair, vincolata a tale cessazione, si sarebbe inoltre ripercossa in misura massiccia sull’occupazione. L’eventuale licenziamento in massa si sarebbe peraltro verificato in un momento particolarmente sfavorevole proprio perché il mercato del lavoro si trovava a una svolta critica. Nelle sue considerazioni su Swissair, il Consiglio federale ha pure integrato la notevole importanza del fulcro di Zurigo per l’economia.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Una delle condizioni dell’impegno della Confederazione era che tutte le cerchie interessate all’esistenza di una compagnia aerea nazionale con collegamenti intercontinentali partecipassero a una soluzione. Fin dall’inizio era chiaro che l’impegno della Confederazione sarebbe stato limitato nel tempo. In un mercato liberalizzato quale l’aviazione, lo Stato deve provvedere alla creazione di condizioni quadro ottimali. L’assunzione di rischi imprenditoriali non rientra invece nei suoi compiti a lungo termine.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Dieter Leutwyler, portavoce del DFF, tel. 079 459 73 76</contact>
      <revisions>
        <revision date="2008-03-25 10:10" type="R"/>
      </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Confederation to receive 63.67 million francs for its earlier share in Swiss</title>
      <lead>Lufthansa will pay the Confederation CHF 63.67 million for the package of shares in Swiss, which it exchanged for a debtor warrant three years ago. The sum spent by the Confederation to launch Swiss is thus reduced from CHF 600 million to CHF 536.33 million. The cash amount transferred by Lufthansa is classed as extraordinary income and will therefore be used for the purposes of debt reduction in accordance with the Financial Budget Act.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Three years ago, as part of the takeover of Swiss by Lufthansa, the major shareholders transferred their stock to AirTrust AG (total shares of the large shareholders: 45,339,948; Confederation shareholding: 10,714,286 or 23.6 per cent). In exchange they received a debtor warrant instead of money. The value of this debtor warrant was linked to the performance of the Lufthansa share price in relation to an index of competitor share prices. British Airways (40 per cent), Air France/KLM (40 per cent) and Iberia (20 per cent) were selected as reference companies. A contractual compensation arrangement was agreed with the major shareholders in the event that the Lufthansa share price should perform better than those of the competition by the date of 20 March 2008. The compensation was to be calculated on the basis of the arithmetical average of the market closing rates of Lufthansa shares compared to those of the reference shares over the last 30 trading days.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;In 2001, the Confederation authorised loans amounting to CHF 2,050 million so that flight operations could be resumed by a new national airline after the grounding of Swissair. The Confederation used CHF 1,169 million of an authorised loan of CHF 1,450 million in payments to maintain Swissair and Crossair flight operations. The Confederation then took a stake in the new national airline, Swiss, in the anticipated region of CHF 600 million. The resulting total expenditure therefore amounts to CHF 1,769 million.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;After payment of the debtor warrant by Lufthansa, the Confederation's provisional commitment in the resumption of flight operations by Swissair and the launch of its successor Swiss amounts to approximately CHF 1,705 million. The final amount will only be known when bankruptcy proceedings have been completed by the liquidator. From today’s standpoint, a further reduction is quite probable (recognition of any reserves of liquid assets in connection with federal loans provided and liquidation dividends).&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The government became involved in Swiss because direct connections to the world’s most important business centres are immensely important for the political, economic and social development of our country. The abandonment of Swissair flight operations and the highly probable subsequent collapse of other Swissair Group companies would have had an enormous impact on employment. A mass layoff of staff would have come at a very inopportune moment just as the labour market was at a critical turning point. In its considerations relating to Swissair, the Federal Council also took into account the major importance of Zurich and the surrounding area for the country’s economy.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;One of the prerequisites for the federal government’s involvement was that all the parties interested in the existence of a national airline with intercontinental connections should be involved in finding a solution. It was clear from the outset that the commitment of the government would be for a limited period only. In a liberalised market such as that of aviation, the state should seek to create an optimum framework. However, its long term tasks do not include assuming entrepreneurial risks.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Dieter Leutwyler, FDF Press Officer, tel. 079 459 73 76</contact>
      <revisions>
        <revision date="2008-03-25 10:10" type="R"/>
      </revisions>
    </content>
    <offers>
      <offer id="3" org-id="603">
        <name lang="de">Wirtschaft, Währung</name>
        <name lang="fr">Economie, monnaie</name>
        <name lang="it">Economia, Moneta</name>
        <name lang="en">Economic, Monetary affairs</name>
      </offer>
    </offers>
    <keywords>
      <keyword id="127" org-id="603">
        <name lang="de">Nationale Airline</name>
        <name lang="fr">Compagnie nationale d'aviation</name>
        <name lang="it">Compagnia aerea nazionale</name>
        <name lang="en">National airline</name>
      </keyword>
    </keywords>
    <topics>
      <topic id="47">
        <name lang="de">Wirtschaft</name>
        <name lang="fr">Économie</name>
        <name lang="it">Economia</name>
        <name lang="en">Economic Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
