<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="9392" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2004-07-19</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="703" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>701</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Staatssekretariat für Wirtschaft</name>
      <name lang="fr">Secrétariat d'Etat à l'économie</name>
      <name lang="it">Segreteria di Stato dell'economia</name>
      <name lang="en">State Secretariat for Economic Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.seco.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.seco.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.seco.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.seco.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@seco.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@seco.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@seco.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@seco.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="701">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Wirtschaft, Bildung und Forschung</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'économie, de la formation et de la recherche</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'economia, della formazione e della ricerca</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Economic Affairs, Education and Research</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Handel mit Tropenholz – Förderung der Nachhaltigkeit statt Verbote</title>
      <teaser>SECO ermöglicht bahnbrechendes Abkommen Gleich zwei Meilensteine setzt das Staatssekretariat für Wirtschaft (SECO) diese Woche in der internationalen Tropenholzpolitik. Unter seiner Federführung wird am 19.07.2004 in Bern ein Abkommen zwischen dem Verband Schweizerischer Türenbranche (VST) und den Umweltverbänden Greenpeace Schweiz und WWF Schweiz unterschrieben, das Entwicklungsländern neue Türen öffnet. Vom 20.–23.07.2004 empfängt die Schweiz zudem als Gastland in Interlaken die Jahreskonferenz der Internationalen Tropenholzorganisation (ITTO).</teaser>
      <lead>SECO ermöglicht bahnbrechendes Abkommen Gleich zwei Meilensteine setzt das Staatssekretariat für Wirtschaft (SECO) diese Woche in der internationalen Tropenholzpolitik. Unter seiner Federführung wird am 19.07.2004 in Bern ein Abkommen zwischen dem Verband Schweizerischer Türenbranche (VST) und den Umweltverbänden Greenpeace Schweiz und WWF Schweiz unterschrieben, das Entwicklungsländern neue Türen öffnet. Vom 20.–23.07.2004 empfängt die Schweiz zudem als Gastland in Interlaken die Jahreskonferenz der Internationalen Tropenholzorganisation (ITTO).</lead>
      <text link="no">Die Internationale Tropenholzorganisation (ITTO) wird an ihrer Jahreskonferenz auf den erzielten Erfolgen aufbauen und neue Wege für eine nachhaltige Tropenholzpolitik ausloten, Verbesserungsmöglichkeiten prüfen und die internationale Zusammenarbeit stärken. An einer nachhaltigen Tropenholzpolitik sind Entwicklungsländer und Industriestaaten gleichermassen interessiert. Da die Holzindustrie wie zum Beispiel in Indonesien bis zu 15% einen wesentlichen Anteil des Bruttoinlandproduktes ausmacht, ist sie für die wirtschaftliche Entwicklung vieler Länder unerlässlich. 90% der 1,2 Milliarden Menschen, die weltweit in extremer Armut leben, sind zur Deckung eines Teils ihrer Grundbedürfnisse auf Wälder angewiesen. Ein nachhaltiger Tropenholzhandel und die Erhaltung der Tropenwälder schafft langfristig zusätzliches Einkommen und leistet einen Beitrag an die Armutsbekämpfung. Dies entspricht dem Oberziel der wirtschaftlichen Entwicklungszusammenarbeit des Staatssekretariats für Wirtschaft (SECO). Der nachhaltige Handel mit Tropenholz erlaubt gleichzeitig auch die Nachfrage der KonsumentInnen und der Möbelindustrie zu befriedigen. Dieses Engagement entspricht ausserdem dem international gesetzten Ziel 7 der sogenannten „Millennium Development Goals“ zur Förderung der nachhaltigen Nutzung natürlicher Ressourcen.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Ein Thema bleibt aber der illegale Tropenholzhandel. Die Berücksichtigung von sozial- und umweltverträglichen Kriterien sowie auf freiwilliger, öffentlich-privater Zusammenarbeit beruhende Abkommen können dem Raubbau effizienter einen Riegel schieben als Verbote. Diese Erkenntnis, und die in letzten Jahren verfolgte Politik bei Wiederaufforstung und Waldmanagement haben den Grundstein für das Abkommen zwischen dem Verband Schweizerische Türenbranche (VST), mit einem Marktanteil am Schweizer Import von Tropenholz von 30% und 400'000 fabrizierten Türen, und den Umweltverbänden WWF und Greenpeace gelegt. In vieler Hinsicht ist dies ein Modell, das zu weiteren fairen Handelsverträgen führen kann.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Für das&amp;nbsp;SECO sind die beiden Ereignisse die Konsolidierung eines langjährigen bilateralen und multilateralen Engagements. Mit verschiedenen Projekten und in Zusammenarbeit mit der Stiftung Intercooperation fördert das seco die Exportkapazitäten nachhaltiger Tropenholzbewirtschaftung, die Einführung der Zertifizierung von Hölzern und Holzprodukten und den Ausbau gewisser Umweltdienstleistungen wie zum Beispiel des Ökotourismus.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Bern, 19.7.2004&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; &lt;b&gt;Staatssekretariat für Wirtschaft&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt; Kommunikation&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; &lt;b&gt;Auskünfte:&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt; Hans-Peter Egler&lt;br /&gt; Ressortleiter Handels- und Umweltechnologiekooperation&lt;br /&gt; Tel. +41 (0)31 324 08 13&lt;br /&gt; &lt;u&gt;hans-peter.egler@seco.admin.ch&lt;/u&gt;&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Christian Hofer&lt;br /&gt; Informationsbeauftragter&lt;br /&gt; SECO&lt;br /&gt; Tel. 079 / 328 74 72&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Fotos zur Medienkonferenz stehen unter &lt;u&gt;www.photopress.ch&lt;/u&gt;&amp;nbsp;der Presse kostenlos zur Verfügung.&lt;br /&gt; Artikel und Fotos zur ITTO – Konferenz werden ab dem 20. Juli 2004 täglich aktualisiert online unter &lt;u&gt;http://www.iisd.ca/forestry/itto/ittc36/&lt;/u&gt;&amp;nbsp;abrufbar sein.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Für weitere seco-unterstützte Tropenwaldprojekte:&lt;br /&gt; &lt;u&gt;www.tropicalforests.ch&lt;/u&gt;</text>
      <contact/>
      <link id="18412">
        <title>&lt;u&gt;www.photopress.ch&lt;/u&gt;</title>
        <uri>http://www.photopress.ch</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="18413">
        <title>&lt;u&gt;http://www.iisd.ca/forestry/itto/ittc36/&lt;/u&gt;</title>
        <uri>http://www.iisd.ca/forestry/itto/ittc36/</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="18414">
        <title>&lt;u&gt;www.tropicalforests.ch &lt;/u&gt;</title>
        <uri>http://www.tropicalforests.ch</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Commerce de bois tropicaux – la voie de la durabilité</title>
      <teaser>Le seco permet la conclusion d’un accord novateurLe Secrétariat d'État à l'économie (seco) a fait franchir cette semaine deux étapes marquantes à la politique internationale en matière de bois tropicaux. Un accord a été conclu sous son égide, le 19.07.2004 à Berne, entre l'Association suisse de la branche des portes (VST) et les deux organisations écologiques Greenpeace Suisse et WWF Suisse, accord qui ouvre de nouvelles possibilités aux pays en développement. Par ailleurs, la Suisse accueille à Interlaken, du 20 au 23.07.2004, la conférence annuelle de l'Organisation internationale des bois tropicaux (OIBT).</teaser>
      <lead>Le SECO permet la conclusion d’un accord novateur Le Secrétariat d'État à l'économie (SECO) a fait franchir cette semaine deux étapes marquantes à la politique internationale en matière de bois tropicaux. Un accord a été conclu sous son égide, le 19.07.2004 à Berne, entre l'Association suisse de la branche des portes (VST) et les deux organisations écologiques Greenpeace Suisse et WWF Suisse, accord qui ouvre de nouvelles possibilités aux pays en développement. Par ailleurs, la Suisse accueille à Interlaken, du 20 au 23.07.2004, la conférence annuelle de l'Organisation internationale des bois tropicaux (OIBT).</lead>
      <text link="no">Lors de sa conférence annuelle, l'Organisation internationale des bois tropicaux développera son activité, à la fois en bâtissant sur les résultats déjà obtenus et en explorant de nouvelles voies; elle examinera les améliorations possibles et renforcera la coopération internationale pour une politique durable en matière d'exploitation des bois tropicaux. Cette politique présente un intérêt tant pour les pays en développement que pour les nations industrialisées. Comme l'industrie du bois représente une part importante du produit intérieur brut dans de nombreux pays (par exemple 15 % en Indonésie), elle est indispensable à leur développement économique. Sur les 1,2 milliard de personnes qui vivent dans une extrême pauvreté, 90 % ne pourraient couvrir une partie de leurs besoins vitaux sans les ressources forestières. La durabilité du commerce de bois tropicaux et la préservation des forêts tropicales sont à long terme créatrices de revenu et contribuent donc à la lutte contre la pauvreté. Tel est l'objectif supérieur du seco. Le commerce durable de bois tropicaux répond par ailleurs à une demande des consommateurs et de l'industrie du meuble. Cet engagement correspond en outre au septième des "Objectifs de développement pour le Millénaire": promouvoir l'utilisation durable des ressources naturelles.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Le commerce illégal de bois tropicaux reste cependant un thème d'actualité. L'exploitation abusive des forêts se laissera plus facilement combattre par la prise en compte de critères sociaux et écologiques et par des accords volontaires reposant sur une coopération mixte entre le privé et les pouvoirs publics que par des interdictions. C'est forts de cette conviction, et dans la droite ligne de la politique suivie ces dernières années en matière de reboisement et de gestion des forêts, que l'Association suisse de la branche des portes (VST), qui représente 30 % des importations de bois tropicaux en Suisse et un volume de production de 400 000 portes, et les deux organisations de protection de l'environnement Greenpeace et WWF ont conclu un accord. Celui-ci, qui possède à plusieurs égards un caractère précurseur, annonce de futurs accords de commerce équitable.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Pour le SECO, ces deux événements sont la consécration de plusieurs années d'efforts sur les plans bilatéral et multilatéral. Le seco, au travers de plusieurs projets et avec le concours de la fondation "Intercooperation", encourage les exportations de bois tropicaux issus de l'exploitation durable, l'instauration de procédures de certification pour le bois et les produits du bois et le développement de certaines prestations de service liées à la protection de l'environnement, par exemple l'écotourisme.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Berne, 19.7.2004&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; &lt;b&gt;Secrétariat d'État pour l'économie&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt; Communication&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; &lt;b&gt;Pour plus de renseignements:&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt; Hans-Peter Egler&lt;br /&gt; chef du secteur Coopération pour le commerce et la technologie environnementale&lt;br /&gt; tél. +41 (0)31 324 08 13&lt;br /&gt; &lt;u&gt;hans-peter.egler@seco.admin.ch&lt;/u&gt;&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Christian Hofer&lt;br /&gt; chargé de l'information&lt;br /&gt; SECO&lt;br /&gt; tél. 079 / 328 74 72&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Des photos de la conférence de presse peuvent être téléchargées gratuitement sur le site &lt;u&gt;www.photopress.ch&lt;/u&gt;.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Des articles et des photos relatifs à la conférence de l'OIBT seront disponibles à l'adresse &lt;u&gt;http://www.iisd.ca/forestry/itto/ittc36/&lt;/u&gt;&amp;nbsp;et régulièrement actualisées.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; &lt;u&gt;www.tropicalforests.ch&lt;/u&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;br /&gt;</text>
      <contact/>
      <link id="18408">
        <title>&lt;u&gt;www.photopress.ch&lt;/u&gt;</title>
        <uri>http://www.photopress.ch</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="18409">
        <title>&lt;u&gt;http://www.iisd.ca/forestry/itto/ittc36/&lt;/u&gt;</title>
        <uri>http://www.iisd.ca/forestry/itto/ittc36/</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="18410">
        <title>&lt;u&gt;www.tropicalforests.ch&lt;/u&gt;</title>
        <uri>http://www.tropicalforests.ch</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Commercio di legno tropicale – promozione della sostenibilità anziché divieti</title>
      <teaser>Un accordo pionieristico raggiunto grazie al SecoIn questa settimana il Segretariato di Stato dell'economia (Seco) ha raggiunto nel contempo due tappe importanti nell'ambito della politica internazionale di legno tropicale. Il 19.07.2004 infatti è stato firmato, sotto la sua egida, un accordo tra l'Associazione Svizzera Ramo Porte (ASRP) e le associazioni ambientalistiche Greepeace e WWF, che apre nuove possibilità ai Paesi in via di sviluppo. Dal 20 al 23.07.2004 la Svizzera accoglierà a Interlaken la conferenza annuale dell'Organizzazione internazionale dei legni tropicali (ITTO) in qualità di Paese ospitante.</teaser>
      <lead>Un accordo pionieristico raggiunto grazie al SECO In questa settimana il Segretariato di Stato dell'economia (SECO) ha raggiunto nel contempo due tappe importanti nell'ambito della politica internazionale di legno tropicale. Il 19.07.2004 infatti è stato firmato, sotto la sua egida, un accordo tra l'Associazione Svizzera Ramo Porte (ASRP) e le associazioni ambientalistiche Greepeace e WWF, che apre nuove possibilità ai Paesi in via di sviluppo. Dal 20 al 23.07.2004 la Svizzera accoglierà a Interlaken la conferenza annuale dell'Organizzazione internazionale dei legni tropicali (ITTO) in qualità di Paese ospitante.</lead>
      <text link="no">Nel corso della conferenza annuale, l'Organizzazione internazionale dei legni tropicali (ITTO) si baserà sui successi ottenuti e sonderà nuove vie, valuterà le possibilità di miglioramento e rafforzerà la cooperazione internazionale per una politica sostenibile del legno tropicale. A questa politica sono interessati sia i Paesi in via di sviluppo sia gli Stati industrializzati. Poiché l'industria del legno costituisce una quota considerevole del prodotto interno lordo, per esempio in Indonesia raggiunge il 15 %, essa è essenziale per lo sviluppo economico di molti Paesi. Su 1,2 miliardi di persone che in tutto il mondo vivono in condizioni di estrema povertà, il 90 % si affida alle foreste per soddisfare una parte dei propri bisogni primari. Il commercio sostenibile di legno tropicale e la conservazione delle foreste tropicali producono a lungo termine un reddito ulteriore e contribuiscono a combattere la povertà. Ciò è in linea con l'obiettivo principale della cooperazione economica allo sviluppo del Segretariato di Stato dell'economia (Seco). Il commercio sostenibile di legno tropicale consente nel contempo anche di soddisfare la domanda dei consumatori e dell'industria del mobile. Questo progetto è in linea inoltre con l'obiettivo 7 del cosiddetto "Millennium Development Goals" fissato a livello internazionale per promuovere l'utilizzo sostenibile delle risorse naturali.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Permane tuttavia la questione del commercio di legno tropicale. Il rispetto dei criteri socio-ambientali e l'accordo che si basa su una cooperazione spontanea, pubblico-privata possono contribuire più efficacemente dei divieti a frenare lo sfruttamento selvaggio. Sia questa consapevolezza sia la politica seguita negli ultimi anni nel rimboschimento e nella gestione delle foreste sono state la prima tappa per l'accordo tra le associazioni ambientalistiche WWF, Greepeace e l'Associazione Svizzera Ramo Porte (ASRP), che nelle importazioni nazionali di legno tropicale detiene una quota di mercato pari al 30 % (400 000 porte prodotte). Per molti aspetti ciò costituisce un modello, che può portare a ulteriori accordi commerciali leali.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Per il SECO entrambi gli eventi rappresentano il consolidamento di un impegno bilaterale e multilaterale di diversi anni. Con diversi progetti e in collaborazione con la fondazione Intercooperation il Seco promuove le esportazioni derivate dello sfruttamento sostenibile della foresta tropicale, l'introduzione della certificazione del legno e dei suoi derivati, nonché l'estensione&amp;nbsp; di certi servizi ambientali, come per esempio l'ecoturismo.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Berna, 19 luglio 2004&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; &lt;b&gt;Segretariato di Stato dell'economia&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt; Servizio Comunicazione&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; &lt;b&gt;Per informazioni:&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt; Hans-Peter Egler&lt;br /&gt; Cooperazione al commercio e alla tecnologia ambientale&lt;br /&gt; tel. +41 (0)31 324 08 13&lt;br /&gt; &lt;u&gt;hans-peter.egler@seco.admin.ch&lt;/u&gt;&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Christian Hofer&lt;br /&gt; portavoce&lt;br /&gt; SECO&lt;br /&gt; tel. 079 / 328 74 72&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Le foto della conferenza stampa sono visionabili gratuitamente sul sito .&lt;br /&gt; &lt;u&gt;www.photopress.ch&lt;/u&gt;.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Gli articoli e&amp;nbsp; le foto della conferenza ITTO, aggiornati quotidianamente, saranno scaricabili online dal 20 luglio 2004 all'indirizzo .&lt;br /&gt; &lt;u&gt;http://www.iisd.ca/forestry/itto/ittc36/&lt;/u&gt;.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; &lt;u&gt;www.tropicalforests.ch&lt;/u&gt;&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;</text>
      <contact/>
      <link id="18416">
        <title>&lt;u&gt;www.photopress.ch&lt;/u&gt;</title>
        <uri>http://www.photopress.ch</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="18417">
        <title>&lt;u&gt;http://www.iisd.ca/forestry/itto/ittc36/&lt;/u&gt;</title>
        <uri>http://www.iisd.ca/forestry/itto/ittc36/</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="18418">
        <title>&lt;u&gt;www.tropicalforests.ch &lt;/u&gt;</title>
        <uri>http://www.tropicalforests.ch</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Tropical timber – promoting sustainable trade instead of banning trade</title>
      <teaser>seco facilitates a pioneering agreementThe State Secretariat for Economic Affairs (seco) is setting two milestones in international policy on tropical timber this week. Under its auspices, an agreement will be signed in Bern on 19 July between the Swiss Door Manufacturers Association and the environmental associations Greenpeace, Switzerland and the WWF, Switzerland, aimed at opening new avenues for developing countries. From 20 to 23 July, Switzerland will play host to the Annual Conference of the International Tropical Timber Organization (ITTO). The Conference will be held in Interlaken.</teaser>
      <lead>SECO facilitates a pioneering agreement The State Secretariat for Economic Affairs (SECO) is setting two milestones in international policy on tropical timber this week. Under its auspices, an agreement will be signed in Bern on 19 July between the Swiss Door Manufacturers Association and the environmental associations Greenpeace, Switzerland and the WWF, Switzerland, aimed at opening new avenues for developing countries. From 20 to 23 July, Switzerland will play host to the Annual Conference of the International Tropical Timber Organization (ITTO). The Conference will be held in Interlaken.</lead>
      <text link="no">At its Annual Conference, the International Tropical Timber Organization (ITTO) will build on its successes to date, sound out new possibilities and examine potential ways of improving and reinforcing international cooperation. Developing countries and industrialised nations have an equal interest in seeing a sustainable policy on tropical timber. Given that in some countries the timber industry accounts for a significant share of GDP of up to 15%, such as in Indonesia, it is a vital industry for the economic development of many countries. 90% of the 1.2 billion people worldwide who live in extreme poverty are dependent on forests to cover a part of their basic needs. Sustainable trade in tropical timber and the preservation of tropical forests would generate additional income in the long term and contribute to reducing poverty. This is also the overriding aim of the economic development cooperation policy of the State Secretariat for Economic Affairs (seco). Sustainable trade in tropical timber also allows demand from the consumer and the furniture industry to be met. Furthermore, this policy conforms with Goal 7 of the “Millennium Development Goals“, i.e.&amp;nbsp; to ensure the sustainable use of natural resources.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; The illegal trade in tropical timber, nevertheless, remains an issue. Seeking to take account of social and environmental criteria and concluding agreements based on voluntary, public-private cooperation are far more effective ways of putting a stop to exhaustive logging than the ordering of bans on trade. This conclusion, together with the policy pursued in recent years of reforestation and forest management, formed the cornerstone of the agreement between the Swiss Door Manufacturers Association, whose market share of Swiss tropical timber imports of 30% and 400,000 manufactured doors, and the environmental associations WWF and Greenpeace. In many respects it is a model that could well lead to further fair-trade agreements.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; For SECO, the two events represent the consolidation of its long-running bilateral and multilateral commitment. Through a variety of projects and in cooperation with the Swiss NGO, Intercooperation, seco has been promoting the export capacities of sustainable tropical timber, the introduction of a certification system for timber and timber products, and the extension of certain environmental services such as eco-tourism.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Bern, 19 July 2004&lt;br /&gt; &lt;b&gt;State Secretariat for Economic Affairs&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt; Communication&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; &lt;b&gt;Further details:&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt; Hans-Peter Egler&lt;br /&gt; Head&lt;br /&gt; Trade and Clean Technology Cooperation&lt;br /&gt; Tel. +41 (0)31 324 08 13&lt;br /&gt; &lt;u&gt;hans-peter.egler@seco.admin.ch&lt;/u&gt;&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Christian Hofer&lt;br /&gt; Information Officer&lt;br /&gt; SECO&lt;br /&gt; Tel. 079 328 74 72&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Photos for the media conference are available to the press free of charge at &lt;u&gt;www.photopress.ch&lt;/u&gt;.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Articles and photos on the ITTO conference will be available online and updated daily from 20 July 2004 at .&lt;br /&gt; &lt;u&gt;http://www.iisd.ca/forestry/itto/ittc36/&lt;br /&gt; &lt;/u&gt;&lt;br /&gt; More Information on seco-funded projects with tropical forests:&lt;br /&gt; &lt;u&gt;www.tropicalforests.ch&lt;/u&gt;</text>
      <contact/>
      <link id="18404">
        <title>&lt;u&gt;www.photopress.ch&lt;/u&gt;</title>
        <uri>http://www.photopress.ch</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="18405">
        <title>&lt;u&gt;http://www.iisd.ca/forestry/itto/ittc36/&lt;/u&gt;</title>
        <uri>http://www.iisd.ca/forestry/itto/ittc36/</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="18406">
        <title>&lt;u&gt;www.tropicalforests.ch &lt;/u&gt;</title>
        <uri>http://www.tropicalforests.ch</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="47">
        <name lang="de">Wirtschaft</name>
        <name lang="fr">Économie</name>
        <name lang="it">Economia</name>
        <name lang="en">Economic Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
