<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="57059" revoked="no">
    <version>3</version>
    <pubdate>2015-04-29</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="1070" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>1070</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Der Bundesrat</name>
      <name lang="fr">Conseil fédéral</name>
      <name lang="it">Il Consiglio federale</name>
      <name lang="en">The Federal Council</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.admin.ch/gov/de/start.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.admin.ch/gov/fr/accueil.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.admin.ch/gov/it/pagina-iniziale.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.admin.ch/gov/en/start.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="yes" id="1060" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>601</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Staatssekretariat für internationale Finanzfragen</name>
      <name lang="fr">Secrétariat d'Etat aux questions financières internationales</name>
      <name lang="it">Segreteria di Stato per le questioni finanziarie internazionali</name>
      <name lang="en">State Secretariat for International Financial Matters</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.sif.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.sif.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.sif.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.sif.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@sif.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@sif.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@sif.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@sif.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="1070">
      <name lang="de">Der Bundesrat</name>
      <name lang="fr">Conseil fédéral</name>
      <name lang="it">Il Consiglio federale</name>
      <name lang="en">The Federal Council</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.admin.ch/gov/de/start.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.admin.ch/gov/fr/accueil.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.admin.ch/gov/it/pagina-iniziale.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.admin.ch/gov/en/start.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <department id="601">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Finanzdepartement</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des finances</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale delle finanze</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Finance</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.efd.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.dff.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.efd.admin.ch/efd/it/home.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.efd.admin.ch/efd/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Bundesrat eröffnet Vernehmlassung zum automatischen Informationsaustausch in Steuersachen mit Australien</title>
      <lead>Der Bundesrat hat heute die Vernehmlassung zum automatischen Informationsaustausch in Steuersachen mit Australien eröffnet. Am 3. März 2015 hatten die Schweiz und Australien eine entsprechende gemeinsame Erklärung unterzeichnet. Der erste automatische Austausch von Bankkundendaten mit Partnerländern soll 2018 stattfinden, sofern die nötigen Gesetzesgrundlagen fristgerecht geschaffen werden.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Die am 3. März 2015 von der Schweiz und Australien unterzeichnete gemeinsame Erklärung sieht die gegenseitige Anwendung des globalen Standards für den automatischen Informationsaustausch vor, sobald die gesetzlichen Grundlagen in beiden Ländern in Kraft sind. Im Weiteren hält die Erklärung fest, dass die Schweiz und Australien die im anderen Staat geltenden Vertraulichkeitsbestimmungen in Steuersachen als ausreichend erachten. Zudem hat Australien ein Regulierungsverfahren für seine Steuer­pflichtigen bereitgestellt. Schliesslich hat sich Australien zu Gesprächen über eine Verbesserung des Marktzutritts für Schweizer Finanzdienstleister bereit erklärt.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Die Vereinbarung mit Australien vom 3. März 2015 und der gestützt darauf nun in Vernehmlassung geschickte Bundesbeschluss sind die ersten dieser Art zur Einführung des automatischen Informationsaustausches mit einem Partnerstaat. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Interessierte Kreise können im Rahmen der Vernehmlassung bis am 19. August 2015 Stellung nehmen zum Bundesbeschluss, gestützt auf den die Schweiz den automatischen Informationsaustausch mit Australien aktivieren wird.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Rechtlich gesehen werden die beiden Staaten den automatischen Informationsaustausch gestützt auf die multilaterale Vereinbarung der zuständigen Behörden über den automatischen Informationsaustausch über Finanzkonten (Multilateral Competent Authority Agreement; MCAA) vornehmen. Das Vernehmlassungsverfahren zum MCAA und zum Entwurf des Bundesgesetzes über den internationalen automatischen Informationsaustausch in Steuersachen wurde am 21. April 2015 abgeschlossen. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Die Schweiz ist mit weiteren Staaten in Kontakt bezüglich Einführung des automatischen Informationsaustauschs. Am 19. März 2015 haben die Schweiz und die EU ein AIA-Abkommen paraphiert, das alle 28 EU-Mitgliedstaaten umfasst. Es soll demnächst unterzeichnet werden.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Mario Tuor, Leiter Kommunikation, Staatssekretariat für internationale Finanzfragen SIF Tel. +41 58 462 46 16, mario.tuor@sif.admin.ch</contact>
      <attachment id="135735">
        <title>Bundesbeschluss</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>14</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/39243.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="135737">
        <title>Brief an die Kantone</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>25</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/39181.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="135739">
        <title>Brief an die Organisationen</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>25</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/39183.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="135741">
        <title>Erläuternder Bericht</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>76</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/39185.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="135743">
        <title>Adressatenliste</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>62</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/39187.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Le Conseil fédéral ouvre la consultation sur l’échange automatique de renseignements en matière fiscale avec l’Australie</title>
      <lead>Le Conseil fédéral a ouvert aujourd’hui la consultation sur l’échange automatique de renseignements en matière fiscale avec l’Australie. Le 3 mars 2015, la Suisse et l’Australie avaient signé une déclaration commune à ce sujet. Le premier échange automatique de données bancaires avec des pays partenaires devrait avoir lieu en 2018, pour autant que les bases légales nécessaires soient créées en temps voulu.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;La déclaration commune signée le 3 mars 2015 par la Suisse et l'Australie prévoit l'application réciproque de la norme mondiale sur l'échange automatique de renseignements dès que les bases légales seront en vigueur dans les deux pays. Elle précise également que la Suisse et l'Australie jugent suffisantes les règles de confidentialité fiscale en vigueur dans l'autre Etat. L'Australie a en outre mis en place une procédure de régularisation destinée à ses contribuables. Enfin, elle s'est déclarée prête à entamer des discussions sur l'amélioration de l'accès au marché pour les prestataires suisses de services financiers.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;La déclaration signée avec l'Australie le 3 mars 2015 et l'arrêté fédéral correspondant qui a été mis en consultation constituent une première en ce qui concerne l'introduction de l'échange automatique de renseignements avec un Etat partenaire. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Dans le cadre de la consultation, les milieux intéressés ont jusqu'au 19 août 2015 pour se prononcer sur l'arrêté fédéral en vertu duquel la Suisse activera l'échange automatique de renseignements avec l'Australie.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Du point de vue juridique, les deux Etats procéderont à l'échange automatique de renseignements sur la base de l'Accord multilatéral entre autorités compétentes concernant l'échange automatique de renseignements relatifs aux comptes financiers (Multilateral Competent Authority Agreement; MCAA). La procédure de consultation relative au MCAA et au projet de loi fédérale sur l'échange international automatique de renseignements en matière fiscale s'est terminée le 21 avril 2015. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;La Suisse est en relation avec d'autres Etats en ce qui concerne l'introduction de l'échange automatique de renseignements. Le 19 mars 2015, la Suisse et l'Union européenne (UE) ont paraphé un accord sur l'échange automatique de renseignements qui englobe les 28 pays membres de l'UE. Cet accord devrait être signé prochainement.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Mario Tuor, responsable de la communication, Secrétariat d’Etat aux questions financières internationales SFI Tél. +41 58 462 46 16, mario.tuor@sif.admin.ch</contact>
      <attachment id="135736">
        <title>Arrêté fédéral</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>25</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/39180.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="135738">
        <title>Lettre aux cantons</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>26</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/39182.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="135740">
        <title>Lettre aux organisations</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>26</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/39184.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="135742">
        <title>Rapport explicatif</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>75</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/39186.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="135743">
        <title>Adressatenliste</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>62</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/39187.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <revisions>
        <revision date="2015-04-29 14:06" type="R"/>
      </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Il Consiglio federale avvia la consultazione concernente lo scambio automatico di informazioni a fini fiscali con l’Australia</title>
      <lead>In data odierna il Consiglio federale ha avviato la consultazione concernente lo scambio automatico di informazioni a fini fiscali con l’Australia. A tal proposito il 3 marzo 2015 la Svizzera e l’Australia hanno firmato una dichiarazione congiunta. Se le basi legali saranno istituite entro i termini stabiliti, il primo scambio automatico di dati relativi a clienti bancari con gli Stati partner avverrà nel 2018.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;La dichiarazione congiunta firmata dalla Svizzera e dall'Australia il 3 marzo 2015 prevede la reciproca applicazione dello standard globale per lo scambio automatico di informazioni non appena entreranno in vigore le relative basi legali in entrambi i Paesi. La dichiarazione precisa inoltre che la Svizzera e l'Australia ritengono sufficienti le norme concernenti la confidenzialità e la protezione dei dati previste dall'altro Stato. L'Australia ha approntato, in aggiunta, una procedura di regolarizzazione per i propri contribuenti. Infine l'Australia si è detta disposta a tenere colloqui allo scopo di migliorare l'accesso al mercato per i fornitori svizzeri di servizi finanziari.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;La dichiarazione congiunta con l'Australia del 3 marzo 2015 e il conseguente decreto ora posto in consultazione sono i primi atti di questo genere volti a introdurre lo scambio automatico di informazioni con uno Stato partner.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Nel quadro della consultazione, le cerchie interessate possono pronunciarsi entro il 19 agosto 2015 in merito al decreto federale, sulla base del quale la Svizzera attiverà lo scambio automatico di informazioni con l'Australia.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Da un punto di vista giuridico entrambi gli Stati effettuano lo scambio automatico di informazioni fondandosi sull'Accordo multilaterale tra autorità competenti sullo scambio automatico di informazioni relative a conti finanziari (Multilateral Competent Authority Agreement; MCAA). La procedura di consultazione sull'MCAA e sull'avamprogetto di legge sullo scambio automatico internazionale di informazioni in materia fiscale (LSAI) si è conclusa il 21 aprile 2015.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;La Svizzera è in contatto con altri Paesi per quanto riguarda l'introduzione dello scambio automatico di informazioni. Il 19 marzo 2015 la Svizzera e l'UE hanno parafato un accordo sullo scambio automatico di informazioni che comprende tutti i 28 Stati membri dell'UE e che verrà firmato prossimamente.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Mario Tuor, responsabile Comunicazione, Segreteria di Stato per le questioni finanziarie internazionali SFI tel. +41 58 462 46 16, mario.tuor@sif.admin.ch</contact>
      <attachment id="135736">
        <title>Arrêté fédéral</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>25</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/39180.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="135738">
        <title>Lettre aux cantons</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>26</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/39182.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="135740">
        <title>Lettre aux organisations</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>26</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/39184.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="135742">
        <title>Rapport explicatif</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>75</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/39186.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="135743">
        <title>Adressatenliste</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>62</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/39187.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <revisions>
        <revision date="2015-04-29 14:06" type="R"/>
      </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Federal Council initiates consultation on automatic exchange of information in tax matters with Australia</title>
      <lead>Today, the Federal Council initiated the consultation on the automatic exchange of information in tax matters with Australia. Switzerland and Australia had signed a corresponding joint statement on 3 March 2015. The first automatic exchange of bank client data with partner countries should take place in 2018, provided the necessary legal foundations are created in time.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;The joint declaration signed by Switzerland and Australia on 3 March 2015 makes provision for the mutual application of the global standard for the automatic exchange of information once the statutory basis has come into force in both countries. In addition, the declaration specifies that Switzerland and Australia are satisfied with the confidentiality rules provided for in the other jurisdiction with regard to tax. Moreover, Australia has established a regulatory procedure for its taxpayers. Finally, Australia has declared its willingness to hold talks on improving market access for Swiss financial service providers.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The agreement of 3 March 2015 with Australia and the federal decree based on this that has now been submitted for consultation are the first of their kind for introducing the automatic exchange of information with a partner state.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Within the framework of the consultation, interested parties have until 19 August 2015 to comment on the federal decree based on which Switzerland will activate the automatic exchange of information with Australia.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;From a legal viewpoint, the two countries will exchange information automatically based on the Multilateral Competent Authority Agreement on the Automatic Exchange of Financial Account Information (MCAA). The consultation procedure on the MCAA and on the draft Federal Act on the International Automatic Exchange of Information in Tax Matters ended on 21 April 2015.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Switzerland is in contact with other countries regarding the introduction of the automatic exchange of information. Switzerland and the EU initialled an AEOI agreement covering all 28 EU member states on 19 March 2015. It should be signed shortly.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Mario Tuor, Head of Communications, State Secretariat for International Financial Matters SIF Tel. +41 58 462 46 16, mario.tuor@sif.admin.ch</contact>
      <attachment id="135735">
        <title>Bundesbeschluss</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>14</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/39243.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="135737">
        <title>Brief an die Kantone</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>25</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/39181.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="135739">
        <title>Brief an die Organisationen</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>25</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/39183.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="135741">
        <title>Erläuternder Bericht</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>76</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/39185.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="135743">
        <title>Adressatenliste</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>62</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/39187.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <revisions>
        <revision date="2015-04-29 14:06" type="R"/>
      </revisions>
    </content>
    <offers>
      <offer id="291" org-id="1060">
        <name lang="de">Wirtschaft, Währung, Finanzplatz</name>
        <name lang="fr">Economie, monnaie, place financière</name>
        <name lang="it">Economia, Moneta, Piazza finanziaria</name>
        <name lang="en">Economic, Monetary and Financial Affairs</name>
      </offer>
    </offers>
    <keywords>
      <keyword id="235" org-id="1060">
        <name lang="de">Internationale Steuerpolitik</name>
        <name lang="fr">Politique fiscale internationale</name>
        <name lang="it">Politica fiscale internazionale</name>
        <name lang="en">International tax policy</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="118" org-id="1060">
        <name lang="de">Finanzmarktregulierung und -aufsicht</name>
        <name lang="fr">Réglementation et surveillance des marchés financiers</name>
        <name lang="it">Regolamentazione e vigilanza dei mercati finanziari</name>
        <name lang="en">Financial market regulation and supervision</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="126" org-id="1060">
        <name lang="de">Finanzplatz Schweiz</name>
        <name lang="fr">Place financière suisse</name>
        <name lang="it">Piazza finanziaria svizzera</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland as a financial centre</name>
      </keyword>
    </keywords>
    <topics>
      <topic id="35">
        <name lang="de">Finanzplatz</name>
        <name lang="fr">Place financière</name>
        <name lang="it">Piazza finanziaria</name>
        <name lang="en">Financial Centre</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="44">
        <name lang="de">Steuern</name>
        <name lang="fr">Impôts</name>
        <name lang="it">Imposte</name>
        <name lang="en">Taxation</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="47">
        <name lang="de">Wirtschaft</name>
        <name lang="fr">Économie</name>
        <name lang="it">Economia</name>
        <name lang="en">Economic Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
