<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="56903" revoked="no">
    <version>2</version>
    <pubdate>2015-04-16</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="1070" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>1070</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Der Bundesrat</name>
      <name lang="fr">Conseil fédéral</name>
      <name lang="it">Il Consiglio federale</name>
      <name lang="en">The Federal Council</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.admin.ch/gov/de/start.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.admin.ch/gov/fr/accueil.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.admin.ch/gov/it/pagina-iniziale.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.admin.ch/gov/en/start.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="401" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>401</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Justiz- und Polizeidepartement</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de justice et police</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale di giustizia e polizia</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Justice and Police</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.ejpd.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.ejpd.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.ejpd.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.ejpd.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-ejpd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">Info@gs-ejpd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-ejpd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-ejpd.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="1070">
      <name lang="de">Der Bundesrat</name>
      <name lang="fr">Conseil fédéral</name>
      <name lang="it">Il Consiglio federale</name>
      <name lang="en">The Federal Council</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.admin.ch/gov/de/start.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.admin.ch/gov/fr/accueil.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.admin.ch/gov/it/pagina-iniziale.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.admin.ch/gov/en/start.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <department id="401">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Justiz- und Polizeidepartement</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de justice et police</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale di giustizia e polizia</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Justice and Police</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.ejpd.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.ejpd.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.ejpd.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.ejpd.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-ejpd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">Info@gs-ejpd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-ejpd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-ejpd.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Bundespräsidentin Sommaruga mit Präsident Hollande in Zürich und Lausanne</title>
      <lead>Die nachhaltige Entwicklung, das duale Bildungssystem, die wirtschaftliche Zusammenarbeit zwischen der Schweiz und Frankreich und der kulturelle Austausch: Diese Themen haben den zweiten Tag des Staatsbesuchs von Frankreichs Präsident François Hollande geprägt. Bundespräsidentin Simonetta Sommaruga und ihr Gast reisten ins Knonauer Amt, nach Zürich und nach Lausanne.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Zu Beginn des Tages besuchten die Bundespräsidentin und der französische Präsident die Ernst Schweizer AG, ein in der Region Zürich ansässiges Familienunternehmen, das unter anderem Solardächer herstellt und 46 Lernende ausbildet. Die Firma hat die nachhaltige Entwicklung zu ihrer obersten Maxime erklärt. Während eines Rundgangs über das Fabrikgelände sprachen die Gäste mit Lernenden und Vertretern der Cleantech-Branche.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;An der Zürcher Hochschule der Künste (ZHdK) trafen Bundespräsidentin Sommaruga und Präsident Hollande anschliessend auf Kulturschaffende. Die ZHdK, eine der grössten Kunstschulen in Europa, präsentierte im Rahmen des Besuchsprogramms innovative, an der Schnittstelle verschiedener Gesellschaftsbereiche angesiedelte Projekte: "The Sound of Trees" will hörbar machen, wie Bäume auf den Klimawandel reagieren; die Installation "Birdly" simuliert den Vogelflug mittels sensorisch-motorischer Kontrolle. In den anschliessenden Gesprächen mit führenden Vertretern der Schweizer Wirtschaft stand das Anliegen im Zentrum, durch eine optimale Gestaltung der wirtschaftlichen Rahmenbedingungen die Wettbewerbsfähigkeit, die Nachhaltigkeit sowie die Zusammenarbeit zwischen den beiden Ländern zu stärken.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Wissenschaft und Innovation in der Westschweiz&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/b&gt;Unter dem Motto "Diversités de la Suisse" trafen die Bundespräsidentin und der französische Präsident im Zug von Zürich nach Lausanne Repräsentanten aus Politik, Kultur und Wissenschaft zum Mittagessen und informellen Austausch. Am Nachmittag besichtigten die Delegationen den "Innovation Park" der École polytechnique fédérale de Lausanne (EPFL). Beim Besuch von Logitech und Startups konnten sich die Vertreter beider Staaten vom dynamischen Umfeld des Innovationsparks überzeugen und sehen, wie innovative Firmen Hand in Hand mit der Wissenschaft zusammenarbeiten. Bundespräsidentin Sommaruga und Präsident Hollande sprachen anschliessend zu EPFL-Studierenden und beantworteten deren Fragen. Über 20 Prozent der Studierenden und mehr als 10 Prozent der Lehrkräfte der EPFL stammen aus Frankreich. Der Staatsbesuch des französischen Präsidenten endete mit einem Spaziergang am Ufer des Genfersees in Ouchy, wo François Hollande in seiner Kindheit mehrmals die Ferien verbrachte.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Informationsdienst EJPD, +41 (0)58 462 18 18</contact>
      <link id="135051">
        <title>Zürcher Hochschule der Künste</title>
        <uri>http://www.zhdk.ch</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="135052">
        <title>Zürcher Hochschule der Künste, "Birdly"</title>
        <uri>http://viad.zhdk.ch/de/projects/birdly</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="135055">
        <title>École polytechnique fédérale de Lausanne</title>
        <uri>http://www.epfl.ch</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions>
        <revision date="2015-04-17 09:00" type="R"/>
      </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>La présidente de la Confédération Simonetta Sommaruga et le président français François Hollande à Zurich et à Lausanne</title>
      <lead>Le développement durable, le système de formation en alternance, la collaboration économique entre la Suisse et la France et les échanges culturels : ces thèmes ont marqué la seconde journée de la visite d’Etat du président français François Hollande. La présidente de la Confédération Simonetta Sommaruga et son invité se sont rendus dans le district d’Affoltern ainsi qu’à Zurich et à Lausanne.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;En début de journée, la présidente de la Confédération et le président français ont visité l’entreprise familiale Ernst Schweizer AG, sise dans la région de Zurich, qui fabrique entre autres des toits solaires et forme 46 apprentis. Cette société s’est donné pour mot d’ordre le développement durable. Durant la visite des ateliers, les invités ont eu l’occasion de discuter avec les apprentis et des représentants de la branche Cleantech. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A la Haute école des arts de Zurich, la présidente de la Confédération Simonetta Sommaruga et le président François Hollande ont rencontré différents acteurs culturels. L’établissement, qui est l’une des plus grandes écoles d’art en Europe, a présenté aux invités des projets innovants à la croisée de différents domaines de la société : "The Sound of Trees" veut rendre audible la façon dont les arbres réagissent au changement climatique ; l’installation "Birdly" simule le vol des oiseaux au moyen d’un contrôle sensorimoteur. A l’issue de cette visite, les discussions menées avec des chefs de file de l’économie suisse ont porté sur la volonté de renforcer la compétitivité, la durabilité et la collaboration entre les deux pays en améliorant le plus possible les conditions-cadre de l’économie. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Science et innovation en Suisse occidentale&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/b&gt;Sur un thème intitulé "Diversités de la Suisse", la présidente de la Confédération et le président français ont discuté en toute décontraction autour d’un repas avec des représentants du monde politique, culturel et scientifique dans le train qui les menait de Zurich à Lausanne. L’après-midi, les deux délégations ont visité l’Innovation Park de l’Ecole polytechnique fédérale de Lausanne (EPFL). A cette occasion, la visite de Logitech et d’autres jeunes entreprises a permis aux délégués des deux pays de se faire une idée concrète de l’environnement dynamique du parc et de voir comment des sociétés innovantes travaillaient main dans la main avec le monde scientifique. La présidente de la Confédération et le président français se sont ensuite entretenus avec des étudiants de l’EPFL et ont répondu à leurs questions. Plus de 20 pour cent des étudiants et plus de 10 pour cent des enseignants de l’EPFL sont originaires de France. La visite d’Etat s’est terminée par une promenade au bord du lac Léman, à Ouchy, où François Hollande a plusieurs fois passé des vacances durant sa jeunesse.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Service d’information DFJP, +41 (0)58 462 18 18</contact>
      <link id="135053">
        <title>Haute école des arts de Zurich</title>
        <uri>http://www.zhdk.ch</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="135054">
        <title>Haute école des arts de Zurich, "Birdly"</title>
        <uri>http://viad.zhdk.ch/de/projects/birdly</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="135055">
        <title>École polytechnique fédérale de Lausanne</title>
        <uri>http://www.epfl.ch</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions>
        <revision date="2015-04-17 09:00" type="R"/>
      </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>La presidente della Confederazione e il suo omologo francese François Hollande in visita a Zurigo e Losanna</title>
      <lead>Lo sviluppo sostenibile, il sistema di formazione duale, la cooperazione economica tra la Svizzera e la Francia e gli scambi culturali sono i temi che hanno segnato la seconda giornata della visita di Stato del presidente francese François Hollande. La presidente della Confederazione Simonetta Sommaruga e il suo omologo si sono recati nel distretto di Affoltern e successivamente a Zurigo e a Losanna.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;All’inizio della giornata la Presidente della Confederazione e il Presidente francese hanno visitato la Ernst Schweizer AG, un’impresa a conduzione familiare con sede nella regione di Zurigo che produce, tra le altre cose, tetti a energia solare e si occupa della formazione di 46 apprendisti. L’impresa ha fatto dello sviluppo sostenibile il suo obiettivo principale. Durante la visita all’area industriale gli ospiti si sono intrattenuti con alcuni apprendisti e con rappresentanti del settore delle energie pulite.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In seguito, la presidente della Confederazione Sommaruga e il presidente Hollande hanno incontrato alcuni operatori culturali presso l’Università delle arti di Zurigo (ZHdK). In occasione della visita la ZHdK, una delle principali scuole d’arte europee, ha presentato progetti innovativi che permettono ai vari ambiti della società di interagire: "The Sound of Trees" vuole far sentire come gli alberi reagiscono ai cambiamenti climatici; l’installazione "Birdly" simula il volo degli uccelli basandosi sull’abbinamento sensori-motore. Nei successivi colloqui con gli esponenti dell’economia svizzera è emerso che l’obiettivo principale è di rafforzare la competitività, lo sviluppo sostenibile e la cooperazione tra i due Paesi, ottimizzando le condizioni quadro economiche.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Scienza e innovazione nella Svizzera occidentale&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/b&gt;All’insegna del motto "Diversités de la Suisse", la Presidente della Confederazione e il Presidente francese hanno incontrato, durante il tragitto in treno tra Zurigo e Losanna, alcuni esponenti del mondo politico, culturale e scientifico per un pranzo e uno scambio informale. Nel pomeriggio le delegazioni hanno visitato l’Innovation Park del Politecnico federale di Losanna (PFL). Visitando Logitech e alcune giovani imprese, i due presidenti hanno potuto constatare la dinamicità del parco dell’innovazione e la stretta collaborazione esistente tra aziende innovative e scienza. In seguito, Simonetta Sommaruga e François Hollande si sono intrattenuti con alcuni studenti del PFL rispondendo alle loro domande. Oltre il 20 per cento degli studenti e oltre il 10 per cento del corpo insegnante del PFL proviene dalla Francia. La visita di Stato si è conclusa con una passeggiata sul lungolago di Ouchy, sulla riva svizzera del lago Lemano, dove durante la sua infanzia François Hollande ha trascorso alcuni periodi di vacanza.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Servizio informazioni DFGP, +41 (0)58 462 18 18</contact>
      <link id="135056">
        <title>Università delle arti di Zurigo</title>
        <uri>http://www.zhdk.ch</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="135057">
        <title>Università delle arti di Zurigo, "Birdly"</title>
        <uri>http://viad.zhdk.ch/de/projects/birdly</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="135058">
        <title>Politecnico federale di Losanna</title>
        <uri>http://www.epfl.ch</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions>
        <revision date="2015-04-17 09:00" type="R"/>
      </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>President Sommaruga travels to Zurich and Lausanne with President Hollande</title>
      <lead>The second day of the state visit by President François Hollande was influenced by the themes of sustainable development, dual-track vocational education and training, economic cooperation between Switzerland and France and cultural exchanges. President Simonetta Sommaruga and her guest travelled to the district of Affoltern before moving on to Zurich and Lausanne.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;At the beginning of the day, the two presidents visited Ernst Schweizer AG, a family-run business in the Zurich region, which manufactures solar panels and trains 46 apprentices. The firm has declared sustainable development to be its core principle. During the tour of the factory, the guests spoke with apprentices and representatives from the cleantech industry.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;At Zurich University of the Arts (ZHdK) President Sommaruga and President Hollande met a number of creative artists. The programme put on for the guests by the ZHdK, one of Europe's largest arts schools, featured innovative projects which transcend various social issues: ‘The Sound of Trees' renders audible how trees react to climate change, while the ‘Birdly' installation simulates bird flight using sensory and motor coupling controls. During the talks with leading Swiss business representatives that followed, the focus was on strengthening competitiveness and sustainability and cooperation between the two countries by optimising the economic framework.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;/p&gt; &lt;h3&gt;Science and innovation in western Switzerland&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt; On the train from Zurich to Lausanne, the two presidents took lunch and shared an informal exchange with political actors and representatives from politics, culture and science under the motto of ‘Diversités de la Suisse'. In the afternoon, the delegations visited the Innovation Park at the École polytechnique fédérale de Lausanne (EPFL) where they were able to appreciate the dynamic environment provided by the Innovation Park and see how innovative businesses such as Logitech and start-ups work hand in hand with scientists. President Sommaruga and President Hollande then spoke with EPFL students and answered their questions. Over 20 per cent of students and 10 per cent of EPFL teaching staff are from France. The state visit concluded with a stroll by the shore of Lake Geneva in Ouchy, where François Hollande spent a number of childhood holidays. &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>FDJP Information Service, +41 (0)58 462 18 18</contact>
      <link id="135059">
        <title>Zurich University of the Arts</title>
        <uri>http://www.zhdk.ch/</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="135060">
        <title>Zurich University of the Arts: Research project Birdly</title>
        <uri>http://viad.zhdk.ch/de/projects/birdly</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="135061">
        <title>École polytechnique fédérale de Lausanne</title>
        <uri>http://www.epfl.ch/</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="10">
        <name lang="de">Bundesrat</name>
        <name lang="fr">Conseil fédéral</name>
        <name lang="it">Consiglio federale</name>
        <name lang="en">Federal Council</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="33">
        <name lang="de">Bundespräsident/-in</name>
        <name lang="fr">Président/e de la Confédération</name>
        <name lang="it">Presidente della Confederazione</name>
        <name lang="en">President of the Swiss Confederation</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
