<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="55438" revoked="no">
    <version>2</version>
    <pubdate>2014-11-28</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="1070" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>1070</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Der Bundesrat</name>
      <name lang="fr">Conseil fédéral</name>
      <name lang="it">Il Consiglio federale</name>
      <name lang="en">The Federal Council</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.admin.ch/gov/de/start.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.admin.ch/gov/fr/accueil.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.admin.ch/gov/it/pagina-iniziale.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.admin.ch/gov/en/start.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="804" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>801</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Generalsekretariat UVEK</name>
      <name lang="fr">Secrétariat général DETEC</name>
      <name lang="it">Segreteria generale DATEC</name>
      <name lang="en">General Secretariat of the Federal Department of Environment, Transport, Energy and Communications; General Secretariat DETEC</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.uvek.admin.ch/uvek/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.uvek.admin.ch/uvek/fr/home.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.uvek.admin.ch/uvek/it/home.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.uvek.admin.ch/uvek/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-uvek.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-uvek.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-uvek.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-uvek.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="810" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>801</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Bundesamt für Kommunikation</name>
      <name lang="fr">Office fédéral de la communication</name>
      <name lang="it">Ufficio federale delle comunicazioni</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Office of Communications</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.bakom.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.ofcom.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.ufcom.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.ofcom.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">media@bakom.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">media@bakom.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">media@bakom.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">media@bakom.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="1070">
      <name lang="de">Der Bundesrat</name>
      <name lang="fr">Conseil fédéral</name>
      <name lang="it">Il Consiglio federale</name>
      <name lang="en">The Federal Council</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.admin.ch/gov/de/start.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.admin.ch/gov/fr/accueil.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.admin.ch/gov/it/pagina-iniziale.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.admin.ch/gov/en/start.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <department id="801">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Umwelt, Verkehr, Energie und Kommunikation</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'environnement, des transports, de l'énergie et de la communication</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'ambiente, dei trasporti, dell'energia e delle comunicazioni</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of the Environment, Transport, Energy and Communications</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.uvek.admin.ch/uvek/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.uvek.admin.ch/uvek/fr/home.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.uvek.admin.ch/uvek/it/home.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.uvek.admin.ch/uvek/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-uvek.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-uvek.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-uvek.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-uvek.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Gebühren für Radio und Fernsehen bleiben unverändert</title>
      <lead>Die Höhe der Gebühren für den Radio- und Fernsehempfang bleibt bis zum Inkrafttreten des neuen Abgabesystems unverändert. Nach dem heutigen Entscheid des Bundesrates werden somit private Haushalte voraussichtlich bis 2018 weiterhin 462 Franken pro Jahr bezahlen müssen. Auch für den gewerblichen und den kommerziellen Empfang bleiben die Gebühren gleich. Die letzte Gebührenerhöhung datiert vom April 2007.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Der Bundesrat überprüft in der Regel alle vier Jahre, ob die Höhe der Radio- und Fernsehempfangsgebühren noch angemessen ist. Der Ertrag der Empfangsgebühren dient insbesondere dazu, die Erfüllung des SRG-Leistungsauftrags zu finanzieren. Die privaten Veranstalter (Lokalradios, Regionalfernsehen) sowie die Nutzungsforschung, die Förderung von neuen Technologien, das BAKOM und die Billag erhalten ebenfalls einen Gebührenanteil. Für die kommenden Jahre bis zum Inkrafttreten des neuen Abgabesystems bleibt die Höhe der Empfangsgebühren unverändert.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Das Parlament hat in der vergangenen Herbstsession eine Revision des Radio- und Fernsehgesetzes (RTVG) beschlossen. Dagegen ist aber das Referendum lanciert worden. Die Gesetzesänderung hätte die Einführung eines neuen Abgabesystems zur Folge, das vor­aussichtlich auf Anfang 2019 zu einer spürbaren Senkung der Radio- und Fernsehgebühren für private Haushalte führen würde. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Nach dem Willen des Parlaments sollen mit den Abgaben für Radio und Fernsehen zusätzliche Aufgaben finanziert werden: So kann der Anteil privater konzessionierter Radio- und Fernsehstationen an den Gebühren bis auf 6 Prozent erhöht werden (heute 4 Prozent), die Förderung neuer Technologien wird verbessert und die Untertitelung für sinnesbehinderte Personen bei regionalen TV-Stationen sowie die Rundfunkarchivierung werden künftig aus Gebührengeldern finanziert.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Der Bundesrat erwartet für die Jahre 2015 bis 2018 durchschnittlich 11 Millionen Franken mehr Gebühreneinnahmen pro Jahr, die auf die steigende Anzahl zahlender Haushalte zurückzuführen sind. Mit diesen Mehreinnahmen und mit bestehenden Gebührenüberschüssen aus früheren Jahren sollten bis zur Einführung des neuen Abgabesystems auch die sich aus der beschlossenen Gesetzesrevision zusätzlich ergebenden Aufgaben finanziert werden können.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Medienstelle BAKOM, Tel. +41 58 460 55 50</contact>
      <link id="153158">
        <title>Höhe und Verteilung der Empfangsgebühren</title>
        <uri>https://www.bakom.admin.ch/bakom/de/home/elektronische-medien/empfangsgebuehren/hoehe-und-verwendung-der-empfangsgebuehren.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="153159">
        <title>Teilrevision RTVG</title>
        <uri>https://www.bakom.admin.ch/bakom/de/home/das-bakom/organisation/rechtliche-grundlagen/bundesgesetze/rtvg-revision/teilrevision-des-radio-und-fernsehgesetzes.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>La redevance radio/TV reste inchangée</title>
      <lead>Le montant de la redevance pour la réception de programmes de radio et de télévision restera inchangé jusqu'à l'entrée en vigueur du nouveau système de perception. Avec la décision prise aujourd'hui par le Conseil fédéral, les ménages privés continueront à payer 462 francs par année probablement jusqu'en 2018. Pas de changement non plus du côté de la redevance pour la réception à titre professionnel ou commercial. La dernière augmentation de la redevance date d'avril 2007.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Le Conseil fédéral réexamine en règle générale tous les quatre ans si le montant de la redevance pour la réception de programmes de radio et de télévision est toujours adéquat. Le produit de la redevance sert principalement à financer l'exécution du mandat de prestations de la SSR. Une partie est également allouée aux diffuseurs privés (radios locales, télévisions régionales), à la fondation pour les études d'audience, à l'encouragement des nouvelles technologies, à l'OFCOM et à Billag. Le montant de la redevance restera inchangé pendant les prochaines années, jusqu'à l'entrée en vigueur d'un nouveau système de perception.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Au cours de la dernière session d'automne, le Parlement a adopté une révision de la loi sur la radio et la télévision (LRTV). Un référendum a été lancé contre cette révision. La modification de la loi aurait permis l'introduction d'un nouveau système de redevance, qui aurait entraîné une baisse sensible du montant de la redevance radio/TV pour les ménages privés, probablement dès début 2019. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Conformément à la volonté du Parlement, la redevance radio/TV doit financer des tâches supplémentaires. La quote-part attribuée aux radios et télévisions privées titulaires d'une concession peut être augmentée jusqu'à 6% (contre 4% actuellement), l'encouragement des nouvelles technologies est amélioré et sur les télévisions régionales, le sous-titrage pour les personnes handicapées sensorielles est financé à l'avenir par le produit de la redevance, tout comme l'archivage audiovisuel.&lt;/p&gt;Le Conseil fédéral s'attend à une augmentation du produit de la redevance de 11 millions de francs par année en moyenne pour les années 2015 à 2018, due au nombre croissant de ménages assujettis. Ces recettes supplémentaires ainsi que les excédents des années précédentes permettront de financer également les tâches supplémentaires résultant de la révision de la loi.</text>
      <contact>Service de presse OFCOM, Tél. +41 58 460 55 50</contact>
      <link id="153160">
        <title>Montant et utilisation de la redevance de réception</title>
        <uri>https://www.bakom.admin.ch/bakom/fr/page-daccueil/medias-electroniques/redevance-de-reception/montant-et-utilisation-de-la-redevance-de-reception.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="153161">
        <title>Révision partielle de la LRTV</title>
        <uri>https://www.bakom.admin.ch/bakom/fr/page-daccueil/l-ofcom/organisation/bases-legales/bundesgesetze/revision-lrtv/revision-partielle-de-la-loi-sur-la-radio-et-la-television--lrtv.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>I canoni di ricezione radiotelevisiva rimangono invariati</title>
      <lead>L'importo del canone di ricezione radiotelevisiva rimarrà invariato fino all'entrata in vigore del nuovo sistema dei canoni. In data odierna, il Consiglio federale ha deciso di continuare a far pagare alle economie domestiche private 462 franchi l'anno fino al 2018. Anche per la ricezione a utilizzo professionale o commerciale, l'importo non subirà cambiamenti. L'ultimo aumento del canone risale all'aprile 2007. </lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Il Consiglio federale verifica di norma ogni quattro anni se l'importo dei canoni di ricezione radiotelevisiva è appropriato. I proventi dei canoni servono in particolare a finanziare l'adempimento del mandato di prestazioni della SSR. Beneficiano di una parte di questi proventi anche le emittenti private (radio locali, tv regionali), la ricerca sull'utenza, la promozione di nuove tecnologie, l'UFCOM e la Billag. Per i prossimi anni, fino all'entrata in vigore del nuovo sistema, l'importo dei canoni di ricezione radiotelevisiva rimarrà invariato. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Nella passata sessione autunnale, il Parlamento ha approvato una revisione della legge sulla radiotelevisione (LRTV). Contro questa decisione è stato indetto un referendum. La modifica di legge prevedrebbe l'introduzione di un nuovo sistema che porterebbe a una sensibile diminuzione dell'importo del canone per le economie domestiche private, presumibilmente all'inizio del 2019. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Secondo la volontà del Parlamento, il canone radiotelevisivo dovrà servire a finanziare ulteriori misure. In questo modo, la quota di partecipazione al canone delle emittenti radiotelevisive private concessionarie potrà essere aumentata fino al 6 per cento (contro l'attuale 4 per cento) e sarà migliorata la promozione delle nuove tecnologie. Anche il sottotitolaggio dei programmi televisivi regionali per persone affette da deficienze sensorie e l'archiviazione dei programmi saranno finanziati in futuro con i proventi del canone.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Per il periodo 2015-2018, il Consiglio federale prevede una crescita media dei proventi del canone pari a 11 milioni di franchi l'anno, per effetto del crescente aumento del numero di economie domestiche soggette all'obbligo di pagamento. Questo incremento e le attuali eccedenze dei proventi degli anni passati dovrebbero permettere, fino all'introduzione del nuovo sistema, di finanziare anche le ulteriori misure derivanti dall'approvata revisione di legge. &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Servizio stampa UFCOM, Tel. +41 58 460 55 50</contact>
      <link id="153162">
        <title>Importo e ripartizione dei canoni di ricezione</title>
        <uri>https://www.bakom.admin.ch/bakom/it/pagina-iniziale/media-elettronici/tasse-di-ricezione/importo-e-impiego-delle-tasse-di-ricezione.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="153163">
        <title>Revisione parziale della LRTV</title>
        <uri>https://www.bakom.admin.ch/bakom/it/pagina-iniziale/l-ufcom/organizzazione/basi-legali/leggi-federali/modifica-della-lrtv/revisione-parziale-della-legge-sulla-radiotelevisione--lrtv---nu.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Fees for radio and television remain unchanged</title>
      <lead>The fees for receiving radio and television programme services will remain unchanged until the entry into force of the new universal fee system. After the Federal Council’s decision today, private households will continue to pay CHF 462 per year until introduction of the new fee system, expected in 2018. The fees for professional and commercial reception also remain unchanged. The last fee increase occurred in April 2007.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;As a rule, every four years the Federal Council reviews whether the level of the radio and TV reception fee is still appropriate. The fee revenue is used in particular to finance fulfilment of the SRG's performance mandate. A proportion of fee revenue supports private broadcasters (local radio stations, regional television stations), usage research and the promotion of new technologies, and OFCOM and the collection agency Billag also receive a share. The level of the reception fee will remain unchanged until the entry into force of the new universal fee system.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In its recent autumn session, Parliament decided on a revision of the Radio and Television Act (LRTA). However, a referendum was launched against the revision. The legislative change would see the introduction of a new universal fee system, which is expected to lead to an appreciable reduction in the radio and television licence fees for private households from early 2019.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Parliament intends to use radio and television fee revenue to finance additional tasks in the future: increasing support to private licensed radio and television stations from today's 4% to 6%, improved promotion of new technologies, subtitling on regional TV stations for people with sensory disabilities and the archiving of broadcasting.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;For the years 2015 to 2018 the Federal Council expects an average annual increase in fee revenue of CHF 11 million due to the increasing number of households paying fees. This additional income and fee surpluses from previous years means that it should be possible to fund the additional tasks arising from the adopted revision until the introduction of the new universal fee system.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Media Service OFCOM, Tel. +41 58 460 55 50</contact>
      <link id="153164">
        <title>Amount and use of reception fees</title>
        <uri>https://www.bakom.admin.ch/bakom/en/homepage/electronic-media/reception-fees/amount-and-use-of-reception-fees.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="153165">
        <title>Partial revision RTVA [only available in German, French and Italian]</title>
        <uri>https://www.bakom.admin.ch/bakom/de/home/das-bakom/organisation/rechtliche-grundlagen/bundesgesetze/rtvg-revision/teilrevision-des-radio-und-fernsehgesetzes.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <offers>
      <offer id="66" org-id="810">
        <name lang="de">Medienmitteilungen Medien</name>
        <name lang="fr">Communiqués de presse Médias</name>
        <name lang="it">Comunicati stampa Media</name>
        <name lang="en">Press releases Media</name>
      </offer>
    </offers>
    <keywords>
      <keyword id="210" org-id="810">
        <name lang="de">Bundesrat</name>
        <name lang="fr">Conseil fédéral</name>
        <name lang="it">Consiglio federale</name>
        <name lang="en">Federal Council</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="950" org-id="810">
        <name lang="de">Radio- und Fernsehen</name>
        <name lang="fr">Radio et télévision</name>
        <name lang="it">Radio e televisione</name>
        <name lang="en">Radio and television</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="970" org-id="810">
        <name lang="de">Radio- und Fernsehen: Empfangsgebühren</name>
        <name lang="fr">Radio et télévision : Redevance de réception</name>
        <name lang="it">Radio e televisione : Tasse di ricezione</name>
        <name lang="en">Radio and television :Reception fees</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="951" org-id="810">
        <name lang="de">Radio- und Fernsehen : Private Veranstalter</name>
        <name lang="fr">Radio et télévision : Diffuseurs privés</name>
        <name lang="it">Radio e televisione : emittenti private</name>
        <name lang="en">Radio and television: privat broadcaster</name>
      </keyword>
    </keywords>
    <topics>
      <topic id="19">
        <name lang="de">Medien</name>
        <name lang="fr">Médias</name>
        <name lang="it">Media</name>
        <name lang="en">Media</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="28">
        <name lang="de">Telekommunikation</name>
        <name lang="fr">Télécommunications</name>
        <name lang="it">Telecomunicazione</name>
        <name lang="en">Telecommunications</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="36">
        <name lang="de">Informatik und E-Government</name>
        <name lang="fr">Informatique et cyberadministration</name>
        <name lang="it">Informatica ed e-government</name>
        <name lang="en">IT and E-Government</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
