<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="84736" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2021-08-18</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="1070" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>1070</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Der Bundesrat</name>
      <name lang="fr">Conseil fédéral</name>
      <name lang="it">Il Consiglio federale</name>
      <name lang="en">The Federal Council</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.admin.ch/gov/de/start.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.admin.ch/gov/fr/accueil.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.admin.ch/gov/it/pagina-iniziale.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.admin.ch/gov/en/start.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="410" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>401</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Institut für Geistiges Eigentum</name>
      <name lang="fr">Institut Fédéral de la Propriété Intellectuelle</name>
      <name lang="it">Istituto Federale della Proprietà Intellettuale</name>
      <name lang="en">Swiss Federal Institute of Intellectual Property</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.ige.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.ige.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.ige.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.ige.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@ipi.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@ipi.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@ipi.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@ipi.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="401" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>401</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Justiz- und Polizeidepartement</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de justice et police</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale di giustizia e polizia</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Justice and Police</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.ejpd.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.ejpd.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.ejpd.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.ejpd.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-ejpd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">Info@gs-ejpd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-ejpd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-ejpd.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="1070">
      <name lang="de">Der Bundesrat</name>
      <name lang="fr">Conseil fédéral</name>
      <name lang="it">Il Consiglio federale</name>
      <name lang="en">The Federal Council</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.admin.ch/gov/de/start.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.admin.ch/gov/fr/accueil.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.admin.ch/gov/it/pagina-iniziale.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.admin.ch/gov/en/start.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <department id="401">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Justiz- und Polizeidepartement</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de justice et police</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale di giustizia e polizia</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Justice and Police</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.ejpd.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.ejpd.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.ejpd.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.ejpd.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-ejpd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">Info@gs-ejpd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-ejpd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-ejpd.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Schweizer Produzenten profitieren von besserem internationalen Schutz für geografische Angaben</title>
      <lead>Schweizer Produzenten können künftig geografische Angaben mit einem einfachen Verfahren in zahlreichen Staaten gleichzeitig zum Schutz anmelden. Der Bundesrat hat an seiner Sitzung vom 18. August 2021 die Inkraftsetzung der Genfer Akte des Lissabonner Abkommens über Ursprungsbezeichnungen und geografische Angaben sowie der Ausführungserlasse per 1. Dezember 2021 beschlossen.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Das Parlament hat die Genfer Akte des Lissabonner Abkommens über Ursprungsbezeichnungen und geografische Angaben sowie die Änderung des Markenschutzgesetzes am 19. März 2021 genehmigt. Mithilfe des Lissaboner Systems können Schweizer Begünstigte von Ursprungsbezeichnungen (z. B. Gruyère) und geografischen Angaben (z. B. Bündnerfleisch oder Swiss für Uhren) auf dem Staatsgebiet der Vertragsparteien einen hohen, zeitlich unbefristeten Schutz erwirken. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;In den Ausführungsverordnungen werden insbesondere die Bedingungen für die internationale Registrierung der schweizerischen Bezeichnungen und die Annahme oder Verweigerung der Wirksamkeit ausländischer internationaler Registrierungen in der Schweiz festgelegt. Die Einzelheiten dieser Verfahren sind in der Markenschutzverordnung (Art. 52p bis 52r MSchV) geregelt. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Die internationale Registrierung von schweizerischen Bezeichnungen sowie die Prüfung ausländischer internationaler Registrierungen durch das Eidgenössische Institut für Geistiges Eigentum (IGE) sind kostenlos. Legt ein Dritter beim IGE Widerspruch gegen die Wirksamkeit einer ausländischen internationalen Registrierung in der Schweiz ein, ist eine Gebühr von 800 Franken fällig. Die internationale Gebühr und die möglicherweise von anderen Vertragsparteien verlangten nationalen Gebühren werden direkt von der Weltorganisation für geistiges Eigentum (WIPO) erhoben.&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Felix Addor, Stellvertretender Direktor, Rechtskonsulent Eidgenössisches Institut für Geistiges Eigentum Direktwahl: +41 31 377 72 01</contact>
      <attachment id="219818">
        <title>Verordnung des IGE über Gebühren (GebV-IGE)</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>97</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/67840.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="219821">
        <title>Verordnung über den Schutz von Marken und Herkunftsangaben (MSchV)</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>137</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/67843.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Une meilleure protection internationale des indications géographiques pour les producteurs suisses</title>
      <lead>Les producteurs suisses pourront à l’avenir demander par une procédure simple la protection des indications géographiques dans de nombreux pays simultanément. Lors de sa séance du 18 août 2021, le Conseil fédéral a décidé que l’Acte de Genève de l’Arrangement de Lisbonne concernant les appellations d’origine et les indications géographiques, de même que les ordonnances d’exécution, entreront en vigueur le 1er décembre 2021.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Le Parlement a approuvé l'Acte de Genève de l'Arrangement de Lisbonne sur les appellations d'origine et les indications géographiques, ainsi que la modification de la loi sur les marques, le 19 mars 2021. Le système de Lisbonne permet aux bénéficiaires suisses d'appellations d'origine (par ex. : Gruyère) et d'indications géographiques (par ex. : Bündnerfleisch ou Swiss pour les montres) d'obtenir une protection élevée sur le territoire des parties contractantes pour une durée illimitée, au moyen d'un enregistrement unique.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;La législation de mise en œuvre fixe notamment les conditions pour l'enregistrement international des dénominations suisses et pour l'acceptation ou le refus des effets d'un enregistrement international étranger en Suisse. Les modalités de ces procédures sont détaillées dans l'ordonnance sur la protection des marques (art. 52p à 52r OPM).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;L'enregistrement international des dénominations suisses et l'examen des enregistrements internationaux étrangers par l'Institut Fédéral de la Propriété Intellectuelle (IPI) sont gratuits. L'opposition soulevée par un tiers contre les effets d'un enregistrement international étranger en Suisse est en revanche soumise à un émolument de 800 francs. L'émolument international et les émoluments nationaux éventuellement exigés par d'autres parties contractantes sont prélevés directement par l'Organisation Internationale de la Propriété Intellectuelle (OMPI).&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Felix Addor, directeur suppléant, jurisconsulte Institut Fédéral de la Propriété Intellectuelle Tél. direct : +41 31 377 72 01</contact>
      <attachment id="219819">
        <title>Ordonnance de l'IPI sur les taxes (OTa-IPI)</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>98</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/67841.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="219822">
        <title>Ordonnance sur la protection des marques et des indications de provenance (OPM)</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>117</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/67844.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>I produttori svizzeri beneficeranno di una migliore protezione internazionale delle indicazioni geografiche</title>
      <lead>In futuro una semplice procedura consentirà ai produttori svizzeri di registrare le indicazioni geografiche in diversi Paesi contemporaneamente. In occasione della sua seduta del 18 agosto 2021 il Consiglio federale ha deciso l’entrata in vigore dell’Atto di Ginevra dell’Accordo di Lisbona sulle denominazioni d’origine e le indicazioni geografiche e dei relativi atti esecutivi per il 1° dicembre 2021.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Il 19 marzo 2021 il Parlamento ha approvato l'Atto di Ginevra dell'Accordo di Lisbona sulle denominazioni d'origine e le indicazioni geografiche nonché la modifica della legge sulla protezione dei marchi. Il sistema di Lisbona consente ai beneficiari di denominazioni d'origine (p. es. "Gruyère") e indicazioni geografiche (p. es. "carne secca dei Grigioni" o "Swiss" per gli orologi) di ottenere una protezione di livello elevato senza limitazioni di tempo nel territorio degli Stati contraenti.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Negli atti esecutivi sono in particolare fissate le condizioni per la registrazione internazionale delle denominazioni svizzere e per l'adozione o il rifiuto degli effetti di registrazioni internazionali estere in Svizzera. I dettagli di queste procedure sono disciplinati nell'ordinanza sulla protezione dei marchi (artt. 52p-52r OPM).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;La registrazione internazionale di denominazioni svizzere nonché l'esame di registrazioni internazionali estere da parte dell'Istituto Federale della Proprietà Intellettuale (IPI) sono gratuiti. Per un'opposizione agli effetti di una registrazione internazionale estera in Svizzera dinanzi all'IPI è riscossa una tassa di 800 franchi. La tassa internazionale e le tasse nazionali eventualmente previste dagli altri Stati contraenti sono riscosse direttamente dall'Organizzazione Mondiale della Proprietà Intellettuale (OMPI).&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Felix Addor, sostituto direttore, consulente giuridico Istituto Federale della Proprietà Intellettuale Tel. diretto: +41 31 377 72 01</contact>
      <attachment id="219820">
        <title>Ordinanza dell'IPI sulle tasse (OTa-IPI)</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>91</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/67842.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="219823">
        <title>Ordinanza sulla protezione dei marchi e delle indicazioni di provenienza (OPM)</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>113</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/67845.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Swiss producers to benefit from better international protection for geographical indications</title>
      <lead>Swiss producers will in future be able to register geographical indications in several states simultaneously via a simple procedure. At its meeting on 18 August 2021, the Federal Council approved the entry into force of the Geneva Act of the Lisbon Agreement on Appellations of Origin and Geographical Indications as well as the implementing ordinances per 1 December 2021.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;On 19 March 2021, Parliament approved the Geneva Act of the Lisbon Agreement on Appellations of Origin and Geographical Indications and the amendment of the Trade Mark Protection Act. The Lisbon System enables Swiss beneficiaries of appellations of origin (e.g. Gruyère) and geographical indications (e.g. Bündnerfleisch or Swiss for watches) to obtain a high level of protection on the territory of the contracting parties for an unlimited period of time. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The implementing ordinances set out, in particular, the conditions for the international registration of Swiss denominations and for the acceptance or refusal of the effectiveness of foreign international registrations in Switzerland. The details of these procedures are outlined in the Trade Mark Protection Ordinance (Art. 52p to 52r TmPO). &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The international registration of Swiss denominations and the examination of foreign international registrations via the Swiss Federal Institute of Intellectual Property (IPI) are free of charge. However, if a third party files an opposition with the IPI against the effectiveness of a foreign international registration in Switzerland, a fee of 800 Swiss francs is to be paid. The international fee and any national fees which may be required by other contracting parties are directly levied by the World Intellectual Property Organization (WIPO).&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Felix Addor, Deputy Director General, Chief Legal Counsellor Swiss Federal Institute of Intellectual Property Direct line: +41 31 377 72 01</contact>
      <attachment id="219818">
        <title>Verordnung des IGE über Gebühren (GebV-IGE)</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>97</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/67840.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="219819">
        <title>Ordonnance de l'IPI sur les taxes (OTa-IPI)</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>98</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/67841.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="219820">
        <title>Ordinanza dell'IPI sulle tasse (OTa-IPI)</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>91</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/67842.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="219821">
        <title>Verordnung über den Schutz von Marken und Herkunftsangaben (MSchV)</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>137</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/67843.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="219822">
        <title>Ordonnance sur la protection des marques et des indications de provenance (OPM)</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>117</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/67844.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="219823">
        <title>Ordinanza sulla protezione dei marchi e delle indicazioni di provenienza (OPM)</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>113</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/67845.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <keywords>
      <keyword id="44" org-id="401">
        <name lang="de">Geistiges Eigentum</name>
        <name lang="fr">Propriété intellectuelle</name>
        <name lang="it">Proprietà intellettuale</name>
        <name lang="en">Intellectual property</name>
      </keyword>
    </keywords>
    <topics>
      <topic id="10">
        <name lang="de">Bundesrat</name>
        <name lang="fr">Conseil fédéral</name>
        <name lang="it">Consiglio federale</name>
        <name lang="en">Federal Council</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="26">
        <name lang="de">Recht</name>
        <name lang="fr">Droit</name>
        <name lang="it">Diritto</name>
        <name lang="en">Legal Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
