<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="84643" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2021-08-17</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="703" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>701</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Staatssekretariat für Wirtschaft</name>
      <name lang="fr">Secrétariat d'Etat à l'économie</name>
      <name lang="it">Segreteria di Stato dell'economia</name>
      <name lang="en">State Secretariat for Economic Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.seco.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.seco.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.seco.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.seco.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@seco.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@seco.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@seco.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@seco.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="701">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Wirtschaft, Bildung und Forschung</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'économie, de la formation et de la recherche</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'economia, della formazione e della ricerca</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Economic Affairs, Education and Research</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>EasyGov.swiss erweitert Angebot um Meldeverfahren für erwerbstätige Flüchtlinge und vorläufig Aufgenommene</title>
      <lead>Das Staatssekretariat für Wirtschaft (SECO) hat per 17. August 2021 EasyGov.swiss, den Online-Schalter für Unternehmen, erneut ausgebaut. Das Meldeverfahren bei einer Erwerbstätigkeit für vorläufig Aufgenommene und anerkannte Flüchtlinge (VA/Flü) steht neu online zur Verfügung. Weiter wurden die Betreibungsprozesse um Eingabemöglichkeiten für Fortsetzungs- und Verwertungsbegehren an die Betreibungsämter ergänzt.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Seit dem 1. Januar 2019 können vorläufig Aufgenommene und anerkannte Flüchtlinge nach einer Meldung an die Arbeitsmarktbehörden eine Erwerbstätigkeit aufnehmen. Das verschafft ihnen leichteren Zugang zum Arbeitsmarkt und entlastet die Arbeitgeber. Damit wird das inländische Arbeitskräftepotenzial besser genutzt und Ausgaben für die Sozialhilfe reduziert. Mit dem neu digitalisierten Meldeverfahren über EasyGov wird der Prozess der Meldung für Arbeitgeber weiter vereinfacht.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Der Prozess VA/Flü bildet die erste Etappe der Integration von ausländerrechtlichen Meldungen und Bewilligungen zur Ausübung einer Erwerbstätigkeit auf EasyGov und steht Arbeitgebern in allen 26 Kantonen zur Verfügung. Ende 2017 wurde eine Arbeitsgruppe eingesetzt, welcher Vertreter des Staatssekretariats für Migration (SEM), der Vereinigung kantonaler Migrationsbehörden (VKM), des Verbands Schweizerischer Arbeitsmarktbehörden (VSAA) und des SECO angehören. Im Rahmen dieser Arbeiten wurden fünf Pilotkantone (Aargau, Basel-Stadt, St. Gallen, Thurgau und Zürich) definiert, die sich gemeinsam mit dem SEM und dem SECO am weiteren Ausbau von ausländerrechtlichen Meldungen und Bewilligungen auf EasyGov beteiligen.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In den nächsten Jahren sind weitere Ausbauschritte für verschiedene Kategorien von Arbeitsbewilligungen mit den fünf Pilotkantonen (AG, BS, SG, TG und ZH) geplant. Bereits in der ersten Hälfte 2022 soll die Abwicklung von Grenzgänger-Bewilligungen für EU/EFTA-Staatsangehörige auf dem Portal bereitgestellt werden. Danach folgen Bewilligungen für Erwerbstätige aus Drittstaaten und in einem nächsten Schritt weitere Arbeitsbewilligungskategorien wie z. B. Entsendungen. Das Fernziel besteht darin, den Melde- und Bewilligungsprozess in allen 26 Kantonen zu erleichtern.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Betreibung: Mehr Funktionen&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;br /&gt;Seit zwei Jahren können Unternehmen und Privatpersonen Begehren an die Betreibungsämter auf EasyGov einreichen. Das Angebot wird seither laufend ausgebaut und optimiert. Mit dem aktuellen Update sind nun auch Eingabemöglichkeiten für Fortsetzungs- und Verwertungsbegehren sowie allgemeine Eingaben an die Ämter möglich. EasyGov schliesst mit diesem Ausbauschritt eine Service-Lücke, die seit der Abschaltung des Betreibungsschalters des Bundesamtes für Justiz Anfang 2020 bestand.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Leistungsumfang von EasyGov.swiss Version 1.8:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;https://aktuell.easygov.swiss&lt;br /&gt;www.EasyGov.swiss&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Staatssekretariat für Wirtschaft SECO Holzikofenweg 36 CH-3003 Bern Tel. +41 58 462 56 56 Fax +41 58 462 56 00</contact>
      <link id="219473">
        <title>https://aktuell.easygov.swiss</title>
        <uri>https://bit.ly/32OhmXD</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="219474">
        <title>www.EasyGov.swiss</title>
        <uri>https://bit.ly/3dZg5n3</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>EasyGov.swiss élargit l’offre de procédures d’annonce pour les réfugiés et personnes</title>
      <lead>Le Secrétariat d’État à l’économie (SECO) a de nouveau étoffé Easygov.swiss, le guichet en ligne pour les entreprises, le 17 août 2021. La procédure d’annonce d’une activité lucrative est désormais disponible en ligne pour les personnes admises à titre provisoire et les réfugiés reconnus (AP-réf.). Par ailleurs, les procédures de poursuite ont été complétées avec les options de saisie pour les réquisitions de continuer la poursuite et les réquisitions de vente auprès des offices des poursuites.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Depuis le 1er janvier 2019, les personnes admises à titre provisoire et les réfugiés reconnus peuvent exercer une activité lucrative après s’être annoncés auprès des offices du travail, ce qui facilite l’accès au marché du travail de cette catégorie de population mais aussi soulage les employeurs. Cette possibilité permet également de mieux utiliser le potentiel de main-d’œuvre suisse et de réduire les dépenses de l’aide sociale. Avec la nouvelle procédure d’annonce dématérialisée sur EasyGov, le processus d’annonce est encore simplifié pour les employeurs.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Première étape de l’intégration sur EasyGov des annonces et autorisations d’exercer une activité lucrative relevant du droit des étrangers, le processus AP-réf. est mis à la disposition des employeurs dans l’ensemble des 26 cantons. Fin 2017, un groupe de travail a été créé, regroupant des représentants du Secrétariat d’État aux migrations (SEM), de l’Association des services cantonaux de migration (ASM), de l’Association des offices suisses du travail (AOST) et du SECO. Dans le cadre de ses travaux, cinq cantons pilotes ont été définis (Argovie, Bâle-Ville, Saint-Gall, Thurgovie et Zurich) et ont participé, conjointement avec le SEM et le SECO, à développer les annonces et autorisations relevant du droit des étrangers sur EasyGov.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;D’autres étapes de développement sont prévues dans les années à venir avec les cinq cantons pilotes (AG, BS, SG, TG et ZH) pour les différentes catégories d’autorisation de travail. Les autorisations relatives aux transfrontaliers pour les ressortissants UE/AELE devraient ainsi être mises à disposition sur le portail dès le premier semestre 2022. Elles seront suivies des autorisations pour les personnes exerçant une activité lucrative et originaires d’États tiers et à une étape ultérieure, par d’autres catégories d’autorisations de travail telles que les détachements. L’objectif final consiste à faciliter les procédures d’annonce et d’autorisation dans l’ensemble des 26 cantons.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Poursuites : davantage de fonctionnalités&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;br /&gt;Depuis deux ans, les entreprises et les particuliers peuvent déposer des réquisitions auprès des offices des poursuites sur EasyGov. Depuis lors, cette offre n’a cessé d’être développée et optimisée. La version actuelle permet désormais de procéder à des options de saisie pour les réquisitions de continuer la poursuite et les réquisitions de vente ainsi qu’à des saisies d’ordre général. Grâce à cette nouvelle mise à jour, EasyGov comble une lacune de service qui résultait de la fermeture du portail des poursuites de l’Office fédéral de la justice début 2020.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Étendue des prestations de la version 1.8 d’EasyGov.swiss&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;https://actuel.easygov.swiss&lt;br /&gt;https://www.easygov.swiss/easygov/#/fr&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Secrétariat d'Etat à l'économie SECO Holzikofenweg 36 CH-3003 Berne tél. +41 58 462 56 56 fax +41 58 462 56 00</contact>
      <link id="219475">
        <title>https://actuel.easygov.swiss</title>
        <uri>https://bit.ly/3sV7eH4</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="219476">
        <title>www.easygov.swiss</title>
        <uri>https://bit.ly/2QqgOoh</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>EasyGov.swiss amplia l’offerta di procedure di notifica per rifugiati e persone ammesse provvisoriamente che esercitano un’attività lucrativa</title>
      <lead>Dal 17 agosto 2021, la Segreteria di Stato dell’economia (SECO) offre una versione ulteriormente ampliata del proprio sportello online per le imprese, EasyGov.swiss. Ora è disponibile online la procedura di notifica di un’attività lucrativa per le persone ammesse provvisoriamente e i rifugiati riconosciuti (AP/RIF). Inoltre, i processi di esecuzione prevedono la possibilità di inserire domande di continuazione dell’esecuzione e di realizzazione destinate agli uffici d’esecuzione.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Dal 1° gennaio 2019 le persone ammesse provvisoriamente e i rifugiati riconosciuti possono esercitare un’attività lucrativa previa notifica alle autorità preposte al mercato del lavoro. Questa soluzione agevola l’accesso al mercato del lavoro per i diretti interessati e sgrava i datori di lavoro. In tal modo è possibile sfruttare meglio il potenziale di lavoratori residenti e ridurre le spese per l’aiuto sociale. La nuova procedura di notifica digitalizzata tramite EasyGov semplifica le operazioni per i datori di lavoro.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Il processo AP/RIF, disponibile per i datori di lavoro in tutti e 26 i Cantoni, rappresenta la prima tappa dell’integrazione su EasyGov di notifiche e permessi del diritto in materia di stranieri per l’esercizio di un’attività lucrativa. A fine 2017 è stato istituito un gruppo di lavoro composto da rappresentanti della Segreteria di Stato della migrazione (SEM), dell’Associazione dei servizi cantonali di migrazione (ASM), dell’Associazione degli uffici svizzeri del lavoro (AUSL) e della SECO. Nell’ambito di questi lavori sono stati definiti cinque Cantoni pilota (Argovia, Basilea Città, San Gallo, Turgovia e Zurigo) che collaborano insieme alla SEM e alla SECO per potenziare l’integrazione di notifiche e permessi del diritto in materia di stranieri su EasyGov.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Nei prossimi anni sono previsti ulteriori ampliamenti per diverse categorie di permessi di lavoro, sempre con i cinque Cantoni pilota (AG, BS, SG, TG e ZH). Già nella prima metà del 2022 si prevede di attivare sul portale la procedura relativa ai permessi per frontalieri per cittadini UE/AELS. Seguiranno poi i permessi per lavoratori di Stati terzi e in una fase successiva anche ulteriori categorie di permessi, come quelli per i lavoratori distaccati. L’obiettivo a lungo termine è quello di semplificare il processo di notifica e autorizzazione in tutti e 26 i Cantoni.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Più funzioni per l’esecuzione&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;br /&gt;Da due anni, imprese e privati possono presentare le proprie richieste agli uffici d’esecuzione su EasyGov. L’offerta viene ampliata e ottimizzata costantemente. Con l’attuale aggiornamento vi è anche la possibilità di inserire domande di continuazione dell’esecuzione e di realizzazione nonché istanze generiche destinate agli uffici. Grazie a questo potenziamento, EasyGov colma una lacuna nei servizi insorta all’inizio del 2020, quando è stato abolito lo sportello delle esecuzioni dell’Ufficio federale di giustizia.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Gamma di servizi di EasyGov.swiss versione 1.8:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;https://attualita.easygov.swiss&lt;br /&gt;www.EasyGov.swiss&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Segreteria di Stato dell'economia SECO Holzikofenweg 36 CH-3003 Berna tel. +41 58 462 56 56 fax +41 58 462 56 00</contact>
      <link id="219477">
        <title>https://attualita.easygov.swiss</title>
        <uri>https://bit.ly/3dWePkc</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="219478">
        <title>www.EasyGov.swiss</title>
        <uri>http://www.easygov.ch/easygov</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>EasyGov.swiss expands offering to include reporting procedure for employed refugees and temporarily admitted persons</title>
      <lead>As of 17 August 2021, the Swiss State Secretariat for Economic Affairs (SECO) has once again expanded EasyGov.swiss, its online service desk for companies. The employment reporting procedure for temporarily admitted persons and recognised refugees is now available online. The debt enforcement processes have also been expanded to include options to submit requests to continue debt enforcement proceedings and sale requests to the debt enforcement offices.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Since 1 January 2019, temporarily admitted persons and recognised refugees have been able to take up employment after a report has been submitted to the labour market authorities. This provides them with easier access to the labour market and reduces the burden on employers, better utilising the potential of the domestic workforce and reducing the cost to the welfare state. The newly digitalised reporting procedure on EasyGov makes the reporting process even simpler for employers.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This process for temporarily admitted persons and refugees constitutes the first stage of integrating reports and permits to pursue employment under the law on foreign nationals on EasyGov and is available to employers in all 26 cantons. At the end of 2017, a working group was established consisting of representatives from the State Secretariat for Migration (SEM), Association of Cantonal Migration Services (VKM), Association of Swiss Labour Market Authorities (VSAA) and SECO. In the course of this work, five pilot cantons (Aargau, Basel Stadt, St. Gallen, Thurgau and Zurich) were chosen to work together with the SEM and SECO on further expanding reports and permits under the law on foreign nationals on Easy-Gov.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;There are other steps planned for expanding the different categories of work permits in the five pilot cantons (AG, BS, SG, TG and ZH) over the next few years. In the first half of 2022, the processing of cross-border commuter permits for EU/EFTA citizens will already be available on the portal. After that, there will be permits for working people from third countries and a further step will entail creating more categories of work permit such as work postings. The long-term goal is to simplify the processes of submitting reports and obtaining permits in all 26 cantons.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Debt enforcement: more functions&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;br /&gt;For two years now, businesses and private individuals have been able to submit requests to debt enforcement offices using EasyGov. Since then, this service has been expanded and optimised on an ongoing basis. The latest update now also offers options to submit requests to continue debt enforcement proceedings and sale requests, as well as send general submissions, to the offices. With this stage of expansion, EasyGov is filling a gap in the services on offer which emerged after the debt enforcement service desk at the Swiss Federal Office of Justice closed at the beginning of 2020.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Services available with EasyGov.swiss Version 1.8:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;https://news.easygov.swiss&lt;br /&gt;www.EasyGov.swiss&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>State Secretariat for Economic Affairs SECO Holzikofenweg 36 CH-3003 Bern Tel. +41 58 462 56 56 Fax +41 58 462 56 00</contact>
      <link id="219479">
        <title>https://news.easygov.swiss</title>
        <uri>https://bit.ly/3eDGjdT</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="219480">
        <title>www.EasyGov.swiss</title>
        <uri>https://bit.ly/32OvW11</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="2">
        <name lang="de">Arbeit</name>
        <name lang="fr">Travail</name>
        <name lang="it">Lavoro</name>
        <name lang="en">Labour</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="47">
        <name lang="de">Wirtschaft</name>
        <name lang="fr">Économie</name>
        <name lang="it">Economia</name>
        <name lang="en">Economic Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
