<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="84733" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2021-08-18</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="1070" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>1070</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Der Bundesrat</name>
      <name lang="fr">Conseil fédéral</name>
      <name lang="it">Il Consiglio federale</name>
      <name lang="en">The Federal Council</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.admin.ch/gov/de/start.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.admin.ch/gov/fr/accueil.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.admin.ch/gov/it/pagina-iniziale.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.admin.ch/gov/en/start.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="410" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>401</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Institut für Geistiges Eigentum</name>
      <name lang="fr">Institut Fédéral de la Propriété Intellectuelle</name>
      <name lang="it">Istituto Federale della Proprietà Intellettuale</name>
      <name lang="en">Swiss Federal Institute of Intellectual Property</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.ige.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.ige.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.ige.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.ige.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@ipi.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@ipi.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@ipi.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@ipi.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="401" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>401</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Justiz- und Polizeidepartement</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de justice et police</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale di giustizia e polizia</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Justice and Police</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.ejpd.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.ejpd.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.ejpd.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.ejpd.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-ejpd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">Info@gs-ejpd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-ejpd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-ejpd.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="1070">
      <name lang="de">Der Bundesrat</name>
      <name lang="fr">Conseil fédéral</name>
      <name lang="it">Il Consiglio federale</name>
      <name lang="en">The Federal Council</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.admin.ch/gov/de/start.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.admin.ch/gov/fr/accueil.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.admin.ch/gov/it/pagina-iniziale.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.admin.ch/gov/en/start.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <department id="401">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Justiz- und Polizeidepartement</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de justice et police</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale di giustizia e polizia</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Justice and Police</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.ejpd.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.ejpd.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.ejpd.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.ejpd.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-ejpd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">Info@gs-ejpd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-ejpd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-ejpd.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Modernisierung des Patentprüfungsverfahrens</title>
      <lead>Der Bundesrat hat an seiner Sitzung vom 18. August 2021 die Vernehmlassungsergebnisse zur Teilrevision des Patentgesetzes zur Kenntnis genommen und über das weitere Vorgehen entschieden. In der Vernehmlassung wurde eine Modernisierung des Patentprüfungsverfahrens grundsätzlich begrüsst. Der Bundesrat hat beschlossen, der in einzelnen Bereichen geäusserten Kritik mit inhaltlichen Anpassungen der Vorlage Rechnung zu tragen. Er hat das Eidgenössische Justiz- und Polizeidepartement (EJPD) beauftragt, ihm bis Ende 2022 eine entsprechende Botschaft zu unterbreiten.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Mit der Teilrevision des Patentgesetzes, die der Bundesrat am 14. Oktober 2020 in die Vernehmlassung geschickt hatte, sollte vor allem der parlamentarische Auftrag erfüllt werden, eine Vollprüfung des Schweizer Patents und parallel dazu als ungeprüftes Schutzrecht das Gebrauchsmuster einzuführen (19.3228 Motion Hefti). Die Vernehmlassung ergab jedoch, dass eine "Entweder-oder"-Lösung - vollgeprüftes Patent oder Gebrauchsmuster - zu starr ist und eine flexible Patentprüfung gewünscht wird. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;h3&gt;Bewährtes "ungeprüftes" Schweizer Patent bleibt&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Gestützt auf die Vernehmlassung hält der Bundesrat an der Einführung eines vollgeprüften Patents fest. Er verzichtet hingegen auf die Einführung eines Gebrauchsmusters und möchte das heutige Patentsystem beibehalten, soweit es sich - gemäss Rückmeldung aus der Vernehmlassung - bewährt hat. Grundsätzlich wird deshalb eine Patentanmeldung wie bisher vom Eidgenössischen Institut für Geistiges Eigentum (IGE) nicht auf Neuheit und erfinderische Tätigkeit geprüft. Damit steht Erfinderinnen und Erfindern nach wie vor ein "ungeprüfter", jedoch kostengünstiger Schutztitel zur Verfügung - wie von der Motion gefordert. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;h3&gt;Flexible Patentprüfung - vollgeprüftes Schweizer Patent auf Antrag &lt;/h3&gt; &lt;p&gt;Neu soll es Erfinderinnen und Erfindern aber auch offenstehen, die Prüfung sämtlicher Patentierungsvoraussetzungen (v. a. Neuheit und erfinderische Tätigkeit) beim IGE zu beantragen. Ein solches vollgeprüftes Schweizer Patent ist insbesondere für KMU eine vollwertige Alternative zu einem vom Europäischen Patentamt (EPA) erteilten vollgeprüften und auf die Schweiz ausgedehnten europäischen Patent - ein Weg, der für KMU oft umständlich und teuer ist. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;h3&gt;Mehr Rechtssicherheit durch obligatorische Recherche &lt;/h3&gt; &lt;p&gt;Der Bundesrat möchte aber auch beim "ungeprüften" Schutztitel mehr Rechtssicherheit schaffen, wie dies mit der Motion und auch in der Vernehmlassung gefordert wurde. Daher soll neu jede Patentanmeldung durch eine obligatorische Recherche ergänzt werden. Der öffentliche Recherchebericht dokumentiert denjenigen Stand der Technik, von welchem sich die Erfindung genügend abheben muss. Aufgrund dieser Informationen lässt sich besser beurteilen, ob die Erfindung tatsächlich schutzfähig ist. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;h3&gt;Schlanker Rechtsmittelweg mit auf Patentsachen spezialisiertem Gericht &lt;/h3&gt; &lt;p&gt;Der Bundesrat will das Schweizer Patentsystem möglichst schlank ausgestalten und so eine attraktive Alternative zum europäischen Patent anbieten. Entscheide des IGE müssen auf Beschwerde hin durch ein Gericht überprüfbar sein. Diese Kontrolle soll in Zukunft direkt durch das Bundespatentgericht erfolgen. Dieses verfügt über die dafür notwendige, hohe technische Expertise. Auf das 2008 eingeführte Einspruchsverfahren soll ganz verzichtet werden. Es wurde bisher nie in Anspruch genommen.&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Alexander Pfister, Leiter Rechtsdienst Gewerbliche Schutzrechte Eidgenössisches Institut für Geistiges Eigentum IGE Direktwahl T +41 31 377 74 88 Esther Marchetti-Baumgartner, Rechtsdienst Gewerbliche Schutzrechte Eidgenössisches Institut für Geistiges Eigentum IGE Direktwahl T +41 31 377 72 64</contact>
      <attachment id="219851">
        <title>Vernehmlassungsergebnisse</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>676</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/67867.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Modernisation de la procédure d’examen des brevets</title>
      <lead>Lors de sa séance du 18 août 2021, le Conseil fédéral a pris acte des résultats de la procédure de consultation sur la révision partielle de la loi sur les brevets et arrêté les prochaines étapes. Les participants à la procédure se félicitent, sur le principe, d’une modernisation de la procédure d’examen des brevets. Le Conseil fédéral a décidé de tenir compte des critiques exprimées dans certains domaines et d’adapter le contenu de l’avant-projet. Il a chargé le Département fédéral de justice et police (DFJP) de lui soumettre un message d’ici fin 2022.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Le principal objectif de la révision partielle de la loi sur les brevets, que le Conseil fédéral a mise en consultation le 14 octobre 2020, était d'introduire un examen complet du brevet suisse et, parallèlement, de mettre en place un modèle d'utilité non examiné, comme le demande la motion Hefti (19.3228). Il ressort toutefois de la consultation que l'alternative entre brevet délivré après un examen complet et modèle d'utilité est trop rigide et qu'un examen flexible des brevets est souhaité. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;h3&gt;Maintien du brevet suisse "non examiné" qui a fait ses preuves &lt;b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/h3&gt; &lt;p&gt;Compte tenu des résultats de la consultation, le Conseil fédéral maintient l'idée d'instaurer un brevet entièrement examiné. Il abandonne par contre la proposition de créer un modèle d'utilité et désire conserver les éléments du système actuel des brevets qui ont fait leurs preuves selon les avis exprimés lors de la consultation. C'est pourquoi les demandes de brevet continueront de ne pas être examinées par l'Institut Fédéral de la Propriété Intellectuelle (IPI) du point de vue de la nouveauté et de l'activité inventive. Cela signifie pour les inventeurs qu'ils disposeront, comme par le passé, d'un titre de protection "non examiné", mais peu coûteux, comme le demande la motion. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;h3&gt;Examen flexible : un examen complet disponible sur demande &lt;/h3&gt; &lt;p&gt;Il est cependant prévu de donner aux inventeurs la possibilité de demander à l'IPI un examen de toutes les conditions de brevetabilité (en particulier la nouveauté et l'activité inventive). Le brevet suisse avec examen complet offre en particulier aux PME une réelle alternative au brevet européen délivré par l'Office européen des brevets (OEB), qui est entièrement examiné et qui produit effet en Suisse. Pour le PME en effet, la voie européenne est souvent trop complexe et trop onéreuse. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;h3&gt;Sécurité juridique accrue grâce à la recherche obligatoire &lt;/h3&gt; &lt;p&gt;Le Conseil fédéral souhaite toutefois accroître la sécurité juridique du titre de protection "non examiné", comme le demandent la motion et les avis exprimés lors de la consultation. C'est pourquoi il sera proposé qu'une recherche obligatoire soit effectuée pour toutes les nouvelles demandes de brevet. Le rapport de recherche rendu public documentera l'état de la technique dont l'invention doit suffisamment s'écarter. Sur la base de ces informations, il sera plus aisé d'évaluer si l'invention peut effectivement être admise à la protection. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;h3&gt;Voie de recours simplifiée avec un tribunal spécialisé en matière de brevets &lt;/h3&gt; &lt;p&gt;Le Conseil fédéral souhaite un système suisse des brevets aussi simple que possible afin d'offrir une alternative attrayante au brevet européen. Les décisions rendues par l'IPI doivent pouvoir faire l'objet d'un recours direct auprès d'une autorité judiciaire. Il sera proposé de donner au Tribunal fédéral des brevets la compétence en la matière puisqu'il dispose du haut niveau d'expertise technique nécessaire. Introduite en 2008, la procédure d'opposition, dont il n'a jamais été fait usage, doit être supprimée.&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Alexander Pfister, chef du service juridique Droits de propriété industrielle Institut Fédéral de la Propriété Intellectuelle (IPI) Tél. direct : +41 31 377 74 88 Esther Marchetti-Baumgartner, service juridique Droits de propriété industrielle Institut Fédéral de la Propriété Intellectuelle (IPI) Tél. direct : +41 31 377 72 64</contact>
      <attachment id="219852">
        <title>Résultats de la procédure de consultation</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>679</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/67868.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Modernizzazione della procedura d’esame del brevetto</title>
      <lead>In occasione della seduta del 18 agosto 2021, il Consiglio federale ha preso atto dei risultati della procedura di consultazione sulla revisione parziale della legge sui brevetti e ha deciso i prossimi lavori. Dalla consultazione emerge che una modernizzazione della procedura di esame del brevetto è generalmente accolta con favore. Il Consiglio federale ha deciso di tenere conto dei pareri espressi in singoli settori modificando il contenuto dell’avamprogetto. Ha incaricato il Dipartimento federale di giustizia e polizia (DFGP) di presentargli un corrispondente messaggio entro la fine del 2022.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;La revisione parziale della legge sui brevetti, che il Consiglio federale ha posto in consultazione il 14 ottobre 2020, doveva innanzitutto adempiere il mandato parlamentare di introdurre un esame completo del brevetto svizzero e, parallelamente, il modello d'utilità come titolo di protezione non esaminato (19.3228 Mozione Hefti). Dalla consultazione è tuttavia emerso che l'approccio "aut aut" (brevetto con esame completo o modello d'utilità) è troppo rigido e che si auspica una soluzione più flessibile. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;h3&gt;Resta il brevetto svizzero "non esaminato" &lt;b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/h3&gt; &lt;p&gt;Alla luce dell'esito della consultazione, il Consiglio federale sostiene l'introduzione di un brevetto svizzero con esame completo. Rinunciando per contro all'introduzione di un modello d'utilità, intende mantenere il sistema brevettuale attuale. In linea di principio, quindi, nel quadro dell'esame delle domande di brevetto, l'Istituto Federale della Proprietà Intellettuale (IPI) continuerà a non esaminare la novità e l'attività inventiva. Gli inventori continueranno quindi ad avere accesso a un titolo di protezione "non esaminato" ma poco costoso, come rivendicato dalla mozione. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;h3&gt;Esame flessibile dei brevetti - brevetto svizzero con esame completo su richiesta &lt;/h3&gt; &lt;p&gt;Si vuole comunque dare la possibilità agli inventori di chiedere all'IPI di esaminare tutte le condizioni di brevettabilità (in particolare la novità e l'attività inventiva). Un brevetto svizzero con esame completo di questo tipo è una valida alternativa, soprattutto per le PMI, al brevetto europeo con estensione alla Svizzera rilasciato dall'Ufficio europeo dei brevetti (UEB), più scomodo e costoso per le PMI. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;h3&gt;Maggiore certezza del diritto grazie alla ricerca obbligatoria &lt;/h3&gt; &lt;p&gt;In linea con la mozione e con i partecipanti alla consultazione, il Consiglio federale chiede una maggiore certezza del diritto anche nell'attuale procedura d'esame di un brevetto svizzero "non esaminato". Ogni domanda di brevetto sarà quindi in futuro integrata con una ricerca obbligatoria. Il rapporto di ricerca pubblico documenta lo stato della tecnica da cui l'invenzione deve distinguersi. Sulla base di queste informazioni è più facile valutare se l'invenzione è effettivamente proteggibile. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;h3&gt;Procedura di ricorso semplificata con un tribunale specializzato in materia di brevetti &lt;/h3&gt; &lt;p&gt;Il Consiglio federale intende snellire il più possibile il sistema brevettuale svizzero e offrire così un'alternativa interessante al brevetto europeo. Su ricorso, le decisioni dell'IPI devono poter essere riesaminate da un tribunale. In futuro, questo esame sarà effettuato direttamente dal Tribunale federale dei brevetti, che dispone delle necessarie competenze tecniche. Si intende rinunciare completamente alla procedura di opposizione introdotta nel 2008, cui finora non è mai stato fatto ricorso.&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Alexander Pfister, capo del Servizio giuridico Diritti di proprietà industriale Istituto Federale della Proprietà Intellettuale (IPI) Tel. diretto: +41 31 377 74 88 Esther Marchetti-Baumgartner, Servizio giuridico Diritti di proprietà industriale Istituto Federale della Proprietà Intellettuale (IPI) Tel. diretto: +41 31 377 72 64</contact>
      <attachment id="219853">
        <title>Risultati della procedura di consultazione</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>716</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/67869.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Modernising the patent examination procedure</title>
      <lead>The Federal Council acknowledged the results of the consultation on the partial revision of the Patents Act at its meeting of 18 August 2021 and decided on the further course of action. Modernising the patent examination procedure was, in principle, welcomed in the consultation. The Federal Council has decided to take into account the criticism voiced in individual areas by making adjustments to the contents of the draft bill. It has mandated the Federal Department of Justice and Police (FDJP) to submit a dispatch by the end of 2022.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;The partial revision of the Patents Act, which the Federal Council submitted for consultation on 14 October 2020, was aimed primarily at fulfilling the parliamentary mandate to introduce a fully examined Swiss patent together with a utility model as an unexamined IP right (19.3228 Hefti Motion). The consultation, however, revealed that an either-or solution - either a fully examined patent or a utility model - is too rigid, while a flexible patent examination is what is wanted. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;h3&gt;The tried and tested 'unexamined' Swiss patent is staying &lt;b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/h3&gt; &lt;p&gt;In view of the results of the consultation, the Federal Council continues to support the introduction of a fully examined patent. It decided, however, that a utility model will not be introduced and that it would like to keep the current patent system, to the extent that - according to feedback from the consultation - it has proved its worth. In general, a patent application will therefore still not be examined for novelty and inventive step by the Swiss Federal Institute of Intellectual Property (IPI). As a result, an 'unexamined' - but less expensive - IP right will continue to be available to inventors as called for by the motion. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;h3&gt;Flexible patent examination - fully examined Swiss patent on request &lt;/h3&gt; &lt;p&gt;In future, inventors should also be able to request that all patentability requirements are examined (in particular novelty and inventive step) by the IPI. Such a fully examined Swiss patent is, in particular, for SMEs a valuable alternative to a fully examined European patent granted by the European Patent Office (EPO) with protection extended to Switzerland - a path that is often laborious and expensive for an SME.&lt;b&gt; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h3&gt;More legal certainty with obligatory searches &lt;b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/h3&gt; &lt;p&gt;The Federal Council would also like to create more legal certainty for the 'unexamined' IP right, as was called for in both the motion and consultation. As a result, every patent application is to be supplemented with a compulsory patent search. The public search report documents the state of the art from which the invention must be sufficiently different. On the basis of this information, it is therefore possible to better evaluate whether the invention can really be protected by a patent. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;h3&gt;Streamlined appeal procedure with a court specialised in patent matters &lt;/h3&gt; &lt;p&gt;The Federal Council wants to make the Swiss patent system as lean as possible in order to offer an attractive alternative to the European patent. IPI decisions must be reviewable by a court on appeal. This review is to happen in future directly through the Federal Patent Court, which has the necessary high level of technical expertise. The opposition procedure introduced in 2008 is to be dispensed with altogether. It has never been resorted to since it was introduced.&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Alexander Pfister, Head of Legal Services – Industrial Property Rights Swiss Federal Institute of Intellectual Property IPI Direct line: T +41 31 377 74 88 Esther Marchetti-Baumgartner, Legal Services – Industrial Property Rights Swiss Federal Institute of Intellectual Property IPI Direct line: T +41 31 377 72 64</contact>
      <attachment id="219851">
        <title>Vernehmlassungsergebnisse</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>676</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/67867.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="219852">
        <title>Résultats de la procédure de consultation</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>679</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/67868.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="219853">
        <title>Risultati della procedura di consultazione</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>716</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/67869.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <keywords>
      <keyword id="18" org-id="401">
        <name lang="de">Behörden</name>
        <name lang="fr">Autorités</name>
        <name lang="it">Autorità</name>
        <name lang="en">Authorities</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="44" org-id="401">
        <name lang="de">Geistiges Eigentum</name>
        <name lang="fr">Propriété intellectuelle</name>
        <name lang="it">Proprietà intellettuale</name>
        <name lang="en">Intellectual property</name>
      </keyword>
    </keywords>
    <topics>
      <topic id="10">
        <name lang="de">Bundesrat</name>
        <name lang="fr">Conseil fédéral</name>
        <name lang="it">Consiglio federale</name>
        <name lang="en">Federal Council</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="26">
        <name lang="de">Recht</name>
        <name lang="fr">Droit</name>
        <name lang="it">Diritto</name>
        <name lang="en">Legal Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
