<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="89577" revoked="no">
    <version>2</version>
    <pubdate>2022-06-30</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="201" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>201</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="703" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>701</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Staatssekretariat für Wirtschaft</name>
      <name lang="fr">Secrétariat d'Etat à l'économie</name>
      <name lang="it">Segreteria di Stato dell'economia</name>
      <name lang="en">State Secretariat for Economic Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.seco.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.seco.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.seco.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.seco.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@seco.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@seco.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@seco.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@seco.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="201">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <department id="701">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Wirtschaft, Bildung und Forschung</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'économie, de la formation et de la recherche</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'economia, della formazione e della ricerca</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Economic Affairs, Education and Research</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Schweiz und EU unterzeichnen Memorandum of Understanding zum zweiten Schweizer Beitrag</title>
      <lead>Die Schweiz und die EU haben heute in Brüssel das Memorandum of Understanding (MoU) betreffend den zweiten Schweizer Beitrag an ausgewählte EU-Mitgliedstaaten unterzeichnet. Die Unterzeichnung für die Schweiz erfolgte durch Staatssekretärin Livia Leu, die für Sondierungsgespräche in Brüssel weilte. Mit der Unterzeichnung dieses MoU wurde ein weiteres wichtiges Etappenziel mit Blick auf eine zügige Umsetzung des Beitrags erreicht.</lead>
      <text link="no">Nach der dritten Sondierungsrunde zum Paketansatz des Bundesrats, hat Staatsekretärin Livia Leu heute zusammen mit der Generalsekretärin der Europäischen Kommission, Ilze Juhansone, das rechtlich nicht verbindliche MoU zum zweiten Schweizer Beitrag unterzeichnet. Das MoU war vom Bundesrat bereits am 24. November 2021 und auf Seiten der EU am 4. April 2022 genehmigt worden. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Am 30. September 2021 hatte das Schweizer Parlament den Beitrag freigegeben und damit ein positives Signal an die EU mit Blick auf die Fortsetzung und Weiterentwicklung des bilateralen Wegs gesendet.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Das MoU hält die wichtigsten Eckwerte des zweiten Schweizer Beitrags fest. Dazu gehören dessen Höhe, die Aufteilung auf die Partnerländer, die thematischen Prioritäten sowie Prinzipien für die Zusammenarbeit und die Umsetzung des Beitrags. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Das MoU bildet somit den Rahmen für die laufenden Gespräche mit den Partnerländern zu den jeweiligen bilateralen Umsetzungsabkommen, in welchen u.a. die länderspezifischen thematischen Schwerpunkte vereinbart werden. Diese Verhandlungen sollen nun rasch vorangetrieben und möglichst in diesem Jahr abgeschlossen werden.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;***&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Der zweite Schweizer Beitrag soll mit Schweizer Expertise zur Verringerung wirtschaftlicher und sozialer Ungleichheiten sowie zur besseren Bewältigung der Migrationsbewegungen in ausgewählten EU-Mitgliedstaaten beitragen.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Mit dem Rahmenkredit Kohäsion in der Höhe von 1047 Millionen Franken sollen die wirtschaftlichen und sozialen Ungleichheiten in den 13 Ländern verringert werden, welche der EU seit 2004 beigetreten sind (EU-13). Der Rahmenkredit Migration in der Höhe von 190 Millionen Franken ist vorgesehen für Massnahmen im Bereich Migration, auch in EU-Ländern ausserhalb der EU-13. Zusammen mit dem Eigenaufwand der Bundesverwaltung von 65 Millionen Franken (5%) bilden die Rahmenkredite den zweiten Schweizer Beitrag im Umfang von 1302 Millionen Franken über 10 Jahre. Wie beim Erweiterungsbeitrag fliesst auch der zweite Schweizer Beitrag in ausgewählte Projekte und Programme in den Partnerländern und wird nicht direkt in deren Haushalte oder an die EU überwiesen.</text>
      <contact>Kommunikation EDA Bundeshaus West CH-3003 Bern Tel. Kommunikationsservice: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Medienstelle: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>La Suisse et l’UE signent un mémorandum d’entente relatif à la deuxième contribution de la Suisse</title>
      <lead>La Suisse et l’UE ont signé aujourd’hui à Bruxelles le mémorandum d’entente relatif à la deuxième contribution de la Suisse en faveur de certains États membres de l’UE. Le document a été signé au nom de la Suisse par la secrétaire d’État Livia Leu, qui se trouvait à Bruxelles pour y mener des discussions exploratoires. Par la signature de ce mémorandum d’entente, une nouvelle étape importante a été franchie en vue d’une mise en œuvre rapide de la contribution.</lead>
      <text link="no">Après la troisième session de discussions exploratoires au sujet de l'approche par paquet du Conseil fédéral, la secrétaire d’État Livia Leu a signé aujourd’hui avec la secrétaire générale de la Commission européenne, Ilze Juhansone, le mémorandum d’entente juridiquement non contraignant relatif à la deuxième contribution de la Suisse. Le mémorandum d’entente a été approuvé par le Conseil fédéral dès le 24 novembre 2021 et par l’UE le 4 avril 2022. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Le 30 septembre 2021, le Parlement suisse avait débloqué cette contribution et envoyé ainsi un signal positif à l’UE quant à la poursuite et au développement de la voie bilatérale.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Le mémorandum d’entente fixe les principales lignes directrices de la deuxième contribution de la Suisse, notamment en ce qui concerne le montant, la répartition entre les pays partenaires, les priorités thématiques et les principes en matière de coopération et de mise en œuvre. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Le mémorandum d’entente forme donc le cadre pour les discussions en cours avec les pays partenaires au sujet des accords bilatéraux de mise en œuvre, dans lesquels sont notamment convenues les priorités thématiques spécifiques au pays concerné. Il faudra maintenant faire avancer rapidement les négociations afin de les conclure si possible cette année encore.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;***&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;La deuxième contribution doit mettre à profit l’expertise suisse pour atténuer les disparités économiques et sociales et améliorer la gestion des flux migratoires dans certains États membres de l’UE.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Le crédit-cadre pour la cohésion, d’un montant de 1047 millions de francs, doit permettre d’atténuer les disparités économiques et sociales dans les treize pays ayant adhéré à l’UE à partir de 2004 (UE-13). Quant au crédit-cadre pour la migration, d’un montant de 190 millions de francs, il est destiné à financer des mesures dans le domaine de la migration, non seulement dans l’UE-13, mais également dans les autres pays de l’UE. Associés aux charges propres de l’administration fédérale, qui se montent ici à 65 millions de francs (5%), ces crédits-cadres constituent la deuxième contribution de la Suisse, qui s’élève au total à 1302 millions de francs sur dix ans. À l’instar de la contribution à l’élargissement, la deuxième contribution de la Suisse est affectée à certains projets et programmes dans les pays partenaires et n’est pas versée directement au budget de ces pays ou à l’UE.</text>
      <contact>Communication DFAE Palais fédéral ouest CH-3003 Berne Tél. Service de communication: +41 58 462 31 53 Tél. Service de presse: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>La Svizzera e l’UE firmano il memorandum d’intesa sul secondo contributo svizzero</title>
      <lead>Oggi a Bruxelles la Svizzera e l’Unione europea hanno firmato il memorandum d’intesa concernente il secondo contributo svizzero ad alcuni Stati membri dell’UE. A firmare per la Svizzera è stata la segretaria di Stato Livia Leu, che si è trattenuta a Bruxelles per colloqui esplorativi. Con la firma del memorandum è stato raggiunto un ulteriore traguardo importante in vista di una rapida attuazione del contributo.</lead>
      <text link="no">Dopo la terza tornata di colloqui esplorativi sull’approccio «a pacchetto» del Consiglio federale, oggi la segretaria di Stato Livia Leu e la segretaria generale della Commissione europea Ilze Juhansone hanno firmato il memorandum d’intesa (Memorandum of Understanding, MoU), giuridicamente non vincolante, concernente il secondo contributo svizzero. Il MoU era già stato approvato sia dal Consiglio federale che dall’UE rispettivamente il 24 novembre 2021 e il 4 aprile 2022. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Il 30 settembre 2021 il Parlamento svizzero aveva sbloccato il contributo lanciando così un segnale positivo all’UE per il proseguimento e l’ulteriore sviluppo della via bilaterale.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Il MoU disciplina i punti chiave del secondo contributo svizzero, tra cui l’importo, la ripartizione tra i Paesi partner, le priorità tematiche, determinati principi di cooperazione e l’attuazione. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Il MoU costituisce pertanto il quadro di riferimento per i colloqui in corso con i Paesi partner sui rispettivi accordi di attuazione bilaterali, che stabiliscono tra le altre cose le priorità tematiche specifiche dei Paesi in questione. I negoziati dovrebbero proseguire speditamente e concludersi possibilmente entro la fine di quest’anno.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;***&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Il secondo contributo svizzero, insieme alle competenze della Svizzera, contribuirà a ridurre le disparità economiche e sociali e a migliorare la gestione dei flussi migratori in alcuni Stati membri dell’UE.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Il credito quadro «coesione», di 1047 milioni di franchi, mira a sostenere la riduzione delle disparità economiche e sociali nei 13 Paesi che hanno aderito all’UE nel 2004 (UE-13). Il credito quadro «migrazione», di 190 milioni di franchi, è destinato invece a misure nel settore della migrazione anche in Paesi dell’UE che non fanno parte dell’UE-13. Insieme alle spese proprie dell’Amministrazione federale, pari a 65 milioni di franchi (il 5 %), i crediti quadro formano il secondo contributo svizzero, che ammonta a 1302 milioni di franchi ripartiti su 10 anni. Come per il contributo all’allargamento, anche il secondo contributo svizzero confluisce in progetti e programmi selezionati nei Paesi partner e non viene trasferito direttamente nei loro bilanci o all’UE.</text>
      <contact>Comunicazione DFAE Palazzo federale ovest CH-3003 Berna Tel. Servizio di comunicazione: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Servizio stampa: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Switzerland and EU sign memorandum of understanding on second Swiss contribution</title>
      <lead>Switzerland and the EU signed earlier today in Brussels a memorandum of understanding (MoU) on the second Swiss contribution to selected EU member states. State Secretary Livia Leu, who was in Brussels for exploratory talks, signed the MoU on behalf of Switzerland. The signing of this MOU marks another important milestone towards a swift implementation of the contribution.</lead>
      <text link="no">State Secretary Livia Leu and the Secretary-General of the European Commission, Ilze Juhansone signed the legally non-binding MoU on Switzerland's second contribution today following the third round of exploratory talks on the Federal Council’s proposed package approach. The MoU was approved by the Federal Council on 24 November 2021 and by the EU on 4 April 2022. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;On 30 September 2021, the Swiss Parliament released the contribution, sending a positive signal to the EU concerning the continuation and further development of the bilateral approach.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The MoU sets out the key parameters of the second Swiss contribution. This includes the amount of the contribution, its distribution among the partner countries, thematic priorities and principles for cooperation and implementation. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The MoU provides the framework for the ongoing discussions with the partner countries on the bilateral implementation agreements which define, among other aspects, the thematic priorities for each country. With the MoU signed, the negotiations are now set to move forward swiftly and, if possible, be concluded this year.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;***&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The second Swiss contribution aims to leverage Swiss expertise to reduce economic and social disparities and to manage migration better in selected EU member states.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The cohesion framework credit in the amount of CHF 1.047 billion is intended to reduce economic and social disparities in the 13 countries that have joined the EU since 2004 (EU-13).The migration framework credit totalling CHF 190 million is earmarked for measures in the area of migration, including in EU countries other than the EU-13.The second Swiss contribution of CHF 1.32 billion over 10 years is comprised of the federal government's own expenditure of CHF 65 million (5%) and the framework credits. As with the enlargement contribution, this second contribution will be channelled into selected projects and programmes in the partner countries and will not be transferred directly into their budgets or to the EU.</text>
      <contact>FDFA Communication Federal Palace West Wing CH-3003 Bern, Switzerland Tel. Communication service: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Press service: +41 58 460 55 55 E-mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @SwissMFA</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <offers>
      <offer id="336" org-id="703">
        <name lang="de">Wirtschaftliche Zusammenarbeit und Entwicklung</name>
        <name lang="fr">Coopération et développement économiques</name>
        <name lang="it">Cooperazione e sviluppo economici</name>
        <name lang="en">Economic Cooperation and Development</name>
      </offer>
    </offers>
    <topics>
      <topic id="47">
        <name lang="de">Wirtschaft</name>
        <name lang="fr">Économie</name>
        <name lang="it">Economia</name>
        <name lang="en">Economic Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
