<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="18443" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2008-04-22</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="201" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>201</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="201">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Offizieller Arbeitsbesuch der Aussen­ministe­rin des Fürstentums Andorra, Meritxell MATEU, in Bern</title>
      <lead>Bundesrätin Micheline Calmy-Rey, Vorsteherin des Eidgenössischen Departe­ments für auswärtige Angelegenheiten (EDA), empfing heute in Bern ihre Amtskollegin Meritxell Mateu zu einem offiziellen Arbeitsbesuch. Im Zentrum der Gespräche standen die bilateralen Beziehungen, die Europapolitik und die multilaterale Zusammenarbeit.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Die bilateralen Beziehungen zwischen den beiden Ländern sind ausgezeichnet und freundschaftlich. Das Fürstentum Andorra hat ein natürliches Interesse daran, die Beziehungen mit der Schweiz auszubauen, und die Gespräche waren von diesem Interesse geprägt.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Die Vorsteherin des EDA informierte ihre Amtskollegin über die europa­politischen Prioritäten der Schweiz sowie über die Weiterführung und Ausdehnung der bilatera­len Abkommen der Schweiz mit der Europäischen Union. Sie erwähnte insbesondere den Beginn der Verhandlungen im Strombereich sowie die kürzliche Verabschie­dung von Verhandlungsmandaten für ein Freihandels­abkommen im Agrar- und Lebens­mittelbereich und ein Abkommen im Bereich des Gesundheits­wesens. Sie bestätigte auch, dass das System der Steuerrückbehalte im Rahmen des Abkommens zwischen der Schweiz und der Europäischen Gemein­schaft über die Zins­besteuerung gut funktioniert. Das Fürstentum Andorra verfolgt wie die Schweiz in seinen Beziehungen zur EU den bilateralen Weg. Ergänzend zur Zollunion mit der EU hat das Fürstentum vor einigen Jahren auch ein Rahmen­abkommen über die Zusammenarbeit mit der EU abgeschlossen.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Schliesslich wurden in den Gesprächen die institutionelle Konsolidierung des Men­schenrechtsrats, die Verbesserung der Arbeitsmethoden des Sicherheitsrats sowie die Bemühungen um mehr Kohärenz im operationellen System der Vereinten Nationen angesprochen.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Presse- und Informationsdienst Bundeshaus West CH-3003 Bern Tel.: +41 (0)31 322 31 53 Fax: +41 (0)31 324 90 47 E-Mail: info@eda.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Visite officielle de travail de la Ministre des affaires étrangères de la Principauté d’Andorre, Mme Meritxell MATEU, à Berne</title>
      <lead>La Conseillère fédérale Micheline Calmy-Rey, Cheffe du Département fédéral des affaires étrangères a reçu aujourd'hui à Berne son homologue, Mme Meritxell Mateu pour une visite officielle de travail. Les entretiens ont porté sur les relations bilatérales, la politique européenne et la coopération multilatérale.</lead>
      <text link="no">Les relations bilatérales entre les deux pays sont excellentes et cordiales. Il existe un intérêt naturel de la Principauté d'Andorre à développer les contacts avec la Suisse et c'est dans cet esprit que les entretiens ont eu lieu.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Au chapitre de la politique européenne la Cheffe du DFAE a orienté son homologue sur les priorités de la Suisse ainsi que sur le renouvellement et l’extension des accords bilatéraux de la Suisse avec l'Union européenne. Elle a notamment évoqué le début des négociations concernant l’électricité ainsi que l'adoption récente par le Conseil fédéral d'un mandat de négociation en vue d’un éventuel accord de libre-échange dans le secteur agroalimentaire et d’un accord dans le domaine de la santé publique. Le bon fonctionnement du système de la retenue d'impôts dans le cadre de l’accord sur la fiscalité de l’épargne entre la Suisse et la CE a également été confirmé. Tout comme la Suisse, la Principauté d’Andorre poursuit une voie bilatérale dans ses relations avec l’Union européenne. En complément d’une union douanière avec l’UE, la Principauté a conclu il y a quelques années un accord-cadre de coopération avec cette dernière.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Les entretiens ont enfin permis d'aborder la consolidation institutionnelle du Conseil des droits de l'homme, l'amélioration des méthodes de travail du Conseil de sécurité ainsi que la mise en œuvre d’une plus grande cohérence du système opérationnel des Nations Unies.</text>
      <contact>Service de presse et d'information Palais fédéral ouest CH-3003 Berne Tél.: (+41) 031 322 31 53 Fax: (+41) 031 324 90 47 E-Mail: info@eda.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Visita ufficiale di lavoro a Berna della ministra degli affari esteri del Principato di Andorra, Meritxell MATEU</title>
      <lead>La Consigliera federale Micheline Calmy-Rey, responsabile del Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri ha ricevuto stamane a Berna la sua omologa, Meritxell Mateu, giunta in visita ufficiale di lavoro. I colloqui si sono incentrati sulle relazioni bilaterali, sulla politica europea e sulla cooperazione multilaterale.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Le relazioni bilaterali tra i due Paesi sono eccellenti e cordiali. Da parte del Principato di Andorra vi è un interesse naturale a sviluppare i contatti con la Svizzera ed è in questo spirito che hanno avuto luogo i colloqui.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; In materia di politica europea la responsabile del DFAE ha orientato la sua omologa sulle priorità della Svizzera nonché sul rinnovo e l’estensione degli accordi bilaterali della Svizzera con l’Unione europea. Micheline Calmy–Rey ha segnatamente evocato l’avvio dei negoziati concernenti l’elettricità nonché la recente adozione da parte del Consiglio federale di un mandato di negoziazione in vista di un eventuale accordo di libero scambio nel settore agroalimentare e di un accordo in materia di sanità pubblica. Il buon funzionamento del sistema della trattenuta d’imposta nel quadro dell’accordo sulla fiscalità del risparmio tra la Svizzera e la CE è stato parimenti confermato. Come la Svizzera, il Principato di Andorra persegue una via bilaterale nelle sue relazioni con l’Unione europea. In complemento di un’unione doganale con l’UE il Principato ha concluso con quest’ultima alcuni anni fa un accordo quadro di cooperazione.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; I colloqui hanno infine permesso di affrontare il consolidamento istituzionale del Consiglio dei diritti dell’uomo, il miglioramento dei metodi di lavoro del Consiglio di sicurezza nonché la realizzazione di una maggiore coerenza del sistema operativo delle Nazioni Unite.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Servizio stampa e informazione Palazzo federale ovest CH-3003 Berna Tel.: (+41) 031 322 31 53 Fax: (+41) 031 324 90 47 E-Mail: info@eda.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Official working visit to Bern by the Minister of Foreign Affairs of the Principality of Andorra, Mrs Meritxell Mateu</title>
      <lead>Today, the Foreign Minister of the Principality of Andorra, Mrs Meritxell Mateu, visited Bern for an official working, where she was received by Federal Councillor Micheline Calmy-Rey, head of the Federal Department of Foreign Affairs (FDFA). The foreign ministers discussed bilateral relations, policy on Europe, and multilateral cooperation.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Relations between Switzerland and Andorra are excellent and friendly. The Principality of Andorra has a natural interest in developing contacts with Switzerland, and the talks were conducted in this spirit.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; On the subject of policy on Europe, the head of the FDFA explained Switzerland’s priorities as well as the system of bilateral agreements between Switzerland and the EU and the method of renewing and extending them. In particular, she mentioned the beginning of negotiations on electricity as well as the recent adoption by the Federal Councillor of a mandate to negotiate a possible free-trade agreement on food and agriculture products as well as an agreement on public health. Mrs Calmy-Rey confirmed that the system of a withholding tax in the framework of an agreement on the taxation of savings between Switzerland and the EU was functioning well. Like Switzerland, the Principality of Andorra pursues a bilateral relationship with the EU. A few years ago, Andorra supplemented a customs union with the EU by concluding a framework agreement on cooperation.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Finally, the talks presented an opportunity to address the subjects of the institutional consolidation of the Human Rights Council, improving the working methods of the Security Council, and implementing a more coherent operational system within the United Nations.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Press and Information Service Bundeshaus West CH-3003 Bern Tel.: (+41) 031 322 31 53 Fax: (+41) 031 324 90 47 E-Mail: info@eda.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
