<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="18493" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2008-04-25</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="yes" id="703" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>701</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Staatssekretariat für Wirtschaft</name>
      <name lang="fr">Secrétariat d'Etat à l'économie</name>
      <name lang="it">Segreteria di Stato dell'economia</name>
      <name lang="en">State Secretariat for Economic Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.seco.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.seco.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.seco.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.seco.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@seco.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@seco.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@seco.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@seco.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="701">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Wirtschaft, Bildung und Forschung</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'économie, de la formation et de la recherche</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'economia, della formazione e della ricerca</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Economic Affairs, Education and Research</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Bundesrätin Doris Leuthard auf Wirtschaftsmission in Indien</title>
      <teaser>Doris Leuthard, die Vorsteherin des Eigenössischen Volkswirtschaftsdepartements (EVD), stattet Indien vom 28. April bis 3. Mai 2008 einen offiziellen Besuch ab. Ziele der Wirtschaftsmission sind einerseits die Verbesserung der Rahmenbedingungen und der Zugang zum indischen Markt für Schweizer Unternehmen, andererseits die Förderung des Standorts Schweiz. Rund 25 Unternehmer und Direktionsmitglieder von Schweizer Unternehmen werden Bundesrätin Leuthard begleiten.</teaser>
      <lead>Doris Leuthard, die Vorsteherin des Eigenössischen Volkswirtschaftsdepartements (EVD), stattet Indien vom 28. April bis 3. Mai 2008 einen offiziellen Besuch ab. Ziele der Wirtschaftsmission sind einerseits die Verbesserung der Rahmenbedingungen und der Zugang zum indischen Markt für Schweizer Unternehmen, andererseits die Förderung des Standorts Schweiz. Rund 25 Unternehmer und Direktionsmitglieder von Schweizer Unternehmen werden Bundesrätin Leuthard begleiten.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Die Schweiz und Indien pflegen generell gute Beziehungen. In diesem Jahr kommt das besonders zum Ausdruck, wird doch in Indien und in der Schweiz das 60jährige Bestehen des Freundschafts-Vertrags zwischen den zwei Staaten gefeiert. Die Schweiz war 1948 das erste Land, das mit Indien einen solchen Vertrag unterzeichnete. Die Wirtschaftsmission steht auch im Zeichen dieses Jubiläums.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;In New Delhi, der ersten Reiseetappe, wird Bundesrätin Leuthard mit dem indischen Handels- und Industrieminister Kamal Nath Gespräche führen. Weitere Treffen sind vorgesehen mit dem Finanzminister Palaniappan Chidambaram sowie mit dem Wissenschafts- und Technologieminister Kapil Sibal. Im Zentrum der Diskussionen wird eine Bestandesaufnahme im Bereich Freihandel und Marktzutritt stehen. Die Bundesrätin wird die Gelegenheit nutzen, um mit ihren Gesprächspartnern die Fortschritte zu analysieren, die im Gemischten Ausschuss für geistiges Eigentum erzielt wurden.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;An den weiteren Stationen der Reise - Bangalore, Mysore und Mumbai - werden einerseits Behördenkontakte gepflegt, andererseits Unternehmen besucht, die in Sparten tätig sind, die Schweizer Unternehmerinnen und Unternehmer besonders interessieren.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Mit einem Handelsvolumen von 3.26 Milliarden Franken im Jahr 2007 (+ 24.2 % gegenüber dem Vorjahr) ist Indien ein wichtiger Handelspartner der Schweiz in Asien. 2007 haben die Schweizer Exporte nach Indien um 22.3 % zugenommen und erreichten 2.3 Milliarden Franken. Importiert wurden im vergangen Jahr indische Erzeugnisse im Wert von 0.95 Milliarden Franken (+ 29 %). Im internationalen Vergleich ist die Schweiz einer der wichtigsten Investoren in Indien. Die kumulierten Schweizer Investitionen in Indien übertreffen heute 2 Milliarden Franken. Rund 150 Schweizer Unternehmen beschäftigen über ganz Indien verteilt rund 41'000 Personen.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Evelyn Kobelt, Pressesprecherin EVD, Tel. 031 322 20 59, Mobile +41 79 301 71 72 Massimo Baggi, Leiter Bilateral Wirtschaftsbeziehungen mit Asien/Ozeanien, SECO, Tel. 031 322 23 02</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>La conseillère fédérale Doris Leuthard en mission économique en Inde</title>
      <teaser>Doris Leuthard, cheffe du Département fédéral de l’économie (DFE), se rendra en visite officielle en Inde du 28 avril au 3 mai 2008. Les objectifs de cette mission ciblent l'amélioration des conditions-cadre et d'accès au marché indien pour les entreprises suisses ainsi que la promotion de la place économique suisse. Lors de ce voyage, la conseillère fédérale sera accompagnée par une nombreuse délégation économique comprenant quelque 25 entrepreneurs et membres de direction d’importantes compagnies suisses.</teaser>
      <lead>Doris Leuthard, cheffe du Département fédéral de l’économie (DFE), se rendra en visite officielle en Inde du 28 avril au 3 mai 2008. Les objectifs de cette mission ciblent l'amélioration des conditions-cadre et d'accès au marché indien pour les entreprises suisses ainsi que la promotion de la place économique suisse. Lors de ce voyage, la conseillère fédérale sera accompagnée par une nombreuse délégation économique comprenant quelque 25 entrepreneurs et membres de direction d’importantes compagnies suisses.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;La Suisse et l'Inde entretiennent de bonnes relations bilatérales qui sont marquées, cette année, par les célébrations prévues du 60ème anniversaire du traité d'amitié entre les deux pays. En 1948, la Suisse fut le premier pays à souscrire un tel traité avec l'Inde. La mission économique s'inscrit donc aussi sous le signe de ces célébrations.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;A New Delhi, première étape de la visite, la conseillère fédérale s'entretiendra avec son homologue, le Ministre du commerce et de l'industrie M. K. Nath, ainsi qu'avec le Ministre des finances M. P. Chidambaram et le Ministre de la science et la technologie M. K. Sibal. Les discussions visent principalement à faire le point de la situation en matière de libre-échange et d'accès au marché. Doris Leuthard profitera également de l'occasion pour analyser avec ses interlocuteurs les progrès accomplis au sein du groupe de travail conjoint en matière de propriété intellectuelle.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Lors des étapes ultérieures du voyage (Bangalore, Mysore et Mumbai), la délégation suisse rencontrera des autres autorités et visitera différentes entreprises, actives dans des secteurs d'intérêt pour l'économie suisse.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Avec un volume de commerce bilatéral de 3.26 milliards de francs en 2007, (+ 24.2% par rapport à l'année précédente), l'Inde représente un partenaire commercial privilégié de la Suisse en Asie. En 2007, les exportations suisses vers l'Inde ont progressé de 22.3% en atteignant 2.3 milliards de francs, tandis que les importations en provenance de ce pays se sont élevées à 0.95 milliards de francs (+ 29%). La Suisse figure parmi les principaux investisseurs internationaux en Inde. La valeur cumulative des investissements suisses en Inde dépasse désormais les 2 milliards de francs. Environ 150 entreprises suisses déploient leurs activités aux 4 coins du pays et y emploient environ 41'000 personnes.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Evelyn Kobelt, port parole du DFAE, Tel. 031 322 2059, portable +41 793017172 Massimo Baggi, responsable de la section Asie/Océanie, Relations bilatérales, SECO Tel. 031 322 23 02</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>La consigliera federale Doris Leuthard in missione economica in India</title>
      <teaser>Doris Leuthard, responsabile del Dipartimento federale dell'economia, si recherà per una visita ufficiale in India dal 28 aprile al 3 maggio 2008. Gli obiettivi della missione sono il miglioramento delle condizioni quadro e d'accesso al mercato indiano per le aziende svizzere nonché la promozione la piazza economica elvetica. In occasione di questo viaggio, la consigliera federale sarà accompagnata da una folta delegazione economica comprendente circa 25 imprenditori e membri di direzione d'importanti aziende svizzere.</teaser>
      <lead>Doris Leuthard, responsabile del Dipartimento federale dell'economia, si recherà per una visita ufficiale in India dal 28 aprile al 3 maggio 2008. Gli obiettivi della missione sono il miglioramento delle condizioni quadro e d'accesso al mercato indiano per le aziende svizzere nonché la promozione la piazza economica elvetica. In occasione di questo viaggio, la consigliera federale sarà accompagnata da una folta delegazione economica comprendente circa 25 imprenditori e membri di direzione d'importanti aziende svizzere.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Svizzera ed India intrattengono buone relazioni bilaterali, che verranno messe in particolare evidenza quest'anno grazie alle previste celebrazioni per il 60esimo anniversario del Trattato di amicizia tra i due Stati. Nel 1948, la Svizzera fu il primo paese a sottoscrivere un simile accordo con l'India. La missione economica è dunque anche posta sotto l'egida di questo giubileo.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;A Nuova Delhi, prima tappa della visita, la consigliera federale s'intratterrà innanzitutto con il suo omologo, il Ministro del commercio e dell'industria K. Nath, per poi incontrare il Ministro delle finanze P. Chidambaram e il Ministro della scienza e della tecnologia K. Sibal. Le discussioni verteranno principalmente sulla situazione in materia di libero scambio e di accesso ai rispettivi mercati. Doris Leuthard approfitterà dell'occasione per analizzare con i suoi interlocutori pure i progressi compiuti in seno al gruppo di lavoro comune in materia di proprietà intellettuale.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;In occasione delle ulteriori tappe del viaggio (Bangalore, Mysore e Mumbai), la delegazione elvetica incontrerà altre autorità e visiterà alcune aziende attive in ambiti d'interesse per l'economia elvetica.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Con un volume di commercio bilaterale di 3.26 miliardi di franchi nel 2007 (+ 24.2% rispetto all'anno precedente), l'India rappresenta un partner commerciale privilegiato per la Svizzera in Asia. Nel 2007, le esportazioni svizzere verso l'India sono aumentate del 22.3% issandosi a 2.3 miliardi di franchi, mentre le importazioni in provenienza dal gigante asiatico hanno raggiunto 0.95 miliardi di franchi (+ 29%). La Svizzera figura tra i principali investitori internazionali in India. Il valore cumulato degli investimenti elvetici in India supera ormai i 2 miliardi di franchi. Circa 150 società svizzere sono attive sul suo territorio, dove impiegano circa 41'000 persone.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Evelyn Kobelt, portavoce del DFE, Tel. 031 322 20 59, Cellulare +41 79 301 71 72 Massimo Baggi, responsabile della sezione Asia/Oceania, Relazioni bilaterali, SECO, Tel. 031 322 23 02</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Federal Councillor Doris Leuthard on economic mission to India</title>
      <teaser>Doris Leuthard, the head of the Federal Department of Economic Affairs (FDEA), will pay an official visit to India between 28 April and 3 May 2008. The economic mission is aimed on the one hand at improving framework conditions and access to the Indian market for Swiss firms, and on the other at promoting Switzerland as a location for business. Federal Councillor Leuthard will be accompanied by representatives from around 25 Swiss firms including a number of board members.</teaser>
      <lead>Doris Leuthard, the head of the Federal Department of Economic Affairs (FDEA), will pay an official visit to India between 28 April and 3 May 2008. The economic mission is aimed on the one hand at improving framework conditions and access to the Indian market for Swiss firms, and on the other at promoting Switzerland as a location for business. Federal Councillor Leuthard will be accompanied by representatives from around 25 Swiss firms including a number of board members.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Relations between Switzerland and India are good. This year, in particular, India and Switzerland will celebrate the 60th anniversary of the Treaty of Friendship and Establishment between the two States. In 1948 Switzerland was the first country to sign such a treaty with India. The economic mission is also intended to mark this anniversary.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;During the first stage of the visit in New Delhi, Federal Councillor Leuthard will hold talks with the Minister of Commerce and Industry, Kamal Nath. Further meetings are planned with the Minister of Finance, Palaniappan Chidambaram, and with the Minister of Science and Technology, Kapil Sibal. Discussions will focus on appraising the situation in the fields of free trade and market access. The Federal Councillor will also use the opportunity to analyse with her colleagues the progress that has been made in the Mixed Commission on Intellectual Property.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Further stops on the visit will include Bangalore, Mysore and Mumbai where contacts will be fostered on the one hand with the authorities and on the other with companies active in fields that are of particular interest to the Swiss business community.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;With a trade volume of CHF 3.26 billion in 2007 (+ 24.2% compared to the previous year), India is an important trade partner for Switzerland in Asia. In 2007 Swiss exports to India rose by 22.3% reaching CHF 2.3 billion. Imports from India last year were valued at CHF 0.95 billion (+ 29%). In international comparison Switzerland is one of the largest investors in India. Today, cumulative Swiss investment in India is in excess of CHF 2 billion. At present there are roughly 150 Swiss companies in India employing around 41,000 people throughout the country.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Evelyn Kobelt, Press Spokesperson FDEA, Tel.: 031 322 20 59, Mobile: +41 79 301 71 72 Massimo Baggi, SECO, Head Bilateral Economic Relations with Asia/Oceania, Tel. 031 322 23 02</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="10">
        <name lang="de">Bundesrat</name>
        <name lang="fr">Conseil fédéral</name>
        <name lang="it">Consiglio federale</name>
        <name lang="en">Federal Council</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="29">
        <name lang="de">Umwelt und Natur</name>
        <name lang="fr">Environnement et nature</name>
        <name lang="it">Ambiente e natura</name>
        <name lang="en">Environment and Nature</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="38">
        <name lang="de">Landwirtschaft</name>
        <name lang="fr">Agriculture</name>
        <name lang="it">Agricoltura</name>
        <name lang="en">Agriculture</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="47">
        <name lang="de">Wirtschaft</name>
        <name lang="fr">Économie</name>
        <name lang="it">Economia</name>
        <name lang="en">Economic Affairs</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="48">
        <name lang="de">Zoll</name>
        <name lang="fr">Douanes</name>
        <name lang="it">Dogane</name>
        <name lang="en">Customs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
