<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="72938" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2018-11-15</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="605" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>601</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössische Steuerverwaltung</name>
      <name lang="fr">Administration fédérale des contributions</name>
      <name lang="it">Amministrazione federale delle contribuzioni</name>
      <name lang="en">The Federal Tax Administration</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.estv.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.estv.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.estv.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.estv.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de"/>
      <email lang="fr"/>
      <email lang="it"/>
      <email lang="en"/>
    </originator>
    <department id="601">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Finanzdepartement</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des finances</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale delle finanze</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Finance</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.efd.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.dff.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.efd.admin.ch/efd/it/home.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.efd.admin.ch/efd/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>STAF - Keine neuen Prinzipalgesellschaften und Swiss Finance Branches mehr ab 2019</title>
      <lead>Im Zuge der Vorlage über die Steuerreform und die AHV-Finanzierung (STAF) wird die Eidgenössische Steuerverwaltung (ESTV) die Bundespraxen betreffend Prinzipalgesellschaften und Swiss Finance Branch ab 2019 nicht mehr auf neue Unternehmen anwenden.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Mit der STAF werden die Vorkehrungen auf Gesetzesstufe getroffen, um das Schweizer Unternehmenssteuerrecht mit den internationalen Anforderungen in Einklang zu bringen. Wie in der Botschaft des Bundesrates zur Steuervorlage 17 (neu: STAF) angekündigt, sollen parallel zur Abschaffung der Regelungen für kantonale Statusgesellschaften auch die Bundespraxen zur Steuerausscheidung bei Prinzipalgesellschaften und zu den Swiss Finance Branches abgeschafft werden. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Im Unterschied zu den Regelungen für kantonale Statusgesellschaften bedarf die Abschaffung der Bundespraxen keiner gesetzlichen Anpassung. Deshalb wird die ESTV in einem ersten Schritt veranlassen, dass die Bundespraxen auf neue Unternehmen ab 2019 nicht mehr angewendet werden. Mit dem Inkrafttreten der STAF auf Anfang 2020 sollen in einem weiteren Schritt die Bundespraxen auch für bisherige Prinzipalgesellschaften und Swiss Finance Branches abgeschafft werden.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class="nsbtextkasten"&gt; International tätige Konzerne fassen ihre Strukturen oft in grösseren Einheiten zusammen und zentralisieren die Funktionen, Verantwortlichkeiten und Risiken innerhalb des Konzerns in sogenannten Prinzipalgesellschaften. Befindet sich diese Prinzipalgesellschaft in der Schweiz, so wird ein Teil des Reingewinns von der Besteuerung in der Schweiz freigestellt (internationale Steuerausscheidung). &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Swiss Finance Branches sind schweizerische Finanzbetriebsstätten ausländischer Unternehmen und als solche namentlich für die Darlehensvergabe innerhalb der ausländischen Konzerne zuständig. Durch die Berechnung eines Nutzungsentgelts für das der schweizerischen Betriebsstätte zur Verfügung gestellte Kapital reduziert sich der in der Schweiz steuerbare Reingewinn der Swiss Finance Branch.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Patrick Teuscher, Leiter Kommunikation / Eidgenössische Steuerverwaltung ESTV Tel.-Nr. +41 58 464 90 00, media@estv.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>RFFA: plus de nouvelles sociétés principales ni de nouvelles Swiss Finance Branches à partir de 2019</title>
      <lead>Dans le sillage du projet de loi fédérale relative à la réforme fiscale et au financement de l’AVS (RFFA), l’Administration fédérale des contributions (AFC) n’appliquera plus les pratiques de société principale et de Swiss Finance Branch à de nouvelles entreprises à partir de 2019.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;La RFFA introduit les mesures nécessaires au niveau législatif pour concilier le droit suisse en matière d’imposition des entreprises avec les exigences internationales. Comme annoncé dans le message du Conseil fédéral concernant la loi fédérale sur le Projet fiscal 17 (désormais RFFA), les pratiques relatives à la répartition fiscale des sociétés principales et aux &lt;i&gt;Swiss Finance Branches&lt;/i&gt; seront abolies en parallèle à la suppression des règles concernant les sociétés à statut fiscal cantonal. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Contrairement à la suppression des règles concernant les sociétés à statut fiscal cantonal, la suppression de ces pratiques fédérales n’exige pas de modifications législatives. Dans un premier temps, l’AFC prendra donc les mesures nécessaires pour que ces pratiques ne soient plus appliquées à de nouvelles entreprises à partir de 2019. Avec l’entrée en vigueur de la RFFA au début de 2020, il s’agira dans un deuxième temps de supprimer également ces pratiques pour les sociétés principales et les &lt;i&gt;Swiss Finance Branches&lt;/i&gt; qui en bénéficient actuellement.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class="nsbtextkasten"&gt; Les groupes opérant au niveau international réunissent souvent leurs structures en de plus grandes entités et centralisent au niveau de sociétés dites principales les fonctions, les responsabilités et les risques au sein du groupe. Si cette société principale se trouve en Suisse, une partie du bénéfice net y est exclue de l’imposition (répartition fiscale internationale). &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Les Swiss Finance Branches sont des établissements financiers stables d’entreprises étrangères, qui sont notamment compétents pour octroyer des prêts au sein des groupes étrangers. Le calcul d’une rémunération pour l’utilisation du capital mis à la disposition de l’établissement stable suisse réduit en conséquence le bénéfice net imposable en Suisse de la Swiss Finance Branch. &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Patrick Teuscher, responsable de la communication, Administration fédérale des contributions AFC Tél. +41 58 464 90 00, media@estv.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>RFFA: dal 2019 non ci saranno più nuove società principali né Swiss Finance Branch</title>
      <lead>Nell’ambito del progetto sulla riforma fiscale e il finanziamento dell’AVS (RFFA), dal 2019 l’Amministrazione federale delle contribuzioni (AFC) non applicherà più alle nuove imprese le prassi amministrative relative alle società principali e alle Swiss Finance Branch.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Con la RFFA vengono prese misure a livello legislativo per adeguare il diritto svizzero in materia di imposizione delle imprese ai requisiti internazionali. Come annunciato nel messaggio del Consiglio federale concernente la legge federale sul Progetto fiscale 17 (ora RFFA), parallelamente all’abrogazione delle norme applicabili alle società con statuto speciale cantonale verranno abolite anche la prassi federale in materia di ripartizione fiscale per le società principali e quella applicata alle Swiss Finance Branch.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Contrariamente a quanto accade per le norme applicabili alle società con statuto speciale cantonale, l’abolizione delle prassi federali non necessita di adeguamenti legislativi. Per questo motivo, in una prima fase l’AFC disporrà che queste prassi non vengano più applicate alle nuove imprese a partire dal 2019. Successivamente, con l’entrata in vigore della RFFA all’inizio del 2020, tali prassi verranno abolite anche per le società principali e le Swiss Finance Branch&lt;i&gt; &lt;/i&gt;esistenti.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class="nsbtextkasten"&gt; I gruppi che operano a livello internazionale concentrano spesso le loro strutture in entità di dimensioni maggiori, centralizzando così in società dette «principali» funzioni, responsabilità e rischi interni al gruppo. Se la società principale si trova in Svizzera, una parte dell’utile netto conseguito viene esentato dalla tassazione in Svizzera (ripartizione fiscale internazionale). &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Le Swiss Finance Branch sono stabilimenti finanziari d’impresa svizzeri di una società estera responsabili della concessione di prestiti infragruppo. Il calcolo di un indennizzo d’uso per il capitale messo a disposizione dello stabilimento d’impresa svizzero riduce l’utile netto imponibile in Svizzera della Swiss Finance Branch. &lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Patrick Teuscher, capo della Comunicazione, Amministrazione federale delle contribuzioni AFC Tel. +41 58 464 90 00, media@estv.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>TRAF – No more new principal companies and Swiss finance branches from 2019</title>
      <lead>In the context of the bill on tax reform and AHV financing (TRAF), the Federal Tax Administration (FTA) will no longer apply the federal practices concerning principal companies and Swiss finance branches to new companies from 2019. </lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;TRAF introduces legislative measures in order to bring Swiss corporate tax law in line with international requirements. As announced in the Federal Council dispatch on tax proposal 17 (now: TRAF), the federal practices on tax allocation for principal companies and Swiss finance branches will also be abolished in parallel to the abolition of the rules concerning cantonal status companies. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Unlike the rules concerning cantonal status companies, the abolition of federal practices does not require any legislative amendment. As a first step, the FTA will therefore ensure that federal practices are no longer applied to new companies from 2019. With the entry into force of TRAF at the beginning of 2020, the federal practices for existing principal companies and Swiss finance branches will also be abolished.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class="nsbtextkasten"&gt; Companies operating internationally often group their structures into larger units and centralise functions, responsibilities and risks within the group in so-called principal companies. If this principal company is located in Switzerland, some of the net profit is exempt from taxation in Switzerland (international tax allocation). &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Swiss finance branches are Swiss financial permanent establishments of foreign companies and as such are responsible for lending within foreign groups. The calculation of a usage fee for the capital made available to the Swiss permanent establishment reduces the taxable net profit of the Swiss finance branch in Switzerland.&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Patrick Teuscher, Head of Communications, Federal Tax Administration FTA Tel. +41 58 464 90 00, media@estv.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <keywords>
      <keyword id="131" org-id="605">
        <name lang="de">Unternehmensbesteuerung</name>
        <name lang="fr">Imposition des sociétés</name>
        <name lang="it">Imposizione delle imprese</name>
        <name lang="en">Corporate taxation</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="235" org-id="605">
        <name lang="de">Internationale Steuerpolitik</name>
        <name lang="fr">Politique fiscale internationale</name>
        <name lang="it">Politica fiscale internazionale</name>
        <name lang="en">International tax policy</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="1717" org-id="605">
        <name lang="de">Steuervorlage 17</name>
        <name lang="fr">Projet fiscal 17</name>
        <name lang="it">Progetto fiscale 17</name>
        <name lang="en">Tax proposal 17</name>
      </keyword>
    </keywords>
    <topics>
      <topic id="35">
        <name lang="de">Finanzplatz</name>
        <name lang="fr">Place financière</name>
        <name lang="it">Piazza finanziaria</name>
        <name lang="en">Financial Centre</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="44">
        <name lang="de">Steuern</name>
        <name lang="fr">Impôts</name>
        <name lang="it">Imposte</name>
        <name lang="en">Taxation</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="47">
        <name lang="de">Wirtschaft</name>
        <name lang="fr">Économie</name>
        <name lang="it">Economia</name>
        <name lang="en">Economic Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
