<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="72847" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2018-11-08</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="323" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>701</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidg. Materialprüfungs- und Forschungsanstalt</name>
      <name lang="fr">Laboratoire fédéral d'essai des matériaux et de recherche</name>
      <name lang="it">Laboratorio federale di prova dei materiali e di ricerca</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Laboratory for Materials Testing and Research</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.empa.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.empa.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.empa.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.empa.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">contact@empa.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">contact@empa.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">contact@empa.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">contact@empa.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="701">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Wirtschaft, Bildung und Forschung</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'économie, de la formation et de la recherche</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'economia, della formazione e della ricerca</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Economic Affairs, Education and Research</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Dübendorf, St. Gallen und Thun</city>
      <title>«Synchronisiertes» Licht</title>
      <lead>Wenn Fotoemitter miteinander kooperieren, dann strahlen sie gleichzeitig, ein Phänomen, das als Superfluoreszenz bekannt ist. Forschenden der Empa, der ETH Zürich und IBM Research Zürich ist es gelungen, diesen Effekt mit Hilfe von geordneten Nanokristall-Strukturen künstlich zu erzeugen. Die Entdeckung könnte zukünftige Entwicklungen in den Bereichen LED-Beleuchtung, Quantensensorik, Quantenkommunikation und zukünftige Quantencomputik ermöglichen. Die Ergebnisse der Studie sind soeben in der renommierten Fachzeitschrift «Nature» erschienen.</lead>
      <text link="no">Einige Materialien emittieren spontan Licht, wenn sie von einer externen Quelle, etwa ein Laser, angeregt werden. Dieses Phänomen wird als Fluoreszenz bezeichnet. In mehreren Gasen und Quantensystemen kann es jedoch zu einer wesentlich stärkeren Lichtemission kommen, wenn sich die einzelnen Emitter innerhalb eines Ensembles spontan synchronisieren und bei Anregung gemeinsam wirken. Die Licht-Emission ist dabei um ein vielfaches stärker als die Summe der einzelnen Emitter, was zu einer ultraschnellen und intensiven Emission von Licht führt, genannt Superfluoreszenz.&lt;br /&gt;Der Effekt tritt jedoch nur auf, wenn die Emitter bestimmte Anforderungen erfüllen, wie gleiche Emissionsenergie, hohe Kupplungsstärke und eine lange Kohärenzzeit. Als solche interagieren sie stark miteinander, werden aber gleichzeitig nicht so leicht durch ihre Umgebung gestört. Dies war bisher bei technologisch relevanten Materialien nicht möglich. Kolloidale Quantenpunkte könnten sich allerdings dafür eignen, handelt es sich bei ihnen doch um einen bereits bewährten, kommerziell attraktiven Ansatz, der bereits in den fortschrittlichsten LCD-Fernsehdisplays zum Einsatz kommt – und sie erfüllen sämtliche Anforderungen.&lt;br /&gt;Forschende der Empa und ETH Zürich unter der Leitung von Maksym Kovalenko in Zusammenarbeit mit IBM Research Zürich haben nun gezeigt, dass die neueste Generation von Quantenpunkten aus Bleihalogenid-Perowskiten einen eleganten und bequemen Weg zur On-Demand-Superfluoreszenz bietet. Dazu ordneten die Forschenden Perowskit-Quantenpunkte zu einem dreidimensionalen Übergitter an, das eine kohärente und kollektive Emission von Photonen ermöglicht – und damit Superfluoreszenz erzeugt. Als Übergitter (engl. superlattice) bezeichnet man einen künstlichen Festkörper aus einer Abfolge dünner Schichten, die sich periodisch wiederholen. Das wiederum bildet die Basis für Quellen von verschränkten Multi-Photonen-Zuständen, bislang eine der fehlenden Schlüsselressourcen für Quantensensorik, Quantenbildgebung und photonisches Quantenrechnen.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;b&gt;Gleich und gleich gesellt sich gern&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Eine kohärente Kopplung der Quantenpunkte erfordert jedoch, dass sie alle die gleiche Grösse, Form und Zusammensetzung aufweisen, denn die Devise «Gleich und Gleich gesellt sich gern» gilt auch im Quantenuniversum. «Solche geordneten Übergitter können nur aus einer hochmonodispersen Lösung von Quantenpunkten gewonnen werden, deren Synthese wir in den letzten Jahren optimiert haben», sagt die Empa-Forscherin Maryna Bodnarchuk. Mit solchen «einheitlichen» Quantenpunkten in diversen Grössen konnten die Forschenden dann Übergitter bauen, indem sie die Verdampfung des Lösungsmittels entsprechend steuerten.&lt;br /&gt;Optische Experimente, die das Forscherteam bei Temperaturen von rund minus 267 Grad Celsius durchführte, lieferten dann den endgültigen Beweis für die Superfluoreszenz – die Photonen emittierten tatsächlich simultan. «Das war unsere Heureka-Moment, als wir erkannten, dass es sich um eine neuartige Quantenlichtquelle handelt», sagt Gabriele Rainò von der ETH Zürich und der Empa, der die optischen Experimente durchführte.&lt;br /&gt;Für das Forschungs-Team sind diese Experimente Ausgangspunkt, um kollektive Quantenphänomene mit dieser einzigartigen Materialklasse weiter zu nutzen. «Da die Eigenschaften des Ensembles gegenüber der Summe seiner Teile gesteigert werden können, kann man weit über das Engineering der einzelnen Quantenpunkte hinausgehen», ergänzt Michael Becker von der ETH und IBM Research. Das kontrollierte Erzeugen von Superfluoreszenz und dem entsprechenden Quantenlicht könnten neue Möglichkeiten in der Quanteninformatik, der Quantensensorik und der quantenverschlüsselten Kommunikation eröffnen.</text>
      <contact>Prof. Dr. Maksym Kovalenko Empa, Thin Films and Photovoltaics ETH, Functional Inorganic Materials Tel. +41 58 765 4557 Maksym.Kovalenko@empa.ch Dr. Maryna Bodnarchuck Empa, Thin Films and Photovoltaics Tel. +41 58 765 59 40 Maryna.Bodnarchuk@empa.ch Dr. Gabriele Rainò ETH Zurich, Laboratory of Inorganic Chemistry Tel. +41 44 633 09 97 rainog@ethz.ch Dr. Thilo Stöferle IBM Research – Zurich Phone +41 44 724 85 01 tof@zurich.ibm.com Redaktion / Medienkontakt Cornelia Zogg Empa, Kommunikation Tel. +41 58 765 45 99 redaktion@empa.ch</contact>
      <link id="183282">
        <title>Empa Medienmitteilung</title>
        <uri>https://www.empa.ch/web/s604/nature-superfluorescence</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Dübendorf, St. Gallen und Thun</city>
      <title>Une rafale de lumière "synchrone"</title>
      <lead>Les photo-émetteurs excités peuvent coopérer et rayonner simultanément, un phénomène appelé superfluorescence. Des chercheurs de l'Empa et de l’ETH, ainsi que des collègues d'IBM Research Zurich, ont récemment réussi à créer cet effet avec des super-réseaux nanocristallins ordonnés. Cette découverte pourrait permettre des développements futurs dans l'éclairage LED, la détection quantique, la communication quantique et l'informatique quantique. L'étude vient récemment d'être publiée dans la célèbre revue "Nature".</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Certains matériaux émettent spontanément de la lumière s'ils sont excités par une source externe, par exemple par un laser. Ce phénomène est connu sous le nom de fluorescence. Cependant, dans plusieurs gaz et systèmes quantiques, une émission de lumière beaucoup plus forte peut se produire lorsque les émetteurs au sein d'un ensemble synchronisent spontanément leur phase mécanique quantique entre eux et agissent ensemble lorsqu'ils sont excités. De cette façon, le rendement lumineux qui en résulte peut être beaucoup plus intense que la somme des émetteurs individuels, ce qui conduit à une émission de lumière ultra-rapide et lumineuse - superfluorescence. Cela ne se produit cependant que lorsque ces émetteurs répondent à des exigences strictes, telles que la même énergie d'émission, une force de couplage élevée avec le champ lumineux et un long temps de cohérence. En tant que tels, ils interagissent fortement les uns avec les autres, et en même temps, ils ne sont pas facilement perturbés par leur environnement. Jusqu'à présent, cela n’a été rendu possible avec aucun matériaux technologiquement pertinents. Les points quantiques colloïdaux pourraient rendre le phénomène possible ; ils sont une solution éprouvée et commercialement attrayante déjà utilisée dans les écrans de télévision LCD les plus avancés - et ils répondent à toutes les exigences.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Des chercheurs de l'Empa et de l'ETH Zurich, sous la direction de Maksym Kovalenko, ainsi que des collègues d'IBM Research Zurich, ont montré que la dernière génération de points quantiques en perovskites aux halogénures de plomb offre une voie élégante et pratique vers la superfluorescence sur demande. Pour cela, les chercheurs ont disposé des points quantiques de pérovskite en un super-réseau tridimensionnel, qui permet l'émission collective cohérente de photons - créant ainsi une superfluorescence. Ceci fournit la base pour les sources d'états multiphotons enchevêtrés, une ressource clé manquante pour la détection quantique, l'imagerie quantique et l'informatique quantique photonique.&lt;/p&gt;"Qui se ressemble s'assemble"&lt;p&gt;Un couplage cohérent entre les points quantiques exige cependant qu'ils aient tous la même taille, la même forme et la même composition, car le proverbe "Qui se ressemble s'assemble" est également valable dans l'univers quantique. "De tels super-réseaux ordonnés à longue portée ne peuvent être obtenus qu'à partir d'une solution de points quantiques hautement monodispersés, dont la synthèse a été soigneusement optimisée au cours des dernières années", explique Maryna Bodnarchuk, chercheuse principale à l'Empa. Avec de tels points quantiques "uniformes" de différentes tailles, l'équipe de recherche pourrait alors former des super-réseaux en contrôlant correctement l'évaporation du solvant.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;La preuve finale de la superfluorescence provient d'expériences optiques réalisées à des températures d'environ moins 267 degrés Celsius. Les chercheurs ont découvert que les photons étaient émis simultanément dans une rafale lumineuse : "C'était notre moment "Eureka !". Dès que nous avons réalisé qu'il s'agissait d'une source lumineuse quantique inédite", explique Gabriele Rainó, de l'ETH Zurich et de l'Empa, qui faisait partie de l'équipe qui a réalisé les expériences optiques.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Les chercheurs considèrent ces expériences comme un point de départ pour exploiter davantage les phénomènes quantiques collectifs avec cette classe unique de matériaux. "Comme les propriétés de l'ensemble peuvent être améliorées par rapport à la somme de ses parties, on peut aller bien au-delà de l'ingénierie des points quantiques individuels", ajoute Michael Becker de l'ETH Zurich et IBM Research. La génération contrôlée de la superfluorescence et de la lumière quantique correspondante pourrait ouvrir de nouvelles possibilités dans l'éclairage LED, la détection quantique, la communication chiffrée quantique et l'informatique quantique future.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Prof. Dr. Maksym Kovalenko Empa, Thin Films and Photovoltaics ETH, Functional Inorganic Materials Tel. +41 58 765 4557 Maksym.Kovalenko@empa.ch Dr. Maryna Bodnarchuck Empa, Thin Films and Photovoltaics Tel. +41 58 765 59 40 Maryna.Bodnarchuk@empa.ch Dr. Gabriele Rainò ETH Zurich, Laboratory of Inorganic Chemistry Tel. +41 44 633 09 97 rainog@ethz.ch Dr. Thilo Stöferle IBM Research – Zurich Phone +41 44 724 85 01 tof@zurich.ibm.com Rédaction / Contact médias Cornelia Zogg Empa, Kommunikation Tel. +41 58 765 45 99 redaktion@empa.ch</contact>
      <link id="183282">
        <title>Empa Medienmitteilung</title>
        <uri>https://www.empa.ch/web/s604/nature-superfluorescence</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Dübendorf, St. Gallen und Thun</city>
      <title>A burst of ”synchronous” light</title>
      <lead>Excited photo-emitters can cooperate and radiate simultaneously, a phenomenon called superfluorescence. Researchers from Empa and ETH Zurich, together with colleagues from IBM Research Zurich, have recently been able to create this effect with long-range ordered nanocrystal superlattices. This discovery could enable future developments in LED lighting, quantum sensing, quantum communication and future quantum computing. The study has just been published in the renowned journal "Nature".</lead>
      <text link="no">Some materials spontaneously emit light if they are excited by an external source, for instance a laser. This phenomenon is known as fluorescence. However, in several gases and quantum systems a much stronger emission of light can occur, when the emitters within an ensemble spontaneously synchronize their quantum mechanical phase with each other and act together when excited. In this way, the resulting light output can be much more intense than the sum of the individual emitters, leading to an ultrafast and bright emission of light – superfluorescence. It only occurs, however, when those emitters fulfill stringent requirements, such as having the same emission energy, high coupling strength to the light field and a long coherence time. As such, they are strongly interacting with each other but at the same time are not easily disturbed by their environment. This has not been possible up to now using technologically relevant materials. Colloidal quantum dots could just be the ticket; they are a proven, commercially appealing solution already employed in the most advanced LCD television displays – and they fulfill all the requirements. Researchers at Empa and ETH Zurich, led by Maksym Kovalenko, together with colleagues from IBM Research Zurich, have now shown that the most recent generation of quantum dots made of lead halide perovskites offer an elegant and practically convenient path to superfluorescence on-demand. For this, the researchers arranged perovskite quantum dots into a three-dimensional superlattice, which enables the coherent collective emission of photons – thus creating superfluorescence. This provides the basis for sources of entangled multi-photon states, a missing key resource for quantum sensing, quantum imaging and photonic quantum computing. “Birds of a feather flock together” A coherent coupling among quantum dots requires, however, that they all have the same size, shape and composition because “birds of a feather flock together” in the quantum universe, too. “Such long-range ordered superlattices could only be obtained from a highly monodisperse solution of quantum dots, the synthesis of which had been carefully optimized over the last few years,” said Maryna Bodnarchuk, a senior scientist at Empa. With such ”uniform” quantum dots of various sizes, the research team could then form superlattices by properly controlling the solvent evaporation. The final proof of superfluorescence came from optical experiments performed at temperatures of around minus 267 degrees Celsius. The researchers discovered that photons were emitted simultaneously in a bright burst: “This was our ‘Eureka! ‘ moment. The moment we realized that this was a novel quantum light source,” said Gabriele Rainó from ETH Zurich and Empa who was part of the team that carried out the optical experiments. The researchers consider these experiments as a starting point to further exploit collective quantum phenomena with this unique class of material. “As the properties of the ensemble can be boosted compared to just the sum of its parts, one can go way beyond engineering the individual quantum dots,” added Michael Becker from ETH Zurich and IBM Research. The controlled generation of superfluorescence and the corresponding quantum light could open new possibilities in LED lighting, quantum sensing, quantum-encrypted communication and future quantum computing. </text>
      <contact>Prof. Dr. Maksym Kovalenko Empa, Thin Films and Photovoltaics ETH, Functional Inorganic Materials Phone +41 58 765 4557 Maksym.Kovalenko@empa.ch Dr. Maryna Bodnarchuck Empa, Thin Films and Photovoltaics Phone +41 58 765 59 40 Maryna.Bodnarchuk@empa.ch Dr. Gabriele Rainò ETH Zurich, Laboratory of Inorganic Chemistry Phone +41 44 633 09 97 rainog@ethz.ch Dr. Thilo Stöferle IBM Research – Zurich Phone +41 44 724 85 01 tof@zurich.ibm.com Editor / Media contact Cornelia Zogg Empa, Communications Phone +41 58 765 45 99 redaktion@empa.ch</contact>
      <link id="183282">
        <title>Empa Medienmitteilung</title>
        <uri>https://www.empa.ch/web/s604/nature-superfluorescence</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="8">
        <name lang="de">Bildung und Forschung</name>
        <name lang="fr">Formation et recherche</name>
        <name lang="it">Formazione e ricerca</name>
        <name lang="en">Education and Research</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="28">
        <name lang="de">Telekommunikation</name>
        <name lang="fr">Télécommunications</name>
        <name lang="it">Telecomunicazione</name>
        <name lang="en">Telecommunications</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
