<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="93285" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2023-02-23</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="201" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>201</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="201">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>New York</city>
      <title>UNO-Generalversammlung: Bundesrat Ignazio Cassis verurteilt die Aggression Russlands und ruft zu einer dauerhaften Friedenslösung in der Ukraine auf</title>
      <lead>Bundesrat Ignazio Cassis nahm am 23. Februar 2023 an einer dringlichen Sondersitzung der UNO-Generalversammlung in New York teil. Im Zentrum stand die seit einem Jahr andauernde militärische Aggression Russlands gegen die Ukraine. Der Vorsteher des EDA sprach sich für die Resolution der Generalversammlung zugunsten einer friedlichen Lösung des Konflikts aus. </lead>
      <text link="no">Bundesrat Ignazio Cassis weilt Ende dieser Woche, ein Jahr nach dem Ausbruch des Krieges in der Ukraine, am Sitz der Vereinten Nationen in New York, um an einer dringlichen Sondersitzung der UNO-Generalversammlung und an einer Debatte im Sicherheitsrat teilzunehmen. Der Vorsteher des EDA betonte in seiner Stellungnahme, dass die Schweiz die andauernde militärische Aggression Russlands gegen die Ukraine auf das Schärfste verurteilt. Er forderte eine sofortige Beendigung des Konflikts und den Abzug der russischen Streitkräfte aus dem souveränen Hoheitsgebiet der Ukraine. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;«Mit der heutigen Resolution senden wir ein starkes Zeichen des Friedens und der Achtung unserer gemeinsamen Grundsätze», sagte Bundesrat Cassis vor der Generalversammlung. In der Resolution werden die UNO-Mitgliedstaaten und internationalen Organisationen aufgefordert, ihre Friedensbemühungen zu verstärken. «Ein klares Signal der Staatengemeinschaft an Russland», so der Vorsteher des EDA, der zudem an die gesamte internationale Gemeinschaft appellierte, «sich geschlossen für eine friedliche Lösung dieses Konflikts einzusetzen». &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Die militärische Aggression Russlands gegen die Ukraine stellt eine schwere Verletzung der UNO-Charta dar. Die Genfer Konventionen schützen die Personen, die nicht oder nicht mehr an den Feindseligkeiten teilnehmen. Der Krieg hat zudem besorgniserregende Auswirkungen auf die weltweite Sicherheit und hat zu massiven Vertreibungen der Zivilbevölkerung sowie zu Ernährungs- und Energieunsicherheit weit über die Grenzen der Ukraine hinaus geführt. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Am 24. Februar 2023 wird Bundesrat Ignazio Cassis an einer Debatte im UNO-Sicherheitsrat teilnehmen, die ebenfalls im Zeichen der Ukrainekrise steht. Die Schweiz will ihr zweijähriges Sicherheitsratsmandat nutzen, um den Multilateralismus durch mehr Solidarität, mehr Dialog und mehr Einheit zu stärken. Diese Werte wird die Schweiz während ihrer Ratspräsidentschaft im Mai dieses Jahres aktiv voranbringen. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Bundesrat Cassis nutzt seinen Aufenthalt in New York auch für verschiedene bilaterale Kontakte. Ausserdem nimmt er virtuell an einer Sondersitzung des Ständigen Rates der OSZE in Wien zum Thema Ukraine teil. </text>
      <contact>Kommunikation EDA Bundeshaus West CH-3003 Bern Tel. Kommunikationsservice: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Medienstelle: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <link id="243177">
        <title>Medienmitteilung 22.02.23 zur BR-Bilanz des Schweizer Engagements</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home/das-eda/aktuell/news.html/content/eda/de/meta/news/2023/2/22/93261</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="243178">
        <title>Newsticker: Schweizer Einsatz in der Ukraine</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home/das-eda/aktuell/newsuebersicht/2022/02/ukraine.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="243179">
        <title>Newsticker: Mitgliedschaft der Schweiz im UNO-Sicherheitsrat</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home/das-eda/aktuell/newsuebersicht/2023/uno-sicherheitsrat.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="243187">
        <title>Déclaration lue par le Conseiller fédéral Ignazio Cassis à l'Assemblée générale de l'ONU</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae/dfae/aktuell/reden.html/content/eda/fr/meta/speeches/2023/2/23/93279</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>New York</city>
      <title>Assemblée générale de l’ONU: Le conseiller fédéral Ignazio Cassis dénonce l’agression russe et appelle à une solution de paix durable en Ukraine</title>
      <lead>Le conseiller fédéral Ignazio Cassis a participé le 23 février 2023 à une séance extraordinaire d’urgence de l'Assemblée générale de l'ONU à New York. L'agression militaire de la Russie contre l'Ukraine, qui dure depuis un an, était au centre des discussions. Le chef du DFAE s’est exprimé en soutien de la résolution de l’Assemblée générale pour un règlement pacifique de ce conflit. </lead>
      <text link="no">Le conseiller fédéral Ignazio Cassis est présent au siège des Nations Unies à New York en cette fin de semaine, un an après le déclenchement de la guerre en Ukraine. Il participe à une session extraordinaire d’urgence de l’Assemblée générale, ainsi qu’à un débat au sein du Conseil de sécurité. L’occasion pour le chef du DFAE de rappeler la condamnation ferme par la Suisse de l’agression russe toujours en cours contre l’Ukraine. Et d’appeler à la cessation immédiate du conflit et au retrait des troupes armées russes du territoire souverain ukrainien.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;« Avec la résolution d’aujourd’hui, notre intention est d’envoyer un message fort de paix et de respect des principes qui nous unissent » a déclaré Ignazio Cassis devant l’Assemblée générale. Ce nouveau texte appelle les Etats membres de l'ONU et les organisations internationales à accroître leur engagement en faveur de la paix. Un signal clair envoyé par la communauté internationale à la Russie selon le chef du DFAE, qui souligne au passage son appel à toute la communauté internationale « à œuvrer main dans la main en vue d’un règlement pacifique de ce conflit ».&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;L'agression militaire de la Russie contre l'Ukraine constitue une violation grave de la Charte de l'ONU. Les Conventions de Genève protègent les personnes ne participant pas ou plus aux hostilités. Les conséquences de la guerre ont par ailleurs des répercussions préoccupantes sur la sécurité dans le monde et ont entraîné d'importants déplacements de populations civiles, ainsi qu’une insécurité alimentaire et énergétique. Des effets négatifs qui se font sentir bien au-delà des frontières de l'Ukraine.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Le 24 février, le conseiller fédéral Ignazio Cassis participera à un débat du Conseil de sécurité de l'ONU, également sur le thème de l’Ukraine. La Suisse entend utiliser son mandat de deux ans dans cette enceinte pour renforcer le multilatéralisme avec plus de solidarité, plus de dialogue et plus d'unité. Des valeurs que la Suisse mettra activement en avant lors de sa présidence du Conseil durant le mois de mai prochain.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Le chef du DFAE a également profité de son séjour à New York pour établir différents contacts bilatéraux. Il se joindra en outre virtuellement à une séance spéciale du Conseil permanent de l'OSCE à Vienne sur l’Ukraine.</text>
      <contact>Communication DFAE Palais fédéral ouest CH-3003 Berne Tél. Service de communication: +41 58 462 31 53 Tél. Service de presse: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <link id="243176">
        <title>Communiqué du 22.02.23 - Bilan du Conseil fédéral de son engagement</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae/dfae/aktuell/news.html/content/eda/fr/meta/news/2023/2/22/93261</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="243174">
        <title>Newsticker Engagement de la Suisse en Ukraine</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home/das-eda/aktuell/newsuebersicht/2022/02/ukraine.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="243175">
        <title>Newsticker: Aperçu des actualités - Le Conseil de sécurité de l'ONU</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae/dfae/aktuell/newsuebersicht/2023/uno-sicherheitsrat.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="243187">
        <title>Déclaration lue par le Conseiller fédéral Ignazio Cassis à l'Assemblée générale de l'ONU</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae/dfae/aktuell/reden.html/content/eda/fr/meta/speeches/2023/2/23/93279</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>New York</city>
      <title>Dinanzi all’Assemblea generale dell’ONU, il consigliere federale Ignazio Cassis condanna l’aggressione russa e chiede una pace duratura in Ucraina</title>
      <lead>Il 23 febbraio 2023 il consigliere federale Ignazio Cassis ha partecipato a una sessione speciale di emergenza dell’Assemblea generale dell’ONU a New York. Le discussioni si sono concentrate sull’aggressione militare della Russia contro l’Ucraina, che si protrae ormai da un anno. Il capo del Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri (DFAE) è intervenuto a sostegno della risoluzione dell’Assemblea generale per una soluzione pacifica del conflitto. </lead>
      <text link="no"> A un anno dallo scoppio della guerra in Ucraina, questo fine settimana il consigliere federale Ignazio Cassis si trova presso la sede delle Nazioni Unite a New York per partecipare a una sessione speciale di emergenza dell’Assemblea generale e a un dibattito in seno al Consiglio di sicurezza. In questa occasione, il capo del DFAE ribadisce la ferma condanna da parte della Svizzera dell’aggressione russa contro l’Ucraina tuttora in atto e chiede la cessazione immediata della guerra oltre che il ritiro delle truppe russe dal territorio sovrano ucraino.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;«Con la risoluzione di oggi lanciamo un forte messaggio di pace e di rispetto dei principi che ci uniscono», ha dichiarato Ignazio Cassis dinanzi all’Assemblea generale. Questo nuovo testo esorta gli Stati membri dell’ONU e le organizzazioni internazionali a rafforzare il proprio impegno a favore della pace. Il capo del DFAE ritiene che si tratti di un segnale chiaro inviato alla Russia da parte della comunità internazionale e sottolinea il suo appello a quest’ultima affinché «collabori in vista di una soluzione pacifica del conflitto». &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;L’aggressione militare della Russia contro l’Ucraina costituisce una grave violazione dello Statuto dell’ONU. Le Convenzioni di Ginevra proteggono le persone che non partecipano alle ostilità o hanno smesso di farlo. La guerra ha anche conseguenze preoccupanti per la sicurezza nel mondo e ha provocato massicci movimenti migratori, oltre che insicurezza alimentare ed energetica, tutti effetti negativi percepibili ben oltre i confini dell’Ucraina. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Il 24 febbraio il consigliere federale Cassis prenderà parte a un dibattito del Consiglio di sicurezza dell’ONU, anch’esso incentrato sull’Ucraina. Durante il suo mandato biennale in questo organo, la Svizzera intende contribuire al rafforzamento del multilateralismo facendo leva su una maggiore solidarietà, unione e capacità di dialogo, valori che promuoverà attivamente durante la sua presidenza del Consiglio il prossimo maggio. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Il capo del DFAE ha colto l’occasione della sua permanenza a New York anche per svolgere vari incontri bilaterali. Parteciperà inoltre virtualmente a una seduta straordinaria del Consiglio permanente dell’OSCE a Vienna dedicata all’Ucraina.</text>
      <contact>Comunicazione DFAE Palazzo federale ovest CH-3003 Berna Tel. Servizio di comunicazione: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Servizio stampa: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <link id="243180">
        <title>Communicato stampa Un anno di guerra contro l’Ucraina: il Consiglio federale stila un bilancio del suo operato e richiede un nuovo pacchetto di aiuti</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae/dfae/aktuell/news.html/content/eda/it/meta/news/2023/2/22/93261</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="243181">
        <title>Ultim’ora: impegno della Svizzera in Ucraina</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae/dfae/aktuell/newsuebersicht/2022/02/ukraine.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="243182">
        <title>Ultim’ora: la Svizzera nel Consiglio di sicurezza dell’ONU</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae/dfae/aktuell/newsuebersicht/2023/uno-sicherheitsrat.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="243187">
        <title>Déclaration lue par le Conseiller fédéral Ignazio Cassis à l'Assemblée générale de l'ONU</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae/dfae/aktuell/reden.html/content/eda/fr/meta/speeches/2023/2/23/93279</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>New York</city>
      <title>UN General Assembly: Ignazio Cassis condemns Russian aggression and calls for path to lasting peace in Ukraine</title>
      <lead>On 23 February 2023, Federal Councillor Ignazio Cassis, head of the FDFA, attended an emergency special session of the UN General Assembly in New York. The deliberations focused on Russia's ongoing military aggression against Ukraine, which began a year ago. Mr Cassis voiced his support for the General Assembly's resolution calling for a peaceful settlement of the conflict. </lead>
      <text link="no">Mr Cassis is at the United Nations headquarters in New York this weekend, one year after the outbreak of the war in Ukraine. He is taking part in an emergency special session of the General Assembly, as well as in a Security Council debate. This serves as an occasion for him to reiterate Switzerland's strong condemnation of the Russian aggression against Ukraine, still under way, and to call for an immediate end to the conflict and the withdrawal of Russian troops from Ukraine's sovereign territory.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;"With today's resolution, we are sending out a strong message of peace and respect for the principles that unite us," said Mr Cassis before the General Assembly. The new text calls on UN member states and international organisations to strengthen their support for peace. For Mr Cassis, who stressed his appeal to the entire international community "to work hand in hand towards a peaceful settlement of this conflict," it is a clear signal from the international community to Russia. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Russia's military aggression against Ukraine is a serious violation of the UN Charter. The Geneva Conventions protect persons not or no longer participating in hostilities. The consequences of the war are also having a serious impact on global security and have led to large-scale displacement of populations, as well as food and energy insecurity. These negative effects are felt far beyond Ukraine's borders.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;On 24 February, Mr Cassis will take part in a UN Security Council debate also held to address the situation in Ukraine. Switzerland seeks to use its two-year term in this forum to strengthen multilateralism with more solidarity, more dialogue and more unity – values that Switzerland will strongly promote this coming May in particular, as it will then hold the presidency of the Security Council.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Mr Cassis is also using his stay in New York to establish various bilateral contacts. In addition, he will join (virtually) a Ukraine-themed special meeting of the OSCE Permanent Council in Vienna.</text>
      <contact>FDFA Communication Federal Palace West Wing CH-3003 Bern, Switzerland Tel. Communication service: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Press service: +41 58 460 55 55 E-mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @SwissMFA</contact>
      <link id="243183">
        <title>Press release of 22 February about Federal Council taking stock of Swiss engagement</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/fdfa/fdfa/aktuell/news.html/content/eda/en/meta/news/2023/2/22/93261</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="243184">
        <title>News platform: Switzerland's engagement in Ukraine</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/fdfa/fdfa/aktuell/newsuebersicht/2022/02/ukraine.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="243185">
        <title>News platform: Switzerland's membership of the UN Security Council</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/fdfa/fdfa/aktuell/newsuebersicht/2023/uno-sicherheitsrat.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="243186">
        <title>UN General Assembly: Declaration by Federal Councilor Ignazio Cassis</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/fdfa/fdfa/aktuell/reden.html/content/eda/en/meta/speeches/2023/2/23/93279</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <offers>
      <offer id="313" org-id="201">
        <name lang="de">Schweizerische Europapolitik</name>
        <name lang="fr">Politique européenne de la Suisse</name>
        <name lang="it">Politica europea della Svizzera</name>
        <name lang="en">Swiss policy on the EU</name>
      </offer>
    </offers>
    <topics>
      <topic id="3">
        <name lang="de">Armee</name>
        <name lang="fr">Armée</name>
        <name lang="it">Esercito</name>
        <name lang="en">Armed Forces</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="10">
        <name lang="de">Bundesrat</name>
        <name lang="fr">Conseil fédéral</name>
        <name lang="it">Consiglio federale</name>
        <name lang="en">Federal Council</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="30">
        <name lang="de">Ausserordentliche Lagen</name>
        <name lang="fr">Situations extraordinaires</name>
        <name lang="it">Situazioni straordinarie</name>
        <name lang="en">Special Situations</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="34">
        <name lang="de">Europa</name>
        <name lang="fr">Europe</name>
        <name lang="it">Europa</name>
        <name lang="en">Europe</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="40">
        <name lang="de">Sicherheit</name>
        <name lang="fr">Sécurité</name>
        <name lang="it">Sicurezza</name>
        <name lang="en">Security</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
