<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="62584" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2016-07-08</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="324" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>301</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Swissmedic, Schweizerisches Heilmittelinstitut</name>
      <name lang="fr">Swissmedic, Institut suisse des produits thérapeutiques</name>
      <name lang="it">Swissmedic, Istituto svizzero per gli agenti terapeutici</name>
      <name lang="en">Swiss Agency for Therapeutic Products</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.swissmedic.ch/</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.swissmedic.ch/?lang=3</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.swissmedic.ch/?lang=4</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.swissmedic.ch/?lang=2</www>
      <email lang="de"/>
      <email lang="fr"/>
      <email lang="it"/>
      <email lang="en"/>
    </originator>
    <department id="301">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement des Innern</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'intérieur</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'interno</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Home Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Rückruf von Einweg-Waschhandschuhen "SINAQUA™ Dermal Glove" wegen Gefahr bakterieller Infektionen</title>
      <lead>Im Rahmen der Marktüberwachung für Medizinprodukte wurde Swissmedic eine Kontamination von Einweg-Waschhandschuhen mit der Bakterienart Burkholderia cepacia gemeldet. Diese Bakterien können schwere Infektionen verursachen. Die Schweizer Vertriebsfirma hat die betroffenen Chargen vom Markt zurückgerufen.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Die Gründe der Kontamination sind noch nicht bekannt. Entsprechende Abklärungen beim italienischen Hersteller sind im Gang. Die Handschuhe werden unter anderem für die lokale Hautreinigung vor und nach Operationen oder für die Körperpflege empfindlicher Hautstellen verwendet.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Die Schweizer Vertriebsfirma hat entschieden, alle möglicherweise betroffenen und zwischen November 2015 und Mai 2016 in der Schweiz ausgelieferten Chargen zurückzuziehen und erst wieder Ware auszuliefern, wenn diese einwandfrei ist.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Alle belieferten Kunden wurden von der Vertriebsfirma direkt angeschrieben. Swissmedic hat den Rückruf auf der Webseite publiziert und alle Kontaktpersonen in den Spitälern entsprechend informiert.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Anwenderinnen und Anwender werden aufgefordert, die Einweg-Waschhandschuhe "SINAQUA™ Dermal Glove", Artikel Nr. WEL-95580, im Moment nicht mehr zu verwenden.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Swissmedic erinnert in diesem Zusammenhang an die Verantwortung der Spitäler, ein internes Meldesystem zu unterhalten und dem Institut schwerwiegende Vorkommnisse mit Medizinprodukten zu melden.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Lukas Jaggi, Mediensprecher a.i. +41 58 462 02 76 media@swissmedic.ch</contact>
      <attachment id="154247">
        <title>Betroffenes Produkt: "SINAQUA™ Dermal Glove" Einweg-Waschhandschuhe, Artikelbezeichnung WEL-95580</title>
        <format>jpg</format>
        <size-kb>1334</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/44831.jpg</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <link id="154251">
        <title>Swissmedic, Abteilung Medizinprodukte</title>
        <uri>https://www.swissmedic.ch/medizinprodukte/02635/index.html?lang=de</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Rappel des gants de soin à usage unique «SINAQUA™ Dermal Glove» en raison d’un risque de contamination bactérienne</title>
      <lead>Dans le cadre de la surveillance du marché des dispositifs médicaux, Swissmedic a été averti au sujet d'une contamination de gants de soin à usage unique par des bactéries de l’espèce burkholderia cepacia. Ces bactéries peuvent engendrer des infections graves. Le distributeur suisse a retiré du marché les lots concernés.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Les raisons de cette contamination n’ont pas encore été identifiées, mais des vérifications sont actuellement en cours chez le fabricant italien. Ces gants sont utilisés notamment pour nettoyer localement la peau avant et après les opérations ou pour soigner les zones cutanées sensibles.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Le distributeur suisse a décidé de rappeler tous les lots qui ont été livrés en Suisse entre novembre 2015 et mai 2016 et qui pourraient être concernés, ainsi que de ne reprendre les livraisons de ces marchandises que lorsqu’elles seront irréprochables.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Tous les clients auxquels ces gants avaient été livrés ont été contactés directement par le distributeur. Swissmedic a publié le présent rappel sur son site Internet et dûment informé toutes les personnes de contact dans les hôpitaux.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;À ce stade, il est demandé aux utilisateurs de ne plus utiliser les gants de soin à usage unique «SINAQUA™ Dermal Glove», numéro d'article WEL-95580.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Swissmedic rappelle en l’occurrence aux hôpitaux qu’ils sont tenus de disposer d’un système d’annonce opérationnel ainsi que d’annoncer à l’institut les incidents graves qui concernent des dispositifs médicaux.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Lukas Jaggi, porte-parole a.i. +41 58 462 02 76 media@swissmedic.ch</contact>
      <attachment id="154248">
        <title>Le produit visé par ce retrait: «SINAQUA™ Dermal Glove» gants de soin à usage unique, numéro d'article WEL-95580</title>
        <format>jpg</format>
        <size-kb>1334</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/44832.jpg</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <link id="154252">
        <title>Swissmedic, division dispositifs médicaux</title>
        <uri>https://www.swissmedic.ch/medizinprodukte/02635/index.html?lang=fr</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Richiamo di guanti preimbevuti monouso «SINAQUA™ Dermal Glove» per rischio di infezioni batteriche</title>
      <lead>Nel quadro della sorveglianza di mercato per i dispositivi medici, a Swissmedic è stato notificato un caso di contaminazione di guanti preimbevuti monouso con batteri del tipo Burkholderia cepacia. Questi batteri possono causare infezioni gravi. Il distributore svizzero ha richiamato dal mercato i lotti interessati.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;I motivi della contaminazione non sono ancora noti. Al momento sono in corso le relative indagini presso il fabbricante italiano. I guanti vengono utilizzati fra l’altro per la pulizia locale della cute prima e dopo le operazioni o per l’igiene di aree delicate del corpo.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Il distributore svizzero ha deciso di ritirare tutti i lotti potenzialmente interessati, consegnati in Svizzera fra novembre 2015 e maggio 2016, e di riprendere le forniture solo quando la merce sarà di nuovo qualitativamente sicura.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Tutti i clienti interessati sono stati contattati per iscritto dal distributore. Swissmedic ha pubblicato il richiamo sul sito e ha informato a riguardo tutte le persone di riferimento negli ospedali.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Gli utilizzatori interessati sono pregati di non impiegare al momento il prodotto «SINAQUA™ Dermal Glove» guanti preimbevuti monouso, articolo n. WEL-95580.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;In questa occasione Swissmedic richiama gli ospedali alla loro responsabilità di gestire un sistema di comunicazione interno e di notificare all’Istituto gli eventi gravi riguardanti i dispositivi medici.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Lukas Jaggi, portavoce a.i. +41 58 462 02 76 media@swissmedic.ch</contact>
      <attachment id="154249">
        <title>Il prodotto oggetto del richiamo: «SINAQUA™ Dermal Glove» guanti preimbevuti monouso, articolo n. WEL-95580</title>
        <format>jpg</format>
        <size-kb>1334</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/44833.jpg</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <link id="154253">
        <title>Swissmedic, divisione dispositivi medici</title>
        <uri>https://www.swissmedic.ch/medizinprodukte/02635/02639/03162/index.html?lang=it</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>"SINAQUA™ Dermal Glove" disposable washing gloves recalled due to the risk of bacterial infections</title>
      <lead>As part of market surveillance activities for medical devices, a case of contamination of disposable washing gloves with the bacterial species Burkholderia cepacia has been reported to Swissmedic. These bacteria can cause severe infections. The Swiss distributor has recalled the affected batches.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;The reasons for the contamination are not yet known. Appropriate investigations are underway at the Italian manufacturer. The gloves are used partly for topical skin cleansing before and after operations or for personal hygiene on sensitive skin areas.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Swiss distributor has decided to withdraw all potentially affected batches that were delivered to Switzerland between November 2015 and May 2016, and to resume delivery of the product only when it is flawless.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The distributor has written directly to all the customers it has supplied. Swissmedic has published the recall on its website and informed all hospital contact people.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Users are asked to stop using the "SINAQUA™ Dermal Glove" disposable washing gloves, article description WEL-95580.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;In this connection, Swissmedic would remind hospitals of their responsibility to maintain an internal reporting system and their obligation to inform the Agency of any serious incidents involving medical devices.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Lukas Jaggi, Acting spokesman (ad interim) +41 58 462 02 76 media@swissmedic.ch</contact>
      <attachment id="154250">
        <title>Affected product: "SINAQUA™ Dermal Glove" disposable washing gloves, article description WEL-95580</title>
        <format>jpg</format>
        <size-kb>1334</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/44834.jpg</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <link id="154254">
        <title>Swissmedic, Medical Devices Division</title>
        <uri>https://www.swissmedic.ch/medizinprodukte/02635/index.html?lang=en</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="15">
        <name lang="de">Gesundheit</name>
        <name lang="fr">Santé</name>
        <name lang="it">sanità</name>
        <name lang="en">Health</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
