<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="62732" revoked="no">
    <version>3</version>
    <pubdate>2016-07-18</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="201" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>201</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="401" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>401</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Justiz- und Polizeidepartement</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de justice et police</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale di giustizia e polizia</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Justice and Police</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.ejpd.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.ejpd.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.ejpd.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.ejpd.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-ejpd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">Info@gs-ejpd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-ejpd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-ejpd.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="201">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <department id="401">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Justiz- und Polizeidepartement</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de justice et police</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale di giustizia e polizia</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Justice and Police</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.ejpd.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.ejpd.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.ejpd.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.ejpd.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-ejpd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">Info@gs-ejpd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-ejpd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-ejpd.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Türkei: Das EDA ruft zur Versöhnung der demokratischen Kräfte auf</title>
      <lead>Nach dem Staatsstreich in der Türkei ruft das EDA zur nationalen Einheit und zur Versöhnung der türkischen Gesellschaft auf.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Das EDA unterstützt die rechtmässige und demokratisch gewählte Regierung der Türkei, nachdem es den Putschversuch vom 16. Juli 2016 unmissverständlich verurteilt hatte. Die Schweiz spricht der Türkei und den Menschen, die durch diese tragischen Ereignisse Tote und Verletzte zu beklagen haben, ihr tiefes Beileid und ihre Solidarität aus.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Das EDA ruft die türkischen Behörden auf, Zurückhaltung zu üben, um die nationale Einheit zu bewahren und auf eine Versöhnung der türkischen Gesellschaft hinzuwirken. Dabei soll jegliche Willkür vermieden, und die Menschenrechte und die Rechtsstaatlichkeit sollen gemäss den internationalen Verpflichtungen der Türkei eingehalten werden. Für die Schweiz ist ein Verzicht auf die Todesstrafe integraler Bestandteil der Menschenrechte. Im Übrigen muss die Unabhängigkeit der Gerichte gewahrt werden. Das EDA hat dem türkischen Geschäftsträger, der auf sein Ersuchen am 18. Juli 2016 empfangen wurde, die Position der Schweiz dargelegt.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Bundesrat Didier Burkhalter verurteilte am 17. Juli 2016 den Putschversuch in der Türkei. Er wies darauf hin, dass Gewalt nicht das richtige Mittel ist, um in einer demokratischen Gesellschaft politische Positionen durchzusetzen. Ausserdem rief er zur Einhaltung der Menschenrechte und der Rechtsstaatlichkeit auf: «Jede Verbesserung der Menschenrechtslage ist ein Zeichen der Stärke.»&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Kommunikation EDA Bundeshaus West CH-3003 Bern Tel. Kommunikationsservice: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Medienstelle: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <revisions>
        <revision date="2016-07-19 14:26" type="R"/>
      </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Turquie: le DFAE appelle à la réconciliation des forces démocratiques</title>
      <lead>Après la tentative de coup d’Etat en Turquie, le DFAE appelle à la préservation de l’unité nationale et à la réconciliation de la société turque.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Le DFAE soutient le gouvernement légitime et démocratiquement élu en Turquie après avoir condamné de manière univoque la tentative de coup d’Etat du 16 juillet 2016. La Suisse exprime ses sincères condoléances et sa solidarité à la Turquie et aux proches des personnes qui ont perdu la vie ou qui ont été blessées dans ces circonstances tragiques.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Le DFAE appelle les autorités turques à faire preuve de retenue pour préserver l’unité nationale du pays et à œuvrer en faveur de la réconciliation de la société turque en évitant tout arbitraire et en respectant les droits de l’homme et l’Etat de droit conformément à leurs engagements internationaux. Pour la Suisse, le renoncement à la peine de mort fait partie des droits de l’homme. Par ailleurs il est essentiel pour la Suisse que l’indépendance des tribunaux soit garantie. Le DFAE a exprimé cette position au chargé d’affaires turc reçu, à sa demande, ce lundi 18 juillet 2016.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Le conseiller fédéral Didier Burkhalter a condamné le 17 juillet 2016 la tentative de coup d’Etat en Turquie. Il a souligné que, dans une société démocratique, la violence ne peut être considérée comme un moyen acceptable pour faire valoir ses positions politiques. Il a également appelé au respect des droits de l’homme et de l’état de droit : « Toute amélioration des droits de l’homme est un signe de force ».&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Communication DFAE Palais fédéral ouest CH-3003 Berne Tél. Service de communication: +41 58 462 31 53 Tél. Service de presse: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <revisions>
        <revision date="2016-07-18 17:34" type="R"/>
        <revision date="2016-07-19 14:26" type="R"/>
      </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Turchia: il DFAE fa appello alla riconciliazione delle forze democratiche</title>
      <lead>Dopo il tentativo di colpo di Stato in Turchia, il DFAE fa appello alla preservazione dell’unità nazionale e alla riconciliazione della società turca.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Il DFAE sostiene il governo legittimo e democraticamente eletto in Turchia, dopo aver condannato in modo univoco il tentativo di colpo di Stato del 16 luglio 2016. La Svizzera esprime le sue più sentite condoglianze e la sua solidarietà alla Turchia e alle famiglie delle persone che hanno perso la vita o sono rimaste ferite in queste tragiche circostanze.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Il DFAE esorta le autorità turche a dare prova di moderazione per preservare l’unità nazionale del Paese e ad impegnarsi a favore della riconciliazione della società, evitando ogni forma di arbitrio e rispettando i diritti umani e lo Stato di diritto, conformemente agli impegni internazionali presi. Per la Svizzera, la rinuncia alla pena di morte è parte integrante dei diritti umani ed è inoltre essenziale che l’indipendenza dei tribunali sia garantita. Il DFAE ha espresso questa sua posizione all’incaricato d’affari turco, ricevuto su sua richiesta lunedì 18 luglio 2016.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Il 17 luglio 2016, il consigliere federale Didier Burkhalter ha condannato il tentato colpo di Stato in Turchia, sottolineando che in una società democratica la violenza non può essere considerata un mezzo accettabile per far valere le proprie posizioni politiche. Burkhalter ha inoltre esortato al rispetto dei diritti umani e dello Stato di diritto: «Ogni miglioramento della situazione dei diritti umani è segno di forza».&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Comunicazione DFAE Palazzo federale ovest CH-3003 Berna Tel. Servizio di comunicazione: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Servizio stampa: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <revisions>
        <revision date="2016-07-19 14:26" type="R"/>
      </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Turkey: the FDFA calls for reconciliation among democratic forces</title>
      <lead>Following the attempted coup d'état in Turkey, the FDFA calls for the preservation of national unity and the reconciliation of Turkish society.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Having unequivocally condemned the attempted coup d'état of 16 July 2016, the FDFA supports the legitimate and democratically elected government of Turkey. Switzerland expresses its sincere condolences and solidarity to Turkey and to the families of those who lost their lives or were injured during this tragic event.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The FDFA calls on the Turkish authorities to show restraint in order to preserve the country's national unity and to work towards the reconciliation of Turkish society while refraining from arbitrary acts and respecting human rights and the rule of law in accordance with Turkey's international commitments. It is Switzerland's position that compliance with human rights includes the rejection of the death penalty. Switzerland also considers it imperative that the independence of the judicial system be guaranteed. The FDFA expressed this position to the Turkish chargé d’affaires, who was received at his request on Monday 18 July 2016.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;On 17 July, Federal Councillor Didier Burkhalter condemned the coup attempt in Turkey. He stressed that in a democratic society, violence cannot be considered an acceptable means of expressing political positions. He also called for respect for human rights and the rule of law: "Any improvement in human rights is a sign of strength."&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>FDFA Communication Federal Palace West Wing CH-3003 Bern, Switzerland Tel. Communication service: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Press service: +41 58 460 55 55 E-mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @SwissMFA</contact>
      <revisions>
        <revision date="2016-07-19 14:26" type="R"/>
      </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
