<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="29403" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2009-10-06</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="201" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>201</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="201">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Bundesrätin Micheline Calmy-Rey führte in Duschanbe politische Gespräche</title>
      <lead>Auf der zweiten Station ihrer Zentralasien-Reise wurde die Vorsteherin des EDA vom Präsidenten Tadschikistans, Emomali Rachmon, empfangen. Sie traf auch ihren Amtskollegen Hamrokhon Zarifi, mit dem sie über verschiedene Projekte sprach, die die beiden Länder gemeinsam durchgeführt haben, insbesondere im Bereich des Wasserressourcenmanagements.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Tadschikistan gehört nebst Usbekistan und Kirgisistan zu den Schwerpunktländern der schweizerischen Entwicklungszusammenarbeit in dieser Region. Im Zentrum steht insbesondere ein besseres Wasserressourcenmanagement im Ferghana-Tal, einer aus ethnischer und politischer Sicht äusserst komplexen Region, da sie durch die Grenzen der drei Länder geteilt wird. Durch einen vernünftigeren Wasserverbrauch sowohl für die Bewässerung der Felder als auch für die Energieerzeugung trägt die Schweiz zu mehr Stabilität in der Region bei.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Die Zusammenarbeit im Rahmen multilateraler Gremien, insbesondere in ihrer Stimmrechtsgruppe der Bretton-Woods-Institutionen (Internationaler Währungsfond, Weltbank), war ebenfalls Thema der Gespräche zwischen den zwei Aussenministern.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Es ist geplant, dass die beiden Länder demnächst einen Menschenrechtsdialog aufnehmen. Die Schweiz führt bereits mit anderen Ländern wie Vietnam einen solchen Dialog, der von konkreten Projekten begleitet wird.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Bundesrätin Michelin Calmy-Rey und ihr Amtskollege Zarifi vereinbarten eine verstärkte Zusammenarbeit, um die Grundlagen für gute Wirtschaftsbeziehungen zwischen den beiden Ländern zu schaffen. Die Schweiz hofft insbesondere, dass das Investitionsschutzabkommen, das im Juni 2009 unterzeichnet wurde, von Tadschikistan rasch ratifiziert wird. Die Schweiz hat zudem zu Diskussionen über ein zukünftiges Kooperationsabkommen im Bereich der Wirtschaft angeregt. Die Vorsteherin des EDA reiste am Nachmittag nach Kasachstan weiter, der dritten Station ihrer Zentralasien-Reise.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Information EDA Bundeshaus West CH-3003 Bern Tel.: +41 (0)31 322 31 53 Fax: +41 (0)31 324 90 47 E-Mail: info@eda.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="60618">
        <title>Dossier: Reise in Zentralasien vom 4. bis 9. Oktober 2009</title>
        <uri>http://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home/dfa/head/event/2009/centralasia.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="60621">
        <title>Bilaterale Beziehungen Schweiz - Tadschikistan</title>
        <uri>http://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home/reps/asia/vtik/biltad.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="60622">
        <title>Schweizerische Entwicklungszusammenarbeit in Zentralasien</title>
        <uri>http://www.deza.admin.ch/de/Home/Laender/Gemeinschaft_Unabhaengiger_Staaten_GUS/Zentralasien_Kirgisistan_Tadschikistan_Usbekistan</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>La Conseillère fédérale Micheline Calmy-Rey a eu des entretiens politiques à Douchanbé</title>
      <lead>Lors de la deuxième étape de son voyage en Asie centrale, la cheffe du DFAE a été reçue par le président Emomali Rachmon, président du Tadjikistan. Au cours de ses entretiens avec son homologue M. Hamrokhon Zarifi, les parties ont discuté des nombreux projets que les deux pays ont pu réaliser ensemble, en particulier dans le domaine de la gestion de l’eau.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Avec l’Ouzbékistan et le Kirghizistan, le Tadjikistan est au centre des efforts de la Suisse en matière de coopération au développement. L’attention porte surtout sur une meilleure gestion de l’eau dans la vallée de la Ferghana, région ethniquement et politiquement très complexe puisqu’elle est divisée par les frontières de ces trois Etats. En soutenant une utilisation plus rationnelle de l’eau, que ce soit pour l’irrigation des cultures et pour la production de l’énergie, la Suisse contribue à la stabilité de cette région.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;La coopération dans le cadre des organisations multilatérales a été discutée par les deux ministres des Affaires étrangères, notamment dans leur groupe de vote commun au sein des institutions de Bretton Woods (Fonds monétaire international, Banque mondiale).&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Un dialogue sur les droits humains est sur le point de s’ouvrir entre les deux pays. Ce dialogue, que la Suisse entretient déjà avec d’autres pays, comme le Vietnam, est accompagné de projets concrets. &amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Tant Mme Calmy-Rey que M. Zarifi ont convenu d’intensifier le travail pour jeter les bases de bonnes relations économiques entre leurs deux pays. La Suisse souhaite en particulier que l’accord sur la protection réciproque des investissements, signé en juin 2009, puisse être rapidement ratifié par le Tadjikistan. La Suisse a en outre proposé l’ouverture de discussions sur un futur accord de coopération économique.&amp;nbsp;La cheffe du DFAE a quitté Douchanbé pour se rendre dans l’après-midi au Kazakhstan, troisième étape de son voyage en Asie centrale.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Information DFAE Palais fédéral ouest CH-3003 Berne Tél.: (+41) 031 322 31 53 Fax: (+41) 031 324 90 47 E-Mail: info@eda.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="60623">
        <title>Dossier: Voyage en Asie centrale du 4 au 9 octobre 2009</title>
        <uri>http://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/home/dfa/head/event/2009/centralasia.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="60624">
        <title>Relations bilatérales Suisse - Tadjikistan</title>
        <uri>http://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/home/reps/asia/vtik/biltad.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="60625">
        <title>La coopération suisse en Asie centrale</title>
        <uri>http://www.deza.admin.ch/fr/Accueil/Pays/Communaute_des_Etats_independants_CEI/Asie_centrale_Kirghizistan_Tadjikistan_Ouzbekistan</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Colloqui a livello politico per la Consigliera federale Micheline Calmy-Rey a Douchanbé</title>
      <lead>Nella seconda tappa del suo viaggio in Asia centrale, la responsabile del DFAE è stata ricevuta dal presidente del Tagikistan Emomali Rachmon. Essa si è poi intrattenuta con il suo omologo Hamrokhon Zarifi, discutendo di vari progetti che i due Paesi hanno realizzato in comune, in particolare nell’ambito della gestione dell’acqua.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Insieme con l’Uzbekistan e il Kirghizistan, il Tagikistan è al centro degli sforzi della Svizzera in materia di cooperazione allo sviluppo. Si tratta in particolare di migliorare la gestione dell’acqua nella valle della Ferghana, una regione molto complessa sul piano etnico e politico poiché suddivisa in tre zone appartenenti a ciascuno dei tre Paesi menzionati. La Svizzera offre un contributo alla stabilità di questa regione promuovendo l’uso più razionale dell’acqua necessaria per l’irrigazione dei campi e la produzione di energia.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;I due ministri degli affari esteri hanno discusso della cooperazione all’interno delle organizzazioni multilaterali e in particolare nel gruppo di voto comune presso le istituzioni di Bretton Woods (Fondo monetario internazionale e Banca mondiale).&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;I due Paesi stanno per avviare un dialogo sui diritti umani. Questo tipo di dialogo, che La Svizzera ha già avviato con altri Paesi ad esempio con il Vietnam, sarà accompagnato da progetti concreti.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Micheline Calmy Rey e Hamrokhon Zarifi hanno concordato un’intensificazione del lavoro che potrà gettare le basi per l’avvio di buone relazioni economiche fra i due Paesi. In particolare la Svizzera auspica che il Tagikistan possa ratificare in tempi brevi l’accordo sulla protezione reciproca degli investimenti sottoscritto nel giugno del 2009. La Svizzera ha inoltre proposto di iniziare i colloqui per la preparazione di un futuro accordo di cooperazione economica. La responsabile del DAFE ha poi lasciato Douchanbé per raggiungere nel pomeriggio il Kazakistan, terza tappa del suo viaggio in Asia centrale.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Informazione DFAE Palazzo federale ovest CH-3003 Berna Tel.: (+41) 031 322 31 53 Fax: (+41) 031 324 90 47 E-Mail: info@eda.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="60626">
        <title>Dossier: Viaggio in Asia centrale dal 4 al 9 ottobre 2009</title>
        <uri>http://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/home/dfa/head/event/2009/centralasia.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="60627">
        <title>Relazioni bilaterali Svizzera - Tagikistan</title>
        <uri>http://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/home/reps/asia/vtik/biltad.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="60628">
        <title>La cooperazione svizzera in Asia centrale</title>
        <uri>http://www.deza.admin.ch/it/Pagina_iniziale/Paesi/Comunita_di_Stati_Indipendenti_CSI/Asia_Centrale_Kirghizistan_Tagikistan_Uzbekistan</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Federal Councillor Calmy-Rey holds political talks in Douchanbé</title>
      <lead>On the second stage of her visit to Central Asia, the head of the FDFA was welcomed by the president of Tajikistan Emomali Rachmon. In the course of her talks with her counterpart foreign minister Mr Hamrokhon Zarifi, she discussed several projects that the two countries have carried out jointly, especially in the area of water management.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Together with Uzbekistan and Kyrgyzstan, Tajikistan is a priority area for Swiss development cooperation. The aim is above all to improve water management in the Fergana Valley, an ethnically and politically highly complex region divided by the borders of the three above-mentioned states. By helping to make more rational use of water both for crop irrigation and for energy production, Switzerland is contributing to the stability of the region.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The two ministers of foreign affairs also discussed cooperation in multilateral organisations, notably their common voting group in the Bretton Woods institutions (International Monetary Fund, World Bank).&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The two countries are about to start a human rights dialogue. Switzerland already holds dialogues of this type with other countries, Vietnam for example. The dialogue will go hand in hand with specific projects. &amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Mrs Calmy-Rey and Mr Zarifi agreed to intensify efforts to create the basis for good economic relations between the two countries. Switzerland wishes in particular that the agreement on the reciprocal protection of investments signed in June 2009, should be quickly ratified by Tajikistan. Switzerland also proposed the opening of discussions on a future economic cooperation agreement. Mrs Calmy-Rey then left&amp;nbsp; Douchanbé for Kazakhstan, the third stage of her journey to Central Asia.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Information FDFA Bundeshaus West CH-3003 Bern Tel.: (+41) 031 322 31 53 Fax: (+41) 031 324 90 47 E-Mail: info@eda.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="60630">
        <title>Dossier: Trip to Central Asia from 4 to 9 October 2009</title>
        <uri>http://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home/dfa/head/event/2009/centralasia.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="60631">
        <title>Bilateral relations between Switzerland and Tajikistan</title>
        <uri>http://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home/reps/asia/vtik/biltad.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="60632">
        <title>Swiss cooperation in Central Asia</title>
        <uri>http://www.deza.admin.ch/en/Home/Countries/Commonwealth_of_Independent_States_CIS/Central_Asia_Kyrgyzstan_Tajikistan_Uzbekistan</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
