<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="29756" revoked="no">
    <version>2</version>
    <pubdate>2009-10-28</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="201" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>201</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="201">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Schweiz verurteilt Anschlag auf UN-Mitarbeiter in Kabul</title>
      <lead>Das Eidgenössische Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten EDA verurteilt die Anschläge, die heute morgen auf UN-Angestellte verübt wurden, auf das Schärfste.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Nach jüngsten Angaben wurden bei einem Anschlag auf das Gästehaus der UN in Kabul neun Personen getötet und neun weitere verletzt. Der Anschlag richtet sich gegen die Bemühungen der Weltgemeinschaft, Afghanistan in seinem demokratischen, sozialen und wirtschaftlichen Aufbau zu unterstützen. &amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Das Eidgenössische Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten EDA verurteilt die menschenverachtenden Attacken, die die aktuellen Bedingungen im krisengeschüttelten Afghanistan unnötig erschweren. Das EDA entbietet den Angehörigen der Opfer seine Anteilnahme.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Die Schweiz wird auch künftig ihr Möglichstes tun um den Prozess der Entwicklung in Afghanistan weiterhin zu fördern.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Information EDA Bundeshaus West CH-3003 Bern Tel.: +41 (0)31 322 31 53 Fax: +41 (0)31 324 90 47 E-Mail: info@eda.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>La Suisse condamne l’attentat contre des agents de l’ONU à Kaboul</title>
      <lead>Le Département fédéral des affaires étrangères (DFAE) condamne avec la plus grande fermeté l’attentat commis ce matin contre des employés de l’ONU.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Selon les informations les plus récentes, neuf personnes ont été tuées et neuf autres blessées dans un attentat contre une maison d’hôtes de l’ONU, à Kaboul. Cet attentat vise à saper les efforts déployés par la communauté internationale pour soutenir l’Afghanistan dans son développement démocratique, social et économique.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Le DFAE condamne les attaques commises au mépris de la vie humaine, qui aggravent inutilement la situation dans un pays déjà secoué par les crises. Il exprime ses sincères condoléances aux proches des victimes.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;La Suisse continuera à faire tout son possible pour promouvoir le processus de développement engagé en Afghanistan.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Information DFAE Palais fédéral ouest CH-3003 Berne Tél.: (+41) 031 322 31 53 Fax: (+41) 031 324 90 47 E-Mail: info@eda.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Berna condanna l’attacco contro i dipendenti dell’ONU a Kabul</title>
      <lead>Il Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri DFAE condanna aspramente gli attacchi compiuti stamattina contro dipendenti delle Nazioni Unite.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Secondo le ultime notizie, durante un attacco a una foresteria dell’ONU a Kabul nove persone hanno perso la vita e altre nove sono rimaste ferite. L’attacco è diretto contro gli sforzi della comunità internazionale volti a sostenere l’Afghanistan nella sua opera di ricostruzione democratica, sociale ed economica.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Il Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri DFAE condanna gli attacchi, indice di disprezzo verso il genere umano, che aggravano inutilmente le attuali condizioni di un Afghanistan squassato dalle crisi. Il DFAE esprime le sue condoglianze alle famiglie delle vittime.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;La Svizzera continuerà anche in futuro a fare il possibile per promuovere il processo di sviluppo in Afghanistan.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Informazione DFAE Palazzo federale ovest CH-3003 Berna Tel.: (+41) 031 322 31 53 Fax: (+41) 031 324 90 47 E-Mail: info@eda.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Switzerland condemns the attack on U.N. staff members in Kabul</title>
      <lead>The Federal Department of Foreign Affairs FDFA condemns in the strongest of terms the attacks perpetrated this morning on U.N. employees.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;According to the latest information, nine persons lost their lives and another nine were wounded in an attack perpetrated on a U.N. guesthouse in Kabul. The attack was intended to undermine the efforts of the world community to support Afghanistan on the road to building democracy and implementing social and economic change. &amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The Federal Department of Foreign Affairs FDFA condemns these barbaric attacks that needlessly complicate the situation currently reigning in crisis-torn Afghanistan. The FDFA presents its condolences to the family members of the victims. &amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Switzerland will continue to do everything it possibly can to foster the process of development underway in Afghanistan.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Information FDFA Bundeshaus West CH-3003 Bern Tel.: (+41) 031 322 31 53 Fax: (+41) 031 324 90 47 E-Mail: info@eda.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
