<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="74025" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2019-02-15</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="201" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>201</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="201">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Schweiz unterstützt Rohingya-Flüchtlinge mit weiteren 10 Millionen Franken</title>
      <lead>Die Schweiz beteiligt sich 2019 an der Bewältigung der Rohingya-Flüchtlingskrise in Bangladesch mit CHF 10 Mio. Ausserdem entsendet sie Experten des Schweizerischen Korps für Humanitäre Hilfe SKH zur Unterstützung der Hilfsbemühungen. Die Not in der Aufnahmeregion im Osten Bangladeschs bleibt gross. Der internationale Joint Response Plan weist einen finanziellen Bedarf von USD 920 Mio. aus.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Bei der Lancierung des &lt;em&gt;Joint Response Plan&lt;/em&gt; in Genf hat die Schweiz bekräftigt, sich weiterhin für die Bewältigung der Flüchtlingskrise in Bangladesch engagieren zu wollen. Mit dem Beitrag von CHF 10 Mio. will sie ihre bisherigen Anstrengungen in den Bereichen Wasser und Siedlungshygiene sowie Schutz und Katastrophenvorsorge weiterführen und vertiefen. Zudem sollen weitere SKH-Experten in den betroffenen Bezirk Cox’s Bazar entsandt werden, um bei der Bewältigung der Krise mitzuwirken. Derzeit engagieren sich sechs Schweizer Experten und Expertinnen vor Ort, entweder in den Reihen der UN-Organisationen oder bei der Koordination der Projekte der Humanitären Hilfe der DEZA. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mit dem neuen Beitrag hat sich die Schweiz seit 2017 mit insgesamt CHF 30 Mio. für die humanitäre Hilfe in der Rohingya-Flüchtlingskrise engagiert. In einem Statement forderte die Schweiz von Myanmar und Bangladesch, dass die Bedingungen für eine freiwillige, sichere und würdevolle Rückkehr der Vertriebenen geschaffen werden. Als Voraussetzung einer dauerhaften Lösung ruft die Schweiz zur Einhaltung des Völkerrechts auf, insbesondere zur Wahrung und zum Schutz der Menschenrechte im Rakhine-Staat in Myanmar, dem Herkunftsgebiet der Rohingya-Flüchtlinge.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Der &lt;em&gt;Joint Response Plan&lt;/em&gt;, der von über 130 humanitären Organisationen erarbeitet wurde, weist einen Bedarf von USD 920 Mio. aus, mit denen einerseits die Grundbedürfnisse der rund 900'000 Flüchtlinge gedeckt werden sollen: Unterkünfte, Nahrung, Gesundheit, Wasser und Siedlungshygiene. Andererseits soll die einheimische Bevölkerung unterstützt werden, deren Lebensbedingungen seit Ausbruch der Flüchtlingskrise durch vermehrte Abholzung, Wassernutzung, Abfallproduktion usw. verschärft wurden. &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Kommunikation EDA Bundeshaus West CH-3003 Bern Tel. Kommunikationsservice: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Medienstelle: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <link id="186787">
        <title>Humanitäre Hilfe: Leben retten und Leiden lindern</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/deza/de/home/aktivitaeten_projekte/aktivitaeten/humanitaere_hilfe.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="186788">
        <title>Engagement der DEZA in Bangladesch</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/deza/de/home/laender/bangladesch.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>La Suisse débloque 10 millions de francs supplémentaires pour venir en aide aux réfugiés rohingyas</title>
      <lead>En 2019, la Suisse participe aux efforts déployés pour résoudre la crise des réfugiés rohingyas au Bangladesh en versant une aide de 10 millions de francs et en y détachant des experts du Corps suisse d’aide humanitaire (CSA). La situation dans la région d’accueil à l’est du Bangladesh reste critique. Le plan de réponse conjoint (Joint Response Plan) des organisations internationales et des ONG nécessite des moyens financiers à hauteur de 920 millions de dollars.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Lors du lancement du plan de réponse conjoint &lt;em&gt;(Joint Response Plan)&lt;/em&gt; à Genève, la Suisse a réaffirmé sa volonté de s’engager en faveur de la résolution de la crise des réfugiés au Bangladesh. Sa contribution de 10 millions de francs est destinée à poursuivre et approfondir les efforts entrepris jusqu’à ce jour dans le domaine de l’eau et de l’assainissement ainsi que dans celui de la protection et de la prévention des catastrophes. Par ailleurs, des experts du CSA supplémentaires seront détachés dans le district de Cox’s Bazar pour participer à la gestion de la crise. À l’heure actuelle, six experts suisses sont engagés sur place, au sein des organisations des Nations Unies ou dans le cadre de la coordination des projets de l’aide humanitaire de la DDC. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Avec cette nouvelle contribution, l’aide humanitaire de la Suisse en faveur des réfugiés rohingyas a atteint un total de 30 millions de francs depuis 2017. Dans une déclaration, la Suisse exige du Myanmar et du Bangladesh qu’ils garantissent les conditions d’un retour volontaire, sûr et digne des personnes déplacées. Pour parvenir à une solution durable, elle appelle au respect du droit international, afin notamment de garantir et de protéger les droits de l’homme dans l’État de Rakhine au Myanmar, région d’origine des réfugiés rohingyas.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Le plan de réponse conjoint &lt;em&gt;(Joint Response Plan)&lt;/em&gt;, élaboré par plus de 130 organisations humanitaires, nécessite des ressources financières à hauteur de 920 millions de dollars. Ces moyens doivent permettre, d’une part, de couvrir les besoins fondamentaux (logement, nourriture, santé, eau et assainissement) des quelque 900 000 réfugiés. D’autre part, il s’agit de soutenir la population locale dont les conditions de vie se sont détériorées depuis le début de la crise en raison de la hausse du déboisement, de l’utilisation des ressources en eau et de la production de déchets. &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Communication DFAE Palais fédéral ouest CH-3003 Berne Tél. Service de communication: +41 58 462 31 53 Tél. Service de presse: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <link id="186789">
        <title>Aide humanitaire: sauver des vies et réduire les souffrances</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/deza/fr/home/activites-projets/activites/aide-humanitaire.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="186790">
        <title>Engagement de la DDC au Bangladesh</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/deza/fr/home/pays/bangladesh.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>La Svizzera sostiene i profughi rohingya con un nuovo contributo di 10 milioni di franchi</title>
      <lead>Per il 2019 la Svizzera contribuisce alla gestione della crisi che riguarda i profughi rohingya in Bangladesh stanziando 10 milioni di franchi. Invia inoltre esperti del Corpo svizzero di aiuto umanitario (CSA) a sostegno degli interventi di assistenza. La situazione di emergenza nella regione di accoglienza nell’Est del Bangladesh rimane grave. Il Joint Response Plan internazionale prevede che siano necessarie risorse finanziarie pari a 920 milioni di USD.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;In occasione del lancio del &lt;em&gt;Joint Response Plan&lt;/em&gt; a Ginevra, la Svizzera ha ribadito di voler portare avanti il suo impegno per superare la crisi dei profughi in Bangladesh. Con il proprio contributo di 10 milioni di franchi intende proseguire e aumentare gli sforzi profusi finora a livello di acqua e della rete idrico-fognaria come pure nel campo della protezione e della riduzione del rischio di catastrofi. Inoltre, è previsto l’invio di ulteriori esperti del CSA nel distretto interessato di Cox’s Bazar per fornire aiuto nella gestione della crisi. Al momento sei esperti ed esperte svizzeri sono impegnati in loco nelle fila delle organizzazioni onusiane o nella coordinazione di progetti dell’Aiuto umanitario della DSC. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Contando questo nuovo contributo, dal 2017 la Svizzera ha stanziato complessivamente 30 milioni di franchi per fornire aiuto umanitario nel contesto della crisi dei profughi rohingya. In una dichiarazione, la Svizzera ha esortato il Myanmar e il Bangladesh a creare le condizioni affinché i profughi possano tornare volontariamente nel loro Paese in modo sicuro e dignitoso. La Svizzera ribadisce che la premessa per una soluzione duratura è il rispetto del diritto internazionale pubblico, in particolare per difendere e tutelare i diritti umani nello Stato di Rakhine, in Myanmar, da cui provengono i profughi rohingya.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Il &lt;em&gt;Joint Response Plan&lt;/em&gt; – elaborato da oltre 130 organizzazioni umanitarie – prevede che siano necessari 920 milioni di USD per finanziare, da un lato, le esigenze primarie dei circa 900 000 profughi – alloggi, cibo, assistenza sanitaria, acqua e rete idrico-fognaria – e, dall’altro, per sostenere la popolazione locale, le cui condizioni di vita sono diventate più difficili dallo scoppio della crisi dei profughi poiché si è verificato un aumento del disboscamento, dell’utilizzo delle risorse idriche, della produzione di rifiuti ecc. &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Comunicazione DFAE Palazzo federale ovest CH-3003 Berna Tel. Servizio di comunicazione: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Servizio stampa: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <link id="186791">
        <title>Aiuto Umanitario: salvare vite e alleviare la sofferenza</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/deza/it/home/attivita-progetti/attivita/aiuto-umanitario.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="186792">
        <title>Impegno della DSC in Bangladesh</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/deza/it/home/paesi/bangladesh.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Switzerland provides additional 10 million francs for Rohingya refugees</title>
      <lead>In 2019, Switzerland will provide CHF 10 million and deploy experts from the Swiss Humanitarian Aid Unit (SHA) to help tackle the Rohingya refugee crisis in Bangladesh. The humanitarian crisis in eastern Bangladesh, a region that has taken in large numbers refugees, remains acute. The international Joint Response Plan seeks to raise USD 920 million to meet basic needs.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;At the launch of the Joint Response Plan in Geneva, Switzerland reaffirmed its commitment to the efforts to address the refugee crisis in Bangladesh. It is now providing CHF 10 million to step up its own relief efforts, focusing on water and sanitation as well as protection and disaster risk reduction. Switzerland will also dispatch additional SHA experts to take part in the relief operation in Cox's Bazar district. Six Swiss experts are currently on the ground, seconded to UN organisations or helping to coordinate Swiss Humanitarian Aid projects. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;With this latest contribution, Switzerland has committed a total of CHF 30 million to the operation to provide humanitarian relief to Rohingya refugees. Switzerland has also called on Myanmar and Bangladesh to ensure the voluntary return in safety and dignity of displaced Rohingyas to their homes. As a prerequisite for a lasting solution, Switzerland calls for compliance with international law, in particular for the protection and safeguarding of human rights in Myanmar's Rakhine state, the Rohingyas' home region.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Joint Response Plan, drawn up by over 130 humanitarian organisations, seeks to raise USD 920 million to meet two urgent objectives: first, to meet the basic needs of some 900,000 refugees for shelter, food, healthcare, water and sanitation and, second, to support local communities whose living conditions have worsened since the refugee crisis began because of increasing deforestation, waste production and use of water and other resources. &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>FDFA Communication Federal Palace West Wing CH-3003 Bern, Switzerland Tel. Communication service: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Press service: +41 58 460 55 55 E-mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @SwissMFA</contact>
      <link id="186793">
        <title>Humanitarian Aid: saving lives and alleviating suffering</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/deza/en/home/activities-projects/activities/humanitarian-aid.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <link id="186794">
        <title>SDC's engagement in Bangladesh</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/deza/en/home/countries/bangladesh.html</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
