<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="73358" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2018-12-12</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="1032" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>701</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eawag: Wasserforschungsinstitut des ETH-Bereichs</name>
      <name lang="fr">Eawag: L'Institut de Recherche de l'Eau du Domaine des EPF</name>
      <name lang="it">Eawag: L'Istituto per la Ricerca sulle Acque nel Settore dei Politecnici Federali</name>
      <name lang="en">Eawag: Swiss Federal Institute of Aquatic Science and Technology</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.eawag.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.eawag.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.eawag.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.eawag.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@eawag.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@eawag.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@eawag.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@eawag.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="701">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Wirtschaft, Bildung und Forschung</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'économie, de la formation et de la recherche</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'economia, della formazione e della ricerca</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Economic Affairs, Education and Research</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Dübendorf</city>
      <title>Resistenzen schmuggeln sich durch Kläranlagen</title>
      <lead>Bakterien, die gegen Antibiotika resistent sind, werden in der Abwasserreinigung nicht vollständig eliminiert. Nur ein Teil der Resistenzen stammt aus dem Zulauf, viele andere finden sich in Belebtschlammbakterien. Wie eine neue Studie des Wasserforschungsinstituts Eawag zeigt, sind Abwasserreinigungsanlagen mehr als nur eine Durchlaufstation – die Resistenzen sind dort aktiv und verändern sich.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Mehr als 95 Prozent aller Bakterien, die aus menschlichen Fäkalien ins Abwasser gelangen, werden in Abwasserreinigungsanlagen entfernt. Trotzdem sind im Auslauf noch viele antibiotikaresistente Bakterien anzutreffen. Wie lässt sich das erklären? Der Mikrobiologe Helmut Bürgmann und seine Gruppe wollten es wissen und untersuchten in zwölf Abwasserreinigungsanlagen (ARA), was mit resistenten Bakterien im Verlauf des Reinigungsprozesses geschieht. Zudem interessierte es die Forschenden, ob Stressoren im Abwasser – zum Beispiel Antibiotika, Biozide oder Schwermetalle – das Auftreten von Resistenzgenen beeinflussen. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Ein «harter Kern» von hartnäckigen Resistenzen&lt;/b&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In den zwölf ARAs haben die Forschenden Biomasseproben aus dem Zufluss, den biologischen Reinigungsstufen sowie dem Ablauf entnommen. Daraus extrahierten sie DNA, sequenzierten diese und identifizierten diejenigen Genabschnitte, die für Resistenzen gegen Antibiotika codieren. Zwar haben die Forschenden generell deutlich weniger resistente Bakterien im gereinigten Abwasser nachgewiesen als im Zulauf. Aber: «Der relative Anteil der resistenten Mikroorganismen nimmt in der ARA zu», sagt Bürgmann.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Die Forschenden fanden viele unterschiedliche Resistenzgene, deren Zusammensetzung innerhalb der ARA stark variierte. Eine kleine Gruppe von Resistenzgenen kam auf allen Stufen der Reinigung vor. Dieser «harte Kern» schmuggelt sich durch die ARA und ist vergleichsweise häufig anzutreffen. Aber rund 70 Prozent der verschiedenen Resistenzgene, die mit dem Abwasser in die ARA gelangen, werden im Verlauf des Reinigungsprozesses eliminiert. Dafür kommen aber auch neue hinzu: «Rund 40 Prozent der Resistenzen im Auslauf der ARA haben ihren Ursprung vermutlich im Belebtschlamm», sagt Bürgmann.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Überleben dank Resistenz&lt;/b&gt; &lt;p&gt;Die Forschenden vermuten, dass die Bedingungen in der ARA einen Überlebensvorteil für resistente Mikroorganismen bieten. Ein Hinweis dafür sei, dass sich zwischen der Häufigkeit von Resistenzen und dem Vorkommen von manchen Antibiotika ein Zusammenhang zeigte – obwohl diese in der ARA nur in sehr tiefen Konzentrationen vorhanden sind. Zudem waren die Resistenzgene in der ganzen ARA bis zum Ablauf tatsächlich aktiv. Dass Belebtschlammbakterien häufig Resistenzen tragen, führt Bürgmann auch auf das enge Beieinander der Mikroorganismen in der ARA zurück: «Die Bakterien in den biologischen Reinigungsstufen enthalten zum Teil Resistenzgene, die zu 100 Prozent identisch sind mit denen von Krankheitserregern. Diese haben sie vermutlich durch Genaustausch erworben.»&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Mobile Gene&lt;/b&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Nebst den eigentlichen Resistenzgenen suchten Bürgmann und seine Gruppe deshalb auch nach sogenannten Mobilitätsgenen. Diese sind ein Hinweis darauf, dass Teile der Erbsubstanz zwischen verschiedenen Bakterien ausgetauscht werden. Wie sich zeigte, befanden sich diese Gene häufig in enger Nachbarschaft zu Resistenzgenen. Das weist darauf hin, dass zwischen menschlichen Krankheitserregern und anderen Bakterien ein substantieller Austausch von Resistenzgenen stattfindet. Das hat Folgen:&lt;b&gt; &lt;/b&gt;«Wenn Resistenzen auf Belebtschlammbakterien übertragen werden und diese in die Umwelt gelangen, können sie dort vermutlich besser überleben als die Krankheitserreger», gibt Bürgmann zu Bedenken. Die einfachste Methode um dies zu verhindern sei, die Biomasse in der ARA möglichst vollständig aus dem Wasser zu eliminieren. Die neuen Reinigungsstufen zur Elimination von Mikroverunreinigungen, die Schweizer Kläranlagen in den nächsten Jahren erhalten, werden dazu einen Beitrag leisten.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Originalpublikation&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Feng Ju, Karin Beck, Xiaole Yin, Andreas Maccagnan, Christa S. McArdell, Heinz P. Singer, David R. Johnson, Tong Zhang, Helmut Bürgmann: Wastewater treatment plant resistomes are shaped by bacterial composition, genetic exchange, and upregulated expression in the effluent microbiomes&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;https://doi.org/10.1038/s41396-018-0277-8&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Artikel und Grafik auch auf: https://www.eawag.ch/de/news-agenda/news-plattform/news/news/resistenzen-schmuggeln-sich-durch-klaeranlagen/&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Dr. Helmut Bürgmann; helmut.buergmann@eawag.ch, +41 58 765 2165</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Dubendorf</city>
      <title>Comment les facteurs de résistance se faufilent à travers les STEP</title>
      <lead>Les bactéries résistantes aux antibiotiques ne sont pas totalement éliminées dans les stations d'épuration. Mais seule une partie des gènes de résistance détectés en sortie provient des eaux usées ; le reste se trouve déjà dans les boues activées. Comme le montre une nouvelle étude de l'Eawag, les stations d'épuration ne constituent pas uniquement un lieu de passage mais également d'activité et de transmission de l'antibiorésistance.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Plus de 95 % des bactéries rejetées avec les excréments humains dans les eaux usées sont éliminées dans les stations d'épuration. Pourtant, de nombreuses bactéries résistantes aux antibiotiques sont détectables dans les effluents d'épuration. Comment est-ce possible ? Pour le savoir, le microbiologiste Helmut Bürgmann et son équipe ont observé le devenir des bactéries antibiorésistantes au cours des étapes de traitement de douze stations d'épuration (STEP). Ils ont par ailleurs cherché à savoir si les facteurs de stress présents dans les eaux usées – comme les antibiotiques, les biocides ou les métaux lourds – avaient une influence sur l'occurrence de l'antibiorésistance.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Un &lt;/b&gt;&lt;b&gt;«&lt;/b&gt;&lt;b&gt;noyau dur&lt;/b&gt;&lt;b&gt;»&lt;/b&gt;&lt;b&gt; d'irréductibles&lt;/b&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Dans chacune des douze STEP, les biologistes ont prélevé des échantillons de biomasse bactérienne en entrée et en sortie de station ainsi qu'au niveau du traitement secondaire. Ils en ont extrait et analysé l'ADN puis identifié les séquences géniques codant la résistance aux antibiotiques. Les résultats indiquent que l'antibiorésistance est plus faible dans les eaux traitées que dans les eaux usées brutes mais également, comme l'indique Helmut Bürgmann, que «le passage dans la station d'épuration s'accompagne d'une augmentation de la part relative de micro-organismes résistants».&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Les scientifiques ont décelé une grande diversité de gènes de résistance dans l'ADN total de la communauté microbienne. Ils ont par ailleurs constaté que leur nature variait fortement au cours des traitements d'épuration mais qu'un petit groupe de gènes de résistance était présent à toutes les étapes. Ce «noyau dur» se faufile à travers la STEP où il est relativement fréquent. Ainsi, alors que près de 70 % des gènes de résistance arrivant à la STEP avec les eaux résiduaires sont éliminés par les traitements d'épuration, d'autres viennent en partie les remplacer. Bürgmann considère que «près de 40 % des gènes de résistance détectés en sortie de STEP proviennent probablement des boues activées». &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;La résistance, gage de survie&lt;/b&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Les microbiologistes supposent que les conditions de vie dans la STEP favorisent la survie des micro-organismes résistants. Le fait qu'il existe une corrélation entre la fréquence de l'antibiorésistance et la concentration de certains antibiotiques – au demeurant très faible dans la STEP – semble l'indiquer. Par ailleurs, les gènes de résistance restaient actifs dans toute la STEP, jusqu'à sa sortie. Pour Bürgmann, le fait que l'antibiorésistance soit fréquente dans les boues activées est lié à la promiscuité des micro-organismes dans la STEP : «Les gènes de résistance des bactéries intervenant dans le traitement biologique sont parfois identiques à ceux détectés chez les germes pathogènes. Il est probable qu'ils aient été acquis par échanges de gènes entre bactéries voisines.»&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;b&gt;Des gènes mobiles&lt;/b&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;En plus des gènes de résistance en eux-mêmes, Helmut Bürgmann et son équipe ont donc également recherché – et trouvé – des gènes marqueurs d'éléments génétiques mobiles indicateurs d'échanges de matériel génétique entre bactéries différentes. Il s'est avéré que ces gènes marqueurs se trouvaient souvent à proximité immédiate de gènes de résistance et leur présence indique donc que des échanges conséquents de gènes de résistance s'effectuent entre les germes pathogènes venant des êtres humains et les autres bactéries. Comme le souligne Bürgmann, ce phénomène n'est pas sans conséquences : «Si des gènes de résistance sont transmis aux bactéries des boues activées et si ces dernières se disséminent dans l'environnement, elles y ont probablement de meilleures chances de survie que les germes pathogènes.» D'après le microbiologiste, le meilleur moyen de l'éviter est d'extraire totalement la biomasse de l'eau dans les STEP. Les nouvelles techniques progressivement mises en œuvre dans les stations d'épuration suisses pour éliminer les micropolluants y contribueront.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Article original&lt;/b&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Feng Ju, Karin Beck, Xiaole Yin, Andreas Maccagnan, Christa S. McArdell, Heinz P. Singer, David R. Johnson, Tong Zhang, Helmut Bürgmann: Wastewater treatment plant resistomes are shaped by bacterial composition, genetic exchange, and upregulated expression in the effluent microbiomes&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;https://doi.org/10.1038/s41396-018-0277-8&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Article et graphique sur: https://www.eawag.ch/fr/news-agenda/actualites/detail/news/resistenzen-schmuggeln-sich-durch-klaeranlagen/&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Dr. Helmut Bürgmann; helmut.buergmann@eawag.ch, +41 58 765 2165</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Dübendorf</city>
      <title>Enrichment of resistance genes in wastewater treatment plants</title>
      <lead>Antibiotic resistance genes are not completely eliminated by wastewater treatment. While some resistance genes are present in the influent, many others are found in activated sludge bacteria. A recent Eawag study shows that, rather than merely passing through, resistance genes are active and evolve within treatment plants.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Although wastewater treatment plants (WWTPs) remove over 95 per cent of human fecal bacteria, many resistant bacteria can still be detected in the final effluent. How is this to be explained? To find out, a group led by microbiologist Helmut Bürgmann investigated the fate and expression of antibacterial resistance genes in the course of treatment at twelve WWTPs. The scientists were also interested in whether the occurrence of resistance genes is influenced by stressors – such as antibiotics, biocides or heavy metals – in wastewater.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Core group of persistent resistance genes&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Biomass samples were collected from the influent, the biological treatment steps and the effluent of the twelve WWTPs. DNA extracted from these samples was then analysed to identify sequences encoding antibiotic resistance. According to Bürgmann, while the levels of resistant bacteria found in treated wastewater were generally much lower than in the influent, “The relative abundance of resistance genes increases in the WWTP.”&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The researchers found a wide variety of resistance genes, with the composition of the “resistome” varying widely across different WWTP compartments. However, a small group of resistance genes was found in all treatment steps. This core group traversing the WWTP is relatively abundant. Bürgmann notes that, while around 70 per cent of the resistance genes found in the influent are eliminated in the course of treatment, others arise within the WWTP: “About 40 per cent of the resistance genes in the effluent presumably originate in the activated sludge.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt;Survival through resistance&lt;/b&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The scientists believe that environmental conditions within the WWTP offer a survival advantage for resistant microorganisms. This is suggested by the correlation observed between the abundance of resistance genes and the occurrence of certain antibiotics – even though these are only present at very low concentrations in the WWTP. In addition, resistance genes were found to be active across the entire WWTP. Bürgmann attributes the abundance of resistance genes in activated sludge bacteria to the close proximity of microorganisms during treatment: “Some bacteria in the biological treatment steps contain resistance genes with 100 per cent identity to known pathogens. These have presumably been acquired through gene exchange.”&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt; &lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Mobility genes&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;For this reason, Bürgmann’s group sought to identify not just resistance genes, but also so‑called mobility genes, which indicate that genetic material is exchanged between different bacteria. These genes were found to be frequently co-localized with resistance genes. This suggests that substantial exchanges of resistance genes occur between human pathogens and other bacteria. As Bürgmann points out, “If resistance genes are transferred to activated sludge bacteria and these enter the environment, they can presumably survive better there than the pathogens.” The easiest way of preventing this, he adds, is to eliminate biomass as far as possible from the water in the WWTP. A contribution to this goal will be made by the new treatment steps designed to remove micropollutants, which are to be introduced at Swiss WWTPs over the coming years.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Original publication&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Feng Ju, Karin Beck, Xiaole Yin, Andreas Maccagnan, Christa S. McArdell, Heinz P. Singer, David R. Johnson, Tong Zhang, Helmut Bürgmann: Wastewater treatment plant resistomes are shaped by bacterial composition, genetic exchange, and upregulated expression in the effluent microbiomes&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;https://doi.org/10.1038/s41396-018-0277-8&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Article and graph see also: https://www.eawag.ch/en/news-agenda/news-portal/news-detail/news/resistenzen-schmuggeln-sich-durch-klaeranlagen/&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Dr. Helmut Bürgmann; helmut.buergmann@eawag.ch, +41 58 765 2165</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="8">
        <name lang="de">Bildung und Forschung</name>
        <name lang="fr">Formation et recherche</name>
        <name lang="it">Formazione e ricerca</name>
        <name lang="en">Education and Research</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="15">
        <name lang="de">Gesundheit</name>
        <name lang="fr">Santé</name>
        <name lang="it">sanità</name>
        <name lang="en">Health</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="29">
        <name lang="de">Umwelt und Natur</name>
        <name lang="fr">Environnement et nature</name>
        <name lang="it">Ambiente e natura</name>
        <name lang="en">Environment and Nature</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="37">
        <name lang="de">Konsum</name>
        <name lang="fr">Consommation</name>
        <name lang="it">Consumo</name>
        <name lang="en">Consumer Affairs</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="45">
        <name lang="de">Technologie</name>
        <name lang="fr">Technologie</name>
        <name lang="it">Tecnologia</name>
        <name lang="en">Technology</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
