<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="51758" revoked="no">
    <version>2</version>
    <pubdate>2014-01-23</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="1070" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>1070</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Der Bundesrat</name>
      <name lang="fr">Conseil fédéral</name>
      <name lang="it">Il Consiglio federale</name>
      <name lang="en">The Federal Council</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.admin.ch/gov/de/start.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.admin.ch/gov/fr/accueil.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.admin.ch/gov/it/pagina-iniziale.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.admin.ch/gov/en/start.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="yes" id="603" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>601</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidg. Finanzverwaltung</name>
      <name lang="fr">Administration fédérale des finances</name>
      <name lang="it">Amministrazione federale delle finanze</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Finance Administration</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.efv.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.efv.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.efv.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.efv.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@efv.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@efv.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@efv.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@efv.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="1070">
      <name lang="de">Der Bundesrat</name>
      <name lang="fr">Conseil fédéral</name>
      <name lang="it">Il Consiglio federale</name>
      <name lang="en">The Federal Council</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.admin.ch/gov/de/start.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.admin.ch/gov/fr/accueil.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.admin.ch/gov/it/pagina-iniziale.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.admin.ch/gov/en/start.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <department id="601">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Finanzdepartement</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des finances</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale delle finanze</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Finance</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.efd.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.dff.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.efd.admin.ch/efd/it/home.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.efd.admin.ch/efd/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Bundesrat verstärkt Massnahmen gegen Überhitzung auf dem Hypothekarmarkt</title>
      <lead>Der Bundesrat geht weiter gegen ein übermässiges Wachstum auf den Immobilien- und Hypothekarmärkten vor. Er hat an seiner gestrigen Sitzung dem Antrag der Nationalbank stattgegeben, den antizyklischen Kapitalpuffer zu erhöhen. Danach werden die Banken ab dem 30. Juni 2014 verpflichtet, die Eigenmittel für Wohnbauhypotheken von 1 auf 2 Prozent zu erhöhen. </lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Auf Antrag der Schweizerischen Nationalbank kann der Bundesrat gestützt auf die Eigenmittelverordnung (ERV) die Banken dazu verpflichten, zusätzliche Eigenmittel in Form eines antizyklischen Kapitalpuffers (AZP) zu halten. Gestern hat der Bundesrat entschieden, den AZP gemäss Antrag der Nationalbank von 1 auf 2 Prozent zu erhöhen. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Die Nationalbank ist zum Schluss gekommen, dass die Erhöhung des AZP notwendig ist. Die Aktivierung des AZP im Februar 2013 und die anderen, schrittweise bis Anfang 2013 in Kraft getretenen Massnahmen zur Reduktion der Risiken auf dem Schweizer Hypothekar- und Immobilienmarkt konnten zwar die Widerstandskraft betroffener Banken stärken. Im derzeitigen Niedrigzinsumfeld führte aber die anhaltend starke Zunahme der Hypothekarkredite und der Immobilienpreise für Wohnliegenschaften dazu, dass sich die Ungleichgewichte weiter verstärkt haben. Diese Ungleichgewichte stellen ein erhebliches Risiko für die stabile Entwicklung der Volkswirtschaft und damit auch für die Stabilität des Bankensektors dar. Die Nationalbank hat deshalb beantragt, dass ab dem 30. Juni 2014 die Banken verpflichtet werden, zusätzliche anrechenbare Eigenmittel in der Höhe von 2 Prozent ihrer risikogewichteten Positionen zu halten, bei denen eine Wohnliegenschaft im Inland als Grundpfand fungiert (gemäss Art. 72 ERV). Der erhöhte AZP zielt weiterhin nur auf Hypothekarkredite für Wohnliegenschaften ab. Andere Kredite, insbesondere solche an Unternehmungen, sind von der Massnahme nicht betroffen. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Vorrangiges Ziel des AZP ist es, die Gesamtwirtschaft und den Bankensektor gegenüber den Risiken eines übermässigen Kreditwachstums widerstandsfähiger zu machen. Die Erhöhung des AZP soll aber auch dazu beitragen, den Anstieg der Hypotheken und Immobilienpreise zu dämpfen. Verschiedene Indikatoren unterstreichen die Notwendigkeit dieser Massnahme.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Die Verschuldung durch Hypothekarkredite ist im vergangenen Jahr weiter angestiegen und hat im Verhältnis zu den Einkommen ein besorgniserregendes Niveau erreicht. Auch die Wohnliegenschaftspreise sind in einem Ausmass gestiegen, das sich nicht allein durch Faktoren wie Bevölkerungsentwicklung oder Einkommensanstieg begründen lässt. Das Verhältnis zwischen den Preisen für Wohnliegenschaften und den Mieten hat mittlerweile ein Mass erreicht, das letztmals während des Immobilienbooms Ende der 1980er Jahre erreicht worden war. Auch gibt es nach wie vor Anzeichen für eine hohe Risikobereitschaft seitens der Banken bei der Vergabe von Wohnhypotheken.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Komplementär zum AZP finden derzeit Gespräche zwischen EFD, FINMA, SNB und der Branche statt, um die Selbstregulierungsrichtlinien zu verstärken. Der Bundesrat unterstützt diese Bestrebungen. &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Serge Gaillard, Direktor, Eidgenössische Finanzverwaltung EFV Tel. 031 322 60 05, Serge.Gaillard@efv.admin.ch</contact>
      <attachment id="118646">
        <title>Verordnung</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>16</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/33539.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <link id="118649">
        <title>SNB-Medienmitteilung</title>
        <uri>http://www.snb.ch/de/</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Le Conseil fédéral renforce les mesures contre la surchauffe du marché hypothécaire</title>
      <lead>Le Conseil fédéral poursuit son action contre une croissance excessive des marchés immobilier et hypothécaire. Lors de sa séance d’hier, il a donné suite à la proposition de la Banque nationale suisse (BNS) concernant un relèvement du volant de fonds propres anticyclique. A partir du 30 juin 2014, les banques seront donc tenues de faire passer de 1 à 2 % la couverture en fonds propres de leurs créances hypothécaires. </lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Sur proposition de la BNS, le Conseil fédéral peut, en vertu de l'ordonnance sur les fonds propres (OFR), obliger les banques à détenir des fonds propres supplémentaires sous la forme d'un volant de fonds propres anticyclique. Hier, le Conseil fédéral a décidé de suivre la proposition de la BNS et de faire passer le volant de fonds propres anticyclique de 1 à 2 % des créances hypothécaires liées au logement. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;La BNS est arrivée à la conclusion que le relèvement du volant anticyclique est nécessaire. Certes, l'activation de ce volant en février 2013 ainsi que les autres mesures de réduction des risques sur les marchés hypothécaire et immobilier suisses, qui sont entrées progressivement en vigueur jusqu'au début de 2013, ont accru la résistance des banques concernées. Cependant, dans le contexte actuel de taux bas, l'augmentation constante des crédits hypothécaires et des prix de l'immobilier résidentiel a encore accentué les déséquilibres, qui représentent un risque considérable pour la stabilité de l'économie et du secteur bancaire. C'est pourquoi la BNS a proposé d'obliger les banques à détenir, à partir du 30 juin 2014, des fonds propres supplémentaires à hauteur de 2 % de leurs positions pondérées en fonction des risques et garanties par des gages immobiliers en Suisse (selon l'art. 72 OFR). Le relèvement du volant anticyclique vise uniquement les crédits hypothécaires destinés au financement d'immeubles d'habitation. Il ne touche pas les autres crédits, notamment ceux qui sont octroyés aux entreprises. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Le volant de fonds propres anticyclique a pour objectif principal de permettre à l'ensemble de l'économie et au secteur bancaire de mieux résister aux risques liés à une croissance excessive des crédits. Son relèvement doit aussi contribuer à freiner la hausse des hypothèques et des prix de l'immobilier. Différents indicateurs soulignent la nécessité de cette mesure.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;L'endettement lié aux crédits hypothécaires a continué à progresser au cours de l'année écoulée et a atteint un niveau préoccupant par rapport aux revenus. Quant aux prix des immeubles d'habitation, ils ont également augmenté dans une mesure que ne peuvent justifier à elles seules l'évolution démographique ou la hausse des revenus. Le rapport entre les prix et les loyers des immeubles d'habitation a atteint aujourd'hui un niveau qui avait été observé pour la dernière fois durant le boom de l'immobilier à la fin des années 1980. Par ailleurs, il existe toujours des indices d'une forte propension des banques à prendre des risques lors de l'octroi de crédits hypothécaires.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;En complément du volant de fonds propres anticyclique, le renforcement des directives d'autorégulation fait actuellement l'objet d'entretiens entre le DFF, la FINMA, la BNS et le secteur bancaire. Ces efforts sont soutenus par le DFF.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Serge Gaillard, directeur de l’Administration fédérale des finances AFF Tél. 031 322 60 05, Serge.Gaillard@efv.admin.ch</contact>
      <attachment id="118648">
        <title>Ordonnance</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>16</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/33541.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <link id="118650">
        <title>Communiqué de la BNS</title>
        <uri>http://www.snb.ch/fr/</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Il Consiglio federale rafforza le misure per contrastare il surriscaldamento sul mercato ipotecario</title>
      <lead>Il Consiglio federale interviene nuovamente contro la crescita eccessiva nel mercato ipotecario. In occasione della sua seduta di ieri ha accolto la proposta della Banca nazionale svizzera (BNS) di aumentare il cuscinetto anticiclico di capitale. Ne consegue che dal 30 giugno 2014 le banche dovranno aumentare i fondi propri per i mutui ipotecari sulle abitazioni dall’1 al 2 per cento.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Su richiesta della Banca nazionale svizzera (BNS) il Consiglio federale può obbligare le banche, in virtù dell'ordinanza sui fondi propri (OFoP), a detenere fondi propri supplementari nella forma di un cuscinetto anticiclico di capitale. Conformemente alla proposta della BNS, il Consiglio federale ha deciso ieri di aumentare il cuscinetto anticiclico di capitale dall'1 al 2 per cento. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;La BNS è giunta alla conclusione che l'aumento del cuscinetto anticiclico di capitale è necessario. Il cuscinetto anticiclico attivato nel mese di febbraio del 2013 e le altre misure per ridurre i rischi sul mercato ipotecario e immobiliare svizzero, entrate in vigore gradualmente fino all'inizio del 2013, hanno permesso di rafforzare la capacità di resistenza delle banche interessate. Tuttavia, in considerazione dell'attuale situazione di interessi bassi, la persistente forte crescita dei crediti ipotecari e dei prezzi degli immobili d'abitazione ha ulteriormente intensificato gli squilibri. Questi squilibri costituiscono un rischio considerevole per lo sviluppo costante dell'economia nazionale e quindi anche per la stabilità del settore bancario. La BNS ha pertanto chiesto che a partire dal 30 giugno 2014 le banche siano obbligate a detenere fondi propri supplementari computabili pari al 2 per cento delle loro posizioni ponderate in funzione del rischio, per le quali un immobile d'abitazione svizzero funge da pegno immobiliare (secondo l'art. 72 OFoP). L'aumento del cuscinetto anticiclico di capitale concerne tuttora solamente i crediti ipotecari per immobili d'abitazione. Gli altri crediti, in particolare quelli destinati alle imprese, non sono toccati dal provvedimento. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Il cuscinetto anticiclico di capitale si prefigge principalmente di rafforzare la capacità di resistenza del settore bancario e dell'economia nazionale nei confronti dei rischi legati a una crescita eccessiva del credito. L'aumento del cuscinetto anticiclico di capitale dovrebbe inoltre attenuare la crescita dei mutui ipotecari e dei prezzi delle abitazioni. Diversi indicatori sottolineano la necessità di questa misura.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Lo scorso anno l'indebitamento causato dai crediti ipotecari è ulteriormente cresciuto e in rapporto ai redditi ha raggiunto un livello preoccupante. Anche i prezzi degli immobili d'abitazione sono aumentati in misura superiore a quanto potrebbe essere giustificato da fattori quali l'evoluzione della popolazione o l'aumento dei redditi. Nel frattempo il rapporto tra i prezzi degli immobili d'abitazione e le pigioni ha raggiunto un livello riscontrato l'ultima volta alla fine degli anni Ottanta durante il boom immobiliare. Inoltre sussiste ancora un'elevata disponibilità al rischio da parte delle banche nella concessione di mutui ipotecari per le abitazioni.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Oltre al cuscinetto anticiclico di capitale, attualmente si tengono colloqui tra il DFF, la FINMA, la BNS e il settore bancario per rafforzare le direttive in materia di autodisciplina. Il Consiglio federale sostiene questi sforzi.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Serge Gaillard, direttore dell’Amministrazione federale delle finanze AFF tel. 031 322 60 05, Serge.Gaillard@efv.admin.ch</contact>
      <attachment id="118647">
        <title>Ordinanza</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>40</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/33540.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <link id="118650">
        <title>Communiqué de la BNS</title>
        <uri>http://www.snb.ch/fr/</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Federal Council reinforces measures to counter overheating on mortgage market</title>
      <lead>The Federal Council is continuing to take action against excessive growth on the real estate and mortgage markets. During its meeting yesterday, the Federal Council accepted the Swiss National Bank's request to increase the countercyclical buffer. Accordingly, banks will be obliged to increase the capital for residential mortgages from 1% to 2% from 30 June 2014. </lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;At the request of the Swiss National Bank (SNB), the Federal Council can oblige banks to hold additional capital in the form of a countercyclical buffer based on the Capital Adequacy Ordinance (CAO). Yesterday, the Federal Council decided to increase the countercyclical buffer from 1% to 2% in line with the SNB's request. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The SNB has come to the conclusion that it is necessary to increase the countercyclical buffer. While the activation of the countercyclical buffer in February 2013 and the other measures gradually introduced up until the start of 2013 to reduce the risks in the Swiss mortgage and real estate markets have boosted the resilience of the banks concerned, the sustained strong increase in mortgage loans and the prices of residential properties has caused the imbalances to become even greater in the current low interest rate environment. These imbalances constitute a considerable risk for the stable development of the economy and thus for the stability of the banking sector too. The SNB has thus requested that banks be obliged from 30 June 2014 to hold additional allowable equity capital in the amount of 2% of their risk-weighted assets (RWA), whereby a residential property in Switzerland acts as real security (in accordance with Art. 72 CAO). The increased countercyclical buffer continues to be aimed at mortgage loans for residential property. Other loans, in particular those for companies, are not affected by this measure. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The primary objective of the countercyclical buffer is to make the banking sector and the overall economy more resilient to the risks posed by excessive credit growth. However, increasing the countercyclical buffer should also help curb the rise in mortgages and real estate prices. Various indicators highlight the need for this measure.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Last year, the levels of debt arising from mortgage loans continued to rise and reached particularly worrisome levels in relation to income. Even residential property prices have risen to an extent which cannot be explained solely by factors such as population growth or rising income levels. The relationship between residential property prices and rents has in the meantime reached a level which was last seen during the real estate boom at the end of the 1980s. Moreover, there are still signs that banks are very willing to take risks when granting residential mortgages.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Complementing the countercyclical buffer, talks are currently taking place between the Federal Department of Finance (FDF), the Swiss Financial Market Supervisory Authority (FINMA), the SNB and the sector in order to strengthen the self-regulatory guidelines. The Federal Council supports these efforts. &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Serge Gaillard, Director of the Federal Finance Administration FFA Tel. 031 322 60 05, Serge.Gaillard@efv.admin.ch</contact>
      <attachment id="118646">
        <title>Verordnung</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>16</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/33539.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <link id="118651">
        <title>SNB Press release</title>
        <uri>http://www.snb.ch/en/</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <offers>
      <offer id="2" org-id="603">
        <name lang="de">Finanzpolitik</name>
        <name lang="fr">Politique budgétaire</name>
        <name lang="it">Politica finanziaria</name>
        <name lang="en">Financial policy</name>
      </offer>
      <offer id="3" org-id="603">
        <name lang="de">Wirtschaft, Währung</name>
        <name lang="fr">Economie, monnaie</name>
        <name lang="it">Economia, Moneta</name>
        <name lang="en">Economic, Monetary affairs</name>
      </offer>
    </offers>
    <keywords>
      <keyword id="126" org-id="603">
        <name lang="de">Finanzplatz Schweiz</name>
        <name lang="fr">Place financière suisse</name>
        <name lang="it">Piazza finanziaria svizzera</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland as a financial centre</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="113" org-id="603">
        <name lang="de">Finanzpolitik Diverses</name>
        <name lang="fr">Politique budgétaire: divers</name>
        <name lang="it">Politica finanziaria: diversi</name>
        <name lang="en">Fiscal Policy misc.</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="128" org-id="603">
        <name lang="de">Wirtschaftspolitik und Finanzmärkte</name>
        <name lang="fr">Politique économique et marchés financiers</name>
        <name lang="it">Politica economica e mercati finanziari</name>
        <name lang="en">Economic policy and financial markets</name>
      </keyword>
    </keywords>
    <topics>
      <topic id="10">
        <name lang="de">Bundesrat</name>
        <name lang="fr">Conseil fédéral</name>
        <name lang="it">Consiglio federale</name>
        <name lang="en">Federal Council</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="35">
        <name lang="de">Finanzplatz</name>
        <name lang="fr">Place financière</name>
        <name lang="it">Piazza finanziaria</name>
        <name lang="en">Financial Centre</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="47">
        <name lang="de">Wirtschaft</name>
        <name lang="fr">Économie</name>
        <name lang="it">Economia</name>
        <name lang="en">Economic Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
