<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="83031" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2021-04-08</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="1080" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>701</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Staatssekretariat für Bildung, Forschung und Innovation</name>
      <name lang="fr">Secrétariat d'Etat à la formation, à la recherche et à l'innovation</name>
      <name lang="it">Segreteria di Stato per la formazione, la ricerca e l'innovazione</name>
      <name lang="en">State Secretariat for Education, Research and Innovation</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.sbfi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.sbfi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.sbfi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.sbfi.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@sbfi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@sbfi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@sbfi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@sbfi.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="701">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Wirtschaft, Bildung und Forschung</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'économie, de la formation et de la recherche</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'economia, della formazione e della ricerca</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Economic Affairs, Education and Research</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>20 Jahre im Zeichen des Unerwarteten: Der Jahresbericht 2020 von Swissnex</title>
      <lead>Swissnex vernetzt die Schweiz in den Bereichen Bildung, Forschung und Innovation (BFI) mit dem Ausland. Es fördert den globalen Austausch von Wissen, Ideen und Talenten und stärkt so die Ausstrahlung der Schweiz als exzellenten Forschungs- und Innovationsplatz. Im letzten Jahr feierte Swissnex sein 20-jähriges Bestehen und nahm das Jubiläum zum Anlass, sich im Rahmen der Kampagne «nex20» mit künftigen Chancen und Herausforderungen des BFI-Standortes Schweiz auseinanderzusetzen. Der Swissnex Jahresbericht 2020 fasst auf annualreport.swissnex.org ein aussergewöhnliches Jahr voller Highlights, Herausforderungen und Ideen zusammen.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;20 Jahre sind seit der Gründung von Swissnex in Boston vergangen. Ansporn dafür war die Vision, der Schweiz und ihrem grossen Innovationspotenzial mit entsprechender Präsenz vermehrte Visibilität zu verschaffen. Heute stellt Swissnex eine einzigartige Vernetzungsplattform dar, ein globales Netzwerk, das durch den Austausch von Wissen, Ideen und Talenten das Potenzial besitzt, die Welt von morgen mitzugestalten.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;«nex20»: Ein Blick in die Zukunft des BFI-Standorts Schweiz&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Sein diesjähriges Jubiläum nahm Swissnex zum Anlass, sich in verschiedenen Formen mit der Zukunft auseinanderzusetzen: Wie positioniert sich der BFI-Standort Schweiz in den nächsten 20 Jahren in der Welt? Welche Aufgaben wird Swissnex im Jahr 2040 haben, und wie wird es den sich verändernden Bedürfnissen seiner Partnerinnen und Partner gerecht?&lt;br /&gt;Unter dem Motto «nex20 – connecting tomorrow» fanden verschiedene Jubiläumsaktivitäten in unterschiedlichen Formaten zu vier Themen statt: «Learning Tomorrow», «Meeting Tomorrow», «Working Tomorrow» und «Living Tomorrow». So organisierte beispielsweise Swissnex in Indien einen 48-stündigen, globalen Hackathon, den «nexHack Edtech», der 130 Teilnehmende aus 45 Nationen zusammenbrachte, um gemeinsam Lösungen für die Herausforderungen, der die Bildung heute gegenübersteht, zu entwickeln.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Swissnex führte im Jahr 2020 zusammen mit rund 190 Schweizer Partnerorganisationen gut 210 Aktivitäten und Anlässe durch. Es unterstützte zudem 53 Schweizer Start-ups im Bereich der Internationalisierung und förderte den Austausch verschiedener Akteure in diversen Themen mit Relevanz für die Schweizer Bildungs-, Forschungs- und Innovationslandschaft. Diese Zahlen unterstreichen den Wert und Nutzen von Swissnex: die Standorte verbinden BFI-Akteure im jeweiligen Land mit jenen in der Schweiz und bringen so Menschen zusammen, deren Wege sich ohne Swissnex kaum kreuzen würden. Die unerwarteten Begegnungen, die Swissnex ermöglicht, erlaubt es Projektpartnern, neue Wege zu gehen und fördert somit ihre Wettbewerbsfähigkeit im internationalen Umfeld. Schweizer Akteure sowie der Forschungs- und Innovationsplatz Schweiz profitieren von der Globalisierung des BFI-Raums, indem der Austausch von Wissen sowie die Mobilität von Talenten gefördert werden.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Swissnex ist das weltweite Schweizer Netzwerk für Bildung, Forschung und Innovation. Es unterstützt seine Partner bei der internationalen Vernetzung und ihrem Engagement im globalen Austausch von Wissen, Ideen und Talenten. Die fünf Hauptstandorte von Swissnex befinden sich in den innovativsten Regionen der Welt. Gemeinsam mit den rund 20 Wissenschaftssektionen sowie Wissenschaftsrätinnen und -räten an Schweizer Botschaften stärken sie die Ausstrahlung der Schweiz als Innovations-Hotspot.&lt;br /&gt;Swissnex ist eine Initiative des Staatssekretariats für Bildung, Forschung und Innovation und ist Teil des Aussennetzes des Bundes unter der Federführung des Eidgenössischen Departements für auswärtige Angelegenheiten. Die Tätigkeiten von Swissnex gründen in einem kooperativen Ansatz sowie auf öffentlichen und privaten Partnerschaften und Finanzierungen.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Kommunikation Staatssekretariat für Bildung, Forschung und Innovation SBFI medien@sbfi.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="214449">
        <title>Swissnex Jahresbericht 2020</title>
        <uri>https://annualreport.swissnex.org/</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Rapport annuel 2020 de Swissnex: 20 ans sous le signe de l’imprévisible</title>
      <lead>Swissnex met en réseau la Suisse et ses partenaires étrangers dans les domaines de la formation, de la recherche et de l’innovation (FRI). Il encourage l’échange de connaissances, d’idées et de talents à l’échelle internationale et contribue ainsi à renforcer la position de la Suisse en tant que pôle de recherche et d’innovation. L’an dernier, Swissnex a fêté ses 20 ans. Le réseau a profité de cette occasion pour se pencher sur les opportunités et les défis qui se posent à la place FRI suisse dans le cadre d’une campagne nommée «nex20». Sur le site annualreport.swissnex.org, le rapport annuel 2020 de Swissnex relate une année hors normes, jalonnée de moments forts, de défis et d’idées.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Vingt ans se sont écoulés depuis la création du site Swissnex à Boston. L’idée était d’augmenter la visibilité de la Suisse et de son fort potentiel d’innovation en renforçant sa présence dans cette ville. Aujourd’hui, Swissnex est une plateforme de mise en relation unique, un réseau mondial qui a le potentiel de façonner le monde de demain grâce à l’échange de savoirs, d’idées et de talents.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;«nex20»: le site FRI suisse de demain&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Swissnex a saisi l’occasion de cet anniversaire pour aborder l’avenir sous différents angles: comment le site FRI suisse se positionnera-t-il dans le monde ces vingt prochaines années? Quelles seront les tâches de Swissnex en 2040? Comment répondra-t-il aux besoins en constante évolution de ses partenaires?&lt;br /&gt;Sous le slogan «nex20 – connecting tomorrow», des activités pour célébrer l’anniversaire du réseau ont eu lieu autour de quatre thèmes et dans différents formats: «Learning Tomorrow», «Meeting Tomorrow», «Working Tomorrow» et «Living Tomorrow». Le site Swissnex en Inde a par exemple organisé un hackathon mondial de 48 heures, le «nexHack Edtech», qui a réuni 130 participants issus de 45 nations différentes dans le but de développer des solutions communes pour faire face aux défis actuels en matière de formation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Avec près de 190 organisations partenaires en Suisse, Swissnex a mené plus de 210 activités et évènements en 2020. Il a en outre soutenu l’internationalisation de 53 start-up suisses et a encouragé les échanges entre divers acteurs sur des thèmes liés au paysage suisse de la formation, de la recherche et de l’innovation. Ces chiffres soulignent la valeur et l’utilité de Swissnex: les sites Swissnex permettent aux acteurs FRI de Suisse de tisser des liens avec des acteurs étrangers et de mettre en contact des personnes qui ne se seraient peut-être jamais croisées autrement. Ces rencontres inattendues, rendues possibles grâce au réseau Swissnex, permettent aux partenaires de projets d’emprunter de nouveaux chemins et ainsi de renforcer leur compétitivité à l’échelle internationale. La mondialisation de l’espace FRI profite aux acteurs suisses, tout comme à l’ensemble du site suisse de recherche et d’innovation. L’échange de savoir et la mobilité des talents sont ainsi encouragés.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Swissnex est le réseau mondial suisse chargé de tisser des liens dans les domaines de la formation, de la recherche et de l’innovation. Son mission est de soutenir le rayonnement international de ses partenaires ainsi que leur participation active à l’échange mondial de connaissances, d’idées et de talents. Les cinq principaux sites Swissnex sont établis dans les régions les plus innovantes du monde. Ils contribuent, en collaboration avec la vingtaine de sections scientifiques et conseillers scientifiques auprès des ambassades de Suisse, à renforcer la position de la Suisse en tant que pôle mondial de l’innovation.&lt;br /&gt;Swissnex est une initiative du Secrétariat d’État à la formation, à la recherche et à l’innovation et fait partie du réseau extérieur de la Confédération géré par le Département fédéral des affaires étrangères. Les activités de Swissnex s’inscrivent dans une approche collaborative et reposent sur des partenariats et des financements publics et privés.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Communication Secrétariat d’État à la formation, à la recherche et à l’innovation SEFRI medien@sbfi.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="214450">
        <title>Rapport annuel 2020 de Swissnex</title>
        <uri>https://annualreport.swissnex.org/</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Swissnex, rapporto annuale 2020: vent’anni di incontri inaspettati</title>
      <lead>Swissnex funge da ponte tra il nostro Paese e l’estero in materia di educazione, ricerca e innovazione (ERI), favorendo lo scambio di conoscenze, idee e talenti oltre i confini nazionali e rafforzando la reputazione della Svizzera come polo d’eccellenza nel campo della ricerca e dell’innovazione. Lo scorso anno Swissnex ha spento la sua ventesima candelina e, nell’ambito della campagna «nex20», ha colto quest’occasione per riflettere sulle opportunità e sfide con cui il settore ERI svizzero dovrà confrontarsi in futuro. Il rapporto annuale 2020 di Swissnex (annualreport.swissnex.org) presenta la panoramica di un anno straordinario, ricco di eventi, sfide e idee.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Sono passati 20 anni dalla fondazione di Swissnex a Boston. L’obiettivo era aumentare la visibilità del nostro Paese e del suo enorme potenziale innovativo grazie a una maggior presenza internazionale. Oggi Swissnex rappresenta una piattaforma di interconnessione unica, una rete globale che, grazie allo scambio di conoscenze, idee e talenti può contribuire a plasmare il mondo di domani.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;«nex20»: uno sguardo al futuro del polo ERI svizzero&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Per Swissnex questo anniversario è stato l’occasione per riflettere in vari modi sul futuro: come si posizionerà a livello internazionale il polo svizzero del settore dell’educazione, della ricerca e dell’innovazione (ERI) nei prossimi 20 anni? Quali compiti avrà Swissnex nel 2040 e come risponderà alle nuove esigenze dei partner?&lt;br /&gt;All’insegna dello slogan «nex20 – connecting tomorrow» sono state organizzate svariate attività, in diversi formati, legate a quattro temi: «Learning Tomorrow», «Meeting Tomorrow», «Working Tomorrow» e «Living Tomorrow». Per esempio, in India è stato proposto un evento mondiale di 48 ore con diversi specialisti in informatica (hackathon), il «nexHack Edtech», nel quale 130 persone provenienti da 45 Paesi hanno collaborato per trovare soluzioni volte a ridurre gli ostacoli a cui ancora oggi la formazione deve far fronte.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Nel 2020 Swissnex ha svolto oltre 210 attività ed eventi in collaborazione con circa 190 organizzazioni partner svizzere, ha sostenuto 53 start-up elvetiche nel processo di internazionalizzazione e ha promosso lo scambio di idee tra diversi attori su vari temi rilevanti per il settore ERI. Queste cifre sottolineano il valore e l’utilità di Swissnex: le sue sedi permettono infatti agli attori ERI dei rispettivi Paesi di comunicare con i loro omologhi svizzeri stabilendo dei contatti che altrimenti difficilmente sarebbero nati. Questi incontri inaspettati, resi possibili da Swissnex, permettono ai partner di progetto di esplorare nuove strade e li rendono più competitivi a livello internazionale. Gli attori svizzeri, così come il polo della ricerca e dell’innovazione del nostro Paese, traggono beneficio dall’internazionalizzazione nel settore ERI, in quanto quest’ultima favorisce lo scambio di conoscenze e la mobilità dei talenti.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Swissnex è la rete globale svizzera che connette in materia di formazione, ricerca e innovazione. La sua missione è sostenere la diffusione e l'impegno attivo dei partner nello scambio internazionale di conoscenze, idee e talenti. Le cinque sedi principali si trovano nei centri più innovativi del mondo e contribuiscono, insieme alla ventina di consiglieri scientifici presso le ambasciate elvetiche, a rafforzare il profilo della Svizzera come hub d'innovazione di livello mondiale.&lt;br /&gt;Swissnex è un’iniziativa della Segreteria di Stato per la formazione, la ricerca e l’innovazione (SEFRI) e fa parte della rete esterna della Confederazione, guidata dal Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri. Le attività di Swissnex si basano su un approccio cooperativo che prevede diversi partenariati e finanziamenti pubblici e privati.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Comunicazione Segreteria di Stato per la formazione, la ricerca e l’innovazione SEFRI medien@sbfi.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="214451">
        <title>Swissnex, rapporto annuale 2020</title>
        <uri>https://annualreport.swissnex.org/</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>The Swissnex 2020 annual report: 20 years of unexpected encounters</title>
      <lead>Swissnex is Switzerland’s international network for education, research and innovation (ERI). It promotes the international exchange of knowledge, ideas and talent, strengthening Switzerland’s reputation in research and innovation excellence. Marking its 20th anniversary last year, Swissnex launched its ‘nex20’ campaign to explore future opportunities and challenges for Switzerland as a centre for ERI. The Swissnex 2020 annual report, available at annualreport.swissnex.org, presents the many highlights, challenges and ideas which shaped an extraordinary year.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Twenty years have passed since Swissnex was founded in Boston. The incentive behind it was to increase the visibility of Switzerland’s enormous potential for innovation by establishing a dedicated local presence. Since then, Swissnex has evolved to become a unique networking platform – a global network with the potential to shape tomorrow’s ERI landscape through a mutual exchange of knowledge, ideas and talent.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;‘nex20’: looking to Switzerland’s future as a centre for ERI&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Swissnex used its anniversary in 2020 as an opportunity to reflect on a number of topics for the future. How will Switzerland position itself in the world as a centre for ERI in the next 20 years? What tasks will Swissnex face in 2040, and how will it meet its partners’ changing needs?&lt;br /&gt;As part of its anniversary campaign ‘nex20 – connecting tomorrow’, a variety of events and activities were held around four individual themes: Learning Tomorrow, Meeting Tomorrow, Working Tomorrow and Living Tomorrow. For example, Swissnex in India organised a 48-hour global hackathon, ‘nexHack Edtech’, which brought together 130 participants from 45 countries to collaborate on finding solutions to the challenges facing education today.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In 2020, Swissnex hosted more than 210 events and activities in partnership with some 190 Swiss organisations. It also assisted 53 Swiss start-ups in their internationalisation process and facilitated exchanges between actors on a variety of topics relevant to Switzerland’s ERI landscape. These figures highlight the added value provided by the Swissnex locations: in connecting ERI actors in their respective countries with partners in Switzerland, they bring together people whose paths may never have crossed otherwise. Such unexpected encounters, made possible by Swissnex, enable the project partners to explore new avenues and enhance their international competitiveness. A global approach to ERI promotes knowledge-sharing and personnel mobility, both of which benefit Swiss actors in ERI and Switzerland’s reputation as a centre for research and innovation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Swissnex is the global network connecting Switzerland and the world in education, research, and innovation. Our mission is to support the outreach and active engagement of our partners in the international exchange of knowledge, ideas and talent. The five main Swissnex locations are established in the world’s most innovative regions. Together with around twenty Science Offices and Counselors based in Swiss Embassies, they contribute to strengthen Switzerland’s profile as a world-leading innovation hotspot.&lt;br /&gt;Swissnex is an initiative of the State Secretariat for Education, Research and Innovation and is part of the Confederation’s network abroad managed by the Federal Department of Foreign Affairs. The Swissnex activities are based on a collaborative approach, relying on public and private partnerships and funding.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Communication State Secretariat for Education, Research, and Innovation SERI medien@sbfi.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="214452">
        <title>Swissnex 2020 annual report</title>
        <uri>https://annualreport.swissnex.org/</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <keywords>
      <keyword id="325.18" org-id="1080">
        <name lang="de">Akademie der Naturwissenschaften Schweiz</name>
        <name lang="fr">Académie suisse des sciences naturelles</name>
        <name lang="it">Accademia svizzera di scienze naturali</name>
        <name lang="en">Swiss Academy of Sciences</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="325.11" org-id="1080">
        <name lang="de">Eidgenössische Technische Hochschule ETH</name>
        <name lang="fr">Ecole polytechnique fédérale EPF</name>
        <name lang="it">Politecnico federale</name>
        <name lang="en">Federal Institutes of Technology</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="325.25" org-id="1080">
        <name lang="de">Euresearch</name>
        <name lang="fr">Euresearch</name>
        <name lang="it">Euresearch</name>
        <name lang="en">Euresearch</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="325.20" org-id="1080">
        <name lang="de">Forschungsförderung</name>
        <name lang="fr">Encouragement de la recherche</name>
        <name lang="it">Promozione della ricerca</name>
        <name lang="en">Research promotion</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="325.27" org-id="1080">
        <name lang="de">Institution</name>
        <name lang="fr">Institution</name>
        <name lang="it">Istituzione</name>
        <name lang="en">Institution</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="325.22" org-id="1080">
        <name lang="de">Raumfahrt</name>
        <name lang="fr">Affaires spatiales</name>
        <name lang="it">Questioni spaziali</name>
        <name lang="en">Space affairs</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="325.16" org-id="1080">
        <name lang="de">Schweizerische Akademie der Geistes- und Sozialwissenschaften</name>
        <name lang="fr">Académie suisse des sciences humaines et sociales</name>
        <name lang="it">Accademia svizzera di scienze morali e sociali</name>
        <name lang="en">Swiss Academy of Humanities and Social Sciences</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="325.17" org-id="1080">
        <name lang="de">Schweizerische Akademie der medizinischen Wissenschaften</name>
        <name lang="fr">Académie suisse des sciences médicales</name>
        <name lang="it">Accademia svizzera delle scienze mediche</name>
        <name lang="en">Swiss Academy of Medical Sciences</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="325.19" org-id="1080">
        <name lang="de">Schweizerische Akademie der technischen Wissenschaften</name>
        <name lang="fr">Académie suisse des sciences techniques</name>
        <name lang="it">Accademia svizzera delle scienze tecniche</name>
        <name lang="en">Swiss Academy of Engineering Sciences</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="325.15" org-id="1080">
        <name lang="de">Schweizerischer Nationalfonds</name>
        <name lang="fr">Fonds national suisse</name>
        <name lang="it">Fondo nazionale Svizzero</name>
        <name lang="en">Swiss National Science Foundation</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="325.12" org-id="1080">
        <name lang="de">Stipendien</name>
        <name lang="fr">Bourses</name>
        <name lang="it">Borse di studio</name>
        <name lang="en">Scholarships</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="325.8" org-id="1080">
        <name lang="de">Technologie</name>
        <name lang="fr">Technologie</name>
        <name lang="it">Tecnologia</name>
        <name lang="en">Technology</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="325.1" org-id="1080">
        <name lang="de">Universitäten</name>
        <name lang="fr">Universités</name>
        <name lang="it">Università</name>
        <name lang="en">Universities</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="325.23" org-id="1080">
        <name lang="de">Weltraum</name>
        <name lang="fr">Espace</name>
        <name lang="it">Spazio</name>
        <name lang="en">Space</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="325.10" org-id="1080">
        <name lang="de">Wissenschaft</name>
        <name lang="fr">Science</name>
        <name lang="it">Scienza</name>
        <name lang="en">Science</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="325.21" org-id="1080">
        <name lang="de">Wissenschaftsaussenpolitik</name>
        <name lang="fr">Politique scientifique extérieure</name>
        <name lang="it">Politica scientifica dell'esterno</name>
        <name lang="en">Foreign scientific policy</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="325.30" org-id="1080">
        <name lang="de">Bildung</name>
        <name lang="fr">Education</name>
        <name lang="it">Educazione</name>
        <name lang="en">Education</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="325.31" org-id="1080">
        <name lang="de">Berufsbildung</name>
        <name lang="fr">Formation professionnelle</name>
        <name lang="it">Formazione professionale</name>
        <name lang="en">Vocational and Professional Education and Training</name>
      </keyword>
    </keywords>
    <topics>
      <topic id="8">
        <name lang="de">Bildung und Forschung</name>
        <name lang="fr">Formation et recherche</name>
        <name lang="it">Formazione e ricerca</name>
        <name lang="en">Education and Research</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="45">
        <name lang="de">Technologie</name>
        <name lang="fr">Technologie</name>
        <name lang="it">Tecnologia</name>
        <name lang="en">Technology</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
