<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="77813" revoked="no">
    <version>2</version>
    <pubdate>2020-01-16</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="301" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>301</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement des Innern</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'intérieur</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'interno</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Home Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="201" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>201</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="301">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement des Innern</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'intérieur</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'interno</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Home Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <department id="201">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Startschuss für die Veranstaltungsreihe zum UN-Weltdatenforum</title>
      <lead>Die öffentliche Statistik ist unverzichtbar, um zu messen, ob die in der Agenda 2030 festgehaltenen Ziele der nachhaltigen Entwicklung erreicht werden. Sie steht daher im Fokus des dritten UN-Weltdatenforums der Vereinten Nationen (UNWDF), das vom 18. bis 21. Oktober 2020 in Bern stattfindet. Im Vorfeld dieser internationalen Konferenz wird unter dem Label «Road to Bern» eine Reihe weiterer Veranstaltungen organisiert.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Die öffentliche Statistik dient der Politik als Grundlage für faktenbasierte Entscheidungen und spielt daher im demokratischen Prozess eine entscheidende Rolle. Sie informiert zudem die Bevölkerung über die Umsetzung der Agenda 2030. Bis zur Eröffnung des Forums am 18. Oktober 2020 wird der Bund an mehreren Tagungen zum Thema Daten bzw. nachhaltige Entwicklung im In- und Ausland teilnehmen. Parallel dazu veranstaltet er im Rahmen der Initiative «Road to Bern» eigene Anlässe. Der erste zum Thema Gesundheit findet am Weltwirtschaftsforum (WEF) in Davos statt. Die verschiedenen Veranstaltungen sollen die Öffentlichkeit auf die statistischen Herausforderungen in Zusammenhang mit der Agenda 2030 aufmerksam machen und deren Umsetzung in der Schweiz fördern. Einige befassen sich zudem mit der Bedeutung der Genderstatistiken, die häufig noch immer lückenhaft sind.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Die Herausforderungen des UNWDF&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;Das UNWDF wurde im Zuge der Agenda 2030 von den UN-Mitgliedstaaten lanciert, um den steigenden Datenbedarf zur Messung der nachhaltigen Entwicklung gerecht zu werden und innovative Ansätze zu fördern. Darüber hinaus soll es dazu beitragen, dass alle Länder hochwertige und vergleichbare Standarddaten veröffentlichen, die zugänglich, aktuell und zuverlässig sind. Vor allem Länder, deren statistisches System weniger gut entwickelt ist, stellt diese Aufgabe vor eine grosse Herausforderung.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Nähere Informationen&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Website: https://roadtobern.ch/de/&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Facebook: https://www.facebook.com/road2bern/&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Twitter: https://twitter.com/road2bern/ &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Instagram: https://www.instagram.com/road2bern/ &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Medienstelle des BFS: media@bfs.admin.ch Kommunikation EDA, kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions>
        <revision date="2020-01-17 15:12" type="R"/>
      </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Forum mondial des Nations unies sur les données: coup d’envoi des manifestations</title>
      <lead>La statistique publique est indispensable pour mesurer la réalisation des objectifs de développement durable fixés dans l’Agenda 2030. Elle sera au cœur des débats du troisième Forum mondial des Nations unies sur les données (UNWDF) organisé à Berne du 18 au 21 octobre 2020. Dans la perspective de cette conférence internationale de premier plan, une série de manifestations seront organisées sous le label «Road to Bern».</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;La statistique publique permet aux politiques de prendre des décisions fondées sur des faits et joue ainsi un rôle essentiel pour la démocratie. Elle permet aussi d'informer les citoyennes et citoyens de la mise en œuvre de l'Agenda 2030. Jusqu'à l'ouverture du Forum le 18 octobre, la Confédération sera associée à plusieurs conférences sur les données ou le développement durable en Suisse et à l'étranger. Elle organisera également ses propres manifestations. La première aura lieu lors du Forum économique mondial de Davos (WEF) et sera consacrée à la santé. Ces différentes manifestations, prévues dans le cadre de l'initiative «Road to Bern», permettront aussi de sensibiliser l'opinion publique aux défis statistiques posés par l'Agenda 2030 et de soutenir sa mise en œuvre en Suisse. Certaines mettront également l'accent sur la nécessité des statistiques de genre qui sont encore souvent lacunaires.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Les enjeux du UNWDF&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;Le UNWDF a été lancé par les États membres de l'ONU dans le sillage de l'Agenda 2030. Il doit permettre de répondre aux besoins croissants en données pour mesurer le développement durable et promouvoir des solutions novatrices. Il doit également favoriser la publication par tous les pays de données de qualité, standardisées et comparables, accessibles, actuelles et fiables. Un défi de taille, notamment pour ceux dont le système statistique est moins développé.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;I&lt;strong&gt;nformations complémentaires&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Site Internet: https://roadtobern.ch/fr/&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Facebook: https://www.facebook.com/road2bern/ &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Twitter: https://twitter.com/road2bern/&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Instagram: https://www.instagram.com/road2bern/ &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Service des médias de l’OFS: media@bfs.admin.ch Communication DFAE, kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions>
        <revision date="2020-01-17 15:12" type="R"/>
      </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Forum mondiale delle Nazioni Unite sui dati: prendono il via le manifestazioni</title>
      <lead>La statistica pubblica è fondamentale per misurare la realizzazione degli obiettivi dello sviluppo sostenibile dell’Agenda 2030, che costituirà il fulcro dei dibattiti del terzo Forum mondiale delle Nazioni Unite sui dati (UNWDF) previsto a Berna dal 18 al 21 ottobre 2020. Nell’ottica di questa conferenza chiave, è stata organizzata una serie di manifestazioni marchiate «Road to Bern».</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;La statistica pubblica, che gioca un ruolo essenziale per la democrazia, consente alla politica di prendere decisioni basate su fatti concreti e permette di informare i cittadini sull'attuazione dell'Agenda 2030. Fino all'apertura del Forum che avrà luogo il 18 ottobre, la Confederazione sarà associata a numerose conferenze sui dati o sullo sviluppo sostenibile in Svizzera e all'estero. Inoltre, organizzerà proprie manifestazioni, la prima delle quali dedicata alla salute in occasione del Forum economico mondale di Davos (WEF). Queste varie manifestazioni, pianificate nell'ambito dell'iniziativa «Road to Bern», permetteranno anche di sensibilizzare l'opinione pubblica sulle sfide lanciate dall'Agenda 2030 e di sostenerne l'attuazione in Svizzera. Alcune evidenzieranno anche la necessità delle statistiche di genere che spesso sono ancora carenti. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Le sfide dell'UNWDF&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;Il Forum mondiale delle Nazioni Unite sui dati (UNWDF), istituito dai Paesi membri dell'ONU quando adottarono l'Agenda 2030, deve permettere di soddisfare le esigenze crescenti in materia di dati, fondamentali per misurare lo sviluppo sostenibile e promuovere approcci innovativi. Inoltre, deve favorire la pubblicazione, da parte di tutti i Paesi, di dati di qualità, uniformi, nonché comparabili, accessibili, attuali e attendibili. Una grande sfida, soprattutto per quei Paesi il cui sistema statistico è meno sviluppato.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Informazioni supplementari&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sito internet: https://roadtobern.ch/fr/ (disponibile in tedesco, francese e inglese)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Facebook: https://www.facebook.com/road2bern/ &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Twitter: https://twitter.com/road2bern/ &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Instagram: https://www.instagram.com/road2bern/&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Servizio stampa dell’UST: media@bfs.admin.ch Comunicazione DFAE, kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions>
        <revision date="2020-01-17 15:12" type="R"/>
      </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>United Nations World Data Forum: first events take place</title>
      <lead>Achievement of the sustainable development goals set out in the 2030 Agenda can only be measured with the help of official statistics. These will be the key focus of the third United Nations World Data Forum (UNWDF) to be held in Bern from 18 to 21 October 2020. Under the label of the «Road to Bern», a series of events is planned in the run-up to this high-profile international conference.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Official statistics enable fact-based political decision making and fulfil an essential democratic role. It also allows information about the implementation of the 2030 Agenda to reach the general public. The Confederation will be involved in several conferences on data or sustainable development in Switzerland and abroad, leading up to the opening of the Forum on 18 October. It will also organise its own events, the first of which will take place during the World Economic Forum in Davos (WEF) on the subject of health. These different events, under the banner of the «Road to Bern», will also raise public awareness of the statistical challenges posed by the 2030 Agenda and lend support to its implementation in Switzerland. Some events will emphasise the need for statistics in areas that are still often lacking in data.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tasks facing the UNWDF&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;The UNWDF was launched by the UN Member States in response to the 2030 Agenda, to meet the growing needs for data to measure sustainable development and harness the power of technology and other innovative tools. It also aims to encourage all countries to publish hig -quality data that is standardised, comparable, accessible, up to date and reliable. This is a formidable challenge, especially for countries whose statistical systems are less well developed.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Further informations&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Site Internet: https://roadtobern.ch/en/ &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Facebook: https://www.facebook.com/road2bern/ &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Twitter: https://twitter.com/road2bern/ &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Instagram: https://www.instagram.com/road2bern/&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>FSO Media Service: media@bfs.admin.ch Communication FDFA, kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions>
        <revision date="2020-01-17 15:12" type="R"/>
      </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
