<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="77809" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2020-01-16</pubdate>
    <blocking-period>2020-01-16</blocking-period>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="1047" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>701</department-id>
      <name lang="de">AGROSCOPE</name>
      <name lang="fr">AGROSCOPE</name>
      <name lang="it">AGROSCOPE</name>
      <name lang="en">AGROSCOPE</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.agroscope.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.agroscope.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.agroscope.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.agroscope.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de"/>
      <email lang="fr"/>
      <email lang="it"/>
      <email lang="en"/>
    </originator>
    <department id="701">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Wirtschaft, Bildung und Forschung</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'économie, de la formation et de la recherche</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'economia, della formazione e della ricerca</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Economic Affairs, Education and Research</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Zürich-Reckenholz</city>
      <title>Ob ein oder mehrere Bt-Toxine in Gentech-Pflanzen – kein Unterschied für Nützlinge</title>
      <lead>Die Forschungsgruppe Biosicherheit bei Agroscope hat Literaturstudien über gentechnisch veränderte Pflanzen durchgeführt, die mehrere insekten-aktive Toxine von Bacillus thuringiensis (Bt) gleichzeitig produzieren. Die Fachleute konnten zeigen, dass sie keine erhöhte Gefahr für Nicht-Zielorganismen wie z.B. Nützlinge darstellen.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Bt-Pflanzen sind gentechnisch verändert und produzieren Eiweisse, die für bestimmte schädliche Insekten giftig sind. Für moderne Bt-Sorten von Nutzpflanzen werden in zunehmenden Masse mehrere Bt-Toxine kombiniert, was die Zielschädlinge effizienter bekämpft, das Spektrum der Zielschädlinge erweitert und die Entwicklung von Resistenzen verlangsamt.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Es wurde wiederholt die Befürchtung geäussert, dass von gentechnisch veränderten Pflanzen mit mehreren Bt-Toxinen eine erhöhte Gefahr für Nicht-Zielorganismen im Ökosystem ausgeht, da die einzelnen Eiweisse miteinander in Wechselwirkung treten könnten. So könnten Arten geschädigt werden, welche gegen die einzelnen Toxine nicht empfindlich sind.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Jörg Romeis und Michael Meissle von Agroscope haben daher eine systematische Literatursuche in allen wichtigen Datenbanken durchgeführt, um nach Hinweisen für Wechselwirkungen von Bt-Toxinen zu suchen, die zu einer unerwarteten Schädigung von Nicht-Zielorganismen führen könnten. Das Ergebnis der Studie wurde gerade in der Fachzeitschrift «Trends in Biotechnology» veröffentlicht. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;In der Literatur wurden keinerlei Hinweise gefunden, dass Bt-Toxine in Kombination ein anderes Wirkungsspektrum als die einzelnen Eiweisse haben. Nach heutigem Wissensstand können gentechnisch veränderte Pflanzen, die kombinierte Bt-Toxine enthalten, als ebenso sicher für Nicht-Zielorganismen angesehen werden wie Pflanzen mit nur einem Bt-Toxin.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Hintergrund zur Studie&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Die Forschungsgruppe Biosicherheit bei Agroscope untersucht seit zwanzig Jahren die Auswirkungen von insektenresistenten, gentechnisch veränderten Pflanzen auf die Biodiversität und ihre Ökosystemdienstleistungen.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Die Experten haben für die aktuelle Studie eine systematische Analyse der Literatur vorgenommen und annähernd 2300 Literaturstellen auf relevante Ergebnisse hin geprüft. Insgesamt 58 wissenschaftliche Publikationen mit Resultaten aus Labor- oder Feldversuchen wurden identifiziert. Im Labor wurden die Studien mit insgesamt 34 Insektenarten aus 24 Familien und 11 Ordnungen durchgeführt. Feldversuche haben die Häufigkeiten von Insekten vor allem in Bt-Mais und Bt-Baumwolle erfasst und wurden in 5 bzw. 7 Ländern durchgeführt.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Gentech-Moratorium&lt;/b&gt;&lt;b&gt; in der Schweiz&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Das seit 2005 geltende Gentech-Moratorium für den kommerziellen Anbau von gentechnisch veränderten Pflanzen wurde vom Parlament dreimal verlängert und läuft Ende 2021 aus. Die Forschung, einschliesslich Feldversuche, ist von diesem Moratorium explizit ausgeschlossen.&lt;b&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Jörg Romeis Agroscope Reckenholzstrasse 191 8046 Zürich Mediendienst Agroscope media@agroscope.admin.ch +41 58 466 88 62</contact>
      <attachment id="197112">
        <title>Bt-Mais in einem Gewächshaus (Mario Waldburger, Agroscope)</title>
        <format>jpg</format>
        <size-kb>2362</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/59948.jpg</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="197115">
        <title>Bt-Baumwolle in einer Klimakabine (Mario Waldburger, Agroscope)</title>
        <format>jpg</format>
        <size-kb>8385</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/59951.jpg</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <link id="197111">
        <title>Paper Link</title>
        <uri>https://www.cell.com/action/doSearch?searchType=quick&amp;searchText=Stacked+Bt+Proteins+Pose+No+New+Risks+to+Nontarget+Arthropods&amp;searchScope=series&amp;journalCode=tibtec&amp;seriesISSNFltraddfilter=0167-7799&amp;occurrences=all&amp;code=cell-site&amp;journalCode=tibtec</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Zurich-Reckenholz</city>
      <title>Plantes OGM avec une ou plusieurs toxine(s) Bt: pas de différence pour les auxiliaires</title>
      <lead>Le groupe de recherche Biosécurité d'Agroscope a réalisé une revue de la littérature scientifique sur les plantes génétiquement modifiées produisant plusieurs toxines de Bacillus thuringiensis (Bt). Ce travail montre que les plantes en question ne présentent pas de risque accru pour les organismes non ciblés comme les auxiliaires.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Les plantes Bt sont génétiquement modifiées et produisent des protéines toxiques pour certains insectes nuisibles. Les variétés modernes contiennent de plus en plus souvent des combinaisons de plusieurs toxines Bt. Ainsi, la lutte contre les ravageurs est plus efficace, la gamme des organismes ciblés est élargie et l’essor des résistances est ralenti.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Des craintes ont été plusieurs fois exprimées par rapport à ces plantes génétiquement modifiées produisant plusieurs toxines, qui présenteraient un risque accru pour les organismes non ciblés: les interactions entre les protéines individuelles pourraient nuire à des espèces insensibles aux toxines individuelles.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Jörg Romeis et Michael Meissle d'Agroscope ont effectué une analyse bibliographique systématique dans les principales bases de données scientifiques. Ils ont cherché à savoir si des interactions entre des toxines Bt peuvent entraîner des dommages imprévus pour les organismes non ciblés. Les résultats de l'étude viennent d'être publiés dans la revue «Trends in Biotechnology». &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Cette étude n’a trouvé aucun indice que les toxines Bt combinées possèdent une gamme d'action différente de celle des toxines individuelles. Selon les connaissances actuelles, les plantes génétiquement modifiées contenant des toxines Bt combinées peuvent être considérées comme aussi sûres pour les organismes non ciblés que les plantes produisant une seule toxine.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Contexte de l'étude&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Depuis vingt ans, le groupe de recherche Biosécurité d'Agroscope étudie les plantes génétiquement modifiées résistantes aux insectes ainsi que leurs effets sur la biodiversité et les services écosystémiques.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Les auteurs de l’étude ont procédé à une analyse systématique de la littérature. Ils ont examiné quelque 2300 références et identifié 58 publications scientifiques rapportant des résultats pertinents: d’une part des études en laboratoire faites sur 34 espèces d'insectes (de 24 familles et 11 ordres), d’autre part des essais en plein champ menés avec du maïs Bt et du coton Bt (dans 5 et 7 pays respectivement) pour mesurer l’abondance des insectes.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Le moratoire sur le génie génétique en Suisse&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;En vigueur depuis 2005, le moratoire sur la culture commerciale de plantes génétiquement modifiées a été prolongé trois fois par le Parlement et expire à la fin de 2021. Il ne s’applique pas à la recherche et notamment aux essais sur le terrain.&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Jörg Romeis Agroscope Reckenholzstrasse 191 8046 Zürich Service medias Agroscope media@agroscope.admin.ch +41 58 466 88 62</contact>
      <attachment id="197114">
        <title>Maïs Bt dans une serre (Mario Waldburger, Agroscope)</title>
        <format>jpg</format>
        <size-kb>2362</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/59950.jpg</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="197116">
        <title>Le coton Bt dans une chambre climatique (Mario Waldburger, Agroscope)</title>
        <format>jpg</format>
        <size-kb>8385</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/59952.jpg</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <link id="197111">
        <title>Paper Link</title>
        <uri>https://www.cell.com/action/doSearch?searchType=quick&amp;searchText=Stacked+Bt+Proteins+Pose+No+New+Risks+to+Nontarget+Arthropods&amp;searchScope=series&amp;journalCode=tibtec&amp;seriesISSNFltraddfilter=0167-7799&amp;occurrences=all&amp;code=cell-site&amp;journalCode=tibtec</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Zurich-Reckenholz</city>
      <title>No Difference for Beneficials between GM Plants with One or More Bt-Toxins</title>
      <lead>The Biosafety Research Group at Agroscope has conducted a review of the literature on genetically modified plants that produce several insect-active Bacillus thuringiensis (Bt) toxins simultaneously. The experts were able to show that the toxins did not pose an increased risk for non-target organisms such as beneficials.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Bt-plants are genetically modified to produce proteins that are toxic for certain insect pests. Increasingly, Bt-crop varieties are engineered to produce several Bt-toxins simultaneously, in order to control target pests more efficiently, expand the range of target pests, and slow down the development of resistance. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The concern has repeatedly been expressed that genetically engineered plants producing several Bt-toxins could pose an increased risk for non-target organisms in the ecosystem, since the individual proteins produced might interact with one another. This could damage species that are not sensitive to the individual toxins. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;For this reason, Agroscope researchers Jörg Romeis and Michael Meissle have conducted a systematic literature search of all major databases in order to spot evidence of interactions between Bt-toxins that might cause unexpected damage to non-target organisms. The results of the study have just been published in the journal &lt;i&gt;Trends in Biotechnology&lt;/i&gt;. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;No evidence was found in the literature that Bt-toxins in combination have a different action spectrum than the individual proteins. According to our current state of knowledge, genetically engineered plants containing combined Bt-toxins can thus be regarded as just as safe for non-target organisms as plants with a single Bt-toxin. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Background to the Study&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The Biosafety Research Group at Agroscope has been studying the effects of insect-resistant genetically modified plants on biodiversity and its ecosystem services for twenty years now.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;For the current study, experts performed a systematic analysis of the literature, checking approximately 2300 literature references for relevant results. Altogether, 58 scientific publications with results from laboratory or field trials were identified. The laboratory studies were conducted with a total of 35 insect species from 24 families and 11 orders. Field trials recording the frequencies of insects chiefly in Bt-maize and Bt-cotton were carried out in 5 and 7 countries, respectively. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Moratorium on Genetic Engineering in Switzerland&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;In force since 2005, the moratorium on the commercial cultivation of genetically engineered plants has been extended three times by the Swiss Parliament, and expires at the end of 2021. Research, including field trials, is explicitly excluded from this moratorium.&lt;b&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Jörg Romeis Agroscope Reckenholzstrasse 191 8046 Zürich Media service Agroscope media@agroscope.admin.ch +41 58 466 88 62</contact>
      <attachment id="197113">
        <title>Bt-maize in a greenhouse (Mario Waldburger, Agroscope)</title>
        <format>jpg</format>
        <size-kb>2362</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/59949.jpg</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="197117">
        <title>Bt cotton in a climate chamber (Mario Waldburger, Agroscope)</title>
        <format>jpg</format>
        <size-kb>8385</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/59953.jpg</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <link id="197111">
        <title>Paper Link</title>
        <uri>https://www.cell.com/action/doSearch?searchType=quick&amp;searchText=Stacked+Bt+Proteins+Pose+No+New+Risks+to+Nontarget+Arthropods&amp;searchScope=series&amp;journalCode=tibtec&amp;seriesISSNFltraddfilter=0167-7799&amp;occurrences=all&amp;code=cell-site&amp;journalCode=tibtec</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <offers>
      <offer id="232" org-id="1047">
        <name lang="de">Nachhaltigkeit</name>
        <name lang="fr">Durabilité</name>
        <name lang="it">Durevolezza</name>
        <name lang="en">Sustainability</name>
      </offer>
      <offer id="234" org-id="1047">
        <name lang="de">Pflanzenbau</name>
        <name lang="fr">Production végétale</name>
        <name lang="it">Produzione vegetale</name>
        <name lang="en">Plant production</name>
      </offer>
      <offer id="235" org-id="1047">
        <name lang="de">pflanzliche Lebensmittel</name>
        <name lang="fr">Aliments végétals</name>
        <name lang="it">Prodotti alimentari végétals</name>
        <name lang="en">Vegetal food</name>
      </offer>
      <offer id="236" org-id="1047">
        <name lang="de">Pflanzenschutz</name>
        <name lang="fr">Stratégies phytosanitaires</name>
        <name lang="it">Strategie fitosanitarie</name>
        <name lang="en">Plant protection</name>
      </offer>
      <offer id="242" org-id="1047">
        <name lang="de">Ökonomie &amp; Technik</name>
        <name lang="fr">Economie &amp; technique</name>
        <name lang="it">Economia &amp; tecnica</name>
        <name lang="en">Economy &amp; technique</name>
      </offer>
      <offer id="243" org-id="1047">
        <name lang="de">Landschaft &amp; Biodiversität</name>
        <name lang="fr">Paysage &amp; diversité biologique</name>
        <name lang="it">Paesaggio &amp; diversità biologica</name>
        <name lang="en">Landscape &amp; biodiversity</name>
      </offer>
      <offer id="246" org-id="1047">
        <name lang="de">Sichereit &amp; Qualität in der Lebensmittelkette</name>
        <name lang="fr">Sécurité &amp; qualité dans la chaîne alimentaire</name>
        <name lang="it">Sicurezza &amp; qualità nella catena alimentare</name>
        <name lang="en">Safety &amp; quality in the food chain</name>
      </offer>
    </offers>
    <keywords>
      <keyword id="4" org-id="1047">
        <name lang="de">Ackerbau</name>
        <name lang="fr">Grandes cultures</name>
        <name lang="it">Campicoltura</name>
        <name lang="en">Field crops</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="11" org-id="1047">
        <name lang="de">Genressourcen</name>
        <name lang="fr">Ressources génétiques</name>
        <name lang="it">Risorse genetiche</name>
        <name lang="en">Genetic resources</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="13" org-id="1047">
        <name lang="de">Pflanzenkrankheiten</name>
        <name lang="fr">Maladies des plantes</name>
        <name lang="it">Malattie delle piante</name>
        <name lang="en">Plant diseases</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="14" org-id="1047">
        <name lang="de">Schädlinge</name>
        <name lang="fr">Ravageurs</name>
        <name lang="it">Parassiti</name>
        <name lang="en">Pests</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="26" org-id="1047">
        <name lang="de">Pflanzliche Biotechnologie</name>
        <name lang="fr">Biotechnologie végétale</name>
        <name lang="it">Biotecnologia vegetale</name>
        <name lang="en">Plant biotechnology</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="41" org-id="1047">
        <name lang="de">Biosicherheit</name>
        <name lang="fr">Biosécurité</name>
        <name lang="it">Sicurezza biologica</name>
        <name lang="en">Biosafety</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="74" org-id="1047">
        <name lang="de">GVO</name>
        <name lang="fr">OGM</name>
        <name lang="it">OGM</name>
        <name lang="en">GMO</name>
      </keyword>
    </keywords>
    <topics>
      <topic id="15">
        <name lang="de">Gesundheit</name>
        <name lang="fr">Santé</name>
        <name lang="it">sanità</name>
        <name lang="en">Health</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="29">
        <name lang="de">Umwelt und Natur</name>
        <name lang="fr">Environnement et nature</name>
        <name lang="it">Ambiente e natura</name>
        <name lang="en">Environment and Nature</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="37">
        <name lang="de">Konsum</name>
        <name lang="fr">Consommation</name>
        <name lang="it">Consumo</name>
        <name lang="en">Consumer Affairs</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="38">
        <name lang="de">Landwirtschaft</name>
        <name lang="fr">Agriculture</name>
        <name lang="it">Agricoltura</name>
        <name lang="en">Agriculture</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="47">
        <name lang="de">Wirtschaft</name>
        <name lang="fr">Économie</name>
        <name lang="it">Economia</name>
        <name lang="en">Economic Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
