<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="69660" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2018-01-31</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="1070" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>1070</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Der Bundesrat</name>
      <name lang="fr">Conseil fédéral</name>
      <name lang="it">Il Consiglio federale</name>
      <name lang="en">The Federal Council</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.admin.ch/gov/de/start.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.admin.ch/gov/fr/accueil.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.admin.ch/gov/it/pagina-iniziale.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.admin.ch/gov/en/start.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="201" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>201</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="1070">
      <name lang="de">Der Bundesrat</name>
      <name lang="fr">Conseil fédéral</name>
      <name lang="it">Il Consiglio federale</name>
      <name lang="en">The Federal Council</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.admin.ch/gov/de/start.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.admin.ch/gov/fr/accueil.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.admin.ch/gov/it/pagina-iniziale.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.admin.ch/gov/en/start.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <department id="201">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Neuer Direktor der Direktion für europäische Angelegenheiten sowie weitere Ernennungen</title>
      <lead>In mehreren Schweizer Auslandvertretungen und an der Zentrale des Eidgenössischen Departements für auswärtige Angelegenheiten (EDA) in Bern kommt es 2018 zu personellen Wechseln. Diese erfolgen im Rahmen der üblichen Versetzungsrhythmen aufgrund von Ernennungen durch den Bundesrat. Die Ernennungen der Missionschefinnen und -chefs im Ausland werden mit der Erteilung des Agréments durch den Gaststaat wirksam. </lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Roberto Balzaretti&lt;/strong&gt;, gegenwärtig Direktor (mit Botschaftertitel) der Direktion für Völkerrecht und Rechtsberater des EDA in Bern, wird per 1. Februar 2018 Direktor der Direktion für europäische Angelegenheiten (DEA) in Bern. Die DEA ist innerhalb der Bundesverwaltung beim Europadossier federführend und soll angesichts zunehmender und dringender Anforderungen in der Europapolitik eine stärkere Koordinationsfunktion wahrnehmen. Der neue DEA-Direktor Balzaretti übernimmt zudem gleichzeitig die Koordination der gesamten Verhandlungen mit der Europäischen Union von Staatssekretärin Pascale Baeriswyl, welche die weiteren Aufgabenbereiche des EDA betreut.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Für die Dauer der Leitung der DEA hat der Bundesrat Herrn Balzaretti den Titel Staatssekretär verliehen. Der bisherige DEA-Direktor, Botschafter Henri Gétaz, wurde zum Generalsekretär der EFTA ernannt; er verbleibt bis zur Übernahme seiner neuen Funktion per 1. September 2018 als Berater im EDA.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Lukas Gasser&lt;/strong&gt;, gegenwärtig Missionschef in Jerewan, wird neu ausserordentlicher und bevollmächtigter Botschafter im Haschemitischen Königreich Jordanien und in der Republik Irak, mit Sitz in Amman. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Lukas Rosenkranz&lt;/strong&gt;, gegenwärtig stellvertretender Leiter der internen Revision EDA in Bern, wird neu ausserordentlicher und bevollmächtigter Botschafter in der Demokratischen Volksrepublik Algerien. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Alexander Hoffet&lt;/strong&gt;, gegenwärtig Postenchef in Shanghai, wird neu ausserordentlicher und bevollmächtigter Botschafter in der Slowakischen Republik.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Arno Wicki&lt;/strong&gt;, gegenwärtig stellvertretender Missionschef in Santiago de Chile, wird neu ausserordentlicher und bevollmächtigter Botschafter in der Republik Chile. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Emilija Georgieva Regamey&lt;/strong&gt;, gegenwärtig stellvertretende Missionschefin in Singapur, wird neu ausserordentliche und bevollmächtigte Botschafterin in der Republik Kroatien. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Georg Steiner&lt;/strong&gt;, gegenwärtig Chef (mit Botschaftertitel) des Krisenmanagement-Zentrums, Staatssekretariat EDA, Bern, wird neu ausserordentlicher und bevollmächtigter Botschafter in der Bundesrepublik Nigeria, der Republik Niger, der Republik Tschad sowie Ständiger Vertreter (Permanent Representative) der Schweiz bei der Wirtschaftsgemeinschaft der westafrikanischen Staaten ECOWAS (Economic Community of West African States), mit Sitz in Abuja. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Patric Franzen&lt;/strong&gt;, gegenwärtig stellvertretender Missionschef in Moskau, wird neu ausserordentlicher und bevollmächtigter Botschafter in Georgien. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pietro Piffaretti&lt;/strong&gt;, gegenwärtig Chef der Sektion Sektorielle Politiken bei der Mission der Schweiz bei der Europäischen Union in Brüssel, wird neu ausserordentlicher und bevollmächtigter Botschafter im Fürstentum Liechtenstein, mit Sitz in Bern. Gleichzeitig ernannte das EDA Herrn Piffaretti zum Chef der Grenzüberschreitende Zusammenarbeit in der Politischen Direktion in Bern. Für die Ausübung dieser Funktion hat ihm der Bundesrat den Botschaftertitel verliehen.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Caroline Bichet-Anthamatten&lt;/strong&gt;, gegenwärtig zweite stellvertretende Missionschefin bei der Mission der Schweiz bei der Europäischen Union in Brüssel, wird neu Vizedirektorin und Chefin der Abteilung Politik in der Direktion für europäische Angelegenheiten in Bern. Für die Ausübung dieser neuen Funktion hat ihr der Bundesrat den Botschaftertitel verliehen. &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Information EDA Tel. +41 58 462 31 53 info@eda.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Nouveau directeur de la Direction des affaires européennes et autres nominations</title>
      <lead>Des changements de personnel auront lieu en 2018 dans plusieurs représentations suisses à l’étranger ainsi qu’à la centrale du Département fédéral des affaires étrangères (DFAE), à Berne. Ils s’inscrivent dans la cadence usuelle des transferts et font suite à des nominations par le Conseil fédéral. Les nominations des cheffes et chefs de mission à l’étranger deviendront effectives au moment où ces personnes recevront l’agrément de l’État hôte. </lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Roberto Balzaretti&lt;/strong&gt;, actuellement directeur (avec titre d’ambassadeur) de la Direction du droit international public et jurisconsulte du DFAE, à Berne, sera à la tête de la Direction des affaires européennes (DAE), à Berne, à partir du 1er février 2018. La DAE exerce au sein de l’administration fédérale un rôle de chef de file sur le dossier européen et devrait voir sa fonction de coordination renforcée face aux demandes croissantes et urgentes auxquelles elle est appelée à répondre en matière de politique européenne. Le nouveau directeur de la DAE Roberto Balzaretti reprend également la coordination de l’ensemble des négociations avec l’Union européenne assurée actuellement par la secrétaire d’État Pascale Baeriswyl, à qui est confiée la responsabilité de tous les autres domaines d’activité du DFAE. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Le Conseil fédéral a conféré à Monsieur Balzaretti le titre de secrétaire d’État pour la durée de son mandat à la tête de la DAE. L’actuel directeur de cette division, l’ambassadeur Henri Gétaz, a été nommé secrétaire général de l’AELE; il restera affecté au DFAE comme conseiller jusqu’à ce qu’il prenne sa nouvelle fonction le 1er septembre 2018.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Lukas Gasser&lt;/strong&gt;, actuellement chef de mission à Erevan, est nommé ambassadeur extraordinaire et plénipotentiaire au Royaume hachémite de Jordanie et en République d’Irak, avec résidence à Amman. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Lukas Rosenkranz&lt;/strong&gt;, actuellement chef suppléant de l’unité Audit interne du DFAE, à Berne, est nommé ambassadeur extraordinaire et plénipotentiaire en République algérienne démocratique et populaire. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Alexander Hoffet&lt;/strong&gt;, actuellement chef de poste à Shanghai, est nommé ambassadeur extraordinaire et plénipotentiaire en République slovaque.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Arno Wicki&lt;/strong&gt;, actuellement chef de mission suppléant à Santiago du Chili, est nommé ambassadeur extraordinaire et plénipotentiaire en République du Chili. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Emilija Georgieva Regamey&lt;/strong&gt;, actuellement cheffe de mission suppléante à Singapour, est nommée ambassadrice extraordinaire et plénipotentiaire en République de Croatie. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Georg Steiner&lt;/strong&gt;, actuellement chef (avec titre d’ambassadeur) du Centre de gestion des crises du Secrétariat d’État du DFAE à Berne, est nommé ambassadeur extraordinaire et plénipotentiaire en République fédérale du Nigéria, en République du Niger et en République du Tchad, ainsi que représentant permanent (Permanent Representative) de la Suisse auprès de la Communauté économique des États de l’Afrique de l’Ouest (CEDEAO), avec résidence à Abuja. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Patric Franzen&lt;/strong&gt;, actuellement chef de mission suppléant à Moscou, est nommé ambassadeur extraordinaire et plénipotentiaire en Géorgie. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pietro Piffaretti&lt;/strong&gt;, actuellement chef de la Section Politiques sectorielles à la Mission de la Suisse auprès de l’Union européenne à Bruxelles, est nommé ambassadeur extraordinaire et plénipotentiaire en Principauté de Liechtenstein, avec résidence à Berne. Le DFAE a également nommé Monsieur Piffaretti chef de l’unité Coopération transfrontalière de la Direction politique à Berne. Le Conseil fédéral lui a conféré le titre d’ambassadeur pour l’exercice de cette fonction.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Caroline Bichet-Anthamatten&lt;/strong&gt;, actuellement deuxième cheffe de mission suppléante à la Mission de la Suisse auprès de l’Union européenne à Bruxelles, est nommée vice-directrice et cheffe de la Division des affaires politiques au sein de la Direction des affaires européennes à Berne. Le Conseil fédéral lui a conféré le titre d’ambassadeur pour l’exercice de cette fonction. &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Information DFAE Tél. +41 58 462 31 53 info@eda.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Nuovo capo della Direzione degli affari europei e ulteriori nomine</title>
      <lead>Con l’inizio del 2018 sono previsti avvicendamenti di personale presso varie rappresentanze svizzere all’estero e alla Centrale del Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri (DFAE) a Berna. Queste misure si iscrivono nei consueti ritmi di trasferimento e sono frutto delle nomine decise dal Consiglio federale. Le nomine dei capimissione all’estero diventeranno però effettive soltanto con il gradimento da parte delle autorità dello Stato ospite. </lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Roberto Balzaretti&lt;/strong&gt;, attuale capo (con titolo di ambasciatore) della Direzione del diritto internazionale pubblico e consulente giuridico del DFAE a Berna, è stato nominato capo della Direzione degli affari europei (DAE) a Berna dal 1° febbraio 2018. La DAE è l’organo dell’Amministrazione federale a cui compete la gestione del dossier europeo e che, alla luce delle sfide sempre più pressanti e numerose nel campo della politica europea, assumerà una maggiore funzione di coordinamento in questo ambito. Il nuovo direttore della DAE rileverà inoltre il coordinamento di tutti i negoziati con l’Unione europea dalla segretaria di Stato Pascale Baeriswyl, incaricata degli altri settori di attività del DFAE.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Per tutta la durata del suo incarico presso la DAE, il Consiglio federale ha conferito al signor Balzaretti il titolo di segretario di Stato. Il direttore uscente della DAE, il signor Henri Gétaz, è stato nominato segretario generale dell’AELS e rimarrà consulente per il DFAE fino al 1° settembre 2018, data in cui assumerà la sua nuova funzione.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Lukas Gasser&lt;/strong&gt;, attualmente capomissione a Erevan, è stato nominato ambasciatore straordinario e plenipotenziario nel Regno hascemita di Giordania e nella Repubblica dell’Iraq, con sede ad Amman.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Lukas Rosenkranz&lt;/strong&gt;, attualmente capo supplente della Revisione interna DFAE a Berna, è stato nominato ambasciatore straordinario e plenipotenziario nella Repubblica algerina democratica e popolare.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Alexander Hoffet&lt;/strong&gt;, attualmente capoposto a Shanghai, è stato nominato ambasciatore straordinario e plenipotenziario nella Repubblica slovacca.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Arno Wicki&lt;/strong&gt;, attualmente capomissione supplente a Santiago del Cile, è stato nominato ambasciatore straordinario e plenipotenziario nella Repubblica del Cile.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Emilija Georgieva Regamey&lt;/strong&gt;, attualmente capomissione supplente a Singapore, è stata nominata ambasciatrice straordinaria e plenipotenziaria nella Repubblica di Croazia.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Georg Steiner&lt;/strong&gt;, attualmente capo (con titolo di ambasciatore) del Centro di gestione delle crisi, Segreteria di Stato del DFAE a Berna, è stato nominato ambasciatore straordinario e plenipotenziario nella Repubblica federale di Nigeria, nella Repubblica del Niger, nella Repubblica del Ciad e rappresentante permanente (permanent representative) presso la Comunità economica degli Stati dell’Africa occidentale ECOWAS (Economic Community of West African States), con sede ad Abuja.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Patric Franzen&lt;/strong&gt;, attualmente capomissione supplente a Mosca, è stato nominato ambasciatore straordinario e plenipotenziario in Georgia.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pietro Piffaretti&lt;/strong&gt;, attualmente capo della Sezione Politiche settoriali presso la Missione della Svizzera presso l’Unione europea a Bruxelles, è stato nominato ambasciatore straordinario e plenipotenziario nel Principato del Liechtenstein, con sede a Berna. Allo stesso tempo il DFAE lo ha nominato capo dell’unità per la cooperazione transfrontaliera in seno alla Direzione politica a Berna. Per l’esercizio di tale funzione, il Consiglio federale gli ha attribuito il titolo di ambasciatore.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Caroline Bichet-Anthamatten&lt;/strong&gt;, attualmente secondo capomissione supplente presso la Missione della Svizzera presso l’Unione europea a Bruxelles, è stata nominata vicedirettrice e capo della Divisione Politica presso la Direzione degli affari europei a Berna. Per l’esercizio della sua nuova funzione, il Consiglio federale le ha attribuito il titolo di ambasciatrice.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Informazione DFAE Tel. +41 58 462 31 53 info@eda.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>New director of Directorate for European Affairs and other appointments</title>
      <lead>Personnel changes will take place in 2018 at several Swiss representations abroad and at the head office of the Federal Department of Foreign Affairs (FDFA) in Bern, within the framework of the usual transfer rotation based on appointments made by the Federal Council. The appointment of heads of mission abroad becomes effective following approval by the respective host state. </lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Roberto Balzaretti&lt;/strong&gt;, currently director (with title of ambassador) of the Directorate of International Law and legal adviser of the FDFA in Bern, will assume the post of director of the Directorate for European Affairs (DEA) in Bern on 1 February 2018. The DEA is in charge of European policy within the Federal Administration and will in future play a stronger coordinating role in view of the growing and increasingly urgent requirements in that area. Also from 1 February, Mr Balzaretti will take over responsibility for coordinating negotiations with the European Union from State Secretary Pascale Baeriswyl, who remains in charge of the other areas of responsibility of the FDFA. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Federal Council has conferred the title of State Secretary on Mr Balzaretti for the duration of his term of office. The former director of the DEA, Ambassador Henri Gétaz, has been appointed Secretary-General of EFTA and will remain in the FDFA in an advisory capacity until he takes up his new post on 1 September 2018.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Lukas Gasser&lt;/strong&gt;, currently head of mission in Yerevan, will become the new ambassador extraordinary and plenipotentiary to the Hashemite Kingdom of Jordan and the Republic of Iraq, based in Amman. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Lukas Rosenkranz&lt;/strong&gt;, currently deputy head of the FDFA Internal Audit office in Bern, will become the new ambassador extraordinary and plenipotentiary to the People's Democratic Republic of Algeria. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Alexander Hoffet&lt;/strong&gt;, currently head of post in Shanghai, will become the new ambassador extraordinary and plenipotentiary to the Slovak Republic.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Arno Wicki&lt;/strong&gt;, currently deputy head of mission in Santiago de Chile, will become the new ambassador extraordinary and plenipotentiary to the Republic of Chile. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Emilija Georgieva Regamey&lt;/strong&gt;, currently deputy head of mission in Singapore, will become the new ambassador extraordinary and plenipotentiary to the Republic of Croatia. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Georg Steiner&lt;/strong&gt;, currently head (with title of ambassador) of the Crisis Management Centre of the FDFA State Secretariat in Bern, will become the new ambassador extraordinary and plenipotentiary to the Federal Republic of Nigeria, the Republic of Niger and the Republic of Chad, and Permanent Representative of Switzerland to the Economic Community of West African States, based in Abuja. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Patric Franzen&lt;/strong&gt;, currently deputy head of mission in Moscow, will become the new ambassador extraordinary and plenipotentiary to Georgia. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pietro Piffaretti&lt;/strong&gt;, currently head of the Sectoral Policies Section of the Swiss mission to the European Union in Brussels, will become the new ambassador extraordinary and plenipotentiary to the Principality of Liechtenstein, based in Bern. At the same time, the FDFA has appointed Mr Piffaretti as head of cross-border cooperation at the Directorate of Political Affairs in Bern. The Federal Council has conferred upon him the title of ambassador for this function.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Caroline Bichet-Anthamatten&lt;/strong&gt;, currently second deputy head of mission at the Swiss mission to the European Union in Brussels, will become assistant director and head of the Division for Political Affairs of the DEA in Bern. The Federal Council has conferred upon her the title of ambassador for this new function. &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>FDFA Information Tel. +41 58 462 31 53 info@eda.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
