<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="34542" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2010-08-10</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="201" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>201</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="201">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Schweiz hilft Russland im Kampf gegen die Brände</title>
      <lead>In Russland ist kein Ende der Brände abzusehen. Wegen der anhaltenden Trockenheit ist weiterhin mit einer Verschärfung der Lage zu rechnen. Die Schweiz unterstützt Russland im Kampf gegen das Feuer.</lead>
      <text link="no">In Russland ist gemäss den Wetterprognosen in den kommenden Tagen nicht mit einer Abkühlung oder mit Regen zu rechnen. Die Brände breiten sich somit weiter aus. Angesichts der dramatischen Situation hat die Schweiz den russischen Behörden bereits letzte Woche Unterstützung im Kampf gegen das Feuer angeboten. &amp;nbsp;&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Die Schweiz hat dem russischen Nothilfeministerium (EMERCOM) ein breites Hilfsangebot unterbreitet. In einer ersten Phase setzt die Humanitäre Hilfe des Bundes rund 500'000 CHF für Material zum Schutz der zur Brandbekämpfung eingesetzten Personen ein. Die Geräte und die Schutzausrüstungen werden in der Schweiz sofort beschafft und nach Russland&amp;nbsp;geliefert.&amp;nbsp;&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Ein vierköpfiges Abklärungs- und Ärzteteam ist seit Dienstag Morgen in Moskau im Einsatz. Es wickelt die Lieferung des Brandbekämpfungsmaterials ab und prüft zusammen mit russischen Ärzten die Unterstützung von Provinzspitälern zur Betreuung von Brandopfern.&amp;nbsp;&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Die Experten verstärken zudem die Schweizer Vertretung in Moskau. Die Botschaft erhält vorderhand den Betrieb aufrecht und sieht von einer Schliessung bzw. Evakuierung aus der Stadt Moskau ab. Die Schweizer Gemeinschaft sowie das Personal der Botschaft werden regelmässig über die Lage informiert.</text>
      <contact>Information EDA Bundeshaus West CH-3003 Bern Tel.: +41 (0)31 322 31 53 Fax: +41 (0)31 324 90 47 E-Mail: info@eda.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>La Suisse vient en aide à la Russie en proie aux flammes</title>
      <lead>En Russie, les incendies ne semblent pas près de cesser. Au contraire, avec la persistance de la sécheresse, la situation risque encore de s’aggraver. La Suisse apporte son soutien aux autorités russes dans leur lutte contre les flammes.</lead>
      <text link="no">D’après les prévisions météorologiques, la Russie ne connaîtra ces prochains jours ni baisse de température, ni pluie. Les incendies vont donc continuer à se propager.&amp;nbsp; Face à cette situation dramatique, la Suisse a offert dès la semaine dernière son aide aux autorités russes. &amp;nbsp;&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; La Suisse a proposé au ministère russe des secours d’urgence (EMERCOM) de lui prêter main-forte dans un grand nombre de domaines. Dans un premier temps, l’Aide humanitaire de la Confédération a débloqué 500&amp;nbsp;000 CHF pour du matériel de protection des personnes mobilisées dans la lutte contre les incendies. Equipements et vêtements de protection seront achetés en Suisse et livrés sans délai.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Une équipe de médecins et d’experts chargés d’évaluer la situation, composée de quatre personnes, est depuis mardi matin à pied d’œuvre à Moscou. Elle supervise la livraison du matériel de lutte contre le feu et examine, en collaboration avec des médecins russes, la capacité des hôpitaux de province à fournir les soins nécessaires aux victimes. &amp;nbsp;&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Les experts viennent en outre renforcer la représentation suisse à Moscou. L’ambassade reste ouverte pour le moment et renonce à évacuer son personnel de la ville. La communauté suisse sur place et les membres de l’ambassade sont informés régulièrement de la situation.</text>
      <contact>Information DFAE Palais fédéral ouest CH-3003 Berne Tél.: (+41) 031 322 31 53 Fax: (+41) 031 324 90 47 E-Mail: info@eda.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>La Svizzera aiuta la Russia nella lotta contro gli incendi</title>
      <lead>Lo spegnimento degli incendi in Russia sembra ancora lontano e la persistente siccità potrebbe anzi comportare un peggioramento della situazione. La Svizzera ha così deciso di affiancare la Russia nella lotta contro il fuoco.</lead>
      <text link="no">Le previsioni del tempo in Russia non preannunciano per i prossimi giorni né un calo della temperatura né precipitazioni e di conseguenza si teme un ulteriore propagarsi degli incendi. Alla luce di questi drammatici eventi, già la scorsa settimana la Svizzera ha offerto il suo aiuto alle autorità russe nella lotta contro gli incendi.&amp;nbsp;&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; La Svizzera ha offerto al Ministero russo delle situazioni di emergenza (EMERCOM) un ampio ventaglio di possibilità d’intervento. In una prima fase l’Aiuto umanitario della Confederazione mette a disposizione circa 500'000 franchi per il materiale necessario a proteggere le persone che stanno lottando contro il fuoco. Le attrezzature e l’abbigliamento ignifugo vengono acquistati immediatamente in Svizzera e forniti con urgenza.&amp;nbsp;&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Un’équipe di quattro persone tra ricognitori e medici è operativa a Mosca dallo scorso martedì e si sta occupando della consegna del materiale per la lotta antincendio e, insieme a medici russi, degli interventi a sostegno dei piccoli ospedali di provincia per la cura degli ustionati.&amp;nbsp;&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Gli esperti stanno inoltre dando man forte alla rappresentanza svizzera a Mosca. Per il momento l’Ambasciata svizzera continua a svolgere la sua attività e non ha ancora ventilato l’ipotesi di una chiusura o di un’evacuazione da Mosca. La comunità svizzera e il personale dell’ambasciata vengono informati regolarmente in merito all’evolversi della situazione. &amp;nbsp;</text>
      <contact>Informazione DFAE Palazzo federale ovest CH-3003 Berna Tel.: (+41) 031 322 31 53 Fax: (+41) 031 324 90 47 E-Mail: info@eda.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Switzerland is helping Russia to fight the fires</title>
      <lead>There is no sign of an early end to the fires ravaging Russia. Given the continuing dry weather, a worsening of the situation is likely. Switzerland is supporting Russia in its attempts to combat the fires.</lead>
      <text link="no">According to the weather forecasts, there is little likelihood of lower temperatures or of rain in the next few days. The wildfires are spreading. In light of this dramatic situation, the Swiss authorities offered Russia support in fighting the fire last week.&amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp;&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Switzerland has offered several forms of assistance to the Russian Ministry for Emergency Situations (EMERCOM). In the first phase, the Swiss Humanitarian Aid Unit provided about 500,000 CHF for protective firefighting material. The equipment and protective clothing were immediately purchased in Switzerland and dispatched to Russia.&amp;nbsp;&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; A four-person assessment and medical team has been working in Moscow since Tuesday morning. It is organising the delivery of the fire-fighting equipment, and together with Russian doctors is looking at ways of caring for burns victims in provincial hospitals.&amp;nbsp;&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; The experts are also strengthening Swiss representation in Moscow. At the moment the embassy is carrying out normal operations and does not envisage closing the embassy or evacuating staff from Moscow. The Swiss community and the embassy staff are receiving regular updates about the situation.&amp;nbsp;</text>
      <contact>Information FDFA Bundeshaus West CH-3003 Bern Tel.: (+41) 031 322 31 53 Fax: (+41) 031 324 90 47 E-Mail: info@eda.admin.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
