<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="75181" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2019-05-23</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="1076" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>701</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Rat der Eidgenössischen Technischen Hochschulen</name>
      <name lang="fr">Conseil des écoles polytechniques fédérales</name>
      <name lang="it">Consiglio dei politecnici federali</name>
      <name lang="en">Board of the Swiss Federal Institutes of Technology</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.ethrat.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.ethrat.ch/fr</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.ethrat.ch/it</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.ethrat.ch/en</www>
      <email lang="de">gian.casutt@ethrat.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">gian.casutt@ethrat.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">gian.casutt@ethrat.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">gian.casutt@ethrat.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="701">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Wirtschaft, Bildung und Forschung</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'économie, de la formation et de la recherche</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'economia, della formazione e della ricerca</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Economic Affairs, Education and Research</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern/Zürich</city>
      <title>ETH-Rat fokussiert strategische Ausrichtung auf die Digitalisierung</title>
      <lead>Der ETH-Rat hat an seiner Sitzung vom 22./23. Mai über die Finanz- und Investitions­planung für das Jahr 2020 entschieden und die Jahresberichte zu den strategischen Fokusbereichen diskutiert. Zudem behandelte der ETH-Rat den Antrag der ETH Zürich auf Entlassung einer Professorin und erhielt einen Zwischenstand zur Administrativuntersuchung betreffend Governance an der ETH Zürich.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Der ETH-Rat verabschiedete an seiner Sitzung vom 22./23. Mai 2019 die Finanz- und Investitionsplanung für das Jahr 2020. Dazu gehören das Budget, der Investitionskredit für Bauten und das Bauprogramm 2020. Die Trägerfinanzierung des Bundes beläuft sich voraussichtlich auf 2,566 Mrd. Franken. Dies entspricht einem Rückgang von 15 Mio. Franken im Vergleich zum Budget 2019. Der operative Ertrag steigt jedoch um 56,5 Mio. Franken an, da im kommenden Jahr viele Lehr- und Forschungsprojekte durchgeführt werden, für welche die Institutionen des ETH-Bereichs erfolgreich kompetitive Mittel eingeworben haben. Im verabschiedeten Budget enthalten sind auch Mittel für den Aktionsplan Digitalisierung des Bundes sowie für die strategischen Fokusbereiche Datenwissenschaften, Personalisierte Gesundheit und zugehörige Technologien sowie Advanced Manufacturing und Energie. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2&gt;Strategische Fokusbereiche zur Stärkung der Digitalisierung&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;Der ETH-Rat nahm Kenntnis von der Jahresberichterstattung zu den genannten strategischen Fokusbereichen. Die Institutionen des ETH-Bereichs, zu denen die ETH Zürich, die EPFL in Lausanne, das PSI, die WSL, die Empa und die Eawag gehören, sind wichtige Akteure, welche die Schweiz erfolgreich ins Zeitalter der Digitalisierung führen. Ein Beispiel aus dem Bereich Lehre ist der neue Master in Cyber Security, der gemeinsam von der ETH Zürich und der EPFL angeboten wird. Viele Lehrstühle werden ausserdem im Zuge der Digitalisierung angepasst und Professorinnen und Professoren mit entsprechendem Profil gesucht. Alleine an der ETH Zürich werden jährlich 25 bis 30 Professuren neu besetzt und entlang der Bedürfnisse aus Forschung und Lehre strategisch neu ausgerichtet. In den letzten Jahren hat die Hochschule knapp 10 Prozent der Studiengänge von Grund auf neu konzipiert und eingeführt, bei einem Viertel hat sie grössere Revisionen vorgenommen. Das Fach Maschinenbau beispielsweise hat sich fundamental gewandelt, von Turbinen zu Mikro- und Nanorobotik für medizinische Anwendungen.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Ein wichtiges Beispiel für ein erfolgreiches Projekt ist die Plattform «Renku» des Swiss Data Science Centers (SDSC), welches Träger des strategischen Fokusbereichs Datenwissenschaften ist. Diese Open-Source-Software ermöglicht den Wissens- und Datenaustausch zwischen Spitzenforschung und Wirtschaft. Damit unterstützt das SDSC die digitale Entwicklung der Schweizer Industrie und seiner zahlreichen KMU.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2&gt;Antrag der ETH Zürich auf Entlassung einer Professorin&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;Die ETH Zürich hat im März beim ETH-Rat die Entlassung einer Professorin beantragt. Der ETH-Rat nahm nun Kenntnis von der Stellungnahme der betroffenen Professorin. Das Verfahren ist hängig und es ist noch offen, wann der Entscheid fallen wird.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2&gt;Administrativuntersuchung an der ETH Zürich&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;Des Weiteren lässt der ETH-Rat Vorwürfe betreffend Governance, Verteilung der finanziellen Mittel und Geschlechtergleichstellung am Physikdepartement der ETH Zürich von einem externen, unabhängigen Wirtschaftsprüfungs- und Treuhandunternehmen untersuchen. Der ETH-Rat nahm Kenntnis vom Zwischenstand der Arbeiten. Der Bericht wird in einigen Wochen erwartet.&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Gian-Andri Casutt Leiter Kommunikation des ETH-Rats Häldeliweg 15, CH-8092 Zürich gian.casutt@ethrat.ch +41 44 632 20 03</contact>
      <link id="190249">
        <title>Medienmitteilung ETH-Rat vom 23. Mai 2019</title>
        <uri>https://www.ethrat.ch/de/medien/medienmitteilungen/strategische-ausrichtung-digitalisierung</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne/Zurich</city>
      <title>Le Conseil des EPF accentue son orientation stratégique sur la numérisation</title>
      <lead>Lors de sa séance des 22 et 23 mai, le Conseil des EPF a approuvé la planification des financements et des investissements pour l’année 2020 et discuté du compte rendu annuel sur les grands axes stratégiques. Le Conseil des EPF a en outre examiné la proposition de l’ETH Zurich de licencier une professeure et a été informé de l’avancement de l’enquête administrative concernant la gouvernance au sein de l’ETH Zurich.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;A l’occasion de sa séance des 22 et 23 mai 2019, le Conseil des EPF a adopté la planification des financements et des investissements pour l’année 2020, qui inclut le budget, le crédit d’investissement dans les constructions du Domaine des EPF et le Programme des constructions 2020. Le financement fédéral devrait s’élever à 2 566 mia CHF, ce qui correspond à un recul de 15 mio CHF par rapport au Budget 2019. Les produits d’exploitation augmentent cependant de 56,5 mio CHF, étant donné que les institutions du Domaine des EPF ont réussi à obtenir des fonds compétitifs importants pour financer de nombreux projets d’enseignement et de recherche qui seront menés l’an prochain. Le budget adopté comprend également des fonds destinés au plan d’action Suisse numérique de la Confédération et aux grands axes stratégiques Science des données, Santé personnalisée et technologies associées, &lt;i&gt;Advanced Manufacturing&lt;/i&gt; et Energie.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2&gt;Renforcer la numérisation grâce aux grands axes stratégiques&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;Le Conseil des EPF a pris acte du compte rendu annuel relatif aux grands axes stratégiques. Les institutions du Domaine des EPF, c’est-à-dire l’ETH Zurich, l’EPFL, le PSI, le WSL, l’Empa et l’Eawag, sont des acteurs importants qui permettront à la Suisse d’entrer pleinement dans l’ère du numérique. Parmi les exemples en matière d’enseignement figure le nouveau master de cybersécurité proposé conjointement par l’ETH Zurich et l’EPFL. De nombreuses chaires d’enseignement sont par ailleurs adaptées en raison des changements induits par la numérisation, et l’on recherche des professeures et professeurs ayant le profil adéquat. A l’ETH Zurich, ce ne sont pas moins de 25 à 30 chaires d’enseignement qui sont repourvues chaque année et font l’objet d’une réorientation stratégique en fonction des besoins identifiés dans la recherche et l’enseignement. Ces dernières années, l’Ecole a intégré à son programme de cours près de 10% de cursus entièrement nouveaux. Dans 25% des cas, elle a procédé à des changements plus marqués. La filière de génie mécanique, p. ex., a connu une mutation profonde: autrefois axée sur les turbines, elle se concentre aujourd’hui sur la microrobotique et la nanorobotique pour les applications médicales.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Un exemple notable de projet réussi est la plateforme «Renku» du &lt;i&gt;Swiss Data Science Center&lt;/i&gt; (SDSC), qui constitue un élément central du grand axe stratégique dédié à la science des données. Ce logiciel &lt;i&gt;open source&lt;/i&gt; permet l’échange de savoir et de données entre la recherche de pointe et l’économie. Le SDSC favorise ainsi le développement numérique de l’industrie suisse et de ses nombreuses PME.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2&gt;Proposition de l’ETH Zurich de licencier une professeure&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;En mars dernier, l’ETH Zurich a proposé au Conseil des EPF de licencier une professeure. Le Conseil des EPF a pris acte de la prise de position de la professeure concernée. La procédure est en cours, et la date de la décision n’a pas encore été fixée.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2&gt;Enquête administrative à l’ETH Zurich&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;Le Conseil des EPF a par ailleurs chargé une société fiduciaire et d’audit indépendante d’examiner les reproches en matière de gouvernance, d’allocation des ressources financières et d’égalité des genres formulés à l’encontre du Département de physique de l’ETH Zurich. Le Conseil des EPF a pris acte de l’état d’avancement des travaux. Le rapport devrait lui être remis dans quelques semaines.&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Gian-Andri Casutt Responsable de la communication du Conseil des EPF Häldeliweg 15, CH-8092 Zurich gian.casutt@ethrat.ch +41 44 632 20 03</contact>
      <link id="190250">
        <title>Communiqué de presse du CEPF du 23 mai 2019</title>
        <uri>https://www.ethrat.ch/fr/medias/communiques/orientation-strategique-numerisation</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Berne/Zurich</city>
      <title>ETH Board focuses its strategic orientation on digitalisation</title>
      <lead>At its meeting of 22/23 May, the ETH Board made decisions concerning the finance and investment planning for 2020 and debated the annual reporting on the strategic focus areas. The ETH Board also dealt with ETH Zurich’s application for the dismissal of a professor and received an interim report on the administrative enquiry into governance at ETH Zurich.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;At its meeting of 22/23 May 2019, the ETH Board adopted the finance and investment planning for 2020. This includes the budget, the investment credit for buildings and the 2020 construction programme. The total federal contribution is expected to amount to 2.566bn CHF. This is a decrease of 15m CHF in comparison with the 2019 budget. Operating revenues, however, will increase by 56.5m CHF since in the coming year, many teaching and research projects will be conducted for which the institutions of the ETH Domain successfully raised competitive funds. The budget that was adopted also includes resources for the Confederation’s digitalisation action plan, as well as for the strategic focus areas of Data Sciences, Personalised Health and related technologies, as well as Advanced Manufacturing and Energy.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2&gt;Strategic focus areas for the reinforcement of digitalisation&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;The ETH Board took note of the annual reporting on the above-mentioned focus areas. The institutions of the ETH Domain, which include ETH Zurich, EPFL in Lausanne, PSI, WSL, Empa and Eawag, are important actors which are leading Switzerland into the age of digitalisation. One example from the field of teaching is the new Master in Cyber Security, which is offered jointly by ETH Zurich and EPFL. Furthermore, many chairs are adapted in the course of digitalisation, and professors with a corresponding profile are being sought. At ETH Zurich alone, 25 to 30 new professors are appointed every year and their chairs are strategically realigned along the axis of research and teaching requirements. In the last few years, the university has reconceptualised and introduced just under 10 per cent of its degree courses; and a quarter of its courses have been subjected to significant revisions. The major in machine-building, for instance, has been fundamentally changed, from turbines to micro- and nanorobotics for medical applications.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;An important example of a successful project is the Renku platform of the Swiss Data Science Center SDSC, a key element of the strategic focus area of Data Sciences. This open-source software enables an exchange of knowledge and data between top-notch research and business. In this way, the SDSC supports the digital development of the Swiss industry and its numerous SMEs.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2&gt;Application by ETH Zurich for a professor’s dismissal&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;In March, ETH Zurich submitted an application for the dismissal of a professor to the ETH Board. The ETH Board now took cognisance of the statement made by the professor concerned; the proceeding is still pending and the date of the decision remains open.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2&gt;Administrative enquiry at ETH Zurich&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;Furthermore, the ETH Board is having reproaches concerning governance, allocation of financial resources and gender equality at ETH Zurich’s Department of Physics investigated by an external, independent auditing and trust company. The ETH Board took note of the interim report. The final report is expected in a few weeks’ time.&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Gian-Andri Casutt Head of Communication of the ETH Board Häldeliweg 15, CH-8092 Zurich gian.casutt@ethrat.ch +41 44 632 20 03</contact>
      <link id="190251">
        <title>Media Release ETH-Board, 23 May 2019</title>
        <uri>https://www.ethrat.ch/en/media/releases/strategic-orientation-digitalisation</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="8">
        <name lang="de">Bildung und Forschung</name>
        <name lang="fr">Formation et recherche</name>
        <name lang="it">Formazione e ricerca</name>
        <name lang="en">Education and Research</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
