<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="74996" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2019-05-14</pubdate>
    <blocking-period>2019-05-14</blocking-period>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="318" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>301</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Bundesamt für Statistik</name>
      <name lang="fr">Office fédéral de la statistique</name>
      <name lang="it">Ufficio federale di statistica</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Statistical Office</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.statistik.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.statistique.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.statistica.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.statistics.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@bfs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@bfs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@bfs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@bfs.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="301">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement des Innern</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'intérieur</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'interno</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Home Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Neuchâtel</city>
      <title>Produzenten- und Importpreisindex bleibt im April 2019 insgesamt stabil</title>
      <lead>Der Gesamtindex der Produzenten- und Importpreise blieb im April 2019 gegenüber dem Vormonat unverändert. Sein Stand beträgt 102,2 Punkte (Dezember 2015 = 100). Höhere Preise zeigten insbesondere Benzin und Maschinen, billiger wurden Diesel und Heizöl. Im Vergleich zum April 2018 ging das Preisniveau des Gesamtangebots von Inland- und Importprodukten um 0,6% zurück. Dies geht aus den Zahlen des Bundesamts für Statistik (BFS) hervor.</lead>
      <text link="no">Diese Medienmitteilung und weitere Informationen zum Thema finden Sie auf der Website des BFS (siehe Link unten)</text>
      <contact>Info PPI, BFS, Sektion Preise, Tel.: +41 58 463 66 06, E-Mail: ppi@bfs.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="189787">
        <title>Kompletter Text und Mediendossier</title>
        <uri>https://www.bfs.admin.ch/news/de/2019-0099</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Neuchâtel</city>
      <title>L’indice des prix à la production et à l’importation est resté stable dans l’ensemble en avril 2019</title>
      <lead>L'indice des prix à la production et à l'importation est resté inchangé en avril 2019 par rapport au mois précédent. Il se situe à présent à 102,2 points (décembre 2015 = 100). L’essence et les machines notamment ont renchéri, alors que le diesel et le mazout sont devenus meilleur marché. Par rapport à avril 2018, l'indice des prix de l'offre totale des produits indigènes et des produits importés a diminué de 0,6%. Ces chiffres ont été établis par l’Office fédéral de la statistique (OFS).</lead>
      <text link="no">Vous trouverez ce communiqué de presse et d'autres informations sur ce thème sur le site web de l'OFS (voir le lien ci-dessous)</text>
      <contact>Info PPI, OFS, Section Prix, tél.: +41 58 463 66 06, e-mail: ppi@bfs.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="189788">
        <title>Texte intégral et dossier de presse</title>
        <uri>https://www.bfs.admin.ch/news/fr/2019-0099</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Neuchâtel</city>
      <title>Nel complesso stabile l’indice dei prezzi alla produzione e all’importazione nel mese di aprile 2019</title>
      <lead>Nell’aprile 2019 l’indice totale dei prezzi alla produzione e all’importazione è rimasto invariato rispetto al mese precedente, portandosi a 102,2 punti (dicembre 2015 = 100). Aumentano in particolare i prezzi di benzina e macchine, mentre scendono quelli di diesel e olio da riscaldamento. Rispetto ad aprile 2018, il livello dei prezzi dell’offerta totale dei prodotti indigeni e importati è diminuito dello 0,6%. È quanto emerge dai risultati dell’Ufficio federale di statistica (UST).</lead>
      <text link="no">Il presente comunicato stampa e ulteriori informazioni sul tema sono reperibili sulla pagina Internet dell'UST (link sotto)</text>
      <contact>Info PPI, UST, Sezione Prezzi, tel.: +41 58 463 66 06, e-mail: ppi@bfs.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="189789">
        <title>Testo integrale e dossier per i media</title>
        <uri>https://www.bfs.admin.ch/news/it/2019-0099</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Neuchâtel</city>
      <title>The Producer and Import Price index remained stable overall in April 2019</title>
      <lead>The Producer and Import Price Index remained unchanged in April 2019 compared with the previous month. The index stood at 102.2 points (December 2015 = 100). Higher prices were seen in particular for petrol and machinery, while diesel and heating oil became cheaper. Compared with April 2018, the price level of the whole range of domestic and imported products fell by 0.6%. These are some of the findings from the Federal Statistical Office (FSO).</lead>
      <text link="no">This press release and further information on this topic can be found on the FSO website (see link below)</text>
      <contact>Info PPI, FSO, Prices section, tel.: +41 58 463 66 06, email: ppi@bfs.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="189790">
        <title>Please note that the English version only includes the release's lead</title>
        <uri>https://www.bfs.admin.ch/news/en/2019-0099</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <keywords>
      <keyword id="317.6" org-id="318">
        <name lang="de">Preise</name>
        <name lang="fr">Prix</name>
        <name lang="it">Prezzi</name>
        <name lang="en">Prices</name>
      </keyword>
    </keywords>
    <topics>
      <topic id="43">
        <name lang="de">Statistik</name>
        <name lang="fr">Statistiques</name>
        <name lang="it">Statistica</name>
        <name lang="en">Statistics</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="47">
        <name lang="de">Wirtschaft</name>
        <name lang="fr">Économie</name>
        <name lang="it">Economia</name>
        <name lang="en">Economic Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
