<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="74881" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2019-05-02</pubdate>
    <blocking-period>2019-05-02</blocking-period>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="324" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>301</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Swissmedic, Schweizerisches Heilmittelinstitut</name>
      <name lang="fr">Swissmedic, Institut suisse des produits thérapeutiques</name>
      <name lang="it">Swissmedic, Istituto svizzero per gli agenti terapeutici</name>
      <name lang="en">Swiss Agency for Therapeutic Products</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.swissmedic.ch/</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.swissmedic.ch/?lang=3</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.swissmedic.ch/?lang=4</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.swissmedic.ch/?lang=2</www>
      <email lang="de"/>
      <email lang="fr"/>
      <email lang="it"/>
      <email lang="en"/>
    </originator>
    <department id="301">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement des Innern</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'intérieur</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'interno</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Home Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Illegale Arzneimittelimporte: Risiken werden unterschätzt</title>
      <lead>Im Auftrag des Schweizerischen Heilmittelinstituts Swissmedic hat die Eidgenössische Zollverwaltung im letzten Jahr 3'203 Sendungen mit illegalen Arzneimitteln sichergestellt. Dank einem neuen, vereinfachten Verfahren liegt die Gesamtzahl bedeutend höher als im Vorjahr (2017: 1'060). Am häufigsten werden nach wie vor Potenzmittel illegal importiert, gefolgt von Arzneimitteln, die abhängig machen können (Psychopharmaka, Schlaf- und Beruhigungsmittel).</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Dass im Vergleich zum Vorjahr mehr Sendungen beschlagnahmt werden konnten, ist auch das Ergebnis einer intensiveren Zusammenarbeit zwischen den Behörden. Im Jahr 2018 entwickelten Swissmedic und die Eidgenössische Zollverwaltung ein vereinfachtes Verfahren und testeten dieses im Rahmen eines Pilotprojekts gegen illegale Importe von Erektionsförderern. Deren Anteil an den zurückbehaltenen Sendungen ist deshalb besonders hoch.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Aufgrund der positiven Ergebnisse wird das vereinfachte Verfahren im Bereich illegale Arzneimittelimporte seit 2019 für weitere Wirkstoffe angewendet. Damit wird der politische Wille umgesetzt, mit den verfügbaren Ressourcen den grenzüberschreitenden Onlinehandel mit illegalen Heilmitteln effizienter zu bekämpfen.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Gefahren eigenmächtiger Importe nicht unterschätzen&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Besorgniserregend sind die Importe des angstlösenden Arzneimittels Xanax aus illegalen Quellen im Internet und über das Darknet. Der darin enthaltene Wirkstoff Alprazolam aus der Gruppe der Benzodiazepine untersteht der Betäubungsmittelregulierung und wird in den letzten Jahren vermehrt missbräuchlich verwendet. Benzodiazepine sind hochwirksam und machen schnell abhängig. Eine Einnahme über längere Zeit erfordert regelmässige ärztliche Kontrollen.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In Zusammenarbeit mit dem Zoll beschlagnahmte Swissmedic im letzten Jahr 15 illegale Sendungen von Xanax aus Kambodscha, Ungarn und anderen Ländern. Gemäss Informationen der Herstellerfirma des Originalpräparates sind mehr als 95 % der illegal gehandelten Xanax-Präparate gefälscht. Schweizer Labors, die Muster aus der Partyszene analysiert haben, wiesen falsche Inhaltsstoffe wie Antiallergika und Psychopharmaka anstelle des Originalwirkstoffs nach. Swissmedic warnt eindringlich davor, Xanax und andere psychotrope Medikamente aus dem Internet zu beziehen. Die sichere Anwendung von rezeptpflichtigen Arzneimitteln erfordert eine persönliche Fachberatung.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Arzneimitteln aus der legalen Vertriebskette in der Schweiz kann nach wie vor vertraut werden. Die einwandfreie Qualität dieser Präparate wird laufend geprüft. Noch nie sind Fälschungen von Arzneimitteln in Schweizer Aufmachung aufgetaucht.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class="nsbtextkasten"&gt;&lt;b&gt;Illegale Medikamente: Nicht drin, was draufsteht&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Beim Bezug von Arzneimitteln aus unbekannter Quelle über das Internet ist die Gefahr gross, dass nicht «drin ist, was draufsteht». Die Einnahme von gefälschten Medikamenten schlechter Qualität ist ein grosses Gesundheitsrisiko. Swissmedic warnt vor dem Bezug und der Anwendung von nicht zugelassenen Medikamenten, die über Werbe-E-Mails und über das Internet angepriesen werden. Bei solchen Produkten fehlen meist jegliche Informationen zu möglichen Risiken. Nur bei Arzneimitteln aus kontrollierten Bezugsquellen ist gewährleistet, dass die Qualität den Anforderungen entspricht und die Gesundheit nicht gefährdet wird.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Swissmedic, Schweizerisches Heilmittelinstitut Medienstelle +41 58 462 02 76 media@swissmedic.ch</contact>
      <attachment id="189489">
        <title>Beim Import beschlagnahmte Sendung mit Xanax aus illegaler Quelle ©Swissmedic</title>
        <format>jpg</format>
        <size-kb>206</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/56773.jpg</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <link id="189481">
        <title>Herkunft der illegalen Importe/Art der Produkte (Tabellen)</title>
        <uri>https://www.swissmedic.ch/swissmedic/de/home/news/mitteilungen/illegally-imported-medicinal-products-2018.html#873556125</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Importations illégales de médicaments : des risques sous-estimés</title>
      <lead>Sur mandat de l’Institut suisse des produits thérapeutiques Swissmedic, l’Administration fédérale des douanes a saisi l’an dernier 3203 envois contenant des médicaments importés illégalement : une nouvelle procédure simplifiée a ainsi permis d’obtenir un résultat nettement supérieur à celui de l’année précédente (2017 : 1060). Les importations illégales concernent toujours majoritairement des médicaments contre l’impuissance. Viennent ensuite les médicaments susceptibles d’engendrer une dépendance (psychotropes, somnifères et calmants).</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;La saisie d’un plus grand nombre d’envois par rapport à l’année précédente est également le fruit d’une collaboration plus intensive entre les autorités. En 2018, Swissmedic et l’Administration fédérale des douanes ont développé une procédure simplifiée et l’ont testée dans le cadre d’un projet pilote visant les importations illégales de stimulants de l’érection. C’est pourquoi ces produits représentent une part particulièrement élevée des envois retenus.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Au vu des résultats positifs, la procédure simplifiée est utilisée depuis 2019 pour d’autres principes actifs dans le domaine des importations illégales de médicaments. La volonté politique de lutter plus efficacement, avec les ressources disponibles, contre le commerce en ligne de produits thérapeutiques illégaux à l’échelle internationale est ainsi mise en œuvre.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Ne pas sous-estimer les risques d’importations non autorisées&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Les importations de Xanax, médicament anxiolytique, provenant de sources illégales sur Internet et via le darknet sont préoccupantes. Son principe actif, l’alprazolam, fait partie du groupe des benzodiazépines et est soumis à la réglementation sur les stupéfiants. Ces dernières années, il a de plus en plus fait l’objet d’une utilisation abusive. Les benzodiazépines sont très efficaces et engendrent rapidement une dépendance. Une prise prolongée nécessite des contrôles médicaux réguliers.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;En collaboration avec les douanes, Swissmedic a saisi l’an dernier 15 envois illégaux de Xanax en provenance du Cambodge, de Hongrie et d’autres pays. Selon les informations du fabricant de la préparation originale, plus de 95 % des préparations de Xanax commercialisées illégalement sont contrefaites. Des laboratoires suisses ayant analysé des échantillons trouvés dans des soirées ont mis en évidence des ingrédients incorrects, tels qu’antihistaminiques et psychotropes, à la place du principe actif original. Swissmedic met instamment en garde la population contre l’achat sur Internet de Xanax et d’autres psychotropes. L’utilisation sûre des médicaments soumis à ordonnance passe par les conseils personnalisés de professionnels.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Les médicaments issus de la chaîne de distribution légale en Suisse restent quant à eux dignes de confiance. La qualité irréprochable de ces préparations fait l’objet de vérifications constantes. Aucune contrefaçon de médicaments dans leur présentation suisse n’a encore été découverte.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class="nsbtextkasten"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Médicaments illégaux : composition non conforme&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;En cas d’achat de médicaments d’origine inconnue sur Internet, il y a un risque important que leur contenu ne soit pas conforme à ce qui est indiqué. La prise de médicaments contrefaits de mauvaise qualité représente un risque élevé pour la santé. Swissmedic met en garde contre l’achat et l’utilisation de médicaments non autorisés proposés via des courriels promotionnels et sur Internet. La plupart du temps, les informations sur les risques éventuels font défaut pour de tels produits. Seuls les médicaments provenant de sources d’approvisionnement contrôlées offrent des garanties de qualité conformes aux exigences et ne mettent pas en danger la santé.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Swissmedic, Institut suisse des produits thérapeutiques Service de presse +41 58 462 02 76 media@swissmedic.ch</contact>
      <attachment id="189490">
        <title>Envoi de Xanax de source illégale saisi à l’importation ©Swissmedic</title>
        <format>jpg</format>
        <size-kb>206</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/56774.jpg</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <link id="189482">
        <title>Provenance des importations illégales/type de produits (tableaux)</title>
        <uri>https://www.swissmedic.ch/swissmedic/fr/home/news/mitteilungen/illegally-imported-medicinal-products-2018.html#36735656</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Importazioni illegali di medicamenti: rischi sottovalutati</title>
      <lead>Su mandato dell’Istituto svizzero per gli agenti terapeutici Swissmedic, lo scorso anno l’Amministrazione federale delle dogane ha sequestrato 3’203 spedizioni contenenti medicamenti illegali, una cifra complessiva che, grazie alla nuova procedura semplificata, è nettamente superiore ai dati dell’anno precedente (2017: 1’060). Le importazioni illegali più frequenti restano quelle degli stimolanti per l’erezione, seguite dai medicamenti con potenziale di dipendenza (psicofarmaci, sonniferi e sedativi).</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;L’aumento dei sequestri di spedizioni rispetto all’anno precedente è anche il risultato di una collaborazione più intensa tra le autorità. Nel 2018 Swissmedic e l’Amministrazione federale delle dogane hanno sviluppato una procedura semplificata, testandola nell’ambito di un progetto pilota contro le importazioni illegali di stimolanti per l’erezione. Questo spiega la porzione particolarmente elevata di tali prodotti tra le spedizioni trattenute.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Visti i risultati positivi, dal 2019 la procedura semplificata nel campo delle importazioni illegali di medicamenti viene applicata anche per altri principi attivi, attuando così la volontà politica di combattere il commercio internazionale online di agenti terapeutici illegali in modo più efficiente con le risorse disponibili.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Non sottovalutare i pericoli delle importazioni arbitrarie&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Le importazioni dell’ansiolitico Xanax da fonti illegali via Internet e Darknet destano preoccupazione. Il principio attivo Alprazolam, che appartiene al gruppo delle benzodiazepine ed è contenuto nello Xanax, è assoggettato alla normativa sugli stupefacenti e negli ultimi anni ne viene fatto un impiego sempre più abusivo. Le benzodiazepine sono molto efficaci e creano rapidamente dipendenza. Un’assunzione per un lungo periodo richiede controlli medici regolari.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In collaborazione con la dogana, lo scorso anno Swissmedic ha sequestrato 15 spedizioni illegali di Xanax provenienti da Cambogia, Ungheria e altri Paesi. Stando alle informazioni del fabbricante del preparato originale, più del 95 per cento dei preparati di Xanax commerciati illegalmente è contraffatto. I laboratori svizzeri che hanno analizzato campioni prelevati dalla scena notturna hanno rilevato sostanze diverse dal principio attivo originale, come antiallergici e psicofarmaci. Swissmedic insiste nel mettere in guardia contro l’acquisto su Internet di Xanax e altri medicamenti psicotropi. Per assumere in modo sicuro medicamenti soggetti all’obbligo di prescrizione medica serve una consulenza specialistica personale.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I medicamenti della catena di distribuzione legale in Svizzera sono sempre affidabili; la qualità impeccabile di questi preparati viene costantemente controllata. Finora non sono mai apparse contraffazioni di medicamenti con confezionamento destinato al mercato svizzero.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class="nsbtextkasten"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Medicamenti illegali: il contenuto non corrisponde a quanto dichiarato sull’etichetta&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Acquistando medicamenti da fonte sconosciuta via Internet, il rischio che il contenuto non corrisponda a quanto dichiarato sull’etichetta è considerevole. Assumere medicamenti contraffatti di scarsa qualità è molto rischioso per la salute. Swissmedic mette in guardia contro l’acquisto e l’uso di medicamenti non omologati, pubblicizzati tramite e-mail promozionali o su Internet. Tali prodotti in genere sono forniti senza indicazioni sui potenziali rischi. Solo i medicamenti da fonti d’acquisto controllate garantiscono una qualità conforme ai requisiti, oltre alla tutela della salute.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Swissmedic, Istituto svizzero per gli agenti terapeutici Ufficio stampa +41 58 462 02 76 media@swissmedic.ch</contact>
      <attachment id="189491">
        <title>Spedizione sequestrata di Xanax importato da fonte illegale ©Swissmedic</title>
        <format>jpg</format>
        <size-kb>206</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/56775.jpg</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <link id="189484">
        <title>Provenienza delle importazioni illegali/tipo di prodotti (tabelle)</title>
        <uri>https://www.swissmedic.ch/swissmedic/it/home/news/mitteilungen/illegally-imported-medicinal-products-2018.html#-736905785</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Illegally imported medicinal products: underestimated risks</title>
      <lead>At the request of Swissmedic, the Swiss Agency for Therapeutic Products, the Federal Customs Administration last year seized 3,203 shipments of illegally imported medicinal products: as a result of a new, simplified procedure, the total number was substantially higher compared to the previous year (2017: 1,060). Potency preparations remain at the top of the list of illegally imported substances, followed by medicines with the potential for dependence (psychotropic agents, sleeping tablets and tranquillisers).</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;The fact that more shipments were confiscated compared to the previous year is also the result of closer cooperation between the authorities. In 2018, Swissmedic and the Federal Customs Administration developed a simplified procedure, which was then tested as part of a pilot project to combat illegal imports of erectile stimulants. Consequently, their number as a proportion of the withheld shipments is especially high.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In view of the positive results, as of 2019 the simplified procedure will be used for illegally imported medicinal products containing other active substances. This procedure implements the political will to combat cross-border online trading in illegal therapeutic products more efficiently with the available resources.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Do not underestimate the dangers of unauthorised imports&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;The importation of the anti-anxiety preparation Xanax from illegal sources on the Internet, including the dark net is particularly concerning. Since the active ingredient in Xanax, alprazolam, is a benzodiazepine, it is subject to narcotics regulation and has been increasingly abused in recent years. Benzodiazepines are highly effective and can quickly become addictive. Regular medical check-ups are required if they are taken for prolonged periods.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Last year, in cooperation with the customs authority, Swissmedic confiscated 15 illegal shipments of Xanax from Cambodia, Hungary and other countries. According to information supplied by the manufacturer of the original product, over 95 % of illegally traded Xanax preparations are counterfeit. Swiss laboratories that have analysed samples from the party scene discovered wrong ingredients such as antiallergic and psychotropic agents instead of the original active substance. Swissmedic urgently warns people not to buy Xanax or other psychotropic medicines from the Internet. Prescription-only medicines can be used safely only if patients obtain expert advice in person.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Medicinal products from the legal distribution chain in Switzerland can still be trusted. The flawless quality of these products is constantly checked. Counterfeit medicinal products in Swiss packaging have never been encountered.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class="nsbtextkasten"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Illegal medicines: they don't contain what is claimed&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;When medicines are procured from unknown sources online, there is a considerable risk that the package does not contain what is stated on the label. Using poor-quality counterfeit medicines poses a major risk to health. Swissmedic advises against purchasing and using unauthorised medicines offered in promotional e-mails and via the Internet. Such products usually come with no information on possible risks. Purchasing medicinal products from controlled sources is the only way of guaranteeing that their quality complies with requirements and that they pose no risk to health.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Swissmedic, Swiss Agency for Therapeutic Products Media Office +41 58 462 02 76 media@swissmedic.ch</contact>
      <attachment id="189492">
        <title>Shipment of illegally sourced Xanax confiscated during import ©Swissmedic</title>
        <format>jpg</format>
        <size-kb>206</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/56776.jpg</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <link id="189485">
        <title>Origin of illegal imports/type of products (charts)</title>
        <uri>https://www.swissmedic.ch/swissmedic/en/home/news/mitteilungen/illegally-imported-medicinal-products-2018.html#999914181</uri>
        <position>Content</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="15">
        <name lang="de">Gesundheit</name>
        <name lang="fr">Santé</name>
        <name lang="it">sanità</name>
        <name lang="en">Health</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="48">
        <name lang="de">Zoll</name>
        <name lang="fr">Douanes</name>
        <name lang="it">Dogane</name>
        <name lang="en">Customs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
