<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="100936" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2024-05-06</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="yes" id="702" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>701</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Generalsekretariat WBF</name>
      <name lang="fr">Secrétariat général DEFR</name>
      <name lang="it">Segreteria generale DEFR</name>
      <name lang="en">Secretariat-General EAER</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="703" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>701</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Staatssekretariat für Wirtschaft</name>
      <name lang="fr">Secrétariat d'Etat à l'économie</name>
      <name lang="it">Segreteria di Stato dell'economia</name>
      <name lang="en">State Secretariat for Economic Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.seco.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.seco.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.seco.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.seco.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@seco.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@seco.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@seco.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@seco.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="1080" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>701</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Staatssekretariat für Bildung, Forschung und Innovation</name>
      <name lang="fr">Secrétariat d'Etat à la formation, à la recherche et à l'innovation</name>
      <name lang="it">Segreteria di Stato per la formazione, la ricerca e l'innovazione</name>
      <name lang="en">State Secretariat for Education, Research and Innovation</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.sbfi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.sbfi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.sbfi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.sbfi.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@sbfi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@sbfi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@sbfi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@sbfi.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="701">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Wirtschaft, Bildung und Forschung</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'économie, de la formation et de la recherche</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'economia, della formazione e della ricerca</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Economic Affairs, Education and Research</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Bundesrat Guy Parmelin in Griechenland</title>
      <lead>Bundesrat Guy Parmelin besucht vom 8. bis 11. Mai 2024 Griechenland. In Athen sind offizielle Gespräche zu Themen aus Wirtschaft und Wissenschaft geplant. Auf der Insel Euböa wird Bundesrat Parmelin eine archäologische Ausgrabungsstätte der École Suisse d’Archéologie en Grèce (ESAG) besuchen, die vom Bund unterstützt wird.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Die Reise von Bundesrat Guy Parmelin, Vorsteher des Eidgenössischen Departements für Wirtschaft, Bildung und Forschung (WBF), dient der Pflege und Vertiefung der bilateralen Wirtschafts- und Wissenschaftsbeziehungen mit Griechenland sowie der Unterstützung von Firmenanliegen. Hierzu sind Treffen mit den zuständigen Ministern für Wirtschaft, Entwicklung und Investitionen vorgesehen. Ausserdem tauscht er sich mit Vertreterinnen und Vertretern der Schweizer Wirtschafts- und Wissenschaftsgemeinschaft vor Ort aus. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;In der griechischen Hauptstadt stehen Gespräche mit Wirtschafts- und Finanzminister Kostis Hatzidakis sowie mit Entwicklungs- und Investitionsminister Konstantinos Skrekas auf dem Programm. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;In wirtschaftlicher Hinsicht dienen die Gespräche dazu, die Rahmenbedingungen für Schweizer Unternehmen in Griechenland zu optimieren und die Anliegen des Schweizer Privatsektors gegenüber den zuständigen Ministerien zu vertreten. Mit Blick auf Bildung, Forschung und Innovation geht es um die Pflege und Weiterentwicklung der bilateralen Beziehungen in diesen Bereichen. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Auf der Insel Euböa wird Bundesrat Parmelin ausserdem eine archäologische Ausgrabungsstätte der École Suisse d'Archéologie en Grèce (ESAG) besuchen, die vom Bund unterstützt wird.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Solide bilaterale Beziehungen&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Die Schweiz pflegt mit Griechenland gute bilaterale Wirtschafts- und Wissenschaftsbeziehungen. Diese stützen sich auf die bilateralen Abkommen mit der EU. Der Handel zwischen der Schweiz und Griechenland betrug im vergangenen Jahr rund 1 Milliarde Franken. Die Schweiz exportiert vorwiegend pharmazeutische Produkte, Präzisionsinstrumente und Maschinen. In Griechenland sind mehr als 60 Schweizer Firmen präsent. Diese schaffen vor Ort knapp 10'000 Arbeitsplätze. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Seit 1961 erhielten über 180 griechische Forschende ein Bundes-Exzellenz-Stipendium für einen Forschungsaufenthalt in der Schweiz. Zwischen 2018 und 2023 finanzierte der Schweizerische Nationalfonds über 120 Projekte, in denen Forschende aus der Schweiz und Griechenland zusammenarbeiten. Ausserdem kooperieren Forschende aus der Schweiz in knapp 270 Forschungsprojekten mit Forschenden aus Griechenland im Kontext des EU-Rahmenprogrammes für Forschung und Innovation Horizon Europe. &lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Kommunikation GS-WBF info@gs-wbf.admin.ch, Tel. 058 464 50 82</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Visite du conseiller fédéral Guy Parmelin en Grèce</title>
      <lead>Le conseiller fédéral Guy Parmelin sera en Grèce du 8 au 11 mai 2024. Des entretiens officiels sur différentes thématiques en lien avec l’économie et les sciences sont prévus à Athènes. Sur l’île d’Eubée, le conseiller fédéral visitera un site de fouille de l’École Suisse d’Archéologie en Grèce, qui bénéficie du soutien de la Confédération.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;La visite du conseiller fédéral Guy Parmelin, chef du Département fédéral de l'économie, de la formation et de la recherche (DEFR), a pour but d'entretenir et d'approfondir les relations économiques et scientifiques bilatérales avec la Grèce et de prendre le pouls des besoins des entreprises. Des rencontres sont prévues à cet effet avec les chargés des domaines de l'économie, du développement et de l'investissement. Le conseiller fédéral Guy Parmelin aura également l'occasion d'échanger avec des représentants de la communauté économique et scientifique suisse.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Des entretiens avec le ministre de l'Économie et des Finances Kostis Hatzidakis ainsi qu'avec le ministre du Développement et de l'Investissement Kostas Skrekas auront lieu dans la capitale grecque.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Sur le plan économique, les discussions viseront à optimiser les conditions-cadres pour les entreprises suisses en Grèce et à défendre les intérêts du secteur privé suisse auprès des ministères grecs compétents. L'objectif est également d'entretenir et de développer les relations bilatérales dans les domaines de la formation, de la recherche et de l'innovation.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Sur l'île d'Eubée, le conseiller fédéral Guy Parmelin visitera un site de fouille de l'École Suisse d'Archéologie en Grèce (ESAG), qui bénéficie du soutien de la Confédération.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Des relations bilatérales solides&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;La Suisse entretient de bonnes relations économiques et scientifiques avec la Grèce. Celles-ci s'appuient sur les accords bilatéraux qu'elle a conclus avec l'Union européenne (UE). L'année dernière, les échanges commerciaux entre la Suisse et la Grèce se sont élevés à environ 1 milliard de francs. La Suisse exporte principalement des produits pharmaceutiques, des instruments de précision et des machines. Au total, plus de 60 entreprises suisses sont présentes en Grèce, générant près de 10 000 emplois sur place.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Depuis 1961, plus de 180 chercheurs grecs ont reçu une bourse d'excellence de la Confédération pour un séjour de recherche en Suisse. Entre 2018 et 2023, le Fonds national suisse (FNS) a financé plus de 120 projets de collaboration entre chercheurs des deux pays. De plus, près de 270 projets de recherche sont menés conjointement dans le cadre d'Horizon Europe, le programme-cadre de l'UE pour la recherche et l'innovation.&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Communication DEFR info@gs-wbf.admin.ch, 058 462 20 07</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Visita del consigliere federale Guy Parmelin in Grecia</title>
      <lead>Dall’8 all’11 maggio 2024 il consigliere federale Guy Parmelin si recherà in visita in Grecia. Ad Atene sono previsti colloqui ufficiali su varie tematiche riguardanti la scienza e l’economia. Inoltre, sull’isola di Eubea il consigliere federale visiterà gli scavi dell’École Suisse d’Archéologie en Grèce (ESAG), finanziati dalla Confederazione.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Il viaggio del consigliere federale Guy Parmelin, capo del Dipartimento federale dell'economia, della formazione e della ricerca (DEFR), servirà a curare e approfondire le relazioni bilaterali con la Grecia in ambito scientifico ed economico e a sostenere gli interessi delle aziende. Sono infatti previsti incontri con i ministri responsabili dell'economia, dello sviluppo e degli investimenti oltre che con i rappresentanti locali della comunità economica e scientifica svizzera.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Nella capitale Atene il consigliere federale Guy Parmelin sarà a colloquio con il ministro dell'economia e delle finanze Kostis Hatzidakis e con il ministro dello sviluppo e degli investimenti Konstantinos Skrekas.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Sotto il profilo economico i colloqui sono finalizzati a migliorare le condizioni quadro per le imprese svizzere in Grecia e a difendere gli interessi del settore privato elvetico presso i ministeri competenti. Per quanto riguarda invece la formazione, la ricerca e l'innovazione l'obiettivo è mantenere e approfondire le relazioni bilaterali.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Inoltre, sull'isola di Eubea il consigliere federale visiterà gli scavi dell'École Suisse d'Archéologie en Grèce (ESAG), finanziati dalla Confederazione.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Relazioni bilaterali solide&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;In campo economico e scientifico la Svizzera e la Grecia intrattengono buone relazioni, basate sugli accordi bilaterali con l'Unione europea. Lo scorso anno gli scambi commerciali con la Grecia sono stati pari a circa 1 miliardo di franchi. Il nostro Paese esporta principalmente prodotti farmaceutici, macchinari e strumenti di precisione. In Grecia sono presenti oltre 60 aziende svizzere, che impiegano poco meno di 10 000 persone.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Dal 1961 sono stati 180 i ricercatori ellenici ad aver ottenuto una borsa d'eccellenza della Confederazione per un soggiorno di studio in Svizzera. Tra il 2018 e il 2023 il Fondo nazionale svizzero (FNS) ha promosso più di 120 progetti ai quali hanno collaborato ricercatori svizzeri e greci. Inoltre, i ricercatori provenienti dal nostro Paese collaborano con i colleghi greci nell'ambito di quasi 270 progetti di ricerca del programma quadro europeo per la ricerca e l'innovazione «Orizzonte Europa».&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Comunicazione DEFR info@gs-wbf.admin.ch, 058 462 20 07</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Federal Councillor Guy Parmelin in Greece</title>
      <lead>From 8 to 11 May, Federal Councillor Guy Parmelin will pay a visit to Greece. Official talks on economic and scientific topics are planned in Athens. On the island of Euboea, Mr Parmelin will visit an archaeological site of the École Suisse d'Archéologie en Grèce (ESAG), which is supported by the Confederation.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;The visit by Mr Parmelin, Head of the Federal Department of Economic Affairs, Education and Research (EAER), is aimed at maintaining and deepening bilateral economic and scientific relations with Greece and supporting the interests of companies. Meetings are planned with the ministers for economic affairs, development and investments. Mr Parmelin will also exchange views with representatives of the Swiss business and scientific community in Greece. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Talks with Minister of Economy and Finance Kostis Hatzidakis and Development and Investment Minister Konstantinos Skrekas are on the agenda in the Greek capital. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The talks are aimed at optimising the economic framework conditions for Swiss companies in Greece and representing the interests of the Swiss private sector vis-à-vis the relevant ministries. A further aim is to maintain and develop bilateral relations in education, research and innovation. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;On the island of Euboea, Mr Parmelin will visit an archaeological site of the École Suisse d'Archéologie en Grèce (ESAG), which is supported by the Confederation.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Solid bilateral relations&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Switzerland maintains good bilateral economic and scientific relations with Greece that are based on its bilateral agreements with the EU. Trade between Switzerland and Greece was around CHF 1 billion last year. Switzerland mainly exports pharmaceutical products, precision instruments and machinery. More than 60 Swiss companies are operating in Greece today; they employ almost 10,000 people locally. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Since 1961, over 180 Greek researchers have received a Swiss Government Excellence Scholarship to do research in Switzerland. Between 2018 and 2023, the Swiss National Science Foundation funded over 120 projects in which researchers from Switzerland and Greece worked together. In addition, researchers from Switzerland and Greece are collaborating in almost 270 research projects within the scope of the EU framework programme for research and innovation, Horizon Europe. &lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>EAER Information Service info@gs-wbf.admin.ch, 058 462 20 07</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <keywords>
      <keyword id="325.20" org-id="1080">
        <name lang="de">Forschungsförderung</name>
        <name lang="fr">Encouragement de la recherche</name>
        <name lang="it">Promozione della ricerca</name>
        <name lang="en">Research promotion</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="325.4" org-id="1080">
        <name lang="de">Hochschullandschaft</name>
        <name lang="fr">Paysage des hautes écoles</name>
        <name lang="it">Panorama universitario</name>
        <name lang="en">University landscape</name>
      </keyword>
    </keywords>
    <topics>
      <topic id="47">
        <name lang="de">Wirtschaft</name>
        <name lang="fr">Économie</name>
        <name lang="it">Economia</name>
        <name lang="en">Economic Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
