<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="101981" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2024-08-01</pubdate>
    <blocking-period>2024-08-01</blocking-period>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="1063" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>701</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Paul Scherrer Institut</name>
      <name lang="fr">Institut Paul Scherrer</name>
      <name lang="it">Istituto Paul Scherrer</name>
      <name lang="en">Paul Scherrer Institut</name>
      <www lang="de"/>
      <www lang="fr"/>
      <www lang="it"/>
      <www lang="en"/>
      <email lang="de">info@psi.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@psi.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@psi.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@psi.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="701">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Wirtschaft, Bildung und Forschung</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'économie, de la formation et de la recherche</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'economia, della formazione e della ricerca</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Economic Affairs, Education and Research</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Villigen</city>
      <title>Einmalig präzise: Neuer Wert für die Halbwertszeit von Samarium-146</title>
      <lead>Forscherinnen und Forscher des Paul Scherrer Instituts PSI und der Australian National University haben die Halbwertszeit von Samarium-146 sehr präzise bestimmt. Das Ergebnis passt perfekt zu den Daten, die Astrophysikerinnen und Astrophysiker, Geochemikerinnen und Geochemiker von extraterrestrischen Proben erhalten haben. Die Studie erscheint heute im Fachblatt Nature Scientific Reports.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Samarium-146 hat eine Halbwertszeit von 103 Millionen Jahren. Oder von 68 Millionen Jahren. Oder etwa doch von 98 Millionen Jahren? So genau wusste man das bisher nicht, denn seit den ersten Messungen in den 1950ern kamen Forscherinnen und Forscher immer wieder zu widersprüchlichen Ergebnissen. In den Wissenschaften Astrophysik und Geochemie ist das ein grosses Problem: Forscherinnen und Forscher brauchen einen möglichst genauen Wert der Halbwertszeit von Samarium-146, um die Bildung von Asteroiden und Planeten zu erklären oder das Alter von Gesteinen zu datieren. Für sie hat die Ungewissheit nun ein Ende. Samarium-146 hat eine Halbwertszeit von 92 Millionen Jahren – was die Altersbestimmungen von Meteoriten oder Mondproben sehr gut bestätigt. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Das bisher präziseste Ergebnis&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Zu diesem Ergebnis kommt ein Team von Forscherinnen und Forschern am Paul Scherrer Institut PSI in Villigen und an der Australian National University in Canberra. «Unser Ergebnis ist das bisher genaueste», sagt Dorothea Schumann, die das Team leitete. Dies bestätigen auch die Gutachter, die die Arbeit beurteilt haben: «Dies ist eine hervorragende Arbeit. Sie ist wie das 'Ei des Kolumbus'», urteilten sie. Besonders hoben sie hervor, dass in der Publikation alle Schritte nachvollziehbar beschrieben wurden und das Ergebnis somit lückenlos erklärt wird. «Ich bin beeindruckt von der ausführlichen Dokumentation und Quantifizierung möglicher Artefakte.», heisst es unter anderem in dem Gutachten. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Das hat gute Gründe. 2012 hatte ein Team aus Japan, Israel und den USA einen überraschend niedrigen Wert für die Halbwertszeit von Samarium-146 veröffentlicht: 68 Millionen Jahre mit einer Unsicherheit von 7 Millionen Jahren. Das hat unter Geowissenschaftlerinnen und Geowissenschaftlern weltweit für Bestürzung gesorgt, da dieser Wert weder zu den älteren Experimenten passte noch zu den Messdaten von Meteoriten, die für die Datierung der Entstehung unseres Sonnensystems verwendet werden. Weil niemand eine endgültige Entscheidung darüber treffen konnte, welches Ergebnis das richtigere ist, lautete die Empfehlung eines Expertenteams, einfach diesen neuen und den zuvor bekannten Wert parallel zu verwenden – ein für Forscherinnen und Forscher unhaltbarer Zustand. Für Mondgesteine ergeben sich so zum Beispiel Unterschiede von 90 Millionen Jahren, was circa 35 Prozent ihres Entstehungsalters entspricht. 2023 kam dann die Erlösung: Die Autoren konnten eine Ungenauigkeit in einem Schritt der Probenherstellung identifizieren und zogen ihre Arbeit deshalb zurück.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Vertagtes Problem&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Doch damit war das Problem nur vertagt. In den Geowissenschaften benötigte man nach wie vor einen genaueren Wert für die Halbwertszeit von Samarium-146 und weiterer radioaktiver Isotope, die eine wichtige Rolle für die Datierung der Planetenentstehung spielen. All diesen Isotopen gemeinsam ist, dass sie lange Halbwertszeiten von vielen Millionen Jahren haben. So lange dauert es, bis die Hälfte des radioaktiven Stoffs zerfallen ist. Bei Samarium-146 handelt es sich um einen reinen Alpha-Strahler, das Atom sendet einen Helium-Kern aus und zerfällt in Neodym-142. Weil man selbstverständlich nicht Millionen Jahre warten kann, bis eine nennenswerte Menge eines Stoffs zerfallen ist, braucht es andere Methoden, die schneller zum Ergebnis kommen. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Das ist in der Theorie ganz einfach. Um die Halbwertszeit eines beliebigen radioaktiven Isotops zu bestimmen, muss man «nur» die Zahl der Atome in der Probe bestimmen sowie die Aktivität, also die Zerfallsrate. Der Quotient ergibt dann die Halbwertszeit bis auf einen konstanten Faktor, den natürlichen Logarithmus von 2. «Nur» ist hier allerdings ein viel zu optimistisches Wörtchen. Denn die exakte Bestimmung der beiden Werte ist kompliziert und gepflastert mit experimentellen Stolpersteinen. Das Team hat aber für alle diese Herausforderungen Lösungen gefunden. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Das Experiment gliedert sich in drei Teile. Erstens die Gewinnung ausreichender Mengen des auf der Erde nicht vorkommenden Isotops Samarium-146. Dafür erwiesen sich Tantal-Proben, die an der Schweizer Spallations-Neutronenquelle SINQ des PSI bestrahlt wurden, als perfektes Ausgangsmaterial. Mithilfe einer Reihe von hoch selektiven chemischen Trennverfahren erhielt man die äusserst reine Lösung einer Samarium-Verbindung zur Herstellung einer sehr dünnen Probe für die Aktivitätsmessung. Dazu wurde ein Teil der Lösung auf einer nur 75 Mikrometer dünnen Kohlenstofffolie abgeschieden.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Zweitens die Aktivitätsmessung: Die so präparierte Samarium-Probe wurde dann in einen wohl definierten Abstand zu einem Detektor für Alpha-Strahlung gebracht. Die Samarium-Abscheidung ist nur Bruchteile eines Mikrometers dünn, sodass sie die Alphateilchen nicht stoppt. Durch die Bestimmung der Energie lässt sich ausserdem erkennen, ob ein Alphateilchen tatsächlich vom Zerfall des Samarium-146 stammt. Kalibriert wurde die Apparatur mit einer sehr genau bestimmten Probe von Americium-241, die von der deutschen Physikalisch-Technischen Bundesanstalt in Braunschweig hergestellt wurde. Wegen der winzigen Menge an Samarium-146 – sogar ein einzelnes Körnchen Puderzucker wiegt 10-mal mehr – musste das Team drei Monate lang messen, um die Aktivität genau genug zu bestimmen, es waren knapp 54 Zerfälle pro Stunde. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Drittens die Bestimmung der Zahl der Atome: Hier haben die Forscherinnen und Forscher die Samarium-Lösung mit verscheiden Massenspektrometern sowohl am PSI als auch an der Australian National University auf seine Zusammensetzung untersucht, wobei die Anzahl der Atome von Samarium-146 und auch aller anderen in der Probe vorhandenen Samarium-Isotope gezählt wurde. Durch die Zugabe von natürlichem Samarium, das kein Samarium-146 enthält, konnte auch der genaue Gehalt aller Samarium-Isotope inklusive Samarium-146 bestimmt werden. Weil in der Mischung noch ein zusätzliches künstliches Samarium-Isotop enthalten ist, das Gamma-Strahlung aussendet, konnten die Forscherinnen und Forscher feststellen, wie viele Samarium-146-Atome auf der dünnen Folie abgeschieden wurden: genau 6,28 mal 1013 Atome oder nur 0,000018 Milligramm Samariumoxid (146Sm2O3). Ausserdem konnte das Team die hohe Reinheit der Probe nicht nur behaupten, sondern tatsächlich auch durch zusätzliche Messungen belegen. «Das ist die Spezialität unseres Labors am PSI und das haben auch die Gutachter an unserer Publikation besonders hervorgehoben», sagt Rugard Dressler vom Labor für Radiochemie. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Nachdem die experimentellen Herausforderungen gemeistert waren, war der Rest ein Fall für den Taschenrechner. Das Ergebnis für die Halbwertszeit von Samarium-146 ist 92,0 ±2,6 Millionen Jahre. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Nur am PSI möglich&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Diese Messung war ausschliesslich am PSI dank der ERAWAST-Initiative (Exotic Radionuclides from Accelerator Waste for Science and Technology) möglich, einem langjährigen Projekt unter Förderung des Schweizerischen Nationalfonds, das radioaktiven Abfall aus den Beschleunigern am PSI zu Forschungszwecken weiterverwendet. Am Protonenbeschleuniger und an der Schweizer Spallations-Neutronenquelle SINQ des PSI entstehen viele radioaktive Isotope in unterschiedlichen Kernreaktionen. Die meisten stören nur durch ihren radioaktiven Zerfall und werden deshalb als radioaktiver Abfall klassifiziert, andere sind jedoch äusserst selten und in der Grundlagenforschung sehr begehrt. Die Forscherinnen und Forscher der Arbeitsgruppe Isotope und Target-Chemie im Labor für Radiochemie am PSI um Dorothea Schumann, Projektleiterin und Initiatorin der ERAWAST-Initiative und Mitautorin des Samarium-Papers, haben in den letzten 15 Jahren in diesem Projekt Techniken entwickelt, um viele der interessanten Isotope aus den Abfällen chemisch abzutrennen und hochreine Proben herzustellen. «Nur so war es möglich, eine ausreichende Menge Samarium-146 für die genaue Bestimmung der Halbwertszeiten zu gewinnen – eine Möglichkeit, die es an keinem anderen Ort der Welt gibt», sagt Zeynep Talip, die die Arbeitsgruppe nun leitet und ebenfalls Mitautorin des Samarium-Papers ist. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Für Rugard Dressler ist die Arbeit zu Samarium-146 erst einmal abgeschlossen, für andere geht sie nun erst los. Der Physiker vom Labor für Radiochemie des PSI betont: «Den einen richtigen Wert für die Halbwertszeit von Samarium-146 gibt es nicht. Unser Ergebnis ist zwar sehr genau, es muss aber nun von anderen Gruppen bestätigt und weiter verbessert werden.»&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Text: Bernd Müller &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Über das PSI&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Das Paul Scherrer Institut PSI entwickelt, baut und betreibt grosse und komplexe Forschungsanlagen und stellt sie der nationalen und internationalen Forschungsgemeinde zur Verfügung. Eigene Forschungsschwerpunkte sind Zukunftstechnologien, Energie und Klima, Health Innovation und Grundlagen der Natur. Die Ausbildung von jungen Menschen ist ein zentrales Anliegen des PSI. Deshalb sind etwa ein Viertel unserer Mitarbeitenden Postdoktorierende, Doktorierende oder Lernende. Insgesamt beschäftigt das PSI 2300 Mitarbeitende, das damit das grösste Forschungsinstitut der Schweiz ist. Das Jahresbudget beträgt rund CHF 460 Mio. Das PSI ist Teil des ETH-Bereichs, dem auch die ETH Zürich und die ETH Lausanne angehören sowie die Forschungsinstitute Eawag, Empa und WSL. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Originalveröffentlichung&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;The 146Sm half-life re-measured: consolidating the chronometer for events in the early Solar System&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/b&gt;Chiera et al.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;i&gt;Nature Scientific Reports&lt;/i&gt;, 01.08.2024&lt;br /&gt;DOI: 10.1038/s41598-024-64104-6&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Dr. Rugard Dressler Labor für Radiochemie PSI Center for Nuclear Engineering and Science Paul Scherrer Institut PSI +41 56 310 24 69 rugard.dressler@psi.ch</contact>
      <link id="277414">
        <title>Bilder und weitere Informationen</title>
        <uri>https://i.psi.ch/4V1</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Villigen</city>
      <title>Précision unique: nouvelle valeur pour la demi-vie du samarium-146</title>
      <lead>Des scientifiques de l’Institut Paul Scherrer PSI et de l’Université nationale australienne ont déterminé la demi-vie du samarium 146 avec une très grande précision. Ce résultat correspond parfaitement aux données obtenues par des astrophysiciens et des géochimistes à partir d’échantillons extraterrestres. L’étude paraît aujourd’hui dans la revue spécialisée Nature Scientific Report. </lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Le samarium 146 a une demi-vie de 103 millions d’années. Ou plutôt de 68 millions d’années. Ou ne serait-ce pas plutôt 98 millions d’années? Comme depuis les premières mesures dans les années 1950, les scientifiques parvenaient sans cesse à des résultats contradictoires. Pour les scientifique en astrophysique et en géochimie, cela représente un gros problème: ils ont besoin d’une valeur aussi précise que possible de la demi-vie du samarium 146 pour expliquer la formation des astéroïdes et des planètes, ou encore pour dater les roches. Leur interrogation est aujourd’hui résolue. Le samarium 146 a une demi-vie de 92 millions d’années, ce qui correspond parfaitement aux datations de météorites et d’échantillons lunaires. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Le résultat le plus précis à ce jour&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Tel est le résultat auquel est parvenue une équipe de scientifiques à l’Institut Paul Scherrer PSI à Villigen et à l’Université nationale australienne à Canberra. «Notre résultat est le plus précis à ce jour», souligne Dorothea Schumann, qui a dirigé cette équipe. Les pairs qui ont évalué ce travail confirment: «Il s’agit d’un travail remarquable, d’une sorte d’‘œuf de Colomb’», ont-ils relevé. Ces experts ont tout particulièrement soulignée le fait que la publication décrit l’ensemble des étapes de manière compréhensible et, ce faisant, explique l’intégralité du résultat. «Je suis impressionné par la documentation détaillée et la quantification des artefacts possibles», mentionne l’un d’eux dans ce rapport d’experts.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Cette remarque a de bonnes raisons d’être. En 2012, une équipe du Japon, d’Israël et des Etats-Unis avait publié une valeur étonnamment basse pour la demi-vie du samarium 146: 68 millions d’années, avec une incertitude de 7 millions d’années. Cela avait suscité la consternation chez les scientifiques en géosciences du monde entier, car cette valeur ne correspondait ni aux expériences plus anciennes ni aux données de mesure des météorites utilisées pour dater la formation de notre système solaire. Comme personne ne pouvait prendre de décision définitive quant au résultat correct, une équipe d’experts avait recommandé de simplement utiliser en parallèle cette nouvelle valeur et celle connue précédemment: une situation intenable pour les scientifiques. Pour les roches lunaires, on obtient par exemple des différences de 90 millions d’années, ce qui correspond à environ 35% de leur âge de formation. La délivrance est venue en 2023: les auteurs ont réussi à identifier une inexactitude lors d’une étape de la fabrication des échantillons et ont donc retiré leur travail. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Problème juste repoussé &lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mais cela ne faisait que repousser le problème. En géosciences, on avait toujours besoin d’une valeur plus précise pour la demi-vie du samarium 146 et d’autres isotopes radioactifs qui jouent un rôle important dans la datation des planètes. Tous ces isotopes ont en commun le fait d’avoir des demi-vies de plusieurs dizaines de millions d’années. C’est le temps qu’il faut pour que la moitié de la substance radioactive se désintègre. Dans le cas du samarium 146, il s’agit d’un émetteur alpha pur: l’atome émet un noyau d’hélium-4 et se désintègre en néodyme 142. Comme l’on ne peut évidemment pas attendre des millions d’années pour qu’une quantité significative d'une substance se désintègre, il faut d’autres méthodes qui permettent d’obtenir un résultat plus rapidement. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;En théorie, c’est très simple. Pour déterminer la demi-vie de n’importe quel isotope radioactif, il suffit «juste» de déterminer le nombre d’atomes dans l’échantillon et leur activité, autrement dit leur taux de désintégration. Le quotient donne alors la demi-vie à un facteur constant près, le logarithme naturel de 2. Mais «juste» est ici un adverbe beaucoup trop optimiste. Car la détermination exacte des deux valeurs est compliquée et pavée d’embûches expérimentales. Or l’équipe a trouvé des solutions à tous ces défis. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;L’expérience s’est articulée en trois parties. Première étape: l’obtention de quantités suffisantes de samarium 146, un isotope qui n’existe pas sur Terre. Des échantillons de tantale irradiés à la source de neutrons de spallation suisse SINQ du PSI se sont avérés être le matériau de départ parfait. Une série de procédés de séparation chimique hautement sélectifs a permis d’obtenir la solution extrêmement pure d’un composé de samarium pour la fabrication d’un échantillon très fin pour mesurer l’activité. Une partie de la solution a été déposée sur une feuille de carbone de seulement 75 micromètres d’épaisseur. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Deuxième étape: la mesure de l’activité. L’échantillon de samarium ainsi préparé a été placé à une distance bien définie d’un détecteur de rayonnement alpha. L’épaisseur du dépôt de samarium ne dépassait pas une fraction de micromètre: il n’arrêtait donc pas les particules alpha. La détermination de l’énergie a permis par ailleurs de savoir si une particule alpha provenait bel et bien de la désintégration du samarium 146. L’appareil a été calibré avec un échantillon très précis d’américium 241, produit par la Physikalisch-Technische Bundesanstalt à Brunswick, en Allemagne. En raison de la minuscule quantité de samarium – un seul grain de sucre glace pèse dix fois plus –, l’équipe a dû effectuer des mesures pendant trois mois pour déterminer l’activité avec suffisamment de précision: celle-ci était de près de 54 désintégrations par heure. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Troisième étape: la détermination du nombre d’atomes. Là, les scientifiques du PSI et de l’Université nationale australienne ont analysé la composition d’une partie du matériau avec différents spectromètres de masse en comptant le nombre d’atomes de samarium 146 et de tous les autres isotopes du samarium présents dans l’échantillon. L’ajout de samarium naturel, qui ne contient pas de samarium 146, a également permis de déterminer la teneur exacte de tous les isotopes du samarium, y compris le samarium 146. Comme le mélange contenait encore un isotope artificiel supplémentaire de samarium qui émettait des rayons gamma, les scientifiques ont pu déterminer combien d’atomes de samarium 146 avaient été déposés sur la feuille mince. Le résultat: exactement 6,28 fois 1013 atomes ou seulement 0,000018 milligrammes d’oxyde de samarium (146Sm2O3). Par ailleurs, l’équipe ne pouvait pas simplement prétendre au haut degré de pureté de l’échantillon, elle devait également en apporter la preuve par le biais de mesures supplémentaires. «C’est la spécialité de notre laboratoire au PSI et c’est un point que les experts chargés de revoir notre article ont particulièrement relevé dans notre publication», relève Rugard Dressler du Laboratoire de radiochimie. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Une fois les défis expérimentaux relevés, le reste a été résolu à la calculatrice. Résultat pour la demi-vie du samarium 146: 92,0 ±2,6 millions d’années. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Possible uniquement au PSI &lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;La mesure était réalisable uniquement au PSI grâce à l’initiative ERAWAST (Exotic Radionuclides from Accelerator Waste for Science and Technology), un projet de longue durée soutenu par le Fonds national suisse, qui réutilise les déchets radioactifs issus des accélérateurs du PSI à des fins de recherche. L’accélérateur de protons et la source de neutrons de spallation suisse SINQ du PSI génèrent nombre d’isotopes radioactifs dans différentes réactions nucléaires. La plupart d’entre eux ne font que gêner par leur désintégration radioactive et sont donc classifiés comme déchets radioactifs. D’autres, en revanche, sont extrêmement rares et très prisés en recherche fondamentale. Au cours des 15 dernières années, les scientifiques du groupe de travail Isotopes et chimie cible au Laboratoire de radiochimie, emmenés par Dorothea Schumann, cheffe de projet, initiatrice de l’initiative ERAWAST et coauteure de l’article sur le samarium, ont développé des techniques dans le cadre de ce projet pour séparer chimiquement nombre d’isotopes intéressants des déchets et produire des échantillons extrêmement purs. «C’était le seul moyen d’obtenir une quantité suffisante de samarium 146 pour déterminer avec précision les demi-vies, explique Zeynep Talip, qui dirige désormais le groupe de travail et est également coauteure de la publication sur le samarium. Cette possibilité n’existe nulle part ailleurs dans le monde.» &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Pour Rugard Dressler, le travail sur le samarium 146 est terminé pour l’instant. Pour d’autres scientifiques, en revanche, les choses ne font que commencer. «Il n’existe pas de valeur correcte pour la demi-vie du samarium-146, souligne ce physicien du Laboratoire de radiochimie. Notre résultat est certes très précis, mais il faudra maintenant que d’autres groupes le confirment et l’améliorent encore.» &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Texte: Bernd Müller &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;À propos du PSI&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;L'Institut Paul Scherrer PSI développe, construit et exploite des grandes installations de recherche complexes et les met à la disposition de la communauté scientifique nationale et internationale. Les domaines de recherche de l'institut sont centrés sur des technologies d'avenir, énergie et climat, innovation santé ainsi que fondements de la nature. La formation des générations futures est un souci central du PSI. Pour cette raison, environ un quart de nos collaborateurs sont des postdocs, des doctorants ou des apprentis. Au total, le PSI emploie 2300 personnes, étant ainsi le plus grand institut de recherche de Suisse. Le budget annuel est d'environ CHF 460 millions. Le PSI fait partie du domaine des EPF, les autres membres étant l'ETH Zurich, l'EPF Lausanne, l'Eawag (Institut de Recherche de l'Eau), l'Empa (Laboratoire fédéral d'essai des matériaux et de recherche) et le WSL (Institut fédéral de recherches sur la forêt, la neige et le paysage). &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Publication originale &lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;The 146Sm half-life re-measured: consolidating the chronometer for events in the early Solar System&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/b&gt;Chiera et al.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;i&gt;Nature Scientific Reports&lt;/i&gt;, 01.08.2024&lt;br /&gt;DOI: 10.1038/s41598-024-64104-6&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Dr Rugard Dressler Laboratoire de radiochimie PSI Center for Nuclear Engineering and Science Institut Paul Scherrer PSI +41 56 310 24 69 rugard.dressler@psi.ch</contact>
      <link id="277415">
        <title>Images et informations supplémentaires</title>
        <uri>https://i.psi.ch/4V3</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Villigen</city>
      <title>Uniquely precise: New value for the half-life of samarium-146</title>
      <lead>Researchers at the Paul Scherrer Institute PSI and the Australian National University have re-determined the half-life of samarium-146 with great precision. The result fits perfectly with the data astrophysicists and geochemists have obtained from extraterrestrial samples. The study appears today in the journal Nature Scientific Reports.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Samarium-146 has a half-life of 103 million years. Or 68 million years. Or maybe 98 million years? Until now, it wasn’t known precisely, because researchers have repeatedly come up with contradictory results since the first measurements in the 1950s. For astrophysicists and geochemists, this is a major problem: They need to know the half-life of samarium-146 as accurately as possible to explain the formation of asteroids and planets and for dating rocks. Now their uncertainty is over. Samarium-146 has a half-life of 92 million years – which confirms very well with the age assessments of meteorites and moon rocks. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;The most precise result to date&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;This result was achieved by a team of researchers from the Paul Scherrer Institute PSI in Villigen, Switzerland, and the Australian National University in Canberra. “Our result is the most precise to date,” says Dorothea Schumann, who led the team. A fact also acknowledged by the peer reviewers who assessed the work: “This is an outstanding paper. It’s like Columbus’s egg,” they wrote. They particularly highlighted that, in this publication, all steps were described in a comprehensible manner and thus the result is fully traceable. “I am impressed by the detailed documentation and quantification of possible artifacts,” comments the expert report. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;There are good reasons for this. In 2012, a team from Japan, Israel, and the USA published a surprisingly low value for the half-life of samarium-146: 68 million years, with an uncertainty of seven million years. That caused a worldwide consternation among geoscientists, as this value neither matched the older experiments nor the measurement data from meteorites used to date the formation of our solar system. Because no one could definitively conclude which of the outcomes was the more correct result, a team of experts recommended using this new value and the previously established value in parallel – an untenable situation for researchers. For moon rocks, for example, this would result in differences of 90 million years, which corresponds to around 35 percent of their formation age. Then relief came in 2023: The authors of the 2012 publication identified an inconsistency in one of the steps during the sample preparation and consequently withdraw their paper.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;A problem postponed&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;With that, though, the problem was merely postponed. Geoscientists still required a more accurate value for the half-life of samarium-146 and some other radionuclides that play important roles in dating the formation of planets. What all these Radioisotopes have in common are half-lives of many millions of years. That’s how long it takes for half of the radioactive material to decay. Samarium-146 is a pure alpha emitter; the atom emits a helium nucleus and decays into neodymium-142. Because you obviously can’t wait millions of years for a significant amount of a material to decay, other methods are needed that can produce results more quickly. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;In theory, that is quite simple. To determine the half-life of any radioactive isotope, you &lt;i&gt;only&lt;/i&gt; need to determine the number of atoms in the sample as well as the activity, that is, the rate of decay. The quotient then gives the half-life up to a constant factor, the natural logarithm of 2. «Only» is a very optimistic little word here, however, because the path to determining the two values exactly is complicated and paved with experimental pitfalls. But the team found solutions for all of these challenges.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The experiment was divided into three parts. First came the extraction of sufficient quantities of the isotope samarium-146, which does not occur naturally on earth. For this purpose, tantalum samples irradiated at PSI's Swiss spallation neutron source SINQ turned out to be the most suitable material. After a series of highly selective chemical separations, an extremely pure solution of a samarium compound was obtained to produce a very thin sample for the activity measurement. Part of the solution was deposited on a carbon film only 75 micrometres thick.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Second, the activity measurement: The carefully prepared samarium sample was placed at a well-defined distance from an alpha radiation detector. The samarium film was only a fraction of a micrometer, so it would not stop the alpha particles. By determining the energy, the researchers could also discern whether or not an alpha particle actually came from the decay of samarium-146. The apparatus had been calibrated with a very precisely determined sample of americium-241 produced by the German Physikalisch-Technische Bundesanstalt PTB in Braunschweig. Because of the tiny amount of samarium-146 – even a grain of icing sugar weight 10 times more – the team had to carry out measurements for three months to determine the activity with sufficient precision; the rate was almost 54 decays per hour.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Third, determination of the number of atoms: Here the samarium solution was examined for its composition using various mass spectrometers at PSI and at the Australian National University by counting the number of atoms of samarium-146 as well as all other samarium isotopes present in the sample. After adding additional quantities of natural samarium, which contains no samarium-146, the total amount of all samarium isotopes and also of samarium-146 could be determined accurately. Because the mixture contained also an additional artificial isotope of samarium that emits gamma radiation, the researchers were able, to deduce how many samarium-146 atoms were deposited on the thin foil: exactly 6.28 times 1013 atoms or only 0,000018 milligram samariumoxide (146Sm2O3). In addition, the team was able not only to claim the high purity of the sample, but also to actually prove it through additional measurements. “This is the specialty of our lab at PSI, and the reviewers of our publication have particularly underlined it,” says Rugard Dressler from the Laboratory for Radiochemistry. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Once all these experimental challenges had been overcome, the rest was a case for the pocket calculator. The result for the half-life of samarium-146 is 92.0 ±2.6 million years.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Only possible at PSI&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;These measurements were made entirely and exclusively feasible thanks to the ERAWAST initiative (Exotic Radionuclides from Accelerator Waste for Science and Technology), a long-term project funded by the Swiss National Science Foundation that reuses radioactive accelerator waste from PSI for research purposes. At PSI’s proton accelerator and the Swiss spallation neutron source SINQ, many radioactive isotopes are produced in various nuclear reactions. Most of these only cause serious issues through their radioactive decay and are therefore categorized as radioactive waste, but some of them are extremely rare and highly desired in fundamental research. The researchers of the Isotope and Target Chemistry group at the Laboratory for Radiochemistry at PSI, managed by Dorothea Schumann – project leader, initiator of the ERAWAST initiative and also co-author of the samarium paper – have developed techniques to chemically separate many isotopes of interest from the waste and to produce samples of high purity over the last 15 years. “Only in this way it was possible to obtain a sufficient amount of samarium-146 for the precise determination of its half-live – a possibility that is not available anywhere else around the world,” says Zeynep Talip, who now heads the research group and is likewise a co-author of the samarium paper. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;For Rugard Dressler, the work on samarium-146 is complete for now. For others, it’s just now getting started. The physicist from the Laboratory for Radiochemistry at PSI emphasises: “There is no finally correct value for the half-life of samarium-146. Our result is very precise indeed, but now it needs to be confirmed and if possible improved by other groups.”&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Text: Bernd Müller&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;About PSI&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;The Paul Scherrer Institute PSI develops, builds and operates large, complex research facilities and makes them available to the national and international research community. The institute's own key research priorities are in the fields of future technologies, energy and climate, health innovation and fundamentals of nature. PSI is committed to the training of future generations. Therefore about one quarter of our staff are post-docs, post-graduates or apprentices. Altogether PSI employs 2300 people, thus being the largest research institute in Switzerland. The annual budget amounts to approximately CHF 460 million. PSI is part of the ETH Domain, with the other members being the two Swiss Federal Institutes of Technology, ETH Zurich and EPFL Lausanne, as well as Eawag (Swiss Federal Institute of Aquatic Science and Technology), Empa (Swiss Federal Laboratories for Materials Science and Technology) and WSL (Swiss Federal Institute for Forest, Snow and Landscape Research).&lt;i&gt; &lt;/i&gt; &lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Original publication&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;The 146Sm half-life re-measured: consolidating the chronometer for events in the early Solar System&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/b&gt;Chiera et al.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;i&gt;Nature Scientific Reports&lt;/i&gt;, 01.08.2024&lt;br /&gt;DOI: 10.1038/s41598-024-64104-6&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Dr. Rugard Dressler Laboratory for Radiochemistry PSI Centre for Nuclear Engineering and Science Paul Scherrer Institute PSI +41 56 310 24 69 rugard.dressler@psi.ch</contact>
      <link id="277416">
        <title>Images and additional information</title>
        <uri>https://i.psi.ch/4V4</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="8">
        <name lang="de">Bildung und Forschung</name>
        <name lang="fr">Formation et recherche</name>
        <name lang="it">Formazione e ricerca</name>
        <name lang="en">Education and Research</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="19">
        <name lang="de">Medien</name>
        <name lang="fr">Médias</name>
        <name lang="it">Media</name>
        <name lang="en">Media</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
