<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="101989" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2024-08-02</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="yes" id="502" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>501</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Generalsekretariat VBS</name>
      <name lang="fr">Secrétariat général du DDPS</name>
      <name lang="it">Segreteria generale del DDPS</name>
      <name lang="en">General Secretariat DDPS</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.vbs.admin.ch/</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.vbs.admin.ch/</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.vbs.admin.ch/</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.vbs.admin.ch/</www>
      <email lang="de">postmaster.vbs@gs-vbs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">postmaster.vbs@gs-vbs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">postmaster.vbs@gs-vbs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">postmaster.vbs@gs-vbs.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="501">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Verteidigung, Bevölkerungsschutz und Sport</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de la défense, de la protection de la population et des sports</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale della difesa, della protezione della popolazione e dello sport</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Defence, Civil Protection and Sports</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.vbs.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.vbs.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.vbs.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.vbs.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@gs-vbs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@gs-vbs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@gs-vbs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@gs-vbs.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Die Schweiz und die Mongolei würdigen Erfolge und Chancen der Beziehungen</title>
      <lead>Bundespräsidentin Viola Amherd und der mongolische Präsident Ukhnaagiin Khurelsukh haben am Freitag, 2. August 2024, in Ulaanbaatar anlässlich des 60-jährigen Bestehens der bilateralen Beziehungen über die erreichten Erfolge und die neuen Perspektiven im Austausch zwischen der Schweiz und der Mongolei gesprochen. Es handelt sich um den ersten Schweizer Präsidialbesuch in dem Land. Die beiden Seiten unterzeichneten eine gemeinsame Erklärung zur künftigen Zusammenarbeit sowie eine Absichtserklärung mit dem Ziel, die demokratischen Institutionen in der Mongolei zu stärken. </lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Mit der gemeinsamen Erklärung wird ein Meilenstein in den bilateralen Beziehungen gewürdigt. Die Schweiz und die Mongolei unterstreichen damit ihre Verbundenheit und ihren Einsatz für Frieden und Stabilität. Die Erklärung führt zudem Themenfelder auf, die sich für eine vertiefte Zusammenarbeit in Zukunft anbieten. Dazu zählen neben dem Austausch über Demokratie und Rechtsstaatlichkeit etwa das Engagement im Rahmen der UNO und die nachhaltige Wirtschaftsentwicklung. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Das Engagement der Direktion für Entwicklung und Zusammenarbeit (DEZA) in der Mongolei – unter anderem in den Bereichen der guten Regierungsführung, Gesundheit, Umwelt oder Einkommenssicherung – wird nach 20 Jahren in dieser Form beendet. Einen Teil der Aktivitäten wird die Schweiz von ihrer Botschaft in Peking aus weiterführen. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Das Gespräch am Freitag war neben bilateralen Themen insbesondere auch dem Engagement beider Länder für die multilaterale Ordnung gewidmet. Die Schweiz und die Mongolei vertreten hier bei vielen Themen ähnliche Positionen; beispielsweise engagieren sie sich für die weltweite Abschaffung der Todesstrafe. Zur Sprache kam am Freitag zudem die Sicherheitslage in Ostasien und in Europa. Mit Blick auf die Suche nach einem gerechten und dauerhaften Frieden in der Ukraine erläuterte die Bundespräsidentin das Engagement der Schweiz nach der hochrangigen Konferenz zum Frieden in der Ukraine Mitte Juni auf dem Bürgenstock.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Auf dem Programm der Bundespräsidentin in der Mongolei standen zudem Treffen mit Premierminister Luvsannamsrain Oyun-Erdene und mit Parlamentspräsident Dashzegviin Amarbayasgalan sowie der Besuch einer Fotoausstellung zum Jubiläum der bilateralen Beziehungen und eines DEZA-Projekts, das der verantwortungsvollen Produktion von Kaschmir- und Yakwolle gewidmet ist. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Weiterreise nach Japan&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Von der Mongolei aus reist die Bundespräsidentin nach Japan, wo an das bereits 160-jährige Bestehen der bilateralen Beziehungen erinnert werden kann. Zum Auftakt des Aufenthalts ist am Montag in Shinagawa, einem Bezirk der Präfektur Tokio, der eine Städtepartnerschaft mit Genf pflegt, ein Austausch mit Behördenvertretern vorgesehen. Die Gespräche der Bundespräsidentin mit Premierminister Fumio Kishida, Aussenministerin Yoko Kamikawa und Verteidigungsminister Minoru Kihara sind am Mittwoch angesetzt. Ausgehend von einer Würdigung des Jubiläums werden die Weiterentwicklung der bilateralen Beziehungen, die Perspektiven für den ostasiatischen Raum sowie die Sicherheitslage in Europa zur Sprache kommen. Ein Empfang durch Kaiser Naruhito ist am Donnerstag, 8. August, geplant.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>VBS Kommunikation Bundeshaus Ost CH - 3003 Bern</contact>
      <link id="277417">
        <title>Bilaterale Beziehungen Schweiz–Mongolei (admin.ch)</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home/vertretungen-und-reisehinweise/mongolei/bilatereale-beziehungenschweizmongolei.html#:~:text=Die%20Schweiz%20und%20die%20Mongolei,zwei%20Jahre%20zu%20politischen%20Konsultationen.</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>La Suisse et la Mongolie se félicitent des succès obtenus et de leur coopération future</title>
      <lead>À l’occasion du 60e anniversaire des relations bilatérales entre la Suisse et la Mongolie, la présidente de la Confédération Viola Amherd et le président mongol Ukhnaagiin Khurelsukh se sont rencontrés le vendredi 2 août 2024 à Oulan Bator. Ils se sont entretenus des succès obtenus grâce aux relations entre les deux pays et des nouvelles perspectives d’échange entre eux. Il s’agit de la première visite présidentielle suisse dans ce pays. Les deux parties ont signé une déclaration commune sur leur coopération future et une déclaration d’intention visant à renforcer les institutions démocratiques en Mongolie. </lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;La déclaration commune marque une étape importante des relations bilatérales. La Suisse et la Mongolie réaffirment ainsi leurs liens et leur engagement en faveur de la paix et de la stabilité. La déclaration énumère des domaines thématiques susceptibles de donner lieu à une coopération approfondie à l’avenir. Parmi ces thèmes figurent, en plus de l’échange portant sur la démocratie et l’état de droit, l’engagement dans le cadre de l’ONU et le développement économique durable. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;La Direction du développement et de la coopération (DDC) a soutenu des projets en Mongolie pendant 20 ans, notamment dans les domaines de la bonne gouvernance, de la santé, de l’environnement et du maintien du revenu. Son engagement sous cette forme prend fin à présent. La Suisse poursuivra une partie de ces activités depuis son ambassade de Pékin. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Outre les sujets liés aux relations bilatérales, les discussions de vendredi ont notamment porté sur l’engagement des deux pays en faveur du multilatéralisme. La Suisse et la Mongolie défendent dans ce domaine des positions similaires sur de nombreuses questions ; toutes deux s’engagent, par exemple, pour l’abolition universelle de la peine de mort. Les échanges de vendredi ont également porté sur la situation en matière de sécurité en Asie de l’Est et en Europe. En ce qui concerne la recherche d’une paix juste et durable en Ukraine, la présidente de la Confédération a expliqué l’action de la Suisse après la conférence de haut niveau sur la paix en Ukraine, qui s’est tenue mi-juin au Bürgenstock.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Lors de sa visite en Mongolie, la présidente de la Confédération a été reçue par le premier ministre Luvsannamsrain Oyun-Erdene et le président du Parlement Dashzegviin Amarbayasgalan. Elle a aussi visité une exposition dédiée à l’anniversaire des relations bilatérales et rencontré les gestionnaires d’un projet de la DDC consacré à la production responsable de laine de cachemire et de yak.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Poursuite du voyage au Japon&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Après sa visite en Mongolie, la présidente de la Confédération se rendra au Japon, où l’on célébrera le 160e anniversaire des relations bilatérales entre la Suisse et le pays du Soleil-Levant. Au début de son séjour, Viola Amherd rencontrera lundi les représentants des autorités de Shinagawa, un district de la préfecture de Tokyo qui est jumelé avec Genève. Mercredi, elle s’entretiendra avec le premier ministre Fumio Kishida, la ministre des Affaires étrangères Yoko Kamikawa et le ministre de la défense Minoru Kihara. Les discussions seront consacrées à la célébration de l’anniversaire des relations bilatérales, au développement de celles-ci, aux perspectives en Asie de l’Est et à la situation sécuritaire en Europe. L’empereur Naruhito offrira une réception le jeudi 8 août.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>DDPS Communication Palais fédéral Est CH - 3003 Berne</contact>
      <link id="277418">
        <title>Relations bilatérales Suisse–Mongolie (admin.ch)</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae/representations-et-conseils-pour-les-voyages/mongolie/suisse-mongolie.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Svizzera e Mongolia riconoscono successi e opportunità delle relazioni bilaterali</title>
      <lead>La presidente della Confederazione Viola Amherd e il presidente della Mongolia Ukhnaagiin Khurelsukh si sono incontrati venerdì 2 agosto 2024 a Ulan Bator in occasione del 60° anniversario delle relazioni bilaterali per discutere dei risultati ottenuti e delle nuove prospettive negli scambi tra Svizzera e Mongolia. Si è trattato della prima visita di un presidente svizzero in Mongolia. Le due parti hanno sottoscritto una dichiarazione comune sulla futura collaborazione e una dichiarazione d’intenti allo scopo di rafforzare le istituzioni democratiche in Mongolia.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;La dichiarazione comune segna una pietra miliare nelle relazioni bilaterali. In tal modo Svizzera e Mongolia sottolineano il loro legame e il loro impegno per la pace e la stabilità. La dichiarazione definisce inoltre una serie di aree tematiche che si prestano a una più stretta collaborazione in futuro, come il confronto sulla democrazia e lo Stato di diritto, l’impegno nell’ambito dell’ONU e lo sviluppo economico sostenibile.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;L’impegno della Direzione dello sviluppo e della cooperazione (DSC) in Mongolia – tra gli altri nei settori del buongoverno, della sanità, dell’ambiente e della garanzia del reddito – termina in questa forma dopo 20 anni. La Svizzera continuerà a svolgere parte delle attività dalla sua Ambasciata a Pechino.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Oltre a temi bilaterali, il colloquio di venerdì era dedicato in particolare anche all’impegno dei due Paesi per l’ordine multilaterale. In questo contesto Svizzera e Mongolia condividono posizioni simili su molte questioni: ad esempio, si adoperano per l’abolizione della pena di morte a livello mondiale. Durante l’incontro di venerdì si è discusso inoltre della situazione in materia di sicurezza nell’Asia orientale e in Europa. In vista di una pace giusta e duratura in Ucraina, la presidente della Confederazione ha illustrato l’ulteriore impegno della Svizzera dopo la Conferenza di alto livello sulla pace in Ucraina, tenutasi a metà giugno sul Bürgenstock.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Il programma della presidente della Confederazione in Mongolia prevedeva altresì incontri con il primo ministro Luvsannamsrain Oyun-Erdene e il presidente del Parlamento Dashzegviin Amarbayasgalan nonché la visita a una mostra fotografica in occasione dell’anniversario delle relazioni bilaterali e a un progetto della DSC dedicato alla produzione responsabile di cashmere e lana di yak.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Prosecuzione del viaggio in Giappone&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Dalla Mongolia la presidente della Confederazione si recherà in Giappone, dove sarà commemorato il 160° anniversario delle relazioni bilaterali. All’inizio del soggiorno, Viola Amherd incontrerà lunedì a Shinagawa, distretto della Prefettura di Tokyo gemellato con Ginevra, rappresentanti delle autorità. Mercoledì sono previsti colloqui con il primo ministro Fumio Kishida, la ministra degli affari esteri Yoko Kamikawa e il ministro della difesa Minoru Kihara. Sottolineando l’anniversario delle relazioni bilaterali, si discuterà del loro ulteriore sviluppo, delle prospettive in Asia orientale e della situazione in materia di sicurezza in Europa. Giovedì 8 agosto è previsto un ricevimento da parte dell’imperatore Naruhito.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>DDPS Comunicazione Palazzo federale est CH - 3003 Berna</contact>
      <link id="277419">
        <title>Relazioni bilaterali Svizzera–Mongolia (admin.ch)</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae/rappresentanze-e-consigli-di-viaggio/mongolia/svizzera-mongolia.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Switzerland and Mongolia recognise successes and opportunities in their relations</title>
      <lead>On 2 August, President Amherd met with Mongolian President Ukhnaagiin Khurelsukh in Ulaanbaatar on the occasion of the 60th anniversary of relations between the two countries. They discussed past successes and new opportunities for exchanges between Switzerland and Mongolia. It was the first visit to Mongolia by a Swiss president. The two parties signed a joint declaration on future cooperation and a memorandum of understanding aimed at strengthening democratic institutions in Mongolia.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;The joint declaration marks a milestone in bilateral relations: it underlines Switzerland’s and Mongolia’s solidarity and commitment to peace and stability. The declaration also identifies areas for closer cooperation in the future; these include a dialogue on democracy and the rule of law, UN engagement and sustainable economic development.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;After 20 years, the successful engagement in the country by the Swiss Agency for Development and Cooperation (SDC) – which included the areas of good governance, health, the environment and income security – is coming to an end. Switzerland will continue some of its activities from its embassy in Beijing.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In addition to bilateral issues, Friday’s talks focused on both countries’ commitment to the multilateral order. Switzerland and Mongolia have similar positions on many issues, such as the global abolition of the death penalty. Also discussed on Friday was the security situation in East Asia and Europe. In addition, Ms Amherd talked about Switzerland’s commitment to the search for a just and lasting peace in Ukraine following the high-level Peace Summit that was held in Switzerland in mid-June.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The programme in Mongolia included meetings with Prime Minister Luvsannamsrain Oyun-Erdene and Speaker of Parliament Dashzegviin Amarbayasgalan, as well as a visit to a photo exhibition celebrating bilateral relations and to an SDC project dedicated to the responsible production of cashmere and yak wool.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Travel to Japan&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;From Mongolia, Ms Amherd will travel to Japan to celebrate the 160th anniversary of bilateral relations. On Monday, Ms Amherd will visit Shinagawa, a city ward of Tokyo that is twinned with Geneva, for talks with local officials. President Amherd is scheduled to meet with Prime Minister Fumio Kishida, Foreign Minister Yoko Kamikawa and Defence Minister Minoru Kihara on Wednesday. They will commemorate the anniversary and discuss the development of bilateral relations, the outlook for the East Asian region and the security situation in Europe. A reception by Emperor Naruhito is planned for Thursday.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>DDPS Communication Federal Palace East CH-3003 Bern</contact>
      <link id="277420">
        <title>Bilateral relations Switzerland–Mongolia (admin.ch)</title>
        <uri>https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/fdfa/representations-and-travel-advice/mongolia/switzerland-mongolia.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <keywords>
      <keyword id="5981" org-id="502">
        <name lang="de">Dossier Departementschef</name>
        <name lang="fr">Dossier Departementschef</name>
        <name lang="it">Dossier Departementschef</name>
        <name lang="en">Dossier Departementschef</name>
      </keyword>
    </keywords>
    <topics>
      <topic id="33">
        <name lang="de">Bundespräsident/-in</name>
        <name lang="fr">Président/e de la Confédération</name>
        <name lang="it">Presidente della Confederazione</name>
        <name lang="en">President of the Swiss Confederation</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
    <catalogueElements>
      <catalogueElement id="107">
        <name lang="de">Viola Amherd</name>
        <name lang="fr">Viola Amherd</name>
        <name lang="it">Viola Amherd</name>
        <name lang="en">Viola Amherd</name>
      </catalogueElement>
    </catalogueElements>
  </message>
</messages>
