<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="94086" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2023-04-04</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="506" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>501</department-id>
      <name lang="de">armasuisse</name>
      <name lang="fr">Armasuisse</name>
      <name lang="it">Armasuisse</name>
      <name lang="en">Armasuisse</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.ar.admin.ch/</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.ar.admin.ch/</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.ar.admin.ch/</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.ar.admin.ch/</www>
      <email lang="de">info@armasuisse.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@armasuisse.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@armasuisse.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@armasuisse.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="502" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>501</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Generalsekretariat VBS</name>
      <name lang="fr">Secrétariat général du DDPS</name>
      <name lang="it">Segreteria generale del DDPS</name>
      <name lang="en">General Secretariat DDPS</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.vbs.admin.ch/</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.vbs.admin.ch/</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.vbs.admin.ch/</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.vbs.admin.ch/</www>
      <email lang="de">postmaster.vbs@gs-vbs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">postmaster.vbs@gs-vbs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">postmaster.vbs@gs-vbs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">postmaster.vbs@gs-vbs.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="505" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>501</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Gruppe Verteidigung</name>
      <name lang="fr">Groupement de la Défense</name>
      <name lang="it">Aggruppamento Difesa</name>
      <name lang="en">Defence</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.vtg.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.vtg.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.vtg.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.vtg.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@vtg.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@vtg.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@vtg.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@vtg.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="501">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Verteidigung, Bevölkerungsschutz und Sport</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de la défense, de la protection de la population et des sports</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale della difesa, della protezione della popolazione e dello sport</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Defence, Civil Protection and Sports DDPS</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.vbs.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.vbs.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.vbs.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.vbs.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@gs-vbs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@gs-vbs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@gs-vbs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@gs-vbs.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Typenwahl für neue Boden-Boden-Lenkwaffe getroffen</title>
      <lead>armasuisse hat mit SPIKE LR2 von Eurospike die Typenwahl für ein neues Boden-Boden-Lenkwaffen System getroffen. Es ist vorgesehen, die Beschaffung des Waffensystems mit der Armeebotschaft 2024 dem Parlament zu beantragen.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Damit die Schweizer Armee gepanzerte Ziele auch auf grosse Distanzen bekämpfen kann, müssen die Bodentruppen über ein weitreichendes Panzerabwehrlenkwaffensystem verfügen.&lt;br /&gt;Vor diesem Hintergrund hat das Bundesamt für Rüstung (armasuisse) nach einer Marktanalyse verschiedene europäische und amerikanische Hersteller um Informationen zu Boden-Boden-Lenkwaffen angefragt. Im Vordergrund standen dabei Informationen wie zum Beispiel die Funktion, die Wirkung, technische Daten des Einsatzsystems, die mögliche Integration in die bestehende Infrastruktur und die kommerziellen Rahmenbedingungen.&lt;br /&gt;Basierend auf einer detaillierten Analyse der erhaltenen Informationen erfüllten noch zwei Hersteller die militärischen Anforderungen an das System. Bei den beiden in der Evaluation verbleibenden Herstellern wurden vertiefte Informationen sowie Offerten eingeholt.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Entscheid für SPIKE LR2 von Eurospike&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Die Entscheidung für die neue Boden-Boden Lenkwaffe der Schweizer Armee fiel auf das Waffensystem SPIKE LR2. Das von der Firma Eurospike produzierte und bei diversen europäischen Armeen bereits eingeführte System wies in der Auswertung den höchsten militärischen Nutzwert auf und war auch wirtschaftlich das attraktivste Angebot.&lt;br /&gt;Das gewählte System soll vorerst von der Infanterie mobil eingesetzt werden. Auf die Integration in eine Trägerplattform wird in einem ersten Schritt verzichtet. Der SPIKE LR2 bietet jedoch die Möglichkeit für eine spätere Fahrzeugintegration. Die Beschaffung soll mit der Armeebotschaft 2024 dem Parlament beantragt werden. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Eurospike ist ein Joint Venture mit Sitz in Röthenbach a.d. Pegnitz (D) zwischen der Diehl Defence GmbH, Rheinmetall Electronics GmbH und Rafael Advanced Defense Systems. Die Entwicklung, das Design und die Qualifikation des Systems erfolgen grösstenteils bei Rafael in Israel. Ein Grossteil der Produktion von Komponenten der SPIKE LR2 für den europäischen Markt erfolgt an Standorten in Deutschland. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Abklärungen zum Vorgängersystem&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Die vor über 30 Jahren beschaffte Panzerabwehrlenkwaffe TOW (&lt;b&gt;T&lt;/b&gt;ube launched, &lt;b&gt;O&lt;/b&gt;pticallly tracked, &lt;b&gt;W&lt;/b&gt;ire guided) bildete die Hauptbewaffnung des Panzerjägers 90 (Radschützenpanzer, hergestellt durch GDELS-MOWAG), der ausser Dienst gestellt wird. Der Panzerjäger 90 wurde im Jahr 1990 beschafft. 2018 hat das Parlament dem Antrag zur Ausserdienststellung zugestimmt; ab 2024 soll diese vollzogen werden.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Im Vorfeld von Ausserdienststellungen nimmt armasuisse jeweils Kontakt mit dem Originalhersteller bzw. dem Herstellerland auf, um abzuklären, ob ein Interesse an einem Rückkauf besteht oder die Systeme entsorgt werden. Diese Abklärungen laufen auch im vorliegenden Fall.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Kaj-Gunnar Sievert Leiter Kommunikation armasuisse +41 58 464 62 47</contact>
      <attachment id="245750">
        <title>SPIKE LR2_Foto 01 ©VBS/DDPS</title>
        <format>jpg</format>
        <size-kb>2759</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/76455.jpg</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="245751">
        <title>SPIKE LR2_Foto 02 ©VBS/DDPS</title>
        <format>png</format>
        <size-kb>8765</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/76477.png</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="245752">
        <title>SPIKE LR2_Foto 03 ©VBS/DDPS</title>
        <format>jpg</format>
        <size-kb>8092</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/76497.jpg</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Choix du modèle du nouvel engin guidé sol-sol</title>
      <lead>armasuisse a choisi le modèle du nouveau système d’engins guidés sol-sol, soit le SPIKE LR2 d’Eurospike. Il est prévu de soumettre au Parlement la demande d’acquisition du système d’arme dans le cadre du message sur l’armée 2024.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Pour que l’armée suisse puisse également lutter contre des cibles blindées sur de grandes distances, les Forces terrestres doivent disposer d’un système d’engins guidés antichars de longue portée.&lt;br /&gt;Sur cette toile de fond, l’Office fédéral de l’armement (armasuisse), après une analyse du marché, a adressé une demande d’informations sur des engins guidés sol-sol à différents fabricants européens et américains. Son intérêt portait avant tout sur le fonctionnement, l’effet, les données techniques du système d’intervention, l’intégration possible dans l’infrastructure existante et les conditions commerciales.&lt;br /&gt;L’analyse détaillée des informations reçues a alors révélé que deux fabricants étaient en mesure de répondre aux exigences militaires applicables au système souhaité. Des informations approfondies et des offres ont donc été demandées aux deux fabricants restants.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Un choix en faveur du SPIKE LR2 d’Eurospike&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Le choix de nouvel engin guidé sol-sol de l’armée suisse s’est porté sur le système d’arme SPIKE LR2. Produit par l’entreprise Eurospike et déjà introduit dans plusieurs armées européennes, ce système faisait état, d’après l’analyse, de la plus grande valeur d’usage militaire et il représentait également l’offre la plus avantageuse sur le plan économique.&lt;br /&gt;Le système retenu doit d’abord être employé de façon mobile par l’infanterie. On renonce dans un premier temps à l’intégration dans une plate-forme porteuse, mais le SPIKE LR2 offre la possibilité d’une installation ultérieure dans le véhicule. La demande d’acquisition doit être soumise au Parlement dans le cadre du message sur l’armée 2024. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Domiciliée à Röthenbach a.d. Pegnitz (Allemagne), Eurospike est une entreprise commune (joint-venture) de Diehl Defence GmbH, Rheinmetall Electronics GmbH et Rafael Advanced Defense Systems. Le développement, la conception et la qualification du système s’effectuent en majeure partie chez Rafael, en Israël. Une grande partie de la production des composants du SPIKE LR2 à destination du marché européen s’opère sur des sites en Allemagne.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Clarifications relatives au précédent système&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Acquis il y a plus de 30 ans, l’engin guidé antichars TOW (&lt;b&gt;T&lt;/b&gt;ube launched, &lt;b&gt;O&lt;/b&gt;ptically tracked, &lt;b&gt;W&lt;/b&gt;ire guided) était l’arme principale du chasseur de chars 90 (char de grenadiers à roues, fabriqué par GDELS-MOWAG) qui sera mis hors service. Le chasseur de chars 90 avait été acquis en 1990. En 2018, le Parlement a accepté la demande de mise hors service; celle-ci devrait s’effectuer à partir de 2024.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;En amont de mises hors service, armasuisse contacte le fabricant d’origine ou le pays de fabrication afin d’établir si ceux-ci sont intéressés par un rachat ou si les systèmes doivent être éliminés. Ces clarifications sont également en cours dans le cas présent.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Kaj-Gunnar Sievert Responsable Communication armasuisse +41 58 464 62 47</contact>
      <attachment id="245753">
        <title>SPIKE LR2_Photo 01 ©VBS/DDPS</title>
        <format>jpg</format>
        <size-kb>2759</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/76498.jpg</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="245754">
        <title>SPIKE LR2_Photo 02 ©VBS/DDPS</title>
        <format>png</format>
        <size-kb>8765</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/76499.png</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="245755">
        <title>SPIKE LR2_Photo 03 ©VBS/DDPS</title>
        <format>jpg</format>
        <size-kb>8092</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/76500.jpg</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Scelto il nuovo tipo di ordigno guidato terra-terra</title>
      <lead>Con lo SPIKE LR2 di Eurospike, armasuisse ha scelto il nuovo tipo di sistema d’ordigno guidato terra-terra. La proposta di acquisto del sistema d’arma sarà presentata al Parlamento per l’approvazione con il messaggio sull’esercito 2024.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Per riuscire a contrastare i carri armati nemici anche sulle lunghe distanze, le unità di terra dell’esercito svizzero dovranno disporre anche in futuro di un sistema d’ordigno guidato anticarro di vasta portata.&lt;br /&gt;Alla luce di ciò, e dopo aver condotto un’analisi di mercato, l’Ufficio federale dell’armamento (armasuisse) ha richiesto informazioni sugli ordigni guidati terra-terra presso vari produttori europei e americani con particolare attenzione a informazioni quali, ad esempio, il funzionamento, l’efficacia bellica, i dati tecnici del sistema d’impiego, le possibilità di integrazione nell’infrastruttura esistente e le condizioni quadro commerciali.&lt;br /&gt;Sulla base di un’analisi dettagliata delle informazioni ricevute, sono emersi due produttori in grado di soddisfare i requisiti militari per il sistema. Ai due produttori emersi dalla valutazione sono state richieste informazioni più dettagliate e offerte.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Decisione a favore dello SPIKE LR2 di Eurospike&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;La scelta per il nuovo ordigno guidato terra-terra dell’esercito svizzero è ricaduta sul sistema d’arma SPIKE LR2. Nella valutazione, questo sistema, prodotto da Eurospike e già introdotto presso vari eserciti europei, presentava l’utilità militare maggiore ed era anche l’offerta più attraente in termini economici.&lt;br /&gt;Il sistema scelto sarà utilizzato dalla fanteria inizialmente come sistema mobile. In un primo momento, il sistema non sarà integrato in una piattaforma. Tuttavia, lo SPIKE LR2 può essere integrato in un veicolo anche successivamente. La domanda di acquisto sarà presentata al Parlamento con il messaggio sull’esercito 2024. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Eurospike è una joint venture tra le aziende Diehl Defence GmbH, Rheinmetall Electronics GmbH e Rafael Advanced Defense Systems con sede a Röthenbach a.d. Pegnitz (D). Lo sviluppo, la progettazione e la qualificazione del sistema si svolgono principalmente a Rafael in Israele. Gran parte dei componenti dello SPIKE LR2 per il mercato europeo viene prodotta in stabilimenti in Germania.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Chiarimenti riguardanti il sistema precedente&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Il sistema d’ordigno guidato anticarro TOW (&lt;b&gt;T&lt;/b&gt;ube launched, &lt;b&gt;O&lt;/b&gt;pticallly tracked, &lt;b&gt;W&lt;/b&gt;ire guided) acquistato oltre trent’anni fa costituiva l’armamento principale del cacciacarri 90 (carro armato granatieri ruotato, prodotto dalla GDELS-MOWAG) che sarà messo fuori servizio.&lt;br /&gt;Il cacciacarri 90 fu acquistato nel 1990. Nel 2018, il Parlamento ha autorizzato la richiesta di messa fuori servizio, che dovrà essere posta in essere a partire dal 2024.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Prima di una messa fuori servizio, armasuisse contatta il rispettivo produttore originale e il paese produttore per verificare se sono interessati al riacquisto o se, invece, occorrerà procedere allo smaltimento dei sistemi. Questi chiarimenti sono in corso anche nella presente fattispecie.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Kaj-Gunnar Sievert Responsabile Comunicazione armasuisse +41 58 464 62 47</contact>
      <attachment id="245750">
        <title>SPIKE LR2_Foto 01 ©VBS/DDPS</title>
        <format>jpg</format>
        <size-kb>2759</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/76455.jpg</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="245751">
        <title>SPIKE LR2_Foto 02 ©VBS/DDPS</title>
        <format>png</format>
        <size-kb>8765</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/76477.png</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="245752">
        <title>SPIKE LR2_Foto 03 ©VBS/DDPS</title>
        <format>jpg</format>
        <size-kb>8092</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/76497.jpg</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Model selected for new anti-tank guided missile</title>
      <lead>armasuisse has selected the model for a new anti-tank missile system with SPIKE LR2 from Eurospike. It is planned to propose procurement of the weapons systems to Parliament in the 2024 Armed Forces Dispatch.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;In order for the Swiss Armed Forces to be able to combat armoured targets even over greater distances, the ground troops need a long-range anti-tank guided missile system.&lt;br /&gt;With this in mind, the Federal Office for Defence Procurement (armasuisse) carried out a market analysis and subsequently requested information on anti-tank guided missiles from various European and American manufacturers. The information on which these requests focused included, for example, the function, the effect, technical data on the operations system, the potential integration in the existing infrastructure, and the commercial framework conditions.&lt;br /&gt;Based on a detailed analysis of the information received, two of the manufacturers met the military requirements expected of the system. Further in-depth information and offers were then obtained from the two manufacturers remaining in the evaluation process.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;SPIKE LR2 from Eurospike chosen&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;The decision regarding which anti-tank guided missile system would be used by the Swiss Armed forces fell in favour of the SPIKE LR2 weapon system. The system produced by Eurospike and already used by numerous European armed forces demonstrated in the evaluation phase that it was the most useful in terms of military capabilities and was also the most attractive offer from a business perspective.&lt;br /&gt;The chosen system is set to be initially used by the infantry on a mobile basis. The system will not be integrated into a carrier platform in the first stage. However, the possibility remains to integrate the SPIKE LR2 system into vehicles at a later date. Procurement is to be proposed to Parliament in the 2024 Armed Forces Dispatch. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Eurospike is a joint venture based in Röthenbach a.d. Pegnitz (D) between Diehl Defence GmbH, Rheinmetall Electronics GmbH and Rafael Advanced Defense Systems. The development, design and qualification of the system will be carried out for the most part at Rafael in Israel. A large part of the SPIKE LR2 components for the European market are produced across locations in Germany. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Clarifications on the previous system&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;The anti-tank guided missile TOW (&lt;b&gt;T&lt;/b&gt;ube launched, &lt;b&gt;O&lt;/b&gt;pticallly tracked, &lt;b&gt;W&lt;/b&gt;ire guided) procured over 30 years ago constitutes the main armament of the anti-tank armoured personnel carrier 90 (wheeled armoured personnel carrier, manufactured by GDELS-MOWAG), which is to be decommissioned. The anti-tank armoured personnel carrier 90 was procured in 1990. In 2018, Parliament approved the motion for decommissioning; this is to be put into practice from 2024.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Before the start of decommissioning, armasuisse will contact the original manufacturer or manufacturing country in each case to clarify whether there is interest in a repurchase or whether the systems are to be disposed of. These clarifications are also ongoing in the present case.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Kaj-Gunnar Sievert Head of Communications armasuisse +41 58 464 62 47</contact>
      <attachment id="245753">
        <title>SPIKE LR2_Photo 01 ©VBS/DDPS</title>
        <format>jpg</format>
        <size-kb>2759</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/76498.jpg</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="245754">
        <title>SPIKE LR2_Photo 02 ©VBS/DDPS</title>
        <format>png</format>
        <size-kb>8765</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/76499.png</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <attachment id="245755">
        <title>SPIKE LR2_Photo 03 ©VBS/DDPS</title>
        <format>jpg</format>
        <size-kb>8092</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/76500.jpg</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <keywords>
      <keyword id="5160" org-id="505">
        <name lang="de">Verteidigung</name>
        <name lang="fr">Défense</name>
        <name lang="it">Difesa</name>
        <name lang="en">defence</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="5180" org-id="505">
        <name lang="de">Armee</name>
        <name lang="fr">Armée</name>
        <name lang="it">Esercito</name>
        <name lang="en">armed forces</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="5310" org-id="505">
        <name lang="de">Rüstung / Beschaffung</name>
        <name lang="fr">Armement / Acquisition d'armement</name>
        <name lang="it">Armamento / Acquisto d'armamenti</name>
        <name lang="en">Armament / Procurement</name>
      </keyword>
      <keyword id="5320" org-id="505">
        <name lang="de">Rüstungspolitik</name>
        <name lang="fr">Politique d'armement</name>
        <name lang="it">Politica d'armamento</name>
        <name lang="en">Armament Policy</name>
      </keyword>
    </keywords>
    <topics>
      <topic id="3">
        <name lang="de">Armee</name>
        <name lang="fr">Armée</name>
        <name lang="it">Esercito</name>
        <name lang="en">Armed Forces</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="40">
        <name lang="de">Sicherheit</name>
        <name lang="fr">Sécurité</name>
        <name lang="it">Sicurezza</name>
        <name lang="en">Security</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
