<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="43532" revoked="no">
    <version>2</version>
    <pubdate>2012-02-23</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="201" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>201</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="201">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Schweiz organisiert humanitäres Briefing über die Lage in Syrien</title>
      <lead>Stellungnahme</lead>
      <text link="no">Auf Initiative der Schweiz fand am Donnerstag in Genf eine Sitzung über die Koordination der humanitären Hilfe in Syrien statt. Dieses Treffen ist eine Fortsetzung der informellen Tagung in Berlin vom 17. Februar 2012, die einen substanziellen Meinungsaustausch über die humanitäre Lage in Syrien und künftige Optionen brachte. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;In Genf kamen neben Regierungsvertreterinnen und -vertretern aus den Schlüsselländern, einschliesslich der Nachbarstaaten, auch Vertreterinnen und Vertreter des Büros der Vereinten Nationen für die Koordinierung humanitärer Angelegenheiten (OCHA), des UNO-Flüchtlingshochkommissariats (UNHCR), des Welternährungsprogramms (WFP) sowie weitere humanitäre Akteure zusammen.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;An diesem Treffen wurde die Notwendigkeit unterstrichen, die Bedingungen für den Zugang der humanitären Hilfe zur syrischen Zivilbevölkerung so rasch wie möglich zu verbessern, namentlich weil die humanitären Bedürfnisse weiter zunehmen. Die Teilnehmenden verständigten sich in diesem Zusammenhang auf die Rolle des UNO-Büros für die Koordinierung humanitärer Angelegenheiten. Angesichts der Lage in Syrien wird der angekündigte Besuch von Valérie Amos, Untergeneralsekretärin für humanitäre Angelegenheiten, in Damaskus von allen Teilnehmenden begrüsst. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Bei dieser Gelegenheit wurde einmal mehr daran erinnert, dass die humanitäre Hilfe unabhängig, unparteiisch und neutral bleiben muss. &lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Kommunikation EDA Bundeshaus West CH-3003 Bern Tel. Kommunikationsservice: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Medienstelle: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Briefing Humanitaire sur la situation en Syrie organisée par la Suisse</title>
      <lead>Prise de position</lead>
      <text link="no">Une réunion sur la coordination de l'aide humanitaire en Syrie a eu lieu jeudi à Genève à l’initiative de la Suisse. Cette rencontre s’inscrit dans la continuité de la réunion informelle de Berlin du 17 février 2012 qui a permis un échange de vues substantiel sur la situation humanitaire en Syrie et les options pour le futur. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;A Genève, les représentants de gouvernements clés, y compris ceux de pays avoisinants, du Bureau de la Coordination des Affaires humanitaires de l'ONU (OCHA), du Haut Commissariat de l'ONU aux réfugiés (HCR), du Programme Alimentaire Mondial (PAM) ainsi que d’autres acteurs humanitaires fortement impliqués dans le contexte se sont réunis. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;La réunion a souligné le besoin urgent d’améliorer les conditions d’accès humanitaire à la population civile syrienne, en raison de besoins humanitaires grandissants. Les participants se sont accordés sur le rôle du Bureau pour la coordination des Affaires humanitaires à cet égard. Dans ce contexte, la visite annoncée de Mme Valérie Amos, Sous-secrétaire générale pour les Affaires Humanitaires, à Damas a été saluée par l’ensemble des participants. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;A cette occasion, l’importance de l’indépendance, de l’impartialité et de la neutralité de l’Aide Humanitaire, a été rappelée.</text>
      <contact>Communication DFAE Palais fédéral ouest CH-3003 Berne Tél. Service de communication: +41 58 462 31 53 Tél. Service de presse: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <revisions>
        <revision date="2012-02-24 13:12" type="I"/>
      </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Briefing umanitario sulla situazione in Siria organizzato dalla Svizzera</title>
      <lead>Presa di posizione</lead>
      <text link="no">Una riunione sulla coordinazione dell’aiuto umanitario in Siria ha avuto luogo giovedì a Ginevra su iniziativa della Svizzera.Tale incontro s’iscrive nella continuazione della riunione informale di Berlino del 17 febbraio 2012, che ha permesso uno scambio sostanziale di punti di vista sulla situazione in Siria e sulle opzioni per il futuro.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;A Ginevra, si sono riuniti i rappresentanti dei governi chiave, compresi quelli dei Paesi vicini, dell’Ufficio per il coordinamento degli affari umanitari delle Nazioni Unite (OCHA), dell’Alto Commissariato delle Nazioni Unite per i rifugiati (ACNUR) e del Programma alimentare mondiale (PAM) nonché altri attori umanitari particolarmente coinvolti in tale contesto.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;La riunione ha sottolineato l’urgente necessità di migliorare le condizioni di accesso agli aiuti umanitari per la popolazione civile siriana, a fronte della crescente emergenza umanitaria. A tale riguardo, i partecipanti si sono accordati in merito al ruolo dell’Ufficio per il coordinamento degli affari umanitari delle Nazioni Unite. In questo contesto, la visita annunciata da Valérie Amos, sottosegretario generale per gli affari umanitari a Damasco è stata accolta con favore da tutti i partecipanti.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;L’occasione è servita infine a ricordare l’importanza dell’indipendenza, dell’imparzialità e della neutralità dell’aiuto umanitario.</text>
      <contact>Comunicazione DFAE Palazzo federale ovest CH-3003 Berna Tel. Servizio di comunicazione: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Servizio stampa: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Humanitarian Briefing on the Situation in Syria organized by Switzerland</title>
      <lead>Position</lead>
      <text link="no">Upon an initiative of Switzerland, a meeting on the coordination of humanitarian aid for Syria took place on Thursday in Geneva. &lt;p&gt;This briefing is part of the follow-up to the informal meeting held on 17 February in Berlin, which provided a platform for a substantial exchange of views on the humanitarian situation in Syria and a discussion of options for the future. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The Geneva meeting brought together government representatives from the key countries, including those in the neighbouring region, as well as representatives of the United Nations Office for the Coordination of Humanitarian Affairs (OCHA), representatives of the UN High Commissioner for Refugees (UNHCR), the World Food Programme (WFP), and other humanitarian actors strongly involved in the Syrian context. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The meeting pointed out the urgent need to improve the conditions of humanitarian access to the civilian population of Syria due to the escalating humanitarian needs. The participants came to an agreement on the role of the UN Office for the Coordination of Humanitarian Affairs in this regard. Against this background, the announcement of a visit to Damascus by Ms. Valerie Amos, Under-Secretary-General for Humanitarian Affairs, was applauded by the entire assembly. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The meeting also provided an opportunity to reiterate the importance of the independence, the impartiality, and the neutrality of humanitarian aid. &lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>FDFA Communication Federal Palace West Wing CH-3003 Bern, Switzerland Tel. Communication service: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Press service: +41 58 460 55 55 E-mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @SwissMFA</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
