<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="43373" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2012-02-16</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="1032" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>701</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eawag: Wasserforschungsinstitut des ETH-Bereichs</name>
      <name lang="fr">Eawag: L'Institut de Recherche de l'Eau du Domaine des EPF</name>
      <name lang="it">Eawag: L'Istituto per la Ricerca sulle Acque nel Settore dei Politecnici Federali</name>
      <name lang="en">Eawag: Swiss Federal Institute of Aquatic Science and Technology</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.eawag.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.eawag.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.eawag.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.eawag.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@eawag.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@eawag.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@eawag.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@eawag.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="701">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Wirtschaft, Bildung und Forschung</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'économie, de la formation et de la recherche</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'economia, della formazione e della ricerca</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Economic Affairs, Education and Research</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Dübendorf</city>
      <title>Seendüngung bringt Fischarten zum Verschwinden</title>
      <lead>Die Überdüngung der Schweizer Seen hat die Zahl der einzigartigen einheimischen Felchenarten innert kurzer Zeit um fast 40% reduziert. Nur in tiefen und von der übermässigen Nährstoffzufuhr weniger betroffenen Alpenrandseen, wie dem Thuner-, dem Brienzer- oder dem Vierwaldstättersee konnten sich die historisch belegten Arten halten. Doch auch sie sind genetisch gesehen näher zusammengerückt. Das weist eine heute in Nature publizierte Studie der Eawag und der Universität Bern nach.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Die Vielfalt der Felchenarten wurde nicht bloss durch den Verlust an Lebensraum reduziert. Vielmehr wurde das Artensterben zum grossen Teil durch die Vermischung einst eigenständiger Arten verursacht. Verantwortlich dafür war – so fanden Wissenschafter der Eawag und der Universität Bern heraus – die Überdüngung der Schweizer Seen zwischen 1950 und 1990: Weil in dieser Zeit viele Seen am Grund und im tiefen Wasser kaum noch Sauerstoff enthielten, fehlten Nischen für Spezialisten, die in grösseren Tiefen fressen oder sich fortpflanzen. Sie, die sich seit der letzten Eiszeit entwickelt hatten, mussten in seichteres Wasser ausweichen. Dort kreuzten sie sich mit verwandten Arten und verloren innert weniger Generationen ihre genetische und funktionale Einzigartigkeit, ein Prozess, der auch als «Umkehr der Artentstehung» bezeichnet wird.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Artenschutz neu definieren&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ein heute in &lt;i&gt;Nature&lt;/i&gt; publizierter Artikel[i] weist nach, dass das Ausmass der Düngung nicht nur den Artenrückgang erklärt, sondern auch dafür verantwortlich ist, dass die noch erhaltenen Arten weniger verschieden geworden sind. Je höher die maximalen Phosphorkonzentrationen in den 17 nördlich der Alpen untersuchten Seen geklettert sind, desto mehr sind unter den verbliebenen Felchenarten die genetische Vielfalt sowie Spezialisierungen an bestimmte Wassertiefen, bestimmte Laichzeiten oder besondere Ernährungsweisen verloren gegangen. «Offensichtlich ist die Umkehr der Artentstehung deutlich häufiger als bisher angenommen», sagt Evolutionsbiologe Ole Seehausen, Leiter der Studie, «in kurzer Zeit verschwinden dabei Arten, die sich zuvor über Jahrtausende durch Anpassung an spezielle ökologische Bedingungen entwickelt haben.» Für den Schutz der Biodiversität heisst es also, nicht nur die bestehenden Arten zu erhalten, sondern auch die ökologischen und evolutionären Prozesse, welche den Spezialisten das Überleben sichern und zur Entstehung neuer Arten beitragen. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Felchen als Untersuchungsobjekt geeignet&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Das Besondere an den Felchen ist, dass es im Alpenraum mindestens 25 Seen gibt, in denen eine oder mehrere endemische Arten leben. Damit werden Arten bezeichnet, die ausschliesslich im jeweiligen See und sonst nirgends vorkommen. Zudem sind von diesen Felchen zahlreiche historische Daten und Gewebeproben erhalten. Nicht nur weil es begehrte Speisefische sind, sondern vor allem weil vor 60 Jahren eine detaillierte Studie die Felchen aus 17 dieser Seen wissenschaftlich untersucht und klassiert hat. Dieselben Seen wurden nun von Seehausens Doktoranden Pascal Vonlanthen (Eawag und Universität Bern) erneut unter die Lupe genommen: Im Mittel ist die Zahl der Felchenarten um 38% zurückgegangen. In sieben Seen sind die ursprünglichen Felchenpopulationen heute gar ganz ausgestorben und wurden durch eingesetzte Fische ersetzt (Genfer-, Murten-, Sempacher-, Baldegger-, Hallwiler-, Greifen- und Pfäffikersee). Keinen Artenrückgang hinnehmen mussten einzig die tiefen und von der Überdüngung weniger stark betroffenen Alpenrandseen Thuner-, Brienzer- und Vierwaldstättersee. Im Walen- und im Zürichsee leben heute noch je zwei von ehemals drei Felchenarten, im Bodensee wurden noch vier von ehemals fünf Arten nachgewiesen. Doch auch unter den verbliebenen Arten sind die genetische und ökologische Differenzierungen sowie die Variationen in der Gestalt der Fische kleiner geworden. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Die Felchen werden von den beteiligten Wissenschaftern als Modell betrachtet. «Wir müssen davon ausgehen, dass die Düngung der Seen auch bei anderen Fischen, vielleicht auch bei den Fischnährtieren, ähnliche Verluste der Vielfalt bewirkt haben», sagt Seehausen. Der gleichzeitig für die Universität Bern und die Eawag arbeitende Forscher sieht in der aktuellen Studie auch eine Warnung an diejenigen, die neuerdings in der Hoffnung auf höhere Fischfangerträge eine Drosselung der Phosphorelimination in Kläranlagen fordern: «Schon eine geringfügige Nährstoffanreicherung über den natürlichen Zustand eines Sees hinaus hat Auswirkungen auf die Artenvielfalt. Und sind endemische Arten als Folge der Düngung einmal aus einem See verschwunden, lässt sich dieser Prozess nicht mehr umkehren», sagt er. Gerade die nähstoffarmen Seen seien daher als einzigartige Artenreservoire und als Orte, wo neue Arten entstehen können, besonders schützenswert.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;[i] Titel der Originalpublikation: Eutrophication causes speciation reversal in whitefish adaptive radiations; DOI: 10.1038/nature10824; Pascal Vonlanthen, David Bittner, Alan G. Hudson, Kyle A. Young, Rudolf Mueller, Bänz Lundsgaard-Hansen, Denis Roy, Sasha di Piazza, Carlo R. Largiarder, Ole Seehausen. 2012</text>
      <contact>Dr. Pascal Vonlanthen, 41 58 765 2161 pascal.vonlanthen@eawag.ch Prof. Dr. Ole Seehausen, Eawag (Abteilung Fischökologie und Evolution) und Institut für Ökologie und Evolution der Universität Bern (Abteilung Aquatische Ökologie); Tel. +41 58 765 21 21, ole.seehausen@eawag.ch; am 16.2. erreichbar unter: +41 31 631 31 31, ole.seehausen@iee.unibe.ch Fotos zum Download auf www.eawag.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Dubendorf</city>
      <title>L’enrichissement des lacs en matières fertilisantes affecte la diversité des poissons</title>
      <lead>L’eutrophisation des lacs suisses a provoqué en très peu de temps la disparition de près de 40% des espèces de corégones indigènes. Seuls les lacs périalpins profonds et relativement épargnés par ce phénomène comme ceux de Thoune, de Brienz ou des Quatre Cantons ont pu conserver leur diversité d’origine. Mais même les espèces préservées se sont rapprochées génétiquement dans les lacs plus perturbés et présentent donc une intégrité fragile. C’est ce que montre une étude de l’Eawag et de l’Université de Berne qui paraît aujourd’hui dans la revue Nature.</lead>
      <text link="no">La diversité des corégones, victime de la perte d’habitats favorisé par l’eutrophisation des lacs qui s’est produite entre 1950 et 1990, a été particulièrement touché par un phénomène de croisement entre espèces autrefois distinctes. C’est ce que viennent de montrer des scientifiques de l’Eawag et de l’Université de Berne. A cette époque, le fond et les couches profondes de nombreux lacs ont été progressivement privés d’oxygène et les niches écologiques occupées par des spécialistes se nourrissant ou se reproduisant en profondeur ont en grande partie disparu. Les espèces de fond qui avaient évolué depuis les dernières glaciations en se spécialisant ont alors été contraintes de remonter pour retrouver des conditions propices. Elles se sont alors croisées avec les espèces parentes qui occupaient déjà les lieux et ont perdu leur intégrité génétique et fonctionnelle en l’espace de quelques générations, un phénomène également appelé «dé-spéciation». &lt;h3&gt;Il faut revoir les stratégies de protection des espèces&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/b&gt;Une étude publiée aujourd’hui dans la revue &lt;i&gt;Nature&lt;/i&gt;[i] démontre que l’importance particulière des apports de substances fertilisantes a non seulement causé l’extinction de nombreuses espèces mais qu’elle a également réduit les différences génétiques et morphologiques existant entre les espèces restantes. L’observation de 17 lacs périalpins au nord des Alpes a en effet révélé que plus les teneurs en phosphates atteintes dans les lacs étaient élevées, plus la différentiation génétique des espèces de corégones restantes et leur degré de spécialisation par rapport à la profondeur, la période de reproduction ou le mode d’alimentation était réduit. «Il semble que le phénomène de dé-spéciation soit beaucoup plus fréquent qu’on ne le pensait“, commente Ole Seehausen, le spécialiste de l’évolution qui a dirigé l’étude. «Il provoque en très peu de temps l’extinction d’espèces qui avaient mis des millénaires à apparaître par adaptation progressive à des conditions écologiques très particulières.» Pour préserver la biodiversité, il faut donc non seulement protéger les espèces existantes mais également les processus écologiques et évolutifs qui permettent la survie des spécialistes et contribuent à l’apparition de nouvelles espèces. &lt;h3&gt;Les corégones sont des objets d’étude privilégiés &lt;/h3&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;L’intérêt des corégones pour la recherche réside d’une part dans le fait que les Alpes et leur pourtour comptent plus de 25 lacs abritant chacun une ou plusieurs espèces endémiques, que l’on ne trouve donc nulle part ailleurs. D’autre part, les scientifiques peuvent s’appuyer sur une grande quantité de données historiques et d’échantillons de tissus dus non seulement à l’intérêt général porté aux corégones en tant que poissons nobles recherchés pour leurs qualités gustatives mais encore et surtout à un inventaire et une étude détaillée des corégones menés il y a 60 ans dans 17 lacs périalpins. Ces mêmes lacs ont maintenant été réexaminés par Pascal Vonlanthen, doctorant de l’équipe d’Ole Seehausen (Eawag et université de Berne). Le résultat est édifiant : le nombre d’espèces de corégones a chuté de 38% en moyenne et la population d’origine a même totalement disparu dans sept des lacs étudiés, remplacée par des corégones introduits (lac Léman, lacs de Morat, de Sempach, de Hallwil, de Pfäffikon, de Baldegg et de Greifen). Seuls les lacs profonds de Thoune, de Brienz et des Quatre Cantons, qui ont été moins touchés par l’eutrophisation, n’ont pas subi de perte de diversité spécifique. Les lacs de Walenstadt et de Zurich abritent encore deux des trois espèces autrefois répertoriées et le lac de Constance a pu en conserver quatre sur cinq. Mais les espèces restantes ont également été affectées et présentent une variabilité morphologique et une différenciation génétique et écologique moins marquées que par le passé. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;p&gt;Les scientifiques considèrent les corégones comme des modèles d’étude représentatifs d’un phénomène plus large. «Il est plus que probable que la fertilisation des lacs ait provoqué des pertes de diversité équivalentes chez d’autres poissons, peut-être même à d’autres niveaux de la chaîne alimentaire“, explique Ole Seehausen. Le chercheur, qui travaille en parallèle pour l’Eawag et l’Université de Berne, voit dans les résultats de l’étude un avertissement pour tous ceux qui souhaitent une atténuation de l’élimination du phosphore dans les stations d’épuration pour accroître les rendements de la pêche : «Le moindre enrichissement d’un lac au-delà de son niveau naturel a déjà un impact sur sa biodiversité. Et une fois qu’une espèce endémique a disparu, il est impossible de revenir en arrière», explique-t-il. En tant que réservoirs de biodiversité ayant conservé leur potentiel de spéciation, les lacs pauvres en nutriments doivent donc être protégés en priorité. &lt;br /&gt;[i] Titre de l’article original: Eutrophication causes speciation reversal in whitefish adaptive radiations; DOI: 10.1038/nature10824; Pascal Vonlanthen, David Bittner, Alan G. Hudson, Kyle A. Young, Rudolf Mueller, Bänz Lundsgaard-Hansen, Denis Roy, Sasha di Piazza, Carlo R. Largiarder, Ole Seehausen. 2012&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Dr. Pascal Vonlanthen, 41 58 765 2161 pascal.vonlanthen@eawag.ch Prof. Dr. Ole Seehausen, Eawag (Dpt. Ecologie &amp; évolution des poissons) et Institut für Ökologie und Evolution der Universität Bern (Dept. Aquatische Ökologie), Tel. +41 58 765 21 21, ole.seehausen@eawag.ch; pour le 16.2. : +41 31 631 31 31, ole.seehausen@iee.unibe.ch Photos à télécharger sur www.eawag.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Dübendorf</city>
      <title>Loss of fish species caused by lake eutrophication</title>
      <lead>Within a relatively short period, eutrophication has led to a reduction of almost 40% in the number of endemic whitefish species in Swiss lakes. Only in deep perialpine lakes least exposed to high nutrient inputs – such as Lakes Thun, Brienz and Lucerne – has the original diversity of endemic species been able to survive. But even these species have become less genetically distinctive. These findings are reported in a study by Eawag and Bern University researchers, published in Nature today.</lead>
      <text link="no">The decline in the diversity of whitefish species is not merely due to a loss of habitats. Rather, the disappearance of species has been largely caused by the hybridization of formerly distinct species. According to a study by scientists from Eawag and Bern University, this in turn can be explained by the eutrophication of Swiss lakes between 1950 and 1980: as the bottom and deep waters of many lakes were severely oxygen-depleted during this period, deep-feeding or deep-spawning species were deprived of their ecological niche. These specialists, which had evolved since the last ice age, had to move to shallower waters. Here, they interbred with related species, thus losing their genetic and functional distinctiveness within a few generations, in a process known as speciation reversal. &lt;h3&gt;Redefining conservation&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/b&gt;As the paper published today in&lt;i&gt; Nature&lt;/i&gt;[i] demonstrates, eutrophication levels not only account for the loss of species but are also responsible for the loss of differentiation among the surviving species. In the 17 pre-alpine lakes studied, the higher the maximum phosphorus concentrations recorded, the greater the loss of genetic diversity and specialization to particular water depths, spawning times or types of feeding among the remaining whitefish species. Evolutionary biologist Ole Seehausen, the lead author of the study, comments: "Speciation reversal appears to be more widespread than has previously been supposed; this process involves the rapid disappearance of species which evolved over thousands of years by adaptation to specific ecological conditions." This means that the protection of biodiversity requires not only the conservation of existing species, but the protection of ecological and evolutionary processes which assure the maintenance of specialists and promote the generation of new species. &lt;h3&gt;Whitefish – suitable objects of investigation&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;What makes whitefish special is the fact that there are at least 25 perialpine lakes which harbour between one and six endemic species – i.e. species found exclusively in the lake in question. In addition, good historical records and tissue samples exist for these species. This is not only because whitefish is a popular commercial fish, but in particular because whitefish from 17 of these lakes were scientifically studied and classified in a detailed study carried out 60 years ago. The same lakes have now been investigated once again by Seehausen's PhD student Pascal Vonlanthen (Eawag and Bern University): on average, the number of whitefish species has declined by 38%. In seven lakes, the original whitefish populations are now extinct and have been replaced by hatchery stocks (Lakes Geneva, Murten, Sempach, Baldegg, Hallwil, Greifen and Pfäffiker). The only study lakes not suffering any species loss were Lakes Thun, Brienz and Lucerne – deep perialpine waterbodies less seriously affected by eutrophication. In both Lake Walen and Lake Zurich, two of three historical whitefish species have survived, and four of five historical species are still found in Lake Constance. But among the extant species, there has been a strong decline of genetic and ecological distinctiveness and also of phenotypic variation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;p&gt;Whitefish are regarded as a model organism by the scientists involved in the study. Seehausen, who is affiliated with both Bern University and Eawag, says: "We must assume that lake eutrophication has caused similar losses of diversity among other fish, and perhaps also among their invertebrate prey species." He also interprets this study as a warning to those in the fishing community who have recently called for the restriction of phosphorus elimination measures at wastewater treatment plants in the hope that fishing yields would be increased as a result of nutrient enrichment: "Even a slight rise in nutrient levels over the natural trophic state of a lake has an impact on species diversity. And if endemic species are lost as a result of eutrophication, this process cannot be reversed." Accordingly, in Seehausen's view, oligotrophic lakes in particular deserve special protection as unique reservoirs of biodiversity, where new species can evolve.&lt;b&gt;&lt;/b&gt; &lt;br /&gt;[i]Title of the original publication: Eutrophication causes speciation reversal in whitefish adaptive radiations; DOI: 10.1038/nature10824; Pascal Vonlanthen, David Bittner, Alan G. Hudson, Kyle A. Young, Rudolf Mueller, Bänz Lundsgaard-Hansen, Denis Roy, Sasha di Piazza, Carlo R. Largiarder, Ole Seehausen. 2012&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Dr Pascal Vonlanthen, +41 (0)58 765 2161, pascal.vonlanthen@eawag.ch Professor Ole Seehausen, +41 (0)58 765 2121, ole.seehausen@eawag.ch; for 16. Feb.: +41 (0)31 631 31 31, ole.seehausen@iee.unibe.ch Photos available for download from www.eawag.ch</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="8">
        <name lang="de">Bildung und Forschung</name>
        <name lang="fr">Formation et recherche</name>
        <name lang="it">Formazione e ricerca</name>
        <name lang="en">Education and Research</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="29">
        <name lang="de">Umwelt und Natur</name>
        <name lang="fr">Environnement et nature</name>
        <name lang="it">Ambiente e natura</name>
        <name lang="en">Environment and Nature</name>
      </topic>
      <topic id="38">
        <name lang="de">Landwirtschaft</name>
        <name lang="fr">Agriculture</name>
        <name lang="it">Agricoltura</name>
        <name lang="en">Agriculture</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
