<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="9277" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2003-12-09</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="703" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>701</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Staatssekretariat für Wirtschaft</name>
      <name lang="fr">Secrétariat d'Etat à l'économie</name>
      <name lang="it">Segreteria di Stato dell'economia</name>
      <name lang="en">State Secretariat for Economic Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.seco.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.seco.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.seco.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.seco.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@seco.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@seco.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@seco.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@seco.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="701">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Wirtschaft, Bildung und Forschung</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'économie, de la formation et de la recherche</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'economia, della formazione e della ricerca</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Economic Affairs, Education and Research</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.wbf.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-wbf.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Informations-und Kommunikationstechnologie im Einsatz für die Armutsbekämpfung</title>
      <teaser>Das Staatssekretariat für Wirtschaft (SECO) stellt am Weltgipfel über die Informationsgesellschaft (WSIS) in Genf seine entwicklungspolitischen Aktivitäten im Bereich der Informations- und Kommunikationstechnologie vor. Den Rahmen dafür bildet die«Information and Communication Technologies for Development Platform» (ICT4D), die vom 9. - 13. Dezember 2003 als sogenanntes «Side Event» auf dem Palexpo-Gelände in Genf stattfindet.</teaser>
      <lead>Das Staatssekretariat für Wirtschaft (SECO) stellt am Weltgipfel über die Informationsgesellschaft (WSIS) in Genf seine entwicklungspolitischen Aktivitäten im Bereich der Informations- und Kommunikationstechnologie vor. Den Rahmen dafür bildet die«Information and Communication Technologies for Development Platform» (ICT4D), die vom 9. - 13. Dezember 2003 als sogenanntes «Side Event» auf dem Palexpo-Gelände in Genf stattfindet.</lead>
      <text link="no">Der WSIS ist der erste Weltgipfel, der sich mit den Chancen und Herausforderungen der Informationsgesellschaft auseinandersetzt. Die ICT4D-Plattform besteht aus einer Ausstellung sowie einem Konferenzprogramm und ist auch für die Öffentlichkeit zugänglich. Das seco und seine Partner präsentieren im Rahmen dieser Plattform gesamthaft 25 Projekte im Bereich der Informations- und Kommunikationstechnologie mit Schwerpunkt e-business, e-waste, e-security und e-procurement.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Am 9. Dezember hat Staatssekretär David Syz das gemeinsam mit der Weltbank organisierte, alljährliche infoDev Symposium eröffnet. Das infoDev-Programm, welches von der Schweiz mitfinanziert wird, unterstützt seit 1995 Entwicklungsländer bei der Einführung und Nutzung moderner Informationstechnologien. Vom 11. - 12. Dezember 2003 organisiert das seco gemeinsam mit dem Internationalen Handelszentrum (ITC) einen zweitägigen, interaktiven Workshop mit Schwerpunktthema e-business. Er soll aufzeigen, wie kleine Exportfirmen aus Entwicklungsländern ihre Wettbewerbsfähigkeit dank Anwendung von ICT-Instrumenten steigern und den bestehenden digitalen Graben überwinden können. Erstmals werden zudem zwei internetgestützte Handbücher zu den Themen Recycling von Elektro-Schrott und elektronische Sicherheit präsentiert. Das seco zeigt hier auf, wie den Herausforderungen der Informationsgesellschaft bezüglich Nachhaltigkeit konkret begegnet werden kann.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Weitere Informationen zu den Aktivitäten des&amp;nbsp;SECO am WSIS:&amp;nbsp;&lt;u&gt;http://www.seco-cooperation.ch&lt;/u&gt;&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Fotos zum WSIS in Genf: siehe auf unserer &lt;u&gt;Online-Fotodatenbank&lt;br /&gt; &lt;/u&gt;&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Bern, 9. Dezember 2003&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; &lt;b&gt;Staatssekretariat für Wirtschaft&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt; Kommunikation&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; &lt;b&gt;Auskünfte:&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt; Christian Hofer&lt;br /&gt; Informationsbeauftragter&lt;br /&gt; Wirtschaftliche Entwicklungszusammenarbeit &lt;br /&gt; Tel. 079 328 74 72</text>
      <contact/>
      <link id="18088">
        <title>&lt;u&gt;http://www.seco-cooperation.ch&lt;/u&gt;</title>
        <uri>http://www.seco-cooperation.ch</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="18089">
        <title>&lt;u&gt;Online-Fotodatenbank&lt;/u&gt;</title>
        <uri>http://www.photopress.ch/image/seco</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Les technologies de l'information et de la communication au service de la lutte contre la pauvreté</title>
      <teaser>Présent à Genève dans le cadre du Sommet mondial sur la société de l'information (SMSI), le Secrétariat d'Etat à l'économie (SECO) y détaille les activités de la Suisse dans le domaine du développement économique touchant aux technologies de l'information et de la communication. Cette intervention s'inscrit dans le cadre de l' «Information and Communication Technologies for Development Platform» (ICT4D) qui se déroule à Palexpo (Genève), du 9 au 13 décembre 2003, sous la forme d'un événement concomitant à ce sommet.</teaser>
      <lead>Présent à Genève dans le cadre du Sommet mondial sur la société de l'information (SMSI), le Secrétariat d'Etat à l'économie (SECO) y détaille les activités de la Suisse dans le domaine du développement économique touchant aux technologies de l'information et de la communication. Cette intervention s'inscrit dans le cadre de l' «Information and Communication Technologies for Development Platform» (ICT4D) qui se déroule à Palexpo (Genève), du 9 au 13 décembre 2003, sous la forme d'un événement concomitant à ce sommet.</lead>
      <text link="no">Le SMSI est le premier sommet mondial axé sur les opportunités et les défis de la société de l'information. La plate-forme ICT4D, constituée d'une exposition et d'une série de conférences, est également accessible au public. Dans le cadre de celle-ci, le seco et ses partenaires présentent 25 projets relatifs aux technologies de l'information et de la communication et plus particulièrement aux cyberaffaires («e-business»), aux déchets électroniques («e-waste»), à la sécurité en ligne («e-security») et aux achats sur l'internet («e-procurement»).&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Le 9 décembre, le secrétaire d'Etat David Syz a ouvert le symposium annuel infoDev, organisé conjointement avec la Banque mondiale. Le programme infoDev, cofinancé par la Suisse, soutient depuis 1995 les pays en développement dans leurs efforts pour introduire et utiliser les technologies modernes de l'information. En partenariat avec le Centre du commerce international (CCI), le seco organise les 11 et 12 décembre 2003 un atelier interactif axé sur les cyberaffaires. Cet atelier a pour objectif de montrer comment les petites entreprises exportatrices des pays en développement peuvent accroître leur compétitivité en utilisant les instruments du CCI, et comment elles peuvent combler le fossé numérique existant. En outre, deux manuels en ligne sont présentés pour la toute première fois qui traitent, pour l'un, du recyclage des déchets électroniques et, pour l'autre, de la sécurité électronique. Le seco explique ainsi de façon concrète comment relever les défis de la société de l'information sous l'angle du développement durable.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Pour de plus amples informations concernant les activités du seco lors du SMSI, consultez le site&lt;u&gt;http://www.seco-cooperation.ch&lt;/u&gt;&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Photos du SMSI/Genève voir sur notre &lt;u&gt;site pour photos online&lt;/u&gt;&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Berne, le 9 décembre 2003&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; &lt;b&gt;Secrétariat d'Etat à l'économie&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt; Communication&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; &lt;b&gt;Renseignements:&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt; Christian Hofer&lt;br /&gt; responsable de l'information&lt;br /&gt; Coopération économique au développement&lt;br /&gt; tél. 079 328 74 72</text>
      <contact/>
      <link id="18086">
        <title>&lt;u&gt;http://www.seco-cooperation.ch&lt;/u&gt;</title>
        <uri>http://www.seco-cooperation.ch.</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="18087">
        <title>&lt;u&gt;site pour photos online&lt;/u&gt;</title>
        <uri>http://www.photopress.ch/image/seco</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>La tecnologia dell'informazione e della comunicazione al servizio della lotta alla povertà</title>
      <teaser>Nel quadro del Vertice mondiale sulla società dell'informazione (VMSI) il Segretariato di Stato dell'economia (SECO) presenta a Ginevra le sue attività di politica dello sviluppo nei campi della tecnologia dell'informazione e della comunicazione. L'occasione è offerta dalla «Information and Communication Technologies for Development Platform»(ICT4D) un cosiddetto «side event» che si tiene al Palexpo di Ginevra dal 9 al 13 dicembre 2003.</teaser>
      <lead>Nel quadro del Vertice mondiale sulla società dell'informazione (VMSI) il Segretariato di Stato dell'economia (SECO) presenta a Ginevra le sue attività di politica dello sviluppo nei campi della tecnologia dell'informazione e della comunicazione. L'occasione è offerta dalla «Information and Communication Technologies for Development Platform»(ICT4D) un cosiddetto «side event» che si tiene al Palexpo di Ginevra dal 9 al 13 dicembre 2003.</lead>
      <text link="no">Il VMSI è il primo vertice mondiale incentrato sulle opportunità e sulle sfide della società dell'informazione. La piattaforma ICT4D, accessibile anche al vasto pubblico, prevede un'esposizione ed una serie di conferenze. Nel quadro di questa piattaforma il seco e i suoi partner presentano in totale 25 progetti riguardanti la tecnologia dell'informazione e della comunicazione (TIC) in particolare nei settori: e-business, e-waste, e-security ed e-procurement.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Il 9 dicembre il Segretario di Stato David Syz ha inaugurato il simposio annuale infoDev organizzato unitamente alla Banca mondiale. Il programma infoDev, cofinanziato dalla Svizzera, sostiene dal 1995 gli sforzi dei paesi in via di sviluppo per introdurre ed utilizzare le moderne tecnologie dell'informazione.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Dall'11 al 12 dicembre 2003 il seco organizza insieme al Centro per il commercio internazionale (ITC) un workshop interattivo sull'e-business. L'obiettivo è illustrare come le piccole aziende d'esportazione dei paesi in via di sviluppo possano incrementare la loro competitività utilizzando strumenti TIC e colmare così il divario digitale esistente. Per la prima volta saranno inoltre presentati due prontuari on-line riguardanti il riciclaggio di rifiuti elettronici e la sicurezza elettronica. Il seco illustra così come è possibile rispondere concretamente e in modo sostenibile alle sfide della società dell'informazione.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Per ulteriori informazioni sulle attività del seco al VMSI si rinvia al sito:&lt;u&gt;http://www.seco-cooperation.ch&lt;/u&gt;&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Le foto dell VMSI sono pubblicate nella &lt;u&gt;banca dati fotografica&lt;/u&gt;&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Berna, 9 dicembre 2003&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; &lt;b&gt;Segretariato di Stato dell'economia&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt; Comunicazione&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; &lt;b&gt;Per informazioni:&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt; Christian Hofer&lt;br /&gt; responsabile dell'informazione&lt;br /&gt; Cooperazione economica allo sviluppo&lt;br /&gt; tel. 079 328 74 72&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;</text>
      <contact/>
      <link id="18090">
        <title>&lt;u&gt;http://www.seco-cooperation.ch&lt;/u&gt;</title>
        <uri>http://www.seco-cooperation.ch</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="18091">
        <title>&lt;u&gt;banca dati fotografica&lt;/u&gt;</title>
        <uri>http://www.photopress.ch/image/seco</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Integrating information and communication technologies for the reduction of poverty</title>
      <teaser>The State Secretariat of Economic Affairs (seco) will present its development policy activities in the field of information and communication technologies at the World Summit on the Information Society (WSIS) in Geneva. The presentation will be given in the context of the Information and Communication Technologies for Development Platform (ICT4D), which will be held 9 - 13 December 2003 as a «side event» at the Palexpo site in Geneva.</teaser>
      <lead>The State Secretariat of Economic Affairs (SECO) will present its development policy activities in the field of information and communication technologies at the World Summit on the Information Society (WSIS) in Geneva. The presentation will be given in the context of the Information and Communication Technologies for Development Platform (ICT4D), which will be held 9 - 13 December 2003 as a «side event» at the Palexpo site in Geneva.</lead>
      <text link="no">The WSIS is the first world summit to deal with the opportunities and challenges related to the information society. The ICT4D platform includes an exhibition and a conference programme, and is also open to the public. In the context of this platform, seco and its partners will jointly present 25 projects in the field of information and communications technologies with a focus on e-business, e-waste, e-security and e-procurement.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; On 9 December, State Secretary David Syz opened the annual infoDev Symposium, which is jointly organised by seco and the World Bank. The infoDev programme, which is cofinanced by Switzerland, has been supporting developing countries in their implementation and use of modern information technologies since 1995. seco and the International Trade Centre (ITC) are jointly organising a two-day interactive workshop with a focus on e-business on 11 - 12 December 2003. The workshop is intended to show how small export firms from developing countries can increase their competitiveness with the help of ICT instruments and bridge the existing digital divide. Two manuals, which can be found on the Internet, on the recycling of electronic waste and electronic safety will be presented for the first time. seco will give concrete examples of how to approach the challenges of the information society in terms of sustainability.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; The following website provides further information on seco's activities at the WSIS:&lt;u&gt;http://www.seco-cooperation.ch&lt;/u&gt;&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Photos of the WSIS/Geneva see on our &lt;u&gt;online photo data base&lt;/u&gt;&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Berne, 9 December 2003&lt;br /&gt; &amp;nbsp;&lt;b&gt;State Secretariat for Economic Affairs&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt; Communications&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; &lt;b&gt;For further details:&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt; Christian Hofer&lt;br /&gt; Public information officer for economic development cooperation&lt;br /&gt; Tel. 079 328 74 72&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;</text>
      <contact/>
      <link id="18084">
        <title>&lt;u&gt;http://www.seco-cooperation.ch&lt;/u&gt;</title>
        <uri>http://www.seco-cooperation.ch</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="18085">
        <title>&lt;u&gt;online photo data base&lt;/u&gt;</title>
        <uri>http://www.photopress.ch/image/seco</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="47">
        <name lang="de">Wirtschaft</name>
        <name lang="fr">Économie</name>
        <name lang="it">Economia</name>
        <name lang="en">Economic Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
