<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="88880" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2022-05-18</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="1070" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>1070</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Der Bundesrat</name>
      <name lang="fr">Conseil fédéral</name>
      <name lang="it">Il Consiglio federale</name>
      <name lang="en">The Federal Council</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.admin.ch/gov/de/start.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.admin.ch/gov/fr/accueil.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.admin.ch/gov/it/pagina-iniziale.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.admin.ch/gov/en/start.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="yes" id="602" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>601</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Generalsekretariat EFD</name>
      <name lang="fr">Secrétariat général DFF</name>
      <name lang="it">Segreteria generale DFF</name>
      <name lang="en">Secretariat-General FDF</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.efd.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.efd.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.efd.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.efd.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="1070">
      <name lang="de">Der Bundesrat</name>
      <name lang="fr">Conseil fédéral</name>
      <name lang="it">Il Consiglio federale</name>
      <name lang="en">The Federal Council</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.admin.ch/gov/de/start.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.admin.ch/gov/fr/accueil.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.admin.ch/gov/it/pagina-iniziale.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.admin.ch/gov/en/start.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <department id="601">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Finanzdepartement</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des finances</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale delle finanze</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Finance</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.efd.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.dff.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.efd.admin.ch/efd/it/home.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.efd.admin.ch/efd/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Nationale Cyberstrategie: Umsetzung verläuft erfolgreich und wird weiter gestärkt</title>
      <lead>Der Bundesrat hat am 18. Mai 2022 den Bericht zur Wirksamkeitsüberprüfung der «Nationalen Strategie zum Schutz der Schweiz vor Cyber-Risiken (NCS) 2018–2022» zur Kenntnis genommen und beschlossen, für den Schutz vor Cyberrisiken weitere 25 Stellen zu schaffen. </lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;Die Umsetzung der aktuellen nationalen Cyberstrategie wird Ende 2022 abgeschlossen. Bis dahin wird die Strategie erneuert und auf die aktuelle Bedrohungslage ausgerichtet. Grundlage für diese Arbeiten bildet die Überprüfung der Wirksamkeit der aktuellen Strategie. Diese hat im zweiten Halbjahr 2021 stattgefunden. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2&gt;Positives Fazit zur Strategieumsetzung&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;Die Strategie und deren bisherige Umsetzung wurde durch externe Gutachter auf ihre Wirksamkeit überprüft. Das Fazit ist insgesamt positiv. Die Umsetzung verläuft planmässig und hat zu entscheidenden Resultaten geführt: So wurden beispielsweise gemeinsam mit den Hochschulen Standards und Labels entwickelt, welche Organisationen helfen, ihre Cybersicherheit systematisch zu prüfen und zu verbessern. Mit der Schaffung des Nationalen Testzentrums für Cybersicherheit in Zug werden in der Schweiz Fähigkeiten aufgebaut, IT-Produkte vertieft zu analysieren und mit der Vorlage zur Einführung einer Meldepflicht hat der Bund auch einen Vorschlag erarbeitet, wie die Cybersicherheit durch regulative Massnahmen verbessert werden kann. Ein wesentlicher Faktor für die erfolgreiche Erarbeitung und Umsetzung der NCS ist die breite Einbindung von Akteuren aus den Kantonen, der Wirtschaft und der Hochschulen.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2&gt;Empfehlungen für die Weiterentwicklung &lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;Aktuell wird die neue nationale Cyberstrategie ausgearbeitet. Dabei werden die Erkenntnisse des Berichtes miteinbezogen, damit die künftige Strategie noch mehr Wirkung erzielen kann. Beispielsweise wurde bei der Überprüfung festgestellt, dass sich die Strategie zu stark auf die kritischen Infrastrukturen, grosse Unternehmen sowie nationale und kantonale Behörden fokussiert hat. Für die KMU, Gemeinden und die Bevölkerung wurde noch zu wenig direkte Wirkung erzielt. Ebenfalls wurde von den Gutachtern ein Optimierungspotential bei der Steuerung für die Umsetzung identifiziert. Die Governance muss künftig so angepasst werden, dass rasch und flexibel Schwerpunkte gesetzt und neue Massnahmen beschlossen werden können. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2&gt;Weiterer Ausbau der Ressourcen&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;Der Bundesrat hat aufgrund der Resultate der Wirksamkeitsüberprüfung beschlossen, die Ressourcen für den Schutz vor Cyberrisiken weiter auszubauen. Er hat dafür insgesamt 25 Stellen bewilligt, wovon zehn im Nationalen Zentrum für Cybersicherheit, sechs im Nachrichtendienst des Bundes, zwei im Bundesamt für Informatik, zwei im Eidgenössischen Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten und fünf in Fachämtern der verschiedenen kritischen Sektoren (Energie, Verkehr, Zivilluftfahrt Telekommunikation und Gesundheit) angesiedelt werden. Damit sind die Grundlagen für die Neuauflage der NCS geschaffen. Sie wird wiederum unter breitem Einbezug von Expertinnen und Experten erarbeitet und bildet die Basis dafür, dass sich die Schweiz gemeinsam, effizient und koordiniert gegen Cyberbedrohungen schützt. &lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Kommunikation EFD Tel.-Nr. +41 58 462 60 33, Info@gs-efd.admin.ch</contact>
      <attachment id="231202">
        <title>Bericht zur Wirksamkeitsüberprüfung der NCS</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>1783</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/71548.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Stratégie nationale de protection contre les cyberrisques: mise en œuvre réussie et nouvelle augmentation des ressources</title>
      <lead>Le 18 mai 2022, le Conseil fédéral a pris connaissance du rapport d'évaluation de l'efficacité de la stratégie nationale de protection de la Suisse contre les cyberrisques 2018–2022 et a décidé de créer 25 postes supplémentaires dédiés à la protection contre les cyberrisques. </lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;La mise en œuvre de l'actuelle stratégie nationale de protection contre les cyberrisques (SNPC) s'achèvera à la fin de l'année 2022. Une nouvelle stratégie adaptée aux menaces actuelles sera développée d'ici là sur la base de l'évaluation de l'efficacité de la stratégie en cours. Cette évaluation a été effectuée au second semestre 2021. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2&gt;Bilan positif pour la mise en œuvre de la stratégie&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;L'efficacité de la stratégie et de sa mise en œuvre a été évaluée par des experts externes. Le bilan est globalement positif. La mise en œuvre se déroule comme prévu et a donné des résultats décisifs. Par exemple, des normes et des labels ont été développés en collaboration avec les hautes écoles afin d'aider les organisations à contrôler et à améliorer leur cybersécurité de manière systématique. La Suisse s'est également dotée d'un institut national de test pour la cybersécurité, à Zoug, afin de pouvoir mener des analyses approfondies de produits informatiques. La Confédération cherche aussi à améliorer la cybersécurité par des mesures réglementaires; elle a élaboré à cet effet le projet d'introduction d'une obligation de signalement. L'implication de nombreux acteurs des cantons, de l'économie et des hautes écoles constitue un facteur essentiel pour le succès tant de l'élaboration que de la mise en œuvre de la stratégie.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2&gt;Recommandations &lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;La nouvelle stratégie nationale de protection contre les cyberrisques est en cours d'élaboration. Les conclusions du rapport sont prises en compte, afin que la future stratégie ait encore plus d'impact. L'évaluation relève par exemple que la stratégie se concentre trop sur les infrastructures critiques, les grandes entreprises et les autorités nationales et cantonales, tandis que l'impact direct sur les PME, les communes et la population est encore trop faible. Les experts notent également que le pilotage de la mise en œuvre peut être optimisé. Enfin, la gouvernance doit être adaptée afin que des priorités puissent être fixées et de nouvelles mesures prises rapidement et de manière flexible. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2&gt;Nouvelle augmentation des ressources&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;Vu les résultats de l'évaluation de l'efficacité, le Conseil fédéral a décidé d'augmenter les ressources consacrées à la protection contre les cyberrisques. Il a approuvé 25 postes au total, dont dix pour le Centre national pour la cybersécurité, six pour le Service de renseignement de la Confédération, deux pour l'Office fédéral de l'informatique et de la télécommunication, deux pour le Département fédéral des affaires étrangères et cinq pour les offices spécialisés dans divers secteurs critiques (énergie, transports, aviation civile, télécommunications et santé). Le cadre de la prochaine stratégie est ainsi posé. Élaborée comme les précédentes en collaboration avec de nombreux experts, la SNPC constitue la base sur laquelle la Suisse s'appuie pour se protéger avec efficacité contre les cybermenaces, en conjuguant et coordonnant les efforts. &lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Communication DFF Tél. +41 58 462 60 33, info@gs-efd.admin.ch</contact>
      <attachment id="231203">
        <title>Rapport d'évaluation de l'efficacité de la SNPC</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>4070</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/71549.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Strategia nazionale contro i cyber-rischi: l’attuazione procede con successo e viene ulteriormente rafforzata</title>
      <lead>Il 18 maggio 2022 il Consiglio federale ha preso conoscenza del rapporto sulla verifica dell’efficacia della Strategia nazionale per la protezione della Svizzera contro i cyber-rischi (SNPC) 2018–2022 e deciso di potenziare le risorse creando altri 25 posti in tale ambito. </lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;L'attuazione della SNPC in vigore si concluderà a fine 2022. Nel frattempo la Strategia viene aggiornata e adeguata in funzione della situazione di minaccia. La base per tali lavori è costituita dalla verifica dell'efficacia della SNPC effettuata nella seconda metà del 2021. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2&gt;Bilancio positivo per quanto riguarda l'attuazione &lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;L'efficacia della Strategia attuale, compresa la sua esecuzione, è stata verificata da esperti esterni. Nel complesso il bilancio è positivo. L'attuazione procede secondo i piani e, finora, ha portato risultati fondamentali. In collaborazione con le scuole universitarie sono ad esempio stati sviluppati standard e marchi di qualità che permettono alle organizzazioni di verificare e migliorare sistematicamente la loro cibersicurezza. Grazie alla creazione dell'Istituto Nazionale di Test per la Cibersicurezza a Zugo vengono ora sviluppate competenze a livello nazionale volte ad analizzare in modo approfondito i prodotti IT. Inoltre, nel quadro del progetto relativo all'introduzione dell'obbligo di notifica dei ciberattacchi, la Confederazione ha anche elaborato una proposta per migliorare la cibersicurezza attraverso misure regolatorie. Il coinvolgimento di numerosi rappresentanti di Cantoni, ambienti economici e scuole universitarie è fondamentale per garantire il successo della SNPC, sia in fase di elaborazione che per la sua attuazione. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2&gt;Raccomandazioni per l'ulteriore sviluppo &lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;La nuova SNPC è attualmente in preparazione. Affinché la futura Strategia possa produrre effetti ancora migliori, nel quadro dei relativi lavori si tiene conto dei risultati del rapporto sulla verifica dell'efficacia della SNPC 2018-2022. Da quest'ultimo emerge ad esempio che la Strategia è concentrata eccessivamente sulle infrastrutture critiche, sulle grandi imprese nonché sulle autorità nazionali e cantonali, mentre per le PMI, i Comuni e la popolazione gli effetti diretti sono ancora troppo limitati. Gli esperti hanno inoltre identificato un potenziale di ottimizzazione nella gestione dell'attuazione. La governance dovrà essere adeguata affinché in futuro priorità e nuove misure possano essere decise in modo rapido e flessibile. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2&gt;Ulteriore potenziamento delle risorse &lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;Basandosi sui risultati della verifica dell'efficacia, il Consiglio federale ha deciso di aumentare ulteriormente le risorse a favore della protezione contro i ciber-rischi. A tal fine ha autorizzato la creazione di 25 posti, di cui dieci presso il Centro nazionale per la cibersicurezza, sei presso il Servizio delle attività informative della Confederazione, due presso l'Ufficio federale dell'informatica e della telecomunicazione, due presso il Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri e cinque presso uffici specializzati in diversi settori critici (energia, trasporti, aviazione civile, telecomunicazione e sanità). I presupposti per la nuova SNPC sono dunque dati. Anche la nuova Strategia verrà elaborata in stretta collaborazione con vari esperti e costituirà la base per una protezione della Svizzera contro le ciberminacce congiunta, efficace e coordinata. &lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>Comunicazione DFF Tel. +41 58 462 60 33, Info@gs-efd.admin.ch</contact>
      <attachment id="231204">
        <title>Rapporto sulla verifica dell’efficacia della SNPC</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>2563</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/71550.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Implementation of national cyberstrategy proceeding successfully and to be strengthened further</title>
      <lead>On 18 May 2022, the Federal Council took note of the report on the effectiveness assessment of the "2018-2022 national strategy for the protection of Switzerland against cyber-risks (NCS)" and decided to create a further 25 positions in the area of protection against cyber-risks.</lead>
      <text link="no"> &lt;p&gt;The implementation of the current national cyberstrategy will be completed at the end of 2022. In the meantime, the strategy will be renewed and geared towards the current threat situation. This work will be based on the effectiveness assessment of the current strategy, which was carried out in the second half of 2021.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2&gt;Positive verdict regarding the implementation of the strategy&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;The strategy and its implementation to date were assessed for effectiveness by external experts. The verdict was positive overall. It is being implemented according to plan and has led to decisive results. For example, standards and labels were developed together with the universities, and these help organisations to systematically check and improve their cybersecurity. With the creation of the National Test Institute for Cybersecurity in Zug, capabilities for analysing IT products in depth are being established in Switzerland, and with the proposal to introduce a reporting obligation, the Confederation has also drawn up a proposal on how cybersecurity can be improved by means of regulatory measures. Broad involvement of players from the cantons, the business community and universities is a key factor in the successful preparation and implementation of the NCS.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2&gt;Recommendations for further development&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;The new national cyberstrategy is currently being drafted. In the process, the findings of the report will be incorporated to ensure that the future strategy can be even more effective. For example, the assessment process revealed that the strategy focused too much on critical infrastructures, large companies and national and cantonal authorities. Not enough of a direct impact was achieved for SMEs, communes and the general public. The experts also found potential for optimisation in implementation governance. In the future, governance must be adapted so that new measures can be decided upon and priorities can be set quickly and flexibly.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2&gt;Further expansion of resources&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;Based on the results of the effectiveness assessment, the Federal Council has decided to further expand the resources for protection against cyber-risks. It has approved a total of 25 positions for this purpose, ten of which will be in the National Cybersecurity Centre, six in the Federal Intelligence Service, two in the Federal Office of Information Technology, Systems and Telecommunication, two in the Federal Department of Foreign Affairs and five in specialist offices in various critical sectors (energy, transport, civil aviation, telecommunications and health). The foundations have thus been laid for the new edition of the NCS. It will once again be prepared with the extensive involvement of experts and will form the basis for Switzerland's joint, efficient and coordinated protection against cyberthreats.&lt;/p&gt; </text>
      <contact>FDF Communications Tel. +41 58 462 60 33, info@gs-efd.admin.ch</contact>
      <attachment id="231202">
        <title>Bericht zur Wirksamkeitsüberprüfung der NCS</title>
        <format>pdf</format>
        <size-kb>1783</size-kb>
        <uri>https://www.newsd.admin.ch/newsd/message/attachments/71548.pdf</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </attachment>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <offers>
      <offer id="348" org-id="602">
        <name lang="de">Cybersecurity</name>
        <name lang="fr">Cybersecurity</name>
        <name lang="it">Cybersecurity</name>
        <name lang="en">Cybersecurity</name>
      </offer>
      <offer id="351" org-id="602">
        <name lang="de">NCSC - Nationales Zentrum für Cybersicherheit</name>
        <name lang="fr">NCSC - Centre national pour la cybersécurité</name>
        <name lang="it">NCSC - Centro nazionale per la cibersicurezza</name>
        <name lang="en">NCSC - National Cyber Security Centre</name>
      </offer>
    </offers>
    <keywords>
      <keyword id="174" org-id="602">
        <name lang="de">Informatik-Sicherheit</name>
        <name lang="fr">Sécurité informatique</name>
        <name lang="it">Sicurezza informatica</name>
        <name lang="en">IT security</name>
      </keyword>
    </keywords>
    <topics>
      <topic id="33">
        <name lang="de">Bundespräsident/-in</name>
        <name lang="fr">Président/e de la Confédération</name>
        <name lang="it">Presidente della Confederazione</name>
        <name lang="en">President of the Swiss Confederation</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
