<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="88925" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2022-05-20</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="1070" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>1070</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Der Bundesrat</name>
      <name lang="fr">Conseil fédéral</name>
      <name lang="it">Il Consiglio federale</name>
      <name lang="en">The Federal Council</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.admin.ch/gov/de/start.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.admin.ch/gov/fr/accueil.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.admin.ch/gov/it/pagina-iniziale.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.admin.ch/gov/en/start.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="201" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>201</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="301" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>301</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement des Innern</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'intérieur</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'interno</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Home Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="501" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>501</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Verteidigung, Bevölkerungsschutz und Sport</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de la défense, de la protection de la population et des sports</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale della difesa, della protezione della popolazione e dello sport</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Defence, Civil Protection and Sports DDPS</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.vbs.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.vbs.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.vbs.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.vbs.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@gs-vbs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@gs-vbs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@gs-vbs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@gs-vbs.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="601" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>601</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Finanzdepartement</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des finances</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale delle finanze</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Finance</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.efd.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.dff.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.efd.admin.ch/efd/it/home.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.efd.admin.ch/efd/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="801" lead="no" topnews="no">
      <department-id>801</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Umwelt, Verkehr, Energie und Kommunikation</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'environnement, des transports, de l'énergie et de la communication</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'ambiente, dei trasporti, dell'energia e delle comunicazioni</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of the Environment, Transport, Energy and Communications</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.uvek.admin.ch/uvek/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.uvek.admin.ch/uvek/fr/home.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.uvek.admin.ch/uvek/it/home.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.uvek.admin.ch/uvek/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-uvek.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-uvek.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-uvek.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-uvek.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="1070">
      <name lang="de">Der Bundesrat</name>
      <name lang="fr">Conseil fédéral</name>
      <name lang="it">Il Consiglio federale</name>
      <name lang="en">The Federal Council</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.admin.ch/gov/de/start.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.admin.ch/gov/fr/accueil.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.admin.ch/gov/it/pagina-iniziale.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.admin.ch/gov/en/start.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@bk.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <department id="201">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <department id="301">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement des Innern</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'intérieur</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'interno</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Home Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.edi.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-edi.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <department id="501">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Verteidigung, Bevölkerungsschutz und Sport</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de la défense, de la protection de la population et des sports</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale della difesa, della protezione della popolazione e dello sport</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Defence, Civil Protection and Sports DDPS</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.vbs.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.vbs.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">http://www.vbs.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="en">http://www.vbs.admin.ch</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@gs-vbs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@gs-vbs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@gs-vbs.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@gs-vbs.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <department id="601">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Finanzdepartement</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des finances</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale delle finanze</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Finance</name>
      <www lang="de">http://www.efd.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="fr">http://www.dff.admin.ch</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.efd.admin.ch/efd/it/home.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.efd.admin.ch/efd/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-efd.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <department id="801">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für Umwelt, Verkehr, Energie und Kommunikation</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral de l'environnement, des transports, de l'énergie et de la communication</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale dell'ambiente, dei trasporti, dell'energia e delle comunicazioni</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of the Environment, Transport, Energy and Communications</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.uvek.admin.ch/uvek/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.uvek.admin.ch/uvek/fr/home.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.uvek.admin.ch/uvek/it/home.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.uvek.admin.ch/uvek/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">info@gs-uvek.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">info@gs-uvek.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">info@gs-uvek.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">info@gs-uvek.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Das Programm der Mitglieder des Bundesrates am WEF-Jahrestreffen 2022</title>
      <lead>Das Jahrestreffen des World Economic Forum (WEF) findet nach der Absage im Vorjahr und einer ebenfalls der Pandemie geschuldeten Verschiebung nun erstmals im Frühling statt. Gemeinsam mit WEF-Gründer Prof. Klaus Schwab eröffnet Bundespräsident Ignazio Cassis das Jahrestreffen am Montag, 23. Mai 2022. </lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;Das Jahrestreffen bietet den Mitgliedern des Bundesrates Gelegenheit für viele weitere Kontakte und Gespräche; es dürften rund 32 bilaterale Treffen stattfinden. Programmänderungen sind immer auch in letzter Minute noch möglich.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;b&gt;Bundespräsident Ignazio Cassis&lt;/b&gt;, Vorsteher des Eidgenössischen Departements für auswärtige Angelegenheiten (EDA), stellt den Krieg in der Ukraine ins Zentrum seiner Gespräche am WEF. Die Situation in der Ukraine und mögliche Auswirkungen auf die Sicherheitsarchitektur in Europa wird er in seiner Eröffnungsrede ansprechen. Das werden auch die wichtigsten Themen in den bilateralen Treffen sein, die der Bundespräsident während seines Aufenthalts in Davos abhalten wird. Vorgesehen sind unter anderem ein Gespräch mit dem ukrainischen Aussenminister Dmytro Kuleba und Spaniens Ministerpräsident Pedro Sánchez. Ausserdem nimmt Bundespräsident Cassis an einer Veranstaltung des Open Forum zum Thema Frieden in Europa und dem Potenzial der multilateralen Zusammenarbeit teil. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;b&gt;Bundesrat Alain Berset&lt;/b&gt;, Vorsteher des Eidgenössischen Departements des Innern (EDI), nimmt an einer Veranstaltung des WEF teil, die sich der globalen Gesundheit und der Gesundheitspolitik widmet. Er wird unter anderem neben den Gesundheitsministern Indonesiens, Budi Gunadi Sadikin, und Malaysias, Khairy Jamaluddin, sprechen. In seiner Funktion als Vizepräsident wird er voraussichtlich die tunesische Premierministerin Najla Bouden, den kosovarischen Premierminister Albin Kurti, den kolumbischen Präsidenten Ivan Duque sowie den simbabwischen Präsidenten Emmerson Mnangagwa treffen. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;b&gt;Bundesrätin Viola Amherd&lt;/b&gt;, Vorsteherin des Eidgenössischen Departements für Verteidigung, Bevölkerungsschutz und Sport (VBS), setzt einen thematischen Schwerpunkt auf die Sicherheitspolitik. Sie wird an einer Podiumsdiskussion über die Zukunft der transatlantischen Beziehungen teilnehmen (IGWEL, Informal Gathering of World Economic Leaders). Darüber hinaus ist ein Gespräch mit dem NATO-Generalsekretär Jens Stoltenberg vorgesehen, mit dem sich Bundesrätin Amherd über die aktuelle sicherheitspolitische Lage, die militärische Friedensförderung im Westbalkan – namentlich die SWISSCOY – sowie die bilaterale Kooperation im Rahmen der NATO austauschen wird. Die Chefin VBS wird zudem das «Swiss Armed Forces Culinary Team» (SACT), die Schweizer Nationalmannschaft der Armeeköche, besuchen – dieses steht während des WEF im «House of Switzerland» im Einsatz.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;b&gt;Bundesrat Ueli Maurer&lt;/b&gt;, Vorsteher des Eidgenössischen Finanzdepartements (EFD), wird am WEF-Jahrestreffen im üblichen Rahmen hauptsächlich bilaterale Gespräche mit ausländischen Amtskolleginnen und Amtskollegen führen. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;b&gt;Bundesrat Guy Parmelin&lt;/b&gt;, Vorsteher des Eidgenössischen Departements für Wirtschaft, Bildung und Forschung (WBF), wird das Jahrestreffen in Davos nutzen, um verschiedene thematische Schwerpunkte in den Bereichen Wirtschaft und Handel voranzutreiben, etwa die wirtschaftlichen Beziehungen zu Partnerländern und der EU oder die Weiterentwicklung mehrerer Freihandelsabkommen. Am Sonntag wird er sich im Vorfeld des WEF gemeinsam mit Bundesrätin Simonetta Sommaruga mit Robert Habeck, dem deutschen Vizekanzler und Bundesminister für Wirtschaft und Klimaschutz, treffen. In den darauffolgenden Tagen wird Bundesrat Parmelin unter anderem mit dem brasilianischen Wirtschaftsminister Paulo Guedes, dem indischen Handels- und Industrieminister Piyush Goyal, dem peruanischen Handelsminister Roberto Sánchez, dem indonesischen Handelsminister Muhammad Lutfi, dem singapurischen Transportminister S. Iswaran, der britischen Staatssekretärin für internationalen Handel Anne-Marie Trevelyan sowie dem EU-Kommissar für Handel Valdis Dombrovskis Gespräche führen.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;b&gt;Bundesrätin Simonetta Sommaruga&lt;/b&gt;, Vorsteherin des Eidgenössischen Departements für Umwelt, Verkehr, Energie und Kommunikation (UVEK), wird sich im Vorfeld des WEF am Sonntag, 22. Mai 2022, gemeinsam mit Wirtschaftsminister Guy Parmelin mit Robert Habeck, dem deutschen Bundesminister für Wirtschaft und Klimaschutz, treffen. Dabei geht es u.a. um die Auswirkungen des Krieges in der Ukraine auf die Energieversorgung. Auf dem Programm von Bundesrätin Sommaruga stehen am Sonntag ausserdem Gespräche mit Arifin Tasrif, dem indonesischen Energieminister, sowie mit Xie Zhenhua, dem chinesischen Sondergesandten für das Klima.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class="nsbtextkasten"&gt;&lt;b&gt;Das «House of Switzerland» am WEF 2022&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Die offizielle Schweiz ist zum dritten Mal mit einem «House of Switzerland» am diesjährigen WEF-Jahrestreffen vertreten. Unter der Federführung von Präsenz Schweiz im Eidgenössischen Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten (EDA) dient das «House of Switzerland» im Eisstadion Davos als Kommunikations- und Netzwerkplattform für die Schweiz als Gastgeberland. Im Rahmen verschiedener thematischer Anlässe bringt es Akteure aus Politik, Wirtschaft und Wissenschaft zusammen und bietet ein vielfältiges Programm. Im Fokus stehen der nachhaltige Aufschwung und die gegenwärtigen Herausforderungen angesichts der globalen Lage. Das Themenspektrum reicht vom Potenzial neuer Technologien in der Entwicklungshilfe, der Neuausrichtung der Arbeit bis hin zu Innovationen im Bereich der Digitalisierung und Zukunft der Ernährungssysteme. Das «House of Switzerland» ist auch ein informeller Begegnungsort für die Schweizer Delegation mit internationalen Gästen und Partnern sowie für Medienschaffende. Für das leibliche Wohl der Gäste im «House of Switzerland» sorgt dieses Jahr das «Swiss Armed Forces Culinary Team» (SACT), die Schweizer Nationalmannschaft der Armeeköche.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Florian Imbach Kommunikation Präsidialdienst, Bundeskanzlei 058 465 47 40, florian.imbach@bk.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="231396">
        <title>World Economic Forum Annual Meeting 2022</title>
        <uri>https://www.admin.ch/gov/de/start/dokumentation/im-gespraech/wef.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="231400">
        <title>Programm</title>
        <uri>https://houseofswitzerland.org/de/events/house-switzerland-am-wef-2022/activities</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Rencontre annuelle du WEF 2022 : programme des membres du Conseil fédéral</title>
      <lead>Après avoir été annulée l’an dernier et reportée cette année en raison de la pandémie, la rencontre annuelle du Forum économique mondial (WEF) se tiendra pour la première fois au printemps. Le fondateur du WEF Klaus Schwab et le président de la Confédération Ignazio Cassis inaugureront ensemble la rencontre, le lundi 23 mai 2022. </lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;La rencontre annuelle du WEF est l’occasion pour les membres du Conseil fédéral de nouer de multiples contacts et de mener de nombreuses discussions ; près de 32 rencontres bilatérales sont prévues au programme. Toutefois, des changements de dernière minute restent possibles.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;b&gt;Le président de la Confédération Ignazio Cassis&lt;/b&gt;, chef du Département fédéral des affaires étrangères (DFAE), place la guerre en Ukraine au centre de ses discussions. Il évoquera la situation en Ukraine et ses possibles répercussions sur l’architecture de sécurité en Europe dans son discours d’ouverture. Il abordera aussi principalement ces thèmes lors des rencontres bilatérales auxquelles il participera pendant son séjour à Davos. Des entretiens sont notamment prévus avec le ministre ukrainien des affaires étrangères Dmytro Kuleba et le président du gouvernement espagnol Pedro Sánchez. Le président de la Confédération participera par ailleurs à une manifestation de l’&lt;i&gt;open forum&lt;/i&gt; sur la paix en Europe et le potentiel de la coopération multilatérale. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;b&gt;Le conseiller fédéral Alain Berset&lt;/b&gt;, chef du Département fédéral de l’intérieur (DFI), participera à un événement du forum consacré à la santé globale et aux politiques de la santé. Il s’exprimera notamment aux côtés des ministres de la santé de l’Indonésie Budi Gunadi Sadikin et de la Malaisie Khairy Jamaluddin. En sa qualité de vice-président, il est prévu qu’il rencontre la première ministre tunisienne Najla Bouden, le premier ministre kosovar Albin Kurti, le président colombien Ivan Duque, et le président zimbabwéen Emmerson Mnangagwa.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;b&gt;La conseillère fédérale Viola Amherd&lt;/b&gt;, cheffe du Département fédéral de la défense, de la protection de la population et des sports (DDPS), mettra l’accent sur le thème de la sécurité. Elle participera à une table ronde sur l’avenir des relations transatlantiques (IGWEL, &lt;i&gt;Informal Gathering of World Economic Leaders&lt;/i&gt;). Un entretien est en outre prévu avec le secrétaire général de l’OTAN Jens Stoltenberg, avec lequel la conseillère fédérale parlera de la situation actuelle en matière de sécurité, de la promotion militaire de la paix dans les Balkans occidentaux – assurée notamment par la SWISSCOY – et de la coopération bilatérale dans le cadre de l’OTAN. La cheffe du DDPS rendra également visite à la &lt;i&gt;Swiss Armed Forces Culinary Team&lt;/i&gt; (SACT), l’équipe nationale des cuisiniers militaires suisses, qui cuisinera dans la Maison de la Suisse pendant le WEF.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;b&gt;Le conseiller fédéral Ueli Maurer&lt;/b&gt;, chef du Département fédéral des finances (DFF), mènera principalement des entretiens bilatéraux avec ses homologues étrangers, dans le cadre usuel. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;b&gt;Le conseiller fédéral Guy Parmelin&lt;/b&gt;, chef du Département fédéral de l’économie, de la formation et de la recherche (DEFR), profitera de la rencontre annuelle de Davos pour faire avancer certains dossiers prioritaires dans le domaine de l’économie et du commerce, tels que les relations économiques avec des États partenaires et l’UE ou le développement de plusieurs accords de libre-échange. Dimanche, accompagné de la conseillère fédérale Simonetta Sommaruga, il rencontrera en amont du WEF Robert Habeck, le vice-chancelier allemand et ministre fédéral de l’économie et du climat. Dans les jours qui suivront, des rencontres sont notamment prévues entre Guy Parmelin et le ministre brésilien de l’économie Paulo Guedes, le ministre indien du commerce et de l’industrie Piyush Goyal, les ministres du commerce du Pérou Roberto Sánchez et de l’Indonésie Muhammad Lutfi, le ministre des transports de Singapour S. Iswaran, la secrétaire d’État britannique au commerce international Anne-Marie Trevelyan et le commissaire européen au commerce Valdis Dombrovskis.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;La conseillère fédérale Simonetta Sommaruga&lt;/b&gt;, cheffe du Département fédéral de l’environnement, des transports, de l’énergie et de la communication (DETEC), rencontrera Robert Habeck, ministre fédéral allemand de l’économie et du climat, en amont du WEF, le dimanche 22 mai 2022. Elle sera à cette occasion accompagnée du ministre de l’économie Guy Parmelin. Lors de cette rencontre, il sera notamment question de l’impact de la guerre en Ukraine sur l’approvisionnement énergétique. Ce même jour, elle s’entretiendra également avec le ministre de l’énergie d’Indonésie Arifin Tasrif et avec l’envoyé spécial de la Chine pour le climat Xie Zhenhua. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class="nsbtextkasten"&gt;&lt;b&gt;La Maison de la Suisse au WEF 2022&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Pour la troisième fois cette année, une Maison de la Suisse sera installée à Davos pour représenter la Suisse officielle lors du WEF. Placée sous l’égide de Présence Suisse, unité rattachée au DFAE, la Maison de la Suisse offre à la Suisse, en tant que pays hôte, une plateforme de communication et de réseautage au cœur de Davos. Les manifestations thématiques qui y sont organisées réunissent des acteurs des milieux politiques, économiques et scientifiques et composent un programme varié qui met l’accent sur une reprise durable et les réponses à apporter aux défis globaux. Les sujets qu’il est prévu d’aborder vont du potentiel des nouvelles technologies dans le cadre de l’aide au développement aux innovations dans le domaine de la numérisation et de la réorientation du travail à l’avenir des systèmes alimentaires. La Maison de la Suisse fait aussi office de lieu de rencontres informel pour la délégation suisse, ses invités et ses partenaires internationaux ainsi que pour les journalistes. Cette année, ce sera la &lt;i&gt;Swiss Armed Forces Culinary Team &lt;/i&gt;(SACT), l’équipe nationale des cuisiniers militaires suisses, qui veillera au bien-être des convives.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Florian Imbach Communication du service présidentiel, Chancellerie fédérale 058 465 47 40, florian.imbach@bk.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="231397">
        <title>Rencontre annuelle 2022 du Forum économique mondial</title>
        <uri>https://www.admin.ch/gov/fr/accueil/documentation/on-en-parle/wef.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="231401">
        <title>Programme</title>
        <uri>https://houseofswitzerland.org/fr/events/une-house-switzerland-au-wef-2022/activities</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>WEF 2022, programma dei membri del Consiglio federale</title>
      <lead>L’incontro annuale del Forum economico mondiale (WEF) si svolgerà per la prima volta in primavera, dopo la cancellazione dello scorso anno e il rinvio dovuti alla pandemia. Lunedì 23 maggio 2022, il presidente della Confederazione Ignazio Cassis aprirà la manifestazione assieme al fondatore del Forum, il prof. Klaus Schwab. </lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;L’incontro annuale offre ai membri del Consiglio federale l’opportunità di numerosi contatti e colloqui; sono previsti circa 32 incontri bilaterali. Il programma potrà però subire cambiamenti anche dell’ultimo minuto. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;b&gt;Il presidente della Confederazione Ignazio Cassis&lt;/b&gt;, capo del Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri (DFAE) incentrerà i suoi colloqui sulla guerra in Ucraina. Nel suo discorso di apertura parlerà della situazione in Ucraina e delle possibili ripercussioni sull’architettura di sicurezza in Europa. Saranno questi i principali temi degli incontri bilaterali che il presidente della Confederazione terrà durante la sua permanenza a Davos. È tra l’altro previsto un colloquio con il ministro degli esteri ucraino Dmytro Kuleba e con il presidente del Governo spagnolo Pedro Sánchez. Il presidente della Confederazione Cassis parteciperà inoltre a un evento dell’Open Forum dedicato alla pace in Europa e al potenziale della cooperazione multilaterale. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;b&gt;Il consigliere federale Alain Berset&lt;/b&gt;, capo del Dipartimento federale dell’interno (DFI), parteciperà a un evento del forum dedicato alla salute mondiale e alle politiche sanitarie. Prenderà la parola in particolare accanto ai ministri della salute dell’Indonesia, Budi Gunadi Sadikin, e della Malesia, Khairy Jamaluddin. In veste di vicepresidente, è inoltre previsto che incontri la prima ministra tunisina, Najla Bouden, il primo ministro kosovaro Albin Kurti, il presidente colombiano Ivan Duque, nonché il presidente zimbabwese Emmerson Mnangagwa.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;b&gt;La consigliera federale Viola Amherd&lt;/b&gt;, capo del Dipartimento della difesa, della protezione della popolazione e dello sport (DPPS), discuterà prioritariamente di politica di sicurezza. Parteciperà a una tavola rotonda sul futuro delle relazioni transatlantiche (IGWEL, Informal Gathering of World Economic Leaders). È inoltre previsto un colloquio con il segretario generale della NATO, Jens Stoltenberg, con il quale la consigliera federale Amherd discuterà dell’attuale situazione in materia di politica di sicurezza, del promovimento militare della pace nei Balcani occidentali – in particolare di SWISSCOY – nonché della cooperazione bilaterale nel contesto della NATO. Durante il WEF, la capodipartimento farà inoltre visita allo Swiss Armed Forces Culinary Team (SACT), la nazionale svizzera dei cuochi dell’esercito impiegata presso la «House of Switzerland».&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;b&gt;Il consigliere federale Ueli Maurer&lt;/b&gt;, capo del Dipartimento federale delle finanze (DFF), terrà colloqui bilaterali con i ministri delle finanze di altri Stati, nel quadro usuale. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;b&gt;Il consigliere federale Guy Parmelin&lt;/b&gt;, capo del Dipartimento federale dell’economia, della formazione e della ricerca (DEFR), approfitterà dell’incontro annuale a Davos per portare avanti alcune priorità tematiche in ambito economico e commerciale, fra cui le relazioni economiche con i Paesi partner e l’UE o l’ulteriore sviluppo di diversi accordi di libero scambio. Domenica, accompagnato dalla consigliera federale Simonetta Sommaruga, incontrerà in vista del WEF Robert Habeck, vicecancelliere tedesco e ministro federale dell’economia e della protezione del clima. Nei giorni successivi, il consigliere federale Parmelin si incontrerà fra l’altro con il ministro brasiliano dell’economia Paulo Guedes, con il ministro indiano del commercio e dell’industria Piyush Goyal, con il ministro peruviano del commercio Roberto Sànchez, con il ministro indonesiano del commercio Muhammad Lutfi, con il ministro dei trasporti di Singapore S. Iswaran, con la segretaria di Stato britannica per il commercio internazionale Anne-Marie Trevelyan e con il commissario UE per il commercio Valdis Dombrovskis.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;b&gt;La consigliera federale Simonetta Sommaruga&lt;/b&gt;, capo del Dipartimento federale dell’ambiente, dei trasporti, dell’energia e delle comunicazioni (DATEC), incontrerà, congiuntamente al ministro dell’economia Guy Parmelin, Robert Habeck, vicecancelliere tedesco e ministro federale dell’economia e della protezione del clima, domenica 22 maggio in vista del WEF. Al centro dei colloqui le ripercussioni della guerra in Ucraina sull’approvvigionamento energetico. Domenica è inoltre previsto un incontro fra la consigliera federale Sommaruga e Arifin Tasrif, il ministro indonesiano dell’energia, nonché con Xie Zhenhua, l’inviato speciale cinese per il clima.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class="nsbtextkasten"&gt;&lt;b&gt;La «House of Switzerland» al WEF 2022&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt; Quest’anno la Svizzera ufficiale sarà rappresentata per la terza volta al WEF dalla «House of Switzerland». Sotto l’egida di Presenza Svizzera presso il Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri, la «House of Switzerland» - situata nella pista di ghiaccio - funge da piattaforma di comunicazione e networking per la Svizzera in quanto Stato ospite. Nell’ambito di diversi eventi tematici riunisce attori del mondo della politica, dell’economia e della scienza e offre un ricco programma incentrato sulla ripresa sostenibile e le attuali sfide a livello globale. I singoli temi vanno dal potenziale delle nuove tecnologie nell’aiuto allo sviluppo al riorientamento del lavoro sino all’innovazione nell’ambito della digitalizzazione e al futuro dei sistemi alimentari. La «House of Switzerland» ospita anche gli incontri informali fra la delegazione svizzera e gli ospiti e partner internazionali, nonché gli operatori dei media. Il servizio di ristorazione nella «House of Switzerland» sarà garantito dallo «Swiss Armed Forces Culinary Team» (SACT), la nazionale svizzera dei cuochi dell’esercito.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Florian Imbach Comunicazione Servizio presidenziale, Cancelleria federale 058 465 47 40, florian.imbach@bk.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="231398">
        <title>World Economic Forum Annual Meeting 2022</title>
        <uri>https://www.admin.ch/gov/it/pagina-iniziale/documentazione/se-ne-parla/wef.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="231402">
        <title>Programma</title>
        <uri>https://houseofswitzerland.org/it/events/house-switzerland-al-wef-2022/activities</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Programme of members of the Federal Council attending the WEF Annual Meeting 2022</title>
      <lead>Following the cancellation of last year’s gathering and a postponement owing to the pandemic, the Annual Meeting of the World Economic Forum (WEF) is being held in spring for the first time. President Ignazio Cassis will open the Annual Meeting together with WEF founder Prof. Klaus Schwab on Monday, 23 May.</lead>
      <text link="no">&lt;p&gt;At the Annual Meeting, members of the Federal Council have the opportunity for many more contacts and discussions; around 32 bilateral meetings are expected to take place. Programme changes are always possible, even at the last minute.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;b&gt;President Ignazio Cassis&lt;/b&gt;, head of the Federal Department of Foreign Affairs (FDFA), will place the emphasis during his talks at the Annual Meeting on the war in Ukraine. In his opening speech, he will address the situation in Ukraine and possible implications for the security architecture in Europe. These will also be the most important topics at the bilateral meetings that the president will hold during his stay in Davos. Among other things, he is scheduled to meet with Ukrainian Foreign Minister Dmytro Kuleba and Spain's Prime Minister Pedro Sánchez. President Cassis will also take part in an event organised by the Open Forum on the topic of peace in Europe and the potential of multilateral cooperation.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;b&gt;Federal Councillor Alain Berset&lt;/b&gt;, head of the Federal Department of Home Affairs (FDHA), will take part in an event on global health and health policy. He will speak alongside the health ministers of Indonesia, Budi Gunadi Sadikin, and Malaysia, Khairy Jamaluddin. In his capacity as vice president, he is scheduled to meet with Tunisian Prime Minister Najla Bouden, Kosovar Prime Minister Albin Kurti, Colombian President Ivan Duque, and Zimbabwean President Emmerson Mnangagwa.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;b&gt;Federal Councillor Viola Amherd&lt;/b&gt;, head of the Federal Department of Defence, Civil Protection and Sport (DDPS), will be focusing on security policy matters. She will take part in a panel discussion on the future of transatlantic relations (IGWEL, Informal Gathering of World Economic Leaders). In addition, a meeting is set to take place with NATO Secretary General Jens Stoltenberg with whom Ms Amherd will exchange views on the current security policy situation, military peace promotion in the Western Balkans – in particular SWISSCOY - and bilateral cooperation within NATO. The head of the DDPS will also pay a visit to the Swiss Armed Forces Culinary Team (SACT), which is on duty in the ‘House of Switzerland’.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;b&gt;Federal Councillor Ueli Maurer&lt;/b&gt;, head of the Federal Department of Finance (FDF), will hold bilateral meetings with various counterparts in line with previous events.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;b&gt;Federal Councillor Guy Parmelin&lt;/b&gt;, head of the Federal Department of Economic Affairs, Education and Research (EAER), will use the Annual Meeting in Davos to advance various thematic priorities in the areas of business and trade, such as economic relations with partner countries and the EU, or the further development of several free trade agreements. On Sunday, in the run-up to the Annual Meeting, he and Federal Councillor Simonetta Sommaruga will meet with Robert Habeck, the German Vice-Chancellor and Federal Minister for Economic Affairs and Climate Protection. In the days that follow, Mr Parmelin will hold talks with Brazilian Economic Affairs Minister Paulo Guedes, India’s Trade and Industry Minister Piyush Goyal, Peruvian Trade Minister Roberto Sánchez, Indonesian Trade Minister Muhammad Lutfi, Singaporean Transport Minister S. Iswaran, the UK Secretary of State for International Trade Anne-Marie Trevelyan, and EU Trade Commissioner Valdis Dombrovskis.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;b&gt;Federal Councillor Simonetta Sommaruga&lt;/b&gt;, head of the Federal Department of the Environment, Transport, Energy and Communications (DETEC), will meet with Robert Habeck, the German Federal Minister for Economic Affairs and Climate Protection, together with Economic Affairs Minister Guy Parmelin on Sunday, 22 May, ahead of the Annual Meeting. Among other things, they will discuss the impact of the war in Ukraine on energy supplies. Ms Sommaruga's programme on Sunday also includes talks with Arifin Tasrif, the Indonesian Energy Minister, as well as Xie Zhenhua, the Chinese Special Envoy for Climate.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class="nsbtextkasten"&gt;&lt;b&gt;The ‘House of Switzerland’ WEF Annual Meeting 2022 &lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;For the third time at a WEF Annual Meeting, the Swiss authorities will be once again be showcased by a ‘House of Switzerland’. Under the auspices of Presence Switzerland, part of the Federal Department of Foreign Affairs (FDFA), the ‘House of Switzerland’ in the Davos ice stadium will serve as a communications and networking hub for Switzerland as host country. Through a variety of thematic events, it will bring together players from politics, business and science and offer a wide-ranging programme. The focus will be on sustainable economic recovery and the current challenges in view of the global situation. The spectrum of topics ranges from the potential of new technologies in development aid and the reorientation of work to innovations in the field of digitalisation and the future of food systems. The ‘House of Switzerland’ is also an informal meeting place for the Swiss delegation with international guests and partners, as well as for media representatives. This year, the Swiss Armed Forces Culinary Team (SACT), the national team of army chefs, will ensure that guests at the ‘House of Switzerland’ are well catered to.&lt;/p&gt;</text>
      <contact>Florian Imbach Communications, Presidential Services Unit, Federal Chancellery 058 465 47 40, florian.imbach@bk.admin.ch</contact>
      <link id="231399">
        <title>World Economic Forum Annual Meeting 2022</title>
        <uri>https://www.admin.ch/gov/en/start/documentation/dossiers/wef.html</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <link id="231403">
        <title>Program</title>
        <uri>https://houseofswitzerland.org/events/house-switzerland-wef-annual-meeting-2022/activities</uri>
        <position>Context</position>
      </link>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <keywords>
      <keyword id="1600" org-id="801">
        <name lang="de">Umweltpolitik</name>
        <name lang="fr">Umweltpolitik</name>
        <name lang="it">Umweltpolitik</name>
        <name lang="en">Umweltpolitik</name>
      </keyword>
    </keywords>
    <topics>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
