<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages xmlns="https://www.news.admin.ch/messages" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="1.0">
  <message id="88914" revoked="no">
    <version>1</version>
    <pubdate>2022-05-20</pubdate>
    <type>Memorandum</type>
    <originator department-msg="no" id="201" lead="yes" topnews="no">
      <department-id>201</department-id>
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </originator>
    <department id="201">
      <name lang="de">Eidgenössisches Departement für auswärtige Angelegenheiten</name>
      <name lang="fr">Département fédéral des affaires étrangères</name>
      <name lang="it">Dipartimento federale degli affari esteri</name>
      <name lang="en">Federal Department of Foreign Affairs</name>
      <www lang="de">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/de/home.html</www>
      <www lang="fr">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/fr/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="it">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/it/dfae.html</www>
      <www lang="en">https://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home.html</www>
      <email lang="de">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="fr">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="it">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
      <email lang="en">kommunikation@eda.admin.ch</email>
    </department>
    <content lang="de">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Europarat: 132. Sitzung des Ministerkomitees im Zeichen des Krieges in der Ukraine</title>
      <lead>Staatssekretärin Livia Leu nahm am 19. und 20. Mai 2022 an der 132. Sitzung des Ministerkomitees des Europarates in Turin teil, die vom italienischen Vorsitz organisiert wurde. Die Hohen Vertreterinnen und Vertreter der 46 Mitgliedstaaten nutzten die Tagung, die von der militärischen Aggression gegen die Ukraine und dem Ausschluss Russlands aus dem Europarat geprägt war, um ihr Engagement für die gemeinsamen Werte – Menschenrechte, Demokratie und Rechtsstaatlichkeit – zu bekräftigen. Die Staatssekretärin hob in ihrer Rede die langjährige Partnerschaft zwischen der Schweiz und dem Europarat in der Ukraine hervor und wies auf die bevorstehende Ukraine Recovery Conference (URC2022) in Lugano hin. </lead>
      <text link="no">«Wir bekräftigen heute unseren Glauben an die multilaterale Zusammenarbeit auf der Grundlage von Regeln und Normen», sagte Staatssekretärin Livia Leu. Vor dem Hintergrund der militärischen Aggression Russlands gegen die Ukraine betonte der Europarat seine entscheidende Rolle in der europäischen Architektur. Seine Normen und Instrumente waren und sind für die Ukraine besonders relevant. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Die Staatssekretärin hob die langjährige Partnerschaft zwischen der Schweiz und dem Europarat in der Ukraine hervor, namentlich seit 2015 durch die Unterstützung des Aktionsplans 2018–2022. An der Ukraine Recovery Conference (URC2022), welche die Schweiz zusammen mit der Ukraine am 4. und 5. Juli 2022 in Lugano durchführen wird, werden sie sowie weitere am Wiederaufbau der Ukraine beteiligte Akteure zusammentreffen.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Die Aussenministerinnen und Aussenminister der 46 Mitgliedstaaten betonten in Turin, dass der Europarat über die notwendigen Prioritäten und Ressourcen sowie die entsprechende Visibilität verfügen muss, um ein wirksames Gremium der Zusammenarbeit zu bleiben. Sie bestätigten ausserdem die Fortschritte bei den thematischen Arbeiten des Europarates, insbesondere im Bereich der künstlichen Intelligenz, wo der Entwurf eines Rechtsinstruments erarbeitet wird.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;b&gt;Irland übernimmt den Vorsitz des Ministerkomitees&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Nach zwei virtuellen Sitzungen des Ministerkomitees unter griechischem (2020) und deutschem (2021) Vorsitz war die Sitzung in Turin die erste, die seit 2019 physisch abgehalten wurde. Rund dreissig Ministerinnen und Minister bzw. Staatssekretärinnen und Vizeminister nahmen daran teil. Irland übernahm heute den Vorsitz und kündigte an, sich insbesondere auf den Schutz der Menschenrechte in Konfliktgebieten, die Stärkung der partizipativen Demokratie und die Beteiligung junger Menschen sowie den Schutz der Rechte und Freiheiten von Minderheiten und vulnerablen Bevölkerungsgruppen konzentrieren zu wollen.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Die Schweiz trat dem Europarat 1963 bei, 14 Jahre nach seiner Gründung. Der Europarat mit Sitz in Strassburg hat 46 Mitgliedstaaten. Russland wurde im März 2022 aufgrund seiner militärischen Aggression gegen die Ukraine aus dem Rat ausgeschlossen.&lt;br /&gt;</text>
      <contact>Kommunikation EDA Bundeshaus West CH-3003 Bern Tel. Kommunikationsservice: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Medienstelle: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="fr">
      <city>Berne</city>
      <title>Conseil de l’Europe: la 132e Session ministérielle placée sous le sceau de la guerre en Ukraine</title>
      <lead>Les 19 et 20 mai, la Secrétaire d’État Livia Leu a participé à la 132e Session ministérielle du Conseil de l’Europe à Turin, organisée par la présidence italienne du Comité des ministres. Marquée par l’agression militaire contre l’Ukraine et l’exclusion de la Russie de l’Organisation, cette session a permis aux Hauts représentants des 46 États membres de réaffirmer leur engagement en faveur des valeurs communes : droits de l’homme, démocratie et état de droit. Dans son discours, la Secrétaire d’État a souligné le partenariat de longue date entre la Suisse et le Conseil de l’Europe en Ukraine et évoqué la prochaine Ukraine Recovery Conference à Lugano (URC2022). </lead>
      <text link="no">« Nous réaffirmons aujourd’hui notre foi en la coopération multilatérale basée sur les règles et les normes », a déclaré la Secrétaire d’État Livia Leu. Dans le contexte de l’agression militaire russe contre l’Ukraine, le Conseil de l’Europe a fait valoir le rôle indispensable qu’il joue dans l’architecture européenne. Ses normes et instruments ont été et restent particulièrement pertinents pour l’Ukraine. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;La Secrétaire d’État a souligné le partenariat de longue date entre la Suisse et le Conseil de l’Europe en Ukraine, notamment par le soutien depuis 2015 du Plan d’action 2018-2022. L’Ukraine Recovery Conference (URC2022), co-organisée par la Suisse et l’Ukraine à Lugano les 4 et 5 juillet, les rassemblera, ainsi que d’autres acteurs impliqués dans la reconstruction de l’Ukraine.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;À Turin, les ministres des Affaires étrangères des 46 États membres ont souligné que le Conseil de l’Europe doit disposer des priorités, ressources et de la visibilité nécessaires pour rester un cadre efficace de coopération. Ils ont également validé l’avancement des travaux thématiques du Conseil de l’Europe, notamment en matière d’intelligence artificielle, où l’élaboration d’un instrument juridique est en préparation.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;b&gt;L’Irlande assurera la Présidence du Comité des ministres&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Après deux sessions virtuelles sous présidences grecque (2020) et allemande (2021) du Comité des ministres, la session ministérielle de Turin était la première à se tenir en présentiel depuis 2019. Une trentaine de ministres et secrétaires d’État ou vice-ministres étaient présents. Le flambeau a été repris aujourd’hui par l’Irlande. Celle-ci a annoncé vouloir notamment concentrer ses efforts sur la protection des droits de l’homme dans les zones de conflit, la promotion de la démocratie participative et l’engagement des jeunes ainsi que la protection des droits et libertés des minorités et des groupes vulnérables. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Pour rappel, la Suisse a adhéré au Conseil de l’Europe en 1963, 14 ans après sa fondation. Basé à Strasbourg, le Conseil de l’Europe compte 46 États membres. La Russie en a été exclue en mars 2022 suite à son agression militaire contre l’Ukraine.</text>
      <contact>Communication DFAE Palais fédéral ouest CH-3003 Berne Tél. Service de communication: +41 58 462 31 53 Tél. Service de presse: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="it">
      <city>Berna</city>
      <title>Consiglio d’Europa: la 132a Sessione ministeriale nel segno della guerra in Ucraina</title>
      <lead>Il 19 e il 20 maggio la segretaria di Stato Livia Leu ha partecipato, a Torino, alla 132a Sessione ministeriale del Consiglio d’Europa organizzata dalla presidenza italiana del Comitato dei Ministri. Segnata dall’aggressione militare contro l’Ucraina e dall’esclusione della Russia dall’Organizzazione, questa Sessione ha permesso agli alti rappresentanti dei 46 Stati membri di riaffermare il loro impegno nella difesa dei valori comuni: diritti umani, democrazia e Stato di diritto. Nel suo discorso la segretaria di Stato ha sottolineato il partenariato di lunga data tra la Svizzera e il Consiglio d’Europa in Ucraina e ha parlato della prossima Ukraine Recovery Conference (URC2022) che si svolgerà a Lugano. </lead>
      <text link="no">«Ribadiamo la nostra fiducia in una cooperazione multilaterale basata su regole e norme», ha dichiarato la segretaria di Stato Livia Leu. Nel contesto dell’aggressione militare russa contro l’Ucraina il Consiglio d’Europa ha messo in evidenza il ruolo indispensabile che svolge nell’architettura europea. Le sue norme e i suoi strumenti sono stati e restano particolarmente rilevanti per l’Ucraina. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;La segretaria di Stato ha sottolineato il partenariato di lunga data tra la Svizzera e il Consiglio d’Europa in Ucraina, in particolare con il sostegno, dal 2015, del piano d’azione 2018-2022. L’Ukraine Recovery Conference (URC2022), co-organizzata dalla Svizzera e dall’Ucraina a Lugano il 4 e 5 luglio, riunirà questi e altri attori coinvolti nella ricostruzione del Paese.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;A Torino i ministri degli Esteri dei 46 Stati membri hanno affermato che il Consiglio d’Europa deve avere le priorità, le risorse e la visibilità necessarie per continuare a rappresentare un quadro di cooperazione efficace. Hanno inoltre convalidato i progressi fatti dal Consiglio d’Europa in vari ambiti tematici, in particolare quello dell’intelligenza artificiale, dove è in fase di elaborazione uno strumento giuridico.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;b&gt;L’Irlanda assumerà la presidenza del Comitato dei Ministri&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Dopo due sessioni virtuali sotto le presidenze greca (2020) e tedesca (2021), la sessione del Comitato dei ministri a Torino è stata la prima a svolgersi in presenza dal 2019. Erano presenti una trentina di ministri e segretari di Stato o viceministri. Il testimone passa oggi all’Irlanda, che ha annunciato di voler concentrare i propri sforzi sulla protezione dei diritti umani nelle zone di conflitto, sulla promozione della democrazia partecipativa e dell’impegno delle giovani generazioni, oltre che sulla protezione dei diritti e delle libertà delle minoranze e dei gruppi più vulnerabili. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;La Svizzera ha aderito al Consiglio d’Europa nel 1963, 14 anni dopo la sua fondazione. Il Consiglio d’Europa, che ha sede a Strasburgo, conta 46 Stati membri. La Russia ne è stata esclusa nel marzo del 2022 a seguito della sua aggressione militare contro l’Ucraina.</text>
      <contact>Comunicazione DFAE Palazzo federale ovest CH-3003 Berna Tel. Servizio di comunicazione: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Servizio stampa: +41 58 460 55 55 E-Mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @EDA_DFAE</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <content lang="en">
      <city>Bern</city>
      <title>Council of Europe: 132nd ministerial session marked by Ukraine war</title>
      <lead>On 19 and 20 May, State Secretary Livia Leu took part in the 132nd Council of Europe ministerial session in Turin, organised by the Italian chair of the Committee of Ministers. This year's session, which was marked by Russia's military aggression against Ukraine and its consequent exclusion from the Council, provided the high representatives of the other 46 member states with the opportunity to reaffirm their commitment to common values: human rights, democracy and the rule of law. In her speech, Ms Leu underscored the long-standing partnership between Switzerland and the Council of Europe in Ukraine, and referred to the upcoming Ukraine Recovery Conference (URC2022) in Lugano. </lead>
      <text link="no">"Today, we reaffirm our belief in multilateral cooperation based on norms and standards," said State Secretary Livia Leu. Against the backdrop of Russia's military aggression against Ukraine, the Council of Europe has highlighted the importance of the organisation's role in the European architecture. The Council's rules and instruments continue to be particularly relevant in Ukraine. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Ms Leu also highlighted the long-standing partnership between Switzerland and the Council of Europe in Ukraine, particularly since 2015 and the launch of the 2018–22 action plan. This year’s Ukraine Recovery Conference (URC2022) in Lugano on 4 and 5 July, which will be organised jointly by Ukraine and Switzerland, will bring together both partners as well as other stakeholders involved in rebuilding Ukraine. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;During the session in Turin, the foreign ministers of the current 46 member states stressed that the Council of Europe must have the necessary priorities, resources and visibility in order to continue to serve as an effective framework for cooperation. They also affirmed the progress of the Council's thematic work, such as the drafting of a legal instrument in the field of artificial intelligence.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;b&gt;Ireland to hold next Committee of Ministers chair&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;This year's ministerial session in Turin was the first to be held in person since 2019, following on from two virtual meetings of the Committee of Ministers under the Greek and German chairs in 2020 and 2021 respectively. Around 30 ministers, state secretaries and deputy ministers were in attendance. The next chair of the Committee of Ministers will be held by Ireland, which has announced that it will concentrate efforts on protecting human rights in conflict zones, promoting participatory democracy and youth engagement, as well as protecting the rights and freedoms of minorities and vulnerable groups. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Switzerland joined the Council of Europe in 1963, 14 years after it was founded. The Council is based in Strasbourg and has 46 member states. Russia was excluded in March 2022 following its military aggression against Ukraine.&lt;br /&gt; </text>
      <contact>FDFA Communication Federal Palace West Wing CH-3003 Bern, Switzerland Tel. Communication service: +41 58 462 31 53 Tel. Press service: +41 58 460 55 55 E-mail: kommunikation@eda.admin.ch Twitter: @SwissMFA</contact>
      <revisions> </revisions>
    </content>
    <topics>
      <topic id="39">
        <name lang="de">Schweiz und Ausland</name>
        <name lang="fr">Suisse et étranger</name>
        <name lang="it">Svizzero ed estero</name>
        <name lang="en">Switzerland and Foreign Affairs</name>
      </topic>
    </topics>
  </message>
</messages>
